<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04113</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>242226</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23077</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Cuando nos despedimos en el pasillo
la pregunté a qué obedecía aquello y respondió con evasivas. En esto salió Tirso de su cuarto
y, como quien está enterado de lo que oye tratar, me dijo:--«¿A qué insistir? ¿No ve Vd. que
no quiere leer indecencias?»

--¿Y qué le contestaste?

--¡A tu hermano y en tu casa! Callar y marcharme; pero, lo confieso, me dieron ganas de meterle
un tomo por los hocicos. ¡Lo menos se ha figurado el hombre que llevo a la chica libros de
mal género!

--¡Qué burro!

--Falta lo mejor. Era la primera vez que Leo y yo nos separábamos así, poco menos que incomodados,
y me faltó tiempo para volver el lunes. ¿Te acuerdas de que fui por la tarde con el pretexto
de las pruebas y estuve hablando con ella?

--Sigue, sigue: ¿y qué te dijo?

--Hombre, hay cosas que no se pueden explicar punto por punto. Ya comprendes tú la diferencia
que hay de estar una mujer cariñosa, que le rebose la satisfacción de verse querida, a estar
fría, esquiva, como a quien no se le importa nada del hombre que tiene al lado.

--Pues una de dos: o estás equivocado, y no hay nada de lo que sospechas, o Tirso tiene la
culpa; y en este caso, no cabe duda, en mi casa va a haber más guerra civil que en el Norte.

--Mucho lo temo; y respecto a lo que veníamos hablando, creo que Leo no está ya por mí.

--Vamos con tiento. ¿Tienes algún lío, algún trapicheo que sabido por ella la haya enojado?

--No: palabra de honor.

--Bueno; pues yo pondré las cosas en claro.

--Te advierto una cosa. No pensaba formalizar aún la cuestión por... por falta de cuartos;
pero puesto que han venido rodadas las cosas, conste que tu padre y tú podéis considerarme,
si queréis, como de la casa; ¿entiendes?--Y tendió a Pepe la mano, que él estrechó cariñosamente.--Ya
lo sabéis, como acostumbran los títulos: os pido la mano...

--Yo te prometo que saldremos de dudas.

--¿Qué vas a hacer?

--Poco he de poder, o despejo la situación. En la primer conversación que tenga con Tirso,
le quito la careta. ¡Veremos quién lleva el gato al agua!

En seguida avivaron el paso, separándose al llegar cerca de la calle de Botoneras, donde se
despidieron, quedando Millán algo esperanzado con la intervención ofrecida. Pepe entró en su
casa de puntillas, abrió despacito, por no despertar a los que dormían, encendió la vela que
a prevención dejaba Leocadia en una palomilla del pasillo, se entró a su cuarto y se acostó,
pensando en los sucesos e ideas que le interesaban, en aquel recelo que le inspiraba su hermano,
en el cariño que tenía a sus padres y en las complicaciones que temía. Luego, serenándose su
ánimo, se acordó de Paz y del recrudecimiento que imaginó notar en su amor. ¿Cuál sería la
causa? ¿Por qué la niña criada en el regalo, lejos de convencerse de que aquello era una locura,
daba a sus promesas más firmeza y mayor expresión de simpatía a sus miradas?

XVI

Viendo Tirso que la madre atendía sus exhortaciones, no solamente insistió en ellas, sino que
trató de conquistar el ánimo de Leocadia, siéndole necesario para ello aguzar la astucia, pues
la diferencia de caracteres entre doña Manuela y su hija pedía táctica diversa. La primera
cedió por bondad y mansedumbre: en ella era hábito plegarse a la voluntad ajena. Cuando joven,
obedeció a su marido; erigido después Pepe en jefe de la familia por la fuerza de las circunstancias,
se acostumbró a mirarle como tal, y en las menudencias caseras seguía el parecer de su hija,
mostrando en todo ser nacida para obedecer. Las condiciones de Leocadia eran distintas: tenía
genio voluntarioso y, aunque sin faltarles al respeto, respondía a sus padres con entereza;
en sus caprichos de muchacha pobre, había siempre cierta obstinación; si se empeñaba en reformarse
un traje, no cesaba de dar vueltas a los trozos de tela, hasta lograr lo que se proponía; gustándole
un peinado, no hallaban paz sus manos hasta que conseguía aprender modo de hacérselo, y hasta
en estos pequeños detalles, por la tenacidad de sus resoluciones, delataba una firmeza muy
difícil de dominar desplegando energía. Tirso notó también que, a pesar de lo humilde de su
situación, la chica era algo vanidosa y estaba pagada de su persona, acusando de distintos
modos el afán de agradar, y como un cierto deseo latente, pero inmoderado, de imitar prendas
y costumbres de muchachas más favorecidas por la suerte. Jamás consintió, por ejemplo, en hacer
a su hermano blusas para trabajar en la imprenta, ni bajó nunca a la tienda de la esquina próxima
con pañuelo a la cabeza; a Pepe quería verle lo mejor vestido que fuera posible; y en sus trajes
propios, aun luchando con la falta de dinero para adornos y perifollos, procuraba siempre imitar
cortes elegantes. Por no tenerlos de oro, llevaba sin pendientes las orejas y los dedos sin
anillos. No era exigente en pedir lo muy costoso al esfuerzo de sus padres; pero sólo aceptaba
la pobreza como un accidente de su vida, no como condición de su origen. Admitió de buen grado
el amor de Millán, al tiempo que éste cursaba con Pepe la carrera; mas el ver que su novio
tuvo que abandonar los libros y dedicarse a un oficio, fue para ella contrariedad grandísima.
De continuar su hermano en la Universidad, acaso hubiese procurado romper pronto sus relaciones
con el impresor; mas viéndose Pepe obligado a hacer lo mismo al poco tiempo, Leocadia comprendió
que no podía por esto rechazar a Millán, y continuó aceptando su cariño, sin que la correspondencia
con que lo pagaba mereciese en realidad nombre de amor. Quizá, por falta de antecedentes, no
estuviera Tirso en situación de apreciar todo esto; pero alcanzó lo bastante para convencerse
de que, ni Leocadia estaba verdaderamente enamorada, ni desecharía por Millán lo que el desvergonzado
lenguaje de la codicia llama una proporción; lo cual le autorizaba a imaginar que, si la madre
había cedido por docilidad, la vanidad y el amor propio serían buenos medios para subyugar
a la hija. Mejor quisiera él llevar la piedad a sus corazones con la vehemencia del celo que
le inflamaba, pero comprendió que le era forzoso seguir la máxima de plegarse a la índole y
carácter de cada pecador, para convertirlo más seguramente. Por fin, muchos días después de
haber hablado con doña Manuela, determinó sondear a Leocadia; y hallándola una tarde leyendo
en el comedor, mientras don José reposaba y la madre había salido, se acercó, llevando él otro
libro en la mano.

--¡Sabe Dios!--la dijo entre severo y sonriente--qué libraco será ese! ¿Es de los que te trae
el novio?

--Sí.

--¡Bonito papel para un joven el de procurar lecturas nocivas a la mujer a quien quiere, y
buen modo de amar... suponiendo que te ame!

--¿Por qué dices eso?

--Cálmate, hija, cálmate; no quiero decir, ¡Dios me libre! que ese joven no te estime: lo que
me choca, es que tú le quieras a él.

--¡Ya lo creo que me quiere!

--No parece de mala índole; pero le sucede lo que a tu hermano: debe estar plagadito de las
ideas de ahora y ser de esos que no creen ni en la luz del día. Listo, sí será; ¡lástima que
tenga oficio tan feo!

--El de su padre... Empezó a estudiar para abogado; pero luego le sucedió lo mismo que a Pepe.

La palabra oficio sonó en los oídos de Leocadia como Tirso había previsto.

--Tendrá que estar siempre metido entre gente ordinaria, trabajadores y jornaleros: luego le
afinarás tú... aunque mala tarea es.

--Pero, ¿imaginas que Millán es mozo de cuerda o sereno?--repuso ella, riéndose forzadamente.--Te
equivocas: es un muchacho decente, igual a Pepe, que tiene que vivir así, trabajando, como Pepe.

--No, hija, como Pepe, no: nuestro hermano es hijo de un funcionario público; el padre de ese
joven, si no he oído mal, era cajista, jornalero.

--Impresor.

--Llámalo como quieras. Siendo ya viejo, llegó a dueño de la imprenta; pero su origen no puede
ser más humilde. Eso no quiere decir que sea mala persona; pero, en fin, ¿por qué te disgusta
que nosotros ambicionemos para tí lo mejor?

Leocadia miró a su hermano, sorprendida de que así se preocupara por su porvenir.

--Lo que quiero decirte--prosiguió el cura--es que, tan joven, y reuniendo condiciones que
son para la mujer llave de sana prosperidad, no debes contraer compromisos formales con un
hombre inferior a tí; porque esto no me lo negarás. Acaso tenga posición más desahogada que
la nuestra; pero, una cosa es el bienestar, y otra la esfera de cada uno. Hoy por hoy, no tenemos
dinero; pero ni nuestros padres ni nuestros abuelos han sido menestrales. Créeme, Leocadia,
no te comprometas con nadie; no renuncies a tu libertad de acción. No has nacido tú para mujer
de un jornalero.

--¡Dale con lo de jornalero! tiene una industria; vamos, una imprenta; pero no es un gañán.

--¡Bah! hija mía: llamemos a las cosas por sus nombres. Trabajador, no es más que trabajador;
y, si te casas con él, sabe Dios si tendrás que ir algún día a llevarle la comida en cesta,
como a un albañil.

--De modo que, según tú, debo esperar a que venga a pedir mi mano un título de Castilla.

--Nada de eso: me parece que, aunque sea un buen chico, no está justificado que renuncies por
él a lo que te reserve el porvenir. Nadie sabe lo que es el porvenir para una doncella.

Harto conoció Leocadia que, tras aquella problemática esperanza de grandezas futuras, lo que
verdaderamente impulsaba a Tirso era la antipatía que sentía contra Millán, desde que conoció
que en política y en falta de religión coincidía con Pepe; mas como estos mismos argumentos
se los hizo a sí propia alguna vez, no dejaron de ejercer presión en su ánimo. Parecíale innegable
la bondad de Millán, pero Tirso tenía, en parte, razón. El roce con la gente de la imprenta
había dado a su franqueza cierto tinte rudo, a veces rayano en la grosería; a sus sentimientos
honrados servía de intérprete un lenguaje tosco; para verle algo aseado y compuesto, era preciso
aguardar al domingo: acaso no anduviese descaminado Tirso y, andando el tiempo, tuviera ella
que llevarle en cesta la comida, resignándose a ser una menestrala, es decir, el tipo contrario
al de las señoritas, cuyos modales y trajes procuraba imitar.

En ocasiones diferentes hizo Tirso a su hermana análogos razonamientos y, como el terreno estaba
bien preparado, la semilla comenzó a germinar. Iniciado en ella el desvío, lo primero que hizo
fue evitar que menudearan las visitas de Millán entre semana, fundadas en el préstamo de libros:
luego ocurrió la escena narrada a Pepe por el amante desdeñado, en la cual intervino Tirso,
y, por último, la muchacha acentuó tan enérgicamente su desamor, que el novio casi dejó de
merecer tal nombre. A ser el afecto de Millán pasión hondamente arraigada, hubiese puesto empeño
en recobrar lo que perdía; mas también en él palpitaba un fondo de propia y exagerada estimación,
en que era de mayor cuenta el orgullo que el cariño.--«No hables de esto a tu hermana--había
dicho a su amigo--porque el querer no se impone ni es cosa para recibida de limosna.»

Aquello produjo a Pepe malísima impresión, pero aún le desagradó más ver demostrada la intervención
del cura. La cosa estaba ya fuera de duda: tras intentar apoderarse del ánimo de la madre,
comenzaba por distintos medios a explorar el de la hija para los mismos fines. ¿Cuáles serían
sus propósitos ulteriores? Motivos de conveniencia personal, al parecer ninguno. Lo único verosímil,
era que obrase impulsado no más que por proselitismo religioso, y en este caso, para comprometer
en la empresa la paz y la dicha de la familia, su fanatismo debía ser grande. ¿Cómo arriesgarse,
de otra suerte, a promover una escisión entre padres e hijos, aventurando la tranquilidad del
hogar y la poca salud de don José, por sólo la falta de cumplimiento en los deberes piadosos?
Tanto repugnaba esto a Pepe, dadas sus ideas, que no le era posible atribuir a su hermano tamaña
obcecación, suponiendo que, si únicamente el celo le impulsara, debía moderarlo con afectos
más terrenales, pero no menos puros. Su entendimiento rechazaba la posibilidad de que existiera
hombre capaz de apenar a sus padres por dar lustre a la religión. La displicencia con que Millán
y Leocadia comenzaron a mirarse, perdió con esto importancia a los ojos de Pepe: su verdadera
preocupación fue la conducta de Tirso, y llegó a disgustarse tanto, que su amada Paz lo echó
de ver en seguida.

       *       *       *       *       *

Primero, cierto espíritu novelesco, propio de niña libremente educada, hizo que Paz se encaprichara
con el amor de Pepe: después, cuando llegó a comprender lo mucho que él valía, aquella inclinación
se acentuó insensiblemente y, lo que al comienzo fue juego de la imaginación, vino a ser, del
modo más natural y sencillo, sincero y bien arraigado amor. El empleadillo, como ella imaginaba
que sus amigas le llamarían si llegaran a conocerle, se le había entrado al alma, persuadiéndose
de que le quería porque empezó a temer la cara que al saberlo pondría su padre, a pesar de
los alardes democráticos que solía hacer en el Parlamento. Pero no era esto lo que más la desazonaba.
Su inquietud nacía de ver disgustado continuamente a Pepe, y el convencimiento de estar enamorada
brotó de aquella relación que estableció su inteligencia entre la pena que ella sentía y la
inquietud que él mostraba. Cuando Paz se hizo cargo de que, aun ignorando la causa, el pesar
de su novio la entristecía; cuando, sin poder aquilatarlo, sintió como propio un dolor ajeno,
entonces advirtió que en su corazón comenzaba a reinar una voluntad distinta de la suya, y
que aquel hombre, sólo con lealtad y buena fe, iba apoderándose de su albedrío lenta, pero
seguramente, como río caudaloso que profundiza el cauce en que se sustenta. Paz, en apariencia
frívola, a semejanza de todo el que no ha sufrido, pero muy lista, se persuadió pronto de que
amaba, porque su pensamiento, lejos de amedrentarse ante las contrariedades que podía el amor
ocasionarla, se fijó exclusivamente en el dolor del hombre a quien quería. La primer muestra
de pasión verdadera, fue la sinceridad con que le habló.

Una mañana, estando en la biblioteca de su padre, que era donde se veían en los ratos que aquél
faltaba de allí, dijo a Pepe, empleando su lenguaje ligero y franco, entonces más franco que nunca:

--Tengo que decirte una cosa muy grave.

--¿Qué?

--He hecho un descubrimiento: que tú no me quieres y que yo te quiero mucho más de lo que me
figuraba.

--No te entiendo.

--Clarito, hijo; que tu amor--emplearemos esta palabra, para mayor solemnidad, aunque ya sabes
que a mí me gusta más decir cariño--pues bien, que tu amor es mucho más tibio que el mío.

--Veamos cómo se demuestra ese grandísimo embuste.

--De un modo muy sencillo. Pase que siempre me estés aburriendo con lo de ser yo rica y tú
pobre, por supuesto, que no me ofendo; pase la manía de los celitos, que no tienen sentido
común; pase el estarte sin venir tres y cuatro días seguidos, para que te espere con más deseo...

--No: por miedo a que tu padre adivine lo que ocurre.

--Déjame acabar: lo que no pasa, es que tengas disgustos, que estés apesadumbrado y me lo calles.
¿Tan tonta soy, que no sirvo para decirte ni una palabra de consuelo?

--¿Y qué tiene que ver esta ternura, alma mía, con el descubrimiento?

--Pues no puede estar más a la vista. Que tú, sufriendo y ocultándomelo, revelas una falta
grande de confianza, que es falta de cariño; y yo, aquejerándome, como dicen en Andalucía,
por tu reserva, demuestro quererte mil veces más.

--Pero, ¿de dónde has sacado tú que tengo disgustos?

--Eso te faltaba, añadir el disimulo a la falta de confianza. ¿No quieres decirme lo que te pasa?

Pepe, que prefería hablar sólo de su amor, o que se había propuesto callar interioridades de
su casa, contestó negando, y Paz acabó por decirle:

--Si crees que es mera curiosidad, no despliegues los labios; pero conste: quedo en libertad
para averiguarlo.

--Averigua lo que se te antoje, pero quiéreme mucho.

La entrada de don Luis cortó el diálogo. Paz se había propuesto saber a qué atenerse respecto
al origen de la tristeza de Pepe, y cuando una mujer enamorada forma resolución semejante,
el secreto puede darse por descubierto. La obstinación de Pepe en callar fue inútil: Paz puso
tanto empeño en saber los disgustos de su amante, como éste en seguir paso a paso los incomprensibles
manejos del cura.

XVII

Cuando Pepe dejaba de ir a ver a Paz, por miedo a infundir sospechas o parecer pegajoso a don
Luis, entraba Pateta en funciones de correo: ya sabía ella que cada tercer día de ausencia
el chico rondaba al oscurecer los alrededores del hôtel y, espiando momento oportuno, metía
el brazo por la verja y dejaba la carta bajo los ladrillos levantados del horno, situado junto
al invernadero.

Una tarde en que don Luis tuvo que asistir a un banquete político, Paz, después de verle partir
y tras alejar con distintos pretextos a los criados, bajó al jardín entre dos luces y aguardó
a Pateta. Al cuarto de hora vio al muchacho que venía aproximándose disimuladamente a la verja,
dando puntapiés a un bote de hoja de lata que encontró allí cerca: entonces ella se ocultó
tras uno de los pilares de mampostería que había en los ángulos del invernáculo y, cuando el
chico se acercó a meter la mano por entre los barrotes de la verja, salió de su escondite,
diciendo:

--Oye, Pateta.

--Guárdese Vd. esta carta no la vean.

--No hay nadie.

Pateta, gorra en mano, arrimando el rostro a los hierros, como mono enjaulado, prestó atención.

Lo apartado del sitio y lo desapacible de la tarde, hacían que reinara en torno del hôtel completa
soledad. En la atmósfera flotaban los últimos resplandores del sol ya puesto, y la árida campiña
aparecía envuelta en una claridad medrosa, mientras al lado opuesto se iba extendiendo una
ancha faja oscura, que se dilataba lentamente por el cielo. El traje de Paz formaba una mancha
clara cortada por los hierros de la verja: Pateta se comía con los ojos a la señorita, sin
adivinar lo que querría decirle.

--Pues a estas horas, estando esto tan solitario--dijo de pronto--ya podía el señor Pepe venir
aquí y hablar con usted.

--Cállate y escucha. Con quien quiero hablar ahora, es contigo.

--Mande Vd.

--¿Eres capaz de hacerme un favor? La verdad, y sin que nadie se entere.

--¿Ni el señor Pepe?

--Menos que nadie.

El chico la lanzó una mirada que no pudo ser más expresiva. Paz comprendió que quizá hacía
mal; pero ya no era posible retroceder.

--Te advierto que se trata de algo que nos interesa mucho a él y a mí.

--No hay más que hablar.

Pero esta sumisión fue acompañada del firme propósito de contárselo todo a Pepe.

--Vamos a ver: ¿Qué le pasa? ¿Qué disgusto es el que tiene? ¿Sabes algo?

--Nada, ni jota.

--Es necesario que lo averigües. Temo que le quiten el destino que tiene en la biblioteca del
Senado, y quisiera estar prevenida para parar el golpe. ¿Sabes tú si es esa la razón de que
esté hace ya muchos días tan tristón? ¿De veras no puedes decirme nada?

Pateta cayó en la red.

--Yo, de eso del destino, no sé ná: preguntaré. Por lo demás, no sé qué le pué haber pasao.
En la imprenta todo anda como siempre... Como no sea por lo del cura...

--¿Qué dices de imprenta? ¿Qué imprenta es esa?

--¡Toma! ¿Cuál ha de ser? La nuestra, es decir, la del señor Millán.

--¿De modo que el señorito trabaja también en la imprenta?

--Como que es el primer corretor y le dan deciocho riales, y eso que no va más que por las
noches. ¿No lo sabía Vd.?

Paz, temerosa de que Pateta se escamara, le dijo, mintiendo:

--Sí, hombre, ¿no he de saberlo? Pero creía que se llevaba el trabajo a su casa.

--¡Quiá, no señora! tié que hacerlo allí.

--Y eso del cura, ¿qué es?

--Su hermano, ¿está Vd.? es cura y ha venío hace cosa de dos meses; y como es cura y muy carca,
les está golviendo tarumba, y trae la casa patas arriba; quié que vayan a misa, que recen más
que un ciego; en fin, que no le puén aguantar... ni yo tampoco.

--¿Por qué?

--Hasta conmigo se ha metío el muy lioso. El domingo pasao tuve yo que ir a trabajar medio
día, porque había prisas, y luego le yevé al señor Pepe unas pruebas a su casa; y como era
domingo, y yo, aunque me esté mal el decirlo, soy corneta del batallón de Voluntarios de la
Libertad de mi barrio, fui de uniforme, pá no tener que andar dos veces el camino. El cura
estaba en la puerta, quiso que le dejara las pruebas y, como yo no le conocía y tenía orden
de ver al mismo señor Pepe, ¿está Vd.? no me dio la gana. Mire Vd., señorita, se puso hecho
una fiera, y lo que me dio rabia fue que me se rió del uniforme: me llamó mamarracho, y dijo
que me fuera a estudiar la dotrina. Yo, la verdad, como aún no sabía que era hermano del señor
Pepe... Vamos, que me despaché a mi gusto: le llamé cucaracha, carca, tóo lo que me se ocurrió.

--¿Y dices que ese hermano trae revuelta la familia?

--¡Ya lo creo! Si no fuera por miedo a dar una pesadumbre al señor viejo, ya le había don Pepe
plantao en mitá el arroyo. Figúrese Vd., señorita, que una de las cosas que más rabia le han
dao al señor Pepe, ha sido que ha hecho reñir... Verá Vd.: la señorita Leocadia se hablaba
con el señor Millán, mi amo; vamos, que eran novios, como quien dice, y el cura ha metío zizaña
y los ha desapartao. Por supuesto, que no estarían muy encariñaos, porque no hubieran reñido
así... tan fácilmente, ¿verdad?

--Pero tu amo y el señorito Pepe no han reñido.

--¡Quiá! ¿No ve Vd. que los dos están convencíos de que la culpa es del cura? A la madre la
tié tonta a fuerza de rezos... ¡Ya sabe el señor Pepe a qué atenerse!

--¡Sí que son motivos de disgusto!

--Fuera de eso--continuó Pateta--siempre ha estado de buen humor: hasta cuando tuvo que dejar
la carrera, que a poco entró en la imprenta... y como si ná: él, en trabajando, ya está contento.
No sabe Vd. la vida que yeva: él aquí con su papá de Vd., él en la imprenta, él en el destino
que ice Vd. que le quién quitar. Es una fiera pá el trabajo, y cuanto gana, a su casita. No
gasta más que en tabaco y algún realejo que me da pá mí.

--Vaya, adiós; vete, no sea que nos vean--añadió Paz, alargándole en la mano una monedita de
dos duros.

Pateta, sin desasirse de la verja, repuso sonriendo, y con entonación muy achulada:

--¡Quiá!

--¡No seas niño, toma!

--¡Quiá, no, señorita!; ¡si yo hago lo que hago por el señor Pepe; pero a mí no me da Vd. ni
eso, ni tan siquiera un chavo!

Paz seguía con la moneda en la mano, más avergonzada que el chico.

--¿Me haces un feo?

--Eso no: y pá que vea Vd., deme usted esa rosa que tiene Vd. prendida en el pecho: luego yo
se la doy a mi novia: Vd. tendrá muchas así, y de esas no se venden en la calle.

Paz, movida de un sentimiento de mujeril delicadeza, corrió a la estufa, cortó dos magníficas
rosas y, dándoselas al chico, además de la que llevaba prendida, le dijo:

--Estas dos, las mayores, para tu novia: esta otra pequeña, la que yo tenía puesta, para Pepe:
¿entiendes? ¿Conque tienes novia?

--Pues, ¿qué cree Vd., señorita, que soy de palo? Entendido: las mayores pá mi chiquiya, y
la otra pá el señor Pepe.

--Adiós, y de lo que hemos hablado antes, ni una palabra... chitito.

--Corriente: quede Vd. con Dios, señorita, y gracias.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00376</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>287311</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20926</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> When we said goodbye in the hallway The
question that was due that and was evasive. In this came out of his room Tirso and, as one is
aware of what you hear try, I said :--«¿ to insist? Can not you see that not read indecency?
"

- What you say?

- For your brother and your home!

Shut up and leave, but, I confess, I wanted to put him a volume by
the snout.

The least has figured the man who took the girl books wrong gender!

- What an ass!

- Not the best. It was the first time Leo and I parted well, slightly less than bothered, and
I could not wait to return on Monday. Do you remember that afternoon was the pretext test and
was talking to her?

- Go on: what did he say?

- Man, there are things that can not be explained point by point.

You understand the difference you there to be a loving woman, who
exudes the satisfaction of being loved, to be cold, aloof, and who
does not care less about the man next to him.

- As one of two things:
either you're wrong, and there is nothing that suspicion, or is Tirso
guilt, and in this case, no doubt in my house is going to be more
civil war in the North.

- Much I fear, and about what we were talking,
I think Leo is no longer for me.

- Come with care.

Do you have any trouble, some wheeling and dealing that she has known
for angry?

- No: word of honor.

- Well, since I put the record straight.

-
I warn you one thing.

I did not think the matter further formalize ... for lack of rooms; but since things have
been filmed, stating that your father and you can consider me, if you like, and the house,
you know? - and tended to Pepe's hand, he warmly shook .-- Since you know, as is customary titles: I
beg the hand ...

- I promise we will leave doubts.

- What are you doing?

- Soon I
will be able, or clearing the situation.

In the first conversation you have with Tirso I remove the mask. We'll see who has the upper
hand!

Next step quickened, spreading to reach street near the keypad, where fired, leaving some hopeful
Millán offered intervention. Pepe entered its house on tiptoe, slowly opened, not to awaken
the sleepers, lit the candle Leocadia left to prevent a wing of the hall, he entered his room
and lay down, thinking about events and ideas that interested him, on suspicion that he felt for
his brother in the affection that had his parents and feared complications. Then, serenely mind,
he remembered the worsening peace and imagined note in his love. What would be the cause?
Why the girl raised in the present, far from convinced that this was crazy gave his promises more
strength and greater expression of sympathy from his eyes?

XVI

Tirso seeing the mother tended to his exhortations, not only insisted on them, but tried to
conquer the minds of Leocadia, sharpen it necessary to be so cunning, as the difference in character
between Dona Manuela and her daughter asked for different tactics. The first ceded by kindness and gentleness:
it was habit bend to the will of others. As a young man due to her husband erected after chief
Pepe family by force of circumstances, got used to looking at him as such, and was home giblets
those of her daughter, showing all be born to obey. Leocadia conditions were different: he
had headstrong genius, but without lacking respect, responding to their parents with integrity; in
their whims poor girl, had always a certain obstinacy, if he persisted in reform a suit, did not stop
to turn the pieces of fabric, to achieve what he wanted; liking styling, could not find peace
until her hands got to learn how to make him, and even in these small details, the tenacity
of its resolutions, betrayed a very firm deploying energy difficult to master. Tirso also noted
that, in spite of its humble situation, the girl was rather vain and was paid him, charging
different Still, the eagerness to please, and as a latent desire, but self-indulgent, to imitate
clothing and customs of girls more favored by fortune. Never consented to, for example, to make
his brother blouses to work in print, and was constantly at the next corner store with tissue in
the head, Pepe wanted to see the best dress possible, and in their costumes own, still struggling
with lack of money for frills and frippery, always tried to imitate elegant cuts. By not having
them gold, had no outstanding ears and fingers without rings. It was not demanding too expensive
to ask what the efforts of their parents, but only accepted poverty as an accident of his life,
not as a condition of their origin. Willingly admitted Miller's love, while this year with Pepe's
career, but seeing her boyfriend had to leave the books and engage in a trade, was for her
very great disappointment. To continue his brother in college, perhaps soon had sought to break
relations with the printer, but seeing Pepe forced to do the same soon after, realized Leocadia
why could not reject Millán, and continued to accept his love, without correspondence that actually
paid it deserved the name of love. Perhaps for lack of background, no Tirso was in a position to appreciate
all this, but enough to convince reached that neither Leocadia was truly in love, and cast off
by the shameless Miller greed language called a proportion, which allowed him to imagine that
if the mother ceded by docility, vanity and self-esteem would be good ways to subdue daughter. I would
rather he take pity in their hearts with the vehemence of zeal inflamed him, but he realized that
he was forced to follow the maximum bend to the nature and character of every sinner, to become
more likely. Finally, many days talking to Dona Manuela, determined to probe to Leocadia, and
finding it an evening reading in the dining room, while Don José rested and mother was out,
approached, bringing him another book in hand.

- Know God - the said between severe and smiling - what tome that will be! Is it that brings you
the groom?

- Yes.

- Lovely role for a young man attempting readings harmful to the woman he wants, and good way
to love ... if you love!

- Why do you say that?

- Calm down, child, calm down, no I mean, God forbid! that young do
not wish, what strikes me is that you love him.

- I think what I
want!

- It seems in bad kind, but what happens to your brother must
be plagadito of ideas now, and of those who do not believe in the
light of day.

Ready, it will be, too bad office has so ugly!

- The of his father ... He began studying to be a lawyer, but then
the same thing happened to Pepe.

The word office rang in the ears of Tirso Leocadia as planned.

- You will always be stuck between ordinary people, workers and laborers, then they tune your ...
but bad work is.

- But can you imagine that Millan is a porter or serene? - "She said,
laughing forcedly .-- I wrong: it's a decent guy, like Pepe, who has
to live well, working as Pepe.

- No, daughter, and Pepe, no, our
brother is the son of a public official, the father of that young,
if I heard correctly, was a compositor, a laborer.

- Printer.

-
Call it what you want.

Being old, was the owner of the printing press, but its origin can
not be more humble.

That does not mean it is bad person, but, finally, why do you dislike we covet for you the best?

Leocadia
looked at his brother, surprised that and worry about their future.

- What I tell you - continued the priest - is that, so young, and
collecting terms Women are key to healthy prosperity, should not a
formal commitment lower man to you, because I do not deny it.

Position has perhaps better off than ours, but one thing is the welfare, and another area
of ??each. Today, we have money, but not our parents or our grandparents were artisans. Believe
me, Leocadia do not commit yourself to anyone, and not give up your freedom of action. No you're
born to women a laborer.

- Dale with journeyman! is an industry, we, a printer, but not a laborer.

- Bah! my dear: let us call things by their names.

Worker is only worker and if you marry him, God knows you have to go some day to take the food
basket as a bricklayer.

- So, according to you, I expect you to come and ask for my hand a degree of Castile.

- Not at all: it seems that even a good guy, is not justified to give
up on it's what you reserve for the future.

Nobody knows what the future for a girl.

Tired Leocadia knew that after that problematic hope of future greatness, which Tirso real impetus
was the antipathy felt against Millan, since he met in politics and lack of religion coincided with
Pepe, but as these same arguments He claimed to be the ever own, succeed in putting pressure
on the heart. It seemed undeniable Millán goodness, but Tirso was partly right. The touch with
the people in the press had given his harsh frankness tinge, sometimes bordering on rudeness, his
feelings served honored coarse language interpreter, to see something neat and composed, it
was necessary wait till Sunday: have not walked Tirso misguided and, in time, she had to bring
in the food basket, resigned to be a craftswoman, ie the opposite
type that of the girls, whose manners and clothes tried to imitate.

At different times her sister did Tirso similar reasoning, and as the ground was well prepared, the
seed began to germinate. It started the turn, the first thing he was to prevent often Millán
visits during the week, based on borrowing books: then came the scene narrated by the lover
scorned Pepe, which intervened Tirso and finally, the girl so strongly stressed his indifference,
the bridegroom almost stopped deserve this name. To be the love of deep-rooted passion Millán, had
been striving to regain what they lost, but he also beat a fund and exaggerated self-esteem,
that was of greater account of the pride that the baby .-- "Do not
talk about this to your sister - had told his friend - because the
will is not imposed or received anything for charity.

"

That was a very bad impression Pepe, but even more displeased to see the intervention demonstrated
the cure. The thing was out of doubt: after trying to seize the spirit of the mother, began to explore
various means of a daughter for the same purpose. What would their ulterior motives? Reasons of
personal convenience, apparently none. The only plausible that work was driven not only by religious
proselytizing, and in this case, to commit company in the peace and happiness of the family,
their fanaticism would be great. How risk, in any other way, promoting a rift between parents
and children, venturing the tranquility of home and the poor health of Don Jose, for only the lack
of compliance by the pious duties? Pepe hated it so much, given his ideas that he could not
be attributed to his brother so great blindness, assuming that if only the zeal prompted him, had
moderate affects more mundane but no less pure. His understanding rejected the possibility that
there man to embarrass their parents to give luster to the religion. The nonchalance with which
Millán Leocadia and began to look lost with this significance in the eyes of Pepe: Her True
concern was the conduct of Tirso, and came to dislike so much that
I threw his beloved Peace to see immediately.

       

* * * * *

First, a romantic spirit, typical of free-educated girl, she becomes infatuated to Peace with the
love of Pepe: later, when he came to understand how much he was worth, that tilt insensibly deepened
and, at the beginning was game of the imagination, came to be, the more natural, simple, sincere
and well-rooted love. The clerk, as she imagined her friends would call him if they should know, he had
entered the soul, persuading that he wanted because his face began to fear that his father would
know that, despite Democratic Posturing I used to do in Parliament. But this was not what most
distress. Their concern stemmed from disgruntled continually see Pepe, and the conviction of
being in love came out of that relationship he established his mind between the pity she felt
and concern he showed. When peace was made aware that, even ignoring the cause, despite saddened
by her boyfriend, when, unable weighed, felt a pain of others as their own, then noticed that
his heart began to reign a will different from his, and the man, only with loyalty and good faith,
was taking over his will slowly but probably as large river channel deepens the underpinning.
Peace, apparently frivolous, like anyone who has not suffered, but very clever, was persuaded
early on that loved, because his thoughts, far from intimidated to the obstacles that could
love cause it was fixed exclusively on the pain of the man he wanted.

The first sample true passion was the sincerity with which he spoke.

One morning, being in the library of his father, who was where whenever
he saw one missing from there, "said Pepe, mild language and using
its free, then more open than ever:

- I have to tell you something
very serious.

- What?

- I made a discovery: you do not want me and
I love you more than me contained.

- I do not understand.

- Clarito,
son, that your love - will use this word, for greater solemnity, but
you know that I prefer to say love - well, your love is much warmer
than mine.

- Let's see how it is shown that great lie.

- In a very
simple way.

I always pass that you are bored with being rich and you me poor,
of course, that does not offend me, pass the mania of celite, which
makes no sense common choke pass without coming three to four days
in a row, so you want to wait more ...

- No, for fear that your father
guess what happens.

- Let me finish, what is not happening, is that
you have trouble, you're sorry and I streets.

So silly me, that no good to say not a word of comfort?

- What does this tenderness, my soul, with the discovery?

- Because
nothing can be more visible.

You, suffering and ocultándomelo, reveal a lack great confidence, which is lack of love, and I,
aquejerándome, as they say in Andalusia for your book, I show love a thousand times.

- But where did you get that I have trouble?

- That I was missing, add the pretense of a lack of confidence. Will
not you tell me what's wrong?

Pepe, who preferred to talk only about their love, or had proposed
internal streets of home, said denying, and ended by telling Peace:

-
If you think it is mere curiosity, it displays the lips, but stating:
stay free to find out.

- Find out what pleases you, but love me a
lot.

The entrance of Don Luis cut dialogue. Proposed peace knowing what to expect regarding the
origin of the sadness of Pepe, and when a woman in love with a similar
resolution, the secret can be overdraft.

Pepe's obstinacy in silence was useless: Peace has so hard to know
the troubles of her lover, as this step by step in the incomprehensible
handling of the priest.

XVII

When Pepe kept going to see peace, for fear or look tacky if suspected
Don Luis, came Pateta in mail functions: she knew that every third
day of absence the boy was about to darken around the hotel and, peering
right time, got arm through the gate and left the letter under the
raised brick kiln, located along the greenhouse.

One afternoon, Don Luis had to attend a political banquet, Peace, after seeing him from and
after going on various pretexts to the servants, fell into the garden at twilight, and waited
to Pateta. Quarter hour saw the boy coming stealthily approaching the gate, kicking a tin pot he found
nearby, so she hid after one of the pillars of masonry that were
in the corners of the greenhouse and, when boy went to put my hand
through the bars of the gate, came out of hiding, saying

- Hey, pathetic.

-
Beware you will not see this letter.

- Nobody.

Pateta, hat in hand, snuggling his face to the bars, like a monkey cage, paid attention.

The remoteness of the site and dreary afternoon, were to reign around the full hôtel loneliness.
In the air floated the last rays of sun set, and the arid countryside
appeared wrapped in a fearful clarity, while the opposite was extending
a broad dark band, which expands slowly across the sky.

The suit was a stain Peace clear cut by the bars of the gate: pathetic ogling Miss no guess what
he would say.

- Well, at this hour, this being so lonely - he suddenly - and Mr. Pepe could come here and
talk to you.

- Shut up and listen.

I want to talk now, it's you.

- Send you

- Can you do me a favor?

The truth, and without anyone knowing.

- Neither Mr. Pepe?

- Less
than anyone else.

The boy glanced could not be more expressive. Was realized that maybe peace wrong, but it was not going
back.

- I warn you that this is something we are very interested in him and me.

- No more to say.

But this submission was accompanied by the firm intention to tell
everything to Pepe.

- Let's see what happens?

What is the one with disgust? You know something?

- Nothing, not Jack.

- We need to find out.

I fear that you remove the destination you have in your library Senate, and would be prevented
to stop the coup.

Do you know whether that is the reason that For many days are so sad?

You really can not tell me anything?

Pateta fell into the net.

- Yo, that's destiny, I do not know ná:
ask.

Otherwise, you may not know what had happen. In the press everything is as usual ... As it is
not the cure ...

- How about printing?

Printing What is this?

- Takes! What could it be?

Ours, that is, Mr. Miller.

- So the Master is also working on printing?

- As it is the first Corretor and give deciocho materials, and that
which goes no further than the nights.

Did not you know you?

Paz, fearful that Pateta flake, he said, lying:

- Yeah, man, do not
I know?

But I thought labor was carried home.

- Who, no ma'am! TAR do it there.

- And that the priest, what is?

- His brother, are you? is cured and has come about two months ago, and as a cure and very carca,
they are Golven Tarumba, and brings the house upside down, Quie to go to Mass, to pray more
a blind man, in short, that bridge will not hold ... nor I either.

- Why?

- To me it has got the very messy.

Pasao Sunday I had to go to work part day, because there was a hurry,
and then Mr. Pepe yevé home tests, and as was Sunday, and I, though
I say it is wrong, I'm battalion bugler volunteers Freedom in my neighborhood,
I was in uniform, PA does not have to walk the path twice.

The priest was at the door, wanted to let him test and, as I did not know him and had orders to
see the same man Pepe, are you? I felt like it. Look you, Miss, was made a beast, and what I
got angry was that I laughed at the uniform, I called bullshit, and said I would study the
doctrine. I, the truth, and still did not know who was the brother of Mr. Pepe ... Come on, I sent
my taste: I called cockroach, carca, too so I was happened.

- You say that revolt brother brings the family?

- You bet!

If not for fear of giving grief to a old man, and had Don Pepe Mita Creek Plant. Imagine you,
miss, that one of the things that have rabies Mr. Pepe harm has been
done to fight ... You will see: Miss Leocadia spoken with Mr. Miller,
my love, come on, they were married, as they say, and the cure has
got tares and has desapartao.

Of course, that would not be very encariñaos, because they had not
fought well ... so easily, right?

- But your love and Master Pepe
have not fought.

- Who!

Can not you see that the two are convinced that the fault is the cure? The mother Tié foolish
by dint of prayers ... You know Mr. Pepe where you are coming!

- Yes that is cause for disappointment!

- Other than that - continued Pateta - has always been in good humor even when he had to leave
the race, that soon came into the press ... and as if ná: he, in
working, and is happy.

You do not know yeva life: he here with you dad, he in the press,
he on the destination that ice you who take it.

Pa is a fierce work, and how much you earn, your house.

No spends more than snuff and it gives me some realejo possesses
me.

- Well, goodbye, go, lest we see - Peace said, handing in his
hand is a tiny two dollars.

Pateta, without detachment from the gate, said smiling, and intonation
very Achille:

- Who!

- Do not be a child, take it!

- Who, no, miss,
if I do what I do for Mr. Pepe, but I do not give you or So not even
a guy!

Peace was the coin in hand, more embarrassed than the lad.

- Do me a ugly?

- That no: and PAs see you, give me that rose that has you pinned
to his chest, then I I give to my girlfriend: You will have many like
that, and those not sold on the street.

Peace, moved by a sense of feminine delicacy, ran to the stove, cut
two magnificent roses, and gave the boy, as well as wearing garments,
said:

- These two, the highest, for your girlfriend this one small,
which I wore for Pepe: Do you understand?

"So you have a girlfriend?

- Well, what do you, Miss, I am to stick?
Understood: the largest pa mi chiquiya and the other Pá Mr. Pepe.

-
Bye, and what we talked about earlier, not a word ... chitito.

-
Current: God is with you, miss, and thanks</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>