<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02868</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>4260</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>747</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Mi madre, que era discreta y callada, o
no sabía o aparentaba no saber del San Vicente sino el nombre del autor, su mérito como objeto
de arte y la inmediata procedencia por donde llegó a sus manos. De sobra reconocía además,
y no lo disimulaba, que el artista había tomado para modelo de su Santo el bello y noble rostro
del marqués, marido de ella, y le había retratado con fidelidad pasmosa.

En varias conversaciones que tuve con el Padre Atanasio, ya muy viejo y que me estimaba y quería
mucho, logré entender y rehacer en mi mente la historia toda de la imagen y de cuanto a ella
se refiere. Y como es curioso y no redunda en perjuicio, sino más bien en honra de mi padre,
voy a dejarlo consignado por escrito en el archivo de nuestra casa.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05313</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>95839</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>710</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> My mother, who was discreet and quiet, or
did not know or pretended not to know the San Vicente but the name of the author, his merit as
an object art and the immediate source from which he came across. Plenty of well recognized,
and not concealed, that the artist had taken to model their beautiful and noble Holy Face the Marquis,
her husband, and had portrayed with astonishing fidelity.

In several conversations I had with Father Athanasius, very old and that I believed and wanted
much, I came to understand and remake in my mind the whole history of the image and how much
it concerns. And it's funny and does not prejudice, but rather in
honor of my father I'll leave it written down in our house file</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>