<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08295</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>4938</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22977</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

CAPÍTULO III

     Y al compás se agitaban mil bellezas
      Que ropajes fantásticos vestían,
      Y a mí cual las visiones se ofrecían
      De un poeta oriental.

         R. PALMA

Aquella noche[30] el teatro de la elegancia habanera sentó sus reales en la Sociedad Filarmónica.
Brillaron allí con todo su esplendor el gusto y la finura de las señoras, lo mismo que el porte
decente de los caballeros. Además de los socios y convidados de costumbre, asistieron los señores
cónsules de las naciones extranjeras, los oficiales de la guarnición y de la real Marina, los
ayudantes del Capitán General y algunos otros personajes notables por su carácter y circunstancias,
como fueron el hijo del célebre Mariscal Ney, que estaba viajando, y el cónsul de Holanda en
Nueva York.

Hiciéronse notables los vestidos de tul bordados de plata y oro sobre fondo de raso blanco,
por ser de última moda e iguales al que Mme. Minette hizo en París para la actual soberana
de España. Las mangas de este traje conocidas con el nombre de a la Cristina, eran cortas,
abobadas y guarnecidas su parte inferior con encaje muy ancho. También se vieron otros de tul
bordados con muchísima delicadeza, sobre fondo celeste. Llamaron así mismo la atención general
los vestidos de tul sobre raso blanco con guarnición en puntas encontradas, adornadas éstas
de encaje estrecho y mangas a la Cristina. Otros iguales a estos últimos, pero con diferentes
guarniciones, pudieron señalarse, sin que dejase de haber muchos más cuya elegancia y gusto
en nada desmerecían de los ya descritos.

Los peinados armonizaban con los vestidos. Llevaban unas turbantes egipcios, otras plumas blancas
puestas con mucho donaire; las más, jirafas de todos tamaños, adornadas con flores azules o
blancas, guardando unión con el color del traje, y algunas tenían lazos de oro graciosamente
colocados. Era grandioso y bello el efecto que producía la reunión de tantas y tan hermosas
lechuguinas. Animaba la concurrencia una completa alegría, y rebosaba la sonrisa en los labios
de todos. La etiqueta, que generalmente caracteriza a los bailes de la Sociedad, no se vio
más que en los vestidos de las señoras y en los trajes de los hombres, los cuales lucieron
a porfía sus recamados uniformes de gentiles-hombres, de generales, de brigadieres, de coroneles,
de altos empleados, Cadaval y Lemaur sus fajas rojas de seda, al paso que los que no poseían
título ni condecoraciones se contentaron con la última moda de París en semejantes reuniones.

Adornaba la testera principal de la sala el magnífico dosel, cuyo centro ocupaba el retrato
del rey Fernando VII. Los paños de la pared sostenían cuadros históricos y de las cornisas
pendía una colgadura de damasco azul con pabellones blancos guarnecidos de vistosos flecos
de seda, sostenida por adornos dorados y clavos romanos, de los cuales caían con gracia cordones
y borlones de seda. El cielo raso de la sala estaba vestido de damasco del mismo color de la
colgadura.

Cosa de las diez empezó el baile y a las once el salón principal estaba completamente lleno.
En los intermedios servían sorbetes y refrescos de todas clases en grandes bandejas de plata
sostenidas por lacayos. Las señoras que preferían tomarlos fuera del salón tenían preparada
para este efecto una sala alumbrada perfectamente, en donde estaba la repostería y criados
prontos para servirlas; pero la política y la urbanidad de los socios y convidados les ahorró
un trabajo que para los caballeros se convierte en placer cuando se emplea en servicio de las
damas.

La cena se principió entre doce y una de la madrugada, y consistía en pavo fiambre, jamón de
Westfalia, queso, gigote excelente, ropa-vieja, dulces secos, conservas, vinos generosos de
España y extranjeros, chocolate suculento, café y frutas de todos los países en comercio con
la isla de Cuba. Y fue lo más notable que, compitiendo la esplendidez de la mesa con su pródiga
abundancia, los manjares no costaban sino el trabajo de pedirlos.

Puede afirmarse sin temor de ser desmentidos que la elegancia y la belleza de La Habana se
habían dado cita aquella noche en la Sociedad Filarmónica. Porque allí estaba la marquesa de
Arcos, hija del famoso marqués Pedro Calvo, con Luisa, su hija mayor, entonces de quince años
de edad. Por ésta había improvisado Plácido aquellos versos que dicen:

      Andaba revoloteando
    En el ambiente exquisito,
    Muerto de sed un mosquito,
    Jugo de flores buscando;
    Llegó a tu boca, y pensando
    Que era una rosa o clavel,
    Introduciéndose en él,
    Porque allí el placer le encanta
    Murió en tu dulce garganta,
    Como en un vaso de miel.

Allí las hermanas Chacón, que merecieron por su hermosura figurar en el gran lienzo pintado
por Vermay[31] para perpetuar la memoria de la misa que se celebró en la inauguración del Templete
de la Plaza de Armas. Allí las Montalvo, de tipo teutónico, una de las cuales fue declarada
reina de la belleza, cuando la corrida de cañas el año anterior, en la antigua plaza de Toros
del Campo de Marte; allí la Arango, célebre por haber contribuido a la evasión del poeta Heredia,
y que después se casó con un Ayudante de campo del Capitán General Ricafort; allí las hermanas
Aceval, Venus de Milo en las formas, tan distinguidas por su talento como desdichadas por sus
pasiones; allí las hermanas Alcázar, modelos de perfección, así por la simetría de sus menudas
facciones, como por las rosas de sus mejillas y el color negro de sus cabellos; allí las Junco
y las Lamar, de Matanzas, conocidas bajo el poético vocativo de las Ninfas del Yumurí; allí
las tres hermanas de Gamboa, las cuales ya hemos tenido ocasión de describir; allí la Topete,
hija del Comandante general del Apostadero de La Habana, que más adelante inspiró a Palma su
inmortal «Quince de Agosto», allí la menor de las Gámez, Venus de Belvedere, cuyo cabello castaño,
ondulante y copioso, llevaba suelto sembrado de estrellas de oro; allí, en fin, entre otras
muchas que sería prolijo enumerar, Isabel Ilincheta, hija del que había sido asesor del Capitán
General Someruelos, quien poseía los rasgos principales del tipo severo y modesto celtíbero,
a que debía su origen.

Como modelos de varonil belleza, entre los jóvenes concurrentes al baile de la Sociedad aquella
noche, pudiera hacerse mención del Teniente coronel de Lanceros del Rey, Rafael de la Torre,
quien unos días después murió estrellado contra las ruedas de los quitrines en el Paseo, junto
a la estatua de Carlos III, víctima de la fogosidad de su caballo; Bernardo Echeverría y O'Gabán,
que en los días de gala gustaba vestir el uniforme de gentil-hombre de Cámara con entrada,
por cuanto podía lucir las bien hechas y rollizas piernas; Ramón Montalvo, en la flor de su
edad, bello como un inglés de la más pura sangre; José Gastón, el verdadero Apolo de Cuba;
Dionisio Mantilla, recién llegado de Francia, que venía hecho un cumplido parisiense; Diego
Duarte, el feliz campeón de las corridas de cañas celebradas el año anterior, con motivo de
las nupcias de Fernando VII con María Cristina de Nápoles; varios oficiales de la marina y
del ejército español en sus vistosos uniformes, más propios de una parada que de un baile particular.

También contribuyó al lustre de la fiesta la presencia de algunos jóvenes que empezaban a distinguirse
en el cultivo de las letras, a saber: Palma, que había sido uno de los competidores en la corrida
de cañas; Echeverría empleado en la Hacienda, que el año siguiente alcanzó el premio en el
concurso poético abierto por la Comisión de Literatura, con objeto de celebrar el nacimiento
de la Infanta de Castilla, Isabel de Borbón; Valdés Machuca, conocido por Desval en la república
de las letras; Policarpo Valdés, que se firmaba Polidoro; Anacleto Bermúdez, que solía publicar
versos bajo el nombre de Delicio; Manuel Garay y Heredia, que imprimía sus versos en La Aurora
de Matanzas; Vélez Herrera, el autor del romance cubano Elvira de Oquendo; Delio, el cantor
de las ruinas del Alhambra; Domingo André, joven abogado, elocuente y amable; Domingo del Monte,
que introdujo el romance cubano, de variados conocimientos y muy distinguido porte.

Diego Meneses, Francisco Solfa, Leonardo Gamboa y otros varios, que también se hallaban en
el baile, si se exceptúan el segundo que era dado a los estudios filosóficos, y el tercero
que entraba ya en la clase rica, no se hacían notables por su talento, aunque los tres solían
escribir en los periódicos literarios; y el último pasaba, además, por mozo de buen parecer
y varoniles formas. Los literatos, mejor dicho, los aficionados a las letras, sobre todo los
que cultivaban la poesía, empezaban a tener entrada con la gente que podía tenerse por noble
en Cuba, o que aspiraba, por su caudal, a la nobleza y alternaba con ella. Mostraban al menos
distinción por ellos algunas familias tituladas de La Habana y los atraían a sus fiestas y
reuniones, entre otras, por ejemplo, los condes de Fernandina, los de Casa Bayona, los de Casa
Peñalver, los marqueses de Montehermoso y los de Arco. Dichas fiestas y reuniones en los días
de pascuas de navidad se trasladaban a los lindísimos cafetales de San Antonio, de Alquízar,
de San Andrés y de la Artemisa, que pertenecían a la gente rica.

No se presentaron en los salones de la Sociedad nuestros amigos Gamboa, Meneses y Solfa, sino
hasta cerca de las once de la noche. Durante las primeras horas habían estado visitando los
bailes de la feria del Ángel, el de Farruco y el de Brito, sin olvidar la cuna de la gente
de color, en la calle del Empedrado, entre Compostela y Aguacate. En ninguno de esos sitios
habían tomado ellos parte activa, si se exceptúa el primero, quien al juego del monte perdió
en un instante las dos onzas de oro que aquella misma tarde le había metido su madre en el
bolsillo del chaleco. No conocía el valor del dinero, ni jugaba por amor a la ganancia, sino
por el placer de la excitación del momento; pero sucedió que los bailes no le prestaron atractivo
ninguno, desertados de las muchachas bonitas; que no logró ver a Cecilia Valdés en la ventana
de la casa, ni en la cuna, cosas todas que se conspiraron para ponerle de malísimo humor. Para
remate de desdichas, cuando perdidoso y disgustado volvía con sus amigos en busca del quitrín,
que había dejado apostado en la calle del Aguacate al abrigo de las altas paredes del convento
de Santa Catalina, descubrió que no estaba allí, ni fue posible encontrarle sino media hora
después y en punto opuesto y distante.

Por otra parte, preguntado el calesero sobre el motivo que le indujo a desobedecer una orden
terminante de su joven amo, dio al principio respuestas evasivas, y al fin, apretado, dijo
que un desconocido, medio cubierto el rostro con un pañuelo, le había forzado a abandonar el
puesto y fingir que se volvía a casa, valiéndose de amenazas terribles. No parecía creíble
el cuento: hubo empero que aceptarlo como bueno y verídico; lo que, si cabe, aumentó el mal
humor de Leonardo, porque en caso de ser cierta la relación del calesero, ¿quién podía ser
ese sujeto, ni qué interés tener en que el carruaje aguardase en una u otra esquina de la calle?
¿Por qué emplear amenazas? ¿Qué autoridad tenía para ello? Aponte no pudo decir si el desconocido
era militar o paisano, comisario de barrio o magistrado, hombre blanco o de color. Tal vez
era un inesperado y desconocido rival que de aquel modo se preparaba a disputarle el cariño
de Cecilia Valdés.

Corroboraba tan desagradable sospecha, el hecho de que ni ella, ni su amiga Nemesia se habían
presentado en parte alguna de la feria del Ángel. Además de eso, la circunstancia de no haber
abierto la ventana, aún cuando Gamboa hizo la señal convenida pasando la punta del bastón por
los pocos balaustres que aún le quedaban, casi no dejaba duda de que algo extraordinario había
ocurrido en el humilde y oscuro hogar.

Mas sea de esto lo que se fuere, que no hay tiempo de verificarlo ahora, Leonardo Gamboa entró
en el baile de la Filarmónica preocupado y de muy mal talante. Armada sin embargo la danza,
en la sala principal y el aposento del palacio, bastante espaciosos por cierto, según dice
el poeta:

      Una noche por fin: entre cristales
    La luz reverberaba en los salones;
    Y la sangre inflamaba con sus sones,
    La danza tropical;

no pudo nuestro héroe sustraerse a su arrobadora influencia. La orquesta, que dirigía el célebre
violinista Ulpiano, ocupaba el anchísimo corredor sobre la mano izquierda, como se sube de
la regia escalera de piedra oscura. Luego, a la derecha, estaba la puerta del salón, enfrente
de otra que daba sobre los más amplios balcones, que formaban los portales llamados del Rosario.
Dejados los sombreros y los bastones en manos de un lacayo negro, a la puerta de un cuarto
entresuelo que abría al descanso de la escalera de doble tramo, y tendiendo la vista por el
soberbio salón, que podía tener «la carrera de un caballo», si se nos permite la exageración,
descubrieron los estudiantes que las animadas parejas le llenaban de extremo a extremo. Recibían
los hombres de espalda, y las mujeres de frente, mientras esperaban su turno para hacer cedazo,
el aire fresco de la media noche, que entraba por las puertas y ventanas abiertas de par en par.

Como hemos dicho antes, allí se hallaba reunido lo más granado y florido de la juventud cubana
de ambos sexos, entregada, por el momento al menos, con alma y cuerpo a su diversión favorita.
Y a la luz deslumbrante de las arañas de cristal, en olas de una música tan plañidera como
voluptuosa, pues que procede del corazón de un pueblo esclavizado, al través de la nube sutil
de polvo que levantaban los bailarines con los pies, las mujeres parecían más hermosas, los
hombres más bizarros. ¿Podía, pues, entregarse el ánimo de la juventud a otros pensamientos
que los que le sugerían los halagadores objetos que tenía delante? No es posible.

Gamboa se ocupó, desde luego, en buscar compañera para tomar parte en el baile, aunque no le
gustaba mucho; pero Meneses, que rara vez bailaba, y Solfa, que no bailaba nunca, se quedaron
de espectadores en el medio del salón, observando el último, con sonrisa amarga, que mientras
aquella loca juventud gozaba a sus anchas de los placeres del momento, el más estúpido y brutal
de los reyes de España parecía contemplarla con aire de profundo desprecio desde el dorado
dosel donde se veía pintada su imagen odiosa.

Andando con algún trabajo entre las apiñadas filas de espectadores y bailarines, tropezó Gamboa
con la más joven de las señoritas Gámez, cuyo retrato hemos hecho arriba a vuela pluma, en
lo más empeñado de la danza. Por todo saludo, sin dejar de girar, como una sílfide, en brazos
de su pareja, le dijo ella antes con los ojos que con la lengua:--Ahí está Isabel.

--¿Bailando? preguntó el joven.

--¡Qué bailar! Esperando por Vd.

--¿Por mí? Qué descanso el suyo. Pues por un tris no vengo al baile esta noche.

En efecto, aquella señorita se hallaba a la sazón en toda apariencia comiendo pavo, según reza
la frase vulgar en Cuba, es decir, sentada a la izquierda, cerca de la puerta del aposento
entre una señora de mediana edad y el culto abogado Domingo André, con quien sostenía animada
conversación. No obstante su natural despreocupación, sintió Gamboa un arranque de celos que
le fue imposible reprimir, no ya porque estuviese de veras enamorado, sino porque el caballero
en cuya compañía la encontraba, era asaz galán y sabía insinuarse en el ánimo de las mujeres
discretas. De paso debemos decir, sin embargo, que el norte de las galanterías de André por
aquella época, se dirigían a otra beldad muy distinta de Isabel Ilincheta, la misma que perdió
por tímido y que ganó por osado el literato dominicano Domingo del Monte, si no estamos muy
equivocados, en la noche de que estamos hablando. Por lo que hace a Isabel, recibió a Leonardo
con una sonrisa adorable, lo cual, lejos de tranquilizarle, fue parte a causarle mayor desazón.
Cambiados los saludos de costumbre, pues la compañera de Isabel, madre de las Gámez, era amiga
del joven estudiante, lo mismo que André, en prueba de que no tenía nada de coqueta, tampoco
de vengativa, dijo muy risueña:

--Decía a este caballero poco hace, que tenía comprometida esta danza, y no me quiere creer.

--Es que Vd. no ha bailado ninguna todavía, que yo sepa, repuso André.

--Cierto que dos se han bailado solamente, replicó Isabel sin cortarse, pero hasta ahora que
se baila la tercera, no ha venido Vd. a invitarme.

--Lo que quiere decir en sustancia, continuó André, que he llegado en hora menguada. ¡Cómo
ha de ser!

--Esta señorita tiene razón, interpuso Leonardo repuesto de su embarazo. Por compromiso anterior,
en cualquier baile donde nos encontremos, me reserva ella la tercera danza. No he podido llegar,
pues, a mejor hora según veo. Por eso se dice que más vale llegar a tiempo que rondar un año.

--Ya, exclamó el galante abogado, el caso es que con las buenas mozas pocos somos los que llegamos
a tiempo.

André saludó y fue a formar coro a las dos hijas del potentado Aldama, de las cuales la menor,
de nombre Lola, cedía a muy pocas aquella noche la palma codiciada de la belleza. Entretanto
Leonardo e Isabel, cogidos por la mano, se metieron en las filas de la danza, no distante de
la cabecera, mediante el favor de amigos mutuos, que, aunque llegaron tarde, no les dejaron
incorporarse a la cola, como era de rigor. La cubana danza sin duda que se inventó para hacerse
la corte los enamorados. En sí el baile es muy sencillo, los movimientos cómodos y fáciles,
siendo su objeto primordial la aproximación de los sexos, en un país donde las costumbres moriscas
tienden a su separación; en una palabra, la comunión de las almas. Porque el caballero lleva
a la dama casi siempre como en vilo, pues que mientras con el brazo derecho la rodea el talle,
con la mano izquierda la comprime la suya blandamente. No es aquello bailar, puesto que el
cuerpo sigue meramente los compases; es mecerse como en sueños, al son de una música gemidora
y voluptuosa, es conversar íntimamente dos personas queridas, es acariciarse dos seres que
se atraen mutuamente, y que el tiempo, el espacio, el estado, la costumbre ha mantenido alejados.
El estilo es el hombre, ha dicho alguien oportunamente; el baile es un pueblo, decimos nosotros,
y no hay ninguno como la danza que pinte más al vivo el carácter, los hábitos, el estado social
y político de los cubanos, ni que esté en más armonía con el clima de la Isla.

La noche en cuestión lucía Isabel Ilincheta a maravilla las gracias naturales de que la había
dotado el cielo. Era alta, bien formada, esbelta, y vestía elegantemente, conque siendo muy
discreta y amable, está dicho que debía llamar la atención de la gente culta. Hasta la suave
palidez de su rostro, la expresión lánguida de sus claros ojos y finos labios, contribuía a
hacer atractiva a una joven que, por otra parte, no tenía nada de hermosa. Su encanto consistía
en su palabra y en sus modos. Entraba en la pubertad cuando perdió a su madre, y para educarla,
lo mismo que para libertarla de los peligros del mundo, su padre la puso al cuidado de las
religiosas Ursulinas, venidas de Nueva Orleans y establecidas en su convento de puerta de Tierra
desde principios de este siglo. Después de un pupilaje de más de cuatro años, en que recibió
una educación antes religiosa que erudita y completa, se retiró al campo, en el cafetal de
su padre, cerca de la población de Alquízar, junto con su hermana menor, Rosa y una tía, viuda
de un cirujano de marina, de nombre Bohorques. Este individuo había hecho varios viajes a la
costa de África en las expediciones despachadas por cuenta de la sociedad de Gamboa y Blanco.
Contrajo de esas resultas una enfermedad terrible, murió en la travesía y le arrojaron al agua,
cual otros muchos de los infelices salvajes a quienes había ayudado a plagiar de su nativo
suelo. En más de una ocasión fue la viuda, con tal motivo, el objeto de la munificencia de
don Cándido Gamboa. Leonardo la visitó en el cafetal de Alquízar, y no pudo menos de enamorarse
de la sobrina, cuya modestia y gracias realzaban su clara inteligencia y fina discreción.

No había nada de redondez femenil, y, por supuesto, ni de voluptuosidad, ya lo hemos indicado,
en las formas de Isabel. Y la razón era obvia: el ejercicio a caballo, su diversión favorita
en el campo; el nadar frecuentemente en el río de San Andrés y en el de San Juan de Contreras,
donde todos los años pasaba la temporada de baños; las caminatas casi diarias en el cafetal
de su padre y en los de los vecinos, su exposición frecuente a las intemperies por gusto y
por razón de su vida activa, habían robustecido y desarrollado su constitución física al punto
de hacerle perder las formas suaves y redondas de las jóvenes de su edad y estado. Para que
nada faltase al aire varonil y resuelto de su persona, debe añadirse que sombreaba su boca
expresiva un bozo oscuro y sedoso, al cual sólo faltaba una tonsura frecuente para convertirse
en bigote negro y poblado. Tras ese bozo asomaban a veces unos dientes blancos, chicos y parejos,
y he aquí lo que constituía la magia de la sonrisa de Isabel.

No debe extrañarse que, siendo Leonardo un tanto descreído y despegado, sintiese pasión por
una joven tal como la que acaba de describirse. Entraba él por las puertas doradas de la vida.
A pesar de sus connotaciones y de su riqueza, no había tenido aún trato con las mujeres de
su esfera y educación, ni había empezado a buscar en ellas tampoco la compañera futura de su
vida. La aspereza suya no era sino externa, estaba en sus maneras bruscas, porque allá en el
fondo de su pecho, como habrá ocasión de observarlo, había raudal inagotable de generosidad,
ternura de sentimientos. Dios, por dicha, no le había negado la capacidad de amar, sólo que
las mujeres con quienes hasta allí había tropezado, o habían cedido a la fogosidad de sus afectos,
a la intrepidez de sus pocos años, o a la influencia de su lluvia de oro. Ninguno de estos
móviles podía tener ascendiente en el ánimo de una joven rica, bien educada, modesta y virtuosa
como Isabel Ilincheta. Atraído Leonardo primero por sus prendas físicas, seducido después por
sus relevantes dotes morales, comprendió desde luego que para ganar su afecto fuerza era tocar
su corazón, hablar a su entendimiento. Por otra parte, aquella mujer que se presentaba a los
ojos de Leonardo bajo un nuevo aspecto, habitaba el trasunto del paraíso terrenal cuando la
vio por la primera vez.

Si podemos prescindir del esclavo y de sus padecimientos, que son, sin embargo, más llevaderos
en los cafetales, se convendrá en que Isabel, su hermana Rosa, su tía doña Juana, su padre
y criados, llevaban una vida de paz y quietud, lejos del bullicio de la ciudad, rodeados de
olorosas flores, de los cafetos y naranjos siempre verdes, de las airosas palmas, del clásico
plátano, embebecidos con el canto perenne de las aves y el susurro melancólico de la brisa
en los campos de Cuba. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09332</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>66174</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20697</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

CHAPTER III

     
      And the beat fluttered thousand beauties
      Who wore fantastic costumes, And to
      me that the views offered Of an Eastern poet.

         

R. PALMA

That night [30] Theatre of Havana chose his elegance in the Philharmonic Society. Shone there
in all its splendor and fine taste of the ladies, as well as the size decent gentlemen. In addition
to the usual members and guests attended the Lords Consuls of foreign nations, the officers
of the garrison and the Royal Navy, the General Captain assistants
and some other notables for their character and circumstances as were
the son of the famous Marshal Ney, who was traveling, and the Dutch
consul in New York.

Made themselves notable tulle dresses embroidered with silver and gold on white satin background,
being trendy and equal to that Mme. Minette was in Paris for the current sovereign Spain. The
sleeves of this outfit known by the name of the Cristina, were short, Abobo and trimmed the bottom
with lace too wide. Were also other tulle delicately embroidered with a lot on blue background.
Likewise drew widespread attention tulle dresses with white satin lining on pointe found, they
adorned narrow lace sleeves to Cristina. Others like the latter, but with different fittings,
could be observed, without leave to be many more whose elegance and
taste desmerecían nothing to those already described.

Hairstyles harmonized with the clothing. Egyptians wore a turban, some white feathers very neatly
made, the most, giraffes of all sizes, decorated with blue flowers or white, keeping union
with the color of the suit, and some had gold loops gracefully placed. It was great and beautiful
the effect produced by the gathering of so many and so beautiful dandies. He encouraged the
audience a complete joy, and overflowing with the smile of all. The label, which generally
characterizes the dances of the Company was not rather than the ladies' dresses and costumes of the
men, who wore a contention his embroidered uniform gentlemen, generals, the brigadier, colonels,
senior employees, Cadaval Lemaur their red sashes and silk, whereas
those who had not title and awards were content with the latest Paris
fashion in such meetings.

Headpiece adorned the main hall the magnificent canopy, which occupied the center portrait
King Ferdinand VII. The wall panels supported historical paintings and cornices hung a curtain of
blue damask trimmed with white flags with bright fringes silk, supported by Roman gold ornaments
and nails, which fell gracefully cords and silk tassels.

The ceiling of the room was wearing the same apricot color hanging.

Began about ten o'clock and eleven dancing the main hall was completely full. In between sherbet
and soft drinks of all kinds in large silver trays supported by lackeys. The women who preferred
to take them out of the room they had prepared for this purpose a well lit room, where he was
raised pastries and ready to serve them, but the politics and manners of the members and guests
were saved a job for men becomes pleasure when used in the service
of ladies.

The dinner began between 0:01 am and consisted of turkey bologna, ham Westphalia, cheese, GIGOT
excellent garment-old, fresh, dried, preserves, liqueur wines Spain and abroad, delicious chocolate,
coffee and fruits of all countries in trade the island of Cuba.

It was most remarkable that, racing the magnificence of the table with her prodigal abundance,
but the food did not cost the job of ordering.

Can say without fear of contradiction that the elegance and beauty
of Havana had met that night at the Philharmonic Society.

      Because there was the
    Marchioness of Arcos, daughter
    of the famous Marquis de Pedro
    Calvo, Luisa, his eldest
    daughter, then fifteen years
    old. For this was improvised
    Plácido those lines:
    
    He went fluttering The exquisite
    atmosphere Parched mosquitoes, Juice of flowers looking; Came to
your mouth, and thinking That was a rose or carnation, Introduced
in it, Because there loves pleasure Sweet died in your throat, Like
a glass of honey.

Chacón sisters there, they deserved for their beauty appear on the large canvas painting by
Vermay [31] to perpetuate the memory of the mass celebrated at the opening of the Temple Plaza
de Armas. There the Montalvo, Teutonic type, one of which was declared beauty queen, when the rod
run last year, in the old Plaza de Toros Champ de Mars, where the Arango, famous for contributing
to the avoidance of the poet Heredia and then married a Captain Field Assistant General Ricafort;
there sisters Aceval, Venus de Milo in the forms, so distinguished for his talent as for his unhappy
passions Alcázar sisters there, models of perfection, and by the symmetry of their tiny factions,
as the roses in her cheeks and the black of her hair there the Junco and Lamar, of Matanzas,
known under the vocative poetry of the Nymphs of Yumurí; there Gamboa's three sisters, which
we have already had occasion to describe him up there Topete daughter of General Commander of
the Naval Station in Havana, which later inspired his Palma immortal "Fifteen of August," there's
less of Gamez, Venus Belvedere, whose brown hair, copious wavy, wore loose star-studded gold,
there, in order, inter many too numerous to list, Ilincheta Isabel, daughter of former adviser
of Captain Someruelos General, who had the main features of severe type, modest Celtiberian,
it owed its origin.

As models of manly beauty, among the young attendees of the dance company that night, could be
mentioned Sunspear Lieutenant Colonel Rey, Rafael de la Torre, who died a few days later crashed
into the wheels of the chitin in the Walk, along the statue of Carlos III, a victim of the fire of
his horse and O'Gavan Bernardo Echeverría, in the days of gala liked to wear the uniform of
Chamber gentleman with input insofar as it might look well-made and plump legs, Ramón Montalvo
in his prime age, beautiful as the pure English blood, Joseph Gaston, the true Apollo of Cuba;
Dionisio Mantilla, newly arrived from France, which had made a compliment Paris; Diego Duarte,
the happy winner of the runs of reeds held the previous year, due to the marriage of Ferdinand
Maria Cristina of Naples, several naval officers and Spanish army in their colorful uniforms,
more appropriate to a stop a particular dance.

Also contributing to the luster of the festival the presence of some young people who began to distinguish
in the cultivation of letters, namely: Palma, who had been one of the competitors in the race
of reeds used in the Finance Echeverría, who the following year achieved the award in poetry
contest launched by the Literature Committee, to celebrate the birth of the Infanta of Castile,
Isabella of Bourbon Valdés Machuca, known as helpless in the republic letters; Policarpo Valdes,
who was signed Polidoro, Anacleto Bermudez, who used to publish verses under the name of delight,
Manuel Garay y Heredia, which printed his poems in The Aurora Matanzas, Velez Herrera, the
Cuban romance author Elvira de Oquendo, Delio, the singer the ruins of the Alhambra, Domingo André,
a young lawyer, eloquent and polite, Domingo del Monte, Cuba introduced
the romance of wide-ranging expertise and very distinguished bearing.

Diego Meneses, Francisco Solfa, Leonardo Gamboa and several others who were also in dance, with
the exception of the second was given to philosophical studies, and the third and entering
into the wealthy class, were not made notable by his talent, although the three used writing
in the literary journals, and the last went further by good-looking boy and masculine forms.
The literati, or rather, fans of the lyrics, especially who cultivated poetry, began to have
entry to people who could be taken by noble in Cuba, or aspiring, for his wealth, nobility
and alternated with her. Showed at least distinction by including some titled families of Havana
and appealed to their parties and meetings, including, for example, the counts of Fernandina,
the Bayonne house, the house Peñalver, the Marquis of Montehermoso and Arc. These parties and
meetings in the days Christmas Easter moved the prettiest coffee
in San Antonio, Alquízar, San Andrés and Artemis, who belonged to
the wealthy.

Were not in the halls of our friends Gamble Company, Meneses and Solfa but until about eleven
o'clock at night. During the early hours had been visiting Fair balls Angel, Farruco and de
Brito, not to mention the birthplace of people of color, Stonehouse Street, between Compostela
and Avocado. In none of these sites They had taken an active part, excepting the first, who
lost the game Mount in an instant the two ounces of gold that same evening he had put his mother
in the vest pocket. He knew the value of money or playing for the love of gain, but for the sake
of the excitement of the moment, but it happened that the dances did not pay attractive none,
defected to the pretty girls, who failed to see Cecilia Valdés in the window home, or in the crib,
all of which conspired to put it a very bad mood. To Unfortunate auction when losing and became
upset with his friends in search of chitin, I had left on the street bet Avocado away from the
high walls of the convent Santa Catalina, he discovered that was not there, nor was it possible
to find half an hour later and point opposite and distant.

Moreover, the coachman asked about the reason that led him to disobey an order strict his young
master, gave evasive answers to the top, and finally, tight, said a stranger, half covered
his face with a handkerchief, he had been forced to leave position and pretend to be returned
home, using dire threats. It did not seem credible the story: There was, however, that accept
as good and true, what, if anything, increased bad Leonardo humor, because if true the relationship
of the coachman, who could be this guy, or what have interest in the carriage wait in one or another
corner of the street? Why use threats? What had authority to do so? Aponte could not say whether
the unknown was military or civilian, district commissioner or magistrate, a white man or colored.
Maybe was an unexpected and unknown rival in that way was preparing
to dispute the love Cecilia Valdés.

Corroborated unpleasant suspicion that neither she nor her friend had Nemesia presented in any
part of the show Angel. Besides that, the fact of not having open the window, even when Gamboa
was the agreed signal from the tip of the cane for few balusters
that still had almost left no doubt that something extraordinary had
occurred in humble, dark home.

But this is what it may, there is no time to check now, Leonardo Gamboa entered the dance of
the Philharmonic worried and very bad mood.

      Navy, however, the dance, in the main
    hall of the palace and the room quite
    spacious by the way, says the poet
    

One night last, between crystals Light shimmered in the classroom; And the blood inflamed his sones,
Tropical dance;

our hero could not avoid its overpowering influence. The orchestra, directed by the famous Ulpiano
violinist, held the very wide corridor on the left hand as she climbs the the royal dark stone
staircase. Then, right, was the door of the room, opposite another that was about the most
spacious balconies, which were called the gates of the Rosary. Left hats and canes in the hands
of a black servant at the door of a room mezzanine open the rest of the double-leg ladder, and tending
the hearing by the magnificent hall, which could have "a horse race," if we are allowed to exaggerate,
students discovered that they filled animated couples end to end.

Received back men and women face as they waited their turn to sieve the fresh air of midnight,
coming through the doors and windows wide open.

As we said before, there were assembled the cream and flower of Cuban Youth of both sexes, delivered,
for the moment at least, with soul and body to your favorite. And in the glare of the chandeliers,
in waves of music as plaintive as voluptuous, because it comes from the heart of an enslaved
people, the subtle through the cloud of dust raised by the dancers
with their feet, women seemed more beautiful, the gallant men.

Could he therefore be given the encouragement of youth to other thoughts he suggested that the
flattering objects before him? It is not possible.

Gamboa took, of course, in seeking partner to take part in the dance, but not liked, but Meneses,
who rarely danced, and Solfa, who never danced, they were viewers in the middle of the room,
watching the last, with a bitter smile, that while that crazy youth
at home enjoyed the pleasures of the moment, the most stupid and brutal
of the kings of Spain seemed to contemplate with an air of utter contempt
from gold canopy where they saw his picture painted hateful.

Walking with some difficulty between the crowded rows of spectators and dancers, stumbled Gamboa
with the youngest of the girls Gamez, whose portrait we made up pen
flies in as committed to dance.

In all regards, while pivoting as a sylph in arms your partner, "she
said before the eyes than the tongue: - Here is Isabel.

- Dancing?
asked the young man.

- What dance!

Waiting for you

- Why me? What break yours. As a tris not come to the dance tonight.

In fact, that young lady was at that time in any appearance eating turkey, as reads vulgar phrase
in Cuba, ie, sitting to the left, near the door of the room between a middle-aged woman and
the cult lawyer Domingo André, who held animated conversation. Despite his carefree nature, Gamboa
felt a surge of jealousy it was impossible to suppress, not because they were really in love,
but because the gentleman in whose company he found, was handsome and knew Asaz insinuate themselves
into the minds of women discrete. In passing, we should say, however, that the northern compliments
by André that time, they went to another beauty very different from Isabel Ilincheta, it lost
by shy and daring won for the writer Dominican Domingo del Monte, if we're not wrong on the night
that we are talking about. As far as Elizabeth, Leonardo received with an adorable smile, which,
far from reassuring, was party to cause further distress. Changed the usual greetings, as the
companion of Elizabeth, mother of Gamez, was a friend the young student, like Andre, in proof
that there was nothing coquettish, not of vindictive, very cheerful
said:

- Said that this gentleman does little, he had committed this
dance, and I want to believe.

- Is that you have not danced any yet
that I know, "said André.

- True, only two have danced, "said Isabel
without cutting, but until now danced the third, did not come to invite
you.

- What it means in essence, continued André, I've arrived in
an unlucky hour.

How has to be!

- This lady is right, Leonardo brought parts of their pregnancy. For previous commitment, in
any dance where we are, I reserved it the third dance.

I can not make, Therefore, a better time as I see it. So they say you better be on time to
be around a year.

- I cried the gallant lawyer, the fact is that
few of us good girls that we time.

André was greeted and joined the choir at Aldama potentate two daughters,
of whom the youngest, named Lola, was down to very few that night
coveted palm of beauty.

Meanwhile Leonardo and Isabella, holding his hand, reached into the ranks of dance, not far from the
head, through mutual friends for that, but arrived late, left them
no join the queue, as was de rigueur.

The Cuban dance without a doubt that was invented to be court lovers. The dance itself is very
simple, comfortable and easy movements, being its primary purpose the approximation of the sexes,
in a country where the Moorish customs tend to their separation, in short, the communion of
souls. Because the gentleman has the lady almost always on edge, so that while with his right
arm around her waist, with the left hand pressed hers softly. Is not that dance, as the body is
merely the bars, is rocking like a dream, to the sound of music gemidora and voluptuous, it
is two people talking intimately dear is stroking two beings attract each other, and that time, space,
status, custom has kept away. The style is the man, someone said promptly, the dance is a people,
we say, and there is none like dance more alive to paint the character, habits, social status
political and Cubans, or you're more in harmony with the climate of the island

The night in question Ilincheta Isabel looked wonderfully natural graces that had endowed the
sky. She was tall, shapely, slender and elegantly dressed, So be very discreet and friendly, is said
to draw the attention of the educated. To smooth pallor of her face, languid expression of his clear
eyes and thin lips, contributed to make it attractive to a young man who, on the other hand, there
was nothing beautiful. His charm was in his word and his ways.

Entered puberty when she lost her mother, and to educate, as well as to free it of the dangers
of the world, her father placed in the care of Ursuline Sisters, coming from New Orleans and
settled in their convent door Earth since early this century. After a boarding more than four
years, he received religious education before scholarly, comprehensive, retired to the country,
in the coffee plantation his father, near the town of Alquízar, along with her younger sister and
an aunt Rosa, widow a naval surgeon, named Bohorques. This individual had made several trips to
the coast of Africa in shipments released on behalf of the Society of Gamboa and White. These
result contracted a terrible disease, died on the journey and thrown into the water, which many
of the unhappy savages who had helped to plagiarizing from his native soil. On more than one
occasion was the widow, on this subject, the object of the bounty of Don Candido Gamboa. Leonardo
visited her in the coffee plantation Alquízar, and could not help falling in love and niece, whose
modesty and thanks enhanced her clear intelligence and fine discretion.

There was nothing feminine roundness, and, of course, or pleasure, we have already mentioned, in
the forms of Isabel. And the reason was obvious: the pursuit on horseback, his favorite pastime
in the field, often swimming in the river of San Andres and San Juan de Contreras where all
the years spent bathing season, walks almost daily in the coffee his father and the neighbors,
their frequent exposure to the weather for fun and because of his
active life, had strengthened and developed his physique to the point
to make him lose the soft, rounded forms of the young men of his age
and status.

For lacked nothing manly and determined air of his person, should be added that shaded his mouth
expressive a dark mustache and silky, which was only one common tonsure to become in black mustache
and village. Following this bozo sometimes sticking white teeth, young and even, and behold what
was the magic of the smile of Elizabeth.

No wonder that, being somewhat skeptical and Leonardo off, felt a passion for a young woman such
as the one just described. He came by the golden gates of life. Despite its connotations and
its wealth, had not yet had intercourse with women their area and education, and had begun
to look at them nor their future companion life. His roughness was only external, was in his brusque
manner, because there in the bottom of his chest, as you have occasion to observe, there were endless
stream of generosity tenderness of feeling.

God, that, had not denied the ability to love, only the women they had met up there, or had
yielded to the impetuosity of his affections, at the fearlessness of his few years, or the influence
of his golden shower. None of these mobile could have influence on the mind of a young rich,
well educated, modest and virtuous as Isabel Ilincheta. Leonardo attracted first by their physical
clothes, seduced then by his outstanding moral qualities, of course understood that to win her
affection was playing strength your heart, speak to your understanding. Moreover, the woman
who appeared to Leonardo's eyes in a new light, inhabited the transcript of the earthly paradise
where saw for the first time.

If we can dispense with the slave and of his sufferings, which are, however, more bearable in coffee,
it will agree that Elizabeth, her sister Rosa, his aunt Juana, his father and raised, lived a
life of peace and quiet away from the bustle of the city, surrounded by fragrant flowers, the
trees and evergreen orange, the graceful palms, the classic plantain, perennial astounded with
the singing of the birds and the rustle of the breeze melancholy in the fields of Cuba.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>