<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01021</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>110653</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23496</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El conde no podía recordar aquella escena, que había quedado profundamente grabada
en su cerebro, sin que las lágrimas se le agolparan a los ojos. De él había heredado la exquisita
delicadeza en el sentir, una susceptibilidad que llegaba a ser enfermiza, no la serenidad,
la iniciativa, la firmeza inquebrantable que realzaban el alma del coronel Campo. El actual
conde tenía un temperamento excesivamente sensible y tierno, un fondo de honradez y de vergüenza
que era el patrimonio moral de los Campo. Mas estas cualidades se contrarrestaban por un carácter
débil, fantástico, sombrío, el cual le venía, sin duda, de la familia de su madre.

D.ª María Gayoso, condesa viuda de Onís, hija del barón de los Oscos, era un ser original,
tan excepcionalmente original que rayaba en lo inverosímil. En toda su familia, desde tres
o cuatro generaciones hasta ella por lo menos, había apuntado algo estrambótico que en algunos
de sus miembros tocaba en las lindes de la locura y en otros entraba de lleno dentro. Su abuelo
había sido un empedernido ateo partidario de Voltaire y la Enciclopedia que a última hora se
había entregado a la embriaguez, y según la conseja del pueblo fue arrastrado un día por los
demonios al infierno. En realidad murió de combustión espontánea, lo que pudo dar pábulo a
semejante fábula. Su padre fue un mentecato a quien su madre, mujer de rara energía, tuvo siempre
esclavizado hasta la degradación. De sus tíos, uno paró en el manicomio, otro fue notabilísimo
matemático, pero tan excéntrico que sus rarezas se guardaban en Lancia como manantial de anécdotas
chistosas; otro se metió en la aldea, se casó con una labradora y se mató a fuerza de aguardiente.
No tenía más que un hermano, el actual barón de los Oscos. También era un ser original y excéntrico.
Al comenzar la guerra civil se pasó al bando del Pretendiente e ingresó en su ejército, pero
a condición de servir como soldado raso. Toda la campaña hizo de esta suerte. No fue posible,
por más empeño que en ello pusieron los magnates que rodeaban a D. Carlos y el mismo rey, obligarle
a aceptar el despacho de oficial. Fue herido varias veces y una de ellas de tan mala manera,
en la cara, que le quedó una profunda cicatriz. Como su rostro era ya de lo más desgraciado
que pudiera verse, aquel surco sinuoso y colorado acabó de prestarle una apariencia monstruosa
y hasta temible.

Era más joven que su hermana María. No llegaba aún a los cincuenta años. Vivía célibe y solo
en la casa solariega que los Oscos tenían en la calle del Pozo, nada magnífica por cierto.
Iba rara vez por casa de su hermana, no por antipatía, sino por lo retraído y áspero de su
genio. Salía poco de casa, sobre todo de día. Tenía contadísimos amigos. El más íntimo de todos,
el único puede decirse que gozaba de su intimidad, un fraile exclaustrado, que antes de ordenarse
había servido en las filas del ejército como oficial. Fray Diego era su perpetuo camarada.
El barón, por su carácter sombrío, por sus excentricidades, y sobre todo por lo espantable
de su rostro, inspiraba general temor en la población. Los niños sentían en su presencia un
terror pánico. Los padres y las niñeras, para reducirlos a la obediencia, les amenazaban con
él:--¡Se lo voy a decir al barón!--¡Que viene el barón!--Hoy he visto al barón y me preguntó
si eras obediente, etc. Y el barón, por su gesto, constantemente desabrido, por lo bronco y
recio de la voz y por la brusquedad con que acostumbraba a hablarles, era para las inocentes
criaturas un verdadero ogro. Iba constantemente armado de un par de pistolas; el estoque de
su bastón era un verdadero sable. Se decía que había disparado sobre un criado sólo porque
le había abierto una carta, y que en varias ocasiones había cogido a los niños que se atrevían
a hacerle muecas en la calle, los metía en la cuadra, los desnudaba y los azotaba cruelmente
con las correas del freno de su caballo. Verdaderos o inventados estos cuentos, contribuían
a acreditarle entre el elemento infantil de Lancia como un monstruo de ferocidad del cual había
que huir, si el temblor de las piernas lo consentía.

Una de las cosas que más coadyuvaban a infundir el terror en los pequeños y cierto respeto,
no exento de miedo, en los grandes, era el caballo que el barón poseía; un caballo de ojo ardiente
y feroz y de genio tan furioso que nadie osaba montarle más que él y su amigo Fray Diego, que
había servido en caballería. Para sacarlo a beber lo llevaban siempre del diestro, y aun así
el indómito bruto iba tirando saltos y coces, poniendo en conmoción a los transeúntes. Cuando
el barón lo montaba, y dando corcovos y alzándose de brazos salía de casa, la calle se estremecía,
los vecinos se asomaban a las ventanas, los niños se refugiaban en las faldas de sus madres,
todos contemplaban atónitos aquel centauro temeroso. Realmente el barón de los Oscos en tal
momento, con su rostro desfigurado, los ojos encarnizados, los grandes bigotes empalmados con
las patillas, cerdosos y erizados, y el formidable torso pegado al caballo, era una figura
que infundía espanto. Había que remontarse con la fantasía a la irrupción de los bárbaros para
hallar algo semejante. Ni Alarico, ni Atila, ni Odoacro debían de tener aspecto más feo y siniestro
ni producir más grima. Júzguese del efecto que causaría entre los vecinos tímidos cuando una
temporada le dio por salir a caballo pasada la medianoche y recorrer las calles de la ciudad
acompañado de un criado, caballero asimismo en otro corcel.

La condesa de Onís era dentro de su sexo un tipo tan estrafalario, por lo menos, como su hermano.
Bajita, rechoncha, cara redonda y pálida con ojos negros y muertos, el cabello pegado a las
sienes con goma de membrillo, vestida constantemente con el hábito morado del Nazareno. Vivía
recluida en su palacio como una monja en el convento. Vivía entregada en absoluto a la devoción,
pero a una devoción caprichosa, fantástica, en nada parecida a la que practican las almas verdaderamente
místicas. Toda su vida había dado señales de un humor excéntrico, mas desde la muerte del conde
se había pronunciado tanto que bien podían tomarse sus excentricidades como manías, y no de
las más leves. Cuando joven había mostrado una naturaleza tan púdica que rayaba por su exageración
en lo ridículo. Sus amigas la embromaban no pocas veces afectando cierta libertad en el hablar.
Tan castísimos eran los oídos de la doncella de los Oscos, que los de una miss inglesa parecerían
los de un sargento a su lado. No podía sufrir que la ropa interior de su hermano fuese en unión
con la suya cuando la lavandera la llevaba o la traía. Si aquél le entregaba unos pantalones
para que le cosiera un botón, cumplido el encargo corría a su cuarto y se lavaba bien las manos,
y aun dicen que se echaba en ellas algunas gotas de agua bendita. Apretábase el seno hasta
hacerse daño; subía el cuello de los vestidos contra las prescripciones de la moda; no se mudaba
la camisa sino a oscuras, y cuando no tenía los guantes puestos jamás daba la mano a un hombre.
La historia de su casamiento fue verdaderamente curiosa, llena de incidentes cómicos que se
repitieron durante mucho tiempo por la ciudad. Sobre todo lo que acaeció en la primera noche
de novios, verdadero o inventado, era muy gracioso y digno de figurar en una novela de Paul de Kok.

Durante el matrimonio esta virtud de la castidad templose un poco. Casi parece excusado decirlo.
Mas luego que quedó viuda volvió a exacerbarse de modo notable. Sobre todo, en los últimos
años adquirió aspecto de locura. Cuando se rezaba el rosario, que era dos veces al día, mandaba
previamente una criada al gallinero para apartar, mientras durase, al gallo de las gallinas;
luego la ordenaba separar las cucharas de los tenedores y los corchetes machos de las hembras.
Por último, la hacía situarse en una ventana de la fachada lateral de la casa para impedir
que ninguno orinara en el rincón donde los transeúntes solían hacerlo. Un día vino el cochero
a decirle que una de las yeguas estaba en el celo. Tanto se indignó que, después de haber reñido
ásperamente por la osadía de notificarle tal asquerosidad, mandó inmediatamente venderla. Una
vez que sorprendió al mozo de cuadra dando un beso a la cocinera se puso enferma del disgusto.
Ambos salieron inmediatamente de la casa.

Le gustaba, no obstante, tener tertulia a primera hora de la noche, pero de clérigos solamente.
Acostumbraba a sentarse en una butaca, delante de la cual, con intención o sin ella, probablemente
con intención, colocaba dos sillas de suerte que parecía estar detrás de una valla. Poco después
de entrar los presbíteros y animarse la conversación, la condesa se dormía profundamente, y
así estaba hasta las nueve en que las sotanas se despedían, por supuesto sin darle la mano.
Como la casa tenía capilla, salía poquísimas veces, y esas en coche. Guardaba todo el oro,
que llegaba a sus manos, en los parajes más ocultos del desván o de la huerta. Algunas veces
por esta avaricia, o más propiamente por esta manía de urraca, la casa se vio en verdaderos
aprietos: consintió en que su hijo pidiera a préstamo algunas cantidades antes que desenterrar
las peluconas. Era además golosa, muy golosa, capaz de comerse una fuente de confites sin asomos
de indigestión. Pero no habían de ser fabricados por las monjas: por extraña contradicción
con sus piadosas inclinaciones, odiaba todo lo que olía a convento.

Pues por esta mujer estrambótica, bien podemos decir loca, fue educado el actual conde de Onís.
Su carácter se resintió muchísimo. Para contrarrestar aquella excesiva sensibilidad, aquel
temperamento débil y vacilante y el humor fantástico y sombrío de que daba en ocasiones tristes
muestras, se hubiera necesitado una educación viril al aire libre, un maestro inteligente y
enérgico que supiera despertar en su organismo el brío y la resolución de los Campo. Sucedió
lo contrario desgraciadamente. La condesa se empeñó en que no siguiese carrera que le apartase
de Lancia. Estudió, pues, en la universidad del pueblo la carrera de jurisprudencia, que es
la capa con que los jóvenes ricos tapan su propósito de holgar toda la vida. Mientras duró,
y mucho tiempo después de terminada, la condesa le tuvo sujeto a su autoridad de un modo que
resultaba ridículo. Jamás salía de casa sin pedirle permiso, no fumaba en su presencia, se
recogía al oscurecer, rezaba el rosario, confesábase cuando ella lo ordenaba. Mientras su cuerpo
se desarrollaba prodigiosamente, se trasformaba en un mancebo bizarro y atlético, su espíritu
continuaba tan infantil y sumiso como si nunca pasara de diez años. En esta vida retraída y
afeminada agravose la nativa timidez de su carácter, su sensibilidad delicada se hizo enfermiza,
su genio sombrío y receloso. Y lo más lamentable era que, sin ser una lumbrera, estaba dotado
de clara inteligencia y poseía una penetración frecuente en los hombres reservados y tímidos.
Carecía de ilustración y de experiencia; pero sabía mantener discretamente una conversación
y no se le escapaban los defectos del prójimo. Como casi todos los seres débiles, gozaba a
veces malignamente a costa de ellos. Es la venganza que la gente sin carácter toma de quienes
lo poseen demasiado vigoroso y espontáneo. No obstante, estas ráfagas de ironía y malignidad
no eran en él frecuentes. Aparecía más bien como un joven prudente, reservado, melancólico,
de trato cortés y caballeroso, de corazón sensible, lleno de cariño y de respeto hacia su madre.

Después que concluyó la carrera tuvo sus anhelos y aun proyectos de salir de Lancia, de ir
a la corte, de viajar durante algún tiempo. Bastó, sin embargo, la negativa de la condesa para
contenerle y hacerle desistir. Prosiguió, pues, su vida de holganza, mayor aún desde que no
tenía siquiera la obligación de mirar de vez en cuando los libros de jurisprudencia.

Sólo la entretenía dedicándose a temporadas al cultivo de ciertos oficios manuales, y con la
lectura de las obras románticas entonces muy en boga. Se hizo hábil ebanista, no tanto como
su padre; luego le dio por la relojería. Últimamente tomó afición a una finca de labor y recreo
que poseía en las inmediaciones de la población y comenzó a mejorarla notablemente. Denominábase
la Granja: distaba poco más de dos kilómetros de Lancia: tenía una casa grande y vieja y destartalada:
a espaldas de ella un hermoso bosque de robles y delante grandes y feraces praderas. Comenzó
a ir todas las tardes después de comer; crió ganado vacuno y también algunos caballos, plantó
árboles, abrió canales y levantó cercas. En la casa apenas tocó. En esta nueva afición ganó
su cuerpo, que se hizo más duro y más ágil, y también su carácter. La melancolía, que tanto
le atormentaba, se fue templando, serenose su espíritu, fue adquiriendo más firmeza en el trato
de la gente y más seguridad de sí mismo, y ciertos accesos de humor negro, de rabia y desesperación
que sin causa alguna le acometían de raro en raro y le hacían aparecer ante los criados como
un epiléptico, desaparecieron por completo. De esta suerte llegó hasta los veintiocho años,
en que comenzó a frecuentar la casa de Quiñones, y su vida experimentó profunda trasformación.

Eran las nueve de la mañana cuando el criado le despertó de un sueño agitado, incompleto, para
entregarle una carta. La dejó caer con afectada indiferencia sobre la mesa de noche; mas luego
que el criado se fue apresurose a cogerla y la abrió con visible agitación. Aunque hacía ya
cerca de dos años que duraban sus relaciones con Amalia, nunca abría carta de ésta sin que
le temblasen las manos. Verdad que se escribían poquísimas veces. Pero más que la rareza de
las cartas contribuía sin duda a turbarle el profundo amor que en su naturaleza sensible y
tímida había arraigado.

«Esta tarde a las tres. Por la tribuna,» decía la carta únicamente. Su turbación no se disipó
por completo. Las citas como aquélla eran extremadamente peligrosas; le causaban, enmedio de
su felicidad, una impresión de miedo que no podía vencer. Había rogado a Amalia que las suprimiese;
pero no le hizo caso alguno. Y él se consideraba absolutamente incapaz de oponerse a su voluntad.
Pasó la mañana nervioso, alterado. Para calmarse dio un paseo a caballo; llegó hasta la Granja;
pero volvió al cabo con la misma intranquilidad que había salido.

Cuando llegó la hora señalada salió de casa y tomó la calle de Cerrajerías. Era la hora en
que apenas se ve un transeúnte. Los vecinos de Lancia comen generalmente a las dos. A las tres
están, pues, de sobremesa o reposando. Al final de Cerrajerías, en la esquina de la calle de
Santa Lucía, está la iglesia de San Rafael, que tiene su entrada principal por aquélla. El
conde penetró en el templo, después de tomar agua bendita, como el que va a hacer sus oraciones.
Estaba enteramente solitario, o al menos así le pareció a la primera ojeada. A los pocos minutos,
acostumbrados ya sus ojos a la oscuridad, percibió dos o tres bultos diseminados por él y postrados
en oración. Arrodillose él también en el fondo oscuro, cerca de la puertecita de la escalera
que conducía a la tribuna de los Quiñones, y fingió orar unos momentos. Aquello le repugnaba
profundamente. Era un creyente sincero, y la piadosa y severa educación que había tenido le
hacía horrorizarse de tal sacrilegio. Se le había pegado el fanatismo de su madre: tenía un
miedo espantoso al infierno. También Amalia era creyente y aun pasaba en la población por piadosa;
pertenecía a varias cofradías; era protectora de algunos asilos; hacía frecuentes regalos a
las imágenes y se la veía acompañada de clérigos. Pero miraba aquella profanación con la mayor
indiferencia. La religión era para ella cosa muy respetable, pero más respetables aún su voluntad
y sus placeres.

Al cabo de unos minutos el conde se levantó cautelosamente y tiró de la puertecita, que una
mano previsora había ya abierto de antemano. Tornó a llegarla y subió por la estrechísima escalera
de caracol. La pequeña tribuna de la casa Quiñones estaba aún más oscura que la iglesia. Buscó
a tientas la puerta del pasadizo y la empujó; mas como tenía cierre de cristales y podían verle
desde la calle, se echó a gatas para atravesarlo. En la puerta que comunicaba con la casa estaba
Jacoba esperándole. Era ésta una mujer de más de cincuenta años, obesa, con un vientre colosal,
que se movía con trabajo, la respiración anhelante, embotada por la grasa y hablando siempre
en voz de falsete. La suma discreción, la encarnación verdadera del sigilo. Nunca habían tenido
otro confidente; nadie en el mundo más que ella estaba enterada de sus amores, y en el curso
de ellos les había servido prodigiosamente; fue su centinela, su salvador en muchas ocasiones,
su ángel tutelar siempre. No era sirviente de la casa, sino protegida de la señora. Dedicábase
a correr los géneros de las tiendas, a traerlos a las casas, ganando por ello pequeñísima comisión.
Esto no le bastaba para vivir aunque era ella sola y una sobrina. Pero en varias casas le hacían
encargos de distinta índole y la ayudaban de mil maneras. Sobre todo en la señora de Quiñones
había encontrado una protectora decidida. Cuando llegó a ser su confidente puede decirse que
halló una verdadera mina. Amalia pagaba con largueza sus servicios que, en realidad, bien merecían
recompensa extraordinaria.

La medianera se llevó el dedo a los labios recomendando silencio al conde, así que éste franqueó
la puerta. Recomendación bien excusada por cierto, porque hasta la respiración iba conteniendo
por no hacer ruido. Luego, adelantándose un poco para explorar el terreno, le hizo seña para
qué la siguiese. Atravesaron un corredor, pasaron por delante de la escalera principal sin
ascender por ella de miedo a encontrarse con algún criado, y fueron a buscar a la biblioteca
una escalerita excusada que allí había para subir al segundo. El conde avanzaba de puntillas
con el corazón palpipante. Aunque ya había penetrado otras veces en casa de Quiñones de aquella
manera, le parecía siempre el colmo de la temeridad y maldecía en su interior del atrevimiento
y despreocupación de su amante. Llegaron al fin al gabinete de la señora. La puerta se abrió
sin que se viese a nadie. Jacoba empujó suavemente al conde, quedando ella fuera. La mano de
Amalia, que se presentó de improviso, volvió a cerrar, y súbito, con arrebatado ademán, echó
los brazos al cuello de su querido y le besó con apasionada ternura. Él, cohibido, agitado
aún por la ascensión y trémulo, permaneció quieto, sin corresponder a tales manifestaciones
de cariño. La dama le dio un golpecito maternal con la palma de la mano en la mejilla.

--Serénate, poltrón, que nadie te come aquí.

Luis hizo un esfuerzo por sonreír y se dejó caer en una marquesita forrada de raso azul.

El gabinete de Amalia contrastaba por su lujo coquetón con el abandono que reinaba en el resto
de la casa. Las paredes cubiertas de tapices soberbios, los mejores de la colección que la
familia poseía; los muebles flamantes, estilo Luis XV, traídos de Madrid con la magnífica cama
de ébano incrustada de marfil que se veía en la alcoba, en los primeros meses del matrimonio,
cuando D. Pedro se esforzaba inútilmente en ganar el corazón de su joven esposa. Respirábase
allí una atmósfera perfumada, sensual, que denunciaba los gustos refinados que la dama forastera
había traído allá de otras tierras a la severa mansión de los Quiñones.

Sentose sobre las rodillas del conde, y tirándole de la barba, exclamó conteniendo a duras
penas los gritos, con una alegría reprimida que le brillaba en los ojos, que estallaba por
todos los poros:

--¿Lo ves? ¿Lo ves como hemos vencido? ¿Lo ves como se han salvado todos esos obstáculos que
se te amontonaban en la cabeza y no te dejaban ver claro? No ha sido necesario más que un poco
de audacia y que Dios nos ayudase.

--¡Dios!--murmuró estremeciéndose el conde.

Ella sintió que había hecho mal en apelar a la divinidad, y se apresuró a decir con desenfado:

--Quise decir la suerte... Vamos, no empieces a ponerte cargante y tristón... Éste es un momento
de felicidad para nosotros... Lo estoy tocando y me parece mentira... Mi hija, la hija de mis
amores, viviendo conmigo, pudiendo verla y besarla a todas horas... ¡Qué hermosa es!... No
pude contemplarla a mi gusto hasta esta mañana; pero hoy me he saciado bien... Se parece a
tí... sobre todo esta parte de aquí arriba, del entrecejo. Jacoba dice que la boca es mía...
No me pesa--añadió sonriendo con coquetería.--Otra cosa peor pudiera sacar de mí, ¿verdad?

--Para mí todo es igualmente hermoso.

--¡Vamos!--exclamó la dama echándose hacia atrás y clavándole una mirada de burla cariñosa.--Al
fin has recobrado el uso de la palabra... Pues bien--añadió en tono serio,--tú no sabes las
vueltas que hemos tenido que dar esta mañana para buscarle nodriza. Me han traído tres. Ninguna
me ha gustado. Al fin la cuarta se quedó. ¡Y qué lindamente comenzó a chupar el ángel mío!
Me costaba trabajo no saltar de alegría... ¡como me cuesta ahora!... Pero seamos graves...
seamos graves y cargantes como el señor conde... Dime, fastidioso, ¿cómo te has arreglado para
traerla? Cuéntame. ¡Qué cara tenías ayer noche al abrir la puerta del salón!

--La cosa no era para menos. A las nueve fui a buscarla a casa de Jacoba. Ya te lo habrá dicho
ella. Me pasé allí cerca de dos horas. Y como si el diablo quisiera mortificarnos, la criatura
chillaba sin cesar...

--Sí, sí, ya sé todo eso... ¿Y luego?

--¡Qué noche! Los chubascos se repetían sin cesar. Las calles estaban perdidas, sobre todo
por aquellos barrios extraviados. Me remangué los pantalones casi hasta la rodilla, porque
¿cómo iba a entrar manchado de barro en tu salón? Quise sostener el canastillo en un brazo
y llevar el paraguas abierto en la otra mano. Fue imposible. A los pocos pasos me volví y le
dejé el paraguas a Jacoba. ¡Qué peregrinación, cielo santo! ¡Qué angustia! El viento me bajaba
a cada instante el embozo de la capa, la lluvia me azotaba la cara y me entraba por el cuello.
Tenía miedo que me mojase la niña. Además iba temiendo resbalar. ¡Figúrate si caigo en aquel
momento! El viento soplaba a veces tan recio que me impedía dar un paso. Bien puedes creerme
que estuve tentado a dar la vuelta y dejarlo para otro día.

--Lo creo sin que me lo jures. Demasiado sé que te ahogas en un plato de agua.

Él le dirigió una larga y triste mirada de reconvención. Amalia soltó a reír y, abrazándole
y besándole con efusión, exclamó:

--No hagas caso, pobrecito. ¿Piensas que no te compadezco? El trance ha sido bien duro. Te
has portado como un héroe.

El conde, bajo el peso de aquellos elogios, se ruborizó. La conciencia le gritaba que no los
merecía. Se acordó de la terrible prueba por que acababa de pasar Amalia, y dijo:

--¡Tú sí, tú sí que has debido de padecer! ¿Cómo te encuentras? Ha sido una imprudencia bajar
tan pronto la escalera.

--¡Oh! Yo, aunque parezco débil, soy una roca.

--Bien lo has demostrado. ¡Padecer esos tremendos dolores sin exhalar ni una queja!

--¿Qué sabes tú de esos dolores, tonto?--dijo poniéndole una mano en la boca.--¿Has parido
alguna vez?

--Luego cuatro días solamente en la cama--prosiguió el joven separando dulcemente aquella mano
y besándola al mismo tiempo,--y al quinto bajar al salón.

--Pues ya estás viendo que no me ha pasado nada. ¡Oh, si no llego a bajar ayer, de fijo Quiñones
me manda al médico! Ya desde el segundo día estaba empeñado en que subiese... Pero ¿no sabes?
Está enamorado, loco por la chiquilla. Toda la mañana ha tenido a la nodriza en su cuarto.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07664</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>66821</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20975</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The count could not remember that scene, which had been deeply impressed in his brain,
without tears crowded to her eyes. He had inherited from the exquisite delicacy of feeling, a susceptibility
that was becoming sick, no serenity, initiative, the unshakable firmness that enhanced the
soul of Colonel Field. The current Earl had an overly sensitive and gentle temperament, background,
honesty and shame it was the moral heritage of the Country. But these qualities are offset by one
character weak, great, gloomy, which come to him, no doubt, from the family of his mother.

Ms María Gayoso, widow Countess de Onis, daughter of baron Oscos was an original being, exceptionally
so original that bordered on the unbelievable. In his entire family, from three or four generations
to her at least, had noted something bizarre in some of its members played on the edge of insanity
and other entered fully inside. His grandfather atheist had been an inveterate supporter of Voltaire
and the Encyclopedia that last minute had given to drunkenness, according to the town council
was dragged by one day demons to hell. Actually died of spontaneous combustion, which could
to fuel like fable. His father was a fool to whom her mother, a woman of unusual energy, had
always enslaved to degradation. Of his uncles, one stood in the asylum, another was very remarkable
mathematician, but as eccentric in his oddities were kept as a source of anecdotes Lancia funny,
another went into the village, married a farmer and was killed by force of spirit. He had only one
brother, the current baron Oscos. It was also an original and eccentric. At the start of the civil
war went to the side of the Pretender and joined his army, but provided to serve as a private. The whole
campaign was in this way. It was not possible more effort that it put the magnates who surrounded
D. Carlos and the king himself, forcing to accept the official's office. He was wounded several
times and one of them so badly, in the face, that he got a deep scar. As his face was the most unfortunate
and that could be seen, winding path that ended Colorado to lend a monstrous appearance and
even feared.

He was younger than his sister Mary.

Not yet reached their fifties. Lived celibate and single in the manor that had on the street
Oscos Well, nothing great indeed. He was rarely at home of his sister, not dislike, but retracted
it and its rough genius. Leaving little house, especially during the day. Had few and friends.
The most intimate of all Only you can say they enjoyed their privacy, a friar exclaustrated, before
being ordained had served in the army as an officer. Fray Diego was its constant companion. Baron,
for his somber, his eccentricities, and especially so frightening of his face, inspired fear
among the population overall. The children felt in their presence a panic. Parents and babysitters,
to reduce them to obedience, threatened them with him - I'm going to tell the Baron! - Here
comes the Baron! - Today I saw the Baron and asked if you were obedient, etc. And the baron,
for his action, always bland, so harsh and loud voice and the suddenness with which he used
to speak, was for the innocent creatures a true ogre. He was always armed with a pair of pistols,
the Rapier his staff was a real sword. It said it had fired on a raised only because had opened
a letter, and that on several occasions had taken the children who dared to make faces on the
street, put them in the barn, stripped and whipped brutally brake with the straps of his horse.
Real or invented these stories, contributed to credit from Lancia child element as a monster of
ferocity which had to flee, if the tremor of the legs so spoiled.

One of the things that helped to instill terror in the small and a certain respect, not without
fear, in large, was the horse that the Baron had, a fiery eye horse
genius and fierce and furious and no one dared to ride him more than
he and his friend Fray Diego, had served in the cavalry.

To remove a drink that always had the right, and yet Gross was the indomitable pulling leaps
and kicks, putting bystanders in shock. When Baron was riding, and bucking and giving arms rising
out of the house, the street is Thrilled residents leaned out windows, children took refuge in
the skirts of their mothers, centaur looked astonished that all afraid. Really the baron in
such Oscos time, his face disfigured, his eyes fierce, big mustaches spliced ??with whiskers,
stubby and bristling, and the formidable torso hit the horse, was a figure that instilled fear. Had
to go back to fantasy to the irruption of the barbarians find something similar. Neither Alaric
and Attila and Odoacer had to have ugly and ominous aspect or produce more grim. Judge yourself
the effect would cause between neighbors when a timid season gave him ride out after midnight
and through the streets of the city accompanied by a servant, also gentleman in another horse.

La
Comtesse de Onis was in a kind of sex so outlandish, at least, as his brother. Short, plump, round
face, pale and dead black eyes, hair stuck to temples with quince paste, always dressed in purple habits
of the Nazarene. Lived secluded in his palace as a nun in the convent. Delivered living in absolute
devotion but devotion to a whimsical, fantastic, nothing like the real souls who practice mystical.
All his life he had shown signs of an eccentric humor, but since
the death of Count had ruled that both could well be his eccentricities
as hobbies, not the slightest.

As a young man had shown a very modest nature of its exaggeration verging on the ridiculous. Her
friends teased quite often affecting some freedom of speech. As castísimos were the ears of
the maiden of the Oscos, the English seem a miss those of a sergeant at his side. I could not
bear that his brother's underwear was in marriage with it when the washer on wearing or carrying.
If that gave him pants to sew a button he was doing as he ran to his room and wash hands thoroughly, and
even tell them was put a few drops of holy water. Apretábase the breast to hurting yourself up
the collar of the dress against the requirements of fashion, not moved around but a dark shirt,
and when the gloves did not ever shook hands with a man. The story of their marriage was truly curious,
full of comic incidents that repeated for a long time in the city. About everything that happened
on the first night boyfriends, real or invented, it was very funny and worthy of inclusion in a novel
by Paul de Kok

During the marriage, the virtue of chastity templose a bit. It almost seems to say excused. But when
she was widowed again flare up markedly. Especially in the past years acquired the appearance
of madness. When praying the rosary, which was twice a day, sent previously raised to divert to
roost for the duration, the cock of the hens; then ordered separate spoons and forks and brackets
males and females. Finally, was placed in a window on the front side of the house to prevent
none pee in the corner where they used to passersby. One day came the coachman to say that one
of the mares were in heat. Both are angry that, having fought sharply
for daring to notify such nastiness, sent immediately sell it.

A After the groom surprised giving a kiss to the cook got sick of disgust. Both came out of the
house immediately.

He liked, however, be gathering in the early hours of the night, but only clerics. I used to
sit in a chair, before which, intentionally or not, probably with intent, two chairs placed so
that seemed to be behind a fence. Shortly after Priests enter and encourage conversation,
the countess slept soundly, and was well until nine in the robes were leaving, of course, without
shaking hands. As the house had a chapel, leaving very few times, and those by car. He kept all
the gold that came into his hands, the most secret places in the attic or the garden. Sometimes
by this greed, or more properly by this mania for magpie, the house was in real trouble: agreed
to let his son asked to borrow some quantities before digging the
pelucones.

He was also greedy, very greedy, could eat candy without a source of hints indigestion. But there
had to be made by the nuns: for strange contradiction with their pious inclinations, I hated everything
smelled convent.

As for this woman bizarre, we can say crazy, educated the present Count de Onis. His character
suffered a lot. To counteract this excessive sensitivity, that weak and vacillating temperament
and great, dark humor that was sometimes sad samples would have required a manly outdoor education,
teacher and intelligent energetic awakening in your body know the spirit and the resolution
of the Country. Happened Otherwise unfortunately. The countess insisted that race should not go
after him depart Lancia. Therefore considered a college town in the career of law, which is the
layer with the rich kids hide their idle purpose of life. While it lasted, and completed long
after the countess was subject to his authority in a way that ridiculous.

Never leaving home without permission, did not smoke in their presence, gathered at dusk, praying
the rosary, confesábase when she ordered. As his body was developed prodigiously, was transformed
into a bizarre and athletic young man, his spirit still so childish and submissive as if it never
happened ten years. In this life withdrawn and agravose the native effeminate timidity of his
character, his delicate sensibilities became sick, shady and suspicious genius. And the most
unfortunate was that, without being a louver, was endowed of clear intelligence and possessed
a common penetration reserved and timid men. Illustration and lacked experience, but knew how
to keep a conversation discreetly and is not escaped the defects of others. Like almost all
weaklings, enjoyed a sometimes viciously at their expense. Vengeance is for people but not making
those I have too vigorous and spontaneous. However, these bursts of irony and malignancy it
was not common. Appeared more like a young conservative, quiet, melancholy of courtesy and chivalrous,
sensitive heart, full of affection and respect for his mother.

After the race had ended their hopes and even projects Lancia leave, to go the court, to travel for
some time. Enough, however, the countess's refusal to contain him and make him desist. Continued,
then, his life of leisure, the more so since no had an obligation to look even occasionally books
of jurisprudence.

Only by engaging in entertaining the growing seasons of certain crafts, and the romantic reading
of the works then in vogue. It was clever carpenter, not as his father, then gave him the watch.
Recently took a liking to farm work and leisure he owned in the vicinity of the village and
began to improve markedly.

Denominábase Farm: Dist little over two miles Lancia had a big old house, ramshackle: behind
her a beautiful forest of oak and large front and fertile prairies. Began to go every afternoon
after lunch, raised cattle and some horses, planted trees opened up channels and fences. At
home barely touched. In this new hobby won His body, which became
harder and more agile, and his character.

Melancholia, that both tormented him, it was tuning, serenose his mind was becoming more firmly
in the treatment people and more security for itself and certain disclosures of black humor,
rage and despair that no cause of rare rushing him and made him appear strange to the servants
as an epileptic, disappeared. Thus came to twenty-eight, he began to frequent the house of Quiñones,
and his life underwent profound transformation.

It was nine o'clock in the morning when the servant awoke from a restless sleep, incomplete, for
deliver a letter. He dropped with affected indifference on the night table, but then that the
servant was hastened to pick it up and opened it with visible excitement. Although it was already
nearly two years lasting relationships with Amalia, never opened this letter without His hands
shook. Truth, they wrote very few times. But the rarity of cards certainly helped troubled about the
deep love in her sensitive nature timid had taken root.

"This afternoon at three o'clock. On the podium, "said the letter
only.

His embarrassment did not dissipate completely. Appointments as it was extremely dangerous, causing
him, amid happiness, a sense of fear that it could not overcome. Amalia had asked that the deleted;
but paid no attention whatsoever. And he felt totally unable to oppose his will. Spent the
morning nervous, upset. To calm gave a ride, got to the Farm; but returned after the unrest
that had left it.

When the appointed time came he left home and took the street of locksmiths.

It was the hour that is just a bystander. Lancia neighbors usually eat both. At three are therefore
desktop or resting. At the end of Locksmith, at the corner of the street Santa Lucia, is the
Church of San Rafael, which has its main entrance on it. The Earl entered the temple after taking holy
water, as that will make their prayers. Was entirely alone, or so it seemed at first glance. A few
minutes and his eyes accustomed to darkness, he saw two or three scattered parcels for him and
prostrate in prayer.

He also knelt in the dark, near the small door of the staircase leading to the rostrum of
Quiñones, and pretended to pray for a moment. That he hated deeply. It was a sincere believer
and a pious and strict upbringing that he had was horrified to such sacrilege. It had hit the
fanaticism of his mother, had a deathly afraid of hell. Amalia also was a believer and even
passed on by pious people; belonged to various guilds, was protective of some homes, made frequent
gifts images and was seen accompanied by clerics. But looking at this defilement with the highest
indifference. Religion was for her something very respectable, but his will still respectable and its
pleasures.

After a few minutes the count got up gingerly and pulled the little door, a anticipatory hand
had already begun to advance. Turned to go and climbed the stairs very narrow spiral. The small
gallery of the house Quiñones was even darker than the church. Sought groping the door of the passage
and pushed, but as he was closing windows and could see from the street, began to crawl to
get through. On the door leading to the house was Jacob expected. She was a woman over fifty years,
obese, with a huge belly, moving with difficulty, panting breathing, dull and fat and always talking
falsetto voice.

The sum option, the true embodiment of stealth. Never had another confidant, nobody in the
world than she was aware of his love, and in the course of them had served them prodigiously, was
his guard, his savior on many occasions your guardian angel forever. There was a servant of the
house, but Mrs. protected. We spent to run the kinds of stores to bring them to the houses, thus
earning very small commission. This was not enough to live even though it was her own and a niece.
But he made several houses orders of various kinds and helped in countless ways. Especially Mrs.
Quiñones had found a protective determined. When it became his confidant may be said found a
mine. Amalia generously paid services, in fact, well deserved extraordinary reward.

The party wall held his finger to his lips silently recommending the count, so he crossed the door.
Excused for a good recommendation, because even breathing was holding not to make noise. Then,
going a bit to explore the terrain, he motioned for to follow. They walked through a corridor, they
passed the main staircase without up for it in fear of meeting a servant, and went to look for the
library a ladder that there was excused to go to the second. The count proceeded on tiptoe palpipante
the heart. Although he had penetrated other times in that house Quiñones Thus, he always seemed
the height of recklessness and cursing inside Dare and indifference of her lover. They came at last
to the case of the lady.

The door opened without anyone saw. Jacoba pushed gently to the count, leaving her out. The labor
Amalia, who suddenly appeared, shut, and suddenly, with snatched Furthermore, I arms around your
loved and kissed him with passionate tenderness. He, embarrassed, agitated yet the rise and
trembling, stood still, without responding to such events affection. The lady tapped her motherly
to the palm on the cheek.

- Be calm, easy chair, that nobody will come here.

Luis made an effort to smile and dropped in a blue satin lined marquise.

Amalia's cabinet for its luxury coquetón contrasted with the abandonment that reigned in the
rest of the house. Tapestry-covered walls superb, the best of the collection that family owned,
brand new furniture, Louis XV, brought from Madrid to the beautiful bed ebony inlaid with ivory,
which was at the bedroom, in the first months of marriage, when D.
Pedro was trying in vain to win the heart of his young wife.

Breathed there an atmosphere scented, sensual, refined tastes denouncing
the stranger lady brought there from other lands to the severe mansion
Quiñones.

He sat on the knees of the count, and tugging at his beard, said holding back hard penalties
cries, with a repressed joy shone in his eyes, exploding in every pore:

- See? Do you see it as we won? Do you see how they overcame all these obstacles you heaped on
the head and not let you see clearly? There was no need more than a little boldness and God help
us.

- God - "murmured the count shudder.

She felt she had done wrong in appealing to the divinity, and hastened to say nonchalantly:

- I meant the fate ... Now do not start to get tiresome and sad ...
This is a time of happiness for us ... I'm playing and I can not believe
... My daughter, my daughter love, living with me and can see her
and kiss her all the time ... How beautiful!

... No I contemplate my taste until this morning, but today I sated
well ... It looks like you ... especially this part up here, between
the eyebrows.

Jacoba said that the mouth is mine ... I do not regret - smiling
coyly added .-- Another thing worse could get from me, right?

- For
me, everything is just beautiful.

- Come on - the lady exclaimed,
leaning back and stabbing him with a look of affectionate mockery
.-- At 've finally recovered the use of the word ... Well - said in
a serious tone - you do not know the laps that we had to give this
morning to look for mother.

I have brought three. No I liked it. Finally the fourth stayed. And what Linda began to suck my
angel! I had trouble not jumping for joy ... As it costs me now! ... But let's be serious ...
we are serious and tiresome as the count ... Tell me, annoying, how you've managed to bring?
Tell me. Which side were you last night to open the door of the room!

- The thing with good reason. At nine I went to look at Jacob's house.
Have told you so it.

I spent about two hours there.

And as if the devil would mortify the creature screamed on ...

- Yes, yes, I know all that ... And then?

- What a night! The showers were repeated endlessly. The streets were lost, mostly for those
missing quarters. Roll up my pants almost to the knee, because How would I get bedraggled in your
living room? I wanted to hold the basket in one arm and carrying
an open umbrella in the other hand.

It was impossible. A few steps I turned and Jacoba left the umbrella. What pilgrimage, good heavens!
What anguish! The wind down every moment the fold of the layer, the rain whipped my face and I
entered through the neck.

I was afraid the girl get wet.

Besides fearing would slip. Imagine if I fall in that time! The wind was blowing so hard sometimes
that I could take a step. Well believe me I was tempted to turn around and leave it for another
day.

- I believe without it I swear. Too know that you drown in a bowl of water.

He gave her a long, sad look of reproach. Amalia burst out laughing and embracing and kissing
her with effusion, said:

- Never mind, poor thing. Do you think you no pity? The trance was
very hard.

Te has behaved like a hero.

The count, under the weight of those compliments, blushed. Shouted awareness that not deserved.
He remembered the terrible ordeal that had just Amalia, and said:

-
You do, you do that you should have to suffer!

How are you? It was a reckless lower as soon as the ladder.

- Oh! Although I seem weak, I am a rock.

- Well you've shown.

Having such tremendous pain without uttering even a complaint!

- What do you know about this pain, stupid? - Said putting a hand
in the mouth .-- Have you given birth ever?

- After only four days
in bed - Young continued that hand gently separating and kissing at
the same time - and the fifth down the hall.

- Well, you see that
I have not happened.

Oh, if it came down yesterday, fixed Quiñones send me a doctor! Since the second day was determined
to come up ... But do not you know? He is in love, crazy for the
girl.

All morning he had the nurse in his room.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>