<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07850</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>764</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22517</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Era el primer día de Mayo. Poldy, casi desesperada ya de volver a ver la cigüeña, acudió, no
obstante, como de costumbre, entre diez y once de la mañana, a la orilla de la laguna.

Apenas hacía dos minutos que estaba allí, absorta, pensativa y fijando larga y melancólica
mirada en la tranquila haz del agua, cuando un precipitado sonar de alas que venía acercándose
estremeció todo su cuerpo y alborozó su alma con agradable susto. La cigüeña blanca había venido
volando, se había abatido a pocos pasos de ella, y ya se le acercaba con su lento y majestuoso
paso y dando con el pico los castañetazos con que solía siempre saludarla.

Indescriptible fue la alegría de Poldy. Su impaciencia fue mayor que su alegría. Impulsada
por su impaciencia, echó las manos al cuello del pájaro zancudo, y empezó a buscar el cordón
o la cinta de donde pendiese la respuesta que a su carta esperaba. ¡Qué cruel aflicción tuvo
entonces! No hallaba carta pendiente. No hallaba cinta ni cordón de que pendiera. A punto estuvo
Poldy de llorar de rabia. Pero la cigüeña, como si adivinase su sentimiento, abrió las largas
alas y al punto con alegría y sorpresa advirtió Poldy que la cigüeña tenía debajo del ala izquierda
y muy bien atado allí con un fuerte y sutil cordoncillo que bajo las plumas se escondía, un
largo y delgado canuto o rollo.

Poldy se apoderó de él en seguida y notó que era ligerísimo, que estaba precintado y sellado
y que era tan fuerte la cuerda del precinto y estaba tan bien anudada, que no podía romperse
ni desatarse sin tijeras. Sobre la exterior superficie del rollo, se veía escrito en lengua
y letras alemanas: A su excelencia la graciosa señorita Condesa Poldy de Liebestein.

Hizo Poldy algunos cariños a la cigüeña a fin de mostrar su gratitud, y hasta hay quien dice
que besó su cabeza en albricias del buen recado. Luego Poldy se fue corriendo al castillo para
encerrarse en su cuarto, cortar el precinto con tijeras y ver lo que el rollo contenía. Había
en el rollo varios objetos que Poldy fue sucesivamente examinando. Era uno la vista fotográfica,
prolija y magistralmente iluminada con colores, de un extenso y magnífico salón oriental, lleno
de primores y de peregrinas elegancias. En todo se advertían y se admiraban pasmoso lujo asiático
y muy acendrado buen gusto. Se diría que era aquello la prodigiosa cámara subterránea, donde
encontró Aladino la lámpara del Genio. Pendían de las paredes armas brillantes, indias, chinas
y japonesas; colgaban del techo cinceladas lámparas de oro; se veían en torno jarrones, tibores
y vasos, artísticamente esculpidos, de metales preciosos, de jaspes rarísimos, de antigua porcelana
y de ataujía o menuda labor de pedrería, marfil, bronce y otras materias ricas. Varios ídolos
de extrañas cataduras y de simbólicas formas, autorizaban y caracterizaban la estancia. Allí
estaban representados Agni, dios del fuego; Kamala o Kamela, Venus de la India, de cuyo nombre
proceden, en nuestro vulgar idioma camama, camelo y sus derivados; y allí estaban también Indra,
Varuna y hasta la misma Trimurti.

En primer término, sobre una espléndida alcatifa de Persia, y sentado en mullidos almohadones
de seda, admirablemente bordados, se parecía un señor, en la flor de la juventud, cubierto
de blanca y rozagante vestidura y coronada la gentil cabeza de un amplio turbante, cándido
también, sobre el cual se erguía un airón o copete de rizadas y lindas plumas, sujeto el airón
al turbante por una enorme piocha de perlas, diamantes y rubíes, que debía valer un imperio.
Delante del señor había varias mesillas enanas, donde en aúreos y repujados azafates, en ligeros
canastillos, en esbeltas ánforas y en cálices esmaltados, se ofrecían para regalo de la vista,
del olfato y del paladar, licores, conservas y sazonados frutos. A un lado y a cierta distancia
del joven señor, se hallaba un rico y elegantísimo narguilé, cuyo flexible y luengo tubo tenía
el joven señor asido por el extremo, dejando ver la gruesa boquilla de ámbar, prendida al tubo
por un anillo de refulgentes esmeraldas. Al lado opuesto del narguilé, aunque mucho más cerca
del joven señor, se alzaba, en muy graciosa postura, nuestra ya conocida amiga la cigüeña blanca,
cuya vista complació a Poldy no poco. No la complació tanto, sino que hubo de enojarla y de
escandalizarla, aunque reprimió el enojo, atribuyendo lo que veía a inveteradas e imprescindibles
modas orientales, que en el fondo del salón apareciesen tres bayaderas, con traje de Apsaras
o inmortales ninfas, las cuales tejían voluptuosa danza, desceñido y leve el transparente ropaje,
los brazos y los pies desnudos, luciendo en las gargantas de los pies y en los brazos, ajorcas
y brazaletes, y dejando ver además las torneadas espaldas y los firmes y redondos pechos. Varios
músicos, vestidos como dicen que se visten los Gandarbas o músicos del cielo de Indra, acompañaban
la danza con arpas, flautas y violines, y con eróticos cantares.

Poldy quedó deslumbrada al contemplar todo esto y formó el concepto más alto del esplendor
y de la riqueza del señor indio. De su traza personal es de lo que aquella fotografía no le
daba idea completamente satisfactoria. Y no era ese tampoco el propósito de la fotografía,
por bajo de la cual había este letrero: mi modo de vivir en Oriente.

En otra fotografía más pequeña, aparecía ya el joven señor con más claros pormenores. Estaba
él solo, de cuerpo entero, pero sin accesorio ninguno. Su traje, aunque sobrado pintoresco,
era más europeo que indio, salvo el extraño sombrero que llevaba en la cabeza y que era de
los que llaman heroínas en Filipinas. La chaqueta o dormán, muy ceñido al cuerpo y adornado
con alamares, revelaba las formas robustas de su torso y de sus brazos. Los calzones eran anchos
y cortos. Desde la rodilla hasta la planta de los pies calzaba botas de becerro. Pendientes
de la ancha charpa, de cuero también, que ceñía su cintura, había un revólver a un lado y al
otro lado un enorme cuchillo de monte. En la mano derecha cubierta de guante de gamuza, tenía
una escopeta de dos cañones, que descansaba en el suelo y sobre la cual se apoyaba. Por bajo,
había un rótulo que decía: al ir a caza de tigres.

Por último, había una tercera fotografía que no dejaba nada que desear. Allí estaba el joven
señor clara, fiel y nítidamente retratado. Su rostro era hermosísimo. Los ojos eran grandes
y expresivos; la barba parecía sedosa, abundante y muy bien cuidada y atusada. La nariz, un
tanto cuanto aguileña, daba cierta majestad a su expresión. Y la anchura y la rectitud de su
frente revelaban poco común inteligencia. Se notaba en todo su aspecto un no sé qué de bondadoso,
de simpático y de egregiamente distinguido. Sus manos sin guantes, aunque fuertes y varoniles,
eran aristocráticas, muy cuidadas y bonitas, con dedos afilados en la extremidad y encanutadas
las uñas, en vez de ser cortas y chatas. En este retrato, el joven señor estaba vestido enteramente
al uso de Europa, de toda etiqueta, con corbata blanca y con un frac, tan admirablemente cortado
y que le caía tan bien, que no soñaría hacerle mejor, ni Frank, el de Viena, ni el sastre más
famoso de Londres. Por bajo de este retrato había otro letrero que decía: en traje de etiqueta
para ir a un baile del Lord Gobernador de la India.

Hechizada quedó Poldy al contemplar los mencionados retratos. Se prendó de la hermosura y distinción
de su remoto amigo. Y no pudo menos de confirmarse en la creencia de que era un príncipe indio
mediatizado, un nababo, o por lo menos un brahman o un chatria de primer orden y de mucho fuste.

Imagine ahora el lector el afán, el asombro, las palpitaciones de gozo y el raro deleite con
que leería Poldy la carta, que también venía en rollo y que estaba concebida en estos términos:

VIII

«Me repugna y hallo difícil escribir cartas dando tratamiento a quien las dirijo, y así, adopto
la antigua costumbre de los orientales. Tú me permitirás, bella condesa Poldy, que desde luego
te tutee sin ceremonias.

La cigüeña blanca, que anida años ha en el tejado de la espléndida quinta que yo poseo en las
floridas márgenes del Ganges, me ha traído gratas noticias tuyas, tus dulces palabras y tu
divina imagen. Bendita sea la cigüeña blanca que tanto bien me ha hecho. Con razón la llamaba
yo antes Garuda. Ahora le confirmo este nombre sagrado, con el que se designa en mi patria
al Dios-rey de las aves todas, al alado destructor de los dragones y de las serpientes.

En extremo me complace saber que eres de noble extirpe y bastante antigua hasta donde cabe
en un pueblo que hace pocos siglos era salvaje todavía, careciendo de documentos y de archivos
que pudiesen acreditar la nobleza de persona alguna, y las hazañas de sus progenitores. Estos,
errantes en las ásperas selvas y en el rudo clima de los países del Norte, decayeron de su
ilustre origen y olvidaron la primitiva cultura de los arios del Paropamiso de donde proceden,
y sólo recientemente se han civilizado, aprovechándose de los estudios y progresos de los hombres
del Mediodía. Pero sea de lo dicho lo que se quiera, relativamente tú eres noble y me basta,
aunque mi clara nobleza preceda a la tuya en dos mil años lo menos.

Te hablo con franqueza y desecho adulaciones y galanterías. Así darás mayor crédito a mis alabanzas
sinceras.

Garuda, por caprichosa y feliz inspiración mía, te llevó unos versos que distaba yo mucho de
imaginar que pudiesen caer en tan hermosas manos. En ellos ponderaba yo mi hastío de cuanto
me rodea y el anhelo vehemente, que consume mi alma, de hallar objeto, escondido y lejano,
que satisfaga mis aspiraciones amorosas, las comprenda y las comparta.

Tu retrato y tu escrito han colmado mis votos. Tú eres la mujer de mis sueños.

Venerandos brahmanes, antiguos sabios de por acá, que han escrito de amores en el Kama Sutra
y en otras disertaciones y tratados, exigen sesenta y cuatro potencias, prendas o aptitudes,
para que exista en realidad la Padmini o mujer perfecta. Yo te declaro que, al ver tu imagen
y al leer tus palabras, he descubierto en ti las sesenta y cuatro aptitudes y te he entronizado
en mi corazón como reina y señora y he reconocido en ti mi Padmini, sin cuyo amor no podré
tener nunca bienaventuranza. Ámame pues, como yo te amo, y hazme dichoso como quiero yo que
tú lo seas.

Nada puede oponerse a nuestra unión futura. La distancia importa poco. No tardaré yo en salvar
la distancia, y el día en que menos lo pienses, apareceré a tu lado y me verás de hinojos a
tus plantas, pidiéndote que correspondas al inmenso amor que me inspiras.

No hay ya en mí calidad exótica y peregrina que te prohíba amarme. Yo poseo el antiquísimo
saber de los brahmanes y de los chatrias, de cuyas castas combinadas desciendo; pero, he estudiado
también y he logrado adquirir bastante del moderno saber de Europa. Y no le miro con prevención
injusta, sino con cariño paternal, como retoño lozano de nuestras primeras, altas y fecundas
doctrinas. Ya habrás notado que no escribo muy mal tu idioma y hasta que he imitado y casi
traducido en sanscrito versos de Goëthe. No ignoro tampoco las literaturas francesa, inglesa
y de otros pueblos. Y en lo tocante a religión, te diré con todo sigilo, pues no quiero aun
escandalizar y alborotar a mis parientes y amigos, brahmanes y chatrias, que he renegado, tres
años ha, de la religión brahmánica, y me he hecho, en secreto, tan católico cristiano, como
tú eres. Se debe esta conversión a cierto Padre jesuita, de nación española, que llegó a esta
ciudad, procedente de Filipinas y se detuvo algún tiempo entre nosotros. Era varón tan ilustrado,
tan piadoso y tan elocuente y melifluo, que logró convencerme. Dios le bendiga y se lo pague.
Callo su nombre, porque de seguro no te importa y porque no quiero lastimar su extremada modestia.
Sólo añadiré que de mi trato frecuente con este bendito Padre, ha nacido en mí grande afición
a la lengua castellana y que he adquirido y leído los mejores prosistas y poetas, que en ella
han escrito o escriben.

Te callo también mi nombre indio, porque no quiero que le estropees y porque es tan enrevesado,
que sólo aprenderás bien a pronunciarle por medio de la voz viva. Conténtate por ahora, con
saber que el venerable padre jesuita mi catequizador, me puso al bautizarme, el sevillano nombre
de Isidoro. No seas voluble: ámame y no me olvides: no te enamores de ninguno de esos dandies
de la Hof-Adel o nobleza palatina de Viena: persuádete de que mi nobleza es por lo menos tan
clara y sin la menor duda muchísimo más rancia que la de ellos. La de ellos constará acaso
en antiguos pergaminos, pero la mía consta en documentos fehacientes, redactados veinte siglos
antes de que el pergamino se inventase, y muchos más siglos antes de que en Austria se usara
y se contara entre los recados de escribir.

Ámame, repito, y ten fe y esperanza en mi amor. No necesitas buscarme, sino aguardarme. Pronto
me verás a tus pies, adorándote rendido y suplicándote con toda el alma que seas la Padmini de tu

ISIDORO.»

IX

Contentísima estaba Poldy al inferir y considerar, por la lectura de la carta, que su indio
era ilustre y rico y que estaba perdidamente enamorado de ella. Puntos había, no obstante,
en la carta, que hacían surgir en el espíritu de Poldy, reparos, contradicciones y hasta quejas.
Harto jactancioso y nada galante ni fino le pareció el encomio que hizo el indio de su nobleza,
con grave detrimento y aun menosprecio de la nobleza austriaca; pero Poldy excusaba y hasta
absolvía al indio, conjeturando que en este particular había de estar un tanto cuanto agriado
su carácter, por que siendo él descendiente de Crishna, de Rama, de los Pandues, o tal vez
de algún Avatar, encarnación de Vishnú, de los que el Mahavarata celebra, se veía sometido
a la extranjera dominación de los pícaros ingleses.

Poldy disculpaba así a su amigo, pero distaba mucho de darle la razón. Pensaba ella que los
documentos nobiliarios valen solo cuando goza de poder, alta posición y riqueza quien los exhibe,
y que todo esto, salvo la riqueza, estaba menoscabado y deteriorado en su indio, que al fin
era un humilde súbdito de S. M. Británica y cualquier inglés empleado de Hacienda o cualquier
coronel de caballería podría mirarle de alto a bajo.

Poldy discurría además, que el que vence y domina es siempre el heredero legítimo del vencido
y dominado. Y esto en todas las épocas y regiones. En la Edad Media, por ejemplo, ya en una
encrucijada, ya en abierto palenque, topaba un caballero andante con otro, y para probar la
bizarría respectiva o para hacer confesar al contrario, que su dama era la más hermosa, o por
quítame allá esas pajas, se arremetían ambos con furia y se daban de lanzadas. De resultas
caía derribado de la silla uno de los dos caballeros, y en el instante, toda la gloria de sus
proezas, toda la nombradía que sus aventuras y hazañas le habían granjeado, se transferían
al caballero vencedor como aditamento o apéndice.

Poldy recordaba también haber leído que, allá en América, cuando un cacique bisoño, que no
había hecho aun cosa de provecho, se encontraba de manos a boca con otro cacique veterano,
enemigo suyo, y célebre autor de doscientas mil ferocidades, y acertaba a darle tan terrible
golpe con la macana que le derribaba y vencía, la fama toda del cacique veterano se trasladaba
al cacique bisoño, y hasta era general creencia que en el bisoño se transfundían los bríos
y la audacia del veterano, sobre todo si el bisoño le bebía la sangre o se le comía, crudo
o guisado, después de haberle muerto.

Deducía Poldy de cuanto va dicho, que los verdaderos nobles del día, son los europeos, y muy
singularmente los alemanes, porque ejercen con los adelantos y mejoras de nuestro siglo, todas
las antiguas artes de la paz y de la guerra, por donde se señalaron y dominaron el mundo asirios
y babilonios, medos y persas, egipcios, fenicios y cartagineses, y griegos y romanos, cuyas
glorias todas, excelencias y privilegios se hallan hoy, según Poldy, en resumen, cifra y compendio,
en sus egregios compatriotas, y por consiguiente en ella también.

A pesar de todo, y después de haber hecho la indispensable rebaja, Poldy se complacía en que
fuera noble su indio y hasta se figuraba llanísimo que fuese él naturalizado, hof-fähig sin
la menor dificultad, y que asistiese con ella a la corte cuando estuviesen casados.

Como en Austria, además de la nobleza alemana, checa, polaca, húngara, rumana, croata, serba,
dálmata, etc., la hay de origen irlandés, francés, español e italiano, claro está que podría
haberla también de origen brahmánico y chatriesco.

Otra cosa, de las que enojaban algo a Poldy, era la presencia en la fotografía de aquellas
tres bayaderas tan ligeramente vestidas y tan poco modestas y comedidas en sus bailes. Pero
también Poldy se mostraba indulgente con este desafuero del indio, y si no le disculpaba, le
explicaba y casi le perdonaba. El indio había tenido bayaderas, y había hecho aquella vida
rota, de puro oriental, cuando estaba aun sumido en las tinieblas del paganismo, pero cuando,
gracias al padre jesuita, se convirtió a la verdadera religión, Poldy daba por segura su enmienda
y el abandono en que había dejado sus viciosos deportes.

Lo único que en este negocio la apesadumbraba era que no hubiese sido el indio su catecúmeno,
porque ella le hubiera convertido mejor que el padre jesuita, y no le hubiera dado en la pila
bautismal un nombre tan feo como el de Isidoro. Poldy ignoraba quizás que había habido un santo
arzobispo de dicho nombre, famosísimo sabio, que recogió y ordenó en sus libros todo el saber
de su tiempo, y se atenía a lo que había oído decir a una vieja princesa, tía suya, terrible
antisemita, la cual princesa se empeñaba en afirmar que el nombre de Isidoro era muy común
entre judíos, por donde le repugnaba de tal suerte, que tuvo tentaciones de despedir a un excelente
criado suyo porque se llamaba Isidoro, y sólo se resignó a conservarle en su servicio obligándole
a llamarse Filidoro en adelante.

Por lo demás, Poldy no podía estar más alegre ni más satisfecha. El istmo de Suez, acababa
de abrirse y ya se presentía Poldy atravesando el canal, salvando el estrecho de Bab-el-Mandeb,
y navegando por el Mar Eritreo, con rumbo hacia la India, para visitar las quintas, jardines
y palacios de su joven esposo.

La venida de éste no podía ya tardar mucho, y Poldy se moría de impaciencia por verle vivo
y no pintado, en cuerpo y alma y no en imagen. Lo que excitaba su curiosidad y le cosquilleaba
suavemente las telas del cerebro era la condición de Padmini, que el joven indio le concedía.
Ansiosa estaba de leer o de que le leyesen el Kama Sutra, y de estudiar bien allí las sesenta
y cuatro aptitudes o excelencias de la Padmini, para buscarlas en ella y convencerse de que
las poseía y de que no era lisonja de su amigo.

En resolución, Poldy estaba inquieta y alborozada, pero con inquietud y alborozo, llenos de
dulces esperanzas y de amorosas y poéticas venturas.

X

Muy distraída o muy afanada debía de andar Garuda, cuando no se mostraba en la margen de la
laguna a donde Poldy iba a buscarla de diario.

El indio seguía también tan invisible como Garuda.

Poldy languidecía de impaciencia, e imaginaba en ocasiones que iba a marchitarse su juventud
como entreabierta rosa, en cuyo seno, donde no cayó el rocío, penetran los rayos del sol en
la estación estiva.

En efecto, estaba para acabar ya el mes de Junio y el indio no había aparecido.

Una mañana, como de costumbre, entre diez y once, volvía Poldy de la laguna, donde en balde
había buscado a la cigüeña.

Fatigada y triste, en medio de la senda por donde se volvía al castillo, Poldy se sentó, al
pie de un olmo, en un asiento rústico, y en lo más frondoso, intrincado y bonito del parque.
Un arroyuelo cristalino corría cerca murmurando. Crecían en su margen blancas y moradas violetas,
y otras no cultivadas florecillas, que embalsamaban el aire con suave y grata fragancia. Floridos
rosales de enredadera y otras plantas, que se ceñían a los troncos, y pasaban de un árbol a
otro, como festones y guirnaldas, formaban allí misteriosa espesura y apartado recinto.

Sentada ya Poldy, se puso a meditar, y hubo de distraerse por tal arte, que, como vulgarmente
se dice, se le fue el santo al cielo. Cual no sería su asombro y cual no sería su júbilo, cuando
de repente sintió ruido y sin tener tiempo para recobrarse, vio llegar a un gentil caballero,
que se aproximó respetuoso y vino a ponerse de hinojos a sus plantas.

Imposible dudar. Era el original de los tres retratos en fotografía. Vestido estaba con elegante
traje de cazador, pero sin armas, porque no iba ya a caza de tigres, sino de palomas. Y en
vez del salacot oriental, cubría su cabeza un airoso sombrero tirolés adornado con una pluma
de águila.

El joven derribó por tierra el sombrero y descubrió los negros y abundantes rizos de su cabeza,
antes de postrarse de rodillas.

Profunda fue la emoción de Poldy. El corazón le daba brincos en el pecho. El joven le pareció
mucho más bello en el original que en los retratos, y cuando oyó su voz, argentina, melodiosa,
y rica de tonos persuasivos y suaves, que roban la prudencia y la calma, apenas pudo sostenerse
y pensó que se desmayaba.

En aquella situación no era dable diálogo alguno. ¿Qué podían decirse los dos enamorados? ¿Con
qué frases, en qué sobrehumano idioma acertarían a expresar sus agitadores sentimientos?

Solo dijo él:

--Aquí estoy, Poldy. Tuya es mi vida. Quiero ser y seré tuyo para siempre. Yo te amo, yo te
idolatro, yo te adoro.

¿Qué había de contestar Poldy, muda de asombro, radiante de alegría, y con el amor y el pudor
luchando en su alma?

Hizo, no obstante un esfuerzo y se puso de pie, aunque turbada y vacilante.

Entonces él se levantó también y la estrechó irresistible y cariñosamente entre sus brazos.
Luego, juntó su rostro al de ella y cubrió de besos su frente, sus mejillas y su fresca boca.

Conoció Poldy al fin el peligro en que se hallaba, se avergonzó de ceder con tanta facilidad
a quien veía y oía por vez primera; y, prestándole fuerzas su lastimado decoro, rechazó con
violencia a su amante, se desprendió de entre sus brazos, y procuró guarecerse de su atrevimiento
huyendo desalada y refugiándose en el castillo.

A solas en su estancia, se repuso Poldy de su temor, logró calmarse, y en el fondo de su alma
no pudo menos de conceder su perdón al príncipe indio. ¿Qué no perdonará una mujer a un joven
gallardo y elegante, enamoradísimo de ella, y que viene a buscarla y a ofrecerle su mano desde
tan remotos países? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08120</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>83553</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20722</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

It was the first of May. Poldy, almost desperate, and of seeing the stork came, not However,
as usual, between ten and eleven in the morning, at the edge of the lagoon.

Barely two minutes that was there, absorbed, pensive and melancholy setting long please look at
the calm water, when a hasty sound of wings coming closer his whole body shook and delight your
soul with pleasant shock. The white stork had been flying, had fallen a few steps away, and I
approached him with their slow and stately and giving way to the
peak of castañetazos that used to always say hello.

Indescribable was the joy of Poldy. His impatience was greater than his joy. Driven for their
impatience, threw his hands around the neck of wading birds, and began looking for the cord or tape
from which depends the answer to your letter expected. What a cruel affliction had then! No letter
was pending. No tape or cord was hanging. A point was Poldy to mourn with rage. But the stork, as if
divining her feelings, opened the long wings and to the point with joy and surprise Poldy warned
that the stork had under the left wing and very well tied there with
a strong and subtle braid feathers hid under a spliff or long thin
roll.

Poldy seized him immediately and felt it was very light, which was sealed and stamped and was
so strong rope seal and was so well-tied, he could not break not
occur without scissors.

On the exterior surface of the roll, it looked written in language German songs: To His Excellency
the gracious Miss Countess of Liebestein Poldy.

He Poldy some love to the stork in order to show his gratitude, and even some say he kissed her head
in glad tidings of good message. Poldy then ran to the castle lock herself in her room, cut the
tape with scissors and see what the roll contained. There on the roll several objects Poldy was successively
examined. It was a sight picture, neat and brilliantly illuminated with colors, an extensive
and magnificent Oriental room, full Pilgrim's workmanship and elegance. In any one could see and
admire stunning lap of luxury unblemished and very tasteful. It seems that was what the prodigious
underground chamber where Aladdin find the Genie Lamp. Hung from the walls bright weapons, Indian,
Chinese and Japanese, hanging ceiling lamps carved gold were around vases, jars and glasses,
artfully carved of precious metals, very rare jaspers of ancient porcelain and work ataujía
or fine gems, ivory, bronze and other rich materials. Several idols degustation of strange and
symbolic ways, and characterized the authorized stay. There were represented Agni, the god of fire,
Kamala or Kamela, Venus in India, whose name come, in our vulgar
language Camama, bluff and their derivatives, and there were also
Indra Varuna and even the Trimurti.

First, on a splendid Alcatifa of Persia, and sitting on soft cushions Silk, beautifully embroidered,
resembled a man in the prime of youth, covered of white and rosy robe and crowned the gentle head
of a large turban, candid also, on which stood a plume or tuft of curly feathers beautiful,
and grasped the plume the turban by a huge goatee of pearls, diamonds and rubies, which was worth
an empire. Before the man had several tables dwarfs, where golden and embossed trays, in light
baskets, in slender vases and chalices glazed, offered gift of sight of smell and taste, liqueurs,
preserves and spiced fruit. On one side and some distance the young lord, was a rich and elegant
hookah, which was flexible tube luengo young Mr. grabbed by the end, revealing the thick amber
mouthpiece, pinned to the tube by a ring of sparkling emeralds. On the opposite side of the hookah,
but much closer the young lord, rose, very funny pose, our familiar friend the white stork, Poldy
whose sight not a little pleased. Not so pleased, it was of anger and shock her, but repressed
anger, attributing what he saw long-standing and essential Oriental fashion, in the back of the room
came three Bayadere, with Apsaras suit or immortal nymphs, which wove voluptuous dance, desceñido
the transparent and light clothing, arms and feet bare, wearing down the throats of the feet and
arms, anklets and bracelets, and also revealing the back and turned round and firm breasts. Several
musicians, dressed as they say they dress the sky Gandarbas and musicians of Indra, accompanied
dance with harps, flutes and violins, and erotic songs.

Poldy was dazzled at the sight all this and formed the highest concept of radiance and wealth
of the Indian lord. Of its design staff is what the photograph does not idea was entirely satisfactory.
And it was that not the purpose of photography, and below which there was this sign: my way
of life in the East.

Another smaller picture, appeared as the young man with clearer details. Was alone, full body,
but without any attachment. His suit, although on picturesque, was more European than Indian,
but the strange hat on his head and was they call heroes in the Philippines. Dolman jacket
or tight to his body and adorned with frogs, revealed the robust forms of his torso and arms. The
pants were wide and short. From the knee to the soles wore calf boots. Earrings the wide Charpa,
also leather, belting his waist, had a gun to one side and On the other hand a large hunting
knife. In the right hand glove leather cover had double-barreled shotgun, which rested on the
ground and on which he supported. For low had a sign saying: when going to hunt tigers.

Finally, there was a third picture that left nothing to be desired. There was the young Mr. clear,
accurate and clearly portrayed. His face was so beautiful. The eyes were large and expressive,
the beard seemed silky, rich and very well kept and stroked. The nose, a as much as columbine,
gave a certain majesty to their expression. And the width and straightness of face showed unusual
intelligence. You could see in all its aspect of an indescribable kind, of sympathetic and distinguished
dearly. Their bare hands, yet strong and manly were aristocratic, very neat and pretty, with pointed
fingers at the tip and encanutadas nails, instead of being short and flat. In this portrait, the
young man was dressed entirely European use of any label, with a white tie and tails, so admirably
cut and that he liked so well, do not dream of better, or Frank, Vienna, or the tailor more Famous
London. On the low end of this portrait was another sign that read, in evening dress to go to
a dance of Lord Governor of India.

Bewitched Poldy was contemplating the portrait. Was captivated by the beauty and distinction of his distant
friend. And could not be confirmed in the belief that it was an Indian prince mediated, a nabob,
or at least a Brahmin or a Kshatriya of first order and a long stem.

Imagine now the reader the desire, the wonder, the palpitations of
joy and the rare delight Poldy'd read the letter, which also came
round and was conceived in these terms:

VIII

"I'm disgusted and
I find it hard to write letters giving the address to whom treatment,
and thus adopted the ancient custom of the Orientals.

You will allow me, a beautiful countess Poldy, which of course tute
you without ceremony.

The white stork, which nests years on the roof of the splendid house
which I own in flowery banks of the Ganges, I have brought welcome
news from you, your sweet words and your divine image.

Blessed is the white stork has made me much good. Rightly called I used to Garuda. Now I can
confirm this sacred name, with which my country is designated the God-king of all birds, the
winged destroyer of dragons and snakes.

I am extremely pleased that you are of noble removed, and old enough
to where it in a village a few centuries ago was still wild, lack
of documents and files that could prove the nobility of any person,
and the deeds of their parents.

These, wandering in the rugged jungles and harsh climate of northern countries, declined from
its forgot illustrious origin and the primitive culture of the Aryans from which Paropamiso, and
only recently have civilized, taking advantage of the studies and progress of men Noon. But what
is this what you want, you are relatively noble and just me, but my clear nobility yours preceding
two thousand years at least.

I speak frankly and disposal flattery and compliments. That will give more credit to my praise
sincere.

Garuda, whimsical and happy for my inspiration, I took some verses
that I was far much imagine that could fall into such beautiful hands.

I pondered them my disgust of what around me and the craving that consumes my soul, to find
the object, hidden and distant love to meet my aspirations, understand them and share them.

Your
picture and your writing have filled my vows. You are the woman of my dreams.

Venerable Brahmans, wise old here, who wrote of love in the Kama Sutra
and other speeches and treaties, require sixty-four powers, brands
or skills, to exist in reality Padmini or perfect woman.

I declare that, to see your picture and reading your words, you have discovered in the sixty-four
talents and you have enthroned in my heart as queen and lady, and I recognize in you my Padmini,
without whose love I can not have never bliss. Love me then, as I love you, and make me happy
as I want to what you are.

Nothing can oppose our future union. The distance does not matter. I will not take to save distance,
and the day when you least think, will appear at your side and you'll
see me on their knees to your plants, asking that corresponds to the
immense love that you inspire.

There is no longer in me as exotic and pilgrim prohibit you love me.

I own the ancient namely the Brahmins and Kshatriyas, whose combined breeds descend, but I
have studied and I also managed to acquire enough knowledge of modern Europe. And do not look to prevention
unfair, but with paternal affection, as our first shoot lush, high and fertile doctrines. You might
have noticed I do not write your language badly until I copied and almost translated into Sanskrit
verses of Goethe. I am not ignorant nor French literature, English and other peoples. And
when it comes to religion, I will say with all secrecy, because I do not even shock and disturb
my relatives and friends, Brahmins and Kshatriyas, which I have denied, three years ago, the
Brahmanical religion, and I've done in secret, as a Catholic Christian, as you are. This conversion
is due to some Jesuit Father of the Spanish nation, who came to this city, from the Philippines
and stopped us for some time. It was so enlightened man, so pious and so eloquent and mellifluous,
who managed to convince me. God bless him and bless him. Callo your name, for surely you do not mind
and I do not want to hurt his extreme modesty. Only say that my frequent dealings with this blessed
Father, born in my great love to the Spanish language and I purchased and read the best prose writers
and poets, which she have written or typed.

We also Callus my Indian name, because I will not spoil it and because
it is so convoluted, well to learn only spoken through the living
voice.

Be satisfied for now, know that the venerable Jesuit my catechist, he put the baptized, the name
Seville Isidore. Do not be fickle: love me and I forget: do not fall for any of these dandies
Hof-Adel the palate or nobility of Vienna: Be convinced that my nobility is at least as clearly
and without doubt far more tolerance than theirs. The chance of them consist in ancient scrolls,
but mine has authentic documents, written twenty centuries before the parchment was invented,
and many more centuries before it was used in Austria and counts among writing materials.

Love
me, again, and have faith and hope in my love. No need to find, but wait. Soon I see your feet,
worshiping exhausted and begging with all my heart that you are the Padmini your

Isidore. "

IX

Poldy was thrilled to infer and consider, for reading the letter that his Indian was famous
and rich and I was madly in love with her. Points were, however, in the letter, which called
up in the spirit of Poldy, repairs, contradictions and even complaints. Tired gallant nor boastful
and nothing seemed fine commendation made by the Indian nobility, with extreme prejudice and even
contempt for the Austrian nobility, but apologized and even Poldy absolved the Indian, guessing
that in this particular had to be somewhat soured as his character, that he being a descendant
of Crishna of Rama, the Pandu, or perhaps some Avatar, the incarnation of Vishnu, of whom
Mahavarata held, was subjected to the foreign domination of English rogues.

Poldy and apologized to his friend, but was far from him right. She thought that noble documents
are worth only if it has power, wealth and high position who displays them, and all this, but the
wealth was undermined and ruined the Indian at last was a humble subject of His Britannic Majesty
and any Englishman or any employee of the Treasury cavalry colonel could look at him from top
to bottom.

Poldy ran well, that he who overcomes and dominates the rightful heir is always the loser and
mastered. And this in all periods and regions. In the Middle Ages, for example, at an crossroads,
and in open palenque, ran into a knight with another, and to test the respective bravery or to
confess to the contrary, that his lady was the most beautiful, or twinkling of an eye, both
lunged furiously and were knocked released. Following fell down from the chair one of the two
gentlemen, and at the moment, all the glory of prowess, all the renown that his adventures
and exploits had earned him, were transferred the gentleman winner
as attachment or appendix.

Poldy also remember reading somewhere that, back in America, when a chief inexperienced, not
still had something to gain, was on hand to mouth with another veteran chief, his enemy, and celebrated
author of two hundred thousand atrocities, and struck him so bad blow with the baton knocked
down and beat him, all the chief fame veteran moved the chief inexperienced, and even general
belief was that the rookie was the impetus transfused and the boldness
of a veteran, especially if you drank the blood inexperienced or you
eat, raw or stew, after he died.

How much is deducted Poldy said, that the true nobility of the day, the Europeans, and very uniquely
the Germans, because they exercise with the advances and improvements in our century, all the
ancient arts of peace and war, which were identified and Assyrians ruled the world and Babylonians,
Medes and Persians, Egyptians, Phoenicians and Carthaginians, and
Greeks and Romans, whose all glory, excellence and privileges are
today, according Poldy, in short, number and compendium in his illustrious
compatriots, and therefore it too.

Nevertheless, and after making the necessary cuts, was pleased that
Poldy outside the Indian noble and even that was it contained llanísimo
naturalized without hof-fähig the slightest difficulty, and attending
to her to court when they were married.

As in Austria, as well as the nobility, Czech, Polish, Hungarian,
Romanian, Croatian, Serbian, Dalmatian, etc., there is of Irish, French,
Spanish and Italian, of course could also having Brahmanical and chatriesco
home.

Another thing, something that angered Poldy, was the presence at the picture of those three Bayadere
so lightly dressed, so little modest and restrained in their dances. But Poldy also be easy
on this Indian outrage, and if not excused, you explained and almost forgave him. The Indian
had Bayadere, and made that life broken, out of pure oriental, when he was still mired in the darkness
of paganism, but when thanks to the Jesuit priest, became the true
religion, Poldy amendment was to secure and neglect that had left
their vicious sport.

The only thing in this business was sorry he had not been the Indian his catechumens because she
had become better than Jesuit priest, and had not given him the stack baptismal name as ugly
as that of Isidore. Poldy perhaps unaware that there had been a saint Archbishop of that name,
famous scholar, who collected and ordered their books all know of his time, and was in line
with what he had heard from an old princess, her aunt, terrible anti-Semitic, which persisted in asserting
princess's name was very common Isidoro among Jews, where he hated in such a way that had temptations
to dismiss an excellent because of his servants named Isidoro, and
just resigned himself to keep him in forcing service Filidoro renamed
onwards.

Moreover, Poldy could not be happier or more satisfied. The Isthmus of Suez, just opened and
already sensed Poldy through the channel, saving the Strait of Bab-el-Mandeb,
and browsing the Eritrean Sea, heading towards India, to visit the
villas, gardens and palaces of her young husband.

It's coming and could not take much, and Poldy was dying of impatience to see him live and not
painted, body and soul, not in picture. What aroused his curiosity and tickled brain soft fabrics
Padmini was the condition that he gave the young Indian. Was anxious to read or read to him
the Kama Sutra, and the sixty study well there and four skill or
excellence of Padmini, to search for it and convince themselves that
possessed them and that was not flattering to his friend.

In short, Poldy was anxious and exhilarated, but with concern and
joy, full of sweet hope and love and poetic ventures.

X

Too distracted or too poring Garuda had to walk, when not shown in the margin of the lagoon
where Poldy going to look every day.

The Indian also was as invisible as Garuda.

Poldy pined with impatience, and sometimes imagined that his youth would fade as pink ajar, within
which, where no dew fell, penetrating rays of the sun the summer season.

In fact, he was to end and the month of June and the Indian had not appeared.

One morning, as usual, between ten and eleven, became Poldy of the lagoon, where in vain had sought
the stork.

Tired and sad, in the middle of the path where the castle was returned, Poldy sat at foot of an elm,
in a rustic seat, and the most lush, intricate and beautiful the park. A crystal stream ran
close whispering. Margin grew white and purple violets and other non-cultivated flowers that
perfumed the air with soft and pleasant fragrance.

Flowery climbing roses and other plants that are stuck to the trees, and passing from tree to tree
other festoons and garlands, there were mysterious and secluded bush
venue.

Sitting and Poldy, pondered, and had to be distracted by such art, which, as commonly it is said,
was the saint to heaven.

What was his astonishment and what was his joy when noise and suddenly felt no time to recover,
saw the arrival of a gentle knight, he approached and came to be
respectful and knelt at his feet.

Impossible to doubt.

Was the original of the three portraits in photography. Stylish dress was hunter costume, but
without weapons, because it was already going to hunt tigers, but
pigeons.

And pith helmet instead of east, covering his head a jaunty fedora
adorned with a feather eagle.

The young man knocked to the ground and discovered the black hat and abundant curls of her head,
before his knees.

Deep was the emotion of Poldy.

Her heart was leaping in his chest. The young man seemed much more beautiful than the original
pictures, and when he heard his voice, Argentina, melodious and rich and soft persuasive tones
that steal prudence and calm, he could barely stand and thought he would faint.
In that situation was not any dialogue possible. What could be said
the two lovers? How what sentences would be correct in what superhuman
language to express their feelings agitators?

Only he said:

- Here
I am, Poldy. Yours is my life. I want to be and I'll be yours forever.
I love you, I will idolize, I adore you.

What was there to answer
Poldy, dumbfounded, radiant with joy, and love and decency struggling
in his soul?

He, however an effort and stood up, though troubled
and uncertain.

Then he got up too and pressed it irresistible and
lovingly in his arms. Then, pressing her face to hers and covered
it with kisses your forehead, cheeks and rosy lips.

Poldy met at
last the danger was, he was ashamed of giving in so easily who saw
and heard for the first time, and, giving his injured forces decency
rejected violence to her lover, fell off his arms, and sought shelter
for their audacity desalted fleeing and taking refuge in the castle.

Alone
in his stay, he said Poldy of his fear, he managed to calm down, and
at the bottom of his soul could not fail to grant his pardon to the
Indian prince. What will not forgive a young woman graceful and elegant,
very much in love her, and coming to look and offer his hand from
as far away countries</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>