<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08084</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>170</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>4490</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

1901

Al Profesor Dean C. Worcester

le dedica este trabajo,

=El Autor.=

ETIMOLOGÍA

DE LOS

NOMBRES DE RAZAS DE FILIPINAS

POR EL

Dr. T.H. Pardo de Tavera.

Despues de la fábula de las mil y quinientas islas que componen el Archipièlago Filipino, viene
la de las «centenares de razas que en babilónica confusion pueblan las islas,» como dice un
autor lírico geográfico que escribió sobre este pais. Haciendo omision de las rocas, peñas,
islotes insignificantes, muchos sin vejetación, otros con solo una especie de aves y algunos
insectos como fauna, y la mayoría sin un ser humano que le habite, quedan, como islas habitadas
y que solo cuentan, al tratarse de Filipinas, unas cuantas desde la de Luzon, que es la mayor,
hasta la de Cagayancillo, que es una de las más diminutas. Asi ocurre con las famosas «razas»,
nombre pomposo cuyo significado se ha confundido aplicándolo á agrupaciones políticas que en
nada se diferencian unas de otras.

Los estudios etnográficos más recientes han demostrado que las razas que habitan nuestro archipiélago
son tres, á saber: Negritos, Indonesianos y Malayos. Pero de estas razas resultan no sólo varios
mestizajes sino una gran variedad de tribus caracterizadas principalmente por las lenguas ó,
mejor dicho, dialectos filipinos que hablan. Si nos fundáramos en razones lingüísticas para
dar nombres á las diferentes agrupaciones de hombres, el numero de las llamadas razas filipinas,
con ser bastante crecido, no llegaría sin embargo á la cifra que hoy alcanza y que el profesor
Blumentritt ha tenido la paciente labor de reunir en un folleto por orden alfabetico, publicado
en español, con el título de «Las razas del archipiélago filipino.»

Como los estudios lingüisticos aclaran poderosamente las cuestiones antropológicas, he creido
que seria util hacer una información que permita establecer la etimología de los nombres que
hoy se aplican á las diferentes tribus que, con el nombre de razas, pueblan Filipinas.

Las divisiones políticas de las islas responden casi siempre á divisiones fundadas en la lengua,
de manera que, principiando por hacernos cargo de los nombres que caracterizan las provincias
cuando estas se aplican á agrupaciones que hablan la misma lengua, hallamos en la isla de Luzón
los siguientes: Tagalog, Pampango, Bicol, Pangasinan, Sambál, Ilocano, Ibanag ó Cagayan. Despues
veremos que dentro de cada una de estas provincias existen diferentes tribus, muchas con lengua
distinta que llevan, por esta razón ó por otra desconocida, un nombre diferente.

Bisayas se aplica á tres dialectos hablados en Cebú, Iloilo y Negros: Calamian ó Cuyo es tambien
nombre de agrupación lingüista y al llegar á Mindanao vemos que la división territorrial no
es ya del carácter que en Luzón.

Muchas tribus tienen por denominación, un nombre geográfico: en otra se descubre una razon
topográfica, ó de costumbres locales, ó de relación con otras tribus vecinas. Algunas veces
los nombres son sencillamente de la localidad aplicados á los habitantes, otras veces el origen
del nombre no aparece tan claro y para descubrir su etimología hay que empezar por descomponerlo
para descubrir la raiz como veremos más adelante.

Para mayor facilidad dividiremos los nombres que vamos á estudiar en las agrupaciones siguientes:

Compuestos con el prefijo Taga. » con el prefijo I. » con el prefijo A. » con el prefijo Ma.
» con el prefijo Non. » con el prefijo Ka y sufijo An. » en otras formas.

       *       *       *       *       *

Prefijo TAGA.

Este prefijo, al juntarse con nombres de lugar, significa «nativo de él, natural». Usado sólo,
no tiene significación alguna y lo encontramos formando nombres de las siguíentes agrupaciones
étnicas: TAGALOG, TAGABALOY, TAGABAWA, TAGABULU, TAGABELI, TAGACAOLO, TAGABANUA ó TAGBANUA,
etc. etc.

El significado de semejante prefijo nos lo dan las lenguas polinesianas: en Samoa se llama
taga-ta el hombre; en Tahiti, perdiendo la g encontramos la palabra taa-ta. Es, pues, indudable
que taga, hoy prefijo sin sentido propio como vóz aislada, significó primitivamente «hombre».
Ahora, veamos la etimología de las otras voces á que lo hallamos unido, para denominar tribus
más ó menos importantes.

Una de las mayores agrupaciones lingüistas de Filipinas está formada por los tagalog con cuyo
nombre se denominan los habitantes de las provincias de Manila, Bulakan, Nueva-Ecija, Batáan,
parte de Tarlac, Laguna, Tayabas y el distrito de Morong, contando con alrededor de 1.250.000
individuos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09785</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>4055</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

1901

Professor Dean C. Worcester

dedicates this work

.= = The Author

ETYMOLOGY

OF

NAMES
OF RACES OF THE PHILIPPINES

BY THE

Dr. TH Pardo de Tavera.

After the story of a thousand and five hundred islands that make up
the Philippine Archipelago is that of the "hundreds of races that
inhabit the islands Babylonian confusion," as says a geographical
lyrical author who wrote about this country.

By omission of rocks, boulders, insignificant islets, many without
vejetación, others with only one species of birds and some insects
and wildlife, and most without a human being who will live in them,
are, as inhabited islands and only have, being the Philippines, a
few from Luzon, which is the largest, to that of Cagayancillo, which
is one of the tiniest.

So it is with the famous 'races' pompous name whose meaning has been
confused by applying it to political groups in no different from each
other.

Recent ethnographic studies have shown that the races that inhabit
our islands are three, viz: Negritos, Indonesian and Malay.

But these breeds are not only various miscegenation but a great variety of tribes mainly characterized
by languages ??or, rather speak Filipino dialects. If we will found in linguistic reasons for
give names to the different groups of men, the number of races called Philippine to be quite
grown, not yet come to the figure reached today and the teacher Blumentritt had the patient
work together in alphabetical order a brochure published in Spanish with the title "The races of
the Philippine archipelago."

As powerfully clear linguistic studies anthropological issues, I believed that would be useful
to information to establish the etymology of the names today apply
to the different tribes, with the name of races, Philippines.

Political divisions of the islands almost always respond to divisions based on language, so that,
beginning with taking charge of the names that characterize the provinces when these are applied
to groups that speak the same language, found on the island of Luzon the following: Tagalog, Pampanga,
Bicol, Pangasinan, sambal, Ilocano, Ibanag or Cagayan. After see that within each of these provinces
have different tribes, many with language carrying different, for this reason or another unknown,
a different name.

Visayas applies to three dialects spoken in Cebu, Iloilo and Negros: Calamian or Cuyo is also
pool name linguist and Mindanao to get see that not a territorial
division the character is already in Luzon.

Many tribes have by name, a geographical name: another reason is discovered topographic, or local
customs, or other relationship with neighboring tribes. Sometimes names are simply applied to local
residents, other times the source the name does not appear so clear and to discover its etymology
is to start by decomposing to discover the root as discussed below.

For convenience we divide the names that we shall study in the following groupings:

Compounds with the prefix Taga. "With the prefix I. "With the prefix A. "With the prefix Ma
"With the Non prefix. "With the prefix and suffix Ka W 'in other ways.

* * * * *

TAGA prefix.

This prefix, to join names, it means "native of it, natural."

       Used alone, has no significance whatsoever and we find the following
names to form clusters Ethnic: TAGALOG, TAGABALOY, TAGABAWA, TAGABULU,
TAGABELI, TAGACAOLO, TAGABANUA or Tagbanúas, etc. etc.

The meaning
of such code is provided for us Polynesian languages: in Samoa is
called taga-ta man, in Tahiti, losing the g we find the word taa-ta.

It is therefore undoubtedly that taga, prefix with no real meaning
today as isolated voice, originally meant "man."

Now, consider the etymology of the other voices to which we find attached, to name tribes more
or less important.

One of the major linguistic groups in the Philippines is composed
of the Tagalog with which name are called the inhabitants of the provinces
of Manila, Bulak, Nueva Ecija, Bataan, part of Tarlac, Laguna, Tayabas
and the District of Morong, with about 1,250,000 individuals.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>