<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03750</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>281536</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>712</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Pero contra esta suposición estaba su nuevo amor, el amor por Vérod:
si ella por su parte amaba ya a otro ¿no debía alegrarse del nuevo afecto del Príncipe? Eso
parecía tanto más cierto, cuanto que la amistad de la Condesa con Vérod no había podido, según
los más, ser inocente. Muy pocos creían en la pureza de sus intenciones: el joven tenía que
haber sido amante feliz de la dama italiana, pues si no ¿qué interés podía haberlo impulsado
a formular la acusación? ¿Era creíble que, amándose y con la libertad de que ambos gozaban,
se hubieran contentado con suspirarse mutuamente? ¿Cómo se podía creer que el joven se conformara
con un afecto fraternal? ¿Y qué habría podido obligar a la Condesa a resistirle? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>704645</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>698</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> But against this assumption was his new love, love candle plant: if she
in turn loved and to another "should not rejoice at the new Prince's affection? That seemed
all the more true given that the friendship of the countess with candle plant had failed, as the
most, be innocent. Few believed in the purity of his intentions: the young man had to having
been the mistress of the Italian lady happy, because if not, what could have driven interest
to make the accusation? Was it credible that, loving and freedom that they both enjoyed, have
been mutually satisfied with sighs? How could one believe that the young man conform with brotherly
affection? What could have forced the Countess to resist</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>