<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07190</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>136080</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20521</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Bajo la denominacion de Republica Bolivar (mas tarde Bolivia), se constituyeron por medio de
una Asamblea general, declarando en independencia, las provincias del Alto Peru a 10 de Julio
del mismo ano 1825 y confiaron al Libertador la autoridad ejecutiva por todo el tiempo de su
permanencia en el territorio del Estado, y Sucre quedo encargado del mando inmediato de los
departamentos en que aquel habia sido dividido. A los tres meses no cabales, esto es, el 6
de Octubre, despues de haber encargado al Libertador que formase una Constitucion politica
para el pais, se disolvio la Asamblea, aplazando la reunion del cuerpo constituyente, reunion
que debia realizarse el 25 de Mayo del siguiente ano.

A pesar de los esfuerzos hechos por los partidarios de la independencia, el general Rodil,
refugiado en el Callao, sostuvo durante mas de un ano esta plaza, rendida por fin el 23 de
Enero de 1826, dia en que el Peru, a consecuencia de este acontecimiento quedaba totalmente
emancipado de Espana y la America del Sud veia terminarse la sangrienta y larga lucha comenzada
y llevada a feliz termino por los valientes hijos de Venezuela, bajo la gloriosa direccion
del celeberrimo Bolivar.

Pero el pueblo colombiano, como sucede con todos los pueblos colocados en analogas circunstancias,
si bien cediendo a un natural impulso, habia desplegado todas sus fuerzas para sacudir el yugo
de la esclavitud, no bien dispuesto aun a recibir la nueva forma de gobierno, poco ilustrado
para conocer los medios de aprovecharse de la libertad que habia conquistado, y no comprendiendo
el valor de los deberes que adquiria al adquirir nuevos derechos, pronto se vio envuelto en
las discordias civiles por no prestarse de buen grado a ellos. Resistiendose los caraquenos
a la tercera invitacion hecha por Paez, que queria dar cumplimiento al decreto sobre la organizacion
de milicias, se vio este jefe obligado a hacer algunas prisiones, y con tal motivo Caracas
presento 17 dias antes a la toma del Callao la imagen de una espantosa revolucion.

So color de haber sido hollados los derechos del pueblo en la manera de dar cumplimiento a
los decretos del gobierno, la Camara de los representantes fulmino contra Paez una acusacion,
que en 30 de Marzo admitio el Senado, suspendiendole de su empleo y citandole a dar cuenta
de su conducta. No solo desobedecio esta orden trasmitida por medio del poder ejecutivo, sino
que por disposicion de la Asamblea municipal de Valencia, en cuya ciudad se hallaba Paez entonces,
el 30 de Abril reasumio el mando de que el Senado le habia separado, dando lugar este hecho
a que todos los pueblos se creyeran autorizados a desconocer el legitimo gobierno, y pronto
se vio la Republica envuelta en las discordias civiles.

Dos fueron los bandos que se alzaron: uno federal y otro central, siendo los partidarios del
primero de los sistemas quienes marchaban a su fin con mayor unidad, con mas perfecta armonia.
Los federalistas de Caracas concitaron a Paez para que convocara y presidiera una Asamblea
general con objeto de fijar el destino politico de Venezuela en aquellas circunstancias; y
verificada la reunion el 7 de Noviembre, despues de mediar violentas discusiones y una incalificable
votacion, Paez quedo autorizado; conforme a los poderes de que la Asamblea le habia investido,
dio un decreto senalando el 10 de Diciembre para la reunion de los colegios electorales y para
la instalacion del Cuerpo constituyente en Valencia fijo igual dia de Enero de 1827.

Bolivar, noticioso de los escandalos promovidos en Venezuela, partio de Lima el 4 de Setiembre
y cuarenta dias mas tarde entraba en Santa Fe de Bogota, siendo recibido con generales muestras
de afecto. El 25 de Noviembre se dirigio a Venezuela y durante su travesia hasta Cucuta fue
reuniendo tropas para presentarse con imponente actitud. El 16 del siguiente mes dio una proclama
desde Maracaibo en que, ofreciendo acelerar la gran Convencion nacional para que legalmente
tuviera el pueblo leyes fundamentales, decia: solo el (el pueblo) conoce su bien y es dueno
de su suerte, y no un poderoso, ni un partido, ni una sola fraccion del mismo pueblo. El Libertador,
al cual volvian algunos de los extraviados patricios, llego por Coro a Puerto-Cabello el ultimo
dia del ano, epoca en que Paez se encontraba en Valencia.

Los acontecimientos del Peru mientras el trascurso del ano que asi espiraba fueron: la reunion
del Congreso constituyente de Bolivia, que con lijeras variantes acepto el proyecto que le
habia enviado Bolivar, acompanado del reconocimiento de aquella republica por el Consejo de
gobierno del Peru; el nombramiento del general Sucre como Presidente vitalicio del Estado,
dignidad que solo admitio por dos anos; la declaracion de nulidad en los poderes otorgados
por los colegios de algunas provincias a sus representantes, hecha por el Consejo de gobierno
peruano en su primer Congreso constitucional; la disolucion de este; la reunion del colegio
electoral de la provincia de Lima, en virtud de decreto de la autoridad competente, el 16 de
Agosto; la aceptacion que el mismo hizo de la Constitucion boliviana como Codigo fundamental
del Peru, y el nombramiento de Bolivar para Presidente perpetuo de la Republica, actos sancionados
por el Consejo de gobierno, en vista de la unanimidad conque los colegios electorales habian
procedido en todos sus acuerdos.

CAPITULO XII

Disposiciones conciliatorias.--Bolivar y Paez se reconcilian.--Error politico.--Reclamaciones
de Nueva-Granada y del Peru.--Dimision del Libertador ante el quinto Congreso reunido en Bogota.--No
es admitida su dimision.--Se levantan facciones en Venezuela.--El Congreso Constituyente del
Peru.--Agitaciones politicas y desunion de Colombia. --Fracasa la Convencion de Ocana.--Acta
del 15 de Junio de 1828. --Conjuracion a mano armada.--Peligro del Libertador.--Acto de justicia
contra los conspiradores.--Nueva convocacion a un Congreso Constituyente.--Trabajos de zapa
de los descontentos.--Manifiesto de Bolivar.--Consecuencias del manifiesto.--Es llamado el
Libertador por algunos miembros del Congreso de Colombia.--Sancion del Codigo politico.--Cesacion
de la dictadura y de la representacion de la Colombia.--Viaje de Bolivar a Cartagena.--Decretos
de Paez.--Instalacion del Congreso en Valencia.--Nueva Constitucion de Venezuela.--Fallecimiento
del Libertador.

El ano 1827 era inaugurado por el Libertador de una manera politica y conciliatoria. El primer
dia de aquel desde Puerto Cabello publico un decreto de amnistia, confirmando a Paez la autoridad
de jefe civil y militar que al principio de la revolucion le habia sido conferido por los concejos
municipales. Este dicto al siguiente otro decreto por el cual reconocia y mandaba reconocer
a Bolivar como Presidente de la Republica, anulando al propio tiempo todas sus anteriores resoluciones,
inclusa la de reunion de un Congreso. El 4, a las dos de la tarde, ambos jefes se habian visto
y abrazado al pie del cerro de Naguanagua, entrando luego juntos en Valencia entre las aclamaciones
entusiastas del pueblo; y el 10 del mismo mes todo Caracas se deshacia en expresiones de la
mas grande admiracion al acoger en su recinto a su ilustre hijo, el Libertador de la America
del Sud.

El excesivo amor de este grande hombre por la causa que tan constante y noblemente habia defendido,
el vivo deseo que le agitaba de consolidar su grande obra, le hizo cometer un error, perdonable
bajo este punto de vista. Pero ?quien que sintiese como el sentia, quien que como el se viese
rodeado de tan rebeldes circunstancias cuando apenas lucia la primer aurora de la libertad
de su patria, quien que como el la encontrase amenazada de ser envuelta entre las sombras de
una devastadora tempestad en el momento mismo de nacer, no hubiera tratado de evitar a toda
costa las tristes consecuencias que resultarian de la desunion entre los elementos politicos
que debian formar entonces su mas firme apoyo? Esto fue sin duda lo que le hizo halagar a los
disidentes, lo que le obligo a apagar su desenfrenada ambicion y deseo de mando, produciendo
entre sus amigos el descontento y la envidia. iAmigos!...iQue lastimoso abuso se ha hecho de
esta bella frase, empleandola sin razon en vez de adeptos al tratarse de aquellos hombres que,
como Bolivar, llegan a tener entre sus manos los destinos de una nacion!

En la Nueva-Granada, lo mismo que en el Peru, muchos militares dirigian representaciones al
gobierno reprobando las reformas introducidas en la primitiva ley del Estado; y despues de
tantos y tan inmensos sacrificios, despues de tanta y tan preciosa sangre vertida en aras de
la patria, mezquinos intereses, miras egoistas de dominio, envidias y rencores mal comprimidos,
encienden los animos y los concitan a la guerra mas inicua que la humanidad conoce entre la
iniquidad misma de la guerra, a la que el genio del mal despierta y mantiene en el corazon
de los que debiera unir el vinculo fraternal de las costumbres, del idioma, del pais y la familia.
Asi, pues, por desgracia, al triunfo de la independencia sucedia la discordia civil en la America
del Sud, enconada y sobreexcitada por medidas cuyo espiritu, cuyo fin no era otro que el de
la conciliacion, el bienestar y la fuerza. Pero el hombre propone y Dios dispone.

Ante el quinto Congreso, reunido en Bogota, dimitio Bolivar su cargo de Presidente, y despues
de largos y acalorados debates, por 50 contra 24 votos no fue atendido. Esta dimision la hizo
desde su pueblo natal; en vista de la negativa, el 10 de Setiembre paso a Bogota, jurando nuevamente
ante el Congreso, al efecto reunido en sesion extraordinaria, sostener y defender como hasta
alli la Constitucion de la Republica. En Venezuela mientras tanto se habian levantado facciones
que, como la de Cisneros en Caracas, llevaban la devastacion a todas partes.

El Congreso constituyente del Peru se habia reunido, con antelacion a los hechos ultimamente
citados, el 1 deg. de Mayo, y declaro que la Constitucion jurada en 9 de Diciembre del ano
anterior era nula y sin ningun efecto, por haber sido sancionada de un modo ilegal y atentatoria
a la soberania del pueblo; restableciendo provisionalmente en su fuerza y vigor, con supresion
de algunos capitulos, interin el Cuerpo Legislativo se ocupaba de formar otra nueva, la admitida
y votada en 1823. Don Jose de Lamar, gran mariscal, y Don Manuel Salazar y Barquijano fueron
elegidos, el primero como Presidente y el segundo como Vice-Presidente de la Republica. Tales
fueron los hechos mas notables o importantes de la America del Sud en este ano.

En el siguiente de 1828 dos eran los grandes partidos que se agitaban en el seno de la Colombia.
Los que aspiraban con la mejor buena fe del mundo a hacer alteraciones liberales en la ley
fundamental,--cuyo medio, a los ojos de sus emulos, era el mas a proposito para derrocar al
Libertador, asi como tambien para los que deseaban dividir el territorio colombiano en tres
distintos estados independientes entre si,--formaban el primero de estos partidos. En el segundo
estaban afiliados la mayor parte de los generales, jefes y oficiales venezolanos, mas todos
los extranjeros que subsistian al servicio de la Colombia y los deudos y amigos de Bolivar,
que se esforzaban en sostener la integridad de la republica creada por la union de Venezuela,
Quito y la Nueva-Granada. Esta era precisamente la division intentada por los de la faccion
contraria.

Despues de haber fracasado la Convencion nacional reunida en Ocana el 9 de Abril, a causa de
lo encontrado de las opiniones y principios politicos alli representados, una junta de personas
notables, formada en Bogota, suscribia el 13 de Junio una acta en la cual hacian solemne protesta
contra toda reforma que emanase de la Convencion, depositando el cargo supremo de la Republica
y su entera confianza en el general Bolivar, ejemplo que luego fue imitado y seguido en toda
su latitud por los demas pueblos. De una manera tan publica y esplicita fue reconocido el ilustre
Libertador como jefe supremo del Estado y revestido de las mas amplias facultades.

El 24 del mismo mes, este hombre, objeto de tantos y tan continuos ataques, doblemente realzados
por ellos, por sus actos de desinteres y por su heroica perseverancia en el fin que se habia
propuesto desde el principio de la campana de la independencia; este hombre, digno de un pueblo,
no mejor, pero si mas ilustrado, comenzo a legislar en importantes materias, suprimiendo la
Vice-Presidencia y dando al Consejo de Estado una forma nueva y mas adecuada a las necesidades
que le rodeaban.

Llego a tan alto grado el encono de sus adversarios politicos, que conjurandose contra el,
dominados por el criminal objeto de arrancarle el mando con la vida a un mismo tiempo, apellidandole
tirano de la patria, el 25 de Setiembre atacaron de mano armada en Bogota el palacio a la hora
de la media noche, despues de asesinar a los centinelas, y lograron penetrar hasta la estancia
del Libertador; afortunadamente pudo este salvarse arrojandose a la calle desde una ventana
que por falta de prevision de parte de los agresores habia quedado sin custodia alguna. Una
vez libre, pudo luego con su actividad y energia de costumbre tomar las medidas necesarias;
y habiendo sido aprehendidos los conjurados, todos pagaron con la vida su temeraria empresa
menos el general Santander, complicado tambien en la trama y a quien la ultima pena fue conmutada
por Consejo de gobierno en la de destierro con privacion del empleo.

De esta manera, y con la convocacion de un Congreso en Bogota para el 2 de Enero de 1830, el
cual vendria investido con el caracter de Constituyente, cerraba sus puertas el ano 1828, ano
lleno de malestar por la efervescencia de los partidos en que estaba dividida la opinion publica
del pais, tanto mas temible cuanto que se alzaba en el corazon de hombres vigorosos y avezados
a los azares de la guerra.

Facil es comprender que a pesar de tan energicas medidas el mal no habria cesado; y asi era
en efecto. Siguio sorda y lentamente bullendo en los animos de los descontentos durante el
ano 1829, y arraigandose mas profundamente toda vez que el peso del poder no le permitia salir
a la superficie; pero como el momento senalado para la instalacion del Congreso se acercase,
publico Bolivar un manifiesto en que autorizaba a los pueblos para que pudiesen emitir libremente
su dictamen, ya por medio de la imprenta, ya por otro cualquiera de los permitidos por la ley.

A una reunion provocada por el jefe general de policia, que lo era Arismendi, acudieron varios
vecinos notables de Caracas con el fin de tratar de las peticiones que debian elevarse al Congreso.
Una carta circular de Paez los animaba tambien a emitir sus opiniones con plena franqueza y
libertad. Asi es que acordaron pedir a la autoridad superior civil de su provincia se convocase
el pueblo a una Asamblea general, suplica que fue atendida, ordenandose inmediatamente la convocatoria.
Esta Asamblea, legalmente constituida en la capital el 26 de Noviembre, resolvio: "desconocer
la autoridad del Libertador; separar a Venezuela del gobierno de Bogota; consultar la voluntad
de los antiguos departamentos de aquella, invitandoles a que por medio de un cuerpo constituyente
reconociesen, defendiesen y manifestasen publicamente la separacion que de aquel gobierno intentaban
los venezolanos, todo lo cual quedo consignado." Por ultimo, decidieron "que el general Paez
se encargase del mando de los departamentos en tanto se verificara la instalacion del nuevo
Congreso."

No reinaba menos agitacion entre los granadinos. El 2 de Enero de 1830, constituidos en comision
preparatoria varios miembros del Congreso de Colombia en Bogota, dieron principio a sus tareas,
y el 4 se pusieron de acuerdo sobre la conveniencia de hacer que Bolivar en persona instalase
el Congreso para demostrar a los pueblos la buena armonia en que sus representantes se hallaban
con el padre de la patria, llamandole a fin de combinar los medios mas acertados de conjurar
las calamidades que amenazaban al pais. Acudio Bolivar al llamamiento, y el 20 del mismo mes,
cinco dias despues de su llegada a Bogota, dejo instalado el Congreso, renunciando formalmente
a la presidencia que se le habia conferido; pero su renuncia fue desechada, exigiendole que
hasta que la Constitucion quedase sancionada y nombrados los funcionarios superiores en el
orden politico, para cortar las alas a la anarquia conservase su autoridad, unico medio que
el Congreso estimaba habil en aquellas amenazadoras circunstancias.

En efecto, el 29 de Abril quedo sancionado el Codigo politico y, nombrados como Presidente
y Vice-Presidente, para el primer cargo Joaquin Mosquera y para el segundo el general Domingo
Caicedo, tuvo fin la dictadura. Doce dias despues cerraba el Congreso las sesiones de aquella
Asamblea legislativa, que fue la postrera de las reunidas a nombre y en representacion de Colombia.

El Libertador de la America del Sud, reducido ya a la simple condicion de ciudadano, el 8 de
Mayo salio para Cartagena con objeto de pasar a Europa; y al despedirse de los constituyentes,
herido en lo intimo de su noble corazon de patriota, no por su separacion del alto cargo que
hasta alli habia ejercido, el cual tantas y tantas veces como al presente renunciara leal y
dignamente, ni tampoco lastimado en su ambicion, puesto que solo se retiraba "rico de honores
y de gloria;" pronuncio estas notables palabras: Me ruborizo al pensarlo, pero la independencia
es el unico bien que hemos conquistado a costa de todos los demas.

En Venezuela, mientras tanto, con fecha 13 de Enero, el general Paez expedia dos decretos,
uno por el cual creaba para el despacho de un gobierno provisional tres ministerios de Estado,
cuyas funciones debian ejercer, en Guerra y Marina, el general Soublette; en Interior, Justicia
y Policia, el Dr. Miguel Pena; en Hacienda y Relaciones exteriores, el Licenciado Diego Bautista
Urbaneja; y el otro concerniente a la manera con que debia precederse para las elecciones del
Congreso Constituyente, que constando al menos de las dos terceras partes, debia reunirse en
Valencia el dia 30 de Abril.

Instalado este el 8 de Mayo, su primer acto fue la confirmacion del poder ejecutivo de que
Paez estaba investido hasta nueva resolucion del Congreso, cuyas tareas quedaron terminadas
el 22 de Setiembre, sancionando un Codigo fundamental por el que declaraba: "que el gobierno
de Venezuela es y sera siempre republicano, popular, representativo, responsable y de eleccion,"
dividiendo la potestad suprema en judicial, legislativa y ejecutiva, con un cuarto poder exclusivamente
destinado a entender en la parte municipal. De este modo la forma adoptada era un termino medio
entre el centralismo y el federalismo. El poder ejecutivo quedaba a cargo de un magistrado
con el titulo de Presidente de la Republica, y tanto este cargo como el de Vice-Presidente,
cesaban a los cuatro anos en sus funciones, no siendo reelegibles sino despues de pasar por
lo menos un periodo constitucional. Cuatro secretarios responsables serian elegidos por el
Presidente para el ejercicio de su ministerio. El poder legislativo constaria de un Congreso
popular, dividido en dos Camaras, una de diputados representantes y otra de senadores, elegidos
tambien por solo cuatro anos.

Este fue el ultimo resultado que alcanzo a ver Bolivar, el hombre cuyos esfuerzos bastaron
a conquistar la independencia de su pais, y los cuales fueron impotentes para conservar la
integridad de Colombia. Desde este momento, perseguido por la idea de la inevitable ruina de
la nacion que a costa de su sangre y de casi toda su fortuna habia logrado sacar de la nada,
herido mortalmente en su tierna y constante afeccion hacia su adorada patria, el 17 de Diciembre,
a la una de la tarde y los 47 anos de edad, espiro en la quinta de San Pedro, situada a corta
distancia de Santa Marta, dirigiendo la expresion de su ultimo sacrificio a los pueblos de
Colombia en estos memorables palabra: Si mi muerte contribuye a que cesen los partidos y la
union se consolide, yo bajare tranquilo al sepulcro.

?Podia exigirse mas del heroico Libertador de la America del Sud? Sus restos descansan en la
Santa Iglesia metropolitana de Caracas desde el 17 de Diciembre de 1842, despues de haber permanecido
doce anos justos entre los granadinos. iCosa extrana! el general Jose Antonio Paez era Presidente
de la Republica de Venezuela cuando el Congreso sancionaba la traslacion de las preciosas cenizas
del Padre de la Patria.

FIN.

</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08882</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>21619</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18603</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Republic under the name of Bolivar (Bolivia later), constituted by a General Assembly, declaring
independence in the provinces of Upper Peru to July 10 the same year 1825 and entrusted the executive
authority Libertador around the time of stay in the territory of the State, and Sucre is charged
with the immediate command of the that departments that had been divided. Three months is not
complete, that is, 6 October, after having instructed the Liberator, which formed a political
constitution for the country, disbanded the Assembly, postponing the constitutional body reunion,
reunion which was to be held on May 25 of next year.

Despite the efforts made by supporters of independence, General Rodil, refugee in Callao, held
for over a year this place, finally surrendered on 23 January 1826, the day that Peru, as
a result of this event was totally emancipated from Spain and South America saw the completion
of the long and bloody struggle started and carried to a successful conclusion by the brave sons
of Venezuela, under the direction glorious the celebrated Bolivar.

But the Colombian people, like all people placed in analogous circumstances While yielding to a natural
impulse, had displayed all his strength to throw off the yoke of slavery, not even willing to
receive the new form of government, unenlightened to find ways to take advantage of the freedom
they had conquered, and not understanding the value of the duties to acquire new rights acquired,
soon became involved in civil strife not willingly given them. Resisting the Caracas the third
invitation made by Paez, who wanted to implement the decree on the organization militia, was
the chief forced to do some prisons, and on that occasion Caracas presented 17 days prior to the seizure
of Callao the image of a terrible revolution.

Pretext of having been trampled people's rights in the way of implementing government decrees,
the House of Representatives Paez fulminated against an accusation, March 30 in the Senate admitted,
suspended from his job and to realize quoting of their behavior. Disobeyed the order not only
transmitted by the executive, but that provision of the Municipal Assembly of Valencia, whose
city was Paez then April 30, retook the Senate that he had separated, resulting in the fact to believe
all people are entitled to ignore the legitimate government, and soon Republic was embroiled
in civil strife.

There were two sides who were raised: one federal and one central, with supporters first system
who marched to an end with more unity, more perfect harmony. The Federalists stirred Paez Caracas
to convene and chair an Assembly general in order to determine the political destiny of Venezuela
in the circumstances, and verified the reunion on November 7, after violent debates and an
unspeakable vote, Paez is authorized, pursuant to the powers that the Assembly had invested, pointing
issued a decree on December 10 for the reunion of polling stations and the installation of fixed
Valencia constituent body as day of January 1827.

Bolivar, news of the scandals promoted in Venezuela, departed from Lima on September 4 and forty
days later went into Santa Fe de Bogota, and was received with general samples affection. On November
25, headed to Venezuela and during his journey to Cucuta was massing troops to perform with
impressive attitude. On 16 the following month gave a proclamation from Maracaibo that, offering
high speed National Convention to legally people had the basic laws, he said: only the (people)
know her well and is owner their fate, not a powerful nor a party, not a single fraction from
the same village. The Liberator which returned some of the patricians lost, I arrive at Puerto-Cabello
Choir last day of the year, a time when Paez was in Valencia.

The events of Peru as the course of the year that were expiring so: the reunion Bolivia's Constituent
Congress, which accepted the draft Thin variants that Bolivar had sent, accompanied by the
recognition of that republic by the Council Peru's government, the appointment of General Sucre
as Life President of the State dignity that only admitted for two years, the declaration of
nullity of the powers conferred by schools in some provinces to their representatives, made
by the Governing Council Peruvian Congress in its first constitutional dissolution of this, the
school reunion election in the province of Lima, by decree of the competent authority, 16 August,
the acceptance that it made the Bolivian Constitution as fundamental Code Peru, and Bolivar's
appointment to president in perpetuity of the Republic, acts punishable by the Governing Council,
in view of unanimity had simply to have polling stations proceeded in all its agreements.

CHAPTER XII

Conciliatory provisions .-- Bolivar and Paez reconcile political failure .-- .-- Claims New-Granada
and Peru .-- Resignation of the Liberator to the fifth Congress meeting in Bogota .-- No his resignation
is accepted .-- factions are raised in Venezuela .-- The Constituent Congress Peru .-- political
unrest and disunity of Colombia. - Fail the Convention of Ocana Act .-- June 15, 1828. - Conspiracy
to armed .-- .-- Hazard Libertador Justice Act against the conspirators .-- New convening a Constituent
Congress .-- spade work of the discontented .-- Bolivar Manifesto .-- .-- Consequences of the
manifest is called the Libertador by some members of Congress of Colombia .-- .-- Punishment
of the Political Code Cessation of the dictatorship and the representation of Colombia .-- Journey
to Cartagena Bolivar .-- Decrees Paez .-- Congress in Valencia Installing New Constitution of Venezuela
.-- Death .-- del Libertador.

The year 1827 was opened by the Libertador in a manner and conciliatory policy. The first day one
from Puerto Cabello post an amnesty decree, thus confirming the authority Paez of civil and military
chief at the beginning of the revolution had been given by councils municipal. This dictated the following
other decree by which he recognized and sent acknowledge Bolivar as President of the Republic,
at the same time canceling all its previous resolutions, including that of reunion of a Congress. 4, at
two in the afternoon, both leaders had been and embraced at the foot of the hill Naguanagua, and
fit together in Valencia amid the acclamations enthusiastic people, and 10 of the same month across
Caracas melted in terms of greatest admiration to host on its campus to its illustrious son,
the liberator of America del Sud

The excessive love of this great man for the cause he had so nobly defended constant, strong desire
to consolidate it shook his great work, I made a mistake, excusable this point of view. But? Who
felt that felt like, who he saw that as as rebels surrounded circumstances when looked just the
first dawn of freedom of his country, who found that as the threat of being wrapped in the
shadows of a devastating storm at the moment of birth, had not tried to avoid at all coast of
the sad consequences that would result from disunion among the political elements which were
to be so strongly supported? This was no doubt what he did flatter the dissidents, which forced
him to put his unbridled ambition and desire to control, producing among his friends discontent
and envy. iAmigos! ... iQue pitiful abuse has been made This beautiful phrase, used without
reason rather than to be followers of those men who and Bolivar, come to have in their hands
the destiny of a nation!

In New Granada, as well as in Peru, many representations they directed the military failing
government reforms in the primitive law of the State, and, after so many great sacrifices,
after so much bloodshed and so precious for the sake of country, narrow interests, selfish view
domain, envy and resentment wrong tablets Tempers flare and ranks first in the most unjust war
the human race is between iniquity of the war itself, which the genius of evil awakens and
keeps the heart than you should join the fraternal bond of custom, language, country and family.
So, unfortunately, the triumph of independence was followed by the civil strife in America del Sud,
bitter and overwrought by measures whose spirit, whose purpose was none other than conciliation,
the welfare and strength. But man proposes and God disposes.

To the fifth congress, held in Bogota, Bolivar resigned his position as President, and then lengthy
and heated debate, by 50 votes to 24, went unheeded. This resignation was made from his hometown,
in view of the refusal, on 10 September step Bogota, vowing again before the Congress, meeting in extraordinary
session effect, and to uphold and defend there the Constitution of the Republic. In Venezuela
meanwhile had risen factions that, like Cisneros in Caracas, brought devastation everywhere.

The Constituent Congress of Peru had been met, prior to the events lately cited by 1 deg. May,
and declare that the Constitution sworn in on December 9th of the year was above zero and
with no effect, being punished by illegal and threatening the sovereignty of the people provisionally
restoring force and effect with suppression some chapters, meantime the Legislature was concerned
with forming a new one, that permitted and voted in 1823. Don Jose de Lamar, Grand Marshall, and
Don Manuel Salazar and were Barquijano elected, the first and the second as President and Vice-President
of the Republic. Such were the most notable or important in South America this year.

In 1828, following two major parties were stirred in the heart of Colombia. Those who aspired to
the best of faith in the world to make liberal changes in the law fundamental - which means,
in the eyes of his rivals, was the most on purpose to overthrow the Libertador, as well as
for those who wanted to divide the territory into three Colombian different states independent
of each other - were the first of these games. In the second Most were members of the generals,
commanders and Venezuelan officials, but all foreigners who remained in the service of Colombia
and the relatives and friends of Bolivar, that strove to uphold the integrity of the republic
created by the union of Venezuela, Quito and New Grenada. This was precisely the division attempted
by the faction contrary.

After having failed the National Convention held in Ocana on April 9 due to the findings of opinions
and political principles represented there, a gathering of people notables, formed in Bogota, signed
on June 13 an act in which they made solemn protest against any reform emanating from the Convention,
depositing the highest office of the Republic and his entire confidence in Gen. Bolivar, example
was later imitated and followed throughout latitude for the other races. In a manner as public
and was recognized by the illustrious esplicita Liberator as supreme chief of the state and invested
with the broadest powers.

On 24 of the month, this man, the subject of so many ongoing attacks, doubly enhanced for them,
for their acts of selflessness and heroic perseverance in the order which had proposed since the
beginning of the bell of independence, this man, worthy of a people not better, but more enlightened,
began to legislate on important matters, suppressing Vice-Presidency and the Council of State
giving a new and more appropriate to the needs around him.

Arrived at such a high degree the hatred of political opponents, who conspire against him, dominated
by the criminal to snatch the remote object with life at the same time, surnamed tyrant of the
country, the September 25 armed attacked the palace in Bogota when at midnight, after killing
the guards and managed to penetrate into the room del Libertador, fortunately could this save
throwing himself into the street from a window that lack of foresight on the part of the attackers
had run out of custody at all. A Once free, he could then his usual activity and energy to
take the necessary measures; and having been arrested the conspirators, all paid with their lives
for their reckless business unless the General Santander, also complicated
the plot and who the last sentence was commuted by Council of Government
in exile with deprivation of employment.

In this way, and the convocation of a Congress in Bogota for the January 2, 1830, the which would
come invested with the constitutional character, closed its doors in 1828, year full of discontent
with the excitement of the matches in which public opinion was divided
the country, the more formidable that stood in the heart of strong
men and seasoned to the vagaries of war.

Easy to understand is that in spite of such energetic measures would not have stopped the evil,
and so was in effect. He kept silent and slowly simmering in the minds of the discontented in
the year 1829, and become more deeply entrenched since the weight of power is not allowed to leave
to the surface, but as the appointed time for the installation of
Congress approaches, Bolivar published a manifesto in which authorized
people so that they could freely express its opinion, and through
the press, and by another one of those permitted by law.

At a reunion caused by the general chief of police, it was Arismendi, attended by several Notable
residents of Caracas in order to deal with requests that should be raised to Congress. Paez A circular
letter also encouraged them to voice their opinions with full openness and freedom. So we agreed to request
civil superior authority of the province should be convened the village at a general meeting,
pleading that was served, he immediately ordered the call. This Assembly, legally constituted
in the capital on November 26, resolved: "ignore the authority of the Liberator, Venezuela separate
Bogota government, will see of the former departments of that, by inviting them to a constituent body
recognize, defend them and publicly manifest that the separation of that government tried Venezuelans,
all of which are recorded. "Finally, they decided" that General Paez take charge of command
of the departments as it will verify the installation of new Congress.

"

No less agitation prevailed among the people of Granada. On January 2, 1830, made on commission
school several members of Congress of Colombia in Bogota, were beginning their work, and 4 agreed
on the desirability of making Bolivar person installs Congress to show people a good harmony
in which their representatives were the father of his country, calling him to combine the most
successful means of averting the calamities that threatened the country. Bolivar She went to the
appeal, and on November 20, five days after his arrival in Bogota, left installed Congress
formally renouncing to the presidency that he had conferred, but his resignation was rejected,
demanding that until the Constitution was enacted and appointed senior officials in political
order to clip the wings of anarchy retain its authority, the only
means Congress considered those skilled in threatening circumstances.

Indeed, the April 29 issue the Code remained political and appointed as President and Vice-President,
for the first charge Joaquin Mosquera and the second General Domingo
Caicedo, came to an end the dictatorship.

Twelve days after Congress closed sessions that Legislative Assembly, which was the season of
the collected on behalf and on behalf of Colombia.

The Liberator of South America, reduced to a mere condition of citizenship, 8 May went to Cartagena
in order to move to Europe, and the leave of the constituent wounded to the heart of his noble
heart of a patriot, not by separation of the high office that until there had been exercised, which
so many times as the present give up fair and dignity, nor hurt in
his ambition, since only retired "rich honors and glory; "utter these
remarkable words: I blush at the thought, but independently is the
only good that we won at the expense of everyone else.

In Venezuela, meanwhile, dated January 13, General Paez expedia two decrees, one which created for
the release of an interim government three Ministers of State whose duties were to carry on, War
and Navy, General Soublette; in Interior, Justice and Police, Dr. Miguel Pena, in Finance and
Foreign Affairs, the Graduate Diego Bautista Urbanski, and the other concerning the way in which
the elections should precede the Constituent Congress, which consist
of at least two-thirds, was to meet in Valencia on the 30th of April.

Installed this on May 8, his first act was a confirmation that the executive Paez was invested
until further resolution of Congress, whose tasks were completed on 22 September, sanctioning a
key code by declaring: "the government Venezuela is and always will be republican, popular, representative,
accountable and choice, " dividing the supreme authority in judicial, legislative and executive,
with a fourth power exclusively designed to understand at the municipal level. This was adopted
as a middle between centralism and federalism. The executive branch was headed by a judge with
the title of President of the Republic, and therefore this position as the Vice-President,
ceased after four years in office, not being re-elected, but after passing through at least
one constitutional term. Four ministers responsible would be elected by the President's exercise
of his ministry. The legislative branch would consist of a Congress popular, divided into two chambers,
one of Deputies and the Senate representatives, elected also for
only four years.

This was the final outcome I can see Bolivar, the man whose efforts were enough to win independence
for his country, and which were powerless to maintain integrity of Colombia. From now on, pursued
by the idea of ??inevitable ruin the nation at the cost of their blood and most of his fortune had
been dragged out of nothing mortally wounded in her tender and constant affection to their beloved
homeland, December 17, at one o'clock in the afternoon and the 47 years of age, expired on
the fifth of San Pedro, located within walking away from Santa Marta, directing the expression
of his ultimate sacrifice for the peoples of Colombia in these memorable
words: If my death contributes to cease and the parties union has
set in, I calm down the pit.

?

Could be required but the heroic liberator of South America? His remains lie in the Caracas
metropolitan Holy Church from the December 17, 1842, after having been just twelve years between the
Granada. ic strange! Gen. Jose Antonio Paez was President of the Republic of Venezuela when Congress
passed the Transfer of the precious ashes Father of the Nation.

FIN</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>