<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10032</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>193988</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18434</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

XII

Al día siguiente comía en casa de mi tía Medea con don Benito y mi tío Ramón. Hacíamos la crónica
del baile antes de sentarnos a comer, pero, al ocupar nuestros asientos, la conversación varió
de tema. Mi tía había tenido aquel día una furibunda reyerta en su Sociedad Filantrópica a
propósito de no sé qué bazar en que sus colegas se habían permitido prescindir absolutamente
de ella. Al oírnos hablar del baile, nos obligó a callar; dirigió dos o tres frases hirientes
a mi tío, por haberse permitido asistir al club y comenzó a contarnos su jornada. Parece que
aquello había sido un campo de Agramante: que la emoción de mi tía había sido puesta tres veces
a votación y que tres veces había sido rechazada. Furiosa, como ella sólo sabía ponerse cuando
le picaba la rabia, había salido de la Sociedad con la gorra toda torcida, bramando como una
leona, con la pollera arremangada, y a pie, con paso corto y rápido, había llegado a su casa
sin interrumpir la serie de colosales blasfemias con que se había despedido de sus odiadas
compañeras.

Mi tía se había sentado a la mesa sin apetito, excitada como nunca por el fuerte altercado
que acabo de narrar sin detalles.

Sus ojos, más congestionados que de costumbre, brillaban de una manera siniestra. Mi tío Ramón
había pasado de un buen humor apacible a un anonadamiento completo, fulminado bajo el fuego
de aquellas pupilas felinas.

La ancha cara de mi tía revelaba la reflección alarmante de sus venas ahogadas por las ondas
perezosas de una sangre espesa e inmóvil. Al sentarse a la mesa le habían asaltado mil incomodidades
desconocidas para ella: acaloramientos súbitos que le enrojecían momentáneamente sus carrillos
laxos, golpes de fuego a la vista, dolores punzantes a la nuca, relampagueos, obscurecimientos,
latidos, y qué sé yo qué vagos presentimientos de un ataque repentino cruzaban pinchándole
su imaginación y haciéndole exclamar de cuando en cuando con cierta desesperante agitación:

--¡Jesús, por Dios! ¿qué tengo yo?

Don Benito trataba de tranquilizarla; mi tío Ramón, sumiso siempre, la miraba guardando un
respetuoso silencio; la idea de una apoplegía le había cruzado la mente; pero, ya fuera por
temor, ya por moderación, se guardaba bien de aconsejar a su mujer la moderación, el reposo
y sobre todo, los purgantes que el desconocido doctor Brown le había instituido como tratamiento
hacía ya muchos años. Para él, la moderación del carácter feroz de su consorte era cuestión
de algunas libras de sal de Inglaterra, medicamento que, dada la fe que tenía en sus efectos,
le hubiera evitado mil disgustos, restableciendo por un instante la tranquilidad del hogar.

Momentos después del altercado, mi tía Medea se había visto atacada súbitamente de una abundante
evacuación de sangre por las narices; pero en el paroxismo de su cólera, temblando nerviosamente
de ira, se había contentado con sorber en abundancia y ruidosamente grandes cantidades de agua
salada, atarse fuertemente el brazo derecho o ponerse en los lujuriosos rodetes de su nuca
adiposa la llave consabida que aconseja la terapéutica popular.

De cuando en cuando se pasaba las manos por los ojos, en los cuales decía sentir un peso enorme;
se comprimía las sienes, donde latían con fuerza sus arterias o se mojaba con el agua del vaso
aquella frente pecosa y chata, bajo la cual ardía un volcán de odios y de futuros proyectos
de venganzas. Estaba irrascible, irritable, convulsa como una fiera herida; la silla tiritaba
bajo el peso de sus muslos pletóricos y su marido volvía a agitarse acariciando tímidamente
el recuerdo favorito del tratamiento del doctor Brown.

--No valen todas ellas el disgusto que me han dado, ¡perras viejas caches!--exclamaba con una
voz tosida y un poco gangosa.

Mi tío don Benito y yo continuábamos inmutables nuestro programa de abstención activa, callados
y reverentes, comiendo con esa moderación respetuosa que se confunde con el hambre modestamente
disfrazada de un apetito discreto. No se oía sino el rabioso crujir de las mandíbulas tiburonianas
de mi tía Medea, que con cierta complacencia maléfica, aunque llena de voluptuosidad, imaginaba
aplastar el cráneo de alguna de sus rivales en el inocente coscorrón de pan que roían sus molares
y el tímido y casi silencioso masticar de los que temíamos herir los oídos susceptibles de
la señora.

Don Benito procuraba, sin embargo, inútilmente, abrir temas de conversación, pero todo era
en vano, la tentativa no prendía. Mi tía Medea volvía a sus imprecaciones, lanzaba un reto
furibundo a sus rivales, las apostrofaba en mil formas y levantando el puño cerrado, les juraba
venganza como una pitonisa poseída por la cólera divina.

Terminábamos la comida e iban a servir el café. Mi tía tomó posiciones para levantarse; pero,
al ponerse de pie, sintió algo extraño, algo terrible pasar por su cabeza; quiso dar un paso
y cayó desplomada sobre el pavimento.

--¡Jesús te ampare!--exclamó mi tío Ramón, abriendo tamaños ojos al verla caer;--ya tenemos
encima la terrible perlesía; y corrió a socorrer a su consorte que había caído sin sentido
a los pies de la mesa, haciendo un ruido extraño con la boca llena de espuma.

Don Benito y yo habíamos corrido al mismo tiempo a socorrer a mi tía.

Su aspecto era verdaderamente aterrador; había caído fulminada por un violento golpe de sangre;
estaba sin conocimiento, insensible, relajada y en una inmovilidad absoluta.

Era una masa inerte, en la cual sólo la persistencia de la respiración y los latidos del corazón
que llegamos a percibir, atestiguaban que la vida aún no se había extinguido.

Mi tío pedía a gritos un médico, el vinagre y los sinapismos; y mientras éstos se aplicaban
abundantemente en las piernas ciclópeas de la señora, don Benito y yo corríamos en busca de
todos los médicos del barrio. Las señoras de la vecindad, algunas de las cuales eran de la
relación de la familia, concurrieron inmediatamente al conocer la desesperación de mi tío.

Todas ellas continuaron las aplicaciones de sinapismos en las pantorrillas, en la nuca, en
la planta de los pies, en los muslos y en los brazos; le desprendieron la ropa y la colocaron
en su cama.

Al bajar con don Benito la escalera para ir a buscar médico, nos chocamos con el pardo Alejandro
en la misma puerta de la calle.

--¿Qué hay, niño; qué sucede? toda la vecindad está alborotada... ¿se prende fuego la casa?...--nos
preguntó.

--Al contrario, creo que se apaga el fuego... tu patrona parece que acaba de reventar--contestó
don Benito con la más perfecta calma.

--¿Quién? ¿la tigra?... ¡al fin!...--replicó el pardo con el acento de un hombre que se desahoga.

Volvimos en seguida; habíamos recorrido dos o tres cuadras y sólo habíamos encontrado cinco
médicos que se prestaron con suma complacencia a nuestro llamamiento.

Mi tía seguía agravándose por momentos. Su respiración era estertorosa y penosísima; a cada
respiración, los carrillos, privados de resistencia, se dejaban destender pasivamente, después
volvían a quedar laxos y flojos.

--Fuma la pipa--dijo uno de los médicos en voz baja;--esto es muy característico.

Mi tío oyó la observación y creyó sin duda que el facultativo preguntaba si la señora tenía
la costumbre de fumar, pues respondió con grande asombro al ver el atrevimiento de aquel hombre:

--No, señor, no, ¿cómo se imagina usted que una señora de esta clase?... ni en pipa ni en nada--agregó
permitiéndose ciertos movimientos de una inopinada energía.

Los médicos sonrieron ligeramente y continuaron examinando a la enferma. Uno de ellos le introdujo
una pluma en la garganta. Mi tía, insensible, no dio señales de sentirla. El médico hizo un
gesto de desagrado.

--Es preciso mudarle la cama--agregó...

--¡Ah! sí--replicó mi tío haciendo una mueca forzada para disimular un profundo pesar;--¡pobrecita,
se conoce lo grave que está!

Otro de los médicos se acercó al oído de mi tío y le hizo una pregunta.

--¡Pfs!... hace muchos años, señor, desde soltero--dijo éste dejando errar por sus labios una
melancólica sonrisa--si nunca hemos tenido hijos, y usted sabe que... el doctor Brown me decía
que sin embargo era posible y que...

--¡Ah, sí!--concluyó el médico que sin duda se vio amagado por una historia patológica de la
familia de mi tío;--sí, el doctor Brown era un gran práctico.

En este momento se acercaban los otros colegas. Habían terminado su examen e iban a celebrar
consulta. Poco tendrían que decir de la enferma; tal era su estado de gravedad. Según opinión
unánime, era una hemorragia cerebral en su más terrible forma. La respiración continuaba siempre
laboriosa, las pupilas dilatadísimas e insensibles a la acción de la luz, y los líquidos que
apenas tomaba, se quedaban en la garganta produciendo esos estertores penosos que impresionan
tanto. Este último síntoma era de augurio fatal. Mi tío estaba consternado: su mujer iba desapareciendo
lentamente sin hacer mención de reconocerlo cuando se acercaba a su lecho.

--¿Tiene mucha fiebre?--se atrevió a preguntar a uno de los médicos que salió el primero de
la consulta.

--No, señor, no, al contrario, su temperatura es más bien muy baja. Sin embargo, es probable
que ahora comience a subir mucho, si, como desgraciadamente lo tememos, esto termina mal. Está
en un coma profundo--agregó, queriendo confundir a mi tío con un tecnicismo confuso:--es una
hemorragia cerebral de forma apoplética paralítica.

--¡Jesús me ampare y me favorezca! ¡cuatro enfermedades a la vez! ¡Quién resiste a tanto!

Y el pobre hombre, haciendo un esfuerzo supremo para manifestar la más suprema emoción, se
llevaba la mano a los ojos y se tiraba nerviosamente del pelo.

Don Benito, que estaba al lado del lecho, miraba extinguirse aquel coloso con una frialdad
perfecta.

Mi tío no se atrevía a acercarse al borde de la cama: los médicos se habían separado, seguros
ya del desenlace.

--Acérquese, señor--dijo a mi tío uno de ellos...

Mi tío se acercó temblando, remiso y casi arrastrado por el deber... al aproximarse retrocedió:
la moribunda presentaba un aspecto terrible: la fisonomía estaba amoratada; la respiración
era difícil y cavernosa.

--¡El sacerdote!--exclamaron algunos de los circunstantes mientras los médicos abandonaban
la habitación.

Se acercó al lecho un fraile obeso, vestido de colores llamativos, impasible como una foca,
gordo como un cerdo: el rostro achatado por el estigma de la gula y de los apetitos carnales,
la boca gruesa como la de un sátiro, el ojo estúpido, la oreja de murciélago, los pómulos colorados
como los de un clown. Abrió entre sus manos grasas y carnudas un libro cuyas páginas alumbraba
un monigote con un cirio, y eruptó sobre el cadáver en latín bárbaro y gangoso algunos rezos
con la pasmosa inconsciencia de un loro.

Al terminar, se retiró algunos pasos del lecho; hizo un ademán a mi tío para que se acercara;
y en aquel momento mismo, mi tía Medea clavó sus ojos inmóviles en su marido, abrió la boca,
esputó un cuajarón de sangre y acabó...

Mientras comenzaban las mujeres a hacer los preparativos para vestirla, don Benito y yo sacamos
a mi tío de la habitación. Era de observarse en aquel momento la cara de mi viejo camarada;--la
cómica solemnidad que se esforzaba por mantener le daba un aire mefistofélico.

Mi tío lo miraba sin comprenderlo, pero era bastante suspicaz para explicarse que don Benito
no estaba tan desolado como lo exigían las circunstancias.

Yo estaba esperando la palabra burlona del viejo solterón y no se hizo esperar. Nos encerramos
en el cuarto de mi tío, aseguramos las puertas y don Benito, con una cara de pascuas, abriendo
los brazos exclamó:

--Don Ramón... ¡apriete, amigo!--y buscó a mi tío para abrazarlo.

--¡Oh! don Benito... ¡qué desgracia!

--¿Desgracia? ¿Me representa usted el hipócrita? Celebre usted, amigo, el más grande de los
aniversarios de su vida...

Y mi tío no pudo contenerse; se deshizo de don Benito y corriendo a la cama, se echó en ella
y depositó sobre la blanda almohada de plumas en que hundió el rostro, una sonrisa de íntima,
de voluptuosa alegría, que ya no podía contener dentro de sí mismo.

En ese instante golpearon la puerta; la abrí; el perfil risueño de Alejandro asomaba por la
rendija.

--¿Qué quieres?--le dije en voz baja y con el tono más serio del mundo.

--¡Oh!--me contestó muy despacio...--¿usted es de los tristes también?--y aquel negro ponía
una cara satánica cuando me decía esas palabras.

--Vete--le dije...--vete.

--Sí, me voy... ¡a buscar el cajón!

A las doce de la noche, mi tía estaba depositada en el ataúd de jacarandá que Alejandro había
traído. Le habían cerrado los ojos y la boca, pero su rostro conservaba siempre el gesto de
amenaza que le era característico, y con el Santo Cristo, que oprimía maquinalmente entre las
manos lívidas y como enceradas parecía en la actitud de un centinela que dormita armado para
el caso de una sorpresa. El mulaterío femenino de la casa y de la vecindad, había invadido
la sala: no faltaban alrededor del féretro dos o tres mulatillas arrodilladas que se turnaban
sucesivamente. Claro es que la sala había sido cubierta en un instante de crespón y de merino
negros en homenaje a su ilustre dueña.

La noticia de su muerte había cundido por la ciudad, y como su influjo en los grandes centros
sociales, a pesar de los desastres políticos del partido de la finada, era de vieja data, la
casa se vio llena toda la noche de las eminencias del pasado, destronadas por el presente.

El primero con quien me encontré en la sala, fue con el doctor Trevexo. ¡Cómo había envejecido
y enflaquecido! Sus piernas y sus brazos desgonzados, no se palpaban al través de la ropa,
pero siempre era el mismo; el gran charlador, difuso y narrador de insulseces; gran expositor
de lugares comunes, de doctrinas tomadas al instinto, de principios incompletos; siempre enemigo
de los libros; desolado por el prodigioso aumento de las librerías y de las ediciones: furioso
contra la exagerada difusión de las obras científicas; partidario constante, invariable, inconmovible
del periodismo: siempre citando su colección del Gorro de la Libertad y de La Espada de Damocles,
los diarios que había escrito después de la caída de Rozas.

¡Pobre doctor Trevexo! ¡Cómo aquel hombre que había sido el primero veinte años antes, era
hoy el último! ¡Cómo se había detenido en su apogeo sin marchar! Me hacía el efecto de una
de esas fotografías antiguas de un álbum de familia, ante las que uno tiene que reír involuntariamente.
Mientras que el mundo político había progresado entre nosotros, con lecturas serias y sazonadas:
en el siglo de Disraeli y de Gladstone, de Bismark y Gambetta, en el siglo de Taine y Lanfrey,
el doctor Trevexo vivía con sus recortes de diarios criollos, con toda su fama del pasado por
capital y toda su estéril informalidad por presente y porvenir. ¡Sin embargo, lo que es la
virtud y la consecuencia de los partidarios! Su partido creía en él todavía: era siempre el
gran orador, el gran diplomático, el gran periodista, el gran abogado, del más grande de los
partidos argentinos.

La muerte de mi tía Medea lo había consternado. Su grande amiga, la mujer resuelta de todas
las épocas; vencida en dos revoluciones, pronta a hacer una nueva a una sola indicación suya,
había muerto; el partido entero la lloraba, era una pérdida irreparable, tan irreparable, que
el más grande de los diarios de la América del Sur, le dedicó un sentido artículo necrológico,
largo como un sermón de agonía, con muchas frases escogidas, que comenzaba recordando con mucho
detalle a las antiguas madres griegas y romanas, las hacía atravesar la trayectoria de la historia
en las múltiples combinaciones de los pueblos, y terminaba con un elogio de las virtudes de
la difunta y una laudatoria especial a la mansedumbre de su carácter.

A este llamamiento, todo el faubourg Saint Germain de Buenos Aires, se presentó al día siguiente.
¡Cómo se elogiaban los méritos de la señora doña Medea Berrotarán! ¡Cómo se condolían de la
triste situación de mi tío! ¡qué dolorosa pérdida había experimentado! ¡Hasta don Buenaventura
había dejado sus múltiples ocupaciones literarias para asistir al entierro! ¡Cómo no premiar
treinta años de vasallaje, mudo, entusiasta, admirador de todas sus hazañas y desgracias!

Un entierro de fuste en Buenos Aires no necesita describirse: el empresario fúnebre conoce
los gustos de la gran capital, en los que prepondera la gran aldea: el convoy tiene que hacer
corso en la calle de la Florida: no hay otra calle para ir a la Recoleta, y si a alguien se
le ocurriera la idea de cambiar el itinerario, no sería difícil que el muerto o la muerta,
siendo de la aristocracia, o sobre todo de la gran política, resucitara protestando contra
la variación de la ruta.

Mi tía había sido muy religiosa; aunque víctima en los últimos tiempos de un padre escolapio,
que le había eliminado graciosamente algunos miles de pesos, su fervor por los frailes y monigotes
corría parejas con sus entusiasmos políticos: de modo que a su entierro asistían todos los
clérigos de las parroquias principales, correctos la mayor parte, y una delegación de cada
cofradía: franciscanos, dominicos, etc., incorrectos bajo el punto de vista de la higiene personal.
Entre esta turba de cuervos negros y pardos, no faltaba algún tribuno ultramontano, pedante
atorado de suficiencia, orador sibilino y hueco, gran momia literaria, rellena de Blair y Hermosilla,
specimen del gongorismo español, que, sentado en el carruaje de duelo, como si lo hubiesen
clavado en una estaca, mantenía su gravedad solemne como para aparentar la profunda desolación
que le causaba la muerte de aquella vieja cuyas virtudes corrían al fin parejas con la sinceridad
de sus convicciones religiosas. Encabezando el grupo, iba la misma dignidad que ya hemos visto
al lado del lecho mortuorio, con su uniforme carnavalesco de colorinches y su impasible cara
de foca.

Mientras depositaban el cajón en la bóveda de la familia, yo me perdí en las calles del cementerio.

¡Cuánta vana pompa!

Cómo podía medirse allí, junto con los mamarrachos de la marmolería criolla, la imbecilidad
y la soberbia humanas. Allí la tumba pomposa de un estanciero... muchas leguas de campo, muchas
vacas; los cueros y las lanas han levantado ese mausoleo que no es ni el de Moreno, ni el de
García, ni el de los guerreros, ni el de los grandes hombres de letras.

Allí la regia sepultura de un avaro, más allá la de un imbécil... la pompa siguiéndolos en
la muerte. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10983</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>31038</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16381</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

XII

The next day I ate at my Aunt Medea with Don Benito and Uncle
Ramon.

Did the chronicle dance before sitting down to eat, but by occupying our seats, the conversation
ranged the subject. My aunt had had a furious quarrel that day in the Philanthropic Society I
do not know what purpose bazaar that his colleagues had allowed to dispense entirely it. To
hear us talk about the dance, we were forced to keep quiet, he directed two or three sentences
hurtful my uncle, having been allowed to attend the club and began to tell their journey. It
seems that this had been a field of Agramante: the emotion of my aunt had been made three times
a vote and three times he had been rejected. Furious, as she knew only be when stung his rage,
had left the company with his hat all bent, roaring like a lioness, with her skirt tucked up,
and on foot, with short, quick step, he had arrived home without interrupting the colossal series
of curses that had been fired from his hated mates.

My aunt was sitting at the table without appetite, excited as ever
because of the altercation I just tell without details.

His eyes, more congested than usual, shone in a sinister way. My Uncle Ramon went from a peaceful
mood to a complete annihilation, struck under fire those feline eyes.

The broad face of my aunt revealed the startling reflection of your veins drowned by waves a
thick blood lazy and motionless. When sitting at the table he had assaulted a thousand discomforts unknown
to her: hot flashes momentarily that his cheeks reddened lax fire blows to the eye, stabbing pains
in the neck, lightning, obscuration, beats and whatnot vague forebodings of a sudden attack crossed
prick your imagination and making it cry out from time to time with some desperate agitation:

-
Jesus God! What do I have?

Don Benito was calm, my uncle Ramon, submissive always looked at saving a respectful silence,
the idea of ??a stroke he had crossed the mind, but, either by fear, and for restraint, kept
well to advise his wife moderation, rest and above all, the laxative that the doctor known
as Brown had established treatment many years ago. For him, the moderation of the fierce nature
of his consort was concerned a few pounds of salt from England, a drug that, given his faith
in its effects, would have saved a thousand disappointments, reestablishing a glimpse of the
tranquility of home.

Moments after the altercation, Aunt Medea had been attacked suddenly abundant evacuation of blood
from the nose, but in a paroxysm of his anger, trembling nervously of anger, had been content
with loud sucking in abundance and lots of water salt right arm tightly tied or put in the
back of his head impellers lustful proverbial fat key therapeutic
counseling popular.

From time to time he ran his hands through my eyes, in which he said felt an enormous weight;
was compressed temples, where pounding your arteries or wet with water glass that freckled face
and flat, under which burned a volcano of hatred and future projects of revenge. Was irrascible,
irritable, whooping like a wounded beast, the chair shivering under
the weight of her thighs and her husband plethoric shaken again timidly
caressing the treatment favorite memory of Dr. Brown.

- Not worth
all the annoyance they have given me, old caches bitches! - Exclaimed
with a voice coughed and a little shrill.

My uncle Don Benito and I we continued our program of abstention immutable force, silent and reverent,
respectful eating with that moderation which is confused with hunger modestly disguised as an appetite
discreet. There was no sound but the rustling rabid jaws tiburonianas My Aunt Medea, with some evil
pleasure, yet full of delight, he imagined crush the skull of one of its rivals in the bread coscorron
innocent gnawing their molars and shy and almost silent chewing of those feared likely to hurt the
ears Mrs.

Don Benito tried, however vainly, to open topics of conversation, but it was in vain, the attempt
would not start. My Aunt Medea returned to his imprecations, threw a challenge furious rivals,
the apostrophe in a thousand ways and raising a clenched fist, I swear revenge as a witch possessed
by divine wrath.

We finished lunch and went to serve the coffee. My aunt took up positions, but when standing
up, he felt something strange, something terrible going through your
head, wanted to step and sank down on the pavement.

- Jesus will
protect him! - Uncle Ramon said, opening his eyes wide to see it fall,
- and we over the terrible palsy, and ran to help his consort who
had fallen senseless at the foot of the table, making a strange noise
with his mouth full of foam.

Don Benito and I had run at the same time to assist my aunt.

His appearance was truly frightening; had fallen struck by a violent rush of blood; was unconscious,
unresponsive, relaxed and completely immobilizes.

It was an inert mass, in which only the persistence of breathing and
heartbeat that we perceive, testified that life was not extinct yet.

My uncle cried out for a doctor, vinegar and mustard plasters, and while they are applied abundantly
in Cyclopean legs of the lady, Don Benito and I ran for all doctors
in the neighborhood.

The ladies of the neighborhood, some of which were from the family relationship, immediately
attended to learn of the despair of my uncle.

All of them continued poultices applications in the calves, in the neck, in the soles of the feet,
thighs and arms, cut off his clothes and placed in his bed.

Going down the stairs with Don Benito to fetch a doctor, we collided with Alexander Brown in the
same front door.

- What is it, child, what happens? the whole neighborhood is abuzz ... "The house is on fire
?...-- us he asked.

- On the contrary, I think it puts out the fire ... Your employer appears to have just burst -
answered Don Benito with the most perfect calm.

- Who?

"The tiger? ... !...-- Finally said the brown with the accent of
a man who vents.

We returned at once, we had gone two or three blocks and we only found five physicians who were provided
with great satisfaction to our appeal.

My aunt was getting worse by the minute. His breath was rattling and excruciating, to each breathing,
cheeks, deprived of strength, were left unmade passively after returned
to become lax and lazy.

- Smoke the pipe - one of the doctors said
in a low voice - this is very characteristic.

My uncle heard the remark and he imagined the doctor wondered if the
lady had the habit of smoking, it responded with great astonishment
at the audacity of the man:

- No, sir, how do you imagine a woman
of this class?

... or a pipe or anything - added allowing certain movements of unexpected
energy.

The doctors smiled slightly and continued to examine the sick.

One of them introduced a feather in the throat. My aunt, insensitive, showed no signs of feeling.
The doctor made an distaste.

- You must mudarle bed - added ...

- Ah! yes - my uncle said with a grimace forced to hide a deep sorrow, - poor thing known how
serious it is!

Another of the doctors came to the ears of my uncle and asked him
a question.

- Pfs!

... For many years, sir, from singles - said it left his lips wander melancholy smile - if
we have never had children, and you know that ... Dr. Brown told
me yet it was possible and that ...

- Ah, yes - the doctor concluded
that certainly was a history amagado pathological my uncle's family,
- yes, Dr. Brown was a great practical.

At this time they approached the other peers. Had completed its review and were to hold query.
Have little to say about the sick, such was his serious condition.

According to opinion unanimously, it was a cerebral hemorrhage in
its most terrible form.

Always continued breathing laborious, the pupils very extensive and insensitive to the action
of light, and liquids just drank, stayed in the throat causing painful
throes those that impress both.

This last symptom was fatal omen. My uncle was shocked: his wife was dying slowly with no
mention of recognizing when he approached his bed.

- Do you have
a high fever? - Dared to ask one of the doctors who came out first
the query.

- No, sir, no, on the contrary, its temperature is rather
low.

However, it is probable now begin to rise much, if, as unfortunately we fear, it ends badly.
Is in a coma - he said, trying to confuse my uncle with a confusing
technicality - is a so apoplectic cerebral hemorrhage paralyzed.

-
Jesus help me and encourages me!

Four diseases at once! Who refuses to so much!

And the poor man, making a supreme effort to express the most supreme emotion, his hand to
his eyes and pulling hair nervously.

Don Benito, who was next to the bed, looked extinguished with a coldness that colossus perfect.

My
uncle did not dare approach the edge of the bed, the doctors had separate insurance and the outcome.

-
Come, sir - my uncle said one of them ...

My uncle came trembling, and almost dragged reluctant to duty ... the approach back: the dying
had a terrible aspect: the face was bruised, the breathing was difficult
and cavernous.

- The priest! - Some of the bystanders shouted as
doctors leaving the room.

He went to bed a fat monk, dressed in bright colors, impassive as
a seal, fat as a pig, his face flattened by the stigma of gluttony
and carnal desires, thick mouth like a satyr, stupid eye, ear of bat,
red cheeks like a clown.

Opened between fat and fleshy hands a book whose pages illuminated a puppet with a candle, and
erupted on the body in barbarous Latin and some prayers nasal with the staggering irresponsibility
of a parrot.

After he retired a few steps from bed, made a gesture to my uncle
to come over; and at that moment, my Aunt Medea still glared at her
husband, opened his mouth, sputum a blood clot and over ...

As women
began to make preparations to dress, and I took Don Benito my uncle
in the room.

Was observed at the time the face of my old comrade, - the comic solemnity that strove to maintain
an air gave Mephistopheles.

My uncle looked at him without understanding it, but it was suspicious
enough to explain that Don Benito was not as desolate as the occasion
demanded it.

I was expecting the word mocking the old bachelor was immediate.

We enclose in my uncle's room, locked the doors and Don Benito, with a side of Easter, opening
arms cried:

- Don Ramon ... Press, man! - And sought to hug my uncle.

- Oh! Don Benito ... Misery!

- Misfortune? Do I represent you the hypocrite?

Celebrate you, friend, the largest anniversaries of his life ...

And
my uncle could not contain himself; got rid of Don Benito and running
to the bed, got into it and deposited on the soft feather pillow that
buried his face, a smile of deep, voluptuous joy, he could no longer
contain within itself.

At that moment knocked on the door, opened it, the profile of Alexander smiling leaning out
of the slit.

- What? - I said quietly and with more serious in the world.

- Oh! - He answered very slowly ...--¿ you the sad, too? - And put that black a satanic face when
I said those words.

- Go - go ...-- said.

- Yes, I'm ... To search the drawer!

At twelve o'clock, my aunt was placed in the coffin of rosewood that Alexander had brought. He
had closed his eyes and mouth, but always kept his face gesture threat that was characteristic,
and the Holy Christ, that squeezed mechanically between waxed livid hands and seemed like the
attitude of an armed sentry to doze the case of a surprise. The female mulaterío house and neighborhood,
had invaded the room: there were plenty around the coffin two or three who took turns kneeling mulatto
on.

Clear is that the room had been covered in an instant and merino crepe black in honor of its
illustrious owner.

The news of his death had spread through the city, and as their influence in large social, despite
the political disasters of the deceased party, was of long standing, the house was full the night
of the eminences of the past, dethroned by this.

The first whom I met in the room, was with Dr. Trevexo. I had aged and emaciated! His legs and
arms unhinged, not palpable to through clothing, but always the same, the great chatter, diffuse
and insulseces narrator, great display platitudes, doctrines taken
to instinct, principles incomplete, always an enemy books; devastated
by the phenomenal growth of libraries and issues: furious against
excessive diffusion of scientific works, consistent supporter, unchanged,
unmoved of journalism: always quoting his collection of liberty cap
and The Sword of Damocles the papers he wrote after the fall of Rosas.

Poor doctor Trevexo! How the man who had been the first twenty years earlier, was Today the last!
How was arrested at his peak no go! I had the effect of a of those old photographs from a family
album, to which one has to laugh involuntarily. While the political world had progressed between
us, and seasoned with serious reading: in the Age of Disraeli and Gladstone, Bismarck and Gambetta,
in the age of Taine and Lanfrey, Dr. Trevexo lived with his Creole newspaper clippings, with
all his fame of the past capital and all its sterile informality
present and future.

However, what is the virtue and consequence of supporters! His party still believed in him: he was
always great orator, the great diplomat, the great journalist, the great lawyer, the largest
Argentine parties.

My aunt's death had shocked Medea.

His great friend, she resolved all times, losing in two revolutions, ready to make a new one
to his suggestion, was dead the whole game the crying, it was an irreparable loss so irreparable
that the largest newspapers in South America, gave him a sense obituary, long as a sermon in
agony, with many choice phrases, which began recalling with much detail to the ancient Greek
and Roman mothers, made them cross the path of history in multiple combinations of people,
and ended with a eulogy of the virtues of the deceased and a special
congratulatory gentleness of his character.

In this appeal, all the Faubourg Saint Germain de Buenos Aires, was presented the next day.
How is praising the merits of Ms. Dona Medea Berriedale! I sympathized with the sad story
of my uncle! Which had experienced painful loss! Even Don Buenaventura had left their busy schedules
to attend the funeral of literature! Do not reward thirty years of bondage, mute, enthusiast,
admirer of all his exploits and misfortunes!

A burial shaft in Buenos Aires need not be described: the employer knows funeral tastes of the
big city, in which prevails the large village, the convoy has to do Street parade in Florida: there
is no street to go to the Recoleta, and if anyone get the idea to change the itinerary, it would
be difficult for the dead or dead being of the aristocracy, or especially of high politics,
protesting resurrected the variation of the route.

My aunt had been very religious, although recently the victim of a parent Piarist who had graciously
removed several thousand dollars, his fervor for the friars and puppets partners ran their political
enthusiasms: so that at his funeral attended all main parish clergy, most correct, and one delegation
from each Guild: Franciscans, Dominicans, etc., incorrect under the
terms of personal hygiene.

Among this crowd of black ravens and browns, not missing a tribune ultramontane pedantic adequacy
stuck, he sibilant and hollow, great literary mummy, filled with
Blair and Herman, Gongorism specimen of Spanish, who sat in the carriage
of mourning, as if they had nailed to a stake, he maintained his solemn
seriousness to it with the utter desolation that caused the death
of that old whose virtues were at the end couples with sincerity of
their religious beliefs. Leading the group was the same dignity as
we have seen beside the bier, with its carnival uniform and his imperturbable
face colorinches seal.

While the box deposited in the vault of the
family, I got lost on the streets of the cemetery.

Vain much pomp!

How
could there be measured, along with daubs of native marble works,
imbecility and human pride. There pompous tomb of a rancher ... many
miles of land, many cattle, hides and wool have been raised that mausoleum
which is neither that of Moreno, nor the Garcia, nor warriors, nor
of the great men of letters.

There the royal tomb of a miser, beyond
that of an idiot ... pump following them in death</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>