<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05554</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>105471</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22248</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Todos los críticos y biógrafos de Velázquez están conformes en considerar este retrato como
obra de mérito excepcional: unos alaban de ella lo que se refiere al modo de concebirla, imprimiendo
al bruto tanta vida y al jinete tanta gallardía; otros elogian el dibujo, donde, al través
de arrepentimientos y correcciones que aún se notan, hay una precisión admirable; otros, finalmente,
la soltura de la ejecución, en la cual ya ha desaparecido por completo aquella pasada dureza
de los primeros cuadros. Por mi parte me limitaré a recordar que a pocos pasos de este retrato
esta en nuestro Museo del Prado el ecuestre de Carlos I, por Ticiano, y que la comparación
resulta favorable al primero, pues al gran maestro veneciano se le allanaron muchas dificultades,
teniendo por modelo una figura con visos de heroica; y el español hubo de infundir al suyo,
sin faltar a la verdad, una grandeza y poesía que en absoluto le faltaban.

Cuentan las historias y relaciones que, de doce mujeres, entre esposas y amigas, tuvo Felipe
IV treinta y dos hijos, incluyendo legítimos y bastardos[43]; pero ninguno le alegraría tanto
como el príncipe Don Baltasar Carlos, habido, después de tres hijas muertas sin cumplir un
año, en su primera mujer y prima la infanta de Francia doña Isabel de Borbón, a quien llama
un escritor de la época fragante flor de lis convertida en purpúrea rosa castellana.

Nació aquel niño el año de 1629, durante la permanencia de Velázquez en Italia, que le retrató
varias veces, y se supone que la primera en un lienzo que hoy se conserva en Castle-Howard.
Tiene allí el Príncipe dos años y esta representado en pie sobre un peldaño en segundo término:
ante él se ve un paje enano. En su mirada brilla la mirada viva característica de sus imágenes
ulteriores, y en su postura, impropia de un niño, puede descubrirse la intención del pintor
de hacer que resalte el rango del modelo: apoya la mano izquierda en la empuñadura de la espada
y la diestra en el bastón de mando. Cruza su rico traje de terciopelo obscuro con pasamanería
de oro una banda roja: al fondo hay un cortinaje rojo, y sobre un almohadón se ve el sombrero
de terciopelo con plumas blancas. El enano, situado un peldaño más abajo que su amo, vuelve
hacia éste la enorme cabeza: lleva amplia valona lisa y cadena al cuello; un delantal le cubre
la parte inferior del cuerpo. En la mano derecha tiene un chupador de plata, y en la izquierda
una manzana[44]. Beruete, de quien tomamos estos datos, dice que, durante algún tiempo, se
atribuyó el cuadro al Corregio, suponiendo que el retratado era un príncipe de Parma; pero
hoy dos ilustres críticos, Justi y Armstrong, el segundo con ciertas reservas, reconocen en
él la mano de Velázquez.

En Madrid esta el Príncipe retratado dos veces, ambas de tamaño natural, a pie y a caballo.
Don Pedro de Madrazo ha descrito estos dos cuadros con una claridad y precisión que no hay
más que pedir: al hablar de uno enumera fielmente las prendas de ropa, desde la gorrilla de
ala y la valona de encaje, hasta el tabardo de mangas bobas y los zapatos de paño; al referirse
a otro, desde el chambergo con plumas y la banda encarnada de cabos de oro hasta las botas
atezadas; ni se olvida en el primero de los dos perros, perdiguero y galgo, ni deja en el segundo
de dar idea de la jaca andaluza de color castaño sencillamente enjaezada: menciona, por último,
los fondos de campo madrileño con sus quebradoras en el piso y sus celajes azulados de nubes
blanquecinas; pero lo que no es dado expresar, ni aun con pluma tan experta, es el atractivo
que la figura del Príncipe, alegre, juguetona y al mismo tiempo regia, tiene en estos lienzos.

En ellos cautiva la augusta personilla por cierto aspecto inocente y travieso, cándido y malicioso
que le imprime una gracia superior a toda ponderación: para aumentar el encanto parece, además,
que existe indudable relación entre su edad y el riente paisaje que le rodea. Ambos cuadros
son de color fresco y jugoso; y en lo que toca a la ejecución de lo más feliz que puede citarse
de la segunda manera del autor.

En el Museo Imperial de Viena hay otro lienzo que representa al mismo Príncipe pasados tres
o cuatro años con traje de terciopelo negro bordado de plata, y ferreruelo: esta junto a una
mesa cubierta de tapete rojo, donde tiene el sombrero, y la figura destaca sobre fondo gris.
«Esta obra--dice Beruete--es en conjunto maravillosa, pero lo más admirable de ella es el prodigioso
modelado del rostro pálido, iluminado de frente, y la expresión de la fisonomía, donde se lee
el carácter de aquel niño universalmente querido, cuya prematura muerte ejerció funesto influjo
en el destino de España.»

Además de los dos mencionados retratos ecuestres, el del Rey y el del Príncipe Baltasar Carlos,
hay en el Museo del Prado otros tres de personas reales y a caballo atribuidos a Velázquez,
pero que hace tiempo se juzgan no hechos en totalidad de su mano. Son los de Don Felipe III
y doña Margarita, su esposa, padres de Felipe IV, y el de la primera mujer de éste, doña Isabel
de Borbón, a quien tuvo pocas veces por modelo Velázquez, acaso por ser éste protegido del
Conde-Duque y ella su enemiga[45]. Artistas y críticos opinan que en esos tres grandes lienzos,
que claramente muestran añadiduras laterales hechas para darles mayores proporciones, el maestro
trabajó sobre retratos anteriores hechos por Bartolomé Gonzalez o Nicolás de Villacis, no como
supone Stirling, de Carreño, que debía entonces de ser muy niño. Mirando atentamente estas
obras se conoce que lo que allí hizo el pincel de Velázquez fue dar valor y realce con enmiendas,
correcciones y toques aislados a la mezquina y pesada labor de artistas inhábiles. Los repintes
se ven aún: el retrato de Felipe III tiene el caballo casi todo rehecho; en el de doña Margarita
esta variado el fondo, convirtiendo el primitivo, que era un jardín con recuadros de boj, en
campo de matas y arbustos; en el de doña Isabel de Borbón también se nota la modificación del
caballo, y en la cabeza de la Reina hay notables variantes. Parece, pues, lo verosímil que
los tres retratos estuvieran pintados cuando hizo Velázquez el de Felipe IV, y que, para hermanarlos
con éste, los retocara ligera y bravamente, dándoles, en particular al de Felipe III, un aspecto
grandioso que no tenían: con lo cual, las que hoy serían obras poco interesantes, lo son muchísimo,
pues en ellas se ve cómo el genio, con poco esfuerzo, convierte en superior lo que, a duras
penas, era mediano.

Retrató, también en traje de caza como al Rey y al Príncipe, al Infante Don Fernando. Acerca
de cuando lo hizo discrepan las opiniones: dicen unos que antes de ir a Italia, lo cual desmiente
el estilo; otros, que hacia el año 1647, cuando ya el personaje era muerto, aprovechando para
el rostro el estudio de una imagen anterior. La figura esta admirablemente colocada y a su
lado tiene un podenco que es de los mejores trozos de pintura que hizo Velázquez. Así como
se dice de las personas bien retratadas que están hablando, pudiera decirse de este can, que
no ladra porque no quiere.

Detalles que, aislados, no representan gran cosa, y juntos dan a entender mucho, atestiguaran
luego que, además de soberano artista, debió de ser Velázquez hombre de bondadoso natural;
por lo menos fue agradecido: yo no vacilo en asegurar que la prueba es el retrato que hizo
al Conde-Duque. La vanidad de éste, que vería en ello un medio seguro de legar su imagen a
la posteridad, le haría desearlo: su rango lo justificaba; pero Velázquez puso en la obra tal
empeño de acercarse a la perfección, que en su género no se concibe mejor.

Fue el privado de Felipe IV tan mal administrador de las rentas del Erario como celoso de las
propias, las cuales llegaron a 450.000 ducados al año; tan vengativo, que mandó poner a Quevedo
grillos de a nueve libras, y estando celebrándose los funerales del ilustre Duque de Fernandina
ordenó que de las manos del difunto se quitase el bastón de general; tan funesto político que
ocasionó la rebeldía de Cataluña y la pérdida de Portugal, el Brasil y el Rosellón; acérrimo
partidario de leyes suntuarias, aunque inventor de las golillas; al mismo tiempo creador del
papel sellado y ordenador de cacerías donde entraban al puesto del Rey veinte jabalíes en una
tarde: la afición que mostró a las letras y las artes amengua en algo lo aborrecible de su
tiranía; pero ni fue militar, ni ganó batallas, ni siquiera salió a campaña. Sin embargo, tal
como le representó Velázquez parece el rayo de la guerra.

En Julio de 1638 Condé puso sitio a Fuenterrabía embistiéndola por mar bajo sus órdenes el
arzobispo de Burdeos: defendiose bravamente la plaza más con tan poca gente, que no podía ser
larga la resistencia ni evitable la entrada. Entonces el Conde-Duque reunió un pequeño ejército
de cerca de doce mil hombres y con ellos el Almirante de Castilla desbarató a los franceses
con tan furiosa acometida que Condé se entró huyendo en el agua hasta ganar una chalupa y el
belicoso arzobispo se acogió a los bajeles quedando libre la plaza; traduciéndose el regocijo
experimentado por el Rey no tanto en premiar pronto al Almirante cuanto en recompensar con
largueza al Conde-Duque.

Esta fue la ocasión que Velázquez, si lisonjero agradecido, aprovechó para retratarle en campo
de batalla de cuerpo entero y tamaño natural, ordenando un combate fantástico a caballo, con
coraza de labores de oro, chambergo de grandes plumas, bastón de mando y aspecto de caudillo
seguro y digno de la victoria. Esta el bruto, que es alazan roano, en corveta afianzado sobre
las patas, las manos en alto y tan bien encajada sobre él la airosa figura del jinete que no
se conciben más viveza en la bestia ni en el hombre más dominio. Nadie diría que aquél es el
ministro cortesano en cuyos días murió en Rocroy el prestigio de la infantería española, sino
un héroe de los que la guiaron en Muhlberg o Nordinga: sin duda el artista pecando de palaciego,
pues no se respira en vano la atmósfera viciada, incurrió aquí en la flaqueza de adular al
privado: mas el mal efecto que esto causa instantáneamente se disipa al considerar que Olivares
fue su protector, y que aquella inocente mentira era la única prueba de gratitud que podía
darle. Nada hizo Velázquez con cuidado tan exquisito: ninguno de sus cuadros denota tan tenaz
empeño de acierto: allí puso lo mejor de su entendimiento y de sus manos como había puesto
el sentimiento más noble de su alma. El color es de frescura y riqueza incomparables: la ejecución,
minuciosa por lo esmerada y grandiosa por el resultado, esta en armonía con la índole de la
figura donde todo revela fuerza, decisión y brío[46].

Es lógico pensar que las obligaciones anejas a los cargos que Velázquez desempeñaba en la servidumbre
de Palacio no le dejarían mucho tiempo para aceptar encargos de particulares, suponiendo que
el Rey se lo tolerase: pero era natural que por conveniencia o amistad hiciera otros retratos:
de éstos se conservan varios, siendo los principales los siguientes.

El busto de un personaje desconocido que en Apsley House posee el duque de Wellington. El del
letrado Don Diego del Corral, de cuerpo entero y tamaño natural, vestido con ropón, junto a
una mesa y papeles en las manos. Debió de pintarlo hacia 1632, y es propiedad de la duquesa
de Villahermosa.

El de Pablillos de Valladolid (núm. 1.092 del Museo del Prado). Decíase hasta hace pocos años
que era éste un representante de comedias de los que a docenas trabajan en los corrales de
Madrid y aun en el Alcázar Viejo: y por esta razón se le llamó El Cómico. Madrazo halló más
tarde que en los Archivos reales, había un cuadro inventariado como retrato de un bufón con
golilla que se llamó Pablillos de Valladolid, cuyas medidas casi coincidían con las del Cómico;
y creyó, siendo su opinión aceptada, que no era el tal representante, sino bufón u hombre de
placer. Yo, con todo el respeto debido a tan insigne crítico, no acabo de persuadirme. Cierto
que no hay en libros ni papeles antiguos, hasta hoy descubiertos, mención de ningún cómico
de tal nombre, pero también lo es que un copiante pudo llamar bufón a quien no lo fuese: para
un escribiente palaciego poca diferencia habría entre un farsante y un bufón: además, todos
los bufones que pintó Velázquez eran enanos ridículos, seres grotescos, y están vestidos de
mamarracho o con lujo impropio a su condición; en tanto que Pablillos ni es deforme ni lleva
ropas de mogiganga o superiores a su clase; sino que antes al contrario, es de gallarda presenscia,
bien proporcionado de miembros y va vestido seriamente, como persona y no como hazme reír.
En verdad que su semblante truanesco le da patente de pícaro, pero no hay en su cuerpo y rostro
nada común con aquellos miserables fenómenos, verdaderos casos patológicos con cuya ruindad
se divertían nuestros piadosos monarcas. Velázquez retrató a cada personaje según quien era
buscando el modo de acusar su condición y carácter: al Rey con majestad, al caballero con nobleza,
a la dama con la elegancia que permitían las malhadadas galas de su tiempo; y a éste, que yo
tengo por comediante mientras no se demuestre plenamente lo contrario, le puso no en reposo
como casi siempre retrató a grandes y señores, sino movido, declamando, acaso en el acto de
recitar una loa o un paso de entremés. Representa menos de cuarenta años, es de ojillos vivos,
ordinario de facciones, juntos el bigote y la perilla tan negros como el pelo, y su traje de
corte es negro, con golilla blanca, severo, casi señoril. La totalidad de la figura sin accesorio
alguno, hasta sin piso, destaca por obscuro sobre fondo gris: esta como en el aire y sin embargo,
no puso Velázquez hombre mejor plantado.

[imagen: MUSEO DEL PRADO

RENDICIÓN DE BREDA]

También es de este período el retrato de un escultor que primero se supuso ser Alonso Cano
y luego Madrazo, demostró que era Martínez Montañés. Es casi seguro que lo pintara cuando en
1636 el artista fue llamado a Madrid para hacer el busto del Rey que se envió a Tacca con objeto
de facilitarle el estudio de la estatua ecuestre. Es de los mejores que salieron de manos de
Velázquez: de tamaño natural hasta cerca de la rodilla, dibujado con seguridad admirable, construida
la cabeza de suerte que se adivina la estructura ósea bajo la piel blanda y carnosa, y ejecutado
libremente, en unos sitios con cuerpo de color, apenas cubierto el lienzo donde no es preciso,
buscando ante todo el carácter, el alma de la forma; como regalo de un artista a otro; hecho
sin miedo a que el vulgo no lo entienda y con certeza de que el interesado ha de apreciar todo
su mérito. Hablando de la sala donde este retrato estaba antes colocado en nuestro Museo, dice
Lefort. «Allí hay retratos de los más grandes maestros, ¡y qué retratos! El Conde de Bristol,
de Van-Dick, el Thomas Morus, de Rubens; otros de Antonio Moro, de Holbein, de Durero, y precisamente
a su lado uno admirable de hombre por el Tintoretto. Pues bien, a esos formidables vecinos,
este retrato les hace parecer ficciones, imágenes convencionales y muertas. Van Dick es soso,
Rubens grasiento, Tintoretto amarillento; sólo Velázquez nos da en toda su plenitud la ilusión
de la vida.»

En el Museo de Módena, existe el que hacia 1638 pintó del duque Francisco de Este. Es un soberbio
busto con armadura y banda, estudio preliminar probablemente para obra de mayor importancia.

Retrató también a Juan Mateos, ballestero principal de Su Majestad, autor del libro famoso
Origen y dignidad de la Caza, impreso en Madrid en 1634. El cuadro esta hoy en la galería real
de Dresde y es seguramente de Velázquez: lo dicen su factura y el parecido de la imagen con
el retrato de Mateos que figura en aquella obra grabado por P. Perete. En el que le hizo don
Diego, esta Mateos representado de busto con traje de paño verde oscuro y cuello blanco, sobre
el cual resalta enérgicamente modelado el rostro: es de fisonomía expresiva; lleva el pelo,
el bigote y la perilla cortos.

El número 1.090 del Museo del Prado, es retrato en media figura y tamaño natural, de un Conde
de Benavente: lo que no se sabe de cierto es si se trata como imaginó don P. de Madrazo, de
don Antonio Alonso Pimentel, noveno de aquel título muerto en 1633, o de alguno de sus sucesores
como se inclina a creer Beruete, observando discretamente que el estilo del cuadro es el característico
de las obras del maestro en época posterior al fallecimiento de aquel caudillo. Sea quien fuere,
parece por su aspecto noble y caballeresco el tipo legendario del capitán español de aquellos
tiempos. Representa su franca fisonomía más de cincuenta años: tiene la mirada expresiva, el
pelo corto, el bigote y la gran perilla entrecanos. Resguarda su pecho una rica armadura entallada
y damasquinada con listas de oro, y lleva guanteletes de lo mismo. Sirven de fondo a su figura
un cortinaje rojo y un hueco, tras el cual se divisa campo. En los antiguos inventarios de
Palacio, fue esta obra atribuida al Ticiano, y esto que a primera vista parece disparatado,
pues no hay confusión posible entre la manera franca, suelta, de Velázquez y la más fundida
y empastada del gran pintor de Venecia, tiene, sin embargo, su explicación: porque este es
el lienzo en que más acentuada aparece en el pintor de Felipe IV la honda impresión que en
él debieron de causar las obras de Domencio Theotocópuli, el Greco, y de su discípulo Luis
Tristán; influencia interesantísima de que se hablara más adelante.

Otros retratos atribuidos a Velázquez hay en galerías y museos del extranjero, mas no de indudable
autenticidad.

Se sabe, por ejemplo, que en 1639 hizo uno del Almirante de Castilla Don Adrián Pulido Pareja:
Palomino que lo vio en casa del Duque de Arcos, dice, que esta hecho «con pinceles y brochas
de astas largas que usaba algunas veces, para pintar con mayor distancia y valentía; de suerte
que de cerca no se comprendía y de lejos es un milagro»; añade que lo firmó en latín; y hasta
refiere una anécdota, según la cual estando el cuadro puesto hacia donde había poca luz y entrando
el Rey, como solía, a ver pintar a Velázquez, confundió la pintura con el hombre, preguntando
al retratado: «¿Qué, todavía estas aquí? ¿No te he despachado ya? ¿Cómo no te vas? y luego
comprendiendo su error dijo al artista: Os aseguro que me engañé.»

Algunos biógrafos, entre ellos Armstrong, Stirling y Lefort, que llega hasta creer la anécdota,
fundándose en que Felipe IV era muy miope, admiten que este retrato sea el que figura en la
Galería Nacional de Londres: pero Beruete lo pone en duda, señalando deficiencias de dibujo
y poca habilidad en la factura indignas del maestro.

También dice Palomino que retrató a Don Francisco de Quevedo «con los anteojos puestos como
acostumbraba de ordinario a traer». A fines del siglo pasado, era este lienzo propiedad de
Don Juan José López de Sedano, quien lo mandó grabar a Carmona para el Parnaso Español[47].
Hoy se considera perdido, y como antigua copia el que posee el Duque de Wellington[48]. ¡Lastima
grande que no se conserve el original! Debió de pintarlo antes de 1639, en cuyo mes de Diciembre,
viviendo en casa del Duque de Medinaceli, fue preso el gran poeta por orden del Conde-Duque.
Acaso fuera esta la única ocasión en que Velázquez tuvo por modelo a quien valía tanto como él.

Huyendo de Richelieu, contra quien había conspirado, vino a España en 1637 Madama María de
Rohan-Montbazon, Duquesa de Luynes y de Chevreuse, favorita de Ana de Austria, mujer de gran
inteligencia, vida llena de aventuras y singular belleza, cuya aparición en Madrid debió de
traer revueltas y curiosas a las gentes. En Zaragoza la hospedaron los Marqueses de los Vélez
y el Rey le envió coche y machos para venir a la corte, donde entró a 6 de Diciembre, saliendo
a recibirla el Almirante, el Condestable, los Duques de Híjar, Villahermosa, Pastrana y otros
grandes, prueba inequívoca de que el Rey la agasajaba. A su encuentro salieron, más de una
legua, las Marquesas de Mirabel y de las Navas, y la Condesa de Santisteban. «Ella muy bizarra,
despechugada y desenfadada, entró mirando a los que caminaban delante y a los lados, a los
coches que estaban parados y atestados desde el arroyo de Bernigal». Traía dos criados franceses,
uno de los cuales dormía en el aposento de su ama; y «dio madama prendas de la grandeza de
su animo no queriendo recibir ocho mil ducados que le presentaban de parte de S. M.[49]». La
dicha duquesa--añade el escrito de donde tomamos estos datos--en todo se porta con mucha modestia,
y Diego Velázquez la esta ahora retratando con el aire y traje francés[50]». Palomino, dice
que retrató por aquel tiempo con «superior acierto, a una dama de singular perfección[51]».
Nadie ha logrado averiguar si este retrato y el anterior son uno mismo, ni caso de que sean
dos dónde han ido a parar. El de la bella Duquesa de Chevreuse, hecho por Velázquez, sería
bien distinto de los de aquellas reinas e infantas de la Casa de Austria, con cuya fealdad,
guardainfantes, pelucas y coloretes, tuvo que luchar para darles distinción y elegancia. No
fue en la suerte de sus retratos afortunado el gran artista: los de los ilustres poetas y las
mujeres hermosas, como Góngora y Quevedo, la dama inglesa y la Chevreuse, se han perdido: en
cambio quedan de su mano aquellos rostros de príncipes y aquellas figuras de bufones, donde
dolorosamente se ve nuestra triste decadencia.

Tampoco se conservan los que hizo del Cardenal Don Gaspar de Borja, de los maestros de la Cámara
del Rey, Pereira y Cardona, de Don Fernando de Fonseca, pariente sin duda de su protector,
ni el de Fray Simón de Rojas en su lecho de muerte. Finalmente, en alguno de los incendios
de Palacio, debió de desaparecer uno ecuestre que hizo al Rey, el cual expuso al público, y
habiéndole censurado el caballo, enfadándose por la ignorancia ajena o modestamente convencido
del error propio, lo borró.

Aquí acaba la relación de los retratos que pintó por aquellos años, inmortalizando a gentes
de varia condición, entre las cuales no había casi nadie que lo mereciera. Veamos ahora, sus
cuadros de la misma época: donde hallaremos maravillas, encanto de los ojos por lo que deleitan;
desesperación de la pluma incapaz de expresar la vida que palpita en ellos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06253</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>117785</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20478</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

All critics and biographers agree in Velázquez consider this portrait as work of exceptional
merit: some praising it as regards the way of conceiving, printing the rough rider so much life and
so bold, others praise the drawing, where, through of regrets and corrections that are still
noticeable, is an admirable precision, others finally the ease of implementation, which has completely
gone past that hardness of the first pictures. For my part, I only recall that a few steps in
this picture is in our Prado Museum equestrian Charles I, by Titian, and that the comparison is
conducive to the first, for the great Venetian master was raided many difficulties having
to model a figure of heroic overtones, and the Spanish had to infuse his own, without violating the
truth, grandeur and poetry that was missing at all.

Tell the stories and relationships, a dozen women, including wives and girlfriends took Felipe
IV thirty-two children, including legitimate and illegitimate [43], but none will be so pleased
as Prince Don Baltasar Carlos, occurred after three children died without fulfilling a year,
his first wife and cousin Princess of France Isabella of Bourbon, whom he calls a writer of
the day lily fragrant purple rose turned into Spanish.

That child was born the year of 1629, during the continuance of Velázquez in Italy, which portrayed
several times, and it is assumed that the first on a canvas that is now housed in Castle-Howard.
Prince Has there two years and is represented standing on a step in the second term: before he
sees a dwarf page. In his eyes shines the property of their living eye images Further, in its
view, inappropriate for a child, can be discovered by painter to do that highlight the range of
the model: the left hand supports the hilt of the sword and her hand on the baton. Crosses its
rich dark velvet dress with lace a red gold: the background is a red curtain, and a pillow is
the hat velvet with white feathers. The dwarf, located a step lower than his master, becomes
to this the enormous head has smooth wide flange and chain around his neck, an apron covering
her the lower body. In his right hand has a silver-sucking, and left an apple [44]. Beruete, who
take these data, said that for some time, Table attributed to Correggio, assuming that the
portrait was a prince of Parma, but today two distinguished critics, Justi and Armstrong,
the second with some reservations, recognized he hand of Velazquez.

In Madrid the Prince portrayed twice, both times natural size, on foot and horseback. Don Pedro
de Madrazo has described these two pictures with a clarity and precision that no but to ask:
when speaking of a listed accurately clothing from the gorrilla of Walloon wing and lace up
sleeves tabard loggerhead and cloth shoes, with reference to another, from the hat with feathers
and red band of gold ends up boots tawny, or forgotten in the first of the two dogs, retriever
and greyhound, or left in the second to give an idea of ??the brown Andalusian mare harnessed simply:
mentioned, finally, Madrid area funds with breakers on the floor and blue colored clouds clouds
white, but what is not given to express, even with a pen as an expert, is the appeal The figure
of the Prince, happy, playful and yet regal, has in these paintings.

In captivity they certainly look majestic little person innocent and playful, candid and malicious
one that gives a greater grace to any weighting: to increase the charm appears also There is no
doubt that the relationship between age and the landscape around him laughing. Both tables
are light and juicy, and it touches on the implementation of the happiest I can cite the second
way of the author.

In the Vienna Imperial Museum there is another canvas depicting the Prince himself after three
or four years with black velvet gown embroidered with silver, and Ferreruela: this together
with a table covered with red carpet, where he has his hat, and the figure stands on a gray background.
"This work - says Beruete - is altogether wonderful, but the most admirable of it is the prodigious
modeling pale face, lit from the front, and the expression of the face, which reads the character
of the universally beloved child, whose premature death, fatal influence
exercised the fate of Spain.

"

Besides the two mentioned equestrian portraits, that of King and Prince Baltasar Carlos, is
in the Museo del Prado three other real people horse and attributed to Velázquez but that has long
been judged not made all of his hand. Are those of Don Felipe III and Margarita, his wife,
parents of Philip IV, and the latter's first wife, Isabel de Bourbon, who had few times a model
Velázquez, perhaps because this is protected Conde-Duque and she your enemy [45]. Artists and critics
say that in these three large canvases, clearly show lateral additions made to give greater proportions,
the teacher worked on previous portraits made by Bartolome Gonzalez and Nicolas de Villacis,
not Stirling is in Carreño, who was then to be very young. Looking carefully these works is known
that there was the brush of Velasquez was to value and enhance with amendments, corrections and
isolated touches the petty and non-working heavy work of artists. Overpainting are even: the portrait
of Philip III has the horse almost all redone, in the Dona Margarita this varied background,
making the original, which was a garden with boxwood boxes in field of bushes and shrubs in the
Dona Isabel de Borbon also note the change of horse, and head of the Queen there are significant
variations. It therefore seems likely that the the three portraits were painted when Velazquez was that
of Philip IV, and, for brothers with it, the tweak and bravely, giving, in particular that of Philip
III, an aspect great that they had, thus, the works that would now be uninteresting, they are much,
because in them we see how the genius, with little effort, becomes higher, which, with great
penalties, was medium.

Portrayed, also in hunting dress like the King and Prince, the Infante Don Fernando. About from
when did opinions differ: some say that before going to Italy, which denies style, others
say by the year 1647, when the character was killed, drawing face the study of a previous
image. The figure is admirably placed and its side has a hound that is among the best pieces
made by Velázquez painting.

And it says it portrayed people who are talking, could be said about this dog, which not bark
because they want.

Details, isolated, do not represent much, and together they suggest a lot, testify Of course,
in addition to sovereign artist must have been natural kind man Velázquez; at least he was grateful:
I do not hesitate to ensure that evidence is his portrait Count-Duke.

The vanity of it, that it would be safe to bequeath half his image posterity, he would desire:
he justified his rank, but Velazquez put in the work that efforts to approach the perfection of
its kind that is not best conceived.

Was deprived of Felipe IV as a bad manager of the income of the Treasury as jealous of own, which
came to 450,000 ducats a year, so vindictive, who said putting Quevedo crickets to nine pounds,
and being celebrated the funeral of the illustrious Duke of Fernandina ordered that the hands
of the deceased were removed from the general staff, as political evil caused the rebellion
in Catalonia and the loss of Portugal, Brazil and Roussillon; staunch favored sumptuary laws,
although the inventor of the washers, while the operator stamped
paper and computer hunts where as the King entered the twenty pigs
in a later: the fans who showed the letters and the arts into something
so abhorrent amengua its tyranny, but neither was in the military,
and won battles, even took the field.

However, such Velázquez as represented you think of the thunderbolt of war.

In July of 1638 Condé ramming Fuenterrabía besieged by sea under his orders Archbishop of Bordeaux:
defendiose bravely the main square with so few people, who could not be long resistance or
prevent entry. Conde-Duque then assembled a small army about twelve thousand men and with them
the Admiral of the French broke Castilla with such a furious onslaught that was entered Condé
fleeing into the water to win a boat and warlike Archbishop welcomed the ships leaving the
square free; translated the exhilaration experienced by the King
not so much reward as soon as the Admiral to reward with largesse
to the Conde-Duque.

This was the occasion that Velázquez, if flattering grateful to portray field advantage Battle
of whole body and size, ordering a fantastic fight on horseback, breastplate of gold work, large
feather hat, baton and look caudillo safe and worthy of victory. Is the gross, which is chestnut
roan in corvette anchored on legs, hands held high and so well embedded on him the graceful
figure of the rider who does not are seen more vividly in the beast or the man domain. Nobody
would say that this is the Minister courtier whose days Rocroy died in the prestige of the Spanish
infantry, but a hero to those who have guided or Nordinga Muhlberg: undoubtedly the artist
sinning chateau they do not breathe the foul air in vain, committed here in the flatter the weakness
of private: but the evil effect it instantly dissipates because considering that Olivares
was his protector, and that innocent lie was the only sign of gratitude could give. Velazquez
did nothing so exquisite care: none of his paintings so tenacious denotes determination of
accuracy: there he put the best of his understanding and his hands and had noblest sense of his soul.
The color is fresh and unique wealth: the implementation, careful and thorough so great about
the outcome, is in harmony with the nature of the figure where everything
shows strength, determination and vigor [46].

It stands to reason that the obligations attached to the charges in servitude played Velázquez
Palace will not leave much time to accept orders from individuals,
assuming King tolerate it, but it was natural for convenience or friendship
made other portraits: Several of these are preserved, the main as
follows.

The bust of an unknown figure in Apsley House has the Duke of Wellington. On the Counsel Don
Diego del Corral, full-length and size, wearing robe, with a table
with papers in their hands.

It must have been painted around 1632, and is owned by the Duchess Villahermosa.

Pablillo that of Valladolid (No. 1092 of the Museo del Prado). It was said a few years ago that
this was a representative of comedies that dozens working in the pens Madrid and even in the
Old Fortress: and for this reason it was called The Comedian. Madrazo found more later than in
the actual files, inventory was a picture as a portrait of a jester ruff Pablillo was called
at Valladolid, which measures almost coincided with those of the Comedian; and believed, but
his views were accepted, which was not such a representative, but buffoon or man pleasure.
I, with all due respect to this distinguished critic, I can not persuade me. True that there
is in books and old papers, so far discovered no mention of comic of the name, but so is that
a copyist might be called a buffoon who was not: for a palace scribe would have little difference
between a fraud and a fool: also, all Velázquez painted clowns were dwarfs ridiculous, grotesque
beings, and are dressed estate mess or unsuited to their condition, while Pablillo or is deformed or
has mogiganga clothes to class or higher, but on the contrary, it is graceful presenscia,
members well-proportioned and is dressed seriously as a person and not make me laugh. In truth,
his face gives patent truanesco rogue, but not in your body and face nothing in common with
those miserable events, true pathological cases whose villainy sporting our pious monarchs.
Velázquez portrayed each character depending on who was looking for ways to acknowledge their condition
and character: the king in majesty, the noble knight, the lady with the elegance that allowed
the wretched finery of his time, and this, I I have by comedian until proven otherwise fully,
put to rest not usually portrayed as large and gentlemen, but moved, declaiming, perhaps in
the act of loa or recite a passage of dish. Represents less than forty years, little eyes is alive
regular features, together mustache and goatee as black as his hair, and clothing court is black,
with white ruff, severe, almost lordly. The entire figure without accessories one, even without floor,
characterized by dark gray background: this and in the air and yet Velazquez got no better man planted.

[Image:
MUSEO DEL PRADO

SURRENDER OF BREDA]

Also of this period, the portrait of a sculptor
who first assumed to be Alonso Cano Madrazo then showed that it was
Martinez Montanes.

It is almost certain that the paint when 1636 the artist was summoned to Madrid to make a
bust of the king who sent Tacca order to facilitate the study of the statue. Is of the best
left hands Velázquez: natural size to about the knee, drawn with admirable security built head so
that it guesses the bone structure beneath the skin soft, fleshy, and carried freely in some
places with body-colored, barely covered the canvas where it is not necessary looking at all the character,
the soul of the form, as a gift from one artist to another, a fact without fear that the populace
does not understand with certainty that the party should appreciate all merit. Speaking of the
room where the portrait was soon placed in our museum says Lefort. "There are portraits of the
great masters, and what pictures! The Earl of Bristol, Van-Dick, Thomas Morus, Rubens, and others
of Antonio Moro, Holbein, Dürer, and precisely next to an admirable man by Tintoretto. Well, these
formidable neighbors, this picture makes it look like fiction, conventional imaging and dead.
Dick Van is dull, Greasy Rubens, Tintoretto yellowish Velázquez only gives us in all its fullness the
illusion of life. "

At the Museum of Modena, there is that by 1638 he painted the Duke Francesco d'Este. It is a superb
Armored bust and band, preliminary study probably the most important
work.

Also portrayed Juan Mateos, principal of HM archer, author of famous book Origin and dignity
of the Chase, printed in Madrid in 1634. The painting is now in the real gallery Dresden and is
likely to Velázquez: they say their bill and the similarity of the image Mateos's portrait
contained in that work recorded by P. Perete. The gift that made him Diego, this bust represented
Mateos green cloth with dark suit and white collar on which strongly underlines shaped the face:
it is expressive face, her hair, the short mustache and goatee.

The number 1,090 of the Prado Museum, is an average figure and portrait size of a Count Benavente:
What is not known for sure is if it is as he imagined Don P. Madrazo, of Don Antonio Alonso
Pimentel, the ninth of that title died in 1633, or any of its successors as inclined to believe
Beruete, quietly observing the style of the painting is the characteristic teacher works in time after
the death of that leader. Whoever, appears from his noble, chivalrous type legendary Spanish master
those times. Represents his frank face more than fifty years has expressive eyes, the short hair,
mustache and graying goatee great. It houses a rich his chest armor Fitted and damask with gold,
and has gauntlets of the same. Backdrop for his figure a red curtain and a hollow, after which the
currency field. In the old inventories Palace, was the one attributed to Titian, and at first
glance this seems absurd, because there is no confusion between the frank, loose, and most
molten Velázquez and pasted the great painter of Venice, has, however, his explanation for
this is the canvas that appears more pronounced in the painter to Philip IV the deep impression
that he had to cause Theotocópuli Domencio works, El Greco, and his disciple Louis Tristan
interesting influence that will be discussed later.

Other portraits are attributed to Velázquez in galleries and museums
abroad, but certainly not authenticity.

We know, for example, that in 1639 became one of the Admiral of Castile Don Adrián Pulido Pareja:
Palomino you saw in the house of the Duke of Arcos, says that this fact "with paintbrushes Long
wearing antlers sometimes to paint with greater distance and courage of luck that was not understood
by and far is a miracle, says it was signed in Latin, and even relates an anecdote, that while
the picture as to where there was little light and entering King, as usual, to see painting Velazquez,
painting confused with the man, asking the portrait: "What, are you still here? Have I not already
dispatched? Why did not you go? and then realizing his mistake said the artist: I assure you
that I cheated. "

Some biographers, including Armstrong, Stirling and Lefort, who comes to believe the story,
Philip IV on the grounds that it was very shortsighted, admit that this portrait should be
as given in National Gallery of London but you doubt Beruete, noting
deficiencies drawing and little ability on the bill unworthy of the
master.

Palomino says also portrayed Don Francisco de Quevedo "wearing glasses as usually used to bring.
" At the end of last century, this painting was owned by Don Juan Jose Lopez de Sedano, who sent
him to record a Spanish Parnassus Carmona [47]. Today is considered lost, and how old copy which
has the Duke of Wellington [48]. Pity large not keep the original! It must have been painted
before 1639, in which month of December, living in the home of the
Duke of Medinaceli, the great poet was arrested by order of the Conde-Duque.

Perhaps it was this the only time that Velazquez had the model who was as good as him.

Fleeing from Richelieu, who had conspired against, came to Spain in 1637 Madame Mary Rohan Montbazon,
Duchess of Luynes and Chevreuse, a favorite of Anne of Austria, a woman of great intelligence,
life full of adventures and unique beauty, whose appearance in Madrid must have Weird riots and
bring the people. In Zaragoza hosted the Marquis de los Vélez and the King sent her car and males
to come to court, where he entered December 6, leaving to receive the Admiral, the Constable,
the Duke of Híjar, Villahermosa, Pastrana and other larger, unequivocal proof that the king entertained.
At the meeting came more than a league, the Marquesas of Mirabel and Navas, and the Countess
de Santisteban. "She's very bizarre, and laid bare-chested, went walking looking at the front and
sides, to cars were stopped and crowded from Bernigal stream. " He had two servants French
one of whom slept in the apartment of his mistress, and "Madame gave clothes to the greatness
of your mood not wanting to receive eight thousand ducats that he had from SM [49]. " The Duchess
said - adding the letter from which we get such data - all behaved with great modesty, Diego
Velázquez and is now portraying the air and brought the French [50]. " Palomino says he portrayed
at that time to "superior skill, a lady of singular perfection [51]." No one has determined
whether this portrait and the former are self, nor should they be two where they went. The
one with the beautiful Duchess of Chevreuse, made by Velázquez, would quite different from
those queens and princesses of the House of Austria, whose ugliness farthingales, wigs and
rouge, had to fight to give them distinction and elegance. No was in the fortunate luck of the
great artist portraits: those of the illustrious poets and beautiful women, as Gongora and Quevedo,
the English lady and Chevreuse, have been lost: in Change your hand are the faces of those
figures of princes and clowns, where pain is our sad decline.

Nor did it keep the Cardinal Don Gaspar de Borja, teachers of the House King, Pereira and Cardona,
Don Fernando de Fonseca, a relative no doubt of his patron, nor the Fray Simón de Rojas on
his deathbed. Finally, some of fire Palace, he must eliminate one horse who did the King, which
exposed the public and Having been censored on the horse, angry about
the ignorance of others or moderately satisfied own error, deleted it.

Here ends the relationship of the portraits he painted during those years, people immortalized several
conditions, among which there was almost no one who deserved it.
Let's see now, your pictures of the same era: where we find wonder,
enchantment of eyes as delight; desperate pen can not express the
life that beats in them</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>