<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>15181</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23042</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Su amor propio se había hecho tan nervioso,
tan excitable, que el más ligero choque con él sentíalo como una profunda puñalada. Su conciencia
la acusaba continuamente de orgullo. Sostenía contra sí misma una lucha cruel, y no lograba
calmar aquella singular irritabilidad.

El P. Gil sondeó aquel día y los sucesivos (porque Obdulia se confesaba a menudo) con profunda
emoción un espíritu verdaderamente piadoso, al cual su lucha consigo mismo hacía aún más interesante.
Era una de esas almas que sólo había visto descritas en los libros místicos. Su inefable dulzura,
la sumisión con que recibía los consejos y advertencias, le sedujo y le inquietó al mismo tiempo:
le inquietó porque desconfiaba mucho de si mismo, temía no acertar a comprender los anhelos
ardientes, las reconditeces sublimes de un ser superior a todos los que hasta entonces había
conocido. Comenzó a prestar intensa atención a las extrañas confidencias de la joven, a sus
escrúpulos, a sus alegrías y terrores, a sus visiones, porque las tenía de vez en cuando. Y
ya no le sorprendió que los demás confesores no la hubiesen comprendido. Recordaba lo que le
sucediera a Santa Teresa, y se propuso con el ejemplo no despreciar por ridículas ciertas menudencias,
señales de una conciencia siempre alerta, ni considerar como deslumbramientos y trampantojos
los que muy bien podrían ser favores reales del Cielo.

Lo que más le impresionó en la piedad de su nueva penitenta fue el afán de mortificarse. Trataba
a su cuerpo sin compasión, un cuerpo delicado como el tallo de una flor. Varias veces durante
la noche levantábase a orar; al amanecer, en los días más húmedos y fríos del año, salía de
casa para ir a la iglesia, donde pasaba algunas horas de rodillas; ayunaba con un rigor que
no había visto ni en su ascético maestro del seminario, abstinencias prolongadas, terribles,
que parecían imposibles de resistir; gastaba cilicios en las piernas y los brazos, y se disciplinaba
los viernes y en las vísperas de las fiestas señaladas. Este desapego de la carne, este odio
de la bestia nunca lo había sentido el joven sacerdote. En vano se lo había querido inculcar
su director espiritual, en vano había trabajado toda su vida por adquirirlo. Todo fue inútil.
Las penitencias corporales le dolían, le aterraban de tal modo que apenas comenzadas tenía
que suspenderlas. Maltrataba a su espíritu con gran valor, sofocaba en él toda aspiración,
todo deseo que le pareciese pecaminoso, lo humillaba siempre que quería; pero temía al dolor
físico como la más sensible damisela: de ello se acusaba al confesor y se dolía en sus largas
y fervorosas oraciones. Por eso las ásperas penitencias de la joven le causaron una admiración
ilimitada.

Todos admiran más aquello que les falta. Nunca se sintió más humillado ni dudó tanto de su
virtud y su salvación. Y tomándolo como una advertencia del Cielo, se propuso intentar nuevamente
este camino de perfección, por el cual habían andado todos los que verdaderamente quieren acercarse
a Dios. Alentado por el ejemplo de la piadosa doncella, comenzó a maltratar su carne como ella:
cada una de sus confidencias servíale de ejemplo. Quiso también ayunar rigurosamente, quiso
también levantarse al primer sueño y pasar una hora en cruz de rodillas, quiso gastar cilicio,
quiso disciplinarse. Fue un combate terrible con su naturaleza pura y tranquila de hombre sin
pasiones, que no siente por tanto la necesidad de aquietarlas a latigazos.

Su admiración por la virtuosa doncella le impulsó no sólo a tomarla de ejemplo, sino también
de consejera. Era tan humilde e inocente de corazón que se sentía avergonzado teniendo que
dirigir y reprender a quien en el fondo consideraba como superior. Poco a poco comenzaron las
mutuas confidencias. El nuevo clérigo, no teniendo en Peñascosa un director espiritual acomodado
a su educación mística, abrió insensiblemente su pecho y comunicó a la joven sus alegrías,
sus triunfos y sus desmayos en la vía de salud que se había trazado. Fue una amistad espiritual,
en que no se trataba otro asunto que el del servicio de Dios, en que se pasaban largos ratos
hablando dulcemente de las cosas del Cielo. Ni faltaban tampoco en sus coloquios algunas bromitas
inocentes que los regocijaban por breves instantes.

--Cuando usted se encuentre en el cielo--decía sonriendo el P. Gil,--muy arrellanadita en la
silla que le corresponda, ¡qué poco se acordará de su pobre confesor, que estará padeciendo
en el purgatorio!

--¡No diga eso, padre! Si usted no va derecho al cielo, ¿quién ha de ir?

--¡Oh, no!--respondía con un suspiro el sacerdote.--Usted tiene formado de mí un concepto muy
equivocado... Yo soy un indigno pecador... Gracias infinitas daré a Dios si me lleva al purgatorio,
aunque esté allí miles de años...

Y lo decía de todo corazón el virtuoso clérigo. Creía de buena fe que, porque no le era posible
macerarse, no poseía una virtud sólida, y se alegraba en el fondo del alma de haber tropezado
con un ser que gozaba de este privilegio. Acudíale a la memoria frecuentemente el ejemplo del
P. Gracián, a quien Santa Teresa tanto había ayudado en el camino de la perfección con sus
virtudes y consejos. Su amor platónico al ascetismo le impulsaba a alentar en vez de reprimir
prudentemente el de su penitenta. Cada mortificación que ésta se infligía y temblando y ruborizada
venía a relatarle en el confesonario le causaba un gozo profundo, le parecía un triunfo sobre
el pecado y se forjaba la ilusión de que a él le correspondía una parte de la victoria.

Muchas y variadas fueron las que la valerosa doncella consiguió sobre la carne en el espacio
de pocos meses. Así como los hombres corrompidos agotan su imaginación en busca de nuevos placeres,
así ella sobresalía en la invención de variados tormentos para su delicado cuerpo. La aprobación
de su confesor, las frases de elogio que a despecho suyo se le escapaban de los labios, indudablemente
calentaban su fantasía y aguijaban sus ímpetus. Un día se pasaba veinticuatro horas sin tomar
alimento, otro echaba ceniza en el plato que más le gustaba, otro se ponía una camisa de lana
burda a raíz de la carne, otro se disciplinaba hasta saltar la sangre, etc.

Cierta tarde se acercó al confesonario con la faz más radiante, con un gozo intenso pintado
en sus grandes ojos negros y misteriosos. Acababa de lograr un nuevo triunfo sobre el enemigo
y ansiaba comunicarlo a su confesor. Pero éste, en vez de entretenerse en coloquios místicos
como otras veces, y de enterarse con afectuoso interés de sus penitencias, de sus luchas con
la carne, se atuvo severamente a los pecados. Se hallaba quizá en un momento de melancolía
o de concentración del pensamiento. Mantúvose en una actitud reservada, hablando poco, tratándola
casi como a una desconocida. Esta reserva impresionó a la joven. Hallábase ella precisamente
en uno de esos momentos de expansión, en que la alegría espiritual rebosa del pecho. Pensaba
hacer partícipe de ella a su virtuoso confesor. Mas hete aquí que a éste le da por callar y
abreviar la confesión todo lo posible. La joven se levantó al fin triste y sin poder reprimir
un movimiento de despecho. Dio algunos pasos por la capilla, que estaba solitaria. De repente,
no pudiendo vencer el deseo de hacer saber a su confesor la terrible penitencia que había llevado
a cabo, se acerca de nuevo al confesonario, no por la ventanilla, sino por la puerta.

--Padre--dice con voz temblorosa, ahogada por la emoción,--se me olvidó decir que esta noche
hice una penitencia que acaso, por excesiva, pudiera ser un pecado.

El joven presbítero levantó los ojos sin comprender bien, expresando una muda interrogación.

--Me he quemado con una plancha.

El confesor permaneció silencioso, mirándola con ojos distraídos.

--Me he puesto la plancha ardiendo en un brazo...

El mismo silencio. El P. Gil, o estaba pensando en otra cosa, o el estupor le había inmovilizado.

Sin duda creyó lo primero Obdulia, porque dijo con cierta viveza:

--Sí, señor, me he hecho en el brazo esta quemadura...

Y al mismo tiempo levantó la manga del vestido y puso al descubierto una herida fea y dolorosa
que tenía en el antebrazo.

El sacerdote se encendió como una amapola, y volviendo prontamente la cabeza, repuso con aspereza
mirando a las tablas del confesonario:

--Bueno, bueno... Deje usted... Me parece excesivo, en efecto... Absténgase en adelante de
hacer tales penitencias sin consultarlas antes con su confesor.

III

A las ocho de la noche, después de haber cenado con D. Miguel y de haberle visto retirarse
a la cama en la dulce compañía de sus pistolas de chispa, el P. Gil salió de la rectoral con
dirección a la casa de su protectora D.ª Eloisa Montesinos. Pocas veces iba a la tertulia que
ésta reunía por las noches. Ni tenía gusto en ello, ni el régimen severo de la casa del cura
lo consentía. Pero su protectora se había quejado del abandono; hasta le pareció que estaba
más fría con él. Temeroso de ser tachado de ingratitud y apesadumbrado realmente, porque profesaba
tierno y respetuoso cariño a la bondadosa señora, resolviose a ir más a menudo, haciéndolo
así presente al párroco.

El agua de un fuerte chubasco le azotó el rostro al poner el pie fuera de la puerta. Abrió
el paraguas, mas a los pocos pasos, el viento que soplaba huracanado en el Campo de los Desmayos
se lo volvió. En la imposibilidad de cerrarlo y sintiéndose empujado violentamente por el huracán,
el joven excusador se refugió en el negro, enorme portal de Montesinos. Nunca pasaba por delante
de él sin sentir cierto estremecimiento de temor y curiosidad. En aquel sombrío palacio habitaba
un hombre misterioso de quien se contaban vagamente mil extrañas historias, a quien se atribuían
además ideas y frases escandalosas contra la religión y sus ministros. El joven clérigo apenas
le conocía. D. Álvaro Montesinos había pasado casi toda su vida en Madrid. Hacía dos o tres
años solamente que había venido a establecerse a Peñascosa. Vivía en un retiro casi absoluto,
paseando alguna que otra rara vez por las orillas del mar, enteramente solo. El resto de los
días lo pasaba encerrado en casa, según se decía, leyendo o escribiendo artículos impíos. El
clero de Peñascosa hablaba de él con cierto desprecio rencoroso, del cual había llegado a participar
el P. Gil, sin conocerle.

Arregló su paraguas lo mejor que pudo, y como los ímpetus del viento hubiesen sosegado un instante,
saliose del portal, no sin dirigir una mirada de miedo y hostilidad a la gran puerta negra
del fondo, en lo alto de la cual ardía tristemente una lamparilla de aceite detrás de una ventanilla
enrejada. Salió del Campo de los Desmayos y, una vez en la calle del Cuadrante (que así se
llamaba la única grande y poblada de Peñascosa), el viento ya no soplaba tan recio y pudo aprovecharse
del paraguas y llegar a casa de Dª Eloisa, situada en la plaza, sin mojarse seriamente. La
morada de D. Martín de las Casas era también antigua, pero notablemente reformada, mucho más
chica que la de su cuñado, con todas las comodidades y aditamentos exigidos por las necesidades
modernas: portal de azulejos con cancela, escalera bien labrada de álamo con pasamano charolado,
las habitaciones con elegantes frisos y papeles, todo muy aseado y pintadito.

--¡Buenos ojos le vean, padre! ¡Qué caro se vende!--exclamó Dª Eloisa, que desde que su protegido
había recibido las sagradas órdenes no le tuteaba.

Al mismo tiempo se levantó y le besó la mano con verdadero afecto. Lo mismo hicieron Dª Rita,
Obdulia, que desde hacía poco tiempo era tertulia asidua de la casa, Marcelina y también Dª
Serafina Barrado, a pesar de la mirada oblicua que le dirigió su capellán D. Joaquín. Dª Marciala
y Dª Filomena se hicieron las distraídas hablando con D. Peregrín Casanova, y saludaron al
fin desde su asiento con sonrisa halagüeña.

Mientras duraron las salutaciones, D. Narciso, que estaba arrimado de espaldas al piano, no
quitó los ojos de su compañero, unos ojos donde se leían claramente la aversión y el recelo.
Sin que el P. Gil la provocara ni aun se diera bien cuenta de ella, existía viva rivalidad
entre él y D. Narciso, a quien había arrancado más de la mitad de las hijas de confesión. Bien
sabía Dios que no había hecho nada por conseguirlo; antes, al contrario, le pesaba mucho cada
vez que una de ellas se acercaba a su confesonario. Pero ¿qué le tocaba hacer? Nada más que
confesarlas, pues era su obligación. Insistir mucho en que no variasen de confesor era conceder
demasiada importancia a la cuestión de persona: no estaba dentro del espíritu del sacramento.
Pero el capellán de Sarrió no se hallaba penetrado de la intención de su compañero, y si se
hallaba, no alteraba gran cosa sus sentimientos. Ateníase al resultado, y éste era triste para
él. Antes de la llegada de Gil puede decirse que campaba él sólo entre el bello sexo de Peñascosa
y señoreaba sus conciencias. Los demás capellanes no le hacían sombra alguna. Era el niño mimado
de las beatas. Ninguno de sus chistes, de sus pasos y gestos pasaba inadvertido: las devotas
que tenían la dicha de escucharlos o presenciarlos, se encargaban prontamente de difundirlos
entre sus amigas. A cada instante testimonios irrecusables de la viva simpatía y veneración
que despertaba en la villa: regalos de casullas, de corporales bordados por dedos primorosos,
de alzacuellos de raso, etc., etc.; ofrendas más positivas aún, de jamones, botellas de jerez,
tartas y chocolate. D. Narciso tenía admirablemente cubiertas sus necesidades espirituales
y temporales. Era un pastor que apacentaba felizmente sus ovejas, conduciéndolas con dulzura
por el sendero de la virtud hacia el paraíso y trasquilándolas de vez en cuando el rico vellón
para que no se enredaran en las zarzas.

La aparición de su nuevo compañero vino a turbar aquella deliciosa Arcadia mística. Las ovejas,
acometidas súbito de agitación insana, se pusieron a saltar y encabritarse cual si escuchasen
los sones de un caramillo encantado. Ni las pedradas ni los halagos lograron retener a una
gran parte de ellas. Quedó en cuadro su rebaño, y él, que había tenido fuerzas para gobernar
un hato tan considerable, desmayaba ahora al verse solo, al percibir la hostilidad con que
le miraban algunas de sus antiguas y queridas ovejitas. Porque no solamente ya no llegaban
a su casa los ricos dones ultramarinos y nacionales de otros tiempos, sino que con profundo
dolor notaba que empezaba a discutírsele. Decíase entre las damas piadosas, y esto llegaba
a sus oídos, que, si era cierto que tenía palabra más fácil que el joven excusador, la mayor
parte de las veces «no había sustancia en lo que decía,» y que éste le aventajaba mucho en
peso, en razón natural y en instrucción. Hubo ocasión en que al lanzar uno de sus chistes más
picantes, relacionado como siempre con las materias fecales, apenas produjo risa entre las
oyentes, y supo que una de ellas, después que se fue, le había calificado de grosero y mal
educado. De las gracias corporales no había que hablar, pues bien se le alcanzaba que nunca
podría competir con la delicada y gallarda figura de su rival. En resumen, D. Narciso se sentía
minado en los cimientos y temía a cada instante venir al suelo. No es maravilla, pues, que
la mirada y el saludo con que acogió al joven presbítero fuesen menos afectuosos de lo que
debía esperarse. No recordaba poco ni mucho la amable recepción que San Juan Bautista, maestro
querido y celebrado, hizo al joven y divino discípulo que le había de eclipsar en seguida.

--No le riñas, mujer. ¿Sabes tú, por ventura, si le será fácil salir de noche, con el miedo
que D. Miguel tiene a los ladrones?--gritó D. Martín de las Casas desde la mesa de tresillo
donde jugaba con otros dos, un cura y un seglar.

--No, señor; no es eso--dijo el clérigo, ruborizándose bajo las miradas de toda la tertulia.

--¿Que no tiene D. Miguel miedo a los ladrones?--preguntó con acento afectadamente brusco el
señor de las Casas.

--Sí que lo tiene--repuso sonriendo dulcemente el joven, sentándose al propio tiempo al lado
de su madrina.--Sus razones habrá. Los ricos son los que temen. Los pobres, como yo, están
tranquilos.

--Pero ¿tendrá el señor cura tanto dinero como se dice?--preguntó D.ª Marciala con curiosidad.

--Yo no puedo decir a usted, señora... Presumo que sí, porque atiende mucho a su hacienda.
Sus gastos son pequeños, y en vez de aumentarse los va restringiendo cada día más. Donde entra
mucho y sale poco no tiene más remedio que hacerse montón.

--Los derechos parroquiales deben producir mucho, ¿verdad?--preguntó con más curiosidad aún
la esposa del boticario de la plaza.

--Ya comprenderá usted que en una parroquia tan extensa como ésta no han de ser cortos.

--Pero D. Miguel perdonará muchos de ellos--replicó la señora, con una leve inflexión cómica
en la voz.

--Es posible, señora. Por mi parte, no lo he visto--repuso con perfecta ingenuidad el excusador.

D. Narciso y D. Joaquín, el capellán de la señora de Barrado, cambiaron una rápida mirada significativa.

Este capellán era un joven delgado, con rosetas en las mejillas, indicio de un temperamento
enfermizo, los ojos vivos e insolentes, la nariz fina, la boca pequeña, con un pliegue hipócrita
y malicioso. Había sido un criadillo que doña Serafina metió en casa para recados y servir
a la mesa, poco después de quedar viuda. Observando su listeza y encariñada con él, una vez
trasladado su domicilio a Lancia, le dio carrera, enviándole al seminario. En las horas que
le dejaban libres las clases, Joaquín seguía desempeñando su oficio de criado. Luego que tomó
las órdenes le hizo su administrador; hoy era sus pies y sus manos. No salía a la calle sino
en su compañía, era su director espiritual y su consejero temporal. Espectáculo curioso en
verdad la trasformación súbita de un doméstico en señor de su propia ama. Ésta le trataba de
usted, le llamaba siempre D. Joaquín y, públicamente al menos, le prodigaba mil muestras de
respeto, obligando asimismo a los criados a tributárselo.

D.ª Eloisa volvió a insistir, preguntando con acento cariñoso:

--Entonces, ¿cuál es la razón de su retraimiento, pícaro?

--Señora, comprendo que a D. Miguel no le gusta mucho que salga de noche; pero la principal
razón es que la mayor parte de los días estoy rendido... ¡Como me levanto a las cuatro de la
madrugada!... Otras veces necesito rezar un poco...

--Usted trabaja demasiado, padre--dijo Marcelina, una joven soltera que, al decir de la gente,
frisaba ya en los cuarenta, fea, apergaminada, muy habilidosa de manos y no poco también de
lengua.--¡Tantas horas de confesonario!... ¡Y luego los enfermos!...

--Sin contar las horas que pasa de rodillas en oración...--apuntó con timidez Obdulia. Después
de soltar la frase se puso colorada.

D. Narciso le clavó una mirada singular, entre irónica y agresiva, que la joven no pudo ver,
porque ponía empeño en no mirar cara a cara a su antiguo confesor.

El P. Gil hizo un gesto de impaciencia, molestado por aquellos elogios, y para desviar la conversación
de su persona, se encaró con uno de los que jugaban al tresillo.

--Señor Consejero, hoy le he visto desde la rectoral sacar con la caña un pez muy gordo. Por
cierto que me pareció un salmonete, y a D. Miguel una robaliza. Hemos disputado un poco.

--Tiene mejor vista el cura que usted. Una robaliza era--dijo gravemente el caballero interpelado,
sin levantar la vista de las cartas.

Este D. Romualdo Consejero era un anciano de bigote y cortas patillas blancas, color cetrino,
la frente surcada con profundas arrugas, los ojos grandes, severos, de párpados caídos. No
sonreía jamás. Hablaba constantemente con acento de mal humor, como hombre desengañado de todo.

--Los salmonetes no caen en el muelle, don Gil de las calzas verdes--profirió el señor de las
Casas con su habitual rudeza, por no decir grosería. Solía llamar así, en broma, a su antiguo
protegido.

--Sí caen tal, D. Martín de las Casas blancas--profirió con voz sorda Consejero.

Los tertulianos rieron, lo cual amoscó un tanto a D. Martín, hombre, como ya sabemos, propenso
a irritarse.

--Yo lo creía así, Consejero de picardías--respondió con retintín, mirándole a la cara fijamente,
y poniendo sobre la mesa al mismo tiempo un rey de copas.

--Pues creía usted muy mal--replicó el anciano, siempre con los ojos sobre las cartas.--También
creía usted que ese rey de copas iba a pasar triunfante, y... vea usted, ¡lo fallo!

--Eso lo hará usted porque es un grosero y ha adquirido malas mañas allá por Málaga. Aquí el
padre Norberto de seguro no lo hubiera hecho.

--¡No, no! Yo soy incapaz...--dijo el cura, sofocado por la risa, tosiendo hasta reventar.--No
he salido de Peñascosa... Yo lo que hago es achicarme y correr ese punto de oros de mi compañero.

Y puso sobre la mesa un cuatro.

--¡Hurra por el cura!--rugió D. Martín, echando el caballo y recogiendo la baza.

--Amigo, yo pensé que D. Martín no tendría el caballo--suspiró D. Norberto, dirigiéndose a
Consejero con ojos de angustia.

--Lo pensó usted porque es un babieca y lo ha sido toda su vida--repuso éste con afectada naturalidad
donde se traslucía la cólera.

--¡Pero hombre de Dios!...--exclamó el clérigo, disponiéndose a dar explicaciones.

Consejero le atajó con ademán colérico, poniendo resueltamente las cartas boca abajo sobre la mesa.

--¡Hombre del diablo! digo yo... ¿Cómo se le ocurre a usted correr un punto no estando cubierto?...

Armose una disputa violenta que duró breves instantes. Las de Consejero y el P. Norberto no
se prolongaban mucho tiempo, porque éste, hombre de buena pasta, flemático, concluía por callarse
alzando los hombros con resignación y sacudiendo al mismo tiempo la cabeza en señal de muda
protesta. Las que se eternizaban eran las de Consejero con D. Martín, siendo ambos a cual más
irascible y tozudo.

D. Martín de las Casas, teniente coronel retirado, que había hecho la guerra de Cuba, donde
había recibido una herida en un hombro que le impidió continuar en el servicio, se creía en
el caso, por su profesión, de llevarlo todo por la tremenda. Desde el año 1873 en que pasó
al cuerpo de Inválidos no volvió a salir de Peñascosa. Contaba en aquella época cuarenta y
dos años. Su esposa se alegró de aquel retiro forzoso, aunque deplorase que viniera al seno
de la familia con un hombro de algodón. Consideraba como virtud excelsa, privativa del militar,
la energía lo mismo en el campo de batalla que tomando café en el casino. Sus disputas, sus
baladronadas en este centro de recreo eran proverbiales en Peñascosa y las bofetadas que solía
repartir al final de ellas también. Desde la llegada del tremendo teniente coronel ningún vecino,
por grave y respetable que fuese, estaba seguro. Muchos hidalgos y ricos hacendados de la villa,
que hasta entonces habían conservado inmaculadas sus mejillas, ni soñaban con que nadie pudiese
atentar a ellas, las vieron selladas y rubricadas cuando más descuidados estaban por los dedos
del feroz inválido. Esto fue causa de un lento reflujo entre sus amigos y conocidos, que le
habían recibido cordialmente a su vuelta del servicio. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04809</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>136614</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20886</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> His pride had been so nervous so excitable, that
the slightest shock to him as a deep stab sentíalo. His conscience constantly accused her of pride.
He maintained a struggle against itself cruel, and could not that singular calm irritability.

Fr
Gil sounded that day and thereafter (because Obdulia confessed often)
with deep true spirit of pious emotion, to which his struggle with
himself was even more interesting.

It was one of those souls who had only been described in mystical books. His ineffable sweetness
submission to receiving the advice and warnings, seduced him and was disturbed at the same time: worried
because he was very suspicious of himself, he feared could not understand the longings burning, the
lofty recesses of a being superior to all those who had hitherto known. He started strong focus on
the strange secrets of the young, their scruples, their joys and terrors, their visions, because
he was from time to time. Y and was not surprised that the other confessors had not understood.
Remembered what happened to Santa Teresa, which was proposed by example not to scorn by some
ridiculous trifles signals an alert conscience, nor considered as glare and optical illusions
which could very well be real favors from Heaven.

What most impressed with the piety of his new penitent was the desire to mortify. Was your body
without compassion, a delicate body as the stem of a flower.

Several times during night rose up to pray at dawn, in the wet and cold days of the year, leaving
home to go to church, where he spent several hours on his knees, fasted with a rigor that had
not seen in his ascetic master of the seminar, prolonged abstinence, terrible that seemed impossible
to resist; spent sackcloth in the legs and arms, and disciplined Fridays and the eves of feasts.
This detachment of the flesh, this hatred of the beast never felt the young priest. In vain
he had wanted to instill his spiritual director, for nothing had worked their entire lives to acquire
it. All was useless. Bodily penances ached, so terrified him that he had just started to adjourn.
Abused his spirit with great value, every aspiration stifled in him, I wish you all seem sinful,
humiliated him whenever he wanted, but feared the pain the most sensitive physical damsel: it
was accused confessor and hurt in their long and fervent prayers. So the harsh penance of
the young caused him admiration unlimited.

All admired more for what they lack. He never felt more humiliated or doubted both their virtue
and salvation. And they took as a warning from Heaven, it was proposed to try again this path
of perfection, which had traveled all who truly want to get closer
God.

Encouraged by the example of the pious maiden, began to abuse her flesh as she: each sample
ministered unto her confidences. It also wanted to fast rigorously, wanted also rise to the first
dream and spend an hour on the cross on his knees, he wanted to spend sackcloth wanted to discipline.
It was a terrible fight with her pure and quiet nature of man without passions, which therefore
does not feel the need to quiet them with whips.

His admiration for the virtuous maiden led him not only to take an example, but also counselor.
He was so humble and innocent heart that he was embarrassed having
to direct and reprimand in the background who considered superior.

Gradually began mutual confidence. The new priest, not having a spiritual director accommodated
Peñascosa their education mystical insensibly opened his chest and told the girl his joys,
their triumphs and their fainting on the road had been planned health. It was a spiritual friendship,
in that it was another matter that the service of God, who spent long periods talking softly of
the things of Heaven. Either missing or some little jokes in his talks innocent than rejoicing
for a brief moment.

- When you meet in heaven - he said smiling P. Gil, - very arrellanadita in seat allotted to him how
little will remember his poor confessor, who will suffer in purgatory!

-
Do not say that, father!

If you do not go straight to heaven, who has to go?

- Oh, no! - Responded with a sigh the priest .-- You have made me
a very concept wrong ... I am an unworthy sinner ... Give infinite
thanks to God if it takes me to purgatory but are there thousands
of years ...

And he said it with all my heart the virtuous priest.

Believed in good faith because he could not macerated, did not have
a solid basis, and rejoiced at the bottom of the soul to have stumbled
with a being who enjoyed this privilege.

AcuDial to mind often the example of P. Gracian, who both helped Santa Teresa on the path of
perfection with virtues and advice. Your crush asceticism led him to encourage rather than suppress
prudently his penitent.

Each mortification that it was inflicted and trembling and blushing came to relate in the confessional
was causing a deep joy, it seemed a triumph over sin and forging the illusion that it accounted
for a part of the victory.

Many and varied were the brave girl that got on the meat in space a few months. Just as corrupt
men exhaust their imagination in search of new pleasures, so she excelled in the invention of various
torments for her delicate body. Approval of his confessor, the words of praise that eluded him
despite his lips, no doubt warming fantasy and goad their impetus.

One day he spent twenty-four hours to take food, another threw ashes in his favorite dish, another
wore a wool shirt crude because of the meat, another disciplined to skip the blood, etc..

One afternoon he approached the confessional with the most radiant face, painted with intense joy in their
big black eyes and mysterious. Had just won a new victory over the enemy and longed to tell your
confessor. But this, rather than linger mystical colloquies as usual, and learn with affectionate
interest of their penances, their struggles with meat, complied severely
sins.

It was perhaps in a moment of melancholy or concentration of thought. Mantúvose a reserved
attitude, saying little, treating almost like a stranger. This book impressed the young. Hallab
it precisely in one of those moments of expansion, in which the chest is brimming with spiritual
joy. Thought to involve it in their righteous confessor. But lo and behold that it gives to
silence and confession short as possible. The young man stood up at last sad and unable to
repress a movement of despair. He took a few steps from the chapel, which was deserted. Suddenly,
can not overcome the desire to tell his confessor had been terrible penance out, comes back
to the confessional, not the window, but through the door.

- Father - said in a trembling voice, choked with emotion - I forgot to say tonight I did a penance
perhaps, excessive, it may be a sin.

The young priest looked up without fully understanding, expressing a dumb question.

- I burned with an iron.

The confessor remained silent, watching her distracted eyes.

- I
put the iron burn on the arm ...

The same silence.

Fr Gil, or was thinking about something else, or stupor had frozen.

No doubt the first thought Obdulia, she said with some vividness:

-
Yes, sir, I've done in the arm is burning ...

And at the same time
lifted the sleeve of the dress and laid bare an ugly and painful wound
I had in the forearm.

The priest went on as a poppy, and turning his head quickly, he replied
tartly looking at the tables of the confessional:

- Well, well ...
Let you ... It seems excessive, indeed ... Henceforth refrain from
do such penance without first talking to your confessor.

III

At eight o'clock in the evening after having dinner with D. Miguel
and have seen him retire to bed in the sweet company of flintlock
pistols, P. Gil left the rectory to toward the house of his protector
Ms Eloisa Montesinos.

Rarely went to the gathering that it met at night. Neither was happy about it, nor the severe
regime of the priest's house I consented. But her protector had complained of neglect, until
he thought he was cooler with it. Fearful of being branded as ungrateful and really sorry, because
he professed tender and respectful affection for the kind lady, resolviose to go more often,
making and submit to the pastor.

The strong shower water hit his face as he set foot outside the door. Opened the umbrella,
but a few steps, the wind was blowing gale in the Field of Fainting
it again.

Unable to close it and feeling violently pushed by the hurricane, the young excuses refuge
in black, huge portal of Montesinos. Never went past it without feeling a shiver of fear and curiosity.
Lived in that gloomy palace a mysterious man who had vaguely thousand strange stories, to whom were
attributed outrageous ideas and phrases in addition to religion and its ministers. The young cleric
just knew him. D. Alvaro Montesinos had spent most of his life in Madrid. For two or three years
only he had come to settle on rocks. He lived in an almost total withdrawal, occasional walking
rarely by the sea, all alone. The remaining days I spent locked up at home, it was said, reading
or writing articles wicked. The Peñascosa clergy spoke of him with contempt spiteful, which
had come to participate Fr Gil, without knowing.

Arranged his umbrella as best he could, and as the impetus the wind had calmed down instantly
went out of the portal, but not one look of fear and hostility to the huge black door the fund, on top
of which sadly burned an oil lamp behind a window gated.

He left the field of fainting and, once in Quadrant Street (which thus called the single largest and
most populated of rocks), and the wind was not blowing so hard and was able to take advantage
umbrella and get home of Ms. Eloisa, located in the square without seriously wet. The D. purple Martín
de las Casas was also old, but remarkably renovated more girl than her brother, with all facilities
and supplies required by the needs Modern: tiles portal gate, well carved poplar staircase with banisters
of patent, elegant rooms with friezes and papers, all very neat and Painted.

- Good eyes see you, father! How expensive is sold! - Ms. Eloisa said that since her protected had
received holy orders not tuteaba.

At the same time he rose and kissed his hand with real affection. So did Mrs. Rita Obdulia, who had
recently was assiduous gathering of the house, and Mrs. Marcelina
Serafina Barrado, despite the sidelong glance he directed his chaplain
D. Joaquín.

Ms Marciala and Mrs. Filomena became the distracted talking to D. Peregrin Casanova, and saluted
the order from his seat, smiling rosy.

While greetings lasted, D. Narciso, who was leaning back to the piano, no his eyes off his
companion, eyes where they read aversion and suspicion.

Without the P. Gil is the cause or even give good account of it, there was lively rivalry between
him and D. Narciso, who had started more than half of the daughters of confession. Well God
knew he had done nothing to get it, before, on the contrary, it weighed heavily each Once
one of them came to his confessional. But what he had to do? Nothing but confess, it was his obligation.
Insist that do not vary much as a confessor was granted too much importance to the issue of person:
he was not in the spirit of the sacrament. But the chaplain was not penetrated Sarrió the intention
of his partner, and whether was not much altered her feelings. Thus compatible with the result,
and it was sad him. Before the arrival of Gil field it can be said that only among the fair sex
of Peñascosa and ruled their consciences. Other chaplains did not shadow. It was the golden
boy of the pious. None of their jokes, their steps and gestures go unnoticed: the devout who had
the good fortune to hear or witness them, were responsible for distributing it quickly among her
friends. A damning evidence every moment of lively sympathy and veneration awakening in the village:
chasubles gifts of embroidery by fingers gorgeous body, the clerical collar of satin, etc.,
etc., offering even more positive, hams, bottles of sherry cakes and chocolate. D. Narciso was
admirably covered their spiritual needs and temporary. He was a shepherd, tending his sheep
happily, leading them gently the path of virtue to paradise and shearing from time to time the
rich fleece to not entangled in a thicket.

The appearance of your new companion came to breaking on the Arcadia delicious mystique. Sheep
sudden rush of insane excitement, began to jump and prance as if listen the happy sound of a pipe.
Neither Peter nor the blandishments managed to retain a most of them.

He was painting his flock, and he had had the strength to govern a herd that large, faint now to
be alone, sensing the hostility with which I watched some of their old and beloved sheep. For
not only no longer reached home the rich gifts overseas and nationals of other times, but
with deep felt pain that was beginning to discutírsele. It was said among the pious ladies,
and this came his ears, that if it was true that word was easier for the young toilets, most
of the time "there was no substance in what he said," and he preceded him much weight, natural
reason and instruction. There were times when throwing one of his jokes spicy, linked as always
with feces, barely produced laughter among listeners, and knew that one of them after he left,
he had been rude and poorly qualified educated. Of the body because there was no talking, well
it never reached could compete with the delicate and graceful figure of his opponent. In summary,
D. Narciso felt undermined the foundation and feared every moment to come to the floor. No wonder,
then, that the look and the greeting that welcomed the young priest were less affectionate
than be expected. Not remember little or much the kind reception that San Juan Bautista, master
held dear, and God made the young disciple who was soon eclipsed.

- Do not fights, women. Do you know, by chance, if it's easy to go out at night, with fear
that D. Miguel has to thieves? - Shouted D. Martín de las Casas from the triplet table where
he played with two others, a priest and a layman.

- No, sir, not that - "the cleric said, blushing under the eyes of the entire gathering.

- Did not have D. Miguel fear of robbers? - Asked smugly sharp focus
the Mr. de las Casas.

- Yes it is - the young man replied, smiling
sweetly, sitting at the same time next her godmother .-- Their reasons
will be.

The rich are those who fear. The poor, like me, are alone.

- But what will the priest as much money as they say? - Ms Marciala
asked curiously.

- I can not tell you, lady ... I presume so, because
it addresses a lot to his estate.

Their costs are small, and instead of increasing each day is restricted. Where to go long and
leaves little choice but to not have done plenty.

- The rights parish should produce a lot, right? - Asked even more
curious the wife of the apothecary of the square.

- You understand
that in a parish as large as it should not be short.

- But D. Miguel
forgive many of them - said the lady, with a slight turning comic
in his voice.

- It's possible, ma'am.

For my part, I have not seen - answered with perfect simplicity the toilet.

D. Narciso D. Joaquin, the chaplain of Madame de Barrado, exchanged
a meaningful glance.

The chaplain was a thin young man with roses in her cheeks, a sign
of a temper sickly, living and insolent eyes, thin nose, small mouth,
a hypocritical fold and malicious.

It had been a Dona Serafina testicles stuck at home to run errands and serve at the table, soon
after being widowed.

Noting the readiness and fond of him once transferred his residence
to Lancia, gave career, sending the seminar.

In the hours left him free lessons, Joaquín continued to play his
trade as a servant.

Then he took orders made him his manager, today was his feet and hands. Do not hit the streets
but in his company, was her spiritual director and counselor time. Curious spectacle indeed the
sudden transformation of a domestic master of his own love. It was you you always called him
D. Joachim and, publicly at least, he lavished a thousand samples respect, also forcing the
servants to tax.

Ms Eloisa reiterated, asking gentle accents:

- So what is the reason for his withdrawal, rogue?

- Madam, I understand that Mr Miguel does not like much to go out
at night, but the main This is because most of the days I am tired
... As I get up at four in the morning!

... Sometimes need a little prayer ...

- You work too, father - said Marcelina, a young unmarried girl who, in the words of the people,
already was nearing forty, ugly, leathery, very skillful hands and not a little also language
.-- So many hours of confessional! ... And then the sick!

...

- Not counting the hours he spends on his knees in prayer ...-- Obdulia
said shyly.

After to drop the phrase blushed.

D. Narciso thrust a unique look, ironic and aggressive, that she could not see, because it put
an effort into not looking face to face with his former confessor.

Fr Gil made an impatient, annoyed by those accolades, and to divert the conversation of his person,
he faced one of those who played the triplet.

- Mr Director, I have seen today from the rectory with the rod out
a very fat fish.

For Admittedly, I thought a mullet, and D. Miguel a robaliza. We played a little.

- The priest has a better view than you. A robaliza era - said the
gentleman seriously questioned, without looking up the charts.

This D. Romualdo Director was an old man with a mustache and short
white whiskers, sallow color, the brow furrowed with deep wrinkles,
large eyes, severe eyelid drooping.

No never smiled.

Constantly spoke with an accent in a bad mood, as a man disenchanted with everything.

- The Mullets do not fall into the spring, Don Gil of the green tights - uttered the lord of Houses
with his usual rudeness, if not rude.

I used to call it, jokingly, to his former protected.

- Yes down just, D. Martin of the White House - he uttered a dull voice director.

The pundits laughed, which piqued somewhat D. Martin, Male, as we know, prone irritated.

- I thought so, Minister of mischief - sarcastically replied, looking
intently at his face, and putting on the table at the same time a
king of hearts.

- So you thought very wrong - the old man replied,
his eyes always on the cards .-- Also did you think that king of hearts
would happen triumphant, y. .. you see, the bug!

- That'll make you
it is a rude and bad habits acquired back in Manchester.

Here the insurance Norberto father had not done.

- No, no! I am unable ...-- the priest said, choking with laughter,
coughing up .-- No burst Peñascosa I left ... What I do is shrink
and take that point of gold from my partner.

He put forward a four.

- Hooray for the cure! - Roared D. Martin, throwing the horse and picking the trick.

- Dude, I thought D. Martin did not have the horse - sighed D. Norberto, addressing Councillor eyes
in anguish.

- What did you think it is a babieca and has been all his life - he
said with affected naturally which shone through anger.

- But the
man of God !...-- said the cleric, ready to give explanations.

Counselor interrupted with angry gesture, firmly placing the cards face down on the table.

-
Man of the devil! I say ... How do you think of running a point not being covered? ...

Armos a violent dispute that lasted a few moments. The Advisor and P. Norberto no dragged on too
long, because he, a man of good pasta, phlegmatic, he concluded to remain silent shrugging
his shoulders with resignation and while shaking his head in silent protest. Those that were on
forever with D. Advisor Martin, both of which more irascible and stubborn.

D. Martín de las Casas, retired lieutenant colonel, who had made the war in Cuba, where had received
a wound in the shoulder that prevented him from continuing in service, is believed the case for
his profession, take it all for the tremendous. Since 1873 when it became the body of Invalids
did not come out of rocks. At that time had forty two years. His
wife was glad that forced retirement, but deplored that came to within
family with a cotton shoulder. Regarded as a virtue exalted, unique
to the military same energy in the field of battle that drinking coffee
in the casino. Their disputes, their bluffs in the recreation center
were proverbial in Peñascosa and slapping it used distributed at the
end of them too. Since the arrival of the tremendous Lt. Col. any
neighbor for serious and respectable as it was, was safe. Many nobles
and wealthy landowners of the village which until then had been kept
immaculate his cheeks, never dreamed that anyone could threatening
to them, were sealed and initialed the most neglected when the fingers
were the fierce invalid. This was due to a slow reflux among his friends
and acquaintances, which warmly received on his return from service</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>