<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05189</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>349523</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21968</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Esta señora, mucho más joven que Clementina, era no obstante su íntima amiga, el confidente
de sus secretos. Comía tres o cuatro veces a la semana con ella, y raro era el día que no salían
juntas a paseo. No podía llamársela hermosa; pero su fisonomía tenía tal animación, sus ojos
brillaban con tanta gracia y su boca se plegaba con tal malicia al sonreír dejando ver unos
dientes de ratón blancos y menudos, que siempre había tenido muchos adoradores. De soltera
fué una coquetuela redomada: trajo al retortero los hombres, gozando en acapararlos todos,
prodigando las mismas sonrisas insinuantes, idénticas miradas abrasadoras al hijo de un duque
que a un empleadillo de ocho mil reales, al viejo de venerable calva y nariz arremolachada
que al mancebo de veinte años gallardo y apuesto, al rico como al pobre, al noble como al plebeyo.
Su coquetería, parecida en esto al amor de Jesucristo a la humanidad, igualaba todas las castas,
todos los estados, unía a los hombres en santa fraternidad para participar del fuego admirable
de sus ojos negros, de unos hoyitos muy lindos que formaban sus mejillas al reir y de otra
multitud de dones y frutos con que la providencia de Dios la había dotado. Después de casada,
seguía mostrando la misma entrañable benevolencia hacia el género humano, si bien de un modo
más sucesivo, esto es, un hombre después de otro o, a lo sumo, de dos en dos. Su marido era
un mejicano rico con rasgos de indio en la fisonomía.

Poco después que éstos entró en el salón Fuentes, un hombrecillo vivaracho, feo, raquítico,
bastante marcado por las viruelas. Nadie sabía de qué vivía: suponíansele algunas rentas. Frecuentaba
todos los salones de algún viso de la corte y se sentaba a las mesas mejor provistas. Sus títulos
para ello eran los de pasar por hombre de animada y chispeante conversación, ingenioso y agradable.
Más de veinte años hacía que Fuentes venía alegrando las comidas y los saraos de la capital,
desempeñando en ellos el papel de primer actor cómico. Algunos de sus chistes habían llegado
a ser proverbiales; repetíanse no sólo en los salones sino en las mesas de los cafés, y hasta
llegaban a las provincias. Contra lo que suele suceder en esta clase de hombres no era maldiciente.
Sus chistes no tendían a herir a las personas, sino a alegrar el concurso y obligarle a admirar
lo fácil, lo vivo y lo sutil de su ingenio. Todo lo más que se autorizaba era apoderarse de
las ridiculeces de algún amigo ausente y formar sobre ellas una frase graciosa; pero nunca
o casi nunca a costa de la honra. Estas cualidades le habían hecho el ídolo de las tertulias.
Ninguna se consideraba completa si Fuentes no daba al menos una vueltecita por ella.

--¡Oh, Fuentes! ¡Oh, Fuentes!--gritaron todos viéndole aparecer.

Y una porción de manos se extendieron para saludarle. Apretando las primeras que llegaron a
chocar con la suya se dirigió desde luego a la señora de la casa, con voz cascada que ayudaba
mucho al efecto cómico, diciendo:

--Perdone usted, Clementina, si llego con un poco de retraso. Viniendo acá me cogió por su
cuenta Perales, ya sabe usted ¡Perales!, no tengo más que decir. Luego, cuando pude desprenderme
de sus manos, ahí en la esquina del ministerio de la Guerra, caí en las manos del conde de
Sotolargo, y ése ya sabe usted que es pesado con un cincuenta por ciento de recargo.

--¿Por qué?--se apresuró a preguntar Lola Madariaga.

--Porque es tartamudo, señora.

Los convidados rieron, algunos a carcajadas; otros más discretamente. La frase venía preparada:
se conocía a la legua; pero así y todo produjo el efecto apetecido, parte porque en efecto
había hecho gracia, parte también porque todo el mundo se creía en el deber de ponerse risueño
en cuanto Fuentes abría la boca.

Un instante después un criado de librea abrió de par en par las puertas del salón, diciendo
en alta voz:

--La señora está servida.

Osorio se apresuró a ofrecer el brazo a la baronesa de Rag y rompió la marcha hacia el comedor
seguido de todos los convidados. Cerrando la comitiva iba el barón conduciendo a Clementina.

Los criados esperaban puestos en fila con la servilleta al brazo, capitaneados por el maître.
Osorio fué designando a cada invitado su puesto. No tardaron en acomodarse todos. La mesa ofrecía
un aspecto elegante, armonioso. La luz, que caía de dos grandes lámparas con reflectores, hacía
resaltar los vivos colores de las flores y las frutas, la blancura del mantel, el brillo del
cristal y la porcelana. Sin embargo, esta luz, demasiado cruda, hace daño a la belleza de las
damas, las desfigura como un aparato fotográfico. Para templarla y producir una iluminación
suave y normal, Clementina hacía colocar dos candelabros con numerosas bujías a los extremos
de la mesa. Todas las señoras estaban más o menos descotadas: alguna, como Pepa Frías, escandalosamente.
Los caballeros, de frac y corbata blanca.

La conversación fué en los primeros momentos particular: cada cual hablaba con su vecino. La
baronesa de Rag, una belga de pelo castaño y ojos claros, bastante gruesa, preguntaba a Osorio
los nombres de los objetos que había sobre la mesa. Hacía poco tiempo que estaba en España
y apetecía con ansiedad conocer el castellano. Clementina y el barón hablaban en francés. Pepa
Frías, que estaba entre Pepe Castro y Jiménez Arbós, le dijo al primero por lo bajo:

--¿Qué le parece a usted de la jeta del marido de Lola? ¿verdad que para gaucho no es del todo
mala?

Castro sonrió con la superioridad que le caracterizaba.

--Sí, debió de haber lazado muchas vacas en la pampa.

--Hasta que al fin una vaca le lazó a él.

--Pero no fué en la pampa.

--Ya sé: en los jardinillos: no me diga usted nada.

El general Patiño, fiel a su naturaleza y a su tradición militar, se desplegó en guerrilla
para atacar a la marquesa de Ujo, que tenía al lado.

--Marquesa, las perlas le sientan admirablemente. Un cutis suave y levemente bronceado como
el de usted, donde se transparenta toda la savia y todo el fuego del mediodía, exige el adorno
oriental por excelencia.

--Usted tan lisonjero como siempre, general. Me pongo las perlas porque es lo mejor que tengo.
Su tuviese unas esmeraldas tan hermosas como Clementina, dejaría las perlas en sus estuches--respondió
la dama, mostrando al sonreír unos dientes bastante desvencijados donde brillaba en algunos
puntos el oro del dentista.

--Haría usted mal. Las mujeres hermosas están en la obligación de ponerse lo que les va mejor.
Dios quiere que sus obras maestras se manifiesten en todo su esplendor. Las esmeraldas sientan
bien a las linfáticas; pero usted es como la uva de Jerez, doradita por fuera y guardando en
el corazón un licor que marea y embriaga.

--¡Si dijera usted como una pasa!

--¡Oh, no, marquesa! ¡oh, no!...

Y el general rechazó con fuego la especie y empleó toda su elocuencia en desbaratarla como
si tuviese delante un ejército enemigo.

Mientras tanto los criados comenzaban a dar vuelta a la mesa presentando los platos. Otros,
con la botella en la mano, murmuraban al oído de los invitados: Sauterne, Jerez, Margaux, en
un tono cavernoso semejante al que emplean los cartujos para recordarse mutuamente la muerte.

--Yo no bebo más que champagne frappé hasta el fin--dijo Pepa Frías al que tenía detrás.

--¡Cuánto calor, Pepa, cuánto calor!--exclamó Castro.

--No lo sabe usted bien--repuso la viuda con entonación maliciosa.

--Por desgracia.

--O por fortuna. ¿Está usted ya cansado de Clementina?

Fuentes no se encontraba bien con aquel cuchicheo. Le dolía desperdiciar su ingenio en conversación
particular, para una sola persona. Asió la primera ocasión por los cabellos para levantar la
voz y atraerse la atención de los comensales.

--Ayer le he visto a usted por la mañana en la carrera de San Jerónimo, Fuentes--le dijo la
condesa de Cotorraso que estaba tres o cuatro puestos más allá.

--Según a lo que usted llame mañana, condesa.

--Serían las once, poco más o menos.

--Entonces, permítame usted que lo dude, porque hasta las dos estoy siempre en la cama.

--¡Oh, hasta las dos!--exclamaron varios.

--Eso ya es una exageración, Fuentes--dijo la marquesa de Alcudia.

--Pero es una exageración aristocrática, marquesa. ¿Quién se levanta primero en Madrid? Los
barrenderos, los mozos de cuerda, los pinches de cocina. Un poco más tarde encontrará usted
a los horteras abriendo las tiendas, alguna vieja que va a oir misa, lacayos que salen a pasear
los caballos, etc. Luego empiezan a salir los empleaditos de las casas de comercio y los escribientes
de las oficinas del Estado que llevan todo el peso de ellas, las modistillas, etc., etc. A
las once ya hallará usted gente más distinguida, oficiales del ejército, estudiantes, empleados
de tres mil pesetas, corredores de comercio, etc. A las doce comienzan a salir los peces gordos,
los jefes de negociado, los banqueros, algunos propietarios; pero sólo después de las dos de
la tarde podrá usted ver en la calle a los ministros, a los directores generales, a los títulos
de Castilla, a los grandes literatos....

Los comensales escuchaban embelesados aquella ingeniosa defensa de la pereza y se creían en
el caso de reir y decirse unos a otros por lo bajo:

--¡Este Fuentes! ¡oh! ¡este Fuentes tiene la gracia de Dios!

Y alguno, por el placer de oirle nada más, le llevaba la contraria.

--Pero hombre, ¿habrá nada más agradable que levantarse por la mañana a respirar el aire puro
y bañarse con la luz del sol?

--Prefiero bañarme en agua tibia con una botellita de Kananga.

--¿Me negará usted que el sol es hermoso?

--Es hermoso, pero un poco cursilón. Yo no digo que allá al principio del mundo no fuese una
cosa asombrosa, digna de verse; pero ustedes comprenderán que ahora está anticuado. ¿Hay nada
más ridículo en una época tan positivista como la presente que llamarse Febo y gastar cabellera
de oro? Además, el sol no tiene mérito alguno intrínseco. Está ahí ardiendo porque Dios lo
ha puesto. Pero la luz del gas, la luz eléctrica representan el esfuerzo de un hombre de genio,
es el triunfo de la inteligencia, hace recordar nuestro poder sobre la materia, la soberanía
del espíritu en todo el Universo.... Luego--añadió bajando un poco la voz--, al sol se le puede
ver sin que cueste dinero, y yo siempre he aborrecido los espectáculos gratis.

Los comensales no cesaban de reir. Fuentes, animado por aquellas risas, se desbordaba en paradojas,
en frases ingeniosas y sutiles, cayendo a ojos vistas en el amaneramiento. Le pasaba lo que
a los grandes actores demasiado aplaudidos. No sabía contenerse a tiempo y entraba al fin en
el terreno de la extravagancia. De aquí a lo insulso no hay más que un paso, y Fuentes lo daba
con frecuencia.

El conde de Cotorraso persistía en defender al astro del día para excitar el ingenio de su
detractor. El sol era quien animaba la Naturaleza, quien calentaba nuestro cuerpo aterido, etc.

--Eso de que el sol produzca animación, lo niego--replicaba Fuentes--; Madrid está mucho más
animado por la noche que por el día, y para calentarme prefiero el cok, que no ocasiona tabardillos....
Vamos a ver, conde, fíjese bien: ¿qué mérito puede tener una cosa que a la fuerza ha de ver
siempre su lacayo primero que usted?

Como alguien dijera riendo que Fuentes tenía "buena sombra", éste replicó vivamente:

--¿Lo ve usted, conde? Hasta para decir que un hombre tiene gracia se dice que tiene buena
sombra. A nadie se le ocurre decir que tiene buen sol.

Y con motivo de las sombras se habló de la del manzanillo. La marquesa de Ujo preguntó al mejicano,
marido de Lola, si en su país había manzanillos. Ballesteros, que así se llamaba, replicó que
no, pero que había visto muchos en el Brasil. La marquesa se informó con viva curiosidad de
las particularidades del árbol; pero quedó sumamente disgustada cuando el mejicano le dijo
que la sombra no mataba y que sólo su fruto desprendía un agua corrosiva.

--¿De modo que durmiendo debajo de él no se muere?

--Señora, yo no he dormido ¿sabe?; pero he almorsado con varios amigo debaho de uno y no nos
ha pasao ná.

--Entonces, ¿cómo se suicida Sélika en La Africana acostándose a la sombra de ese árbol?

--Eso es una patraña, una invensión de los poeta ¿sabe? Será una cosa bonita, pero no tiene
nada de verdá.

La marquesa, desencantada por aquel dato realista, no quiso salir de su poética creencia; arguyó
que tal vez los manzanillos de la India fuesen distintos de los del Brasil.

Hablóse de las producciones de Méjico.

--¿Es verdad que usted posee ochocientas mil vacas, Ballesteros?--preguntó Clementina.

--¡Oh, señora; eso es una exagerasión! A lo sumo que llegará mi rebaño es a tresientas mil.

--Si fuesen mías--dijo Fuentes--, construiría un estanque mayor que el del Retiro, lo llenaría
de leche y navegaría por él.

--Nosotro no utilisamo la leche, señor, ni la manteca tampoco. La carne alguna vese la convertimo
en tasaho ¿sabe? y la esportamo. Mas por lo regulá sólo sacamo partido de las piele ¿sabe?
Los cuerno también los vendemo para la fabricación de los objeto de asta.

--¡Que te quemas! ¡que te quemas!--exclamó Pepe Castro por lo bajo.

Pero no tanto que no lo oyese Jiménez Arbós, que estaba del otro lado de Pepa Frías, y no le
acometiese un acceso de risa que procuró con todas sus fuerzas sofocar.

--Anda, barbiana, alárgame ese frasquito de mostaza--dijo Pepa Frías dirigiéndose a Clementina
para disimular también la risa que le había acometido.

--Bajbiana, bajbiana.... ¿Qué es que bajbiana?--preguntó, la baronesa de Rag a Osorio en su
afán de aprender pronto el español.

Este se apresuró a explicárselo como pudo.

Pepa hablaba de vez en cuando por lo bajo con Jiménez Arbós. Solían ser algunas frases rápidas
que probaban la inteligencia en que estaban y al mismo tiempo el deseo de mostrarse prudentes.
La conversación con Pepe Castro, que tenía a su izquierda, era más animada.

--¿Por qué no aconseja usted a Arbós que coma más carne?--le preguntaba el lechuguino al oído.

--¿Para qué?

--Para lo que se come carne generalmente; para nutrirse y adquirir fuerzas con que soportar
las fatigas que nuestros deberes nos imponen.

--¡Ya!--exclamó la viuda con entonación irónica--. Mire usted por sí y deje a los demás arreglar
sus cuentas como Dios les dé a entender.

--Ya ve usted que procuro nutrirme.

--Sí, pero que vaya un poco también al cerebro, porque el día menos pensado se cae usted en
la calle de tonto.

--¿Se ha ofendido usted?--preguntó riendo el elegante como si hubiese dicho la cosa más descabellada
del mundo.

--No, hombre, no: es que lo creo así. No entiendo cómo Clementina puede sufrir semejante narciso.

--¡Chis, chis! ¡Prudencia, Pepa, prudencia!--exclamó Castro con susto, levantando los ojos
hacia su querida.

--¿Sabe usted que disimula muy bien? No la he visto dirigirle a usted una sola mirada hasta ahora.

Castro, que hacía días estaba un poco despechado por la frialdad de su dueño, sonrió forzadamente
frunciendo en seguida el entrecejo. A Pepa no le pasó inadvertido este gesto.

--Mire usted qué cara tan nublada tiene en este momento Osorio. ¡Inspira horror! Y toda la
culpa la tiene usted, pícaro.

--¡Yo! Nada de eso. Deben de ser cuestiones de guita las que le ponen tan amarillo. Me han
dicho que está arruinado o muy próximo a arruinarse.

Pepa se estremeció visiblemente.

--¿Qué dice usted? ¿Por dónde ha sabido usted eso?

--Pues me lo han dicho ya varios.

La viuda se volvió bruscamente hacia Jiménez Arbós sin ocultar su agitación y le preguntó en
voz baja y alterada:

--¿Has oído algo de que Osorio esté arruinado?

--Sí, lo he oído. Osorio viene jugando a la baja hace tiempo y los fondos se empeñan en subir--respondió
el estadista levantando la cabeza con gesto petulante de pavo real.

En el tono con que pronunció estas palabras se advertía satisfacción. Para un ministro, jugar
a la baja es siempre un crimen digno de castigo.

--Yo no sé lo que tendrá comprometido en esta liquidación; pero si es mucho está perdido, porque
el consolidado ha subido un entero. Y si se empeña en no liquidar inmediatamente, a fin de
mes puede tener muy bien dos enteros de alza.

Todo el buen humor de Pepa había desaparecido de repente. Bajó la cabeza y dejó caer el tenedor
sin ánimo para concluir el trozo de jamón de York que se había puesto. El ministro, observando
su silencio y su tristeza, le preguntó:

--¿Tienes por casualidad fondos en su poder?

--Por casualidad, no ... ¡por estupidez mía! Tiene en su mano casi toda mi fortuna.

--¡Oh diablo, diablo!

--Se me está haciendo rejalgar en el cuerpo lo que he comido. Creo que me voy a poner mala--dijo
la viuda poniéndose realmente pálida.

Arbós hizo esfuerzos por tranquilizarla. Tal vez no fuese cierto todo. En las ruinas como en
las fortunas improvisadas se exagera siempre mucho. Además, si algún compromiso había sagrado
para Osorio, debía ser el de ella, una dama que le confía su dinero por pura amistad.

Aunque hablaban en falsete, sus fisonomías graves y sus ademanes decididos llamaron la atención
del general Patiño, el cual, con admirable penetración, dijo a la marquesa de Ujo:

--Mire usted a Pepa y a Arbós. Hay nube de verano entre ellos. ¡Qué hermoso es el amor hasta
en sus fugaces tormentas!

Mientras tanto, los condes de Cotorraso, Lola Madariaga, Clementina y los barones de Rag hablaban
del arsénico como medicamento para engordar y poner terso y brillante el cutis. Lola Madariaga
era la primera vez que lo oía y se mostraba llena de júbilo, y anunciaba que iba inmediatamente
a ensayar la virtud milagrosa del veneno.

--¡Dios mío, Lolita!--exclamó Fuentes--. Si usted, como es ahora, causa tales estragos en los
corazones masculinos, ¡qué va a suceder cuando lleve cuatro o cinco meses con un régimen de
arsénico! Señor Ballesteros, no consienta usted que lo tome: es tratarnos con demasiada crueldad.

--Vamos, amigo Fuentes--repuso la graciosa morena dirigiendo una mirada insinuante a Castro,
porqué se le había metido en la cabeza arrancársele a Clementina--¿me quiere usted tomar el pelo?

--¡Tomaj el pelo!... ¿Qué es que tomaj el pelo?--preguntó la baronesa de Rag a Osorio.

A esta baronesa la estaba desvistiendo con la imaginación Bonifacio, contemplándola desde lejos
sin pestañear. Hacía días que había comprado entre otras fotografías obscenas la de una mujer
desnuda meciéndose en una hamaca. Se le antojaba que la baronesa se parecía mucho a aquella
mujer, y trataba de averiguar, por medio de un prolijo examen exterior, si interiormente guardaría
la misma semejanza.

Terminó al fin la comida no sin dedicar, por supuesto, un buen rato de conversación al teatro
Real, a Gayarre y a la Tosti. No la hubieran digerido bien si les faltase. El café, como era
costumbre en casa de Osorio, se sirvió en el mismo comedor. Luego, las señoras con algunos
hombres se fueron al salón. Otros se quedaron fumando, pero no tardaron en ir a reunirse con
los demás. Hacía allí un calor insufrible.

Pepe Castro aprovechó la confusión de la salida para preguntar a Clementina:

--¿Cómo no has ido esta mañana?

Clementina detuvo el paso, le miró con sonrisa protectora.

--¿Esta mañana?... No sé.

--¿Cómo no sabes?--dijo frunciendo su augusta frente el real mozo.

--No sé; no sé--y dió un paso para alejarse sin dejar de sonreír con leve matiz de burla.

--¿Y mañana irás?

--Veremos--respondió alejándose.

Castro sintió aquella sonrisa como un golpe en medio del pecho. Se mordió el labio inferior
y murmuró:--¿Coqueteamos, eh? ¡Ya me la pagarás, hermosa!

En el salón había ya algunas personas, entre ellas Ramón Maldonado y la hija de Pepa Frías
con su marido. En otro saloncito contiguo estaban preparadas hasta seis mesas de tresillo.
Algunos se sentaron desde luego a jugar. Otros esperaron a que llegasen los compañeros de costumbre.
No tardaron, en efecto, en poblarse entrambos salones. Llegó D. Julián Calderón con Mariana
y Esperancita, Cobo Ramírez con León Guzmán y otros tres o cuatro pollastres, el general Pallarés,
los marqueses de Veneros y otras varias personas, entre las cuales predominaban los banqueros
y hombres de negocios.

Uno de los últimos en llegar fué el duque de Requena, a quien se hizo la misma acogida ruidosa
y lisonjera que en todas partes. Entró jadeando, fumando, escupiendo, con la seguridad insolente
que su inmensa fortuna le había hecho adquirir. Hablaba poco, reía menos; emitía sus opiniones
con rudeza y se dejaba adorar del corro de señoras que le rodeaba. Tenía las mejillas más amoratadas
que nunca, los ojos sanguinolentos, los labios negros. Estaba tan feo, que Fuentes dijo a Pinedo
y a Jiménez Arbós señalándole:

--Ahí tienen ustedes al diablo recibiendo a sus brujas en el aquelarre de los sábados.

Se le invitó a jugar al tresillo como siempre; pero rehusó. Había visto a dos banqueros a quienes
quería pescar para su negocio de la mina de Riosa. Además le convenía hacer la corte a Jiménez
Arbós algunos momentos. Ya había conseguido que la mina saliese a subasta con todos sus accesorios
de montes y pertenencias. En la Gaceta se había insertado el anuncio. La compañía para comprarla
estaba ya formada. Pero entre los socios había desavenencia. Unos pretendían comprarla al contado
(entre ellos estaba Salabert) y otros querían aprovechar los diez plazos que el Gobierno concedía.
La diferencia en la tasación de una a otra forma, era enorme.

El duque se acercó a Biggs, el representante de una casa inglesa que entraba con parte muy
considerable en la compañía y que capitaneaba el partido de la compra a plazos. Le echó familiarmente
el brazo sobre el hombro y le llevó al hueco de un balcón, diciéndole con rudeza:

--¿Conque ustedes empeñados en que nos arruinemos?

Y comenzó a tratar el asunto con una franqueza que desconcertó al inglés. Este respondía a
las salidas brutales del duque con razonamientos corteses y suaves, sonriendo siempre benévolamente.
El duque acentuaba su rudeza, que en el fondo era muy diplomática.

--Yo no tengo gana de tirar mi dinero. Me ha costado mucho trabajo adquirirlo, ¿sabe usted?
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08737</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>249415</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19571</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> This
lady, much younger than Clementina, was nonetheless his close friend, confidant of its secrets.
Ate three or four times a week with her, and rare was the day I did not leave walk together. I could
not call it beautiful, but her face was so animated, his eyes shone with such grace and folded
her mouth with such malice smile revealing a teeth and tiny white mouse, who had always had
many admirers. Maiden was a downright coquetuela: retortero brought the men, enjoying in monopolize
all lavishing the same smiles landslides, scorching looks identical to the son of a duke that
a clerk of eight thousand reais, the venerable old bald nose arremolachada that the young man
of twenty gallant and handsome, the rich and the poor, the noble and the commoner. His flirtation,
like in this love of Jesus Christ to mankind, matched all castes, all states, joined in holy men of
the fire community to take part admirable their dark eyes, a very cute dimples that made her cheeks
to laugh and other multitude of gifts and fruits with which the providence of God had endowed.
After getting married, still showed the same affectionate kindness to mankind, but in a way
more thereafter, that is, a man after another or, at most, two by two. Her husband was a Mexican
Indian rich with features of the physiognomy.

Shortly after they entered the room Fuentes, a dapper man, ugly, stunted,
quite marked by smallpox.

No one knew what lived: suponíansele some rents. Frequented all classrooms in some semblance
of the court and sat at the table better supplied. Their titles for it was the man going through lively
and sparkling conversation, witty and enjoyable. Over twenty years ago had been cheering Fuentes
meals and evening parties in the capital them play the leading role comedian. Some of his jokes had
come to be proverbial; repetíanse not only in classrooms but in the tables of the cafes, and
even came to the provinces. Contrary to what usually happens in this class of men was not cursing.
His jokes did not tend to hurt people, but to brighten up the contest and force you to admire
easy, the living and subtle wit. Everything else was authorized to seize the absurdities of some absent
friend and training on them a funny phrase, but never or almost never at the expense of honor.
These qualities had made him the idol of the gatherings. None was considered complete if Fuentes
was at least a walk around it.

- Oh, Sources! Oh, Fuentes! - They shouted when he saw him appear.

And a lot of hands reached out to greet him. Pressing the first that came to colliding with
it went from then to the lady of the house, cracked voice that helped much to the comic effect,
saying:

- Excuse me, Clementina, if I'm a little late. Coming here took me by the account Perales, Perales
you know!, I have nothing to say. Then when I let go their hands, one on the corner of the
Ministry of War, fell into the hands of Count Sotolargo, and that
you know that is heavy with a fifty cent surcharge.

- Why? - Was
quick to ask Lola Madariaga.

- Because it is stuttering, ma'am.

The guests laughed, some out loud, others more discreetly. The phrase came prepared: known to the
league, but they still produced the desired effect, partly because in effect had been amused,
partly because everyone believed in the duty to be cheerful Fuentes as he opened his mouth.

A moment later a servant in livery opened wide the doors of the hall, saying aloud:

- The lady is served.

Osorio was quick to offer his arm to the Baroness of Rag and broke
up the march to the dining room followed by all the guests.

Closing the convoy was driving Baron Clementina.

The servants waited in ranks with his napkin on his arm, led by the maître. Osorio was appointed
to his post each guest. Soon they accommodate everyone. The board offered an elegant, harmonious.
The light falling from two lamps with reflectors, was highlight the bright colors of the flowers
and fruits, the white tablecloth, the brightness of glass and porcelain. However, this light,
too harsh, hurts the beauty of ladies, disfigured as a camera. To tune and produce a light smooth
and normal, Clementina was placing two candlesticks with candles to the ends of many the table. All the
ladies were more or less low-cut: some, like Pepa Frias, loudly.

The gentlemen in tails and white tie.

The conversation was at first particular: each spoke with his neighbor. The Baroness Rag, a
Belgian brown hair and eyes, rather thick, asked Osorio the names of the objects on the table.
Short time ago I was in Spain and eagerly wanted to know Castilian.

Clemence and the Baron spoke in French. Pepa Frias, who was among Arbós Pepe Castro and Jimenez,
told the first in a low

- What do you think of the snout of the
husband of Lola?

Gaucho is it that is not entirely bad?

Castro smiled with superiority that characterized him.

- Yes, must
have roped a lot of cows in the pampa.

- Until finally he lassoed
a cow to him.

- But it was in the pampa.

- I know: in the little
gardens: you do not tell me anything.

The general Patiño, true to their nature and military tradition, was deployed in guerrilla
to attack the Marquise de Ujo, beside him.

- Marquise, pearls will feel wonderfully. A soft, slightly tanned skin as yours, that reveals all
the sap and all the noon heat, requires trim East par excellence.

-
You so flattering as ever, general.

I wear pearls because it is the best I have. Its had about as beautiful as Clementina emeralds,
pearls leave in their cases - said the lady, showing teeth smile which shone quite dilapidated in some
Dentist gold points.

- Would you do wrong. Beautiful women are obliged to wear what they do best. God wants his masterpieces
are revealed in all its glory. Feel Emeralds While the lymph, but you're like the grapes of Jerez,
golden brown outside and saved heart a dizzying and intoxicating liquor.

- If you say you like a raisin!

- Oh, no, marquise! Oh, no! ...

And the general refused to fire the species and used all his eloquence to derail as if I were
faced with a hostile army.

Meanwhile the servants were beginning to turn the table presenting
the dishes.

Others with the bottle in his hand, whispering in the ears of the
guests: Sauterne, Sherry, Margaux, in cavernous tone similar to that
used by Carthusian monks to remind each other to death.

- I do not
drink more champagne frappe until the end - Pepa Frias said that behind
him.

- How much heat, Pepa, how hot! - Said Castro.

- Do not know
you well - "the widow with malicious intonation.

- Unfortunately.

-
Or fortunately.

Are you tired of Clementina?

Fuentes was not well with that whisper.

It hurt him to waste his wit in conversation particular, for a single person. He grabbed the first
opportunity by the hair to lift the voice and attract the attention of diners.

- Yesterday I have seen you in the morning in the Carrera de San Jerónimo, Fuentes - he said
Cotorraso Countess was three or four places beyond.

- According to what you call tomorrow, countess.

- It was about eleven
or so.

- So, permit me to doubt it, because until two am always in
bed.

- Oh, till two! - Cried several.

- That it is an exaggeration,
Fuentes - said the Marquise de Alcudia.

- But it is an exaggeration
aristocratic Marquise.

Who gets up first in Madrid? The sweepers, porters, the skewer.

A little later you find to opening the store clerks, some old woman
who goes to hear Mass, lackeys who go walking horses, etc. Then start
to get their empleaditos trading house and the clerks State offices
that carry the full weight of them, dressmakers, etc.., etc. A eleven
and you will find most distinguished people, army officers, students,
employees three thousand pesetas, brokers, etc. A noon start out the
big guns, negotiated leaders, bankers, some owners, but only after
two afternoon you can see on the street ministers, CEOs, to titles
Castilla, great writers ....

The guests listened spellbound this
ingenious defense of laziness and believed in For laugh and say to
each other in a low

- The Power!

Oh! This source has the grace of God!

And some, for the pleasure of hearing him nothing else, it had the opposite.

- But man, there's nothing nicer than getting up in the morning to breathe fresh air and bathe in sunlight?

-
I prefer to bathe in warm water with a bottle of Kananga.

- Can I deny you that the sun is beautiful?

- It's beautiful, but a little cursilón. I'm not saying there at the beginning of the world was
not a amazing thing, worth seeing, but you will understand that it
is now outdated.

Is there anything more ridiculous in an age so positivistic as this be called Phoebus and hair
spend Gold? In addition, the sun has no intrinsic merit.

It is there because God burning has set.

But the light of gas, electricity represent the effort of a man of
genius is the triumph of intelligence, recalls our power over matter,
sovereignty spirit throughout the universe .... Then - he added, lowering
his voice a little - at the sun can see without costing money, and
I've always hated the shows free.

The guests did not stop laughing.

Fuentes, encouraged by the laughter, overflowed in paradoxes in one-liners
and subtle, visibly falling into affectation.

What happened to him the big players too much applauded. I did not know contained in time and
came at last the ground of insanity. From here to there is more bland than a step, and gave Fuentes
frequently.

The Count of Cotorraso persisted in defending the star of the day to drive his wit detractor. The
sun was the one who encouraged Nature, who warmed up the body numb, etc.

- That the sun produces animation, deny - replied Sources -, Madrid
is much more lively at night than during the day, and I prefer warm
coke, that does not cause sunstroke .... Let's see, count, mind you,
what merit can be a thing that force must see always the first thing
you groom?

As someone said, laughing, that Fuentes had "good shadow," he replied sharply:

- Do you see it, count?

So to say that a man has grace is said to have good shadow. No one would think that you have
good sun.

And because of the shadows of the manzanillo discussed. The Marquise of Ujo asked the Mexican, Lola's husband,
if his country had manchineel. Ballesteros, who was his name, replied that no, but he had seen
many in Brazil.

The Marquise was reported with deep curiosity the particularities
of the tree, but was extremely upset when told Mexican not kill the
shadow and only the fruit off a corrosive water.

- So you sleeping
under it does not die?

- Madam, I have not slept you know, but I
have several friends Debah almorsado one and we has pasao ná.

- So
how Selika commits suicide in the African sleeping in the shade of
that tree?

- This is a hoax, a invensión of the poet you know?

It will be a beautiful thing, but no nothing is right.

The Marquise, disappointed by that fact realistic, would not leave his poetic belief, argued maybe the
manchineel in India were different from those of Brazil.

Hablóse productions of Mexico.

- Is it true that you have eight hundred thousand cows, Ballesteros?
- Asked Clementina.

- Oh, madam, that's a exagerasión!

At best it will my herd is tresientas thousand.

- If they were mine - said Fuentes - build a pool larger than the
Retiro, would fill milk and sail for it.

- We do not utilisamo milk,
sir, not butter either.

Wash your meat any of convertimo in tasaho you know? and esportamo. But usually only get me
from the hides you know?

The horn also sell me for making the object pole.

- That you burn! You burn! - Pepe Castro said softly.

But while not hear Arbós Jiménez, who was on the other side of Pepa Frias, and not undertaken a
fit of laughter that tried with all his might suffocate.

- Anda,
Barbiana, alárgame that bottle of mustard - Pepa Frias said Clementina
addressing to cover also the laughter that he had undertaken.

- Bajbiana,
bajbiana .... What is that bajbiana? - Asked the Baroness de Osorio
in Rag desire to quickly learn Spanish.

This was quick to explain as he could.

Pepa talked from time to time by the low to Arbós Jiménez. They used to be some rapid phrases
intelligence that proved they were and at the same time the desire
to be prudent.

The conversation with Pepe Castro, who had left, was more animated.

- Why do not advise you to eat more meat Arbós? - Asked the dandy in his ear.

- Why?

- For what you usually eat meat, for nutrients and to withstand forces that the hardships that
our duties imposed on us.

- Ya! - Said the widow with an ironic intonation -.

Look for himself and let others fix accounts as God implies.

- You see I try to nurture.

- Yes, but also go a little brain, because when you least expect you
fall Street fool.

- Have you ever offended you? - Asked, laughing
as if this stylish the craziest thing the world.

- No, man, no, is
that I think so.

Clementine can not understand how to suffer like narcissus.

- Chis, hush! Prudence, Pepa, prudence! - Said Castro with fright, looking up to his mistress.

- Do you know that very well concealed? Have not seen you guide a single glance so far.

Castro, who for days was a little disgruntled by the coldness of its
owner, forced a smile then his brow furrowing.

Pepa does not go unnoticed by this gesture.

- Look what a face so clouded currently has Osorio. It inspires horror!

And the whole blame is you, rogue.

- Yo! Not so. Should be matters of twine that you get so yellow. Me said he is broke or close
to ruin.

Pepa shuddered visibly.

- What do you say? "Where have you know that?

- As I have said already several.

The widow turned sharply Jiménez Arbós not hide his excitement and
asked him altered low voice:

- Have you heard that Osorio is ruined?

-
Yes, I've heard.

Osorio has been playing down some time ago and strive to raise funds - said statesman gesture
by lifting the head with peacock petulant.

The tone in which he uttered these words warned satisfaction. For a minister, play down is
always a crime worthy of punishment.

- I do not know what will be involved in this settlement, but if much is lost, because the consolidated
whole has risen.

And if he persists in not immediately settle, so month may be two
integers great hike.

All the good humor of Pepa had suddenly disappeared. He lowered his head and dropped his fork no
mood to finish the piece of ham that had set.

The minister, noting their silence and sadness, he asked

- Do you happen to funds in his possession?

- By chance, no ... For my stupidity! In his hand most of my fortune.

- O devil, devil!

- I'm running realgar in the body I have eaten. I think I'm going to get bad - said the widow getting
really pale.

Arbós made efforts to reassure her. Might not be all true. In the ruins as improvised fortunes
always much overdone. Also, if there was a sacred commitment for Osorio, should be hers, a
lady who entrusted their money out of pure friendship.

While speaking in falsetto, their faces serious and manner determined
drew attention General Patiño, which, with admirable penetration,
said the Marquise de Ujo:

- Look for Pepa and Arbós.

There are summer cloud between them. How beautiful is the love to
in their fleeting storm!

Meanwhile, the counts of Cotorraso, Lola Madariaga, Clementina barons and spoke Rag of arsenic
as a medicine to fatten and make the skin smooth and shiny. Lola Madariaga was the first time I heard
and was full of joy, and immediately announced that it would to test
the miraculous virtue of the poison.

- My God, Lolita! - Said Fuentes
-.

If you, as it is now causing such havoc in male hearts, what will happen when you take four or
five months with a regimen of Arsenic! Mr. Ballesteros, you do not consent to take it: it is
too cruel to treat.

- Come on, buddy Fuentes - the pretty brunette said with a glance
insinuating Castro, why he had made up his mind to Clementina torn
out - I want you to kid?

- Tomaj hair!

... Tomaj What is your hair? - Rag asked the baroness to Osorio.

At this Baroness was undressing with the imagination Bonifacio, watching
from afar without blinking.

For days she had bought from other obscene photographs of a woman
naked swinging in a hammock.

It seemed to him that the Baroness was much like that Women, and
tried to figure out, through a careful external examination, if the
inside would keep the same image.

Finally finished the meal without spending not, of course, a good
time to talk to the theater Real, Gayarre and Tosti.

They had not digested well if they are missing. Coffee, as was Osorio custom house, was served
in the same room. Then the ladies with some men left the room.

Others were smoking, but they soon go to meet others. There was an unbearable heat.

Pepe Castro took the confusion of departure for asking Clementina:

- Why did not you go this morning?

Clementina stood still, looked at him with a smile protective.

-
"This morning?

... I do not know.

- Why did not you know? - Said his August brow furrowing the actual waiter.

- I do not know I do not know - and took a step away, still smiling with a slight tinge of mockery.

-
The future go?

- We'll see - said walking away.

Castro felt that smile like a punch in the chest. She bit her lower lip and murmured: - flirted, eh?
You pay me, beautiful!

In the lounge there and some people, including Ramon Maldonado and daughter Pepa Frias with her husband.
In another adjoining sitting room were prepared up to six tables
seating area.

Some sat course to play. Others wait for co-habit. Soon, in effect, both of halls populated.
D. reached Julián Calderón Mariana and Esperanza, Cobo León Ramírez Guzmán and three or four Pollastre,
General Pallarés the Marquis of Veneros and several other people,
including bankers dominated and businessmen.

One of the last to arrive was the Duke of Requena, who was receiving the same noisy and flattering that
everywhere. Came panting, smoking, spitting, with insolent security
his vast fortune had been acquired.

He spoke little, he laughed less, aired their views rudely and left
the circle of ladies worship around him. Her cheeks are bruised than
ever, bloodshot eyes, black lips. I was so ugly that Fuentes told
Pinedo Arbós Jiménez and pointing:

- There you have the devil getting
his witches in the coven on Saturdays.

He was invited to play sitting
as usual, but he refused. Had seen two bankers who wanted to fish
for her business Riosa mine. In addition to the court suited him Jiménez
Arbós few moments. He had already gotten mine come out in the auction
with all accessories forestry and belongings. In the Gazette had inserted
the advertisement. The company to buy was already formed. But there
was disagreement between the partners. Some wanted to purchase for
cash (Among them was Salabert) and others wanted to take ten times
that the Government attached. The difference in pricing from one to
another form, was enormous.

The Duke went to Biggs, the representative
of an English house that came with some very significant in the company
and headed the party hire purchase. She threw her familiarly arm on
the shoulder and led him into the hollow of a balcony, saying roughly:

-
"So you determined to ruin us?

And he began to discuss the matter
with a frankness that surprised the English. This responded to Duke
exits with arguments brutal polite and gentle, always smiling benevolently.
The Duke emphasized his toughness, which basically was very diplomatic.

-
I have no desire to throw my money. I have a hard time acquiring them,
you know</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>