<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04696</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>109326</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18082</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Le puso el peinador o matinée que la niña vestía, y se entretuvo buen
rato a dibujar minuciosamente los lazos de seda con que se sujetaba por delante. Cuando el
retrato estuvo terminado. Venturita le dijo con acento picaresco:

--Ahora, pon debajo quién es.

El joven levantó la cabeza y sus miradas chocaron sonrientes. Luego, con viveza y decisión,
escribió debajo de la figura: Lo que más quiero en el mundo.

Venturita tomó el papel entre las manos y lo contempló unos instantes con deleite. Después,
haciendo una mueca de fingido desdén, se lo alargó otra vez diciendo:

--Toma, toma, embustero.

Pero antes de llegar a manos de Gonzalo, Cecilia extendió la suya y se lo arrebató riendo.

--¿Qué papelitos son ésos?

Venturita, como si la hubieran pinchado, brincó en el asiento y sujetó fuertemente la muñeca
de su hermana.

--¡Trae, trae, Cecilia! ¡Deja eso!--exclamó con el rostro echando fuego, contraído por forzada
sonrisa.

--No; quiero verlo.

--Ya lo verás después; ¡suelta!

--Quiero verlo ahora.

--Vamos, niña, déjaselo ver. ¿Qué te importa?--dijo doña Paula.

--No quiero que me lo quite nadie por fuerza--gritó poniéndose seria. Después, comprendiendo
la imprudencia de esto, tornó a ponerse risueña.

--Vamos, Cecilia, suelta; no seas mala.

--¡Vaya un empeño! ¡Suelta tú, que me lastimas!

--¿Quién eres tú para quitarme el papel de la mano?--profirió con rabia, poniéndose esta vez
seria de verdad.--¡Suelta, suelta, fea, narices de cotorra, tonta!... ¡Suelta, o te araño!--añadió
con los ojos centelleantes y la faz descompuesta por la cólera.

Al verla de aquel modo, la risa que agitaba el pecho de Cecilia paralizóse súbito, y abriendo
sus grandes ojos donde se pintaba la sorpresa, exclamó:

--¡Jesús! Pareces loca, niña. Toma, toma, no vaya a darte algo.

Y soltó el papelito que arrugaba en el puño. Venturita, la faz alterada aún, lo hizo mil trozos.

--¡En los días de mi vida he visto una criatura más loca!--exclamó doña Paulina santiguándose.--¡Ave
María! ¡Ave María! ¿De quién has sacado ese genio, chiquilla?

--Sería de ti--respondió Venturita enfoscada, sin mirar a nadie.

--¡Desvergonzada!... ¡Si no fuera mirando a que hay gente delante!... ¿Cómo contestas de ese
modo a tu madre, picara? ¿No sabes los mandamientos de la ley de Dios? Mañana mismo te llevo
a confesar con don Aquilino.

--Bueno, dale memorias a don Aquilino.

--¡Espera, espera, grandísima picara!--gritó la señora haciendo ademán de levantarse para castigar
a su hija.

Pero en aquel instante aparecía en la puerta la figura de don Rosendo con bata multicolor y
gorro de terciopelo con borla de seda.

--¿Qué pasa?--preguntó sorprendido viendo la actitud airada de su esposa.

Esta le puso al corriente, sofocada por los sollozos, de la falta de respeto de su hija.

Don Rosendo se creyó en el caso de arrugar el entrecejo, y decir con tono solemne:

--Eso está mal hecho, Ventura. Ve a pedir perdón a tu mamá.

Se le conocía que estaba distraído, absorto por algún pensamiento, y que aquel suceso doméstico
no conseguía más que a medias arrancarle de su preocupación.

Sin embargo, al ver a la chica inmóvil, en actitud altiva y desdeñosa, dijo de nuevo, con más
firmeza:

--Vamos, hija, ve a pedirla perdón, ya que la has ofendido.

La niña hizo su peculiar mohín de desprecio con los labios, y murmuró muy bajito:

--¡Sí, en eso estoy pensando!

--Vaya, Ventura, ¿qué murmuras ahí? Anda, antes que me enfade.

--Anda, anda, Venturita. Ve allá. No seas así--le dijeron por lo bajo las costureras.

--No me da la gana. ¿Queréis dejarme en paz?--les respondió ella en voz baja también, mas con
acento iracundo.

--¿No quieres ir?--preguntó don Rosendo con afectada severidad.--¿No quieres ir?

La niña permaneció inmóvil y silenciosa.

--¡Pues sal de aquí ahora mismo! ¡Quítate de mi vista!

Venturita se levantó de la silla, pasó por el medio del concurso erguida y enfurruñada, y salió
de la sala dando un gran portazo.

Don Rosendo, después de permanecer un momento inmóvil con los ojos puestos en la puerta por
donde su hija había salido, volvióse diciendo:

--Siento mucho estar tan fuerte con mis hijas... pero algunas veces no hay más remedio.

VII

QUE TRATA DE DOS TRAIDORES

Borróse súbito de su noble faz pseudomarítima la temerosa expresión que la obscurecía, y apareció
de nuevo aquella otra distraída, signo de constantes meditaciones.

--Gonzalo, si no te molesta, te rogaría que pasases conmigo al despacho--manifestó dirigiéndose
a su futuro yerno.

Este, que durante la anterior escena había empalidecido y vuelto a su ser varias veces, tornó
a desconcertarse. Nada menos se le ocurrió que don Rosendo se había percatado de la instabilidad
de sus sentimientos amorosos, y le iba a pedir de ello estrecha cuenta. Fuese, pues, detrás
de él cabizbajo y receloso, y penetró en el escritorio. Era una estancia espaciosa, amueblada
con lujo de comerciante rico: gran mesa de caoba maciza, armarios de caoba también, donde había
más legajos de papeles que libros, alfombra de terciopelo, divanes forrados de brocatel, y
escribanía de plata enorme como un monumento. Cerca de la cuarta parte de esta cámara ocupábalo
un montón de paquetitos envueltos en papel de varios colores, que para cualquiera que por primera
vez entrase en ella, sería un misterio. No lo era para Gonzalo ni para ninguno de los íntimos
de la casa. Aquellos paquetes guardaban palillos de dientes.

¿Cómo?--preguntará el lector.--¿Don Rosendo Belinchón, un negociante de tanto fuste, comerciaba
también en palillos de dientes? No, don Rosendo no comerciaba con ellos, los fabricaba. Y esto
no con el fin de especular, cosa indigna de su categoría, sino por pura y desinteresada inclinación
de su espíritu. Desde muy joven se le había manifestado. Las asiduas ocupaciones del comercio
y las vicisitudes por que había pasado su existencia, no le habían consentido satisfacer esta
pasión sino de una manera precaria en los ratos materialmente perdidos. Pero desde que pudo
dejar el escritorio confiado a algunos fieles dependientes, entregóse de lleno con alma y vida
a tan útil y honesta distracción. Por la mañana en la tienda de Graells, por la tarde en el
Saloncillo, por la noche en su casa o en la de don Pedro Miranda, siempre trabajando. Su criado
ocupaba una gran parte del día en cortarle unos tacos de avellano seco perfectamente iguales,
de donde su mano diestra había de sacar la gala de los palillos.

Y como no se daba punto de reposo, ni aun en los días festivos, la producción era excesiva.
No había bastantes consumidores en la villa, y se veía necesitado a remitir paquetes de ellos
a los amigos de la capital, cuando el montón del despacho llegaba al techo. Gracias a los esfuerzos
nobilísimos de este claro representante de su comercio, podemos decir con orgullo que Sarrió,
en tal ramo interesante del progreso, se hallaba a la altura de las grandes capitales. Ninguna
otra villa española o extranjera podría sufrir con ella competencia. En casa del rico, como
en la del menestral, jamás faltaba un bien abastecido palillero, testimonio indiscutible de
la refinada cultura de sus habitantes.

Señaló don Rosendo un diván a su hijo en ciernes, y éste, asustado, dejóse caer en él hundiéndole
profundamente. Acercó después el comerciante una silla con ademán misterioso, y sentándose
frente al joven y mirándole entre risueño y avergonzado, dijo, dándole al propio tiempo una
palmadita en el muslo:

--Vamos a ver, Gonzalito: ¿qué te parece de la cuestión del matadero?

--¿El matadero?--preguntó aquél abriendo unos ojos como puños.

--Sí, el nuevo matadero; ¿crees que debe emplazarse en la Escombrera, o en la playa de las
Meanas detrás de las casas de don Rudesindo?

Gonzalo vió el cielo abierto, y, sonriendo de placer, respondió:

--Yo creo que en la playa de las Meanas estaría bien... Muy abierto aquello... muy ventilado...

Pero notando que la frente de su suegro se fruncía, y en sus ojos se apagaba repentinamente
la sonrisa, añadió balbuciendo:

--Tampoco me parece que estaría mal en la Escombrera...

--Mucho mejor, Gonzalo... ¡Infinitamente mejor!

--Puede, puede.

--Hombre, tan puede ser, que reservadamente te diré que el emplazarlo en la playa lo juzgo
(hazme el favor de guardar reserva sobre esta opinión), lo juzgo... una verdadera insensatez...
u-na ver-da-de-ra in-sen-sa-tez--repitió señalando mejor todas las sílabas.

--Y esta opinión mía--añadió--no vayas a figurarte que es de ayer mañana, sino de toda la vida.
Desde que fuí capaz de entender ciertas cosas, comprendí que el matadero no debía estar donde
hoy está. En una palabra, que debía trasladarse. ¿Dónde? Una voz interior me decía siempre
que a la Escombrera. Antes de poder dar ninguna razón científica, estaba tan convencido como
ahora de que allí debía emplazarse, y no en otra parte. Hoy que la resolución del problema
se aproxima, me creo obligado a sostener esta opinión, a comunicar al pueblo mi pensamiento
y el resultado de mis meditaciones. Si no tienes que hacer voy a leerte la carta que dirijo
con este motivo al Progreso de Lancia.

Y en efecto, sin aguardar la contestación de Gonzalo, se dirigió a la mesa, tomó unos pliegos
de papel que había sobre ella, se puso las gafas, y acercándose al balcón dió comienzo, no
sin cierta emoción que se le traslucía en la voz, a la lectura de la carta.

Estaba escrita en papel comercial, grande y rayado. Todas las que desde hacía años dirigía
al Progreso de Lancia y a otros periódicos de la capital de la provincia, iban escritas en
el mismo papel por las dos caras. Aun no sabía que para la imprenta debía escribirse por una
solamente. Pero muy pronto adquirió este precioso conocimiento, como hemos de ver.

Casi al mismo tiempo que la de los palillos de dientes había nacido en don Rosendo Belinchón
la afición a escribir comunicados a los periódicos: es decir, que databa de una remota antigüedad.
Ardiente partidario de los progresos humanos, de las reformas en todos los órdenes, de la discusión
y de la luz, claro está que la prensa había de infundirle respeto y entusiasmo. Los periódicos
habían sido siempre un elemento indispensable de su existencia. Estaba suscripto a muchos nacionales
y extranjeros; porque, como educado para el comercio, conocía bastante bien el francés y el
inglés, y nunca le había faltado, ni aun en los días más ocupados, un par de horas que dedicar
a su lectura. Estas horas se aumentaron considerablemente desde hacía algunos años, no sin
que se resintiese por ello el bacalao. El goce que nuestro héroe experimentaba por las mañanas
después de tomar el chocolate tragándose los artículos de fondo del Pabellón Nacional, los
sueltos de La Política y las Nouvelles à la main del Fígaro era tan vivo, que le quedaba impreso
largo tiempo en el rostro, hasta que por la irradiación se iba perdiendo en la atmósfera.

Como todos los hombres de miras amplias y elevadas, no era exclusivista en sus gustos periodísticos.
Amaba el periódico por el periódico, por ser una muestra gentil del progreso de la razón humana,
o como él decía mejor, «una manifestación levantada de la conciencia pública». Las opiniones
que cada cual defendía, eran cosa secundaria. Estaba suscripto a periódicos de todos colores,
y los gozaba por igual. Si alguna predilección mostraba, era únicamente por los artículos y
sueltos intencionados. Porque eso de decir una cosa aparentando expresar la contraria y retorcer
las frases de modo que una cláusula inocente en la apariencia llevase dentro «una saeta envenenada»
llenaba de admiración a don Rosendo y le volvía loco de alegría. ¡Cuántas veces al leer en
La España algún párrafo por el estilo:--«Ayer apareció por fin la circular del señor Presidente
del Supremo a sus subordinados. Felicitamos al general O'Donnell, presidente de esta situación
liberal, al señor Negrete, que en algún rato lúcido ha dado cima a obra tan colosal, y a los
demócratas protectores de este Gobierno»,--hubo exclamado agitando el periódico en las manos:--¡Qué
intención! ¡Caracoles! ¡¡Qué intención!!

Este afán, mejor dicho, esta pasión por la prensa, no era platónico como ya hemos advertido.
Allá en sus mocedades había dirigido dos cartas a un periódico semanal que se publicaba en
Lancia, titulado El Otoño, con motivo de las fiestas anuales que en Sarrió se celebran en el
mes de septiembre. Estas cartas leyéronse con fruición en la villa y le valieron no pocos plácemes.
Esto le animó para escribir otras tres al año siguiente, dando cuenta al público del número
asombroso de cohetes que se dispararon en Sarrió los días 13, 14 y 15, la lindísima iluminación
del 16, y el suntuoso baile celebrado en el Liceo la noche del 17. Después de haber gustado
las dulzuras de la publicidad, don Rosendo no podía menos de paladearlas de vez en cuando.
El menor pretexto le bastaba para dirigir, bien una carta, ora un comunicado a los periódicos.
Unas veces firmaba con su nombre, otras con cualquier gracioso pseudónimo o anagrama. Celebraban
los mareantes una fiesta en honor de San Telmo: don Rosendo escribía inmediatamente su carta
al Progreso de Lancia o a La Abeja, describiendo la verbena, los fuegos artificiales, la misa,
la procesión, etc. Se daba un banquete en el nuevo edificio de las escuelas para inaugurarlo:
a los tres o cuatro días se recibía el periódico de Lancia con la consabida carta publicando
los brindis y los sonetos improvisados. Se caía un albañil de un andamio; comunicado de don
Rosendo pidiendo más garantías para los albañiles que se ponen en los andamios. Cantaba misa
el hijo de don Aquilino; carta de don Rosendo describiendo la conmovedora ceremonia, y elogiando
la voz clara, y sonora y la serenidad del joven presbítero. Si las mareas eran altas y fuertes
y arrancaban algunas piedras de la punta del Peón; carta. Si los buques de Bilbao se negaban
a recibir a bordo los prácticos de Sarrió; comunicado. Si se perdía la cosecha del maíz por
la sequía; carta. Si los vientos reinantes eran del Noroeste; carta. En fin, no acaecía suceso
en el suelo o en la atmósfera de la villa digno de mención, que no la recibiese de la diestra
y bien tallada pluma de nuestro comerciante.

¡Cuánto trabajo se evitarán los futuros historiadores de Sarrió con esto, valiosísimos materiales
acumulados por uno de sus más claros hijos!

Según iba avanzando en años don Rosendo Belinchón, daba a sus cartas un carácter menos romántico,
por no decir frívolo (sería tan inexacto como irrespetuoso tal calificativo aplicado a los
escritos de aquel estimable caballero). Es decir, que los temas de ellas no eran tan a menudo
los holgorios y recreos de los habitantes de la villa, como cualquier cosa que tendiera directa
o indirectamente a fomentar los intereses morales y materiales de ella. Los mercados, las escuelas,
el salvamento de náufragos, la erección de un templo o de una cárcel, etc., etc., eran los
asuntos en que para gloria suya y bien del pueblo que le vió nacer, se ejercitaba con más frecuencia.

Uno de ellos, de «vital interés para Sarrió», como él afirmaba muy bien, era el matadero. Hasta
entonces jamás había abordado esta cuestión, porque sabía que su parecer iba a discrepar algo
del de una gran parte del vecindario. Mas había llegado, a su entender, la hora de «emitirlo
sin ambages ni rodeos». El comunicado que leyó era el primero que acerca de este asunto dirigía
al Progreso de Lancia. Comenzaba así:

«Señor Director de El Progeso de Lancia.

Muy señor mío: La preferencia con que se miran las ciencias físico-naturales, y en particular
la ciencia de la Higiene, como que de ella depende la salud, tanto de los pueblos como de los
individuos, en vista de su gran utilidad práctica, ha ido poco a poco desterrando la timidez
de los que, influídos por una educación casi errónea y deficiente, condenaban el estudio de
estos grandes problemas arrastrados por antiguas y torpes preocupaciones que felizmente se
van disipando al soplo poderoso del siglo XIX, llamado con razón el siglo de las luces.»

Los párrafos de don Rosendo eran siempre nutridos como el anterior. Seguía:

«Hoy que la civilización, rotas las cortapisas que detenían las conciencias y supeditaban el
espíritu, nos abre vasto campo a todos por medio de la prensa para expresar nuestro libre pensamiento
y emitirlo a la faz del mundo, confiado en la amistad con que usted me ha distinguido siempre,
y en la benevolencia con que el público ha acogido hasta ahora los humildes partos de mi pluma,
etc., etc.»

Después de otros tres o cuatro párrafos a modo de preámbulo (que el director de El Progreso
acostumbraba a recortar) entraba don Rosendo en la cuestión, estudiando el matadero o macelo
público, como él lo nombraba, por todas sus fases, para venir a condenar, en términos que no
daban lugar a dudas, su emplazamiento en la playa de las Meanas. Las razones que tenía para
oponerse a él, eran «obvias». Por una parte, los vientos del Sudoeste, reinantes la mayor parte
del año, que arrastraban consigo fétidos miasmas, etc., etcétera. Por otra parte, la dificultad
de hallar terreno firme para la cimentación, lo cual originaría un gasto excesivo, etc., etc.
Por otra, la necesidad de penetrar en la población con las reses, etc., etc. Por otra, la proximidad
de las casas, etc. Por otra, el perjuicio que a los bañistas se les irrogaba, etc., etc. En
fin, eran más de veinte las razones que don Rosendo «apuntaba de un modo ligero y sucinto»,
proponiéndose darle «más amplitud y desarrollo» en otras cartas sucesivas con que pensaba «molestar
la atención de los lectores de su ilustrado periódico».

Cuando terminó la lectura, Gonzalo las juzgó incontrovertibles, y don Rosendo (con las gafas
en la punta de la nariz) declaró que no tenían vuelta de hoja. Habiendo llegado a un acuerdo
tan perfecto, se separaron llenos de alegría, como es natural. Don Rosendo se quedó en el despacho
poniendo en limpio su carta. Gonzalo se fué de nuevo a la sala de costura. No obstante, antes
que franquease la puerta, llamóle su futuro suegro para decirle:

--De esto, ni una palabra a nadie, ¿eh?

--¡Don Rosendo, por Dios!--respondió el joven alzando la mano en señal de protesta.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02576</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>77601</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16386</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> He put the hairdresser or the girl wearing matinee, and entertained good
while carefully drawing silk ties that are holding ahead. When portrait was finished. Venturita
accent told picaresque:

- Now, who is put under.

The young man raised his head and smiling eyes clashed. Then, with brilliance and decision wrote
under the picture: What I love most in the world.

Venturita took the paper in his hands and stared for a moment with
pleasure.

Then with a grimace of disdain handed it back saying:

- Take, take,
liar.

But before reaching the hands of Gonzalo, Cecilia extended his and snatched him laughing.

- What are those pieces of paper?

Venturita, as if it had a flat tire, jumped on the seat and held her
wrist tightly of his sister.

- Give, give, Cecilia!

Stop it! - Said breathing fire with his face, made by forced smile.

- No, I see it.

- You'll see later, go!

- I see it now.

- Come on, girl, Leave it to see.

What do you care? - Said Dona Paula.

- I do not want anyone to force it off - cried becoming serious. Then, realizing the recklessness of
this, turned to be cheerful.

- Come on, Cecilia, loose, do not be evil.

- What a commitment!

Drops you who hurt me!

- Who are you to take my hand paper? - Uttered in anger, turning this
time really serious .-- Loose, loose, ugly parrot noses, silly!

... Let go, or I scratch you! - Added with flashing eyes and the face broken by anger.

Seeing her in that way, the laughter that shook his chest suddenly
paralizóse Cecilia, and opening her large eyes which was painted surprise,
exclaimed:

- Jesus!

You look crazy, girl. Take, take, will not give you something.

And dropped the crumpled piece of paper that in the fist.

Venturita have altered the face, he did a thousand pieces.

- In the days of my life have I seen a wild creature! - Crossing himself exclaimed Dona Paulina
Ave .-- Mary!

Ave Maria! Who did you get that genie, girl?

- Would you - plastered Venturita said, without looking at anyone.

-
Shameless!

... If not there are people looking forward!

... How do you answer that So your mother, naughty? Do not you know
the commandments of God's law?

Tomorrow I will Don Aquilino to confess.

- Well, give reports to Don Aquilino.

- Wait, wait, very great rascal! - Called Mrs. doing started to rise
to punish her daughter.

But at that moment appeared at the door of Don Rosendo with multicolored robe velvet hat with
silk tassel.

- What? - Asked amazed watching his wife's angry attitude.

This will put the current, choked with sobs, the lack of respect for
his daughter.

Don Rosendo was believed in the case of frown, and say solemnly:

- That's wrong, Ventura. Go to apologize to your mom.

He knew he was distracted, absorbed in some thought, and that domestic incident could not wring
more than half of their concern.

However, to see the girl still in haughty and dismissive, he said again, more firmly

- Come, daughter, go to ask for forgiveness, because you have offended.

The

girl made his peculiar grimace of contempt in his lips, and whispered softly:

- Yes, that's what I'm thinking!

- Go, Ventura, what muttering there? Go, before I get angry.

- Go, go, Venturita. Go there. Do not be so - he said under his seamstresses.

- I do not want. Will you leave me alone? - She answered quietly, too, but with angry tone.

- Do not want to go? - Asked Don Rosendo with severely affected .--
Do not you want to go?

The girl stood motionless and silent.

- Then get out of here now! Get out of my sight!

Venturita rose from his chair, went through the middle of the upright and sulking competition,
and went the room making a big bang.

Don Rosendo, after remaining motionless for a moment with eyes fixed on the door where his daughter
had gone, he turned, saying:

- I'm sorry to be so strong with my
daughters ... but sometimes no choice.

VII

THAT IS OF TWO TRAITORS

Sudden blurred pseudomarítima his noble face the fearful expression that darkened and appeared
distracted again that another sign of constant meditation.

- Gonzalo,
if you do not mind, I ask you to pierce me at the office - said addressing
to his future son.

This, that during the previous scene was pale and returned to his
being repeatedly turned at confusing.

Nothing less struck him that Rosendo was unaware of the instability their feelings of love,
and I would ask it close consideration. Was, therefore, behind his head bowed and suspicious, and
entered the desktop.

It was a spacious room, furnished with rich merchant class: large solid mahogany table, mahogany
cabinets, too, where there bundles of papers more than books, velvet carpet, couches lined with
brocade, and massive silver inkstand as a monument. About a quarter of this camera ocupábalo
a lot of packets wrapped in several colors, to whoever first Once entered into it, would be
a mystery. Gonzalo was not for or to any of the intimate of the house. Those packages kept
toothpicks.

How? - Ask the reader .-- Don Rosendo Belinchón, a dealer in both
stem, traded also on toothpicks?

No, Don Rosendo not traded with them, make them. And this not to speculate, unworthy of its kind,
but pure and selfless inclination of his spirit. From a very young man had told him. The regulars
trade occupations and the vicissitudes through which he passed his
existence, had not consented to meet this passion but in a materially
poor at times lost.

But since she could leave the desktop to some of the faithful entrusted dependent entregóse
full heart and soul a distraction so helpful and honest. In the morning at the store Graells,
in the afternoon Saloncillo in the evening at home or in the Don Pedro Miranda, always working.
His servant occupied much of the day in court a few blocks of dry
hazel perfectly equal, where his right hand had to take the show of
the sticks.

And was not about to rest, even on holidays, production was excessive. There were not enough consumers
in the village, and saw packages needed to recall them friends of the capital, when the pile reached
the ceiling clearance. Thanks to the efforts noblest of the clear representative of their trade, we
can proudly say that Sarrio in this interesting field of progress, was at the height of the
big cities. No other Spanish town or foreign competition could suffer with it. Home of the rich,
as in the artisan, never missing a well-stocked toothpick, undisputed testimony the refined
culture of its inhabitants.

Rosendo said a couch to his son in infancy, and he was frightened and let himself fall into it sinking
deeply.

After the trader approached a chair with an air of mystery, and sitting front of the young and looking
between smiling and embarrassed, he said, giving the same time a pat on the thigh

- Let's see, Gonzalito: how about the issue of slaughter?

- Is the slaughter? - Said it opened his eyes wide as fists.

- Yes, the new slaughterhouse, do you think should be placed in the dump, or on the beach of
Meanas behind the houses of Don Rudesindo?

Gonzalo saw heaven opened, and, smiling with pleasure, he replied:

- I believe that the Meanas beach would be nice ... Very open that
... well ventilated ...

But noting that his father's forehead was
wrinkled, and her eyes suddenly subsided smile, said stammering:

-
Nor do I think it would be wrong with the spring ...

- Much better,
Gonzalo ... Infinitely better!

- Can, can.

- Man, so it may be,
I will tell you privately that the location on the beach I judge (Please
save me the reservation on this opinion), I judge ... a veritable
folly ... u-na do-da-de-ra in-sen-sa-skinned - all the best pointing
repeated syllables.

- And this opinion of mine - he said - do not
go to refiguring it yesterday morning, but throughout life.

Since I was able to understand certain things, I realized that the slaughterhouse would not
be where is today. In a word, that should be moved. Where? An inner voice always told me that
the dump. Before you can give any scientific reason, I was as convinced as that there was now
located, and not elsewhere. Now that the resolution of the problem approaches, I think I have to hold
this view, to communicate my thoughts to the people and the result of my musings. If you do
not have to do I will read your letter I am writing Progress on this occasion the Lancia.

And indeed, without waiting for the answer to Gonzalo, he went to the table, picked up a specification
paper that was on it, put on his glasses, and stood on the balcony gave beginning, not without
some emotion that is reflected by the voice, reading the letter.

Commercial paper was written in large, striped. All that for years led the Advancement of Lancia
and other newspapers in the capital of the province, were written in the same role on both sides.
Although he did not know that the press was written by a only. But soon acquired this precious
knowledge, as we shall see.

Almost simultaneously with that of toothpicks Rosendo was born in Belinchón the fans to write press
releases to newspapers: that is, dating from a remote antiquity. Ardent supporter of human progress,
reforms at all levels, from the discussion and light, it is clear that the press had to command
respect and enthusiasm. Newspapers had always been an essential element of their existence.
He was signed to many national and foreign, because, as taught to trade, was well acquainted with
French and English and had never missed, even in the busiest days, a couple of hours to spend
to read.

These times are significantly increased for some years, but not that it would suffer by cod. The
enjoyment that our hero felt in the morning after taking the chocolate
swallowing the substantive articles of the national flag, the Loose
Politics and the Nouvelles à la main of Figaro was so vivid, it was
printed long in the face until the radiation was being lost in the
atmosphere.

Like all men of broad and lofty view, it was not exclusive in their tastes newspaper. He loved
the daily newspaper, as a kind shows the progress of human reason or as he put it best, "a demonstration
raised public awareness." Opinions which each defended, were a secondary. I was subscribed to newspapers
in all colors, and equally enjoyed. If you showed any predilection, it was only for the items
loose meaning.

Because that's saying one thing and pretending to express the opposite twist phrases so that a
clause carry innocent appearance in a "poisoned arrow" was in awe of Don Rosendo and drove him
crazy with joy. Read many times The Spain one paragraph with the style: - "Yesterday it was
finally the circular of the President Supreme of their subordinates. Congratulations to General
O'Donnell, president of this situation liberal, Mr. Negrete, who
has given a lucid moment atop a colossal work, and Democrat protection
of this Government "- had exclaimed waving a newspaper in his hands:
- What intention!

Caracoles! What intention!

This desire, rather, this passion for the press, it was not platonic as we warned. Back in his
youth had sent two letters to a weekly newspaper that was published in Lancia, entitled The
Fall, on the occasion of the annual festivals that are held in Sarrió September. These letters
leyéronse to fruition in the town and earned him quite a few congratulations. This encouraged
him to write three more the following year, informing the public
of the number Amazing rockets that were fired Sarrió on 13, 14 and
15, the pretty little light of 16, and the lavish ball held at the
Lyceum on the night of 17.

After having tasted the sweetness of advertising, Rosendo could not
help tasting it from time to time.

The slightest pretext was enough to lead either a letter, sometimes a statement to newspapers.
Sometimes signed his name, others with any funny pseudonym or anagram. Celebrating the skippers a party
in honor of San Telmo: Rosendo immediately wrote a letter Lancia or the Progressive Bee, describing
the festival, fireworks, Mass, the procession, etc. It gave a banquet in the new school building
to inaugurate: after three or four days, the newspaper received the
usual letter Lancia publishing toasts and improvised sonnets.

It fell from a scaffold builder, reported Don Rosendo asking for more guarantees for the builders
who put on the scaffolding. Sung mass the son of Don Aquilino, Rosendo letter describing the
moving ceremony, praising clear voice and sound and serenity of the young priest. If the tides
were high and strong and tore some stones from the tip of the Pawn; letter. If the vessel refused
Bilbao to take on board pilots Sarrió; statement. If you missed the corn harvest drought; letter.
If the prevailing winds were from the Northwest; letter. In short, no event befell in the soil
or the atmosphere of the town worthy of mention, who did not receive the right hand and well-cut
pen of our merchant.

Much work is avoided Sarrió to future historians of this valuable material Joined by one of
the clearest children!

As he advanced in years Belinchón Rosendo, his letters gave a less romantic, if not frivolous
(it would be as inaccurate as such disrespectful epithet applied to writings of that estimable
gentleman). That is, these issues were not so often the feast and recreation of the inhabitants of
the town, as anything that would tend directly or indirectly to promote the moral and material
from it.

Markets, schools, the rescue of the shipwrecked, the erection of
a temple or a prison, etc., etc. were the issues that for His glory
and good of the people that he was born, they exercised more often.

One of them, of "vital interest to Sarrió" as he said very well,
was the slaughterhouses. Up then he had never addressed this issue,
knowing that their views would differ somewhat of a large part of
the neighborhood. More had come, in his view, the time of 'making
unambiguously or detours. " The statement he read was the first thing
about this issue addressed the Advancement of Lancia. Began:

"Mr.
Director of the Lancia Progeso. 

Dear Sir: The choice with which
you look at the physical and natural sciences, and in particular Health
science as it influences the health of both peoples as the individuals,
in view of its great practical value, has been slowly banish shyness
of those who, influenced by a poor education and almost wrong, condemned
the study of these great problems dragged by old and clumsy happily
concerns will dispel the powerful breath of the nineteenth century,
rightly called the Age of Enlightenment. "

Don Rosendo paragraphs
were always abundant as the previous. Continued:

"Today that civilization,
broken the constraints holding back the consciousness and subject
the spirit, opens vast field all through the press to express our
free thinking and issue to the face of the world, trusting friendship
with you I have always distinguished, and the leniency with which
the public has received so far the humble birth of my pen, etc., etc.
"

After three or four paragraphs by way of preamble (that the director
of El Progreso used to cut) Rosendo entered on the issue, studying
the slaughterhouse or Macelo groups, as he named them, through all
its stages, to come to condemn, in terms not gave rise to doubts,
its location on the beach of Meanas. His reasons for opposing it were
"obvious." On the one hand, winds from the southwest, reigning most
year, they pulled it foul miasma, etc. and so on. Moreover, the difficulty
to find firm ground for the foundation, which could cause excessive
spending, etc.., etc. In addition, the need to enter the cattle population,
etc., Etc. In addition, proximity houses, etc. In addition, the injury
to bathers are incurred, etc., Etc. In end, were more than twenty
reasons Rosendo "pointed in a light and brief" proposes to give "wider
and development" in other letters successive thought 'disturbing the
attention of the readers of your illustrious newspaper. "

When finished
reading, the deemed incontrovertible Gonzalo and Don Rosendo (with
goggles at the tip of the nose) said that they had no turning back.
Having reached agreement so perfect, full of joy broke naturally.
Don Rosendo stayed in the office putting clean your letter. Gonzalo
went back to the sewing room. However, before crossing the door, called
his father to tell his future:

- Of this, not a word to anyone, eh?

-
Don Rosendo, for God's sake - the young man raising his hand in protest.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>