<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>68556</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23613</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Al salir del baño le dolían los ojos: a los tres días era ciego.

Como aún tenía dinero, pudo algún tiempo vivir sin implorar la caridad pública, con la tristeza
inherente al no ver, y la no menos honda producida por el brusco paso de la vida activa a la
sedentaria. El muchacho ágil y fuerte se hizo de la noche a la mañana hombre enclenque y achacoso,
y sus ambiciones de comerciante y sus entusiasmos de viajero quedaron reducidos a un continuo
meditar sobre lo inseguro de los bienes terrenos, y la infalible justicia con que Dios Nuestro
Padre y Juez sienta la mano al pecador. No se atrevía el pobre ciego a pedirle que le devolviese
la vista, pues esto no se lo había de conceder. Era castigo, y el Señor no se vuelve atrás
cuando pega de firme. Pedíale que le diera dinero abundante para poder vivir con desahogo,
y una muquier que le amara; mas nada de esto le fue concedido al pobre Mordejai, que cada día
tenía menos dineros, pues estos iban saliendo, sin que entraran otros por ninguna parte, y
de muquieres nada. Las que se acercaban a él fingiéndole cariño, no iban a su covacha más que
a robarle. Un día estaba el hombre muy molesto por no poder cazar una pulga que atrozmente
le picaba, burlándose de él con audacia insolente, cuando... no es broma... se le aparecieron
dos ángeles.

XIV

«¿Pero tú ves algo, Almudena?--le preguntó Cuarto e kilo.

--Ver mí burtos ellos».

Explicó que distinguía las masas de obscuridad en medio de la luz: esto por lo tocante a las
cosas del mundo de acá. Pero en lo de los mundos misteriosos que se extienden encima y debajo,
delante y detrás, fuera y dentro del nuestro, sus ojos veían claro, cuando veían, mismo como
vosotras ver migo. Bueno: pues se le aparecieron dos ángeles, y como no era cosa de aparecérsele
para no decir nada, dijéronle que venían de parte del Rey de baixo terra con una embajada para
él. El señor Samdai tenía que hablarle, para lo cual era preciso que se fuese mi hombre al
Matadero por la noche, que estuviese allí quemando ilcienso, y rezando en medio de los despojos
de reses y charcos de sangre, hasta las doce en punto, hora invariable de la entrevista. No
hay que añadir que los ángeles se marcharon con viento fresco en cuanto dieron conocimiento
de su mensaje a Mordejai, y este cogió sus trebejos de sahumar, la pipa, la ración de cáñamo
en un papel, y se fue caminito del Matadero: el largo plantón que le esperaba, se le haría
menos aburrido fumando.

Allí se estuvo, sentado en cuclillas, aspirando los vahos olorosos del sahumerio, y fumando
pipa tras pipa, hasta que llegó la hora, y lo primerito que vio fue un par de perros, más grandes
que el cameio, brancos, con ojos de fuego. Él, Mordejai, mocha medo, un medo que le quitaba
el respirar. Vino después un arregimiento de jinetes con mucho cantorio, galas mochas; luego
empezó a caer lluvia espesísima de arena y piedras, tanto, tanto, que se vio enterrado hasta
el pescuezo... y no respiraba. Cada vez más medo... Por encima de toda aquella escoria pasó
velocísimo otro escuadrón de jinetes, dando al viento los blancos alquiceles, y sin cesar disparando
tiros. Siguió un diluvio de culebras y alcranes, que caían silbando y enroscándose. El pobre
ciego se moría de medo, sintiéndose envuelto en la horrorosa nube de inmundos animales... Pero
luego vinieron hombres y mujeres a pie, en pausada procesión, todos con blancas vestiduras,
llevando en la mano canastillas y bateas de oro, y pisando sobre flores, pues en rosas y azucenas
se habían convertido mágicamente las serpientes y alacranes, y en olorosas ramas de menta y
laurel todo aquel material llovido de arena cálida y puntiagudos guijarros.

Para no cansar, apareció por fin el Rey, hermoso, con humana y divina hermosura, barba larga
y negra, aretes en las orejas, corona de oro que parecía tener por pedrería el sol, la luna
y las estrellas. Verde era su traje, que por lo fino debía de ser obra de unas arañas muy pulidas
que en los profundos senos de la tierra tejen con hebras de fuego. El séquito de Samdai era
tan vistoso y brillante que deslumbraba. Como le preguntara la Petra si no venía también Su
Majestad la Reina, quedose un momento parado el narrador, recordando, y al fin dio cuenta de
que vido también a la señora del Rey, pero con la cara muy tapada, como la luna entre nubes,
y por esta razón Mordejai no pudo distinguirla bien. La Soberana vestía de amarillo, de un
color así como nuestros pensamientos cuando estamos entre alegres y tristes. Expresaba esto
el ciego con dificultad, supliendo las torpezas de su lenguaje con el juego fisonómico de la
convicción, y los mohines y gestos elocuentes.

Total: que a una orden del Rey le fueron poniendo delante todas aquellas bateas y canastos
de oro que traían las mujeres de blanco vestidas. ¿Qué era? Pieldras de diversas clases, mochas,
mochas, que pronto formaron montones que no cabrían en ninguna casa: rubiles como garbanzos,
perlas del tamaño de huevos de paloma, tudas, tudas grandes, diamanta fina en tal cantidad,
que había para llenar de ellos sacos mochas, y con los sacos un carro de mudanzas; esmeraldas
como nueces y trompacios como poño mío...

Oían esto las tres mujeres embobadas, mudas, fijos los ojos en la cara del ciego, entreabiertas
las bocas. Al comienzo de la relación, no se hallaban dispuestas a creer, y acabaron creyendo,
por estímulo de sus almas, ávidas de cosas gratas y placenteras, como compensación de la miseria
bochornosa en que vivían. Almudena ponía toda su alma en su voz, y con la lengua hablaban todos
los pliegues movibles de su cara, y hasta los pelos de su barba negra. Todo era signos, jeroglífico
descifrable, oriental escritura que los oyentes entendían sin saber por qué. El fin de la espléndida
visión fue que el Rey le dijo al bueno de Mordejai que de las dos cosas que deseaba, riquezas
y mujer, no podía darle más que una; que optase entre las pedrerías de gran valor que delante
miraba, y con las cuales gozaría de una fortuna superior a la de todos los soberanos de la
tierra, y una mujer buena, bella y laboriosa, joya sin duda tan rara que no se podía encontrar
sino revolviendo toda la tierra. Mordejai no vaciló un momento en la elección, y dijo a Su
Majestad de baixo terra, que para nada quería tanta pedrería por fanegas, si no le daban muquier...
«Querer mi ella... gustar mí muquier, y sin muquier migo, no querer pieldras finas, ni diniero
ni naida».

Señalole entonces el Rey una hembra que bien envuelta en un manto que la tapaba toda, el rostro
inclusive, iba por el camino, y le dijo que aquella era la suya, y que la siguiese hasta cogerla
o más bien cazarla, pues a paso muy ligero iba la condenada. Y dicho esto por el Rey, se dignó
Su Majestad desaparecerse, y con él se fueron todos los de su comitiva, y los arregimientos
y las señoras de blanco, y tudo, tudo, no quedando más que un olor penetrante del ilcienso,
y los ladridos de los dos perrazos que se iban perdiendo en las lontananzas de la noche fría,
cual si despavoridos huyeran hacia los montes. Tres meses estuvo enfermo Mordejai después de
este singular suceso, y no comía más que agua y harina de cebada sin sal. Quedose tan flaco
que se contaba al tacto todos los huesos, sin que se le escapara uno en la cuenta. Por fin,
arrastrándose como pudo, emprendió su camino por toda la grandeza del mundo en busca de la
mujer que, según dicho del divino Samdai, era suya.

«Y no la encontraste hasta tantismos años de correr, y se llamaba Nicolasa--dijo la Petra,
queriendo ayudar al biógrafo de sí mismo.

--¿Tú qué saber? No ser Nicolasa.

--Entonces será la señora--apuntó la Diega, señalando no sin cierta impertinencia a la pobre
Benina, que no chistaba.

--¿Yo?... ¡Jesús me valga! Yo no soy ninguna tarascona que anda por los caminos».

Contó Almudena que desde Fez había ido a la Argelia; que vivió de limosna en Tlemcén primero,
después en Constantina y Orán; que en este punto se embarcó para Marsella, y recorrió toda
Francia, Lyon, Dijon, París, que es mu grande, con tantos olivares y buenos pisos de calle,
todo como la palma de la mano. Después de subirse hasta un pueblo que le llaman Lila, volviose
a Marsella y a Cette, donde se embarcó para Valencia.

«Y en Valencia encontraste a la Nicolasa, con quien veniste por badajes, que vos daban los
aiuntamientos, con dos riales de tapa--dijo la Petra--, y de Madrid vos fuisteis a los Portugales,
y tres años te duró el contento, camastrón, hasta que la golfa se te fue con otro.

--Tú no saber.

--Que cuente la historia de Nicolasa y cómo a él le cogieron en Madrid para llevarle a San
Bernardino, y ella fue al espital; y estando él una noche durmiendo, se le aparecieron dos
mujeres del otro mundo, verbigracia, ánimas, para decirle que la Nicolasa hablaba en el espital
con uno que le iban a dar de alta...

--No ser eso, no ser eso: cállate tú.

--Otro día nos lo contará--indicó Benina, que, aunque gustaba de oír aquellos entretenidos
relatos, no quería detenerse más, recordando sus apremiantes quehaceres.

--Espérese, señora: ¿qué prisa tiene?--le dijo la Diega--. ¿A dónde irá usted que más valga?

--Otro día contar más--indicó el ciego sonriendo--. Mí ver mundo mocha.

--Estás cansadito, Jai. Convídanos a un medio para que se te remoje la lengua, que la tienes
más seca que suela de zapato.

--Yo no convidar mí ellas, b'rrachonas. No tener diniero migo.

--Por eso no quede--dijo la Diega, rumbosa.

--Yo no bebo--declaró la Benina--, y además tengo prisa, y con permiso de la compañía me voy.

--Quedar ti rato más. Dar once reloja.

--Dejarla--manifestó con benevolencia la Petra--, por si tiene que ir a ganarlo; que nosotras
ya lo hemos ganado».

Interrogadas por Almudena, refirieron que habiendo cogido la Diega unos dineros que le debían
dos mozas de la calle de la Chopa, se habían lanzado al comercio, pues una y otra tenían suma
disposición y travesura para el compra y vende. La Petra no se sentía mujer honrada y cabal
sino cuando se dedicaba al tráfico, aunque fuese en cosas menudas, como palillos, mondarajas
de tea, y torraé. La otra era un águila para pañuelos y puntillas. Con el dinero aquel, venido
a sus manos por milagro, compraron género en una casa de saldos, y en la mañana de aquel día
pusieron sus bazares junto a la Fuentecilla de la Arganzuela, teniendo la suerte de colocar
muchas carreras de botones, varas muchas de puntilla y dos chalecos de bayona. Otro día sacarían
loza, imágenes, y caballos de cartón de los que daban, a partir ganancias, en la fábrica de
la calle del Carnero. Largamente hablaron ambas de su negocio, y se alababan recíprocamente,
porque si Cuarto e kilo era de lo que no hay para la adquisición de género por gruesas, a la
otra nadie aventajaba en salero y malicia para la venta al menudeo. Otra señal de que había
venido al mundo para ser o comercianta o nada, era que los cuartos ganados en la compra-venta
se le pegaban al bolsillo, despertando en ella vagos anhelos de ahorro, mientras que los que
por otros medios iban a sus flacas manos, se le escapaban por entre los dedos antes de que
cerrar pudiera el puño para guardarlos.

Oyó Benina muy atenta estas explicaciones, que tuvieron la virtud de infundirle cierta simpatía
hacia la borracha, porque también ella, Benina, se sentía negocianta; también acarició su alma
alguna vez la ilusión del compra-vende. ¡Ah! si, en vez de dedicarse al servicio, trabajando
como una negra, hubiera tomado una puerta de calle, otro gallo le cantara. Pero ya su vejez
y la indisoluble sociedad moral con Doña Paca la imposibilitaban para el comercio.

Insistió la buena mujer en abandonar la grata tertulia, y cuando se levantó para despedirse
cayósele el lápiz que le había dado D. Carlos, y al intentar recogerlo del suelo, cayósele
también la agenda.

«Pues no lleva usted ahí pocas cosas--dijo la Petra, cogiendo el libro y hojeándolo rápidamente,
con mohines de lectora, aunque más bien deletreaba que leía--. ¿Esto qué es? Un libro para
llevar cuentas. ¡Cómo me gusta! Marzo, dice aquí, y luego Pe...setas, y luego céntimos. Es
mu bonito apuntar aquí todo lo que sale y entra. Yo escribo tal cual; pero en los números me
atasco, porque los ochos se me enredan en los dedos, y cuando sumo no me acuerdo nunca de lo
que se lleva.

--Ese libro--dijo Benina, que al punto vislumbró un negocio--, me lo dio un pariente de mi
señora, para que lleváramos por apuntación el gasto; pero no sabemos. Ya no está la Magdalena
para estos tafetanes, como dijo el otro... Y ahora pienso, señoras, que a ustedes, que comercian,
les conviene este libro. Ea, lo vendo, si me lo pagan bien.

--¿Cuánto?

--Por ser para ustedes, dos reales.

--Es mucho--dijo Cuarto e kilo, mirando las hojas del libro, que continuaba en manos de su
compañera--. Y ¿para qué lo queremos nosotras, si nos estorba lo negro?

--Toma--indicó Petra, acometida de una risa infantil al repasar, con el dedo mojado en saliva,
las hojas--. Se marca con rayitas: tantas cantidades, tantas rayas, y así es más claro... Se
da un real, ea.

--¿Pero no ven que está nuevo? Su valor, aquí, lo dice: «dos pesetas».

Regatearon. Almudena conciliaba los intereses de una y otra parte, y por fin quedó cerrado
el trato en cuarenta céntimos, con lápiz y todo. Salió del café la Benina, gozosa, pensando
que no había perdido el tiempo, pues si resultaban fantásticas las pieldras preciosas que en
montones Mordejai pusiera ante su vista, positivas y de buena ley eran las cuatro perras, como
cuatro soles, que había ganado vendiendo el inútil regalo del monomaníaco Trujillo.

XV

El largo descanso en el café le permitió recorrer como una exhalación la distancia entre el
Rastro y la calle de la Cabeza, donde vivía la señorita Obdulia, a quien deseaba visitar y
socorrer antes de irse a casa, pues era indudable que a la niña correspondía la mitad, perra
más o menos, de uno de los duros de D. Carlos. A las doce menos cuarto entraba en el portal,
que por lo siniestro y húmedo parecía la puerta de una cárcel. En lo bajo había un establecimiento
de burras de leche, con borriquitas pintadas en la muestra, y dentro vivían, sin aire ni luz,
las pacíficas nodrizas de tísicos, encanijados y catarrosos. En la portería daban asilo a un
conocido de Benina, el ciego Pulido, que era también punto fijo en San Sebastián. Con él y
con el burrero charló un rato antes de subir, y ambos le dieron dos noticias muy malas: que
iba a subir el pan y que había bajado mucho la Bolsa, señal lo primero de que no llovía, y
lo segundo de que estaba al caer una revolución gorda, todo porque los artistas pedían las
ocho horas y los amos no querían darlas. Anunció el burrero con profética gravedad que pronto
se quitaría todo el dinero metálico y no quedaría más que papel, hasta para las pesetas, y
que echarían nuevas contribuciones, inclusive, por rascarse y por darse de quién a quién los
buenos días. Con estas malas impresiones subió Benina la escalera, tan descansada como lóbrega,
con los peldaños en panza, las paredes desconchadas, sin que faltaran los letreros de carbón
o lápiz garabateados junto a las puertas de cuarterones, por cuyo quicio inferior asomaba el
pedazo de estera, ni los faroles sucios que de día semejaban urnas de santos. En el primer
piso, bajando del cielo, con vecindad de gatos y vistas magníficas a las tejas y buhardillones,
vivía la señorita Obdulia; su casa, por la anchura de las habitaciones destartaladas y frías,
hubiera parecido convento, a no ser por la poca elevación de los techos, que casi se cogían
con la mano. Esteras y alfombras allí eran tan desconocidas, como en el Congo las levitas y
chisteras; sólo en lo que llamaban gabinete había un pedazo de fieltro raído, rameado de azul
y rojo, como de dos varas en cuadro. Los muebles de baratillo declaraban con sus chapas rotas,
sus patas inválidas, sus posturas claudicantes, el desastre de sus infinitas peregrinaciones
en los carros de mudanza.

La misma Obdulia abrió la puerta a Benina, diciéndole que la había sentido subir, y al punto
se vio la buena mujer como asaltada de una pareja de gatos muy bonitos, que mayando la miraban,
el rabo tieso, frotando su lomo contra ella. «Los pobres animalitos--dijo la niña con más lástima
de ellos que de sí misma--, no se han desayunado todavía».

Vestía la hija de Doña Paca una bata de franela color rosa, de corte elegante, ya descompuesta
por el mucho uso, las delanteras manchadas de chocolate y grasa, algún siete en las mangas,
la falda arrastrada, revelándose en todo, como prenda adquirida de lance, que a su dueña le
venía un poco ancha, por aquello de que la difunta era mayor. De todos modos, tal vestimenta
se avenía mal con la pobreza de la esposa de Luquitas.

«¿No ha venido anoche tu marido?--le dijo Benina, sofocada de la penosa ascensión.

--No, hija, ni falta que me hace. Déjale en su café, y en sus casas de perdición, con las socias
que le han sorbido el seso.

--¿No te han traído nada de casa de tus suegros?

--Hoy no toca. Ya sabes que lo dejaron en un día sí y otro no. No ha venido más que Juana Rosa
a peinarme, y con ella se fue mi Andrea. Van a comer juntas en casa de su tía.

--De modo que estás como los camaleones. No te apures, que Dios aprieta, pero no ahoga, y aquí
estoy yo para que no ayunes más de la cuenta, que el cielo bien ganado te lo tienes ya... Siento
una tosecilla... ¿Ha venido ese caballero?

--Sí: ahí está desde las diez. Con las cosas bonitas que cuenta me entretiene, y casi no me
acuerdo de que no hay en casa más que dos onzas de chocolate, media docena de dátiles, y algunos
mendrugos de pan... Si has de traerme algo, sea lo primero para estos pobres gatos aburridos,
que desde el amanecer no me dejan vivir. Parece que me hablan, y dicen: «Pero ¿qué es de nuestra
buena Nina, que no viene con nuestra cordillita?».

--En seguida traeré para remediaros a todos--dijo la anciana--. Pero antes quiero saludar a
ese caballero rancio, que es tan fino y atento con las señoras».

Entró en el llamado gabinete, y el señor de Ponte y Delgado se deshizo con ella en afectuosos
cumplidos de buena sociedad. «Siempre echándola a usted de menos, Benina... y muy desconsolado
cuando brilla usted por su ausencia.

--¡Que brillo por mi ausencia!... ¿Pero qué disparates está usted diciendo, Sr. de Ponte? O
es que no entendemos nosotras, las mujeres de pueblo, esos términos tan fisnos... Ea, quédense
con Dios. Yo vuelvo pronto, que tengo que dar de almorzar a la niña y a los señores gatos.
Y aunque el Sr. D. Frasquito no quiera, ha de hacer aquí penitencia. Le convido yo... no, le
convida la señorita.

--¡Oh, cuánto honor!... Lo agradezco infinito. Yo pensaba retirarme.

--Sí, ya sabemos que siempre está usted convidado en casas de la grandeza. Pero como es tan
bueno, se dizna sentarse a la mesa de los pobres.

--Consideración que tanto le agradecemos--dijo Obdulia--. Ya sé que para el Sr. de Ponte es
un sacrificio aceptar estas pobrezas...

--¡Por Dios, Obdulia!...

--Pero su mucha bondad le inspira estos y otros mayores sacrificios. ¿Verdad, Ponte?

--Ya la he reñido a usted, amiga mía, por ser tan paradójica. Llama sacrificio al mayor placer
que puede existir en la vida.

--¿Tienes carbón?...--preguntó Benina bruscamente, como quien arroja una piedra en un macizo
de flores.

--Creo que hay algo--replicó Obdulia--; y si no, lo traes también».

Fue Nina para adentro, y habiendo encontrado combustible, aunque escaso, se puso a encender
lumbre y a preparar sus pucheros. Durante la prosaica operación, conversaba con las astillas
y los carbones, y sirviéndose del fuelle como de un conducto fonético, les decía: «Voy a tener
otra vez el gusto de dar de comer a ese pobre hambriento, que no confiesa su hambre por la
vergüenza que le da... ¡Cuánta miseria en este mundo, Señor! Bien dicen que quien más ha visto,
más ve. Y cuando se cree una que es el acabose de la pobreza, resulta que hay otros más miserables,
porque una se echa a la calle, y pide, y le dan, y come, y con medio panecillo se alimenta...
Pero estos que juntan la vergüenza con la gana de comer, y son delicados y medrosicos para
pedir; estos que tuvieron posibles y educación, y no quieren rebajarse... ¡Dios mío, qué desgraciados
son! lo que discurrirán para matar el gusanillo... Si me sobra dinero, después de darle de
almorzar, he de ver cómo me las compongo para que tome la peseta que necesita para pagar el
catre de esta noche. Pero ¡ay! no... que necesitará ocho reales. Me da el corazón que anoche
no pagó... y como esa condenada Bernarda no fía más que una vez... será preciso pagarle toda
la cuenta... y a saber si le ha fiado dos o tres noches... No, aunque yo tuviera el dinero,
no me atrevería a dárselo; y aunque se lo ofreciese, primero dormía al raso que cogerlo de
estas manos pobres... ¡Señor, qué cosas, qué cosas se van viendo cada día en este mundo tan
grande de la miseria!».

En tanto el lánguido Frasquito y la esmirriada Obdulia platicaban gozosos de cosas gratas,
harto distantes de la triste realidad. Desde que vio entrar a la Providencia, en figura de
Benina, sintiose la niña calmada de su ansiedad y sobresalto, y el caballero también respiró
por el propio motivo feliz, y se le alegraron las pajarillas viendo conjurado, por aquel día,
un grave conflicto de subsistencias. Uno y otro, marchita dama y galán manido, poseían, en
medio de su radical penuria, una riqueza inagotable, eficacísima, casi acuñable, extraída de
la mina de su propio espíritu; y aunque usaban de los productos de este venero con prodigalidad,
mientras más gastaban, más superabundancia tenían sus caudales. Consistía, pues, esta riqueza,
en la facultad preciosa de desprenderse de la realidad, cuando querían, trasladándose a un
mundo imaginario, todo bienandanzas, placeres y dichas. Gracias a esta divina facultad, se
daba el caso de que ni siquiera advirtiesen, en muchas ocasiones, sus enormes desdichas, pues
cuando se veían privados absolutamente de los bienes positivos, sacaban de la imaginación el
cuerno de Amaltea, y lo agitaban para ver salir de él los bienes ideales. Lo extraño era que
el Sr. de Ponte Delgado, con tener tres veces lo menos la edad de Obdulia, casi la superaba
en poder imaginativo, pues en la declinación de la vida, se renovaban en él los aleteos de
la infancia.

D. Frasquito era lo que vulgarmente se llama un alma de Dios. Su edad no se sabía, ni en parte
alguna constaba, pues se había quemado el archivo de la iglesia de Algeciras donde le bautizaron.
Poseía el raro privilegio físico de una conservación que pudiera competir con la de las momias
de Egipto, y que no alteraban contratiempos ni privaciones. Su cabello se conservaba negro
y abundante; la barba, no; pero con un poco de betún casi armonizaban una con otro. Gastaba
melenas, no de las románticas, desgreñadas y foscas, sino de las que se usaron hacia el 50,
lustrosas, con raya lateral, los mechones bien ahuecaditos sobre las orejas. El movimiento
de la mano para ahuecar los dos mechones y modelarlos en su sitio, era uno de esos resabios
fisiológicos, de segunda naturaleza, que llegan a ser parte integrante de la primera. Pues
con su melenita de cocas y su barba pringosa y retinta, el rostro de Frasquito Ponte era de
los que llaman aniñados, por no sé qué expresión de ingenuidad y confianza que veríais en su
nariz chica, y en sus ojos que fueron vivaces y ya eran mortecinos. Miraban siempre con ternura,
lanzando sus rayos de ocaso melancólico en medio de un celaje de lagrimales pitañosos, de pestañas
ralas, de párpados rugosos, de extensas patas de gallo. Dos presunciones descollaban entre
las muchas que constituían el orgullo de Ponte Delgado, a saber: la melena y el pie pequeño.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10379</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>58781</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21591</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Upon leaving the bathroom it hurt the eyes: on the third day was blind.

As

I still had money, some time could live without imploring the public charity, with sadness inherent
not see, and the equally deep caused by the abrupt transition from working life to sedentary.
The boy was strong and agile for overnight frail and sickly man, Merchant and his ambitions and enthusiasms
of travelers were reduced to a continuous reflect on the uncertainty of earthly goods, and the
infallible justice of God Our Father and Judge feel the hand of the sinner. No one dared to ask
the poor blind man to give her back sight, since it had not granted. It was punishment, and the
Lord will not go back when it hits hard. Time asking his to give him plenty of money to live
comfortably, and muqui love you, but none of this was given to the poor Mordechai, every day
had less money, as these were leaving, but others enter anywhere and of muquieres anything. Those
who approached him pretending you love, would not only his den stealing. One day the man was
very upset about not being able to catch a flea atrociously stung him, taunting him with insolent
audacity, when ... no joke ... it appeared two angels.

XIV

"But you see something, Almudena? - Fourth and asked kilo.

- Watch
me burt them.

"

He explained that distinguished the dark mass in the middle of the light: that it regards the things
of the world from here. But what of the mysterious worlds that extend above and below, front
and rear, outside and inside of us, his eyes were clear, when they saw, the same as you see me.
Well, as two angels appeared to him, as he was not haunt him thing to say nothing, they said they
came from the King of terra baixo an embassy to him. Mr. Samdai had to speak, for which it
was necessary to be my man Slaughter by night, which was burning there ilcienso, and praying in
the middle of the spoils cattle and pools of blood, until twelve o'clock, time constant of
the interview. No should be added that the angels went away with a fresh wind in knowledge
were Mordechai your message, and this took its chess pieces to fumigate the pipe, the ration
of hemp on paper, and went little way of Slaughterhouse: the long encampment before him, he
would smoking less boring.

There he was, squatting, sniffing the fragrant fumes of incense, and smoking pipe after pipe,
until the time came, and primerito he saw was a couple of dogs, larger the cameio, Branco, with
eyes of fire. He, Mordechai, mocha Mede, he removed a Mede breathing. Next came a fix it with
a lot of riders Cantoria, galas mochas, then Rain began to fall very thick sand and stones,
so, so, who was buried up neck ... and not breathing. Median increasingly ... On top of all that happened
slag superfast another squadron of cavalry, giving the whites alquiceles wind, and constantly
shooting shots. There followed a flood of snakes and alcranes, which fell hissing and coiling.
Poor Mede was dying blind, feeling involved in the horrible tag unclean animals ... But Then
came men and women on foot, in slow procession, all with white robes, holding in his hand baskets
and trays of gold, and stepping on flowers as roses and lilies in magically had become snakes
and scorpions, and fragrant mint and branches laurel rained all the
material warm sand and sharp stones.

To avoid fatigue, the King finally appeared, beautiful, human and divine beauty, long beard and black,
earrings, gold crown jewels seemed to be by the sun, moon and stars. Green was his costume,
which was fine as being the work of a highly polished spiders in the deep bosom of the earth
woven with threads of fire. The entourage was Samdai so colorful and bright dazzling. As I asked
Petra if not also His coming Majesty the Queen, he remained standing a moment the narrator,
recalling, and finally realized which also saw Mrs. King, but very stuffy face like the moon
between clouds Mordechai and therefore could not distinguish right. The Sovereign wore yellow,
a color as well as our thoughts when we are between happy and sad. Expressed this the blind
with difficulty supplying the clumsiness of his language with the
physiognomy of the game conviction, and the grimaces and gestures
speak volumes.

Total: than an order of the King you were putting forward all the trays and baskets of gold that
were dressed in white women. What was it? Pieldras of various kinds, mochas, mochas, which
soon formed clumps that would not fit in any home: Rubilar as chickpeas, pearls the size of pigeon
eggs, tudas, tudas large fine diamond in such quantities that they
had to fill bags mochas, and bags a car moving, emeralds such as nuts
and pono trompacios as mine ...

Heard that the three women gawking,
silent, eyes fixed on the face of the blind, half-open mouths.

At the beginning of the relationship, were not willing to believe, and ended up believing by stimulation
of their souls, eager to things pleasant and enjoyable, as compensation for the misery embarrassing
in which they lived. Almudena put all his soul in his voice, and they all spoke the language movable
folds of his face, and even the hairs of his beard black. All were signs, hieroglyphics decipherable,
oriental writing that listeners understood without knowing why. The end of splendid view was that the
king told Mordechai's good that the two things I wanted, wealth and wife could not give more than one;
to opt between the jewels of great value to front watched, and which would enjoy a fortune greater
than that of all the sovereigns of the land, and a good woman, beautiful and industrious, certainly
as rare gem that could not be found but stirring all the earth. Mordechai did not hesitate
a moment in the election, and said to His Baixo terra Majesty, that wanted nothing so much jewels
in bushels, if they did not muqui ... "Want me she ... muqui like me, and without muqui me,
this fine pieldras unwilling or diniero and Naida. "

Then the King Señalole a female wrapped tightly in a blanket that
hid all the face inclusive, was on the road, and told him that was
his, and that continue to catch or rather hunt, then a slight step
was the doomed.

And with that by the King deigned His Majesty disappearing, and with him went all of his entourage,
and fix it and the ladies in white, tudo, tudo, leaving no more than a strong odor of ilcienso,
and the two big dog barking that were lost in the background of the cold night, as if terrified
to flee into the mountains. Mordechai was sick three months after this unique event and would
not eat more than water and barley meal without salt. He remained so thin which had to touch
all the bones without being escaped an account. Finally, crawling as he could, made his way around
the greatness of the world in search of woman who, as divine Samdai said, was his.

"And you found to tantismos years running, and called Nicole - Petra said, wanting to help the
biographer himself.

- What do you know? Not to be Nicole.

- So is the lady - the Diega said, noting not without some impertinence
to poor Benina, not a whimper.

- Me?

... Jesus me excuses! I am no Tarascon who walks along the roads. "

Almudena was from Fez had gone to Algeria, who lived on alms in Tlemcen
first Constantine and Oran then, that at this point he sailed for
Marseilles, and went through all France, Lyon, Dijon, Paris, which
many large with many floors and good olive street all like the back
of the hand.

After climbing up a people who called Lila, turned to Marseilles and Cette, where he sailed for
Valencia.

"And in Valencia found to Nicole, with whom you came to clappers, which gave you the aiuntamientos,
with two cover materials - Petra said - and you you were in Madrid
to Portugal and three years I did the happy, sly, until the slut you
went with another.

- You do not know.

- To tell the story of Nicole
and how he caught him in Madrid to take you to San Bernardino, and
she went to espital, and one night while he slept, he saw two Women
in the other world, eg, souls, to say that Nicole spoke in espital
one that he was to be discharged ...

- Do not be that, not just that:
shut up you.

- One day we will tell - Benina said, that although
he liked to hear those entertained stories, would not stop more, recalling
their pressing chores.

- Wait, madam, what hurry? - Said the Diega -.

Where will you most worth?

- Another day count more - said the blind man smiling -. Mocha me see the world.

- You cansadito, Jai. Convídanos a half to soak you language, you have it drier than shoe leather.

-
I do not invite me to them, b'rrachonas. Not having diniero me.

- Why is not - said Diego, lavish.

- I do not drink - declared Benina -, and I have quickly, and with the permission of the company
I'm leaving.

- Getting you some more. Dar eleven clock.

- Letting - Petra said kindly - in case you need to go to win, that
we we have already won.

"

Questioned by Almudena, reported that having taken the Diega some
money owed two girls in the street from the top deck, were thrown
into the trade, then again and were highly available and mischief
for the buying and selling.

Petra did not feel honest and complete female but when it was dedicated
to traffic, even if in small things, such as chopsticks, mondarajas
of tea, and Torrão.

The other was an eagle and lace handkerchiefs. With that money, come their hands by a miracle,
bought a house gender balance, and on the morning of that day put
their bazaars next to the Arganzuela Fuentecilla, having the kind
of place many races of buttons, sticks, many of lace and two vests
Bayonne.

Another day would remove china, pictures, and horses that gave carton, from gains in factory
Sheep Street. Both spoke at length about your business, and praised each other, Fourth and kilo
because if it was not there for the acquisition of gender by thick, the another one was advancing
in salt and malice for retail sale. Another sign that there was been born to be retailer or
anything, was that the quarter earned in the sale you hit the pocket, awakening in her vague hopes
of saving, while those by other means were at his thin hands, he escaped through his fingers
before could close his fist to keep them.

Benina very attentive heard these explanations, which had the virtue of infusing some sympathy
to the drunk, because she too, Benin, felt businessman, also touched her soul ever dream of
buying and selling. Ah! if, instead of engaging in service, working as a black woman had taken
a front door, another rooster will sing. But old age and the indissoluble moral society Doña
Paca it impossible for the trade.

He stressed the good woman to leave the pleasant chat, and when he rose to say goodbye cayósele
the pen he had given D. Carlos, and when trying to collect soil cayósele
also on the agenda.

"Well, does not lead you there are few things - Petra said, picking up the book and leafing through
it quickly, with grimaces of reading, but spelled more I read -. What is this? A book keep
accounts. How I like it! March, it says here, then Pe ... mushrooms,
then cents.

Is mu bonito point here everything that comes and goes. I write as is, but the numbers I jam,
because I caught on eight fingers, and when most do not remember him ever you get.

- The book - said Benin, which envisioned a business point - a relative gave me my lady to take her
by apuntación spending, but do not know. No longer the Magdalena for these taffeta, and said
the other ... And now I think, ladies, you, trading, they should be this book. Hey, I sell
it, if I pay well.

- How much?

- As for you, two dimes.

- It's a lot - and kilo Fourth said, looking at the pages of the book,
which continued in the hands of co -.

And why do you want us, if we clog the black?

- Toma - Petra said,
children rush to review a laugh, his finger dipped in saliva, leaves
-.

Is marked with broken lines, so many numbers, so many stripes, and
this is more clear ... It gives a real, ea.

- But do not see that
is new?

Its value, here, says: "Two pesetas."

Haggled. Almudena reconciled the interests of both sides, and finally was closed treatment in forty
cents, with pen and everything. Left the cafe the Benina, joyful, thinking who had not lost
time, because if were fantastic in the beautiful pieldras Mordechai
lots put before him, positive and good law was four dogs, as Four
Suns, who had earned selling the useless gift Trujillo monomaniac.

XV

The long break in the cafe allowed to go like a shot the distance between the Trail and Calle de
la Cabeza, where he lived Miss Obdulia, who wanted to visit and help
before leaving home, it was clear that the child belonged half, bitch
more or less, one of the hard of D. Carlos.

A quarter to twelve he entered the portal, that seemed uncanny and
humid outside a prison.

As there was a settlement under donkey's milk, with little donkeys painted in the sample, and
within living without air or light, the nurses of consumptive peaceful, emaciated and cold.
In goal gave asylum to a Benina known, the blind Pulido, who was also a fixed point in San Sebastian.
With him and with Burrero chatted a while before climbing, and they gave him two very bad news:
that would raise the bread and had fallen sharply the stock market, the first signal that it was not
raining, and the latter of which was to drop a fat revolution, all because the artists asked
the eight hours and the masters did not want to give them. Burrero announced soon with prophetic
gravity would remove all the cash money and there would be more than paper, even for the ESP,
and that would throw new contributions, including, for scratching and be a who's who good days.
With these bad impressions Benina up the ladder, as rested as bleak, with the steps in rumen,
the peeling walls, without missing the signs of carbon or pencil scrawled with paneled doors,
through which loomed the lower hinge piece of mat, and dirty street lamps seemed like urns day
Saints. In the first floor, coming down from heaven, with neighborhood cats and a magnificent
view of the shingles and dormers, Miss Obdulia lived, his house, by the width of dilapidated
rooms and cold would like convent, but for the low elevation of the roofs, which almost caught
hand. Mats and carpets were so unknown there, as in the Congo and the Levites top hats; only
in what they called the Cabinet had felt a bit frayed, blue-flowered and red, about two yards
square. The flea market furniture with sheets declared broken disabled legs, limping their
positions, the disaster in its infinite wanderings in moving cars.

It opened the door Obdulia Benina, saying he had felt up, and the point The good woman was assaulted
as a very nice pair of cats that mayando watched, stiff tail, rubbing his back against it.
"The poor animals - said the girl with more feeling about them than herself - not had breakfast
yet. "

He wore the daughter of Doña Paca a pink flannel nightgown, elegant
cut and broken by the heavy use, the front stained chocolate and fat,
some seven in the sleeves, pulled her skirt, revealing at all, as
a token acquired lance, which he owns came a bit wide, by that which
the deceased was older.

However, such clothing got along poorly with poverty Luquitas's wife.

"Did not come last night your husband? - Benina said, breathless from the painful ascent.

- No, daughter, needless to me. Let him in your coffee, and at their homes in ruin, with the members
that have sucked the brains.

- Do not you have brought nothing home for your in-laws?

- Now do not touch. You know that left him in a day every other.

There has been more than Juana Rosa a comb, and she was my Andrea. They will eat together at home
with his aunt.

- So you're like chameleons. Do not worry, that God squeezes but does not drown, and here I'm not
fast for more than note that heaven or what you have already won
... Feel and hacking ... Has been the gentleman?

- Yes, there are
from ten.

With the nice things that has amused me, and I hardly there is no agreement on home more than
two ounces of chocolate, half a dozen dates, and some crusts of bread ... If you bring me something,
be the first for these poor cats bored that since the dawn will not
let me live.

Looks like I speak, and say, "But what is our Good girl, that does not come with our cordillita?.
"

- Then bring to remediaros all - said the old woman -. But I want to greet that gentleman stale,
which is so fine and friendly with the ladies. "

He entered the cabinet called, and M. de Ponte and Delgado broke up
with her loving compliments of the good society.

"Whenever you throwing it less, Benina ... and very distressed when you shine by their absence.

-
That shine for my absence! ... But what nonsense are you saying, Mr. de Ponte? O do not understand
is that we women of a village, such terms as Fisnar ... Hey, stay
with God.

I'll be back soon, I have to give lunch to the girl and Mr cats. And although Mr. D. Frasquito
forbid, has to do penance here. I invited him ... no, you Miss invites.

- Oh, how much honor! ... I am not ungrateful. I thought I retire.

- Yes, we know that you are always invited houses of greatness.

But as is so well, you dizna sit at the table of the poor.

- Taking into account that both thank you - said Obdulia -. I know that Mr. de Ponte is a sacrifice
to accept these poverty ...

- By God, Obdulia! ...

- But his great kindness inspires these and other great sacrifices.

Right, Ponte?

- I have already fought for you, my friend, for being so paradoxical.

Llama sacrifice the greatest pleasure that can exist in life.

- Do you have coal ?...-- Benina asked abruptly, as one who throws a stone into a solid flowers.

-
I think there is something - said Obdulia - and if not, bring it too. "

Nina was inward, and having found fuel, though small, began to turn fire and prepare their pots. During
the prosaic operation, talked with chips and coals, and using the bellows as a conduit phonetic
he said: "I'm having again like to feed the hungry poor, who confesses his hunger for shame
that gives ... How much misery in this world, Lord! Well say who else has seen, else sees. And when you
create one that is the last straw poverty, is that there are others more miserable, because
one takes to the street and ask, and give, and eat, and half a bagel is fed ... But those who
join the shame with the desire to eat, and are sensitive and thrive for request, the ones that
were possible and education, and will not stoop ... God, how unfortunate are! it will flow to
kill the bug ... If I have money left after giving him lunch, I see how I compose to take the
penny you need to pay cot tonight. But alas! no ... you'll need eight reales. Heart tells
me that last night did not pay ... and how that trust does not Bernard ordered more than once
... will need to pay any account ... already know if you have two
or three nights on credit ... No, but I had the money, I would not
give it, and although it offered, first slept in the open to catch
it these poor hands ... Lord, what, what things are seeing every day
in this world so big misery!

".

While the languid and scrawny Frasquito Obdulia talked joyful pleasant things, distant tired
of the sad reality. Since I saw her come to Providence, in figure Benin, the girl felt herself
calm your anxiety and shock, and the gentleman also breathed by the very happy occasion, and
was glad to see the birds conjured them by the day, a serious conflict of subsistence. Each
other, well-worn faded lady and leading man, had, in through its radical shortage, an inexhaustible
wealth, efficacious, almost mint, extracted from the mine of his own spirit, and though they used
the products of this venerable lavishly, the more you spend, more glut had their flows. It
was, therefore, this wealth on the faculty lovely detached from reality, when they wanted,
moving to a imaginary world, all bienandanzas, and such pleasures. With this divine faculty,
if it was not even warned, in many cases, enormous sufferings, because when they were deprived
of property absolutely positive, taken out of the imagination Amalthea's horn, and waved to
see out of it the ideal property. The strange thing was that Mr. de Ponte Delgado, having at
least three times the age of Obdulia, nearly exceeded in imaginative power, as in the decline
of life, was renovated in the flapping childhood.

D. Vial was what is commonly called a soul from God. His age was not known, or in part have consisted,
for he had burned the church record of Algeciras where he was baptized. He had the physique
of a rare privilege that could compete with conservation of the mummies Egypt, which did not
alter setbacks and hardships. His black hair is kept and abundant beard, no, but with a little
polish almost harmonized with each other. Spent hair, not the romantic, disheveled and sullen,
but those used to the 50, shiny, with a side parting, well ahuecaditos tufts over the ears.
Movement hand to cup the two strands and modeling in place, was one of those bad habits physiological,
second nature, they become part of the first. Well with Melenita of kink and beard greasy and
retinta's face was Frasquito Ponte they call childish, not to know what expression of naivete
and trust that you would see in nose girl, and her eyes were lively and were already dying. Always
looked tenderly, throwing the rays of sunset amid gloomy clouds of the horizon of bleary tear, tab
sparse, eyelid rough, large crow's feet. Two assumptions stood out among many that were the
pride of Ponte Delgado, namely the hair and small feet</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>