<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09087</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>445564</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24521</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Yo pensaba pasar esta tarde a palacio
para preguntar a doña Visita por su salud.

--Calla, tonta; nunca me he sentido mejor: especialmente desde esta mañana. La bofetada que
he dado a «ésos» no asistiendo al coro por no rozarme con ellos me ha puesto de un humor magnífico.
Para que conste mejor mi intención, he venido a verte. Quiero que sepan que estoy bien, que
lo de la enfermedad no es cierto. Que se enteren todos en Toledo que el arzobispo no quiere
ver a sus canónigos, y que esto lo hace por dignidad, no por soberbia, pues al mismo tiempo
baja a ver a su antigua amiga la jardinera.

Y el temible hombrón reía como un niño al pensar en el disgusto que esta visita podía dar a
los del cabildo.

--Y, no creas, Tomasa--continuó--, que he venido a verte sólo por conveniencia; esta tarde
estaba triste en palacio, me aburría. Visitación anda ocupada con unas amigas de Madrid, y
yo he sentido ese arrechucho que me da de vez en cuando al recordar el pasado. Sentía necesidad
de verte, y he pensado además en que el jardín de la catedral es siempre fresco. Fuera de aquí
hace un calor de horno... ¡Ay, Tomasa!, ¡qué fuerte te veo! Tan delgada y tan ágil, te mantienes
mejor que yo. No estás envuelta en grasa como este pecador, ni tienes dolencias que te amarguen
las noches. Tu pelo aún está casi negro, la dentadura se conserva bien, no necesitas, como
este cardenal, llevar un artefacto dentro de la boca.... Pero de todos modos, Tomasa, eres
vieja como yo. Nos quedan pocos años de vida, por mucho que el Señor quiera conservarnos. ¡Quién
pudiese volver a aquellos tiempos, cuando subía a tu casa con la sotanita roja, en busca de
tu padre el sacristán, y te quitaba el almuerzo! ¿Eh, Tomasa...?

Los dos ancianos, olvidando las diferencias sociales, con esa fraternidad resignada de los
seres que caminan a la muerte, recordaban el pasado. Todo estaba lo mismo que en su niñez:
el jardín, el claustro; la catedral no había cambiado.

Su Eminencia, cerrando los ojos, se creía aún el monago travieso de medio siglo antes. La espiral
azulada de su cigarrillo parecía arrastrar su pensamiento por las interminables revueltas del
pasado.

--¿Te acuerdas cómo se burlaba de mí tu pobre padre? «Este chiquillo--decía en la sacristía--es
un Sixto V.» «¿Qué quieres ser?», me preguntaban. Y yo respondía siempre lo mismo: «Arzobispo
de Toledo.» ¡Y poco que se burlaba el buen sacristán de la seguridad con que hablaba yo de
mis pretensiones! Cuando me consagraron obispo, cree, Tomasa, que me acordé mucho de él, sintiendo
que hubiese muerto. Habría gozado viendo sus lágrimas de alegría al contemplarme con la mitra
en la cabeza.... Yo os he querido siempre; sois una familia excelente, y muchas veces me matasteis
el hambre.

--Calle, señor, calle y no recuerde esas cosas. Yo soy la que tengo que agradecerle que sea
tan bueno, tan llanote, a pesar de su categoría, que casi es la que viene detrás del Papa....
Y la verdad es--añadió la vieja con la arrogancia de su franqueza--que nada pierde siendo así.
Amigas como yo no tendrá usted ninguna. A usted no le rodean más que aduladores y pillos, como
a todos los grandes de la tierra. Si se hubiera quedado en cura de misa y olla, nadie le miraría
la cara; pero Tomasa continuaría siendo su amiga, siempre dispuesta a hacerle un servicio.
Si le quiero tanto, es porque usted es sencillo y afable. Si gastase orgullo, como otros arzobispos,
le besaría el anillo y ¡hasta la vista! El cardenal en su palacio y la jardinera en su jardín.

El prelado acogía con sonrisas la franqueza enérgica de la buena mujer.

--Usted siempre será don Sebastián para mí--continuó--. Cuando me dijo que no le llamase Eminencia
y todos esos tratamientos que le da la gente, lo agradecí más que si me hubiese regalado el
manto de la Virgen del Sagrario. Se me atragantaba tanto tratamiento; me daban ganas de gritar:
«¡Pero qué porra de Eminencia e Ilustrísima, si nos hemos arañado de pequeños mil veces, porque
este grandísimo ladrón no veía mendrugo ni albaricoque en mis manos que no quisiera zampárselo!»
Gracias que le hablo de usted desde que le vi beneficiado de la catedral, pues a un sacerdote
no está bien tutearle como a un monago.

Quedaron silenciosos los dos viejos. Sus miradas vagaban por el jardín con cierto enternecimiento,
como si en cada árbol o arcada cubierta de follaje encontrasen un recuerdo.

¿Sabe usted lo que ahora me viene a la memoria?--dijo Tomasa--. Pues me acuerdo de otra vez
que nos vimos aquí mismo, en este jardín, hace una friolera de años: lo menos cuarenta y ocho
o cincuenta. Yo estaba con mi pobre hermana mayor, que acababa de casarse con Luna el jardinero.
Por el claustro andaba rondándome el que luego fue mi marido. Vi entrar en el cenador un hermoso
soldadote, un sargento, con gran ruido de espuelas, el chafarote al brazo y un casco con rabo,
como el de los judíos del Monumento. Era usted, don Sebastián, que había venido a Toledo para
ver a su tío el beneficiado, y no quería marcharse sin visitar a su amiga Tomasita. ¡Y qué
guapo estaba usted! Es la verdad; no lo digo por adularle. ¡Tenía usted un aire de pillo para
las muchachas! Hasta recuerdo que me dijo algo sobre lo hermosa y fresca que me encontraba
después de los años de ausencia. A usted no le sienta mal que recuerde esto, ¿verdad? Eran
chicoleos de soldado. ¡Tantos diría entonces! Cuando se fue usted, dijo mi cuñado: «Éste ha
colgado los hábitos para siempre; es inútil que su tío el beneficiado quiera hacerlo sacerdote.»

--Fue una locura de la juventud--dijo el cardenal, que sonreía con orgullo recordando al arrogante
sargento de dragones--. En España sólo hay tres carreras dignas del hombre: la de la espada,
la de la Iglesia o la de la toga. La sangre me bullía, y quise ser soldado; pero tuve la desgracia
de pillar tiempos de paz. Mi carrera hubiese sido lenta, y para no amargar los últimos años
de mi tío, seguí sus consejos y reanudé los estudios, volviendo a la Iglesia. En un sitio y
en otro se puede servir a Dios y a la patria; pero cree que muchas veces, con todo mi cardenalato
a cuestas, pienso con envidia en aquel militar que tú viste. ¡Qué tiempos tan dichosos! Aún
me tira la espada. Cuando veo a los cadetes, cambiaría a gusto con cualquiera de ellos, entregándoles
mi báculo y mi cruz. ¡Y tal vez lo hiciese mejor que todos ellos! ¡Ah! ¡si volviesen aquellos
tiempos de la Reconquista, en que los prelados salían a matar moros! ¡Qué gran arzobispo de
Toledo hubiese hecho yo...!

Y don Sebastián erguía su cuerpo de anciano obeso, estirando los brazos con la arrogancia de
los últimos restos de su vigor.

--Usted ha sido siempre muy hombre--dijo la jardinera--. Yo se lo digo muchas veces a ciertos
curitas qué hablan de usted, criticándolo por si patatín o patatán. «No jueguen ustedes con
Su Eminencia, que es muy capaz de entrar un día en el coro, y a éste quiero y a éste no, sacarlos
a todos a bofetada limpia.»

--Más de una vez he estado tentado de hacerlo--dijo el prelado con firmeza, brillando en sus
ojos una chispa de energía--. Pero me detiene la consideración de mi cargo y mi carácter de
sacerdote pacífico. Soy pastor del católico rebaño, no lobo que aterra a las ovejas con su
fiereza. Pero a veces no puede uno más, y ¡Dios me perdone! he sentido la tentación de levantar
el cayado para empezar a golpes con el rebaño rebelde que se guarece en la catedral.

El prelado excitábase hablando de sus luchas con el cabildo. La placidez de espíritu que le
proporcionaba la tranquilidad del jardín desaparecía al recordar a sus hostiles subordinados.
Necesitaba, como otras veces, confiar sus pesares a la jardinera, con esa benevolencia instintiva
que impulsa a los grandes a franquearse con los humildes.

--Tú no sabes, Tomasa, lo que esos hombres me hacen sufrir. Quiero dominarlos porque soy el
amo, porque me deben obediencia con arreglo a la disciplina, sin la cual no habría Iglesia
ni religión, y se me resisten y me desobedecen. Mis órdenes son cumplidas a regañadientes,
y cuando quiero imponerme, hasta el último cura sale con lo que llama sus derechos, y me pone
pleito, y acude a la Rota y a Roma si es preciso. Vamos a ver: ¿soy el amo o no lo soy? ¿Es
que el pastor discute con sus ovejas y las consulta para guiarlas por el buen camino...? Me
marean y aturden con sus pleitos y cuestiones. No hay entre ellos ni medio hombre; todos son
chismosos y cobardes. En mi presencia tienen la vista baja; sonríen y alaban a Su Eminencia;
y apenas vuelvo la espalda, son víboras que intentan morderme, lenguas de escorpión que nada
respetan... ¡Ay, Tomasa! ¡Hija mía! ¡Tenme lástima! Cree que cuando pienso en esto me pongo
muy enfermo.

Y el prelado palidecía, abandonando su asiento con gesto doloroso, como si sus entrañas se
conmoviesen con intensas punzadas.

--No haga usted caso--dijo la jardinera--. Usted está por encima de todos; usted los vencerá.

--Claro que los venceré; ¡pues no faltaba más! Sería la primera vez que quedase debajo. Estas
triquiñuelas de comadres me molestan poco. Sé que al final veré a mis pies a los repugnantes
enemigos. ¡Pero sus lenguas, Tomasa! ¡Lo que dicen de los seres que más amo en el mundo! Esto
es lo que me hiere, lo que me mata.

Volvió a sentarse, aproximándose a la jardinera para hablar en voz queda:

--Tú conoces mi pasado mejor que nadie; te lo he contado porque me inspiras gran confianza.
Además, tú eres lista, y lo que no sabes lo adivinas. Conoces lo que es Visitación para mí,
e indudablemente no ignoras lo que esos miserables dicen de ella. No te hagas la tonta: lo
sabes; todos en la catedral y aun fuera de ella se enteran de esas calumnias y las creen. Tú
eres la única que no puedes creerlas, porque conoces la verdad... Pero ¡ay!, la verdad no puedo
decirla, no puedo gritarla: me lo impiden estos hábitos.

Y agarraba un puñado de su sotana con los dedos crispados, como si quisiera rasgarla.

Transcurrió un largo rato de silencio. Don Sebastián miraba al suelo con ojos duros, contrayendo
sus manos como si quisiera agarrar a los invisibles enemigos. De vez en cuando sentía las punzadas
de su enfermedad y suspiraba dolorosamente.

--¿Por qué pensar en tales cosas?--dijo la jardinera--. Se pone usted malo, y para esto no
era preciso que se molestase bajando a verme. Mejor hubiera hecho quedándose en palacio.

--No; tú me distraes; encuentro cierto consuelo comunicándote mis penas. Allá arriba me desespero
solo, teniendo que hacer esfuerzos para tragarme la rabia. No quiero que se enteren mis familiares,
pues serían capaces de reírse; no quiero que sepa nada mi pobre Visitación... ¡Y yo no sé disimular!,
¡no puedo fingir alegría cuando estoy irritado...! ¡Qué infierno el que sufro! ¡No poder decir
que he sido hombre, que he sido débil, como hecho de carne que soy, y que llevo conmigo los
frutos de mi falta, sin querer separarme de ellos aunque la calumnia me persiga! Cada uno obra
como quien es, y yo quiero ser bueno en medio de mis pecados. Podía haberme separado de mis
hijos, haberlos abandonado, como hacen otros por conservar su fama de santos; pero yo soy hombre,
me enorgullezco de ello: un hombre con sus defectos y sus virtudes, ni una más ni una menos
que la generalidad de los humanos. El sentimiento de la paternidad está en mí tan arraigado,
tan hondo, que antes perdería la mitra que abandonar a mis hijos. Ya recuerdas cómo me puse
cuando murió el padre de Juanito, que pasaba por mi sobrino. Creí morir. ¡Un hombrón tan hermoso
y con un porvenir tan brillante! Yo le hubiese hecho magistrado, presidente del Supremo, ministro,
¡qué sé yo! Y en veinticuatro horas se me muere, como si el cielo quisiera castigarme. Es verdad
que me queda mi nieto; pero ese Juanito en nada se parece a su padre, y te lo confieso: le
quiero poco; no veo en él más que un reflejo lejano de mi pobre hijo. De mi pasado, de aquella
época que fue la más feliz de mi vida, sólo me resta Visitación. Es el retrato de la pobre
muerta; ¡la adoro! Y esta dicha mezquina me la turba esa gentuza con sus calumnias... ¡Hay
para matarlos!

Dominado por el grato recuerdo de la primavera que había florecido en sus primeros años de
obispo, allá en una diócesis andaluza, repetía a Tomasa, una vez más, sus relaciones con cierta
dama devota que sentía desde la niñez horror al mundo. La devoción los había juntado, pero
la vida no tardó en recobrar sus fueros, abriéndose paso en sus relaciones casi místicas y
uniéndolos en carnal abrazo. Habían vivido fieles uno al otro en el misterio de la vida eclesiástica,
amándose con prudencia escrupulosa, sin que el secreto de sus relaciones trascendiese al público,
hasta que ella murió, dejándole dos hijos. Don Sebastián, hombre de enérgicas pasiones, sentía
la paternidad hasta la vehemencia. Aquellos dos seres eran la imagen de la pobre muerta, el
recuerdo del único idilio de una vida dedicada por completo a la ambición. Las calumnias que
circulaban los enemigos, fundándolas en la presencia de su hija en el palacio arzobispal, le
ponían como loco.

--¡La creen mi querida!--decía con acento iracundo--. ¡Mi pobre Visitación, tan buena, tan
cariñosa, tan mansita para todo, convertida en una cualquiera por esos miserables! ¡Una amante
que he sacado para mi diversión del Colegio de Doncellas nobles...! ¡Como si yo, viejo y enfermo,
estuviera para pensar en esas porquerías! ¡Indecentes...!, ¡miserables...! ¡Por menos se cometen
muchos crímenes...!

--Déjelos que digan; Dios está en lo alto y nos ve a todos.

--Lo sé; pero esto no basta a tranquilizarme. Tú tienes hijos, Tomasa, y conoces lo que es
quererlos. No sólo nos hiere lo que se hace contra ellos, sino lo que se dice... ¡Qué días
llevo de sufrimiento! De pequeño ya sabes que toda mi ilusión era llegar a lo que soy. Miraba
el trono del coro y pensaba en lo bien que se estaría en él, en la inmensa felicidad de ser
príncipe de la Iglesia. Pues bien; ya estoy en el trono. He caminado medio siglo apartando
las piedras, dejando la piel y hasta la carne en las zarzas de la cuesta. ¡Yo sé cómo pude
salir del montón negro y llegar a obispo! Después... ¡ya soy arzobispo!, ¡ya soy cardenal!,
¡ya no puedo llegar a más! ¿Y qué? La felicidad siempre marcha delante de nosotros, como la
nube de luz que guiaba a los israelitas. La vemos, casi la tocamos, pero no se deja coger.
Me siento ahora más infeliz que en la época en que luchaba por ser algo y me creía el más desgraciado
de los hombres. No tengo la juventud: la altura en que me veo, fijas en mí todas las miradas,
me impide defenderme. ¡Ay, Tomasa! Compadéceme, soy digno de lástima. ¡Ser padre, y tener que
ocultarlo como un crimen! ¡Querer a mi hija con un cariño que se acrecienta más y más conforme
se aproxima la muerte, y tener que sufrir que la gente tome este afecto tan puro por algo repugnante...!

Y la terrible mirada de don Sebastián, que asustaba a toda la diócesis, nublóse con lágrimas.

--Además, tengo otras penas--continuó--, pero son de hombre previsor que teme el porvenir.
Cuando muera, todo lo que tengo será para mi hija. Juanito cuenta con lo de su madre, que era
rica, y además tiene una carrera y el apoyo de mis amigos. Visitación será poderosa. Ya sabes
que-mis adversarios me echan en cara lo que ellos llaman mi avaricia. Avaricioso, no: previsor,
amante del bienestar de los míos. He ahorrado mucho; no soy de los que reparten pan a la puerta
de su palacio, ni busco la celebridad por la limosna. Tengo dehesas en Extremadura, muchas
viñas en la Mancha, casas, y sobre todo, papel del Estado, mucho papel. Como buen español,
quiero ayudar al gobierno con mi dinero, tanto más cuanto que ésto produce ganancias. No sé
ciertamente lo que poseo: serán veinte millones de reales: tal vez más. Todo ahorrado por mí,
aumentado con buenos negocios. No puedo quejarme de la suerte; el Señor me ha ayudado. ¡Y todo
para mi pobre Visitación! Mi gozo sería verla casada con un hombre bueno, pero ella no quiere
separarse de mí. Le atrae la iglesia, y éste es mi miedo. No lo extrañes, Tomasa; yo, príncipe
de la Iglesia, tiemblo al ver cómo se entrega a la devoción, y hago cuanto puedo por desviarla.
Me gusta la mujer religiosa, no la devota que sólo se encuentra bien en la iglesia. La mujer
debe vivir, debe gozar y ser madre. Siempre he mirado mal a las monjas.

--Déjela, señor--dijo la jardinera--. Nada tiene de extraño que le guste la iglesia. Del modo
como vive, no puede tener otras aficiones.

--Por hoy, nada temo. Estoy a su lado, y nada me importa que guste del trato con monjitas.
Pero puedo morir mañana, y ¡figúrate qué magnífico bocado será la pobre Visita con sus millones,
sola, y con esa afición a la vida religiosa, que otros más listos pueden explotar...! Yo he
visto mucho; soy de la clase y estoy en el secreto. No faltan órdenes religiosas que se dedican
a la caza de herencias, para mayor gloria de Dios, según dicen. Además, andan por ahí esas
monjas extranjeras, de gran papalina, que son linces para esta clase de trabajo. Me aterra
el pensar que caigan sobre mi hija. Yo soy del catolicismo a la antigua, de aquella religiosidad
española neta: un catolicismo castellano, como quien dice de panllevar, limpio de extranjerías
modernas. Sería triste haber pasado la vida ahorrando, para engordar a los jesuítas o a esas
hermanas que no saben hablar en castellano. No quiero que mis dineros sufran la misma suerte
que los del sacristán del adagio. Por esto, a los sinsabores de mi lucha con la gentuza enemiga
se une el dolor que me causa el carácter débil de mi hija. Tal vez la cacen, y algún tuno se
ría de mí apoderándose de mi dinero.

Y excitado por sus negros pensamientos, soltó una interjección castiza y obscena, recuerdo
de sus tiempos de soldado. En presencia de la jardinera, no tenía por qué contenerse. La vieja
estaba acostumbrada a los desahogos de su carácter.

--Vamos a ver--dijo imperiosamente, después de un largo silencio--. Tú que me conoces mejor
que nadie: ¿soy tan malo como suponen los enemigos? ¿Merezco que el Señor me castigue por mis
faltas? Tú eres un alma de Dios, sencilla y buena, y sabes más de esto con tu instinto que
todos los doctores en Teología.

--¿Usted malo, don Sebastián? ¡Jesús...! Usted es un hombre como los otros: ni más ni menos.
Tal vez mejor que muchos, pues es sencillo, todo de una pieza, sin engaños ni hipocresías.

--Un hombre: tú lo has dicho. Soy un hombre como los demás. Los que llegamos a cierta altura
somos como los santos que están en las fachadas de las iglesias. De abajo, causan admiración
por su hermosura; vistos de cerca, producen horror por la fealdad de la piedra roída por el
tiempo. Por más que intentemos santificarnos, poniéndonos a distancia, no somos más que hombres;
seres de carne flaca para aquellos que nos rodean. En la Iglesia son contadísimos los que se
libran de las pasiones humanas. ¡Y quién sabe si aun esos pocos privilegiados no se sienten
mordidos por el demonio de la vanidad, y al extremar los ascetismos de su vida, piensan en
la gloria de verse en los altares...! El sacerdote que logra dominar la carne cae en la avaricia,
que es el vicio eclesiástico por excelencia. Yo jamás he atesorado por vicio; he ahorrado para
los míos, nunca para mí.

Calló largo rato el prelado; pero en su irresistible afán de confesarse con la sencilla mujer,
continuó:

--Estoy seguro de que no me despreciará Dios cuando llegue mi hora. Su infinita misericordia
está por encima de todas las pequeñeces de la vida. ¿Cuál es mi delito? Haber amado a una mujer,
como mi padre amó a mi madre; tener hijos, como los tuvieron apóstoles y santos. ¿Y qué? El
celibato eclesiástico es una invención de los hombres, un detalle de disciplina acordado en
los concilios; pero la carne y sus exigencias son anteriores en muchísimos siglos: datan del
Paraíso. Quien salta esta barrera, no por vicio, sino por pasión irresistible, porque no puede
vencer el impulso de crear una familia y tener una compañera, ése falta indudablemente a las
leyes de la Iglesia, pero no desobedece a Dios.... Al aproximarse la muerte, tengo miedo. Muchas
noches dudo y tiemblo como un niño.... Yo he servido a Dios a mi modo. En otros tiempos le
hubiera defendido con la espada, peleando contra los herejes; ahora soy su sacerdote, y por
él batallo cada vez que veo la impiedad de los tiempos cercenar algo de su gloria. El Señor
me perdonará, recibiéndome en su seno. Tú que eres tan buena, Tomasa, y tienes alma de ángel
bajo tu corteza ruda, ¿no lo crees así...?

La jardinera sonrió, y sus palabras atravesaron con lentitud el silencio de la tarde agonizante.

--Tranquilícese, don Sebastián. Yo he visto muchos santos en esta casa, y valían menos que
usted. Por asegurar su salvación hubiesen abandonado a los hijos. Por mantener lo que llaman
la pureza del alma habrían renegado de la familia. Créame usted a mí: aquí no entran santos;
hombres, todos hombres. No hay que arrepentirse de haber seguido el impulso del corazón. Dios
nos hizo a su imagen y semejanza, y por algo nos puso el sentimiento de la familia. Lo demás,
castidad, celibato y otras zarandajas, lo inventaron ustedes para distinguirse del común de
las gentes. Sea usted hombre, don Sebastián, que cuanto más lo sea, resultará más bueno y mejor
lo acogerá el Señor en su gloria.

IX

Pocos días después del Corpus, una mañana don Antolín fue en busca de Gabriel. El Vara de plata
sonreía a Luna, hablándole con aire protector.

Había pensado en él toda la noche. Le dolía verle inactivo, paseando por el claustro. La falta
de ocupación era lo que le inspiraba aquellas ideas tan perversas.

--Vamos a ver--añadió--: ¿te convendría bajar conmigo todas las tardes a la catedral para enseñar
el Tesoro y las demás preciosidades? Vienen muchos extranjeros que apenas si se dejan entender
cuando me preguntan. Tú conoces su lenguaje: sabes el francés, el inglés y no sé cuántos idiomas
más, según afirma tu hermano. La catedral ganaría mucho pudiendo demostrar a esos extranjeros
que tiene un intérprete a su disposición; tú nos harías un favor y no perderías nada. Siempre
es un entretenimiento ver caras nuevas. En cuanto a recompensa....

Se detuvo aquí don Antolín, rascándose la cabeza por debajo del bonete. Vería de arañar algo
de los fondos de la Obrería; si no era posible en el primer momento, por estar flaca y escurrida
la renta de la Primada, ya se proveería más adelante. Y aguardó con mirada ansiosa la respuesta
de Gabriel. Éste mostróse conforme. Al fin era un huésped de la catedral, y algo la debía.
Y desde aquella tarde bajó al templo a la hora de coro para enseñar a los extranjeros las riquezas
de la iglesia.

Nunca faltaban viajeros que, exhibiendo los papelillos de colores de don Antolín, esperaban
el momento de admirar las alhajas. El Vara de plata no veía un extranjero que no se imaginase
que era un lord o un duque, extrañándose muchas veces de su desgarbo en el vestir. Para él,
sólo los grandes de la tierra podían permitirse el placer de viajar, y abría unos ojos escandalizados
e incrédulos cuando Gabriel afirmaba que muchas de aquellas gentes eran zapateros de Londres
o tenderos de París que se daban en las vacaciones el regalo de una excursión por el antiguo
país de los moros.

Avanzaban por las naves cinco canónigos con sobrepellices de coro, cada uno con una llave en
la mano. Eran los guardadores del Tesoro. Abría cada cual la cerradura confiada a su custodia,
giraba pesadamente la puerta y quedaba abierta la capilla con sus antiguas riquezas. En enormes
vitrinas, como en un museo, se exhibía la vieja opulencia de la catedral: imágenes de plata
maciza; globos enormes coronados por graciosas figurillas, todo de precioso metal; arquillas
de marfil de complicada labor; custodias y viriles de oro; enormes platos dorados y repujados,
con escenas mitológicas que resucitaban la alegría del paganismo en aquel rincón sórdido y
polvoriento del templo cristiano. Las piedras preciosas extendían su gama de colores por pectorales,
mitras y mantos de la Virgen. Eran diamantes tan enormes que hacían dudar de su autenticidad,
esmeraldas del tamaño de guijarros, amatistas, topacios y perlas, muchas perlas, a centenares,
a miles, caídas como granizo sobre las vestiduras de la Virgen, Los forasteros admirábanse
ante esta opulencia, deslumbrados por su enormidad, mientras Gabriel, habituado a la visita
diaria, lo miraba todo fríamente. El Tesoro tenía un aire de vetustez lamentable. Las riquezas
habían envejecido con la catedral. Los diamantes no brillaban, el oro parecía empañado y polvoriento,
la plata se ennegrecía, las perlas estaban opacas y como muertas. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07684</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>114275</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22383</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I planned to spend this evening at the
palace Visit Donna to ask about his health.

- Shut up, fool, I've
never felt better, especially since this morning.

The slap I have given to "those" not attending to the choir with them, grazed my not put me
in a great mood. For the record my best intentions, I have come to see you. Please know that I'm fine,
what the disease is not true. That they know everyone in Toledo that the archbishop does not
see its canons, and this makes for dignity, not for pride, because while low to see his old
friend the gardener.

And the fearsome big man laughed like a child to think about the disappointment that this visit
could give the town hall.

- And, believe me, Tomasa - continued
- I come to you only as a convenience, this afternoon was upset in
the palace, I was bored.

Visitation busy walking with some friends in Madrid and I have felt that arrechucho that gives
me time to time to reminisce. Felt need see you, and I thought well in the garden of the cathedral
is always fresh. Outta here Heat oven makes ... Oh, Thomas, how strong I see! So thin and so quick,
you keep better than me. You're not wrapped in fat as this sinner, or have medical conditions
that bitter tea night. Your hair is still almost black, well-preserved teeth, no need, as This cardinal,
wearing a device in the mouth .... But anyway, Tomasa, you old like me. We have a few years of
life, much as the Lord would preserve us. Who could return to those days when up to your house
with the red sotanita, seeking your father, the sexton, and I took off for lunch! Hey, Tomasa
...?

The two old men, ignoring the social differences, with the resignation
of fraternity beings who walk to death, they remembered the past.

Everything was the same as in childhood: the garden, the cloister, the cathedral had not changed.

His
Eminence, closing his eyes, he still believed the acolyte Naughty half century earlier. The
spiral blue drag of his cigarette seemed his mind by the endless
riots past.

- Do you remember how fun of me your poor father?

"This boy - said in the sacristy - it a Sixto V. "What will you be?" I asked. And I said the same
thing: "Archbishop of Toledo. "And some that mocked the good sexton of the confidence with which
I spoke of my claims!

When I was consecrated bishop, he believes, Tomasa, I remembered a lot from him, feeling that he
had died. Would have enjoyed seeing his tears of joy to contemplate with the miter in the head
.... I have always loved, you are an excellent family, and many times you killed me hunger.

-
Calle, sir, street and remember those things. I am that I have to thank it so good, so llanote, despite
its category, which is almost in the back of Pope .... And the truth is - said the old with the
arrogance of his candor - which loses nothing that way. Friends like me you will not have any. You
do not surround more than sycophants and crooks, as all the great
land.

If it had been a priest for Mass and pot, no one would look face, but Thomas would continue
to be their friend, always ready to do a service. If you want both, it is because you are simple
and friendly. If you spend pride, like other bishops, would kiss the ring and hasta la vista!
The cardinal in his palace and the gardener in your garden.

The bishop welcomed with smiles energetic openness of the good woman.

- You will always be Don Sebastian for me - continued -.

When he told me not to call him Eminence and all those treatments
that gives people, I thanked him more than if I had given the mantle
of the Virgin del Sagrario.

It choked me further treatment, I wanted to scream: "But what Eminence truncheon and Grace, if we
scratched small thousand times, because thief saw this great crust and apricot in my hands
that I would not scoff! " Thanks I talk to you since I saw him benefited from the cathedral, as
a priest is not well tutearle as an acolyte.

The two old men were silent. His eyes wandered around the garden with some tenderness, as if each
tree or foliage covered arcade find a souvenir.

Do you know what now comes to my memory? - Said Tomasa -. Then again I remember we met here
in this garden, a whopping years ago: the least forty-eight or fifty. I was with my poor sister,
who had just married the gardener Luna. Walked through the cloister which was then hovering around
my husband. Vi enter a beautiful arbor soldadote, a sergeant, with a great noise of spurs, the Shiv
arm and a helmet with a tail like the Jews of the Monument. Were you, Don Sebastian, who had come
to Toledo see his uncle, the beneficiary, and would not leave without visiting his friend Tomasita.
And what you were cute! It's the truth I do not mean flatter. You had a rogue air for Girls!
I even remember that I said something about how beautiful and fresh that I was after years of
absence. You do not feel bad to remember, right? Were chicoleos soldier. So many say then!
When it was you, my brother said: "This has hung habits forever, it is useless to his uncle,
the priest wants to do it benefited. "

- It was a folly of youth - said the Cardinal, smiling with pride recalling the arrogant Sgt dragons
-. In Spain there are only three races worthy of man of the sword, of the Church or the toga.
My blood boiled, and I wanted to be a soldier, but had the misfortune to catch peacetime. My career
had been slow, and not bitter in recent years my uncle, I followed your advice and return to
school, returning to the Church. In one place and in another it can not serve God and country,
but believes that many times, with all my cardinal in tow, I think with envy that you saw military.
What times so happy! Even I pulled the sword. When I see the cadets would change comfortable
with any of them, giving them my staff and my cross. Doing so and maybe better than all of them! Ah!
Who should they be returned time of the Reconquista, in which the prelates went to kill Moors!
What a great Archbishop of Toledo had made me ...!

And Don Sebastian stood his old body fat, stretching his arms with the arrogance of the last
remnants of his force.

- You have always been men - said the gardener -. I tell you many times a certain bandages do
they talk about you, criticizing him for if patatin or potatoes. "Do not play with you His Eminence,
who is very able to get a day in the choir, and I want and it does
not, remove them slap everyone to clean.

"

- More than once I've been tempted to do so - said the prelate firmly, shining in their eyes
a spark of energy -. But I stopped considering my position and my character peaceful priest. I
am pastor of the Catholic flock, not a wolf that frightens the sheep
with fierceness.

But sometimes one can not more, and God forgive me! I've been tempted to raise the staff to
start a fight with the rebel who flock shelter in the cathedral.

The prelate excitábase talking about his struggles with the council.

The calmness of spirit that provided the tranquility of the garden disappeared hostile to remind
their subordinates. Needed, as usual, confide his sorrows to the gardener, with that instinctive
benevolence that drives the big to cross with the humble.

- You do not know, Tomasa, which these men make me suffer. I am the master because master, because
I owe obedience under the discipline, without which there would be no Church or religion, and
I resist and disobey me. My orders are complied reluctantly and when I want to impose, to the
last priest comes out with what he calls his rights, and makes me litigation, and go to the
Rota and Rome if necessary. Let's see: I am the master or am I not? Is it discusses the shepherd
with his sheep and consultation to guide them in the right direction ...? I dizzy and stunned
with their disputes and issues.

There is no middle man between them, they are all gossips and cowardly. In my presence with
downcast eyes, smile and praise to His Eminence and just turn my
back, they are snakes who try to bite, scorpion than anything language
respect ... Oh, Thomas!

My daughter! Hold me sorry! Cree when I think I get it very sick.

And the prelate paled, leaving his seat with painful gesture, as if his bowels moved by intense
throbbing.

- Pay no attention - said the gardener -. You are above all, you win.

- Of course I shall overcome, because not so! Be the first time that it is below. These wives'
tricks annoy me slightly. I know that eventually I will see my feet to the repugnant enemies.
But their languages, Tomasa! What they say about things I love most in the world! This is what
hurts me, what kills me.

He sat down again, closer to the gardener to speak quietly,

- You know my past better than anyone I've told you because you inspire great confidence. Besides,
you are ready, and I guess you do not know.

Visitation know what is for me and certainly not ignore what these wretches say about it.
Do not play dumb: the You know, all in the cathedral and even outside
these slanders they hear and believe.

You you're the one that you can not believe them, because you know the truth ... But alas, I can
not quite say it, I can not cry: me prevent these habits.

And grab a handful of his cassock with clenched fingers, as if to tear it.

It took a long silence. Don Sebastian looked down with hard eyes, contracting his hands as if to
catch the invisible enemy. Occasionally felt pangs of their illness and sighed painfully.

- Why think about such things? - Said the gardener -. It makes you bad, and this is not was
necessary to bother coming down to me. Best had been staying at the palace.

- No, you distracted me, find some comfort communicating my sorrows. Up there, I despair alone, having
to make efforts to swallow the rage. I do not want them to know my family they would be able to laugh,
do not want you to know anything my poor Visitation ... And I do not know disguise!, I can not fake
joy when I'm angry ...! What the hell I suffer! Unable to say I've been a man, I've been weak,
as I am made of flesh, and I carry the fruits of my fault, not wanting to part with them even
slander after me! Each work as she is, and I want to be good in the midst of my sins. I could
have separated from my children have abandoned them, as others to maintain their reputation
of saints, but I am a man, I am proud of it: a man with his faults
and virtues, no more nor less the generality of humans.

The feeling of parenthood is so ingrained in me, so deep, you lose before the miter to leave
my children. And remember how I got when Juanito's father died, was going through my nephew. I
thought he died. A beautiful big man and a future so bright! I had made judge, Chief Justice
minister I do not know! And in twenty-four hours I die, as if heaven would punish me. True
I have left my grandchild, but that Juanito in no way resembles his father, and I confess: I I bit, I
do not see it but a distant reflection of my poor child. In my past, that time that was the happiest
of my life, I can only Visitation. A portrait of the poor dead, I love it! And that this petty
rabble me that the mob with their slander ... There to kill them!

Dominated by the fond memories of the spring which had flourished in its early years bishop in
a diocese there Andalusian Tomasa repeated once more, his relations
with certain devout lady felt since childhood horror to the world.

Devotion had gathered, but life does not soon recover its rights, breaking through in their
relationship almost mystical uniting them in carnal embrace. They had lived faithful to each other
in the mystery of church life, loving wisely scrupulous, without the secret of their relationship
transcended the public, until she died, leaving two children. Don Sebastian, a man of strong passions,
I felt parenthood to the vehemence.

Those two things were the image of the poor dead, the I remember
the one romance of a life entirely devoted to ambition.

Calumnies circulating enemies, rooted in the presence of his daughter in the archbishop's
palace, he put like crazy.

- The think my dear! - Said in a tone angry -. My poor Visitation, so good, so affectionate,
so tame for all converted into any one of these wretches! A lover I've taken my fun for the
College of noble maidens ...! As if I, old and sick, was to think about that crap! Indecent
...!, miserable ...! For less committed many crimes ...!

- Let them say, God is high and sees us all.

- I know, but this is not enough to reassure me. You have children, Tomasa, and you know what
love them. Not only hurts us what you do against them, but what you say ... Which days I've been
suffering! As a child you know that my dream was to become what I am. Looking the throne of the
chorus and thought how good it would be him in the immense joy of
being Prince of the Church.

Well, I'm on the throne. I walked half a century away stones, leaving
the skin and even the meat in the bushes of the hill.

I know how I black mass exit and get to Bishop! Then ... Archbishop am already!, And I am
a cardinal!, I can not get more! So what? Happiness always march ahead of us, as bright cloud
guided the Israelites. We see, almost touch, but not get caught. I now feel more unhappy than
at the time struggling to be something and I thought the most unfortunate men. I have no youth:
the height where I am, look at me all the looks, prevents me defend myself. Oh, Thomas! Pity me,
I'm pitiful. Being a parent, and having conceal a crime! Wanting my daughter with a love that
grows more and more as death approaches, and having to suffer people to take this love so
pure for something disgusting ...!

And the dreadful sight of Sebastian, which frightened the whole diocese, hazy with tears.

- Also, I have other pains - continued - but are farsighted man who fears the future. When I die,
all I have is for my daughter. Juanito has about his mother, who was rich, and has a career and
support my friends. Visitation will be powerful. You know that, my adversaries reproach me what
they call my greed. Greedy, no: proactive, welfare lover of mine.

I saved a lot, I'm not handing out the bread at the door of his palace, nor seek celebrity for
charity.

I have pastures in Extremadura, many vineyards in La Mancha, houses, and especially the role
of the state, a lot of paper. As good Spanish I want to help the government with my money, especially
as this produces a profit. I do not know certainly what I have: will be twenty million reais,
maybe more. All saved for me increased with good business. I can not complain of fate, the Lord
has helped me. And all Visitation for my poor! My joy would see her married to a good man,
but she does not want leave me. You like the church, and this is my fear. Do not be surprised,
Tomasa, I, Prince of the Church, I shudder to see how it comes to devotion, and do all I can to
deflect it. I like the religious woman, devoted not only found it in the church. Women must live,
must enjoy and be a mother. I've always looked bad to the nuns.

- Leave it, sir - said the gardener -. No wonder you like the church. Mode as live, can not have
other hobbies.

- For today, I fear no evil. I am at your side, and I care not who likes dealing with nuns.
But I can die tomorrow, and just imagine how great the poor bite will visit with his millions,
alone, and with this love of religious life which others can exploit
ready ...!

I seen a lot, I'm in class and I'm in the secret. There is no shortage religious orders engaged
hunting for inheritance, for the greater glory of God, they say. In addition, those out there
foreign nuns of great coif, who are lynxes for this kind of work. It terrifies me thinking
about my daughter falling.

I'm from the old Catholicism, of that religion net Spanish: Castilian Catholicism, as they say
in panllevar, clean Aliens modern.

It would be sad to have spent my life saving, to fatten the Jesuits or those sisters who can
not speak in Castilian. I want my money not suffer the same fate The sexton of the adagio. Therefore,
the troubles of my fight with the enemy mob joins the pain it causes the weak character of
my daughter. Perhaps the hunt, and a rascal is fun of me taking over my money.

And excited by his dark thoughts, gave a pure and obscene interjection, I remember of his time
as a soldier. In the presence of the gardener, had no reason to hold back. The old was used
to the outbursts of his character.

- Let's see - he said desperately, after a long silence -.

You know me better nobody: I'm as bad as supposed enemies? Do I deserve that God will punish me
for my faults?

You are a good soul, simple and good, and you know more about this with your instinct all doctors
in Theology.

- Do you mean, Mr. Sebastian? Jesus ...! You are a man like any other, neither more nor less.
Perhaps better than most, it is simple, all in one piece, without deception or hypocrisy.

- A man: You have said. I am a man like everyone else. We reach a certain height we are like
saints in the church facades. Below, are admired for their beauty, viewed closely, a horror by the
ugliness of the stone gnawed by time. As much as we try to sanctify us, putting us at a distance,
we are but men weak flesh beings to those around us. In the church are few and those get rid
of human passions. And who knows if even those few do not feel privileged bitten by the demon
of vanity, and the extreme asceticism of his life, they think seen the glory of the altars ...!
The priest who manages to dominate the meat falls into greed, which
is the ecclesiastic service excellence.

I've never treasured by service, I have saved for mine, never for me.

The prelate was silent a long time, but in his irresistible desire to confess to the simple woman
continued

- I'm sure God will not despise me when my time comes. His infinite mercy is above all the littleness
of life. What is my crime? Having loved a woman as my father loved my mother, have children,
as were apostles and saints. So what? The ecclesiastical celibacy is an invention of men, a detail
of agreed discipline councils, but the flesh and their demands are
many centuries earlier, dating from Paradise.

Whoever breaks this barrier, not vice, but irresistible passion,
because it can not overcome the impulse to create a family and have
a companion, that certainly needed to Church law, but disobeys God
.... Approaching death, I have fear.

Many nights doubt and tremble like a child .... I have served God in my way. At other times he
had defended with the sword, fighting heretics, now I'm your priest,
and He battled every time I see the wickedness of the times curtail
some of its glory.

The Lord forgive me, receiving me in his bosom. You who are so good, Tomasa, and you have a soul
of an angel under your bark rough, do not you think so ...?

The gardener smiled, and his words pierced the silence slowly dying afternoon.

- Calm down, Mr. Sebastian. I have seen many saints in this house worth less than you. To ensure
their salvation had abandoned the children. To maintain what they call the purity of the soul
would have denied the family. Believe you me, come here not saints;
men, all men.

No regret having followed the impulse of the heart. God made us in His image and likeness, and
gave us some sense of the family. Moreover, chastity, celibacy and other trifles, which you invented
to distinguish from ordinary people. Whether you are a man, Don Sebastian, the more it is, will
be more good and better will welcome the Lord in his glory.

IX

Corpus few days after a morning Don Antolin was in search of Gabriel. Silver Stick Luna smiled,
talking with a patronizing air.

He had thought about him all night. It hurt him inactive, walking in the cloister. Lack occupation
was what inspired those ideas as evil.

- Let's see - he said -: "I should be down with me every evening at the Cathedral to teach Treasury
and other treasures? Many foreigners come to understand only if left when asked. You know its
language, know the French, I do not know how many languages more, according to your brother. The
cathedral may prove to win a lot of these foreign having an interpreter available, you'd do
us a favor and do not lose anything. Always is entertainment to see new faces. As a reward ....

Don
Antolin stop there, scratching his head under the bonnet. Would be to scratch something of funds
Obrería, if it was not possible at first, being weak and drained income of the Primacy, as
would be provided later. And waited with anxious eyes the answer Gabriel. He showed himself satisfied.
At the end was a guest of the cathedral, and something should. And since that afternoon down
to the temple choir when to teach foreign riches of the church.

Never missing passengers, displaying color confetti Don Antolin, expected Time to admire the
jewelry. Silver Stick not seen a foreigner who does not imagine I was a lord or a duke, wondering
many times their clumsiness in dress. For him, only the great of the earth could afford the pleasure
of traveling, and opened some eyes shocked and incredulous when Gabriel
said that many of these people were shoemakers in London or Paris
shopkeepers were given in the holiday gift of a trip by former country
of the Moors.

The ships moved through five canons to surplices chorus,
each with a key hand. They were the guardians of the Treasury. Opened
every lock in their custody, heavily spun and left the door open the
chapel with its ancient treasures. In large displays, like a museum,
displaying the old opulence of the cathedral silver images massive,
huge balloons topped by graceful figurines, all of precious metal;
chests complicated task ivory, gold and virile custody; huge golden
plates and embossed, mythological scenes came back to life the joy
of paganism in that sordid spot dusty Christian church. Gemstones
extended their range of colors pectoral turbans and robes of the Virgin.
Diamonds were so huge that cast doubt on its authenticity, pebble-sized
emeralds, amethysts, topaz and pearls, many pearls, hundreds, thousands,
dropping like hail on the garments of the Virgin, The strangers were
astonished before this opulence, dazzled by its sheer size, while
Gabriel, accustomed to visiting Daily, I looked around coldly. The
Treasury had an air of sad disrepair. Riches had aged with the cathedral.
The shining diamonds, gold seemed tarnished and dusty, The blackened
silver, pearls were dull and dead</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>