<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>509008</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23440</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Era su hijo el joven que había visto entrando en el albergo cuando él marchaba á encargarse
de la goleta para llevar combustible á los submarinos alemanes.

VIII

EL JOVEN TELÉMACO

Siempre que el Mare nostrum volvía á Barcelona, Esteban Ferragut experimentaba una sensación
de deslumbramiento, lo mismo que si se abriese un glorioso ventanal en su existencia obscura
y monótona de hijo de familia.

Ya no vagaba por el puerto, admirando de lejos los grandes trasatlánticos anclados frente al
monumento de Colón ó los vapores de carga que se alineaban en los muelles comerciales. Un buque
importante era de su absoluta propiedad por algunas semanas. El capitán y los oficiales pasaban
el tiempo en tierra con sus familias. Tòni, el segundo, era el único que dormía á bordo. Muchos
de los marineros solicitaban permiso para vivir en la ciudad, y el vapor quedaba confiado á
la guarda del tío Caragòl, con media docena de hombres para la diaria limpieza.

El pequeño Ferragut podía hacerse la ilusión de que era el capitán del Mare nostrum. Se movía
en el puente imaginándose que estaba arrostrando una gran tormenta; examinaba los instrumentos
náuticos con una gravedad de experto conocedor; corría todos los departamentos habitables del
buque, bajaba á las bodegas, que se aireaban, abiertas, en espera de carga, y finalmente se
metía en el bote de servicio, desamarrándolo de la escala, para remar unas horas con más satisfacción
que en los ligeros yoles del Club de Regatas.

Sus visitas terminaban en la cocina, invitado por el tío Caragòl, que le trataba con una familiaridad
paternal. El joven remero estaba sudando. «¿Un refresquet?...» Y preparaba su dulce mixtura,
que hacía caer á los hombres de un solo salto en las nebulosidades de la embriaguez.

Esteban tenía en mucho los «refrescos» del cocinero. Su imaginación, excitada por la frecuente
lectura de novelas de viajes, le había hecho concebir un tipo de marino heroico, atrevido,
galanteador, y capaz de tragarse á jarros las bebidas más incendiarias sin pestañear. El quería
ser así; todo buen navegante debe beber.

Aunque en tierra no conocía otros licores que los inocentes y dulzones guardados por su madre
para las fiestas de familia, una vez pisaba la cubierta del buque sentía la necesidad de líquidos
alcohólicos, para hacer ver que era todo un hombre. «No había en el mundo una bebida que pudiese
con él...» Y al segundo «refresco» del tío Caragòl quedaba sumido en plácido nirvana, viéndolo
todo de color de rosa y considerablemente agrandado: el mar, los buques cercanos, los docks
y la montaña de Montjuich, que servía de fondo.

El cocinero, al contemplarle amorosamente con sus ojos enfermos, creía haber dado un salto
atrás de docenas de años y hallarse todavía en Valencia hablando con el otro Ferragut que se
escapaba de la Universidad para remar en el puerto. Casi llegó á creer que había vivido dos veces.

Escuchaba las quejas del muchacho, interrumpiéndolas con solemnes consejos. Este Ferragut de
quince años se mostraba descontento de la vida. Era un hombre, y tenía que vivir entre mujeres:
su madre y dos sobrinas que le acompañaban haciendo encajes, lo mismo que ella había acompañado
en otro tiempo á su suegra doña Cristina. Quería ser marino, y le obligaban á estudiar las
materias antipáticas del bachillerato. ¿Acaso un capitán necesita saber latín?...

Deseaba terminar su vida de estudiante, para hacerse piloto y seguir las prácticas en el puente,
al lado de su padre. Tal vez llegase á mandar á los treinta años el Mare nostrum ú otro buque
semejante.

Mientras tanto, la atracción del mar le arrastraba lejos de las aulas, yendo á ver á Caragòl
á la misma hora en que sus profesores pasaban lista á los alumnos, anotando sus ausencias.

El viejo y su protegido se recluían en la cocina con una inquietud de culpables. Pasos y voces
en la cubierta alteraban su conversación. «¡Escóndete!» Y Esteban se metía debajo de una mesa
ó se ocultaba en el cuartucho de las provisiones, mientras el cocinero salía al encuentro del
recién llegado con una cara seráfica.

Algunas veces era Tòni, y el muchacho osaba salir, contando con su silencio. También éste le
quería y aprobaba su aversión por los libros.

Si de tarde en tarde era el capitán el que venía al buque por unos momentos, Caragòl le hablaba
obstruyendo la puerta con su cuerpo, al mismo tiempo que sonreía maliciosamente.

Para Esteban, las dos cosas más dignas de admiración eran el mar y su padre. Todos los héroes
novelescos que desde las páginas de los libros habían pasado á alojarse en su imaginación tenían
el rostro y los gestos del capitán Ferragut.

De pequeño había visto llorar algunas veces á su madre con resignada tristeza. Años adelante,
al conocer con su precocidad de muchacho poco vigilado las relaciones que existen entre hombres
y mujeres, presintió que todas estas lágrimas debían ser motivadas por ligerezas é infidelidades
del lejano navegante.

El adoraba á su madre con una pasión de hijo único y mimado, pero no admiraba menos al capitán,
excusando todas las faltas que pudiese cometer. Su padre era el hombre más valiente y más hermoso
de la tierra. Así lo veía él. Y un día que, examinando los cajones de su camarote, encontró
varias fotografías de mujeres llevando al pie los nombres de lejanos países, su admiración
aún fué más grande. Todas debían haber enloquecido de amor por el capitán del Mare nostrum.
¡Ay! Por más que él hiciese al ser hombre, nunca llegaría á igualarse con este triunfador que
le había dado la existencia...

Cuando el buque llegó á Barcelona sin su propietario de vuelta de Nápoles, el hijo de Ferragut
no experimentó ninguna sorpresa.

Tòni, que era siempre de pocas palabras, las prodigó en la presente ocasión. El capitán Ferragut
se había quedado allá por un negocio importante, pero no tardaría en volver. Su segundo le
esperaba de un momento á otro. Tal vez hiciese el viaje por tierra, para llegar antes.

Esteban se asombró al ver que su madre no aceptaba esta ausencia como un suceso insignificante.
La buena señora se mostró preocupada y con los ojos lacrimosos. Su instinto femenil le hacía
presentir algo malo en el retraso de su marido.

Por la tarde, cuando la visitó, como de costumbre, su antiguo enamorado el catedrático, los
dos hablaron lentamente, con palabras medidas, pero entendiéndose con los ojos durante los
largos intervalos de silencio.

Llegado don Pedro á la cumbre de su carrera gloriosa con la posesión de una cátedra en el Instituto
de Barcelona, visitaba todas las tardes á Cinta, pasando hora y media en su salón con exactitud
cronométrica. Ni el más leve pensamiento de impureza agitó jamás al profesor. Lo pasado había
caído en el olvido... Pero él necesitaba ver diariamente á la esposa del capitán tejiendo encajes
entre sus dos pequeñas sobrinas, como había visto años antes á la viuda de Ferragut.

Le hacía saber los sucesos más importantes de Barcelona y del mundo entero; comentaban juntos
los futuros destinos de Esteban; oía él con arrobamiento su voz dulce, concediendo gran importancia
á los detalles de economía doméstica ó á las descripciones de fiestas religiosas, sólo porque
era ella la que hacía tales relatos.

Muchas veces quedaban en largo mutismo. Don Pedro representaba la paciencia, el humor igual,
el respeto silencioso, en aquella casa tranquila y limpia, que únicamente perdía su calma monástica
al presentarse el dueño por unos días, entre dos viajes.

Cinta se había acostumbrado á las visitas del catedrático. Al marcar el reloj las tres y media
presentía sus pasos en la escalera.

Si alguna tarde no llegaba, la dulce Penépole sufría una decepción.

--¿Qué le pasará á don Pedro?--preguntaba á sus sobrinas con inquietud.

Esta pregunta la hacía algunas veces extensiva al hijo; pero Esteban, sin odiar al visitante,
le apreciaba en muy poco.

Don Pedro pertenecía al grupo de aquellos señores del Instituto que pagaba el gobierno para
que fastidiasen con sus explicaciones y sus exámenes á la juventud. Recordaba aún los dos años
que había pasado en su cátedra, como en una cámara de tormento, sufriendo el suplicio del latín.
Además, era un miedoso, que siempre temía resfriarse y no osaba salir á la calle en los días
nublados si le faltaba el paraguas. A él que le hablasen de hombres valientes.

--No sé...--respondía á su madre--. Tal vez estará metido en cama, con siete pañuelos en la cabeza.

Cuando volvía don Pedro, la casa recobraba su normalidad de reloj pausado y seguro. Doña Cinta,
de consulta en consulta, había acabado por considerar indispensable su colaboración. El catedrático
suplía dulcemente la autoridad del marido viajero: él se había encargado de representar al
jefe de la familia en todos los asuntos exteriores... Muchas veces le esperaba con impaciencia
la esposa de Ferragut para pedirle un consejo urgente, y él emitía su opinión con voz lenta,
después de largas reflexiones.

Esteban encontraba intolerable que este señor, que no era mas que un pariente lejano de su
abuela, se mezclase en los asuntos de la casa, pretendiendo dirigirle á él como un padre. Pero
aún le irritaba más verlo de buen humor y con pretensiones de gracioso. Le daba rabia que llamase
á su madre Penépole y á él joven Telémaco... «¡Tío latero y pesado!»

El joven Telémaco no vacilaba en sus venganzas. De pequeño interrumpía sus diversiones para
«trabajar» en el recibidor, junto al perchero vecino á la puerta. Y el pobre catedrático encontraba
abollado su sombrero de copa, con los pelos en desorden, ó salía llevando en las haldas del
gabán varios salivazos.

Ahora el muchacho se limitaba á ignorar su existencia, pasando ante él sin reconocerle, saludándolo
únicamente cuando su madre se lo ordenaba.

El día en que trajo la noticia de la vuelta del vapor sin su capitán, don Pedro hizo la visita
más larga que de costumbre. Cinta derramó dos lágrimas sobre los encajes, pero tuvo que cortar
su llanto, vencida por el buen sentido de su consejero.

--¿Por qué llorar y calentarse la cabeza con tantas suposiciones sin fundamento?... Lo que
usted debe hacer, hija mía, es llamar á ese Tòni que es el segundo del buque. El debe saberlo
todo... Tal vez le diga la verdad.

Recibió Esteban el encargo de buscarle al día siguiente, y pudo darse cuenta de la inquietud
que experimentó Tòni al saber que doña Cinta quería hablarle. Salió del buque con lúgubre mutismo,
como si le llevasen á sufrir tormentos mortales. Luego canturreó sordamente, lo que era en
él indicio de honda preocupación.

No pudo asistir el joven Telémaco á la entrevista, pero rondó por las inmediaciones de la puerta
cerrada, alcanzando á oír algunas palabras en voz más fuerte que se deslizaron por las rendijas.
Su madre era la que hablaba con más frecuencia. Tòni repetía con voz sorda las mismas excusas:
«No sé. El capitán va á llegar de un momento á otro...» Pero al verse fuera del salón y de
la casa, estalló su cólera contra él mismo, contra su maldito carácter que no sabía mentir,
contra todas las mujeres, malas y buenas. Creía haber dicho demasiado. Aquella señora tenía
una habilidad de juez para extraer las palabras.

En la noche, á la hora de la cena, la madre apenas abrió la boca. Sus dedos comunicaron un
temblor nervioso á los platos y los tenedores. Miraba á su hijo con trágica conmiseración,
como si presintiese enormes desgracias que iban á desplomarse sobre su cabeza. Opuso un mutismo
desesperado á las preguntas de Esteban, y al fin exclamó:

--¡Tu padre nos abandona!... ¡Tu padre se ha olvidado de nosotros!...

Y salió del comedor para ocultar las lágrimas que habían afluído á sus párpados.

El muchacho durmió algo intranquilo, pero durmió. La admiración que sentía por su padre y cierta
solidaridad con los ejemplares fuertes de su sexo le hicieron tener en poco estos llantos.
¡Cosas de mujeres! Su madre no sabía ser la esposa de un varón extraordinario como el capitán
Ferragut. El, que era todo un hombre á pesar de sus pocos años, iba á intervenir en el asunto
para poner en claro la verdad.

Cuando Tòni, desde la cubierta del buque, le vió avanzar por el muelle á la mañana siguiente,
tuvo tentaciones de esconderse... «¡Doña Cinta, que le llamaba otra vez para interrogarle!...»
Pero se tranquilizó al decirle el muchacho que venía por su voluntad á pasar unas horas en
el Mare nostrum. Aun así, quiso evitar su presencia, como si temiese algún descuido al hablar
con él, y fingió trabajos en las bodegas. Luego salió del buque, yendo á visitar á un amigo
en un vapor algo lejano.

Esteban entró en la cocina, llamando alegremente al tío Caragòl. Tampoco éste era el mismo.
Sus ojos húmedos y rojizos miraban al muchacho con una ternura extraordinaria. Detenía repentinamente
su lengua, con una expresión de inquietud en el rostro. Miraba indeciso en torno de él, como
si temiese que fuera á abrirse un precipicio ante sus pies.

No olvidaba nunca los respetos debidos á todo visitante de sus dominios, y preparó dos «refrescos».
Por primera vez iba á obsequiar á Esteban en esta vuelta de viaje. Los días anteriores, por
inverosímil que parezca el hecho, no había pensado en confeccionar uno siquiera de sus delirantes
brebajes. El regreso de Nápoles á Barcelona había sido triste; el buque tenía un ambiente fúnebre
sin su dueño.

Por todas estas razones, se le fué la mano á Caragòl en la medida, prodigando la caña hasta
que el líquido tomó un color de tabaco.

Bebieron... El joven Telémaco empezó á hablar de su padre cuando los vasos sólo guardaban la
mitad del «refresco», y el cocinero agitó ambas manos en el aire, dando un gruñido que significaba
su deseo de no ocuparse de la ausencia del capitán.

--Tu padre volverá, Estevet--añadió--. Volverá, pero no sé cuándo. Seguramente más tarde de
lo que asegura Tòni.

Y no queriendo decir más, se tragó todo el resto del vaso, dedicándose á la confección de un
segundo «refresco» precipitadamente, para recobrar el tiempo perdido.

Poco á poco se deshizo la prudente barrera que contenía su verbosidad, y habló con el mismo
abandono de siempre; pero su flujo de palabras no arrastraba noticias precisas.

Caragòl predicó moral al hijo de Ferragut; una moral á su modo, interrumpida por frecuentes
caricias al vaso.

--Estevet, hijo mío, respeta mucho á tu padre. Imítale como marino. Sé bueno y justiciero con
los hombres que mandes... pero ¡huye de las mujeres!

¡Las mujeres!... No había tema mejor para su elocuencia de ebrio piadoso. El mundo le infundía
lástima. Todo en él estaba gobernado por la infernal atracción que ejerce la hembra. Los hombres
trabajaban, peleaban, querían hacerse ricos ó célebres, todo por conquistar la posesión de
un pedazo de carne, el más inmundo y vergonzoso del cuerpo humano.

--Mira cómo será, Estevet, que hasta en los animales comestibles no hay cocinero que sepa aprovecharlo.
Siempre lo arrojan á la basura... Créeme, hijo mío: no imites en eso á tu padre.

El viejo había dicho demasiado para retroceder, y tuvo que ir soltando á fragmentos todo lo
restante. Así se enteró Esteban de que el capitán andaba en amoríos con una señora de Nápoles,
y se había quedado allá fingiendo negocios, pero en realidad dominado por la influencia de
esta mujer.

--¿Es guapa?--preguntó el muchacho con avidez.

--Guapísima--repuso Caragòl--. ¡Y unos olores!... ¡y un ruido de ropas finas!...

Telémaco se estremeció con una sensación contradictoria de orgullo y de envidia. Admiró á su
padre una vez más, pero esta admiración sólo duró breves instantes. Una nueva idea se apoderó
de él, mientras el cocinero seguía hablando.

--No vendrá por ahora. Conozco lo que son esas mujeres elegantes y llenas de perfumes: verdaderos
demonios que enclavijan sus uñas cuando agarran y hay que cortarles las manos para que suelten...
¡Y el buque sin trabajar, como si estuviese varado, mientras que los otros se llenan de oro!...
Créeme, hijo mío: en el mundo sólo esto es verdad.

Y acabó de beberse de un trago todo lo que quedaba del segundo vaso.

Mientras tanto, el muchacho seguía dando forma en su pensamiento á una idea sugerida por la
dulce embriaguez. ¡Si él fuese á Nápoles para traer á su padre!...

En este momento todo le parecía posible. El mundo era de color de rosa, como siempre que lo
contemplaba vaso en mano junto al tío Caragòl. Los obstáculos resultaban blandos, todo se arreglaba
con prodigiosa facilidad; los hombres podían caminar á saltos.

Pero horas después, cuando su pensamiento quedó limpio de nubes seductoras, sintió miedo acordándose
de su padre. ¿Cómo le recibiría al verle llegar?... ¿Qué excusa darle de su presencia en Nápoles?...
Tembló evocando la imagen de su ceño fruncido y sus ojos irritados.

Al día siguiente, una repentina confianza se sobrepuso á esta inquietud. Se acordó del capitán
tal como le había visto algunas veces al celebrar desde la cubierta del buque sus hazañas de
remero en el puerto de Barcelona ó al comentar con los amigos la inteligencia y la fuerza de
su hijo. La imagen del héroe paterno surgía ahora en su memoria con los ojos bondadosos y una
sonrisa que parecía agitar como un viento dulce el bosque de sus barbas.

Le diría toda la verdad. Le haría saber que llegaba á Nápoles para llevárselo, como un buen
camarada que socorre á otro en un peligro. Tal vez se irritase y le diese un golpe; pero él
conseguiría su propósito.

El carácter de Ferragut renació en él con toda la fuerza de un argumento decisivo. Si el viaje
resultaba absurdo y peligroso... ¡mejor! ¡mucho mejor! Bastaba esto para que lo emprendiese.
Era un hombre, y no debía conocer el miedo.

Durante dos semanas preparó su fuga. Nunca había hecho un viaje importante. Sólo una vez había
acompañado á su padre en una rápida excursión de negocios á Marsella. Hora era ya de que saliese
á correr el mundo un hombre como él, que conocía por sus lecturas casi todos los pueblos de
la tierra.

El dinero no le preocupaba. Doña Cinta lo tenía en abundancia, y era fácil encontrar su manojo
de llaves. Un vapor viejo y lento, mandado por un amigo de su padre, acababa de entrar en el
puerto y zarpaba al día siguiente para Italia.

Aceptó este marino al hijo de su camarada sin papeles de viaje. El arreglaría la irregularidad
con sus amigos de Génova. Entre capitanes se debían estos servicios; y Ulises Ferragut, que
esperaba á su hijo en Nápoles--así lo afirmó Esteban--, no iba á perder el tiempo en vano por
unas formalidades oficinescas.

Telémaco, con mil pesetas en el bolsillo extraídas de un costurero que servía á su madre de
caja de caudales, se embarcó al día siguiente. Una pequeña maleta sacada de su casa con lentas
y hábiles astucias era todo su equipaje.

De Génova fué á Roma, y de aquí á Nápoles, con el atrevimiento de la inocencia, empleando palabras
españolas y catalanas para reforzar un italiano de corto léxico adquirido en las representaciones
de opereta. El único informe positivo que le guiaba en su viaje de aventuras era el nombre
de albergo de la ribera de Santa Lucía que le había dado Caragòl como residencia de su padre.

Buscó á éste inútilmente durante varios días. Visitó á los consignatarios de Nápoles, que se
imaginaban al capitán de regreso á su país hacía mucho tiempo.

Al no encontrarle sintió miedo. Debía estar ya en Barcelona, y lo que había empezado como un
viaje heroico iba á convertirse en una fuga de adolescente travieso. Se acordó de su madre,
que tal vez lloraba á aquellas horas releyendo la carta que le había dejado para anunciarle
el objeto de su fuga.

Sobrevino además repentinamente la intervención de Italia en la guerra, suceso que todos esperaban,
pero que muchos veían aún lejano. ¿Qué le quedaba que hacer en este país?... Y una mañana había
desaparecido.

Como el portero del hotel no podía decir más, el padre, una vez pasada la primera impresión
de sorpresa, pensó en la conveniencia de visitar la casa consignataria. Tal vez allí le diesen
otras noticias.

La guerra era lo único interesante para los de esta oficina. Pero Ferragut, dueño de buque
y antiguo cliente, fué guiado por el director hasta dar con los empleados que habían recibido
á Esteban.

No sabían gran cosa. Recordaban vagamente á un joven español que decía ser hijo del capitán,
pidiéndoles noticias de éste. Su última visita había sido dos días antes. Dudaba entre volver
á su país por ferrocarril ó embarcarse en uno de los tres vapores que estaban en el puerto
listos á salir para Marsella.

--Creo que se ha ido en ferrocarril--dijo uno de los empleados.

Otro de ellos apoyó á su compañero con rotunda afirmación, para atraerse la mirada del jefe.
Estaba seguro de su partida por tierra. El mismo le había ayudado á calcular lo que le costaría
el viaje á Barcelona.

Ferragut no quiso saber más. Necesitaba marcharse cuanto antes. Este viaje inexplicable de
su hijo era para él un remordimiento y un motivo de alarma. ¿Qué ocurría en su casa?

El director de la oficina le indicó un vapor francés que salía aquella misma tarde para Marsella,
procedente de Suez. El se encargaba de arreglar todo lo concerniente á su pasaje y de recomendarlo
al capitán. Sólo quedaban cuatro horas para la salida del buque; y Ulises, después de recoger
sus maletas y enviarlas á bordo, dió un último paseo por todos los lugares donde había vivido
con Freya. ¡Adiós, jardines de la Villa Nazionale y blanco Acuario!... ¡Adiós, albergo!...

La inexplicable presencia de su hijo en Nápoles había amortiguado el disgusto por la fuga de
la alemana. Pensó tristemente en el amor perdido, pero pensó al mismo tiempo, con doloroso
titubeo, en lo que podría ver al entrar en su casa.

Poco antes de la puesta del sol zarpó el vapor francés. Hacía muchos años que Ulises no navegaba
como simple pasajero. Vagó desorientado por las cubiertas entre la muchedumbre viajera. La
fuerza de la costumbre le arrastró al puente, hablando con el capitán y los oficiales, que
apreciaron á las primeras palabras su mérito profesional.

La consideración de que no era mas que un intruso en este sitio, la molestia de verse sobre
un puente en el que no podía dar orden alguna, le hicieron descender á las cubiertas bajas,
examinando los grupos de pasajeros. Eran franceses en su mayor parte que venían de la Indo
China. En la proa y la popa estaban alojadas cuatro compañías de tiradores asiáticos, pequeños,
amarillentos, con ojos oblicuos y una voz semejante al maullar de los gatos. Iban á la guerra.
Sus oficiales vivían en los camarotes del centro del buque, llevando con ellos á sus familias,
que habían adquirido un aspecto exótico con la larga permanencia en las colonias.

Ulises vió señoras vestidas de blanco haciéndose abanicar, tendidas en sillones, por sus pequeños
pajes chinescos; vió militares bronceados y enjutos, con aspecto enfermizo, que parecían galvanizados
por la guerra que los arrancaba á la siesta asiática, y niñas, muchas niñas, contentas de ir
á Francia, el país de sus ensueños, olvidando en esta felicidad que sus padres marchaban tal
vez á la muerte.

La navegación no podía ser mejor. El Mediterráneo era una llanura de plata bajo la luz de la
luna. De la costa invisible llegaban tibias bocanadas de perfume campestre. Los grupos de la
cubierta hacían memoria, con una satisfacción egoísta, de los grandes peligros que arrostraban
las gentes al embarcarse en los mares del Norte, plagados de submarinos alemanes. Por fortuna,
el Mediterráneo estaba libre de tal calamidad. Los ingleses tenían bien guardada la puerta
de Gibraltar, y todo él era un lago tranquilo dominado por los aliados.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07947</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>320790</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21052</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

It was her young son had seen entering the harbor when he was going to take charge the schooner
to carry fuel to German submarines.

VIII

The young Telemachus

Whenever the Mare Nostrum back to Barcelona, ??Esteban Ferragut felt a sense glare, just as if
it was opened a glorious window in his dark existence child and family monotonous.

No longer wandering the harbor, admiring from afar the great ocean liners anchored off the Columbus
monument or cargo vapors that lined the commercial docks. A vessel important was his absolute
property for several weeks. The captain and officers spent ground
time with their families.

Toni, the second was the only one who slept on board. Many of the sailors asked permission to
live in the city, and the steam is entrusted to Caragol Uncle guard with half a dozen men for
daily cleaning.

The small Ferragut could be under the illusion that he was the captain of the Mare Nostrum. He moved imagining
that the bridge was braving a storm; examining instruments water
with a severity of knowledgeable expert, ran all departments habitable
ship, down to the cellars, which aireaban, open, pending charge, and
finally got into the boat service, undoing of the scale, to row a
few hours with more satisfaction Yoles that in light of the Race Club.

His visits ended in the kitchen, invited by his uncle Caragol, who
treated him with a familiarity paternal.

The young oarsman was sweating. "A refresquet ?...» and preparing the sweet mixture, I did fall
to men of a single jump in the nebulosity of intoxication.

Stephen had much the "soft" chef.

His imagination, excited by the frequent Travel reading novels had made him conceive a type of
marine heroic, daring, philanderer, and able to swallow the beverage jars incendiary without blinking.
He wanted If so, every good mariner should drink.

While on the ground did not know other spirits that the innocent and sweet kept by his mother
family holiday once trod the deck of the ship felt the need for fluids
alcoholics, to show that he was a man.

"There was a beverage in the world that could with him ... And the second "refresh" the uncle
was sunk in a placid Caragol nirvana, seeing all pink and considerably enlarged: the sea, nearby
ships, the docks and the mountain of Montjuic, which served as background.

The cook, to behold with his eyes lovingly sick, he thought he had a jump dozen years ago and is
still in Valencia talking to the other Ferragut that University escape to paddle in the harbor.
Almost came to believe that he had lived twice.

The boy listened to the complaints, interrupting with solemn advice. This Ferragut fifteen years
of life showed discontent. He was a man, and had to live among women: his mother and two nieces
who accompanied him making lace, as she had accompanied once to his
mother Dona Cristina.

I wanted to be a sailor, and he was forced to study the Baccalaureate unfriendly materials.
Can a captain needs to know Latin? ...

Wanted to end his life as a student, to become a pilot and follow the practices in the bridge
next to his father. Maybe you'll command the thirty years or another ship Mare Nostrum similar.

Meanwhile,
the lure of the sea drew him away from the classroom, going to see
Caragol at the same time the roll call teachers to the students, noting
their absence.

The old man and his protégé are recruited in the kitchen with a responsible concern. Steps and voices
on the cover altered their conversation. "Hide!"

And Stephen crawled under a table or hidden in the storeroom of the provisions, while the cook
came out to meet the newcomer with a seraphic face.

Sometimes it was Toni, and the boy ventured out, with his silence. It also will wanted and approved
of his distaste for the books.

If from time to time was the captain who came to the ship for a few
moments, he spoke Caragol obstructing the door with his body, while
smiling slyly.

For Stephen, the two most worthy of admiration were the sea and his father. All heroes novelistic
that from the pages of the books had gone to stay in his imagination had the face and gestures
of Captain Ferragut.

As a child he had seen sometimes to mourn his mother with sad resignation.

Years later, to meet with his precocious little boy watched the relationships between men and women,
he felt that all these tears should be motivated by indiscretions
and infidelities Far navigator.

He loved his mother with a passion only child and spoiled, but not
least the captain admired, excusing all sins that might commit.

His father was the bravest man and most beautiful land. So he saw it. And one day, examining the
drawers in his cabin, found several photographs of women wearing the foot the names of distant
countries, his admiration was even larger.

All must be mad with love for the captain of the Mare Nostrum. Ay! For more than him to do
to be a man, never get to catch up with the winner to had given the existence ...

When the ship came to Barcelona without their owner around Naples, the son of Ferragut experienced no
surprise.

Toni, who was always short, lavished on this occasion. Captain Ferragut had been there for a business,
but would soon return. His second will expected at any moment.

Perhaps hiciese land travel to get there first.

Esteban was amazed to see that his mother did not accept this absence as an insignificant event.
The good lady was concerned and the watery eyes.

Her feminine instinct made him sensed something wrong with the delay of her husband.

In the afternoon, when he visited, as usual, his former love the professor,
the two spoke slowly, with measured words, but understood his eyes
during the long intervals of silence.

Pedro arrived at the pinnacle of his illustrious career with the possession
of a professorship at the Institute Barcelona, ??visiting every afternoon
to tape, and a half hours from his room exactly clockwork.

Not the slightest thought of impurity professor never stirred.

The past had forgotten ... But he needed daily to see the captain's wife knitting lace between
two young nieces as she had seen years before the widow of Ferragut.

Let him know the most important events in Barcelona and around the world, discussing them the future
destiny of Stephen, he heard her sweet voice with rapture, to attach great importance to the
details of domestic economy or to the descriptions of religious holidays,
just because it was she who had such accounts.

Often remained in a long silence. Don Pedro represented patience, humor equal respect silent, quiet
and clean the house, lost his composure only monastic the present owner for a few days, including
two trips.

Tape had been accustomed to the visits of Professor.

By checking the clock half past three sensed his footsteps on the stairs.

If any evening did not arrive, the sweet Penépole suffered a disappointment.

- What will happen to Don Pedro? - Asked with concern to his nieces.

This question was sometimes extended to the child, but Stephen, without hating the visitor liked
him very little.

Don Pedro belonged to the group of those gentlemen of the Institute
that the government paid for teaser with their explanations and their
reviews to the youth.

Still remembered two years had happened in his chair, and in a chamber of torture, suffering the
punishment of Latin. He was also a coward, always afraid and did not dare take cold to go out
on days cloudy if the umbrella was missing.

He spoke of you brave men.

- I do not know his mother answered ...-- -.

May be stuck in bed, with seven headscarves.

When I returned Don Pedro, the house resumed its normal slow clock and safe. Doña Film, from
consultation to consultation, he had finally consider indispensable
for your cooperation.

Professor sweetly made up for the husband's authority traveler, he had to represent the head of
the family in all foreign affairs ... I often looked forward to Ferragut's wife for advice urgently,
and he issued his opinion in a slow voice, after much reflection.

Esteban was intolerable that this man, who was but a distant relative of grandmother, meddling
in the affairs of the house, trying to address him as a father. But irritated him even more
to see in a good mood and with claims of funny.

He was angry that flames Penépole his mother and him Telemachus ... "Uncle lateral and heavy!"

The
young Telemachus did not hesitate in their revenge. Small interrupted their diversions for
"Work" in the hall, next to the neighbor to the door hanger. And the poor professor was dented
his top hat, hair in disarray, or in carrying out the Haldas several
spit coat.

Now the boy was confined to ignore its existence, going before him without giving him, greeting him
only when his mother told him to.

The day brought news of the return of steam without their captain, Don Pedro made the visit longer
than usual.

Tape shed two tears on the laces, but had to cut her tears, overcome by the good sense to your
counselor.

- Why mourn and head warm with so many unfounded assumptions? ... What you should do, my dear,
is to call that Toni is the second ship. He should know all ... Maybe tell you the truth.

Stephen received the commission to seek the next day, and could see the concern Toni experienced
knowing that he wanted to talk Dona Cinta. Ship left the gloomy silence, as if it leads to death suffer
torture. Then she sang quietly, it was in The indication of serious concern.

Unable to attend the young Telemachus to the interview, but he hung near the door closed overheard some
words louder than they slipped through the cracks. His mother was the one who spoke more often.
Toni dully repeating the same excuses: "I do not know. The captain is going to get from one point
to another ... "But to look beyond the classroom and the house, broke his anger against himself,
against his character that he knew damn lie, against all women, bad
and good.

Thought he had said too much. This lady had judge's ability to extract the words.

At night, at the dinner, the mother just gasped. His fingers reported a nervous trembling to
the plates and forks. Looked at her son with tragic commiseration as if he sensed enormous misfortunes
that were about to collapse on his head.

Opposed a silence desperate to Stephen's questions, and finally exclaimed:

- Your father left us! ... Your father has forgotten us! ...

And left the room to hide the tears that had flowed into his eyelids.

The boy slept a little uneasy, but fell asleep. The admiration he felt for his father and some
strong solidarity with copies of their sex made him take some little
tears.

Women Talking Dirty! His mother could not be the wife of an extraordinary man as Captain Ferragut.
He, who was a man in spite of its short tenure, he was going to intervene
in the case to clarify the truth.

When Toni, from the deck of the ship, saw him move through the dock the next morning, was tempted
to hide ... "Doña tape, which was called for questioning again !...»

But was relieved to tell the boy who came for their willingness to spend some time in Mare nostrum. Still,
wanted to avoid his presence, as if afraid some careless talk with
him, and pretended to work in the cellars.

Then came the ship, going to visit a friend vapor in a remote.

Stephen went into the kitchen, calling cheerfully to Uncle Caragol. Nor was it the same. His
eyes were moist and red looked at the boy with an extraordinary tenderness.

Suddenly stopped language, with a look of concern on his face.

Looked undecided about him, as if he feared it was to open a cliff
at his feet.

Never forgot the respect due to every visitor to your domains, and
prepared two "soft."

For the first time Stephen was about to give away to this return trip. Previous days, by seems unlikely
that the fact had not even thought to make one of his delirious concoctions. The return of Naples
to Barcelona had been sad, the vessel had a funereal atmosphere without its owner.

For all these reasons, it was the hand to the extent Caragol, lavishing
the shank to the liquid took snuff color.

Drank ... The young Telemachus began to speak of his father when only vessels guarding the half
of the "refresh" and the cook waved both hands in the air, giving a grunt which meant their desire
not to deal with the absence of captain.

- Your father will return, Estevet - added -. Return, but do not know when. Surely later ensuring Toni.

And
meaning no more, swallowed the rest of the vessel, engaged in making
a second "drink" rushed for lost time.

Little by little they broke the barrier prudent containing his verbosity, and spoke with the
same abandoned forever, but his flow of words drew no accurate news.

Caragol preached moral Ferragut's son, a moral in his own way, interrupted by frequent touch
the glass.

- Esteve, my son, your father is very respectful. Imitate as a seaman. Be good and righteous to
men who send ... but women fleeing!

Women! ... There was no better theme for pious drunken eloquence. The world infused pity. Everything
was ruled by the infernal attraction to the female. Men worked, fought, they wanted to be rich or
famous, all to win possession of a piece of meat, the most filthy and shameful of the human
body.

- Watch how it will be, Estevet that even in food animals is not known chef who use it. I always
throw it away ... Believe me, my son: do not imitate your father
about it.

The old man had said too much to go back, and had to go dropping everything to pieces Left. So
he learned that Captain Stephen walked in an affair with a woman
from Naples, and had stayed there pretending business, but in reality
dominated by the influence of this woman.

- Is it pretty?

"- Asked the boy eagerly.

- Gorgeous - said Caragol -. And some smells!

... Noise and fine clothes! ...

Telemachus shook with a contradictory feeling of pride and envy. He admired his father again,
but this admiration only lasted a few moments. A new idea seized
him, while the cook was still talking.

- Do not come yet.

I know what these women are elegant and full of incense: true interlocking nails demons when
they grab and you have to cut off their hands to let go ... And the
ship without working, as if he were stranded, while others are filled
with gold!

... Believe me, my son in the world only this is true.

And finally to drink in one gulp all that remained of the second vessel.

Meanwhile, the boy was taking shape in his mind to an idea suggested by sweet intoxication. If he were
to Naples to bring his father! ...

At this point everything seemed possible. The world was rosy, as it always glass in hand watching
the guy next Caragol. The obstacles were soft, everything is arranged with prodigious ease, the
men could walk to falls.

But hours later, when his thought was seductive cloudless, was afraid
remembering of his father.

How you would get to see him get there ... What excuse him of his presence in Naples? ... Trembled
evoking the image of his frown and his eyes are red.

The next day, a sudden confidence overcame this concern.

He remembered the captain as he had seen a few times to celebrate
from the deck of his exploits rower at the port of Barcelona or to
discuss with friends the intelligence and strength your child.

The father of the hero image in his memory now emerged with kind eyes and a smile that seemed
to shake like a fresh wind, the forest of his beard.

I would tell the whole truth. We do know that coming to Naples to take him as a good comrade
who aids another in danger. Perhaps irritated and give him a blow,
but he achieve his purpose.

Ferragut's character was revived in him with all the strength of a decisive argument. If travel
was absurd and dangerous ... Better! Much better! This was enough to undertake it. He was a man,
and should not know fear.

For two weeks to prepare their escape. I had never done a big trip. Only once had accompanied
his father on a quick business trip to Marseilles.

It was already time to come out to run the world a man like him, who knew from his reading almost
all the peoples of land.

The money did not care.

Doña tape had it in abundance, and it was easy to find your bunch keys. A vapor old and slow,
sent by a friend of his father, had just entered the port and sailed the next day to Italy.

This
sailor's son accepted his comrade without travel papers. The fix the irregular with friends
in Genoa. Among these services were captains, and Ulises Ferragut, which waiting for his son in
Naples - Esteban said so - was not going to waste time in vain a clerical formalities.

Telemachus, a thousand pesetas in his pocket a sewing learned that
his mother served safe, he embarked the next day.

A small suitcase taken from her home with slow and clever tricks was all his luggage.

From Genoa he went to Rome, and thence to Naples, with the boldness of innocence, using words
Spanish and Catalan to reinforce a short Italian lexical representations acquired operetta.
The only positive report held him on his journey of adventure was
the name Hostels the shore of St. Lucia had given Caragol as a residence
of his father.

Seek this in vain for several days. He visited Naples to the agents, which imagine the captain
back to his country a long time.

Not finding was afraid. Should already be in Barcelona, ??and what
had begun as a heroic journey was going to be a naughty teen drain.
He remembered his mother, maybe cry to those hours re-reading the
letter he had left to announce In order to escape. 

Also came suddenly
the intervention of Italy in the war, an event that everyone expected,
but many were still distant. What was left to do in this country?
... And one morning there disappeared.

As the hotel porter could
not say more, the father, once the first impression surprise, he thought
about the advisability of visiting the home consignee. Perhaps there
should give you other news.

The war was the only thing interesting
to this office. But Ferragut, ship owner and former client, was led
by the director to find those employees who had received to Esteban.

Do
not know much. Vaguely remembered a young Spanish man who claimed
to be the son of Captain asking this news. His last visit was two
days earlier. Torn between returning to his country by rail or embark
on one of the three ships that were in port ready to leave for Marseilles.

-
I think it has gone by train - said one employee.

Another of them
supported his companion with strong affirmation to attract the eye
of the boss. Was sure of his ground game. He himself had helped to
calculate what it would cost the trip to Barcelona.

Ferragut not
want to know more. I needed to leave soon. This trip unexplained his
son was for him a regret and a cause for alarm. What happened in your
home?

The office manager told a French steamer that came that afternoon
to Marseille from Suez. The fix was in charge of all matters relating
to recommend its passage and Captain. There were only four hours for
the departure of the ship, and Ulysses, after collecting your bags
and send them on board, took a last walk by all the places he had
lived with Freya. Goodbye, gardens of the Villa Nazionale, white Aquarius!
... Goodbye, albergo! ...

The unexplained presence of his son in
Naples had softened the disappointment of the flight German. He thought
sadly of lost love, but thought at the same time, with painful hesitation,
as you might see upon entering your home.

Shortly before sunset the
French steamer sailed. For many years sailed Ulysses as a mere passenger.
Wandered bewildered through the crowd covers travel. The force of
habit drew him to the bridge, talking to the captain and officers,
which appreciated at the first words his professional merit.

The
consideration that was but an intruder on this site, the discomfort
of being on a bridge that could not give any orders, made him descend
to the lower decks, examining groups of passengers. French were mostly
coming from the Indo China. In the bow and stern were housed Asian
shooters four companies, small yellow, with slanting eyes and a voice
like the meowing of cats. Iban to war. Its officers were living in
cabins amidships, bringing with them their families, who had taken
an exotic with long tenure in the colonies.

Ulysses saw ladies dressed
in white getting fan, lying on couches and their little chinoiserie
pages; military saw tanned and lean, sickly-looking, which seemed
galvanized the war that tore at the Asian nap, and girls, many girls,
happy to go to France, the country of his dreams, forgetting the joy
that parents initiated such time to death.

Navigation could not be
better. The Mediterranean was a plain silver in the light of moon.
Invisible coast came warm breaths of perfume country. Groups memory
were covered with a selfish satisfaction of the great dangers that
face people to embark on the North Sea, full of German submarines.
Fortunately, the Mediterranean was free from such a calamity. The
English were well guarded gate of Gibraltar, and yet he was a calm
lake dominated by allies</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>