<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01622</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>354375</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>711</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Al fijarme
en aquellos ojos fijos en nosotros, ¿tuvo Magdalena una sospecha? Lo creo, porque se volvió
de pronto como para sorprenderme. Yo sostuve el fuego de su mirada, el más inmediato y más
clarividente que jamás he afrontado. Si se hubiese tratado de su vida no habría yo estado más
resuelto a un acto de temeridad que me exigió el mayor esfuerzo. El resto de la velada se pasó
mal. Magdalena parecía menos ocupada de la música, distraída por una idea molesta, como si
aquel encuentro y aquella permanencia cara a cara la importunasen. Una o dos veces todavía,
trató de aclarar las dudas; después quedó extraña a todo lo que en torno de ella sucedía y
comprendí que se retiraba al fondo de su pensamiento.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00430</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>136410</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>651</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> By noticing
in those eyes on us, Magdalena had a suspicion? I believe, because it became suddenly as to
surprise me. I held the fire in his eyes, the most immediate and clairvoyant I have ever faced.
If it had been in his life I would not have been more committed to an act of recklessness that
he demanded the best. The rest of the evening was spent wrong. Magdalena seemed less busy of the
music, distracted by an annoying idea, as if that meeting and that remain face to face importunity.
Once or twice yet sought to clarify the doubts, then was foreign to everything happening around
her and I realized that was removed from the back of his mind.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>