<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04335</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>9238</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16742</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Babuco entonces se empezo a rezelar de que tenia razon el genio Ituriel. Con el dote que tenia
de grangearse la confianza, supo aquel dia mismo los secretos de la dama, la qual le fio su
carino al mago mozo, asegurandole que en todas las casas de Persepolis encontraria lo mismo
que en la suya habia visto. Infirio Babuco que no podia durar semejante sociedad; que todas
las casas habian de estar asoladas por zelos, venganzas y rencillas; que sin cesar habian de
verterse lagrimas y sangre; que infaliblemente habian de matar los maridos a los cortejos de
sus mugeres, o de ser muertos por ellos; finalmente que hacia Ituriel muy bien en destruir
de una vez un pueblo abandonado a horrendos desordenes.

Fuese despues de comer a uno de los mas soberbios templos de la ciudad, y se sento en medio
de una muchedumbre de hombres y mugeres que habian ido alli a matar el tiempo. Subio un mago
a una maquina alta, y discurrio largo tiempo acerca del vicio y la virtud; y habiendo dividido
en varias partes lo que no era menester dividir, probo metodicamente las cosas mas claras,
enseno lo que sabia todo el mundo, se exalto sin motivo, y salio sudando y sin respiracion.
Despertose entonces la gente, y creyo que habia asistido a una instruccion. Babuco dixo: Este
buen hombre ha hecho quanto ha podido por fastidiar a doscientos o trescientos conciudadanos
suyos; pero su intencion era buena, y esto no es motivo para destruir a Persepolis.

Llevaronle, al salir de esta asamblea, a que viera una fiesta publica que se celebraba todos
los dias del ano en una especie de basilica, en cuya parte interior se via un palacio. Formaban
tan hermoso espectaculo las ciudadanas mas hermosas de Persepolis, y los principales satrapas
colocados en orden, que al principio creyo Babuco que se reducia a esto la fiesta. En breve
se dexaron ver en el vestibulo de este palacio dos o tres personas que parecian reyes y reynas;
su idioma era muy distinto del que estilaba el vulgo, y tenia ritmo, harmonia y sublimidad.
No se dormia nadie, que todos en alto silencio escuchaban, y si le interrumpian, era para dar
pruebas de admiracion y ternura general; y con tan vivos y bien sentidos terminos se hablaba
de las obligaciones de los reyes, del amor de la virtud, y de los riesgos de las pasiones,
que arrancaron lagrimas a Babuco: el qual no dudo que fuesen los predicadores del imperio aquellos
heroes y heroinas y aquellos reyes y reynas que acababa de oir, y hasta hizo proposito de persuadir
a Ituriel que los viniese a escuchar, cierto de que semejante espectaculo le reconciliaria
con Persepolis para siempre.

Concluida la fiesta, quiso visitar a la reyna principal que en aquel hermoso palacio habia
anunciado tan sublime y acendrada moral. Hizo que le introduxeran en casa de su magestad; y
le llevaron por una mala escalerilla a un segundo piso, donde hallo en un aposento pobremente
alhajado una muger mal vestida, que con noble y patetico ademan le dixo: Mi oficio no me da
para vivir; uno de los principes que habeis visto me ha hecho un hijo: estoy para parir: no
tengo dinero, y sin dinero todo parto es un mal parto. Babuco le dio cien daricos de oro, diciendo:
Si no hubiera cosas peores en la ciudad, poco motivo tuviera Ituriel para estar tan enojado.

Fue de alli a pasar la tarde a las tiendas de mercaderes de magnificencias superfluas. Llevole
un sugeto inteligente que se habia hecho amigo suyo, compro lo que hallo de su gusto, y con
muchas cortesias se lo vendieron mucho mas caro de lo que valia. Quando hubo vuelto a casa,
le hizo ver su amigo que le habian estafado; y apunto Babuco en su libro de memoria el nombre
del mercader, para que el dia del castigo de la ciudad no le echara Ituriel en olvido. Estando
escribiendo, llamaron a la puerta, y entro el mercader que le traia a Babuco su bolsillo que
se habia dexado olvidado encima del mostrador. ?Como es posible, dixo Babuco, que seais tan
generoso y escrupuloso, despues de haber tenido cara para venderme vuestras buxerias quatro
tanto mas de lo que valen? No hay en toda la ciudad, le respondio el mercader, negociante ninguno
algo conocido, que no hubiese venido a traeros el bolsillo; mas quando os han dicho que os
he vendido lo que en mi tienda habeis comprado el quadruplo de su valor, os han enganado, porque
os lo he vendido diez veces mas de lo que ello vale; y esto es tan cierto, que si dentro de
un mes os quereis deshacer de ello, no os daran ni el diezmo: y no hay empero cosa mas conforme
a razon, porque siendo el antojo de los hombres lo que da valor a estas fruslerias, ese mismo
antojo da de comer a cien obreros que empleo yo, y a mi me da una casa bien puesta, un buen
coche, y buenos caballos. Este antojo es quien vivifica la industria, y mantiene el fino gusto,
la circulacion y la abundancia. A las naciones comarcanas les vendo mucho mas caras que a vos
esas mismas frioleras, y de este modo sirvo con provecho al imperio. Parose Babuco pensativo
un, rato, y le borro luego de su libro.

No sabiendo que pensar de Persepolis, se determino a visitar a los magos y a los literatos,
lisonjeandose de que alcanzarian estos el perdon de todo lo restante del pueblo, porque unos
se aplican a la sabiduria, y a la religion los otros. La manana siguiente fue a visitar un
colegio de magos, y le confeso el archimandrita que tenia trescientos mil escudos de renta
por haber hecho voto de pobreza, y que exercia una vasta jurisdiccion en virtud de otro voto
de humildad. Dicho esto, dexo a Babuco en manos de un aprendiz de mago, para que le obsequiase.

Ensenabale este las preciosidades de esta casa de penitencia, quando se esparcio la voz de
que traia comision de hacer reformas. Al punto le dieron memoriales de cada una, que todos
en sustancia venian a decir: Conservadnos a nosotros, y suprimid todos los demas. Si daba credito
a sus propias apologias, todas estas congregaciones eran necesarias; si atendia a sus reciprocas
acusaciones, todas merecian ser destruidas. Pasmabase Babuco de que no hubiese ninguna que,
por edificar al universo, no quisiese ser arbitro de el. Presentosele entonces un hombrecillo
que era semi-mago, el qual le dixo: La grande obra se va a cumplir, y Zerdust ha vuelto a la
tierra; por tanto os rogamos que nos ampareis contra el Gran Lama. ?Con que contra el pontifice
monarca, respondio Babuco, que reside en el Tibet?--Contra ese mismo.--?Pues que? le haceis
guerra, y alistais contra el un exercito?--No es eso; pero dice que el hombre es libre, y nosotros
no lo creemos: escribimos contra el libracos que no lee; y apenas si nos ha oido mentar, puesto
que nos acaba de condenar, como un propietario que manda extirpar las orugas de su huerto.
Asombrose Babuco de la locura de hombres que profesan la sabiduria, de las maranas de los que
habian renunciado del mundo, de la ambicion y altiva codicia de los que predicaban humildad
y desinteres; y coligio que sobraban razones valederas a Ituriel para destruir toda esta raza.

Retirose a su casa, mando que le compraran libros nuevos para calmar su enfado, y convido a
comer a varios literatos para su recreo. Llegaron mas del doble de los que habia llamado, como
acuden las avispas a la miel. No se daban vado estos gorreros a hablar y a engullir, y elogiaban
dos clases de hombres, los muertos y ellos propios, mas nunca a sus coetaneos, exceptuando
el amo de casa. Si decia uno un dicho agudo, baxaban los demas los ojos, y se mordian la lengua
de sentimiento de no ser ellos los autores. Eran menos cautelosos que los magos porque no aspiraba
su ambicion a tan altos objetos, solicitando cada uno un empleo de sirviente y la reputacion
de grande hombre. Decianse en su cara denuestos, que se les figuraban agudos epigramas. Habiaseles
traslucido algo de la comision de Babuco, y uno de ellos en voz baxa le suplico que exterminase
a un autor que no le habia dado suficientes elogios; otro lo pidio la perdida de un ciudadano
que en sus comedias nunca se reia; y otro la extincion de la academia, porque jamas habia podido
conseguir ser su individuo. Acabada la comida, se fueron solos todos, porque en toda esta caterva
no habia dos que se pudieran sufrir, ni se hablaban mas que en las casas de los ricos que a
su mesa los convidaban. Creyo Babuco que poquisimo se perdia con que pereciese toda esta landre
en la general destruccion.

Apenas se zafo de ellos, se puso a leer algunos de los libros que acababan de publicarse, y
advirtio en ellos el caracter de sus convidados. Indignaronle mas que todo las gacetillas de
calumnias, y los archivos de mal gusto dictados por la envidia, la hambre y la torpeza; viles
satiras que respetan los buytres y despedazan las palomas; novelas faltas de imaginacion, donde
se ven mil retratos ideales de sugetos que sus autores no conocen. Tiro al fuego todos estos
detestables escritos, y salio aquella tarde de casa, para ir al paseo. Presentaronle a un literato
anciano que no habia venido a aumentar el numero de sus pegotes. Esquivaba este la muchedumbre,
conocia a los hombres, sabia servirse de ellos, y se explicaba con cordura. Hablole Babuco
con mucho sentimiento de quanto habia visto y leido. Cosas muy despreciables habeis leido,
le dixo el cuerdo letrado; pero en todos tiempos y en todo pais es muy comun lo malo, y rarisimo
lo bueno. Habeis dado acogida en vuestra mesa a las heces de la pedanteria, porque en toda
profesion lo que siempre se presenta con mas descaro es lo que menos merece salir a la plaza.
Viven unos con otros, sosegados y en el retiro, los verdaderos sabios, y aun no nos faltan
libros y autores que son acreedores a vuestra atencion. Mientras que estaba hablando, llego
otro literato, y fueron sus razonamientos tan instructivos y agradables, tan superiores a las
preocupaciones, y tan conformes con la virtud, que confeso Babuco que nunca habia oido semejante
cosa. Hombres son estos, decia para si, a quien no se atrevera el angel Ituriel a hacer mal,
a menos que sea muy despiadado.

No conservaba menos enojo contra lo demas de la nacion, puesto que se habia reconciliado con
los literatos. Sois un extrangero, le dixo el hombre juicioso que le hablaba, y se os presentan
de tropel los abusos, mientras que se os esconde el bien oculto, y que no pocas veces de estos
mismos abusos resulta. Supo entonces que habia entre los literatos muchos que no eran envidiosos,
y hasta entre los magos algunos que eran virtuosos. Al fin entendio que estos grandes cuerpos,
que con sus choques preparaban al parecer su ruina comun, eran en la realidad fundaciones provechosas;
que cada asociacion de magos era un freno para sus emulas; que si a veces estas diferian de
opinion, todas ensenaban una moral misma; que instruian el pueblo, y sujetas a las leyes: semejantes
a los preceptores que zelan los hijos de casa, mientras que a ellos los zela el amo. Trato
a muchos, y encontro entre ellos almas celestiales; y supo que entre aquellos mismos locos
que querian poner guerra al Gran Lama, habia varones eminentes. Sospecho al cabo que podian
ser lo mismo las costumbres de Persepolis que sus edificios, que unos le habian parecido dignos
de lastima, y otros le habian sobrecogido en admiracion.

Dixo un dia al literato: Ahora conozco que los magos, que por tan peligrosos habia tenido,
pueden ser muy provechosos, especialmente quando un prudente gobierno estorba que se grangeen
sobrado influxo: ?pero que utilidades, pueden resultar de las colosales riquezas de los asentistas
y agentes del fisco? Aquel mismo dia vio que la opulencia de estos, que tanto le habia repugnado,
producia a veces mucho fruto, porque habiendo necesitado dinero el soberano, hallo en una hora
por su medio lo que por las vias ordinarias no hubiera en seis meses encontrado; y se convencio
de que estas pardas nubes, alimentadas con el rocio de la tierra, le restituian en lluvias
lo que de ellas recibian: aparte de que los hijos de estos hombres nuevos, por lo comun mas
bien educados que los de las mas antiguas familias, valian mucho mas que estos; porque tener
por padre un buen calculador no quita que sea uno juez recto, valiente soldado, o habil estadista.

Poco a poco perdonaba Babuco la codicia del asentista, que en la realidad no es ni mas ni menos
codicioso que los demas, y que es indispensable; disculpaba la locura de disipar su caudal
por hacer la guerra, que era origen de tantas belicas proezas; y perdonaba los zelos de los
literatos, entre quienes se hallaban sugetos que ilustraban el mundo: se reconciliaba con los
magos ambiciosos y tramoyistas, que con pequenos vicios juntaban grandes virtudes; puesto que
le quedaban no pocos escrupulos, especialmente sobre los galanteos de las damas, y las horrendas
consequeencias que infaliblemente habian de producir, y que le llenaban de horror y sustos.

Queriendo examinar todos los estados, hizo que le llevaran a casa de un ministro, y en el camino
iba temblando de ver alguna muger asesinada por su marido en presencia suya. Llego a la antesala
del hombre de estado, y estuvo dos horas aguardando a que dixeran que estaba alli, y otras
dos despues que lo hubieron dicho, haciendo en este tiempo firmisimo proposito de recomendar
al ministro y sus insolentes concierges al enojo del angel Ituriel. Estaba la antesala atestada
de damas de todas clases, de magos de todos colores, de jueces, mercaderes, oficiales y pedantes,
que todos estaban quejosos del ministro. Decian el avariento y el logrero: No hay duda de que
roba este hombre las provincias; afeaba sus rarezas el extravagante; decia el sensual que solo
con sus gustos tenia cuenta; y esperaban las mugeres que en breve le sustituiria otro ministro
mas mozo.

Oia Babuco todas estas razones, y no pudo menos de decir: iQue hombre tan dichoso es este!
Todos sus enemigos los tiene en su antesala; su potencia abruma a sus envidiosos, y mira a
sus plantas a quantos le detestan. Al fin entro en su gabinete, y vio a un viejecito agobiado
de anos y quehaceres, pero vivo todavia, y muy inteligente. Gustole Babuco, y a Babuco le parecio
un sugeto muy digno de estimacion. Fue muy interesante la conferencia: el ministro le confeso
que era el hombre mas desgraciado; que le tenian por rico, y era pobre; que le creian omnipotente,
y para todo encontraba impedimentos; que todos sus beneficios habian sido pagados con ingratitudes,
y que en quarenta anos de continuas faenas habia tenido apenas un rato de satisfaccion. Enterneciose
Babuco, y dixo entre si que si habia cometido algunos yerros este hombre, y por ellos le queria
castigar el angel Ituriel, bastaba con dexarle su cargo, sin exterminarle.

Estaba razonando con el ministro, quando entro desatentada la hermosa dama en cuya casa habia
comido Babuco, manifestando su rostro y sus ojos los sintomas del dolor y el enojo. Prorumpio
en amargas quejas contra el hombre de estado; vertio lagrimas; se lamento amargamente de que
hubieran negado a su marido un cargo a que podia aspirar por su cuna, y de que le hacian acreedor
sus heridas y servicios; y hablo con tanta energia, se quejo con tal gracia, desvanecio con
tal mana los reparos, con tal eloqueencia esforzo sus razones, que no salio del gabinete hasta
haber conseguido la fortuna de su marido.

Salio Babuco dandole la mano, y le dixo: ?Es posible, senora, que os hayais tomado tanto trabajo
por un hombre que no quereis, y que tanto teneis por que temer? ?Como es eso que no le quiero?
replico la dama: sabed que mi marido es el mejor amigo que tengo en este mundo, y que sacrificare
por el todo quanto tengo, como no sea mi amante; lo mismo que hiciera el, menos sacrificar
a su querida. Quiero que la conozcais, que es una muy linda senora, muy discreta, y de excelente
genio; esta noche cenamos juntos con mi marido y mi amiguito el mago: venid a participar nuestro
gusto.

Llevose la dama consigo a Babuco, y el marido que estaba sumido en el mas hondo dolor recibio
a su muger con raptos de gratitud y alborozo, dando mil abrazos a su muger, a su dama, al mago,
y a Babuco. El banquete le animaron el contento, las gracias y los donayres. Sabed, le dixo
la hermosa dama con quien cenaba, que las que a veces califican de mugeres sin honra casi siempre
poseen las virtudes de un hombre honrado; y en prueba de ello, venid manana a comer conmigo
en casa de la hermosa Teone. Algunas vestales viejas murmuran de ella, pero mas obras de beneficencia
hace ella sola que todas juntas las que la muerden; no cometiera la mas leve injusticia por
todos los intereses del mundo; a su amante le da siempre consejos generosos; solo su gloria
la ocupa, y se sonrojaria el si en su presencia malograra una sola ocasion de obrar bien; porque
no hay mayor estimulo para virtuosas acciones, que tener por juez y testigo de su conducta
una amada cuyo aprecio anhela uno a merecer.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01098</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>99510</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15430</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Babuca then started to the apprehension of that was right Ituriel genius. With the dowry had Granger
confidence, he knew the secrets that very day the lady, will fio their qual affection to the
boy wizard, ensure that all houses would find the same Persepolis that had been hers. Babuca
inferred that such a society could not last, that all the houses were to be struck by jealousy,
revenge and feuds, which constantly had to shed tears and blood that inevitably had to kill
their husbands to processions their wives, or of being killed by them finally to very well destroy
Ituriel once an abandoned village to horrendous disorders.

After eating was one of the most magnificent temples of the city, and sat in the middle a crowd
of both men and women who had gone there to kill time. Climbed a magician to a high machine
and pondered long about vice and virtue, and having divided in several parts so it was not necessary
to divide, test methods things clearer, taught what he knew everyone, no reason is exalted,
and came out sweating and breathless. Then people awoke, and believed that he had attended
an instruction. Babuca said: "This quanto good man has done has been for the hell of two or three
hundred citizens own, but his intention was good, and this is no reason to destroy Persepolis.

Brought
him, emerging from this gathering, to see a public holiday that was
celebrated every day of the year in a kind of basilica, whose inner
part via a palace.

Were so beautiful spectacle most beautiful women citizens of Persepolis, and the main Satraps
arranged in order, at first believed Babuca that came down to this party. In brief dexaron be seen
in the vestibule of the palace two or three people who looked like kings and queens; their language
was very different from the fashionable to the masses, and had rhythm, harmony and sublimity.
No one is sleeping, we all listened in silence high, and if interrupted him, was to give tests
of general admiration and affection, and with senses so alive and well spoken terms the obligations
of the kings, love of virtue, and the risks of the passions, that drew tears to Babuca: who no
doubt were the preachers of those rule heroes and heroines and those kings and queens who had
just heard, and even made purpose of persuading Ituriel that came to listen, some of which
show similar you reconcile with Persepolis forever.

After the party, wanted to visit the queen at the main palace was beautiful announced and unblemished
moral sublime.

Introduxeran had him at her majesty, and I took a bad ladder to the second floor, where am
in a room poorly adorned and furnished a poorly dressed woman, that noble and pathetic gesture,
he said: "My job gives me no to live, one of the princes who have seen has made me a child: I
am ready to be delivered: no I have money, and without money every birth is a miscarriage.
Darics Babuca gave him a hundred gold, saying: If there were worse things in the city, Ituriel
had little reason to be so angry.

Was there to spend the afternoon at the shops of merchants of magnificence superfluous. Brought
him an intelligent sugeto who had befriended him, bought what I find to their liking, and many
courtesies sold it much more expensive than it was worth. Quando had returned home, let him
see his friend that he had been swindled, and pointed Babuca memory in his book the name the
merchant, for the day of the punishment of the city not take Ituriel forgotten. While writing,
knocked on the door and entered the merchant who brought him to his pocket Babuca forsaken had
been forgotten on the counter. ? As possible, he said Babuca, so that you may be generous and
scrupulous, after having had face to sell your buxerias four much more than they're worth?
There throughout the city, he answered the merchant, merchant none something known, had not come
to bring the pocket, but I have said Quando I I sold in my store that have bought the quadruple
in value, you've been deceived, because I've sold ten times more than what it is worth, and this
is so true that if within one month you get rid of it you want, will not give or tithe, and
there is more thing however as to reason, because as the whim of men that gives value to these
trifles, that same feeds craving hundred workers who use me and my house gives me a good start,
a good car, and good horses. This craving is the one who gives life to the industry, and keeps
the fine taste circulation and abundance. The nations neighboring towns sell them much more expensive
than you the same trifles, and thus serve to benefit the empire. Paros thoughtful Babuca a, time,
and then delete it from his book.

Not knowing what to think of Persepolis, was determined to see wizards and writers, flattering
himself that such a pardon would reach all the rest of the people, because some apply to the
wisdom, and religion of others. The next morning was to visit a school for witches, and he
confessed that he was Archimandrite three hundred thousand crowns for having taken a vow of
poverty, and exercies a vast jurisdiction under another vote humility. That said, I leave to
Babuca in the hands of a magician's apprentice, so gave her.

Ensenabale that the beauties of this house of penance, when the voice spread who brought commission
for reform. Memorials given point each, that all essentially came to say Conservadnos us and remove
all others. If credit was their own apologies, all these congregations were necessary, if attended
to their mutual charges, all deserved to be destroyed. Babuca Pasmabase that there is none
that by building the universe, did not want to be the referee. Then a man Presentosele I was
semi-magician, qual said to him: The great work is going to comply, and has returned to Zerdust
earth: therefore I request that you ampareis against the Grand Lama. ? With that against the pontiff
monarch replied Babuca, which lies in Tibet? - against the same .--? For what? you make him
war, and alistais against an army? - not that, but says that man is free, and we do not believe: we
write against the tomes do not read, and we've heard hardly mind, because we just condemn, as an
owner who sends remove caterpillars from their garden. Babuca Asombrose the folly of men who
profess the wisdom, the tangle of that had renounced the world, lofty ambition and greed of those
who preached humility and disinterest, and gathered that left over good reasons to Ituriel
to destroy all this race.

He retired to his home, sent to buy her new books to calm his anger, and bade eat several writers
for recreation. Reached more than double what had been called as Wasps go to honey. They did not
ford these gorreros to speak and swallow, and praised two classes of men, the dead and their
own, but never to their peers, except the householder. If you said one is a saying acute baxaban
others eyes and bit his tongue feeling of not including the authors. Were less cautious than mages
because they aspired his ambition at such high objects, asking each servant's employment and
reputation of a great man. They began to insults in his face, that they contained sharp epigrams.
Habiaseles Translucent some of the commission of Babuca, and one voice descends beg him to exterminate
an author who had not given enough praise, another asked what the loss of a citizen who in his
plays never laughed, and another the extinction of the academy, because they never had been get
to be your guy. Finished eating, they went away all because in this whole bunch there was two that
might suffer, or talked more than in the homes of the rich than your table guests. Babuca believed
that very little was lost with all this Landre perish in the general destruction.

Just pulled away from them, began to read some books that had just been published, and warned
them the character of his guests. Indignaronle most of all the newsletters of slander, and files
in poor taste dictated by envy, hunger and stupidity, vile satires that respect and tear buytres
pigeons; novels lack of imagination, where thousand portraits are ideal sugetos their authors do
not know. Tyre fire these detestable writings, and came home that afternoon to go for walks.
A literary Presentaronle old man who had not been to increase the number of blobs. Dodging the crowd,
knew the men, wise use of them, and explained to sanity. Spake Babuca with feeling of quanto had
seen and read. Despicable things you have read, The lawyer told him sane, but at all times
and in every country is very common evil, and very rare good. You have been hosting at your
table to the stool of pedantry, because in all profession that is always presented with more chutzpah
is the least deserving out of the square. They live with each other, calmer and in retirement,
the truly wise, and still no shortage of books and authors are entitled to your attention. While
he was talking, I get another writer, and his arguments were so instructive and pleasant,
so far superior to concerns, and so in accordance with virtue, who confessed that he had never
heard Babuca such thing. Men are these, he said to himself, who will not dare to do evil angel
Ituriel, unless it is very ruthless.

No less anger kept the rest of the nation, since it had reconciled
with the literati.

You are a foreigner, he said to the wise man who spoke, and it will show of crowd abuse, while
you hide the well hidden, and that often these same abuses it. He knew then that there was among
many who were not writers envious and even among some who were virtuous wizards. Finally understood
that these large bodies clashes with its apparently preparing common ruin, were in fact beneficial
foundations; each association of wizards was a brake on his rivals, for if sometimes these differed
from opinion, all teach the same morals, who taught the people and subject to the laws, such Zelan the
preceptors that the children at home, while the master Zela them. Treatment many, and found
among them heavenly souls, and knew that among those same crazy they wanted to bring war to the Grand
Lama, had great men. I suspect they could after same thing Persepolis customs of their buildings,
which had seemed a worthy of pity, and others had overwhelmed in astonishment.

One day he said to the writer: Now I know that the Magi, which had been so dangerous, can be very
helpful, especially Quando a prudent government that hinders grange
Influx left:? but profits may result from the colossal wealth of the
contractors and agents of the Treasury?

That same day saw the opulence of these, which had so disgusted, sometimes produces much fruit,
because having the sovereign needed money, I find in one hour through him as through regular
channels in six months had not found, and conventional that these brown clouds, fed with the dew of
the earth, I returned in rain what they received them: besides that the children of these new men,
usually more well educated than those of the oldest families, worth more than these, because having
a father a good calculator does not remove a judge who is right, brave soldier, and skilled statesman.

Slowly
forgive Babuca greed of the settlement, which in reality is neither more nor less greedy than
the others, and is indispensable; apologized to dispel his madness flow for war, that war was
the source of many exploits, and forgave the jealousy of writers, among whom were sugetos illustrating
the world is reconciled with ambitious magicians and stagehands,
who gathered with small vices great virtues, since you were not unscrupulous,
especially on wooing the ladies, and the horrendous consequeencias
that inevitably had to produce, and filled him with horror and fright.

Wanting to examine all statements made to bring him home from a minister, and on the way would
see a woman shaking her husband murdered by his presence. I get to third base of the statesman,
and spent two hours waiting for Dixer he was there, and other two after they had said, by this
time very firm purpose to recommend the minister and his insolent anger of the angel concierges
Ituriel. Was the crowded waiting room ladies of all kinds of wizards
of all colors, judges, merchants, officials and pedantic everyone
was complaining to the minister.

They said the greedy and profiteers: There is no doubt that this guy steals the provinces; disfigured
his flamboyant oddities, said the only sensual has had his tastes, and hoped the women would soon
replace him another minister more handsome.

Babuca heard all these reasons, and could not say, iQue is this man so happy! All your enemies have
them in your waiting room, their power overwhelms their envy, and looks quantos plants to hate him.
At last came into his cabinet, and saw an old man overwhelmed of years and chores, but still
alive, and very smart. Babuca Gustole because it seemed Babuca one worthy of esteem sugeto. The
conference was very interesting: the minister confessed it was most unfortunate man, who had by
rich and poor was, that he believed omnipotent and all was impaired,
that all benefits had been paid with ingratitude, and in forty years
of continuous tasks had been just a bit of satisfaction.

Enterneciose Babuca, and said among themselves that if he had made some mistakes this man,
and they loved him Ituriel punish angel, dexarle enough to charge, not exterminate.

I was arguing with the minister, when I enter the beautiful lady inattentive in whose house had Babuca
eaten, showing his face and eye symptoms of pain and anger. Burst out in bitter complaints against
the statesman, shed tears, lamented bitterly that her husband had denied a charge that could achieve
on its cradle, and that they made him creditor his wounds and services and speak with so much energy,
complained with such grace, faded with mana such objections, provided eloqueencia strengthened their
reasons, that left the cabinet until having the fortune of her husband.

Salio Babuca giving his hand and said to him: Is it possible, madam, that you have taken so much
work you by a man who you want, and how much you have to be afraid? ? How is it you do not love
him? replied the lady, know that my husband is the best friend I have in this world, and that
sacrificeth quanto by all I have, as it is not my lover to do the same thing, less sacrifice his
sweetheart. I want you to know it, it's a very nice lady, very quiet, and excellent genius
had dinner tonight with my husband and my friend the magician: come to join our taste.

She took the lady with him Babuca, and the husband who was plunged into deep grief over received
to his wife in a fit of gratitude and joy, give thousand hugs to his wife, his lady, the magician,
and Babuca. The banquet is encouraged by the happy, thanks and Donayre. Know, he told him the beautiful
lady who was having dinner, which is sometimes described as almost always women without honor
possess the virtues of an honest man, and in proof of this, come dine with me tomorrow home of the
beautiful Theon. Some old Vestal whisper it, but most charities do that together herself that the
bite; not commit the slightest injustice all interests in the world,
to her lover gives advice always generous, just glory by it, and would
blush if their presence on one occasion broken? to do good, because
there is no greater stimulus to virtuous actions, which have the judge
and witness of his conduct which longs for a beloved one to deserve
appreciation.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>