<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02125</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>40319</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18991</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Ignorando la causa, Leonardo, que era intrépido, retrocedió a la carrera, penetró por fuerza
por el corrillo y sacó a su amigo del apuro. Mas así que se informó por él mismo de lo que
había pasado, rió de ganas y le dijo: Te tomaron por montuno, Pancho. Tú también tienes una
figura...

--Mi figura no tiene nada que ver con el asunto, le interrumpió Pancho de mal talante; es que
estos españoles tienen más de judíos que de caballeros.

Siguiendo la calle de San Ignacio nuestros estudiantes, a poco andar desembocaron en la Plazuela
de la Catedral. Cuando llegaban a los portales de la casa conocida por de Filomeno, les llamó
la atención un grupo numeroso y compacto de pueblo que entraba en la misma por el lado opuesto,
es decir, por la calle de Mercaderes y el Boquete. La vanguardia, compuesta en su mayor parte
de gente de color, hombres, mujeres y muchachos sucios, harapientos y descalzos, ya marchaba,
ya hacía alto, y de cuando en cuando volvía atrás la cabeza, como por resorte. Entre dos filas
de soldados equipados a la ligera, pues su uniforme consistía de chaqueta de paño azul, pantalón
blanco, canana atada al cinto por delante, sombrero redondo y carabina corta, que portaban
por los tercios, iban hasta doce mulatos y negros vestidos en traje talar de sarga negra, con
caperuza de muselina blanca, cuya punta larga flotaba por detrás de la cabeza, a guisa de gallardete;
y cada cual llevaba en la mano derecha una cruz negra de brazo corto y árbol largo. Cuatro
de esos lúgubres hombres conducían al hombro, en silla de mano, a una al parecer criatura humana,
cuya cabeza y cuerpo desaparecían bajo los pliegues de un paño negro (manto de estameña), cayendo
a plomo por fuera de todo el aparato.

A un lado de este ser misterioso venía un sacerdote con sotana negra de seda, bonete en la
cabeza y un crucifijo en ambas manos; al otro un negro bastante joven, robusto y ágil. Este
vestía pantalón blanco, sombrero redondo y chaqueta de paño negro, en cuya espalda se le descubría
una como escalera bordada de seda amarilla. Eso indicaba su oficio, y era nada menos que el
verdugo. Andaba a paso medido y no levantaba los ojos del suelo. Detrás venía un hombre blanco
vestido de calzón corto, medias de seda, chupa de paño y sombrero de tres picos, todos de color
negro. Este era el escribano. Inmediato a él marchaba un militar de alta graduación indicada
por los tres entorchados de la casaca y el sombrero de tres picos galoneado de oro, con pluma
blanca de avestruz. Cerraban el cortejo otros negros y mulatos en el traje negro talar y caperuza
blanca, ya descrito, y más pueblo, todos moviéndose en solemne y silenciosa procesión, pues
no se oía otro ruido que los pasos acompasados de la tropa y la voz gangosa del sacerdote recitando
las oraciones de los moribundos.

Por esta rápida descripción advertirá el lector habanero que se trataba de un reo de muerte
que conducían al patíbulo, acompañándole los hermanos de la Caridad y de la Fe, institución
religiosa compuesta exclusivamente de gente de color que se ocupaba en asistir a los enfermos
y moribundos y en enterrar a los muertos, principalmente los cadáveres de los ajusticiados.
Es bien sabido que la justicia española lleva su saña hasta las puertas del sepulcro, y he
ahí la necesidad de la institución religiosa dicha, que se encarga de recoger el cadáver del
criminal y de darle sepultura, en vez de los parientes y amigos, privados de esos oficios por
la ley o la costumbre.

La tropa que custodiaba al reo en tales circunstancias, en La Habana al menos, era un piquete
de la célebre partida de Armona, especie de guardia civil, establecida por Vives, que desempeñaba
el papel de la policía de otras partes: el militar de alta graduación, el mayor de plaza, a
la sazón coronel Molina, después castellano del Morro, en cuyo empleo murió cargado con el
odio de aquéllos a quienes había oprimido y explotado mientras desempeñó el primero de estos
cargos: el individuo que conducían al suplicio de la manera referida no era hombre, sino mujer
y blanca; la primera tal vez de su clase que ejecutaban en La Habana.

CAPÍTULO IX

     ...Esta es la justicia
     Que facer el Rey ordena...

         EL DUQUE DE RIVAS

     D. Alvaro de Luna.

Contarse merece, siquiera sea brevemente, la historia de la mujer cuyo delito se castigaba
con la pena de muerte. Casada con un pobre campesino, vivía en los arrabales de la pequeña
población del Mariel, no sabemos cuanto tiempo hacía, ni hace mucho al caso tampoco. Pero sin
ser joven ni hermosa, contrajo ella relaciones ilícitas con un hombre soltero del mismo pueblo.
Séase que el marido averiguara lo que pasaba y amenazara tomar venganza, séase que los amantes
quisieran librarse de aquel estorbo, el hecho fue que entre los dos concertaron matarle. Y
conseguido esto, que no cuesta gran trabajo matar a un hombre, trataron de ocultar las huellas
del crimen descuartizando el cadáver y arrojando a un río inmediato los cuartos ensangrentados,
cosidos en un saco. Tales fueron los hechos principales dilucidados en la causa.

Ahora bien, ¿qué papel desempeñó la mujer en el horrible drama? Eso no se puso en claro. En
su defensa desplegó tan desinteresada como rara elocuencia el joven y brillante abogado Anacleto
Bermúdez,[16] que acababa de llegar de España, en cuyos consejos se había recibido de abogado
e hizo en esa causa su estreno como hábil criminalista. El hecho era atroz, sin embargo, y
la criminalidad de la mujer quedó probada, pues si no había herido con su propia mano, había
tomado parte principal en el asesinato y en la ocultación del cadáver. Se hizo, por tanto,
necesaria su condenación a último suplicio, aunque éste fuese el de horca, pues que entonces
sólo se aplicaba el del garrote a la gente noble, suceso todavía más raro en Cuba que el de
ejecutar a una mujer blanca.

La pena de muerte en horca, en los dominios españoles era, si cabe, más terrible que la del
garrote, introducida o generalizada algún tiempo después de aquel a que nos referimos ahora.
El verdugo, así que ataba dos sogas al pescuezo del reo, le lanzaba desde lo alto de la escalera,
se le montaba a horcajadas en los hombros, y con los calcañales le golpeaba el estómago para
apresurar su fin; deslizándose por los pies del ajusticiado, cuyo cadáver, dentro de un traje
talar, quedaba meciéndose al aire libre por ocho horas, a dos varas del suelo. Semejante espectáculo
no debía presentarse en La Habana con una mujer blanca, por vulgar que ella fuese u horrible
su delito.

En tal situación, y cuando hubo fallado el recurso de una supuesta preñez, Bermúdez solicitó
y obtuvo como gracia especial que se la hiciera morir en garrote. Recordará el lector que siete
u ocho años después de aquel a que nos contraemos ahora, se abolió el suplicio de horca en
Cuba, y que hallándose la cárcel en el ángulo occidental del edificio conocido por la Casa
de Gobierno, donde funcionaba asimismo el Ayuntamiento con todas sus dependencias, donde residía
el Capitán General con las suyas, y existían las escribanías públicas, tenía el reo que recorrer
una larga y angustiosa carrera antes que se pusiera fin a su vida en el campo de la Punta,
inmediato a la mar. En efecto, por la calle de Mercaderes pasaba a la plazuela de la Catedral,
torcía luego a la de San Ignacio, luego a la de Chacón, luego a la de Cuba, enseguida por la
orilla de la muralla a pasar por debajo de la puerta abovedada y oscura llamada de la Punta,
en que había cuerpo de guardia y daba salida a los cadáveres de la ciudad que llevaban a enterrar
en el cementerio general.

Al salir por aquella puerta de plaza sitiada, podía distinguir el reo a lo lejos, frente al
arrecibe de la costa contra la cual se rompían las olas del mar en menudos copos de brillante
espuma, la máquina terrible, horca, garrote o banquillo en que había de tener fin su vida.
Para los de ánimo apocado, la muerte con todos sus horrores era fuerza que se les presentase
mucho antes de recibirla. Por suerte, la mujer de que ahora hablamos, desde el momento que
la metieron en capilla perdió las fuerzas, y con ellas la conciencia de su horrible situación,
siendo preciso, como se ha visto, que la condujeran al lugar del suplicio en silla de mano,
sentarla a brazos en el banco del garrote, y, muerta ya, dislocarle la vértebra del cuello
para sofocar en su pecho el último soplo de vida.

Cinco o seis años después de los sucesos que acaban de referirse, había cambiado de un todo
el aspecto del campo de la Punta. Al yermo desolado y polvoroso que limitaba al oeste las primeras
casas de madera de la barriada de San Lázaro, por el sur rimeros de tablas y alfardas importadas
de los Estados Unidos del Norte de América, por el norte la mar y el castillo de la Punta,
que asomaba sus enanas almenas detrás de apiñadas calderas férreas de Carrón para la elaboración
del azúcar, sucedió un edificio de tres cuerpos, macizo, cuadrangular, erigido por el Capitán
General don Miguel Tacón para cárcel pública, depósito presidial y cuartel de infantería.

El espacio descubierto que quedó al lado septentrional de ese edificio, todavía se obstruyó
más con la construcción de unos cobertizos de madera para abrigo de una parte del presidio,
empleada en picar piedra menuda a martillo, con destino al empedrado de las calles de la ciudad,
según el sistema de McAdam. Pero, de todos modos, así quedó separada la prisión de la Casa
de Gobierno; los presos pasaron a un edificio, aunque defectuoso en muchos respectos, fabricado
expresamente para su desahogo y seguridad; hubo más conveniente separación de sexos y de delitos,
y, en especial, se redujo a la tercera parte la via crucis de los infelices reos de muerte,
pues que apenas se cuentan doscientos pasos de la cárcel nueva a la orilla del arrecife, donde
se efectuaban las ejecuciones capitales. De allí y de la Punta, a la parte opuesta, salieron
a recibir la muerte del patriota y del héroe, años adelante, Montes de Oca y el joven Facciolo;
el General López y el español Pintó; el bravo Estrampes; y, en nuestros días, Medina y León
y los inocentes estudiantes de la Universidad de La Habana.

Incorporáronse los tres amigos a la lúgubre procesión, y la acompañaron por el costado de la
Catedral hasta la puerta del Seminario, edificio que se extiende por el fondo de ella y da
sobre el puerto. No habían abierto aún la entrada a las aulas, y el golpe como de doscientos
estudiantes de derecho, filosofía y latín, la flor de la juventud cubana, se dilataba desde
las gradas de piedra de la portería hasta el cuartel de San Telmo por un lado, y por el otro
largo trecho hacia las bocacalles del Tejadillo y de San Ignacio, a causa de la estrechura
de la vía. Por un movimiento espontáneo, la muchedumbre estudiantil se dividió en dos filas,
dando paso franco por medio de la calle a la extraña comitiva, a la cual precedía un rumor
sordo como de enjambre de abejas que busca donde posarse.

Hizo alto por un momento ante la puerta del Seminario, para dar tiempo a que cuatro hermanos
de la Caridad y de la Fe relevasen a los que portaban la silla de mano desde la cárcel. La
figura entre tanto, no cambió de posición ni hizo el menor movimiento; pero aunque los pliegues
del manto negro ocultaban por completo sus facciones, su nombre y la historia de su crimen
corrieron de boca en boca entre todos los estudiantes.

--Nadie diría que llevan ahí a una mujer, dijo un estudiante de latín.

--En efecto, más parece la estatua de una llorona que ser viviente, agregó otro.

--El remordimiento la agobia, dijo un tercero. Por eso dobla la cabeza sobre el pecho.

--Ya, exclamó un estudiante alto, de aspecto amulatado; el caso no es para menos. Ahora supongo
yo que está horrorizada de su propio crimen.

--¿Pero está probado, como luz del mediodía, según reza la ley de Partida, preguntó nuestro
conocido Pancho, que Panchita mató a su marido?

--Tan cierto es que lo mató que le van a dar garrote, volvió a observar el estudiante amulatado,
con cierta sonrisa de desdén. Por más señas que después de muerto le hizo tasajo, y, cosiéndole
en un saco de henequén, le arrojó al río para pasto de los peces.

Todo eso no constituía un argumento de la criminalidad de Panchita Tapia, y su tocayo iba a
replicar cuando otro estudiante se interpuso diciendo en voz campanuda y acento español:

--Por un tris hace la chica con su consorte lo que dispone la ley de Partida que se haga con
el parricida. Sólo faltó que el saco fuera de cuero, que tuviese pintadas llamas coloradas
al exterior y que hubiese puesto en el interior un gallo, una víbora y un mono, animales que
no conocen padre ni madre.

--La ley de las Doce Tablas,[17] se apresuró a decir Pancho alzando la voz y empinándose un
tanto, contento de poder corregirle la plana al estudiante españolado--copiada pedem litterae
en las Partidas, que mandó compilar don Alfonso el Sabio--no habla de gallos, sino de perro,
víbora y mono, y no porque estos animales conozcan o desconozcan padre o madre, sino simplemente
para entregar el criminal a su furor. El Código Alfonsino considera parricida aún a la mujer
que mata a su marido. La práctica hoy día es arrastrar al reo en un serón atado a la cola de
un caballo hasta el pie del patíbulo. De suerte que, si no arrastran a Panchita Tapia, acusada
de ese horrendo crimen, la razón es porque no lo consienten nuestras costumbres. He dicho.

Con esto Pancho se alejó prontamente de aquel grupo, cosa de no dar tiempo a una réplica de
parte del estudiante españolado. Pero éste se contentó con decir, viéndole alejarse:

--Se conoce que el chico ha estudiado la lección.

En aquel mismo punto se abrieron las ponderosas hojas de cedro de la puerta del Seminario,
más conocido entonces bajo el nombre de Colegio de San Carlos. El gran patio lo constituían
cuatro corredores anchos, de columnas de piedra, formando un cuadrado. En el centro había una
fuente, y por todo el derredor naranjos lozanos y frondosos. En el lado opuesto a la entrada
principal, a la izquierda, había una escalera de piedra que conducía a los claustros de los
profesores; a la derecha, una reja que separaba el corredor de un callejón oscuro y húmedo,
por el cual se penetraba en un salón lateral, largo y sucio, separado de las aguas del puerto
por un jardín o huerto de tapias elevadas. Hacia allá daban unas cuatro ventanillas altas por
donde entraba la única luz que a medias alumbraba el salón. Contra la pared de enfrente, en
el centro, se poyaba una mala cátedra, y a ambos lados de ella había muchos bancos de madera,
rudos, fuertes y de elevado respaldo, colocados transversalmente.

Ahí se enseñaba filosofía; ahí enseñó por la primera vez esta ciencia a la juventud cubana
el ilustre padre Félix Varela, quien para ello redactó un texto, apartándose enteramente del
aristotélico, único seguido en Cuba hasta entonces, desde la fundación de la Universidad de
La Habana, en 1714, en el Convento de Santo Domingo. Cuando después, en 1821, el padre Varela
marchó de representante a las Cortes españolas, quedó sustituyéndole en la misma cátedra el
más aventajado de sus discípulos, José Antonio Saco, y en los momentos de nuestra historia
la desempeñaba el abogado Francisco Javier de la Cruz, por ausencia en el norte de América
del propietario y expatriación de su virtuoso fundador.

En el ángulo de la izquierda había otro salón, con entrada directamente del corredor, donde
enseñaba latín el padre Plumas. Luego, ocupando casi todo el otro lado, estaba el refectorio
de los seminaristas y algunos profesores que residían permanentemente en el mismo edificio,
y a la izquierda de la entrada principal estaba la ancha escalinata, dando acceso a los corredores
del piso alto. Por ésta subían los estudiantes de derecho no seminaristas; mientras los de
filosofía y latín entraban en los salones respectivos, ya mencionados, por las puertas al ras
del patio.

En la mañana del día que vamos refiriendo, cuando los estudiantes de derecho ponían el pie
en el primer escalón de la escalinata, se detuvieron en masa como reparasen en un grupo de
tres sujetos en animada conversación cerca de allí, bajo el corredor. El que llevaba la palabra
podía tener de 28 a 30 años de edad. Era de mediana estatura, de rostro blanco, con la color
bastante viva, los ojos azules y rasgados, boca grande de labios gruesos y cabello castaño
y lacio, aunque copioso. Había cierta reserva en su aspecto y vestía elegantemente, a la inglesa.
El otro de los tres personajes se podía decir el reverso de la medalla del ya descrito, pues
a un cuerpo rechoncho, cabeza grande, cuello corto, cabello crespo y muy negro: los ojos grandes
y saltones, el labio inferior belfo, dejando asomar dientes desiguales, anchos y mal puestos
agregaba un color de tabaco de hoja que hacía dudar mucho de la pureza de su sangre. El tercero
difería en diverso sentido de los dos mencionados, siendo más delgado que ellos, de más edad,
de color pálido y aspecto muy amable y delicado. Este era el catedrático de filosofía, Francisco
Javier de la Cruz; el anterior José Agustín Govantes, distinguido jurisconsulto que regentaba
la cátedra de derecho patrio; y el primero, nombrado José Antonio Saco, recién llegado del
Norte de América.

Precedía a éste la fama de sus escritos en el Mensajero Semanal, que publicaba en Nueva York,
según decían, con la cooperación del muy amado padre Varela, principalmente los que versaban
acerca de los sucesos y eminentes personajes de la revolución de México y de Colombia. Sobre
todo, acababa de leerse en La Habana, produciendo un vivo entusiasmo, su polémica crítico-política
con el encargado del Jardín Botánico, don Ramón de la Sagra, en defensa del poeta matancero[18]
José María Heredia.

De resultas de eso, los jóvenes cubanos, que ya se daban a la política, comenzaron a alejarse
de la clase de botánica que pretendía enseñar La Sagra, burlándose de él a medida que admiraban
a Saco, a quien tenían por un insurgente decidido, con cuya opinión, cosa singular, concurría
de plano el gobierno de la colonia.

Algunos de los estudiantes de derecho le reconoció, desde luego, por haber estudiado filosofía
con él en 1823 y murmuró su nombre, lo que fue bastante para que se pararan e hicieran una
exclamación más bien de curiosidad que de otra cosa. Esto hubo de atraer la atención de Govantes,
el cual, por señas, ordenó a sus discípulos que salieran al salón de clase, adonde él los seguiría
en breve.

Allá, en efecto, se encaminaron de tropel y entraron en el salón con gran algazara, hablando
de Saco, de Heredia, de su célebre Himno del desterrado y su no menos famosa oda Al Niágara,
inclusa en la colección de sus poesías impresas en Toluca, México; de las lecciones de botánica
de La Sagra, y de los héroes de la revolución de Colombia, aunque entonces imperfectamente
conocida por la juventud habanera. Cuando, poco después, entró Govantes a paso tardo, con un
libro debajo del brazo y el semblante risueño y animado, callaron de golpe los estudiantes
y reinó allí completo silencio. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00804</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>67634</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16883</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Ignoring
the cause, Leonardo, who was fearless, back to the race, entered by force the huddle and took
his friend's trouble. More so he was informed by what had happened, laughed at will and he
said, I took for montuno, Pancho. You too have a figure ...

- I figure it has nothing to do with it, Pancho broke in a bad mood, is that these Spanish Jews
have more than men's.

Following the road from San Ignacio our students, before long led to the Square the Cathedral.
When they reached the gates of the house known by Filomeno, called them attention to a large and
compact group of people who entered the same on the opposite side, ie, Merchants Street and Boquete.
The vanguard, composed mostly people of color, men, women and boys dirty, ragged and barefoot,
and walked away, was already high, and occasionally turned his head back, and by spring. Between
two rows equipped soldiers lightly, because their uniform was of blue cloth jacket, pants white
belt holster attached to the front, round hat and short rifle, carrying by thirds were mulatto
and black twelve dressed in black serge robe, with white muslin cap, the tip of long floated
behind the head, by way of a pennant; and every man carried in his right hand a black cross on the short
arm and long shaft. Four of those grim men drove to the shoulder, hand chair, apparently a
human creature, whose head and body hidden beneath the folds of black cloth (muslin robe), falling
to lead out of the whole apparatus.

On one side of this mysterious priest came a black silk robe, cap in head and a crucifix in
both hands, the other a black quite young, strong and agile. This wore white trousers and round
hat, black wool jacket, whose back was discovered one as a yellow silk embroidered ladder. Indicated
that his office, and was nothing less than the executioner. He walked a measured pace and not
raise his eyes from the ground. Behind came a white man dressed in knee breeches, silk stockings,
cloth waistcoat and cocked hat, all in color black. This was the scribe. He immediately marched
a senior military officer indicated by the three braid of the coat and cocked hat laced with
gold, with pen white ostrich. Closed the procession other blacks and mulattos in the cut black
suit and cap White, already described, and more people, all moving in solemn and silent procession,
for not heard another noise rhythmic steps of the troops and the shrill voice of the priest
reciting the prayers of the dying.

For this quick overview habanero warn the reader that he was a prisoner death that led to the
gallows, accompanying the Brothers of Charity and Faith, an institution Religious composed
exclusively of people of color who was busy attending to the sick and dying and burying the dead,
especially the bodies of the executed. It is well known that the Spanish justice takes his
anger to the gates of the grave, and I Hence the need for such a religious institution, which
is responsible for collecting the body of criminal and burial, rather than relatives and friends
of those offices by private law or custom.

The troops guarding the prisoner in such circumstances, in Havana at least, was a picket of the
famous game of Armona, a kind of civil guard, established by Vives, who played the role of police
in other parts, the senior military, the largest square, Colonel Molina the time after the
Morro Castilian, whose employment died loaded with hatred of those who had oppressed and exploited
while he held the first of these charges: the individual that led to execution in the manner
referred to was not a man, but women and white, perhaps the first of its kind that ran in Havana.

CHAPTER
IX

     ... This is justice That
     the King orders facer ...

THE DUKE OF RIVAS

D. Alvaro de Luna.

         

     

Deserves to be counted, even briefly, the story of the woman whose crime was punishable with
the death penalty. Married to a poor peasant living in the outskirts of the small Mariel population,
did not know how long, or make the case much either. But without be young and beautiful, she
contracted illicit relations with an unmarried man of the people. Seas, which the husband find
out what was happening and threatened to take revenge, that lovers séase wanted to get rid of
that nuisance, the fact was that the two agreed on killing him. Y got this great job that
it costs to kill a man, tried to hide the traces Crime dismembering the body and thrown into a
nearby river bloodstained rooms, sewn into a sack. Such were the main facts elucidated in the case.

But
what role women played in the terrible drama? It was not clear.

In defense deployed as disinterested as rare eloquence the brilliant young lawyer Anacleto
Bermudez, [16] who had just arrived from Spain, whose advice had been received from attorney and
in that case made its debut as a working criminal. The fact was outrageous, however, and Women's
crime was proved, for if there had wounded with his own hand, had taken a leading part in
the murder and hiding the corpse. It was therefore required its condemnation at the last execution,
but it was the gallows, because then only applied the stick of noble people, even rarer event
in Cuba than run at a white woman.

The penalty of death hanging in the Spanish dominions was, if anything,
more terrible than the club, or generalized introduced some time after
that to which we refer to now.

The executioner, so I tied two ropes around the neck of the defendant, he threw from the top
of the stairs he sat astride the shoulders, and the heel will hit the stomach to hasten its
end by sliding the foot of the executed, whose body, in a suit cut, was rocking outdoors for eight
hours, two yards from the ground. Show similar should not be presented in Havana with a white
woman, for her to be vulgar or ugly his crime.

In such a situation, and when he had failed the appeal of an alleged pregnancy, Bermudez asked
and obtained as a special grace that make her die in a club.

The reader will recall that seven or eight years after that to which we incur now abolished
the punishment of gallows Cuba, which the prison sits on the western corner of the building known
as the House Government, which also operated the City with all its dependencies, where he
lived Captain General with theirs, and there was the notary public, the inmate had to go a
long and harrowing race before it ended its life in the countryside of Punta, immediately to sea.
In effect, Merchants Street went to the square of the Cathedral then twisted to San Ignacio, then
to the Chacón, then to Cuba, then by edge of the wall to pass under the vaulted door of the
dark called Punta, he had body guards and gave out the bodies of the city who had to bury in the
general cemetery.

Walk out that door besieged city, could see the defendant in the distance, against arrecibe the coast
against which the waves broke in tiny flakes of bright foam machine
terrible, hanging, club, or dock, which was to have his life end.

For a fearful mood, death with all its horrors was force them to submit long before you receive
it. Luckily, the woman who now speak, from the moment Chapel put her in His strength, and with
them the awareness of their horrible situation, be accurate, as we have seen, that would lead
to the place of execution in sedan chair, sit at arms on the club's bank, and now dead, dislocate
the neck vertebra to put down on his chest the last breath of life.

Five or six years after the events just mentioned, had changed a whole the appearance of the
area of ??Punta. The desolate and dusty west limiting early wooden houses in the neighborhood
of San Lazaro, on the south stacks of tables and imported rafters
United States of North America in the north sea and Castle Point,
their dwarf battlements looming behind crowded railway boilers for
the production of Carron Sugar, did a building of three bodies, massive,
square, built by Captain General Miguel Tacon for public prison presidial
tank and infantry barracks.

The space was found on the north side of the building, still blocked more with the construction of
wooden sheds to shelter a portion of the presidio employed in chopping pebble hammer, towards
the cobbled streets of the city McAdam by system. But, anyway, so the prison was separated from
the House Government, prisoners went to a building, although flawed in many respects, made specifically
for relief and security, was more convenient single-sex and crime,
and, in particular, was reduced to one third of the via crucis of
the unfortunate death row inmates, they have barely two hundred yards
from the new jail on the edge of the reef, where were carried out
executions.

From there and the Punta, to the opposite side, left receiving the death of the patriot and
hero, years later, Montes de Oca and young Facciolo; General Lopez and Spanish painted, the
brave Estrampes and, today, and Leon Medina and the innocent students of the University of Havana.

Incorporáronse
three friends to the grim procession, and accompanied by the side of the Cathedral seminar
to the door of a building which extends from the bottom of it and gives on the port. They had not
yet opened the entrance to the classroom, and the coup as two hundred students of law, philosophy
and Latin, the flower of Cuban youth, expands from the stone steps of the goal to the headquarters
of San Telmo on the one hand, and on the other long way toward the canopy and side streets of
San Ignacio, because of the narrow road. By a spontaneous movement, the student crowd was divided
in two rows, giving free passage through the street to the strange procession, which preceded a
rumor deaf as a swarm of bees looking for resting place.

He stopped for a moment before the door of the seminar, to allow time for four children of Charity
and Faith relieve the chair carried by hand from the jail. The Figure meanwhile, did not change
position or made the slightest movement, but although the folds black mantle completely hid
his face, his name and his crime story ran from mouth to mouth among all students.

- No one would say that there are a woman, said a student of Latin.

- Indeed, the statue looks more like a screamer to be living, added another.

- Regret the overwhelming, "said a third. So bend your head on your chest.

- Ya, a student said high amulatado aspect, the case no wonder. Now suppose I was horrified that
his own crime.

- But is tested, as the light of noon, as stated in the party law,
asked our Pancho known that Panchita killed her husband?

- So much
so that killed him will give him stick, he returned to observe the
student amulatado, with a certain smile of disdain.

For more signs that after his death, he jerked, and cosiéndole in
a sisal sack, he threw into the river to feed the fishes.

All this argument did not constitute a crime of Panchita Tapia, and
his namesake would replicate when another student was brought calling
out Campanula Spanish accent:

- By an inch makes the girl with his
consort is hereby given that the law is made to Item the parricide.

Just missed the bag out of leather, which had flames painted red outside and inside had put
a rooster, a snake and a monkey, animals do not know father or mother.

-
The Law of the Twelve Tables, [17] Pancho said quickly, raising his
voice and raising up a So happy to correct your student flat Spanish
- copied pedem litterae in games, he sent Alfonso the Wise compile
- not talking about cocks, but dog snake and monkey, and not because
these animals known or unknown father or mother, but simply to deliver
the criminal to his fury.

The Code considers parricide Alfonsino women still who kills her husband. The practice today is
to drag the defendant in a basket attached to the tail a horse to the foot of the gallows. So that,
if not drag Panchita Tapia, accused of this heinous crime, the reason
is because I do not agree to our customs.

I said.

This Pancho away quickly from that group, something not allow time for replication part of the
Spanish students. But he contented himself with saying, seeing him away:

- It is known that the boy has studied the lesson.

At that point they opened the powerful cedar leaves the door Seminar better known then under
the name of Colegio de San Carlos. The large patio is constituted four riders wide, stone columns,
forming a square. In the center was a source, and all around lush and leafy orange trees. On
the opposite side of the entry main, left, had a stone staircase leading to the clusters of
teachers, on the right, a fence that separated the corridor of a dark alley and humid which is
penetrated by a side room, long and dirty water separate port a garden
or orchard high walls.

That way they gave a high and four windows where the only light came half lit the room. Against
the opposite wall, in the center, poyaba a bad chair, and on both
sides of it there were many wooden benches tough, strong and high
back, placed transversely.

There he taught philosophy, then taught for the first time this science to Cuban youth the illustrious
Father Felix Varela, who wrote a text for it, withdrawing entirely from Aristotle, followed in
Cuba only until then, since the founding of the University of Havana in 1714, in the Convent
of Santo Domingo. When later, in 1821, Father Varela representative went to the Spanish Cortes,
was replaced in the same chair the most outstanding of his disciples, José Antonio Saco, and
the moments of our history The lawyer played Francisco Javier de la Cruz, the absence in North
America Owner and founder of his virtuous expatriation.

In the corner on the left was another room, with input directly from the corridor, where Plumas
father taught Latin.

Then, occupying most of the other hand, was the refectory of seminarians and some faculty
residing permanently in the same building and left of the main entrance was the broad staircase,
giving access to brokers upstairs. It rose by law students not seminarians, while those of
philosophy and Latin entering respective classrooms, already mentioned, for flush doors the patio.

In
the morning we are referring to, when law students set foot in the first step of the stairs,
stopped mass repairs in a group of three subjects in lively conversation about there, under
the corridor. On his remarks could take 28 to 30 years of age. He was of medium height, his
face white with color very much alive, and torn blue eyes, large
mouth with thick lips and dark hair and straight, but hearty.

There was some reservation in appearance and elegantly dressed, in the English. The other three
characters you could say the reverse of the medal already described, as a stocky body, large
head, short neck, curly and very black hair, big eyes and protruding lower lip lip, leaving
uneven teeth hover, wide and misplaced snuff added a leaf color that was much doubt the purity of
their blood. The third differed in several respects from the two mentioned, being thinner
than them, older pale and looked very nice and delicate. This was the philosophy professor, Francisco
Javier de la Cruz, José Agustín Govantes above, a distinguished jurist
who ran the chair of patriotic duty, and the first named José Antonio
Saco, fresh from North America.

It preceded the fame of his writings in the Weekly Messenger, which published in New York, they
said, with the cooperation of the beloved Father Varela, especially those who dealt with about
events and prominent figures of the revolution in Mexico and Colombia. About However, just
read in Havana, producing a lively enthusiasm, critical and political controversy with the manager
of the Botanic Garden, Don Ramón de la Sagra, in defense of Matanzas poet [18] José María Heredia.

Following
that, the young Cuban, who already gave to politics, began to drift away botany class that sought
to teach La Sagra, taunting him as he admired to Saco, who had decided by an insurgent, with
whose opinion, something unique, she attended plane the government of the colony.

Some law students recognized him, of course, having studied philosophy with him in 1823 and murmured
his name, which was enough to make it stop and make a exclamation rather curious than anything
else. This was to attract the attention of Govantes, which, by signs, ordered his followers
to leave the classroom, where he would shortly.

There, in fact, headed in droves and entered the room with great jubilation, speaking Saco, de
Heredia, in his famous anthem of the exile and his equally famous ode to Niagara including the collection
of his poems printed in Toluca, Mexico, of botany lessons La Sagra, and heroes of the revolution
in Colombia, even then imperfectly known by the youth of Havana.

When, soon after, entered Govantes a slow pace, with a book under his arm and smiling face and
lively, stopped abruptly students and complete silence reigned there.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>