<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04501</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>52679</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18946</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Lejos, en el sitio donde la barca había estado próxima a zozobrar, flotaba un objeto negro
sobre las aguas.

--¡Allá está!

Y el padre se arrojó al agua, nadando vigorosamente, mientras el compañero amainaba la vela.

Nadó y nadó, pero sus fuerzas casi le abandonaron al convencerse de que el objeto era un remo,
un despojo de su barca.

Cuando las olas le levantaban, sacaba el cuerpo fuera para ver más lejos. Agua por todas partes.
Sobre el mar sólo estaban él, la barca que se aproximaba y una curva negra que acababa de surgir
y que se contraía espantosamente sobre una gran mancha de sangre.

El atún había muerto... ¡Valiente cosa le importaba! ¡La vida de su hijo único, de su Antoñico,
a cambio de la de aquella bestia! ¡Dios! ¿Era esto manera de ganarse el pan?

Nadó más de una hora, creyendo a cada rozamiento que el cuerpo de su hijo iba a surgir bajo
sus piernas, imaginándose que las sombras de las olas eran el cadáver del niño que flotaba
entre dos aguas.

Allí se hubiera quedado, allí habría muerto con su hijo. El compadre tuvo que pescarlo y meterlo
en la barca como un niño rebelde.

--¿Qué hacemos, Antonio?

Él no contestó.

--No hay que tomarlo así, hombre. Son cosas de la vida. El chico ha muerto donde murieron todos
nuestros parientes, donde moriremos nosotros. Todo es cuestión de más pronto o más tarde...
Pero ahora, a lo que estamos; a pensar que somos unos pobres.

Y preparando dos nudos corredizos apresó el cuerpo del atún y lo llevó a remolque de la barca,
tiñendo con sangre las espumas de la estela.

El viento les favorecía, pero la barca estaba inundada, navegaba mal, y los dos hombres, marineros
ante todo, olvidaron la catástrofe, y con los achicadores en la mano, encorváronse dentro de
la cala, arrojando paletadas de agua al mar.

Así pasaron las horas. Aquella ruda faena embrutecía a Antonio, le impedía pensar; pero de
sus ojos rodaban lágrimas y más lágrimas, que, mezclándose con el agua de la cala, caían en
el mar sobre la tumba del hijo.

La barca navegaba con creciente rapidez, sintiendo que se vaciaban sus entrañas.

El puertecillo estaba a la vista, con sus masas de blancas casitas doradas por el sol de la tarde.

La vista de tierra despertó en Antonio el dolor y el espanto adormecidos.

--¿Qué dirá mi mujer? ¿Qué dirá mi Rufina?--gemía el infeliz.

Y temblaba como todos los hombres enérgicos y audaces, que en el hogar son esclavos de la familia.

Sobre el mar deslizábase como una caricia el ritmo de alegres valses. El viento de tierra saludaba
a la barca con melodías vivas y alegres. Era la música que tocaba en el paseo, frente al Casino.
Por debajo de las achatadas palmeras desfilaban, como las cuentas de un rosario de colores,
las sombrillas de seda, los sombreritos de paja, los trajes claros y vistosos de toda la gente
de veraneo.

Los niños, vestidos de blanco y rosa, saltaban y corrían tras sus juguetes, o formaban alegres
corros girando como ruedas de colores.

En el muelle se agolpaban los del oficio: su vista, acostumbrada a las inmensidades del mar,
había reconocido lo que remolcaba la barca. Pero Antonio sólo miraba, al extremo de la escollera,
a una mujer alta, escueta y negruzca, erguida sobre un peñasco, y cuyas faldas arremolinaba
el viento.

Llegaron al muelle. ¡Qué ovación! Todos querían ver de cerca el enorme animal. Los pescadores,
desde sus botes, lanzaban envidiosas miradas; los pilletes, desnudos, de color de ladrillo,
echábanse al agua para tocarle la enorme cola.

Rufina se abrió paso entre la gente, llegando hasta su marido, que con la cabeza baja y una
expresión estúpida oía las felicitaciones de los amigos.

--¿Y el chico? ¿Dónde está el chico?

El pobre hombre aún bajó más su cabeza. La hundió entre los hombros, como si quisiera hacerla
desaparecer, para no oír, para no ver nada.

--¿Pero dónde está Antoñico?

Y Rufina, con los ojos ardientes, como si fuera a devorar a su marido, le agarraba de la pechera,
zarandeando rudamente a aquel hombrón. Pero no tardó en soltarle, y levantando los brazos,
prorrumpió en espantoso alarido.

--¡Ay, Señor!... ¡Ha muerto! ¡Mi Antoñico se ha ahogado! ¡Está en el mar!

--Sí, mujer--dijo el marido lentamente con torpeza, balbuceando y como si le ahogaran las lágrimas--.
Somos muy desgraciados. El chico ha muerto; está donde su abuelo; donde estaré yo cualquier
día. Del mar comemos y el mar ha de tragarnos... ¡Qué remedio! No todos nacen para obispos.

Pero su mujer no le oía. Estaba en el suelo, agitada por una crisis nerviosa, y se revolcaba
pataleando, mostrando sus flacas y tostadas desnudeces de animal de trabajo, mientras se tiraba
de las greñas, arañándose el rostro.

--¡Mi hijo!... ¡Mi Antoñico!...

Las vecinas del barrio de los pescadores acudieron a ella. Bien sabían lo que era aquello:
casi todas habían pasado por trances iguales. La levantaron, sosteniéndola con sus poderosos
brazos, y emprendieron la marcha hacia su casa.

Unos pescadores dieron un vaso de vino a Antonio, que no cesaba de llorar. Y mientras tanto,
el compadre, dominado por el egoísmo brutal de la vida, regateaba bravamente con los compradores
de pescado que querían adquirir la hermosa pieza.

Terminaba la tarde. Las aguas, ondeando suavemente, tomaban reflejos de oro.

A intervalos sonaba cada vez más lejos el grito desesperado de aquella pobre mujer, desgreñada
y loca, que las amigas empujaban a casa.

--¡Antoñico! ¡Hijo mío!

Y bajo las palmeras seguían desfilando los vistosos trajes, los rostros felices y sonrientes,
todo un mundo que no había sentido pasar la desgracia junto a él, que no había lanzado una
mirada sobre el drama de la miseria; y el vals elegante, rítmico y voluptuoso, himno de la
alegre locura, deslizábase armonioso sobre las aguas, acariciando con su soplo la eterna hermosura
del mar.

¡Hombre al agua!

Al cerrar la noche, salió de Torrevieja el laúd San Rafael, con cargamento de sal para Gibraltar.

La cala iba atestada, y sobre cubierta amontonábanse los sacos, formando una montaña en torno
del palo mayor. Para pasar de proa a popa, los tripulantes iban por las bordas, sosteniéndose
con peligroso equilibrio.

La noche era buena; noche de verano, con estrellas a granel y un vientecillo fresco algo irregular,
que tan pronto hinchaba la gran vela latina, hasta hacer gemir el mástil, como cesaba de soplar,
cayendo desmayada la inmensa lona con ruidoso aleteo.

La tripulación, cinco hombres y un muchacho, cenó después de la maniobra de salida, y una vez
rebañado el humeante caldero, en el que hundían su mendrugo con marinera fraternidad desde
el patrón al grumete, desaparecieron por la escotilla todos los libres de servicio, para reposar
sobre la dura colchoneta, con los vientres hinchados de vino y zumo de sandía.

Quedó en el timón el tío Chispas, un tiburón desdentado, que acogió con gruñidos de impaciencia
las últimas indicaciones del patrón, y junto a él su protegido Juanillo, un novato que hacía
en el San Rafael su primer viaje, y le estaba muy agradecido al viejo, pues gracias a él había
entrado en la tripulación, matando así su hambre, que no era poca.

El mísero laúd antojábasele al muchacho un navío almirante, un buque encantado, navegando por
el mar de la abundancia. La cena de aquella noche era la primera cena seria que había hecho
en su vida.

Había llegado a los diez y nueve años, hambriento y casi desnudo como un salvaje, durmiendo
en la torcida barraca donde gemía y rezaba su abuela, inmóvil por el reuma: de día ayudaba
a botar las barcas, descargaba cestas de pescado, o iba de parásito en las lanchas que perseguían
al atún y la sardina, para llevar a casa un puñado de pesca menuda. Pero ahora, gracias al
tío Chispas, que le tenía ley por haber conocido a su padre, era todo un marinero, estaba en
camino de ser algo, podía con todo derecho meter su brazo en el caldero, y hasta llevaba zapatos,
los primeros de su vida, unas soberbias piezas capaces de navegar como una fragata, que le
sumían en éxtasis de adoración. ¡Y aún dicen que si el mar!... Vamos, hombre. El mejor oficio
del mundo.

El tío Chispas, sin apartar la vista de la proa ni las manos del timón, agachándose para sondear
la oscuridad por entre la vela y el montón de sacos, le escuchaba con sonrisa marrullera.

--Sí; no has escogido mal oficio. Pero tiene quiebras. Las verás... cuando tengas mis años...
Pero tu sitio no es aquí: anda a proa y avisa si ves por delante alguna barca.

Juanillo corrió por la borda con la segura tranquilidad de un pillo de playa.

--Cuidado, muchacho, cuidado.

Pero él ya estaba en la proa, y se sentó junto al botalón, escudriñando la negra superficie
del mar, en cuyo fondo se reflejaban como serpeantes hilos de luz las inquietas estrellas.

El laúd, panzudo y pesado, caía tras cada ola con un solemne ¡chap! que hacía saltar las gotas
hasta la cara de Juanillo: dos hojas de espuma fosforescentes resbalaban por ambos lados de
la gruesa proa, y la hinchada vela, con el vértice perdido en la oscuridad, parecía arañar
la bóveda del cielo.

¿Qué rey ni qué almirante estaba mejor que el serviola del San Rafael?... ¡Brrru! Su estómago
repleto le saludaba con eructos de satisfacción. ¡Vida más hermosa!...

--¡Tío Chispas!... Un cigarro.

--Ven por él.

Juanillo corrió por la borda del lado contrario al viento. Era un momento de calma, y la vela
rizábase con fuertes palpitaciones, próxima a caer desmayada a lo largo del mástil. Pero vino
una ráfaga, y la barca se inclinó con rápido movimiento; Juanillo, para guardar el equilibrio,
agarrose al borde de la vela, y en el mismo instante ésta se hinchó como si fuera a estallar,
lanzando al laúd en una carrera veloz y empujando con fuerza tan irresistible todo el cuerpo
del muchacho, que lo disparó como una catapulta.

En el ruido de las aguas al tragarse a Juanillo creyó oír éste un grito, palabras algo confusas;
tal vez el viejo timonel que gritaba: «¡Hombre al agua!»

Bajó mucho, ¡mucho! atolondrado por el golpe, por lo inesperado de la caída; pero antes de
darse cuenta exacta de ello viose otra vez en la superficie del mar braceando, absorbiendo
con furia el fresco viento... ¿Y la barca? No la vio ya. El mar estaba oscurísimo; más oscuro
que visto desde la cubierta del laúd.

Creyó distinguir una mancha blanca, un fantasma que flotaba a lo lejos sobre las olas, y nadó
hacia él. Pero de pronto ya no lo vio allí, sino en lugar opuesto, y cambió de dirección, desorientado,
nadando con fuerza, pero sin saber dónde iba.

Los zapatos pesaban como si fuesen de plomo: ¡malditos! ¡la primera vez que los usaba! La gorra
le martirizaba las sienes; los pantalones tiraban de él como si llegasen hasta el fondo del
mar y fuesen barriendo las algas.

--Calma, Juanillo, calma.

Y arrojó la gorra, lamentando no poder hacer lo mismo con los zapatos.

Tenía confianza. Él nadaba mucho: se sentía con aguante para dos horas. Los de la barca virarían
para pescarle: un remojón y nada más... ¿pues qué así como así mueren los hombres? En un temporal,
como habían muerto su padre y su abuelo, bueno, pero en noche tan hermosa y con buena mar,
morir empujado por una vela sería una muerte de tonto.

Y nadaba y nadaba, siempre creyendo ver aquel fantasma indeciso que cambiaba de sitio, esperando
que de la oscuridad surgiera el San Rafael viniendo en su busca.

--¡Ah de la barca! ¡Tío Chispas!... ¡Patrón!

Pero el gritar le fatigaba y dos o tres veces las olas le taparon la boca. ¡Malditas!... Desde
la barca parecían insignificantes, pero en medio del mar, hundido hasta el cuello y obligado
a un continuo manoteo para sostenerse, le asfixiaban, le golpeaban con su sorda ondulación,
abrían ante él hondas y movibles zanjas, cerrándolas en seguida como para tragarle.

Seguía creyendo, pero con cierta inquietud, en sus dos horas de aguante. Sí; contaba con ellas.
Dos horas y más nadaba allá en su playa sin cansancio. Pero era en las horas de sol, en aquel
mar de cristal azul, viendo allá bajo, a través de fantástica transparencia, las rocas amarillas
con sus hierbajos puntiagudos como ramos de coral verde, las conchas de color rosa, las estrellas
de nácar, las flores luminosas de pétalos carnosos estremeciéndose al ser rozados por el vientre
de plata de los peces; y ahora estaba en un mar de tinta, perdido en la oscuridad, agobiado
por sus ropas, teniendo bajo sus pies ¡quién sabe cuántos barcos destrozados, cuántos cadáveres
descarnados por los peces feroces! Y estremecíase al contacto de su mojado pantalón, creyendo
sentir el rozamiento de agudos dientes.

Cansado, desfallecido, se echó de espaldas, dejándose llevar por las olas. El sabor de la cena
le subía a la boca. ¡Maldita comida, y cuánto cuesta de ganar! Acabaría por morir allí tontamente...
Pero el instinto de conservación le hizo incorporarse. Tal vez le buscaban, y estando tendido
pasarían cerca de él sin verle. Otra vez a nadar, con el ansia de la desesperación, incorporándose
en la cresta de las olas para ver más lejos, yendo tan pronto a un lado como a otro, agitándose
siempre en un mismo círculo.

Le abandonaban como si fuese un trapo caído de la barca. ¡Dios mío! ¿Así se olvida a un hombre?...
Pero no; tal vez le buscaban en aquel momento. Un barco corre mucho; por pronto que hubiesen
subido a cubierta y arriado vela, ya estarían a más de una milla.

Y acariciando esta ilusión, se hundía dulcemente como si tirasen de sus pesados zapatos. Sintió
en la boca la amargura salitrosa; cegaron sus ojos, las aguas se cerraron sobre su rapada cabeza;
pero entre dos olas se formó un pequeño remolino, asomaron unas manos crispadas y volvió a salir.

Los brazos se dormían; la cabeza se inclinaba sobre el pecho como vencida por el sueño. A Juanillo
le pareció cambiado el cielo: las estrellas eran rojas, como salpicaduras de sangre. Ya no
le infundía miedo el mar; sentía el deseo de abandonarse sobre las aguas, de descansar.

Se acordaba de la abuela, que a aquellas horas estaría pensando en él. Y quiso rezar como mil
veces había oído a su pobre vieja. «Padre nuestro que estás...» Rezaba mentalmente, pero sin
darse cuenta de ello, su lengua se movió y dijo con una voz tan ronca que le pareció de otro:

--¡Cochinos! ¡ladrones! ¡Me abandonan!

Se hundía otra vez: desapareció pugnando en vano por sostenerse. Alguien tiraba de sus zapatos...
Buceó en la oscuridad, sorbiendo agua, inerte, sin fuerzas, pero sin saber cómo, volvió otra
vez a la superficie.

Ahora las estrellas eran negras, más negras que el cielo, destacándose como gotas de tinta.

Se acabó. Esta vez se iba al fondo de veras: su cuerpo era de plomo. Y bajó en línea recta,
arrastrado por sus zapatos nuevos, y en su caída al abismo de los barcos rotos y los esqueletos
devorados, el cerebro, cada vez más envuelto en densas neblinas, iba repitiendo:

--Padre nuestro... Padre nuestro... ¡ladrones! ¡granujas! ¡Me han abandonado!

Un silbido

El entusiasmo caldeaba el teatro. ¡Qué debut! ¡Qué Lohengrin! ¡Qué tiple aquella!

Sobre el rojo de las butacas destacábanse en el patio las cabezas descubiertas o las torres
de lazos, flores y tules, inmóviles, sin que las aproximara el cuchicheo ni el fastidio; en
los palcos silencio absoluto; nada de tertulias y conversaciones a media voz; arriba, en el
infierno de la filarmonía rabiosa, llamado irónicamente paraíso, el entusiasmo se escapaba
prolongado y ruidoso, como un inmenso suspiro de satisfacción, cada vez que sonaba la voz de
la tiple, dulce, poderosa y robusta. ¡Qué noche! Todo parecía nuevo en el teatro. La orquesta
era de ángeles: hasta la araña del centro daba más luz.

En aquel entusiasmo tomaba no poca parte el patriotismo satisfecho. La tiple era española,
la López, sólo que ahora se anunciaba con el apellido de su esposo el tenor Franchetti; un
gran artista que, casándose con ella, la había hecho ascender a la categoría de estrella. ¡Vaya
una mujer! Legítima de la tierra. Esbelta, arrogante; brazos y garganta con adorables redondeces,
y los blancos tules de Elsa amplios en la cintura, pero estrechos y casi estallando con la
presión de soberbias curvas. Sus ojos negros, rasgados, de sombrío fuego, contrastaban con
la rubia peluca de la condesa de Brabante. La hermosa española era en la escena la mujer tímida,
dulce y resignada que soñó Wágner, confiando en la fuerza de su inocencia, esperando el auxilio
de lo desconocido.

Al relatar su ensueño ante el emperador y su corte, cantó con expresión tan vagorosa y dulce,
los brazos caídos y la extática mirada en lo alto, como si viese llegar montado en una nube
al misterioso paladín, que el público no pudo contenerse ya, y como la retumbante descarga
de una fila de cañones, salió de todos los huecos del teatro, hasta de los pasillos, la atronadora
detonación de aplausos y gritos.

La modestia y la gracia con que saludaba enardeció aún más al público. ¡Qué mujer! Una verdadera
señora; y en cuanto a buenos sentimientos, todos recordaban detalles de su biografía. Aquel
padre anciano, al que todos los meses enviaba una pensión para que viviera con decencia: un
viejo feliz, que desde Madrid seguía la carrera de triunfos de su hija por todo el mundo.

Aquello era conmovedor. Algunas señoras se llevaban a los ojos una punta del guante, y en el
paraíso, un vejete lloriqueaba metiendo la nariz en el embozo de la capa para sofocar sus gemidos.
Los vecinos se reían.

¡Vamos hombre, que no era para tanto!

La representación seguía su curso en medio de los ecos del entusiasmo. Ahora el heraldo invitaba
a los presentes, por si alguno quería defender a Elsa. Bueno, adelante. Aquel público, que
se sabía de memoria la ópera, estaba en el secreto. No se presentaría ningún guapo. Después,
con acompañamiento de tétrica música, avanzaron las damas veladas para llevarse la condesa
al suplicio. Todo era broma; Elsa estaba segura. Pero cuando los bravos guerreros brabanzones
se agitaron en la escena, viendo a lo lejos el misterioso cisne y su barquilla, y se fue armando
en la imperial corte una batahola de dos mil demonios, el público, por acción refleja, se movió
ruidosamente, arrellanándose en el asiento, tosiendo, suspirando, revolviéndose para hacer
provisión de silencio. ¡Qué emoción! Iba a presentarse Franchetti, el famoso tenor, un gran
artista de quien se murmuraba que habíase casado con la López buscando una compensación a sus
facultades decadentes en la frescura y valentía de su mujer. Aparte de esto, un maestrazo que
sabía salir triunfante con auxilio del arte.

¡Ah!... Ya estaba allí, de pie en el esquife, apoyado en larga espada, el escudo embrazado,
cubierto el pecho de escamas de acero, irguiendo su arrogante figura de buen mozo festejado
por toda la aristocracia de Europa, y deslumbrando de cabeza a pies, cual un pescado de plata
envuelto en seda.

Silencio absoluto; aquello parecía una iglesia. El tenor miraba su cisne, como si allí no hubiese
otro ser digno de atención, y en el místico ambiente fue desarrollándose un hilo de voz tenue,
dulce, vagoroso, cual si viniera de una distancia invisible.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01943</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>47</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16911</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Far to the site where the boat had been close to capsizing, a black object floating on the
water.

- There he is!

And the father jumped into the water, swimming vigorously, while the
companion slackened sail.

He swam and swam, but its forces left him convinced that the object
was a rowing a wreck of his boat.

When the waves lifted up, pulled the body out to see farther. Water everywhere. Over the sea
were just him, the boat approached and a black curve that had just emerged and horribly contracted
on a large bloodstain.

The tuna was dead ... Valiente thing he cared!

The life of his only son, of Anton in exchange of that beast!

God! Was this way of earning a living?

He swam more than an hour, believing that each friction body of his
son would arise under his legs, imagining that the shadows of the
waves were the child's body floating between two stools.

There had been, there would have died with his son. The friend had to catch it and put in the boat
like a rebellious child.

- What we do, Anthony?

He did not answer.

- Do not take it well, man. Are things in life. The dead boy that
killed all our relatives, where we die.

All a matter of sooner or later ... But now, what we are, to think
that we are poor.

And preparing two nooses tuna seized the body and took him to tow the boat with blood staining the
foam of the wake.

The wind favored them, but the boat was flooded, was sailing badly, and the two men, sailors Above
all, forget the disaster, and the scoops in hand, worshiped the inside
the creek, throwing shovels of water into the sea.

So the hours passed. That tough task brutalized Antonio, prevented him from thinking, but tears
were rolling their eyes and more tears, which, mixing with water from the creek, fell in the sea
over the grave of the child.

The boat was sailing with increasing speed, feeling emptied their bowels.

The small port was in sight, with its masses of white houses by the
golden afternoon sun.

The sight of land awoke in pain and Antonio numb horror.

- What will
my wife?

What will my Rufina? - Groaned the unhappy.

And all men trembling as energetic and daring, which at home are slaves
of the family.

Glided over the sea like a caress cheerful rhythm of waltz.

The land breeze greeted the boat with live and lively melodies.

It was the music played on the promenade, opposite the Casino. Below the flattened palm parade, like
beads on a string of colors, the umbrellas of silk, straw hats, clear and colorful costumes
of all people summer.

The children, dressed in white and pink, leaping and running after their toys, or were gay Outcry
as color wheels turning.

In the spring thronged the office: his eyes, accustomed to the vastness of the sea, had recognized
what was towing the boat. But Anthony only looked at the end of the pier, a tall, bald and blackened,
standing on a rock, whose skirts swirled the wind.

They arrived at the pier. What cheer!

Everyone wanted to see up close the huge animal.

Fishermen, from their boats, threw envious glances, the rascals, nude-colored brick echábanse
water to touch the huge tail.

Rufina was opened through the crowd, reaching her husband, who with his head down and stupid expression
I heard the congratulations of friends.

- And the boy? Where's the boy?

The poor man still more his head down.

The sunk between his shoulders, as if to make disappear, refusing to hear, not see anything.

- But Where is Anton?

And Rufina, with shining eyes, as if to devour her husband, she held on to the front, rudely shaking
that big man. But soon release him, and lifting the arms, burst into terrible scream.

- Oh, Lord ... He is dead! My Anton has drowned! Is in the sea!

- Yes, women - the husband slowly said awkwardly, mumbling, as if you drown the tears -. We are very
unfortunate. The boy is dead, is where his grandfather, where I will
be any day.

Eat sea and the sea has to swallow ... What a relief! Not everyone is born for bishops.

But his wife did not hear him. Was on the ground, shaken by a nervous breakdown, and rolled kicking,
showing her thin and roasted animal nakedness of work, while pulling
by the hair, scratching his face.

- My son!

... My Anton! ...

The neighboring district of fishermen flocked to it.

They knew what it meant: nearly all had gone through the same perils. They lifted her up, holding
it with his powerful arms, and marched towards his house.

Some fishermen took a glass of wine to Antonio, who never ceased to mourn. Meanwhile, compadre,
dominated by the brutal selfishness of life, with buyers haggled fiercely fish that wanted to
purchase a beautiful piece.

The afternoon. The waters, waving gently, taking gold reflections.

At intervals sounded farther and farther away the desperate cry of the poor woman, disheveled and
crazy, jostled her friends home.

- Anton! My son!

And under the palm trees were still parading the colorful costumes,
happy, smiling faces, a world that had not felt the misfortune to
spend with him, who had launched a look at the drama of poverty, and
the elegant waltz, rhythmic and voluptuous, anthem cheerful madness,
harmonious glided over the water, stroking his breath the eternal
beauty the sea.

Man overboard!

As the night, left the lute Torrevieja San Rafael, with a cargo of salt to Gibraltar.

The cove was packed, and on deck amontonábanse sacks, forming a mountain around the mainmast.
To move from stem to stern, the crew were on the edges, holding with
dangerous balance.

The night was good summer night with stars in bulk and a cool breeze, somewhat irregular, that
as soon swelled the great lateen sail up the mast to moan as ceased to blow, falling faint the
vast canvas with loud flapping.

The crew, five men and a boy, had dinner after the exit maneuver, and once slicing the steaming
cauldron, which sank the fishing fraternity from crust to the pattern
to the boy disappeared down the hatch all off duty, to stand on the
hard mattress, their bellies swollen with wine and watermelon juice.

It was at the helm Uncle Sparks, a toothless shark that growls eagerly welcomed the latest
indications of the pattern, and with him his protege Juanillo, a rookie who did San Rafael
in his first trip, and I was very grateful to the old man through whom he entered in the crew,
killing your hunger, it was not little.

The wretched lute antojábasele the boy a ship Admiral, a happy ship,
sailing sea ??of ??plenty.

Dinner that night was the first dinner he had made serious in your life.

Had reached nineteen years, hungry and almost naked as a savage, sleeping
the crooked hut where her grandmother wailed and prayed, still by
rheumatism: day helped to launch the boats unloading fish baskets,
or pest was in boats chasing tuna and sardines, to take home a handful
of tiny fish.

But now, thanks to Uncle Sparks, who was law for having known his
father, he was a sailor, was in way if anything, could rightly put
his arm into the cauldron, and even wore shoes, the first of his life,
superb pieces able to navigate as a frigate, which plunged in an ecstasy
of worship.

And yet they say that if the sea! ... Come on, man. The best profession
the world.

Uncle Sparks, without looking away from the bow rudder and hands, bending to probe the dark
between the sail and the pile of bags, we listened with crafty smile.

-
Yes, no profession has made a bad choice.

But is bankruptcy. You'll see ... when you're my age ... But your site is here: go ahead and warn
if you see a boat ahead.

Juanillo ran overboard with the peace of a rogue safe beach.

- Careful, boy, watch out.

But he was in the bow, and sat next to boom, peering into the black surface sea, at the bottom of
reflected light as serpentine thread of the restless stars.

The lute, paunchy and heavy, fell after each wave with a grand chap! I did jump drops Juanillo to
face: two sheets of phosphorescent foam running down both sides of the thick nose, swollen and sailing,
with the top lost in the darkness, seemed to scratch the vault of heaven.

What king or what Admiral was better than the watchman of the San Rafael? ... Brrru! Her stomach
belching greeted him with full satisfaction.

Life more beautiful! ...

- Uncle Sparks! ... A cigar.

- Come get it.

Juanillo ran down the side of the side opposite the wind. It was a moment of quiet, and sailing rizábase
with strong palpitations, fainting next to fall along the mast. But wine a burst, and the boat
tipped with fast motion, Juanillo, to keep the balance agarrose the
edge of the sail, and at the same moment it swelled up as if it were
to explode launching the lute in a sprint and pushing hard throughout
the body so irresistible Boy, that shot like a catapult.

At the sound of water to swallow it Juanillo thought he heard a cry,
somewhat confused words; maybe the old helmsman who shouted, "Man
overboard!"

Fell much, much! dazed by the blow, so unexpected fall, but before
exact realize it saw himself again in the sea surface brewing, absorbing
fresh wind furiously ... And the boat?

Did not see it now. The sea was very dark, darker that seen from the deck of the lute.

Believed to distinguish a white, a ghost floating in the distance
on the waves, and swam to him.

But suddenly no longer saw him there, but rather the opposite, and
changed direction, disoriented swimming strongly, but not knowing
where to go.

The shoes were weighed as lead, damn!

The first time so I was! Cap I racked the temples, he pulled his
pants as if it came to the bottom of sea ??and were swept algae.

-
Quiet, Juanillo, quiet.

He threw his cap, wishing he could do the same with shoes.

I was confident.

He swam a lot: he was to hold for two hours.

Those in the boat would turn for fishing: a dip and nothing more ... What then die just like
men? In a storm as they had killed his father and grandfather, good, but beautiful night with
good sea die driven by a candle would be a fool's death.

And swam and swam, always thinking she saw that ghost hesitant to move around, waiting that emerge
from the darkness the San Rafael coming after him.

- Ah the boat! Uncle Sparks! ... Pattern!

But the screaming and distressed him two or three times the waves they covered his mouth. Damn!
... From the boat seemed insignificant, but at sea, up to his neck and forced a continuous nudging
to hold, choked him, beat him with their deaf undulation opened before him and moving deep
trenches, then closing them to swallow.

He continued to believe, but with some concern, in his two hours of endurance. Yes, had them. Two
hours and over there on the beach swam tirelessly.

But it was in daylight hours, at the sea ??of ??blue glass, looking down there, through great
transparency, yellow rocks with sharp grass like branches of coral green, pink shells, stars
pearl, bright flowers quivering fleshy petals to be touched by the belly Silver fish, and
was now in a sea of ??ink, lost in the dark, overwhelmed From their clothes, having under his feet
who knows how many boats destroyed, how many bodies emaciated by
the ferocious fish!

And trembled at the touch of his wet pants, thinking feel the friction of sharp teeth.

Weary, faint, lay on his back, carried away by the waves. The flavor of the meal rose to her
mouth. Damn food, and how much it costs to win!

There would eventually die foolishly ... But the survival instinct made him sit up. Maybe you
were looking for, and being stretched would go near him without seeing him. Another swim, with the
anxiety of despair, joining on the crest of the waves to see farther,
going as soon as another aside, waving always in the same circle.

Leaving him like a rag fell from the boat. My God! So forget a man? ... But, perhaps he was
wanted at that time. A boat runs a lot, and soon they had uploaded onto the deck and lowering
sail, and would be more than a mile.

And stroking this illusion, sank gently as if tirasen their heavy shoes. Felt bitterness in mouth
salty, blinded their eyes, the waters closed over his shaved head; but between two waves formed
a small eddy, clenched hands and peered out again.

The arms were asleep, his head bent over his chest as overcome by sleep. A Juanillo Heaven seemed
changed: the stars as red as blood splatter. No I was afraid of the sea, felt the desire to be
abandoned on the waters of rest.

She remembered her grandmother, who at that hour would be considering it. And he wanted to pray
a thousand times had heard his poor old woman. "Our Father ..." I prayed mentally, but realizing
it, her tongue moved, and said in a voice so hoarse that he thought
of another:

- Pigs!

Thieves! I give up!

Sank again, disappeared struggling in vain to stand. Someone threw
their shoes ... Delved into the dark, sipping water, inert, helpless,
but not knowing how, turned back Once the surface.

Now the stars
were black, blacker than the sky, standing like drops of ink.

It's
over. This time they really get to the heart: your body was made of
lead. And fell in a straight line dragged by his new shoes, and his
fall into the abyss of broken boats and skeletons eaten, the brain,
increasingly surrounded by thick fog, kept repeating:

- Our Father
... Our Father ... Thieves! Rascals! I have left!

A whistle

The
excitement warmed the theater. What a debut! What Lohengrin! Tiple
do that!

On the red of the seats in the courtyard stood out bareheaded
or towers ties, flowers and tulle, motionless, without approaching
the whisper or the boredom, in the boxes silence, no talk shows and
talks in a low voice, up in the raging inferno of the philharmonic
hall, ironically called Paradise, enthusiasm escaped long and loud,
like a huge sigh of satisfaction, every time the voice sounded the
soprano, sweet, powerful and robust. What a night! Everything seemed
new in the theater. The orchestra was angels until the spider was
more light center.

In this excitement took no small part patriotism
satisfied. The treble was Spanish, the Lopez, but now it was announced
by the surname of her husband, tenor Franchetti, a great artist who,
by marrying her, had made up to star status. Go a woman! Legitimate
land. Lean, arrogant, arms and throat with adorable curves, and Elsa
large white tulle at the waist, but narrow and almost bursting with
superb pressure curves. His black eyes, torn, of gloomy fire, contrasted
with the blonde wig Countess of Brabant. The beautiful Spanish was
on the scene the timid woman, sweet and resigned dreamed Wagner, relying
on the strength of his innocence, waiting for help of the unknown.

In
recounting his dream to the emperor and his court, as vagorosa sang
with sweet expression, arms down and the ecstatic look on top, as
if he saw come riding on a cloud the mysterious champion, that the
public could not hold anymore, and as the booming download a row of
guns, all the holes left the theater, even the hallways, the thunderous
explosion of applause and screams.

The modesty and grace with which
he greeted even more enraged the public. What a woman! A true lady,
and as good feelings, they all remembered details of his biography.
That old father, who every month sends a pension to live with decency:
a Happy old, from Madrid followed the career of her daughter wins
worldwide.

That was touching. Some ladies were taking their eyes
a tip of the glove, and paradise, a whimpering old man putting his
nose into the fold of the layer to stifle her moans. The neighbors
laughed.

Come on man, that was not bad!

The representation was under
way amid the echoes of excitement. Now the preacher invited to the
present, if anyone wanted to defend Elsa. Well, go ahead. That audience,
which had memorized the opera, was in secret. Not present any handsome.
Then accompaniment of eerie music, the ladies proceeded to take the
Countess evenings to execution. Everything was a joke, Elsa was safe.
But when the brave warriors Brabant stirred at the scene, watching
from afar the mysterious swan and car, and was arming the imperial
court in a din of two thousand demons, the public, by reflex action,
moved loudly, leaning back in his seat, coughing, sighing, turning
to provision of silence. How exciting! Franchetti was to perform the
famous tenor, a large artist who was rumored that Lopez had married
her seeking compensation decadent powers in the freshness and courage
of his wife. Apart from this, a maestrazo that knew triumphant with
the help of art.

Ah ... Was there, standing in the boat, leaning
on long sword, shield, bracing, scale-covered steel chest, straightening
his arrogant handsome figure celebrated by all the aristocracy of
Europe, and dazzling from head to foot, like a silver fish wrapped
in silk.

Silence, it seemed like a church. The wording looked his
swan, as if there had not one worthy of attention, and in the mystic
atmosphere was developing a soft whisper, sweet vagoroso, as if coming
from an invisible distance</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>