<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>380059</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24731</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Sentían la necesidad de respirarla, de vivir en el ambiente perfumado
que la envolvía, siguiendo sus pasos.

Al ver al capitán le tendió una mano simplemente, lo mismo que si se hubiesen visto el día
anterior.

--¡No se quejará usted, Ferragut!... Como no le encontraba en el hotel, he sentido la necesidad
de visitarle en su buque... Deseaba conocer su casa flotante. Todo lo de usted me interesa.

Parecía otra mujer. Ulises se dió cuenta del gran cambio que se había efectuado en su persona
durante los últimos días. Sus ojos eran atrevidos, incitantes, de un impudor tranquilo. Toda
ella parecía ofrecerse. Sus sonrisas, sus palabras, su modo de marchar por la cubierta hacia
las cámaras del buque, denotaban una resolución de dar fin cuanto antes á su larga resistencia,
cediendo á los deseos del marino.

A pesar de los anteriores fracasos, éste sintió de nuevo la alegría del triunfo. «¡Ahora va
á ser! Mi ausencia la ha vencido...» Y al mismo tiempo que paladeaba la dulce satisfacción
del amor y el orgullo triunfantes, un vago instinto le sugirió la sospecha de que esta mujer,
repentinamente transformada, tal vez le quería menos ahora que en los días anteriores, cuando
se resistía, aconsejándole que huyese.

En el comedor hizo la presentación de su segundo. El rudo Tòni experimentó el mismo deslumbramiento
que había perturbado á todos los del buque. ¡Qué mujer!... En el primer instante excusó y comprendió
la conducta de su capitán. Luego, sus ojos quedaron fijos en ella con una expresión de alarma,
como si su presencia le hiciese temblar por la suerte del vapor.

Acabó por sentirse cohibido delante de esta señora que examinaba el salón como si fuese á quedarse
en él para siempre.

Freya se interesó unos momentos por la peluda fealdad de Tòni. Era un verdadero mediterráneo,
tal como ella se los imaginaba: un fauno perseguidor de ninfas. Ulises rió de los elogios dirigidos
á su segundo.

--Debe tener dentro de los zapatos--continuó ella--unas pezuñitas lindas como las de las cabras.
Debe saber tocar el caramillo. ¿No lo cree así, capitán?...

El fauno, enfurruñado y rabioso, acabó por marcharse, saludando torpemente al salir. Ferragut
sintió un gran alivio con esta ausencia, pues temía alguna palabra ruda de Tòni.

Al quedar sola con Ulises, corrió de un lado á otro por la gran cámara.

--¿Aquí es donde vive usted, querido tiburón?... Déjeme que lo vea todo, que lo registre todo.
Me interesa lo suyo: no dirá ahora que no le quiero. ¡Qué orgullo para el capitán Ferragut!
Las señoras vienen á buscarle en su buque...

Interrumpió su parloteo irónico y amoroso para defenderse suavemente del marino. Este, olvidando
lo pasado y queriendo aprovechar la felicidad que se le ofrecía de pronto, abrazaba á la visitante,
besándola en la nuca.

--¡Luego... luego!--suspiró ella--. Ahora déjeme ver. Siento una curiosidad de niña.

Abrió el piano, el pobre piano del capitán escocés, y unos acordes tenues y lloriqueantes,
producto de una desafinación de varios años, conmovieron el salón con la melancolía de los
recuerdos que resucitan.

Era una música igual á la de las cajas melódicas que se encuentran olvidadas en el fondo de
un armario, entre las ropas de una vieja difunta. Freya declaró que esta música olía á rosas secas.

Luego, abandonando el piano, abrió una tras otra todas las puertas de los camarotes que daban
al salón. En la del dormitorio del capitán se detuvo, sin querer pasar del umbral, sin soltar
el picaporte de bronce que mantenía en su diestra. Ferragut, detrás de ella, la empujaba con
suave traición, repitiendo al mismo tiempo sus caricias en la nuca.

--No, aquí no--dijo ella--. ¡Por nada del mundo!... Seré tuya, te lo prometo: te doy mi palabra.
Pero donde yo quiera, cuando á mí me parezca... ¡Muy pronto, Ulises!

El sintió toda la voluptuosidad de estas afirmaciones, hechas con una voz acariciadora y sumisa;
todo el orgullo de este tuteo espontáneo, que equivalía á una primera entrega.

La llegada de un acólito del tío Caragòl les hizo recobrar su tranquilidad. Traía dos enormes
vasos llenos de un cocktail rojizo y espumoso; embriagadora y dulce mixtura, resumen de todos
los conocimientos adquiridos por el cocinero en su trato con los borrachos de los primeros
puertos del mundo.

Ella probó el líquido, entornando los ojos como una gata golosa. Luego prorrumpió en alabanzas,
elevando el vaso de un modo solemne. Ofrecía su libación á Eros, el más bueno de los dioses.
Y Ferragut, que siempre había sentido cierto pavor ante las infernales y gratas mixturas de
su cocinero, apuró de un trago su vaso, para unirse á la invocación.

Todo quedó concertado entre los dos. Ella daba las órdenes. Ferragut volvería á tierra, aposentándose
en el mismo albergo. Continuarían su vida de antes, como si nada hubiese ocurrido.

--Esta tarde me esperarás en los jardines de la Villa Nazionale... Sí, allí donde quisiste
matarme, ¡bandido!...

Antes de que pudiese evocar la imagen de aquella noche de violencia, Freya se adelantaba á
sus recuerdos con una astucia femenil... Era Ulises el que había querido matarla; lo afirmaba
ella, sin admitir respuesta.

--Iremos á visitar á la doctora--continuó--. La pobre desea verte, y me ha rogado que te lleve.
Se interesa mucho por ti desde que sabe que te amo, ¡pirata mío!...

Después de haber fijado la hora del encuentro, Freya quiso irse. Pero antes de volver á su
lancha sintió la curiosidad de registrar el buque, como había registrado el salón y los camarotes.

Con aires de princesa reinante, precedida del capitán y seguida de los oficiales, corrió las
dos cubiertas; se asomó á las galerías de hierro de las máquinas y al abismo cuadrado de las
escotillas de carga, recibiendo el olor mohoso de las bodegas. En el puente tocó con un entusiasmo
pueril la caperuza de bronce de la bitácora y los demás instrumentos de dirección, brillantes
como si fuesen de oro.

Quiso ver la cocina, ó invadió los dominios del tío Caragòl, poniendo en lamentable desorden
sus formaciones de cacerolas, asomando su hocico sonrosado á la boca humeante del gran puchero
en el que hervía el almuerzo de la gente.

El viejo pudo verla de cerca con sus ojos cegatos. «¡Sí que era guapa!» El revoloteo de sus
faldas y los frecuentes encontrones que tuvo con ella en sus idas y venidas por la cocina perturbaron
al apóstol. Su olfato de guisandero se sintió molestado por el perfume de esta señora. «Guapa,
pero con olor de...», repitió mentalmente. Para él, todo perfume femenil merecía este título
injurioso. Las mujeres buenas huelen á pescado y á estropajo: estaba seguro de ello... En su
lejana juventud, los conocimientos del pobre Caragòl no habían ido más allá.

Al quedar solo, agarró un trapo, agitándolo violentamente como si sacudiese moscas. Quería
limpiar el ambiente de malos olores. Sentíase escandalizado, como si hubiesen dejado caer una
pastilla de jabón en uno de sus arroces.

Los hombres del buque se amontonaron en las bordas para seguir la marcha del bote que se alejaba.

Tòni, al pie del puente, lo contempló también con ojos enigmáticos.

--Hermosa eres; pero ¡que la mar te trague antes de que vuelvas!...

Un brazo tremolaba un pañuelo en la popa de la barca. «¡Adiós, capitán!» Y el capitán movía
la cabeza, sonriente y emocionado por el saludo femenil, mientras los marineros envidiaban
su buena suerte.

Otra vez un hombre de la tripulación llevó el equipaje de Ferragut al albergo de la ribera
de Santa Lucía. El portero, como si presintiese las inclinaciones de este cliente de propina
fácil, se encargó de escoger su habitación: un piso más abajo que la vez anterior, cerca de
la que ocupaba la signora Talberg.

Se encontraron á media tarde en la Villa Nazionale, y emprendieron juntos la marcha por las
calles de Chiaia. Al fin iba á saber Ulises dónde ocultaba la doctora su majestuosa personalidad.
Presentía algo extraordinario en este alojamiento, pero estaba dispuesto á disimular sus impresiones,
por miedo á perder el afecto y el apoyo de la sabia dama, que parecía ejercer un gran dominio
sobre Freya.

Entraron en el zaguán de un antiguo palacio. Muchas veces se había detenido el marino ante
su puerta, pero seguía adelante, desorientado por las chapas de metal que anunciaban las oficinas
y escritorios instalados en sus diversos pisos.

Vió un patio de arcadas, pavimentado con grandes losas, al que daban los balcones ventrudos
en los cuatro lados interiores del palacio. Subieron por una escalera de ecos despiertos, grande
como una calle en pendiente, con revueltas anchurosas que permitían en otros tiempos el paso
de las literas y sus portadores. Como recuerdo de los personajes de blanca peluca y las damas
de anchuroso guardainfante que habían pasado por ella, quedaban algunos bustos clásicos en
los rellanos, una baranda de hierro forjada á martillo y varios farolones de oros borrosos
y vidrios turbios.

Se detuvieron en el primer piso, ante una fila de puertas algo carcomidas por los años.

--Aquí es--dijo Freya.

Y señaló precisamente la única puerta que estaba cubierta con una mampara de cuero verde, ostentando
un rótulo comercial, enorme, dorado, pretencioso. La doctora se alojaba en una oficina... ¡Cómo
hubiera llegado él á encontrarla!

La primera pieza era realmente una oficina, un despacho de comerciante, con casillero para
los papeles, mapas, caja de caudales y varias mesas. Un solo empleado trabajaba: un hombre
de edad incierta, con cara pueril y bigote recortado. Su gesto obsequioso y sonriente contrastaba
con su mirada fugitiva; una mirada de alarma y desconfianza.

Al ver á Freya se levantó de su asiento. Esta le saludó llamándole Karl, y pasó adelante, como
si fuese un simple portero. Ulises, al seguirla, adivinó fija en sus espaldas la mirada recelosa
del escribiente.

--¿También es polaco?--preguntó.

--Sí, polaco... Es un protegido de la doctora.

Entraron en un salón amueblado á toda prisa, con el arte especial y fácil de los que están
acostumbrados á viajar y tienen que improvisarse una vivienda: divanes con indianas vistosas
y baratas, pieles de guanaco americano, tapices chillones, de un falso orientalismo, y en las
paredes láminas de periódicos entre varillas doradas. Sobre una mesa lucía sus marfiles y platas
un gran neceser con la tapa de cuero abierta. Unas cuantas estatuillas napolitanas habían sido
compradas á última hora para dar cierto aire de sedentaria respetabilidad á este salón que
podía deshacerse rápidamente, y cuyos adornos más valiosos eran objetos de viaje.

Por una cortina entreabierta distinguieron á la doctora, que escribía en la pieza inmediata.
Estaba encorvada sobre un pupitre americano, pero los vió inmediatamente en el espejo que tenía
delante de ella para espiar todo lo que pasaba á sus espaldas.

Adivinó Ulises que la imponente señora había hecho ciertos preparativos de tocador para recibirle.
Un vestido estrecho como una funda moldeaba la exuberancia de su formas. La falda, recogida
y angosta en el remate de sus piernas, parecía el mango de una maza enorme. Sobre el verde
marino del traje llevaba un tul blanco con lentejuelas plateadas, á modo de chal. El capitán,
á pesar de su respeto por la sabia dama, la comparó á una nereida madre bien alimentada en
las praderas oceánicas.

Con las manos tendidas y una expresión gozosa en el rostro, que hacía irradiar sus lentes,
avanzó hacia Ferragut. Su encontrón casi fué un abrazo... «¡Querido capitán! ¡tanto tiempo
sin verle!...» Sabía de él con frecuencia, por los informes de su amiga; pero aun así, lamentaba
como una desgracia que el marino no hubiese venido á verla.

Parecía olvidar su frialdad al despedirse en Salerno, el cuidado que había tenido en ocultarle
las señas de su domicilio.

Ferragut tampoco se acordó de esto, gratamente conmovido por la amabilidad de la doctora. Se
había sentado entre los dos, como si quisiera protegerles con toda la majestad de su persona
y el afecto de sus ojos. Era una madre para su amiga. Acariciaba, al hablar, los mechones de
la cabellera de Freya, que acababan de librarse del encierro del sombrero. Y Freya, adaptándose
al ambiente tierno de la situación, se apelotonaba contra la doctora, tomando un aire de niña
tímida y acariciante, mientras fijaba en Ulises sus ojos de dulce promesa.

--Quiérala usted mucho, capitán--siguió diciendo la matrona--, Freya sólo habla de usted...
¡Ha sido tan desgraciada!... ¡La vida se ha mostrado tan cruel con ella!...

El marino sintió la misma emoción que si se hallase en un plácido ambiente de familia. Aquella
señora daba las cosas por hechas discretamente, hablándole como á un yerno. Su mirada de bondad
tenía una expresión melancólica. Era la dulce tristeza de las personas maduras que ven monótono
el presente, medido el porvenir, y se refugian en los recuerdos del pasado, envidiando á las
jóvenes porque pueden gozar en la realidad lo que ellas sólo paladean con la memoria.

--¡Felices ustedes!... ¡Amense mucho!... Únicamente por el amor vale la vida la pena de ser vivida.

Y Freya, como si le enterneciesen de un modo irresistible estos consejos, avanzó un brazo sobre
los globos encorsetados de la doctora, apretando convulsivamente la diestra de Ulises.

Los lentes de oro, con su brillo protector, parecían incitarles á mayores intimidades. «Podían
besarse...» La imponente señora, para facilitar sus expansiones, iba á salir, alegando un pretexto
insignificante, cuando se levantó el cortinaje de la puerta que comunicaba el salón con la oficina.

Entró un hombre de la edad de Ferragut, pero más bajo de estatura, menos endurecido el rostro
por el curtimiento de la intemperie. Iba vestido á la inglesa, con escrupulosa corrección.
Se adivinaban en él las preocupaciones más nimias y pueriles en todo lo referente al adorno
de su persona. El traje, de lanilla gris, aparecía realzado por la unidad de la corbata, los
calcetines y el pañuelo asomado al bolsillo del pecho. Las tres prendas eran azules, sin la
más leve variación en su tono, escogidas con exactitud, como si este hombre pudiese sufrir
crueles molestias saliendo á la calle con la corbata de un color y los calcetines de otro.
Sus guantes tenían el mismo amarillo obscuro de sus zapatos.

Ferragut pensó que este gentleman, para ser completo, debía llevar el rostro afeitado. Y sin
embargo, usaba barba, una barba recortada á flor de piel en las mejillas y formando sobre el
mentón una punta corta y aguda. El capitán presintió que era un marino. En la flota alemana,
en la rusa, en todas las marinas del Norte, los oficiales que no iban rasurados á la inglesa
usaban esta barbilla tradicional.

Se inclinó, ó más bien dicho, se dobló en ángulo, con brusca rigidez, al besar las manos de
las dos señoras. Luego se llevó un monóculo de impertinente fijeza á uno de sus ojos, mientras
la doctora hacía las presentaciones.

--El conde Kaledine... El capitán Ferragut.

Dió la mano el conde al marino, una mano dura, bien cuidada y forzuda, que se mantuvo largo
rato sobre la de Ulises, queriendo dominarla con una presión sin afecto.

La conversación continuó en inglés, que era el idioma empleado por la doctora en sus relaciones
con Ulises.

--¿El señor es marino?--preguntó éste para aclarar sus dudas.

No se movió el monóculo de su órbita, pero un temblor ligero de sorpresa parecía rizar su luminosa
convexidad. La doctora se apresuró á responder:

--El conde es un diplomático ilustre que está ahora con licencia, cuidando su salud. Ha viajado
mucho, pero no es marino.

Y continuó sus explicaciones. Los Kaledine eran una noble familia rusa de tiempos de la gran
Catalina. La doctora, por ser polaca, estaba relacionada con ellos hacía muchos años... Y cesó
de hablar, dando entrada á Kaledine en la conversación.

Al principio el conde se mostró frío y algo desdeñoso en sus palabras, como si no pudiera despojarse
de su altivez diplomática. Pero lentamente esta altivez se fué fundiendo.

Conocía por su «distinguida amiga la señora Talberg» muchas de las aventuras náuticas de Ferragut.
A él le interesaban los hombres de acción, los héroes del Océano.

Ulises notó de pronto en su noble interlocutor un afecto caluroso, un deseo de agradar semejante
al de la doctora. ¡Hermosa casa aquella, en la que todos se esforzaban por hacerse simpáticos
al capitán Ferragut!

El conde, sonriendo amablemente, dejó de valerse del inglés, y le habló de pronto en español,
como si hubiese reservado este golpe final para acabar de captarse su afecto con el más irresistible
de los halagos.

--He vivido en Méjico--dijo para explicar su conocimiento de esta lengua--. He hecho un largo
viaje por las Filipinas cuando vivía en el Japón.

Los mares del Extremo Oriente eran los menos frecuentados por Ulises. Sólo dos veces había
navegado hacia los puertos chinos y nipones, pero conocía lo suficiente para mantener la conversación
con este viajero que mostraba en sus gustos cierto refinamiento de artista. Durante media hora
desfilaron por el vulgar ambiente del salón imágenes de enormes pagodas de techos superpuestos,
vibrantes á la brisa, como un arpa, con sus filas de campanillas; ídolos monstruosos tallados
en oro, en bronce ó en marfil; casas de papel, tronos de bambú, muebles de nacaradas incrustaciones,
biombos con filas de cigüeñas volantes.

Desapareció la doctora, aturdida por este diálogo, del que sólo podía adivinar algunas palabras.
Freya, inmóvil, con los ojos adormecidos y una rodilla entre sus manos cruzadas, se mantuvo
aparte, entendiendo la conversación, pero sin intervenir en ella, como si le ofendiese el olvido
en que la dejaban los dos hombres. Al fin se deslizó discretamente, siguiendo el llamamiento
de una mano asomada á un cortinaje. La doctora preparaba el té y pedía auxilio.

La conversación continuó, sin hacer alto en estas ausencias. Kaledine había abandonado los
mares asiáticos para pasar al Mediterráneo, y se anclaba en él con una insistencia admirativa.
Un motivo más de afecto para Ferragut, que lo encontraba cada vez más simpático, á pesar de
su trato un poco glacial.

Se dió cuenta repentinamente de que ya no era el conde ruso el que hablaba, pues con breves
y certeras preguntas le hacía hablar á él, lo mismo que si lo sometiese á un examen.

Agradeció las muestras de interés que este gran viajero daba por el pequeño mare nostrum, y
especialmente por las particularidades de su cuenca occidental, que deseaba conocer minuciosamente.

Podía preguntar cuanto quisiera. Ferragut poseía milla por milla todo el litoral español, el
francés y el italiano, así en la superficie como en sus fondos.

Kaledine, tal vez por vivir en Nápoles, insistió con predilección en la parte mediterránea
comprendida entre la Cerdeña, la Italia del Sur y la Sicilia, ó sea lo que los antiguos habían
llamado el mar Tirreno... ¿Conocía el capitán Ferragut las islas poco frecuentadas y casi perdidas
enfrente de Sicilia?

--Yo lo conozco todo--afirmó éste con orgullo.

Y sin discernir completamente si era curiosidad del conde ó si quería someterle á un examen
interesado, habló y habló.

Conocía el archipiélago de las islas Lípari, con sus minas de azufre y de piedra pómez, grupo
de cimas volcánicas que emergen de las profundidades del Mediterráneo. En ellas habían colocado
los antiguos á Eolo, señor de los vientos; en ellas está el Stromboli vomitando enormes bolas
de lava, que estallan con un estrépito de trueno. Las escorias volcánicas vuelven á caer en
las chimeneas del cráter ó ruedan por la pendiente de la montaña, sumiéndose en las olas.

Más al Oeste, aislada y solitaria en un mar limpio de escollos, está Ustica, una isla volcánica
y abrupta que colonizaron los fenicios y sirvió de refugio á los piratas sarracenos. Su población
es escasa y pobre. Nada hay que ver en ella, aparte de ciertas conchas fósiles que interesan
á los hombres de ciencia...

Pero el conde se sintió interesado por este cráter muerto y solitario en medio de un mar que
sólo frecuentan las barcas de pesca.

Ferragut había visto igualmente, aunque de lejos, al entrar en el puerto de Trápani, el archipiélago
de las Egades, donde existen grandes pesquerías de atunes. Había desembarcado una vez en la
isla Pantelaria, situada á medio camino entre Sicilia y África. Era un cono volcánico altísimo
que emergía en mitad del estrecho, y á cuyo pie existían lagos alcalinos, humaredas sulfurosas,
aguas termales y construcciones prehistóricas de grandes bloques, semejantes á las de Cerdeña
y las Baleares. Los buques que iban á Túnez y Trípoli tomaban cargamento de pasas, única exportación
de esta antigua colonia fenicia.

Entre la Panteleria y Sicilia, el suelo submarino se elevaba considerablemente, guardando sobre
su dorso una capa acuática que en algunos puntos sólo tenía doce metros de espesor. Era el
extenso banco llamado de la Aventura, hinchazón volcánica, doble isla anegada, pedestal submarino
de Sicilia.

También el banco de la Aventura pareció interesar al conde.

--Conoce usted bien su mar--dijo con tono de aprobación.

Ferragut iba á seguir hablando, pero entraron las dos señoras con una bandeja que contenía
el servicio de té y varios platos de pasteles. El capitán no extrañó esta falta de servidumbre.
La doctora y su amiga eran para él unas mujeres de costumbres extraordinarias, y todos sus
actos los encontraba lógicos y naturales. Freya sirvió el té con una gracia púdica, como si
fuese la hija de la casa.

Pasaron el resto de la tarde conversando sobre lejanos viajes. Nadie aludió á la guerra ni
á las preocupaciones de Italia en aquel momento por mantener su neutralidad ó salir de ella.
Parecían vivir en un lugar inaccesible, á miles de leguas de todo tropel humano.

Las dos mujeres trataban al conde con una familiaridad de buen tono, como personas de su mismo
mundo; pero el marino creyó notar en ciertos momentos que le tenían miedo.

Al terminar la tarde, este personaje abandonó su asiento, y Ferragut hizo lo mismo, comprendiendo
que debía poner fin á su visita. El conde se ofreció á acompañarle. Mientras se despedía de
la doctora, agradeciendo con extremos corteses que le hubiese hecho conocer al capitán, éste
sintió que Freya le apretaba la mano de modo significativo.

--Hasta la noche--murmuró levemente, sin mover apenas los labios--. Volveré tarde... Espérame.

¡Oh, dicha!... Los ojos, la sonrisa, la presión de la mano, decían para él mucho más.

Nunca dió un paseo tan agradable como al marchar al lado de Kaledine por las calles de Chiaia
hacia la ribera. ¿Qué decía aquel hombre?... Cosas insignificantes para evitar el silencio,
pero á él le parecieron observaciones de profunda sabiduría. Su voz era, según él, armoniosa
y acariciadora. Todo lo encontraba igualmente amable, la gente que transitaba por las calles,
el ruido napolitano del anochecer, el mar obscuro, la vida entera.

Se despidieron ante la puerta del hotel. El conde, á pesar de sus ofrecimientos de amistad,
se fué sin decirle cuál era su domicilio.

«No importa--pensó Ferragut--. Volveremos á encontrarnos en casa de la doctora.»

El resto de la velada lo pasó agitado alternativamente por la esperanza y la impaciencia. No
quería comer; la emoción había paralizado su apetito... Y una vez sentado á la mesa, comió
más que nunca, con una avidez maquinal y distraída.

Necesitaba pasear, hablar con alguien, para que transcurriese el tiempo con mayor rapidez,
engañando su inquieta espera. Ella no volvería al hotel hasta muy tarde... Y precisamente se
retiró á su habitación más temprano que de costumbre, creyendo, con un ilogismo supersticioso,
que de este modo llegaría antes Freya.

Su primer movimiento al verse en su cuarto fué de orgullo. Miró al techo, apiadándose del marino
enamorado que una semana antes habitaba el piso superior. ¡Pobre hombre! ¡Cómo se habían reído
de él!... Ulises se admiró á sí mismo como una personalidad completamente nueva, feliz y triunfadora,
separado de la otra por un período doloroso de humillaciones y fracasos que no quería recordar.

¡Las horas larguísimas del que aguarda con ansiedad!... Se paseó fumando, encendiendo un cigarro
en el resto del anterior. Luego abrió la ventana, queriendo borrar este perfume de tabaco fuerte.
Ella sólo gustaba de los cigarrillos orientales... Y como persistiese el acre olor del cigarro
habano, jugoso y bravío, rebuscó en su maletín de aseo, derramando sobre la cama el fondo de
varios frascos de esencia largo tiempo olvidados.

Una repentina inquietud amargó su espera. La que iba á llegar ignoraba tal vez cuál era su
habitación. El no estaba seguro de haberle dado las señas con suficiente claridad. Era posible
que se hubiese equivocado... Empezó á creer que, efectivamente, se había equivocado.

El miedo y la impaciencia le hicieron abrir su puerta, plantándose en el corredor para mirar
de lejos el cerrado cuarto de Freya. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02019</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>286098</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22205</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Felt the need to breathe, to live in the scented environment that enveloped
her, following in his footsteps.

Seeing the captain reached out just the same as if they had seen the
day above.

- You will not complain, Ferragut!

... As I did not find the hotel, I felt the need to visit your vessel ... He wanted to know their
houseboat. All I care about you.

It seemed another woman. Ulises noticed the great change that had taken place in him Over the
past days. His eyes were bold, enticing, a tranquil immodesty. All it seemed to offer. Their
smiles, their words, their way of marching on the cover the chambers of the vessel, to denote a
resolution of an early end to his long resistance, yielding to the
wishes of the ocean.

Despite past failures, he felt again the joy of victory. "Now is to be! My absence has expired
... "And while savoring the sweet satisfaction love and pride of triumph, a vague instinct suggested
the suspicion that this woman suddenly transformed, you may want
less now than in previous days, when refused, advising him to flee.

In the dining room was the presentation of his second. The harsh glare Toni experienced the same
that had troubled to all of the ship. What a woman!

... In the first apologized and realized instantly the conduct of their captain. Then his eyes were
fixed upon her with an expression of alarm, as if his presence do
him tremble for the fate of the steam.

Ended up feeling embarrassed in front of this lady who was examining
the room as if it were to stay there forever.

Freya was interested a few moments for the hairy ugliness of Toni. He was a true Mediterranean
as she imagined them: a faun tracker nymphs.

Ulysses smiled at the praise directed his mate.

- Must be in the shoes - she went - a nice pezuñitas such as goats. You must know how to play
the flute. Did not think so, Captain? ...

The Faun, sulking and angry, finally leaving, waving awkwardly on exit. Ferragut was relieved with this
absence, fearing a dirty word Toni.

When left alone with Odysseus, ran from one side to another by the great camera.

- Here is where you live, dear shark? ... Let me see you all, that you register it. I'm interested
in him: he will not say now that I love him. What pride to Captain
Ferragut!

The ladies come to seek him in his ship ...

Stopped their chatter to defend ironic and gently loving sailor. This, forgetting the past and
wanting to take the happiness she gave him suddenly, he hugged the
visitor kissing her neck.

- Then ... then! - she sighed -.

Now let me see. I feel a curious child.

He opened the piano, piano poor Scottish captain, and a faint line and whimpering, detuning product
of several years, moved the room with the melancholy of revived memories.

The music was equal to that of melodic boxes that are forgotten in the bottom of a closet, among
the clothes of an old dead. Freya said that he smelled of dried roses music.

Then, abandoning the piano, opened one after another all the cabin doors giving the classroom. In
the master bedroom is stopped, not wanting to pass the threshold, hold brass latch held in his
right hand. Ferragut, behind her, pushed her to soft treason, while repeating his touch in
the neck.

- No, not here - she said -. Nothing in the world! ... I'll be yours,
I promise: I give you my word.

But wherever I want, when I look ... Soon, Ulysses!

He felt all the delight of these statements, made with a caressing voice and submissive; all
the pride of this familiarity spontaneous, equivalent to a first delivery.

The arrival of an acolyte of Uncle Caragol made them regain their peace of mind. He had two huge
cocktail glasses filled with red and sparkling, heady and sweet mixture,
summary of all knowledge acquired by Cook in his dealings with the
first drunk ports worldwide.

She tasted the liquid, squinting like a cat tooth. Then she burst into singing, raising his glass
in a dignified manner. Offered his libation to Eros, the most good of the gods. And Ferragut,
who had always felt a certain fear of hell and pleasing to the mixtures of cook, drained his glass
in one gulp, to join the invocation.

Everything was arranged between them. She gave the orders. Ferragut return to the land, apartments
in the same harbor. Continue their former life as if nothing had happened.

- This afternoon, I wait in the gardens of the Villa Nazionale ... Yes, wherever you wanted
kill me, villain! ...

Before he could evoke the image of that night of violence, came forward to Freya memories with
a cunning female ... Ulysses was the one who had wanted to kill her, I said it, without admitting
response.

- Go to visit the doctor - he continued -. The poor wants to see, and asked me to take you. Is
very interested in you since you know I love you, my pirate!

...

After fixing the time of the meeting, Freya wanted to go.

But before returning to his boat felt the curiosity to search the ship, and had registered
the room and cabins.

With an air of reigning princess, preceded and followed the captain of the officers, ran the
two decks, overlooks the iron galleries of the machines and the squared pit cargo hatch, getting
the musty smell of the cellars. On the bridge played with enthusiasm childish brass cap of
the blog and other management tools, bright as if they were gold.

Wanted to see the kitchen, or invaded the domains of Uncle Caragol, putting in an appalling mess formations
of pans, sticking his pink nose to the mouth of the large pot smoking in boiling lunch people.

The
old man could see her up close with their short-sighted eyes.

"Yes she was beautiful!" The fluttering of their Frequently encontrones skirts and took her
in his comings and goings through the kitchen disrupted the apostle. His eye for guisandero felt
bothered by the scent of this woman.

"Beautiful, but with the smell of ...», repeated mentally. For him, all women's perfume deserved
this title offensive. Women smell good to fish and to wool: he was sure of it ... In its distant
youth, the poor knowledge Caragol had not gone further.

When left alone, he grabbed a rag, shaking violently as if shaking off flies. Wanted clean
the air of odors. He felt shocked, as if they had dropped a bar of soap in one of its rice.

The
ship's men piled on the edges to follow the progress of the boat
pulled away.

Toni, at the foot of the bridge, also looked enigmatic eyes.

- Beautiful you are, but that the sea will swallow before you come
back!

...

An arm waved a handkerchief at the stern of the boat. "Farewell, Captain!" And the captain moved head,
smiling and excited about the women's greeting, while the sailors
envious good luck.

Another time a man of the crew carried luggage Ferragut the harbor
from the shore Santa Lucia.

The porter, as if sensing the inclinations of the client tips easy,
took care to choose his room one floor below the previous time, around
which occupied the signora Talberg.

Was found in mid afternoon at the Villa Nazionale, and waged together the march through the streets
of Chiaia. When Ulysses finally going to know where the doctor concealed his majestic personality.
Sensed something special in this space, but was willing to conceal her impressions, for fear of
losing the love and support of the wise lady, who seemed to have a large domain on Freya.

Entered the vestibule of an ancient palace.

Many times he had stopped the ocean before your door, but kept going, misled by the metal sheets
announcing offices and desks installed at various floors.

Saw an arcaded courtyard, paved with large slabs, which gave the balconies bellied on all four sides
inside the palace. They climbed a ladder of echoes awake, large as a sloping street, with width
riots in the past allowed the passage of berths and carriers. As a reminder of the characters
in white wigs and ladies guardainfante widths that had passed through it, there were some busts
in landings, a wrought iron railing hammer of gold and several fuzzy farolones and murky glass.

They
stopped at the first floor, doors to a row of some decayed over the
years.

- Here is - Freya said.

He noted specifically the only door that was covered with a green leather screen, displaying a commercial
sign, huge, golden, pretentious.

The doctor was staying in an office ... How He had come to find it!

The first piece was actually an office, a merchant's office, with box for papers, maps, safe
and several tables. One employee worked: a man of uncertain age, with boyish face and mustache
trimming. Their obsequious and smiling gesture contrasted with fleeting glance, a look of alarm
and distrust.

Seeing Freya rose from his seat. This Karl greeted him by calling
him, and passed on, as if a porter.

Ulysses, follow guessed fixed on their backs look suspicious the clerk.

- Is it also Polish? - Asked.

- Yes, Polish ... He is a protégé of Dr..

They entered a room furnished in a hurry, with special art and which
are easy accustomed to travel and have to improvise a home: sofas
with colorful Indian and cheap American guanaco skins, garish carpets,
a false Orientalism, and the sheets of newspapers from walls golden
rods.

On a table wearing their ivory and silver a great need to open the
leather cover.

A few statues were Neapolitan purchased at the last moment to give an air of respectability to
sedentary this room could quickly dispose, and which were most valuable
ornaments travel items.

Distinguished by a curtain parted to the doctor, writing in the next
room.

He was hunched over a desk America, but immediately saw in the mirror that was in front of her
to spy on what was happening behind him.

Ulises guessed that the lady had made some impressive toilet preparations to receive him. A narrow
dress as a cover molding the exuberance of its forms. The skirt collection and narrow at the
top of his legs, looked like the handle of a huge club. On the green Marine wore a white tulle
dress with silver sequins, as a shawl. The captain, notwithstanding his respect for the wise
lady, compared to a well-fed mother mermaid ocean meadows.

With hands outstretched and a joyful expression on his face, which was irradiated lenses, advanced
to Ferragut. Your encontrón almost was a hug ... "Dear Captain! Long !...» knew without seeing
him often, reports of her friend, but even so, sorry as a disgrace that the ocean had not come
to see her.

He seemed to forget his cold to leave in Salerno, care was taken to conceal the address of your
home.

Ferragut also agreed that, greatly moved by the kindness of the doctor. It was sitting between
them, as if to protect them with all the majesty of his person and
affection of his eyes.

She was a mother for her friend. Stroking, talking, tufts Freya's hair, which had just fought the
closure of the hat.

And Freya, adapting the tender atmosphere of the situation, will
ball up against the doctor, taking an air of girl timid, caressing,
while his eyes fixed on Ulysses sweet promise.

- You Want it very
much, captain - kept telling the midwife - Freya just talking about
you ... It was so miserable!

... Life has been so cruel to her! ...

The sailor felt the same excitement as if he were in a quiet family atmosphere. That lady was quietly
made things, speaking as a son.

His look of kindness had a melancholy expression. It was the sweet sadness of older people that
are monotonous This measured the future, and take refuge in the memories of the past, I envy the
young people because they can enjoy in reality what they savored
only in memory.

- Blessed are you!

... Love one a lot! ... Only love is worth the life is worth living.

And Freya, as if irresistibly softened to the above, and moved an arm corseted balloons to the doctor,
pressing convulsively the right hand of Ulysses.

The lenses of gold, with its brightness protector, seemed to encourage them to greater intimacy.
"They could kissing ... "The impressive lady, to facilitate its expansion,
was about to leave, citing a pretext insignificant, when it lifted
the curtain of the door between the room with the office.

A man entered the age of Ferragut, but lower in height, less hardened
face tanning by the weather.

He was dressed to the English with scrupulous correctness. Hinted at in the most trivial and
childish concerns at all about the trim of person.

The suit, gray flannel, appeared enhanced by the unity of the tie, socks and handkerchief
overlooking the breast pocket. The three pieces were blue, with no slightest variation in tone, chosen
with precision, as if this man could suffer cruel now out into the street with a color tie and
socks in another. Her gloves had the same dark yellow of his shoes.

Ferragut felt that this gentleman, to be complete, should bring his face shaved. And however, wore a
beard, a beard to the surface of the cheeks and forming the chin
short and sharp tip.

The captain felt he was a sailor. In the German fleet in Russian, in all North Sea, the officers
were not shaved to the English used this traditional chin.

He bowed, or better said, bent at an angle, with sudden stiffness, kissing hands the two ladies.
Then he took a monocle impertinent fixity to one of his eyes, while
Dr. made the presentations.

- Count Kaledine ... Captain Ferragut.

Count shook hands with the sailor, a tough, well maintained and strong that remained long while
on the Ulysses, wanting to dominate with a pressure no affection.

The conversation continued in English, which was the language used by the doctor in their relations
with Ulysses.

- "The Lord is ocean? - He asked for clarification.

Monocle not moved in its orbit, but a slight tremor of surprise seemed to ruffle his luminous convexity.
The doctor was quick to respond:

- The Count is a distinguished diplomat who is now on leave, caring
for your health.

He has traveled much, but it is not marine.

He continued his explanation. The Kaledine were a noble Russian family of great times Catalina.
The doctor, being Polish, I was connected with them for many years ... And stopped speak, giving
entrance to Kaledine in the conversation.

At first the count was cold and somewhat cavalier in his words, as
if he could shed of diplomatic arrogance.

But this pride went slowly melting.

Known for his "distinguished friend Mrs. Talberg" many of the nautical adventures Ferragut. He
wanted to know the men of action, the heroes of the ocean.

Ulises suddenly noticed his noble interlocutor warm affection, such a desire to please to the doctor.
Beautiful home that, in which all strove to be sympathetic Captain Ferragut!

The count, smiling graciously, left to fend English, and he suddenly spoke in Spanish, as if he
had booked this final blow to finish captured his affection with the most irresistible of flattery.

-
I lived in Mexico - said to explain his knowledge of the language -. I made a long trip to the Philippines
when I lived in Japan.

The seas of the Far East were the least frequented by Ulysses. Only twice had Chinese sailed
to ports and Nipponese, but knew enough to keep the conversation with this flyer showing some sophistication
in his tastes as an artist.

For half an hour paraded through the lounge atmosphere of vulgar
images of huge roof pagodas overlapping vibrating in the breeze, like
a harp, with its rows of bells, idols carved monstrous in gold, bronze
or ivory paper houses, bamboo thrones, furniture inlaid mother of
pearl, screens with rows of cranes flying.

Dr. disappeared, stunned by this dialogue, which could only guess at some words. Freya, still, with
the sleepy eyes and a knee between his hands crossed, he kept addition, understanding the
conversation, but without intervening in it, as if offended oblivion in which the two men left.
Finally he slipped quietly, following the call leaning a hand to
a curtain.

The doctor prepared the tea and asked for help.

The conversation continued without a halt in these absences.

Kaledine had abandoned the Asian seas to go to the Mediterranean, it was anchored to an insistence
admiration. Another reason of affection for Ferragut, who was increasingly
sympathetic, notwithstanding her try a little ice age.

Suddenly realized that was not the Russian count who spoke, as with brief and accurate questions
made him speak to him, as if he is subjected to review.

Appreciated the expressions of interest that this great traveler gave
the small mare nostrum, and especially by the particularities of its
western basin, which wanted to know thoroughly.

Could ask how I wanted. Ferragut had mile by mile all the Spanish coast, the French and Italian,
and on the surface and in its funds.

Kaledine, perhaps to live in Naples, insisted on the Mediterranean predilection between Sardinia,
Southern Italy and Sicily, or is what the ancients called the Tyrrhenian
Sea ... Did you know Captain Ferragut islands unfrequented and almost
forgotten across from Sicily?

- I know everything - he said proudly.

And fully discern whether it was curiosity or if the count would be subject to a review concerned,
talked and talked.

He knew the Lipari archipelago, with its mining of sulfur and pumice, group of volcanic peaks
rising from the depths of the Mediterranean. They were placed the former to Aeolus, god of the
winds in them is throwing huge balls Stromboli lava, bursting with
a roar of thunder.

The volcanic scoria fall back into the chimneys of the crater or roll down the slope of the mountain
sinking into the waves.

Further west, isolated and lonely in a sea clear of obstacles, is
Ustica, a volcanic island and abrupt that the Phoenicians settled
and served as a refuge for pirates Saracen.

Its population is scarce and poor. Nothing to do with it, apart from some fossil shells of interest
to men of science ...

But the count was interested in this crater, dead and alone in the middle of a sea only frequent
the fishing boats.

Ferragut had seen also, although by far, entering the port of Trapani, the archipelago of Egadi
where large tuna fisheries. Once he landed in Pantelleria island,
midway between Sicily and Africa.

He was a towering volcanic cone emerging in the middle of the strait, and at whose feet were
alkaline lakes, sulphurous smoke, hot springs and prehistoric building
blocks, like those of Sardinia and the Balearics. Ships to Tunis and
Tripoli were taking shipment of raisins, only export of this ancient
Phoenician colony.

Between Pantelleria and Sicily, the sea floor
rose considerably, saving on its back a water layer at some points
was only twelve feet thick. Was extensive bank called the Adventure,
swelling volcanic island flooded twice, submarine pedestal Sicily.

Also,
the bank appeared to interest the Count Aventura.

- Well you know
the sea - said in a tone of approval.

Ferragut was going to keep
talking, but the two ladies entered with a tray containing service
area and various dishes of cakes. The captain was no surprise that
lack of bondage. The doctor and his friend were to him a women of
extraordinary ways, and all the actions was logical and natural. Freya
served tea with modest grace, as if was the daughter of the house.

They
spent the rest of the afternoon talking on distant voyages. No one
mentioned the war or to the concerns of Italy at that time to maintain
their neutrality or leave it. Seemed to live in a place inaccessible
to thousands of miles around the human throng.

The two women tried
to count, with a familiarity of tone, as persons of the same world,
but the sailor thought he noticed at times that you were afraid.

By
late afternoon, this person left his seat, and Ferragut did the same,
comprising that would put an end to his visit. The count offered to
accompany him. While saying goodbye the doctor, thanking him with
extreme courtesy would have made known to the captain, he Freya felt
squeezed his hand significantly.

- After Dark - mumbled slightly,
without moving his lips barely -. Come back later ... Wait.

Oh, joy!
... The eyes, the smile, the pressure of the hand, saying to him more.

Never
got a ride as nice as they marched alongside Kaledine through the
streets of Chiaia toward the shore. What did this man? ... Little
things to keep silence, but he seemed to observations of deep wisdom.
His voice was, he said, harmonious and caressing. Everything was just
lovely, the people walking the streets, Neapolitan noise dark, dark
sea, the whole life.

They parted at the door of the hotel. The count,
in spite of his offers of friendship, went without saying what their
home.

"No matter - thought Ferragut -. Return home to find the doctor.
"

The rest of the evening was spent alternately agitated by hope
and impatience. No I wanted to eat, the emotion had paralyzed his
appetite ... And once seated at table, ate More than ever, with an
eagerness mechanical and distracted.

I needed to walk, talk to someone,
for the passage of time more quickly, deceiving his restless waiting.
She did not return to the hotel until very late ... And precisely
retired to his room earlier than usual, thinking, with an illogical
superstitious that this would come before Freya.

His first movement
was seen in his room with pride. Looked at the ceiling, pitying the
ocean love that one week before lived upstairs. Poor man! How they
had laughed it! ... Odysseus himself was admired as a completely new
personality, happy and successful, separated from each other by a
painful period of humiliations and failures did not want to remember.

Very
long hours of anxiously awaiting! ... Paced smoking, lighting a cigarette
in the rest of the former. He opened the window, wanting to erase
the scent of strong snuff. She just liked oriental cigarettes ...
And the acrid smell persists cigar Tan, juicy and brave, reached into
his bag of toiletries, spilling onto the bed fund several bottles
of essence long forgotten.

A sudden concern bitter waiting. Which
was about to reach what was perhaps unaware of their room. He was
not sure giving him the address with sufficient clarity. It was possible
that would have been wrong ... Began to believe that indeed he was
wrong.

The fear and impatience made him open his door, standing on
the porch to watch by far the closed room Freya</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>