<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09169</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>503955</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23226</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El distinguido señor Céspedes, cónsul argentino
en Colón, que está allí labrando su fortuna con un heroísmo incomparable, se encuentra, por
mi desgracia, en cama. ¿Qué hacer? ¿Visitar la ciudad? Veinte minutos y c'est fait. Barro y
casas de madera; nada. Ponerme a leer... ¿en mi cuarto? ¡Prefiero la muerte! Y aquí me tienen
ustedes, tal como lo oyen, instalado en una mesa del bar-room de mi hotel, con un cocktail
pro forma, por delante, estudiando, durante seis horas consecutivas, a los marineros que jugaban
al billar y a los numerosos parroquianos del mostrador. Uno de ellos, un capitán mercante yanqui,
entró a la una, ligeramente punteado y se absorbió medio vaso de una bebida que tenía que rodear
los bordes de azúcar quemada para evitar el contacto de los labios. Durante cuatro horas, el
yanqui entró regularmente cada veinte minutos y se ingurgitó una dosis de idénticas proporciones.
Bajo el insoportable calor del día y en la lucha con los vapores internos que estaban a punto
de hacerle estallar, los ojos del yanqui saltaban rojos... A las cuatro de la tardo cayó ebrio,
muerto; dos marineros lo arrastraron a un rincón y allí quedó.

En una de las esquinas de la pieza, ocupando a lo sumo un espacio de metro y medio cuadrado,
un joven suizo había instalado su vidriera y su mesita de relojero. Lo tenía frente a mí; durante
media hora frotó con una gamuza un resorte de reloj; luego dejó caer la cabeza entre las manos,
y cuando al final del día lo observé (¡no había llegado un solo cliente!) vi correr dos grandes
lágrimas por sus mejillas. Más de una vez tuve el impulso de ir a conversar con el pobre relojero;
pero a mi vez, estaba tan nervioso e irascible, que acabé por fastidiarme hasta del infeliz
que tenía delante.

Los que no han viajado o los que sólo lo han hecho en los grandes centros europeos, no pueden
darse cuenta exacta de una situación de ánimo como aquella en que me encontraba. El espíritu
se forma la quimera de que es imposible salir de ella, que ese martirio se va a prolongar indefinidamente.
A cada instante, y para cobrar valor, es necesario echar mano a la cartera (nunca la he cuidado
como allí), decirse que hay medios para partir en cualquier momento, que los vapores esperan,
y en fin, que, si uno se encuentra en ese centro, es por un acto libro y premeditado de la
voluntad.

Por fin vino la noche, y cuando la recuerdo, declaro que siento una viva satisfacción por haber
contemplado ese cuadro único y característico. He dicho ya que Colón se compone casi en su
totalidad de una sola calle, pero he olvidado mencionar que a lo largo de la misma corre una
especie de recoba para proteger las entradas contra las lluvias frecuentes. Me paseaba bajo
ella al caer las primeras sombras y me llamó la atención que delante de cada hotel, de cada
bar-room, de cada puerta, un individuo sacaba una pequeña mesa de tijera, se instalaba ante
ella, encendía un farol, arreglaba en un semicírculo artístico algunas docenas de pesos fuertes
en plata, y comenzaba a batir con estruendo un enorme cuerno provisto de dados. De los buques
amarrados a la orilla, una vez que dieron las siete, empezó a salir una nube de marineros y
oficiales, contramaestres, etc., que pronto obstruyeron la vía, formando grupos compactos delante
de cada mesa. Como si un soplo hubiera animado el barro y formado con él cuerpos de mujeres,
brotaron del suelo en un instante centenares de negras, mulatas, cuarteronas lívidas, descalzas
en su mayor parte, ebrias, inmundas, que a su vez, atraídas por la fascinación del juego, se
agolpaban alrededor de las mesas, rechinaban los dientes cuando perdían y saltaban a los marineros
tambaleantes, pidiéndoles, en un idioma que no era inglés ni francés, ni español, ni nada conocido,
una de esas monedas de a real que los americanos llaman a dime.

Los bar-rooms estaban llenos; no se oía más que la voz ronca y gutural de los negros de Jamaica,
la eterna blasfemia del marinero inglés y el hablar soez de algunos gaditanos. Salían y en
la primera mesa arrojaban una moneda, luego otra y, una vez exhaustos, la emprendían con el
vecino, las navajas relucían y sólo con esfuerzo era posible separarlos. Uno rodaba en el barro,
dos o tres mujeres ebrias bailaban al son de un órgano en el que un italiano con cara de mártir,
tocaba un cancán desenfrenado. Un calor sofocante y una atmósfera insoportable, como el ruido,
las maldiciones, el sarcasmo, la eterna pelea con el banquero que iba más aprisa a medida que
veía a sus parroquianos más en punto... y yo reclinado en mi pilar, preguntándome qué hacía
entre aquel mundo, verdadero sabat moderno y tanteándome para persuadirme que no soñaba. He
ahí Colón; una licencia, una libertad absoluta para todos los vicios y las degradaciones humanas.
El que paga un pequeño impuesto tiene el derecho de establecer su tapete al aire libre, ¡y
qué tapete! La explotación, el robo más escandaloso al marinero ignorante como una bestia y
que, bajo los vapores del aguardiente, se deja despojar del premio de un año de labor, jugando
su vida en las tormentas. ¡Esas mujeres, sobre todo, esas mujeres, asquerosas arpías, negras
y angulosas, esparciendo a su alrededor la mezcla de su olor ingénito y de un pacholí que hace
dar vuelta al estómago!... Pouah!...

Llegado a mi cuarto, sofocándome, sin poderme desnudar por asco a la cama, me senté en un sillón
y me llamé a cuentas. Había resuelto pasar diez días en el Istmo y ese mismo día había casi
retenido mi pasaje en el City of Para, que salía para Nueva York en el término indicado. Allí
mismo, con toda solemnidad, me impuse el juramento de dejar Colón, renunciando a Panamá, al
canal, al mundo entero, en el primer barco que zarpase, sin importarme para dónde. Cómo pasé
esa noche, ¿a qué decirlo? Al alba estaba en pie, me ponía en campaña y sabía que dos días
después partía para Nueva York el vapor Alene, de la compañía Atlas. Tomé en el acto mi billete
e hice transportar a bordo mi equipaje, felicitándome de tener el tiempo suficiente para ir
a una de las próximas estaciones del canal y poder apreciar por mis ojos la marcha de las obras
y el porvenir de la empresa. Pagué mi cuenta al infame mulatillo, y cuando me encontré a bordo,
en un vapor pequeño e incómodo, creí que entraba solemnemente en el paraíso.

Una simple mirada a la carta geográfica de la tierra ha hecho nacer en el espíritu de los hombres
la idea de corregir ciertos caprichos de la naturaleza en el momento de la formación geológica
del mundo. Los Istmos de Corinto, de Suez y de Panamá, han sido sucesivamente, en el tiempo
y en el espacio, objeto de preocupación para todos aquellos que buscaban los medios de aumentar
el bienestar de la raza humana. Los griegos, con sus ideas religiosas que los impulsaban a
la personificación de todos los elementos, consideraban un sacrilegio el solo intento de modificar
los aspectos del mundo conocido, y Esquilo atribuye el desastre de Jerjes a la venganza divina,
por la altiva manera con que el monarca persa trató al Helesponto. Los romanos, poco navegadores,
ni aun fijaron su mirada en el Istmo de Suez, porque sus legiones estaban habituadas a recorrer
la tierra entera con su paso marcial.

Ha sido necesario el portentoso desenvolvimiento comercial del mundo de Occidente, para que
el sueño de abrir rutas marítimas nuevas y económicas se convirtiese en realidad. La vieja
vía terrestre que conducía al Oriente, fue abandonada cuando Vasco de Gama dobló el Cabo de
las Tempestades, y a su vez el itinerario del ilustre portugués cedió el paso al que trazó
el ingenio moderno tan admirablemente personificado en el «Gran Francés», como se ha llamado
a M. de Lesseps. Lo que impone respeto en la obra de este hombre, no es la concepción de la
idea, que corría hacía ya muchos años en el campo intelectual. Es la perseverancia para habituar
el espíritu público a encarar una empresa de tal magnitud con serenidad, con las vistas positivas
de un negocio fácil y rápido; es la tenacidad de su lucha contra Inglaterra, que cree ver en
ella comprometidos sus intereses. ¡La experiencia de Suez se ha embotado contra la implacable
resistencia británica, y dentro de diez años se leerá con indecible asombra el libro que acaba
de publicarse, en el que los hombres más notables de Inglaterra declaran un peligro para su
independencia la perforación del túnel de la Mancha! ¡Tal así, vemos hoy el artículo sarcástico
del Times, burlándose de Stephenson que pretendía recorrer con su locomotora una distancia
de veinte millas por hora!

El Istmo de Panamá es uno de esos puntos geográficos que, como Constantinopla, están llamados
a una importancia de todos los tiempos. Punto céntrico de dos continentes, paso obligado para
el comercio de Europa con cinco o seis naciones americanas, natural es que haya llamado la
atención del gran perforador. Los americanos, construyendo el ferrocarril que lo atraviesa
y estableciendo las tarifas más leoninas que se conocen en la tierra[28], creyeron innecesaria
la excavación del canal, que, dignos hijos de los ingleses, nunca miraron con buenos ojos.
La perseverancia de Lesseps triunfó una vez más, y la nueva ruta recibió su trazo elemental[29].

¿Cuál será el resultado económico del Canal de Panamá? Desde luego, la aproximación, por la
baratura del transporte, de todas las tierras que baña el Pacífico, desde el Estrecho de Behring
hasta Chile mismo, con los grandes centros europeos. La ruta de Magallanes será abandonada
por la misma e idéntica causa que se abandonó la de Vasco de Gama, y la importancia comercial
de ese estrecho que ha estado a punto de encender la guerra en el extremo Sur de la América,
habrá desaparecido por completo.

Aun en el día, el comercio entero del Perú y el movimiento de pasajeros, se hace por Panamá,
a pesar de las incomodidades y retardos del trasbordo y la enormidad del flete del ferrocarril
istmeño. Los chilenos mismos suelen preferir esa vía, que les evita los rudos mares del Sur
y el cansancio de esa navegación monótona, mientras la ruta del norte presenta mares tranquilos
y las frecuentes escalas que aligeran la pesadez del viaje. Una vez abierto el canal, raro
será, pues, el buque que vaya a buscar el Estrecho de Magallanes para entrar en el Pacífico.
Para los chilenos, y tal vez para los peruanos, sólo un camino luchará con ventaja contra la
vía de Panamá; será el ferrocarril que una a Buenos Aires con Chile. Esa será la ruta obligada
de la mayor parte de los americanos del Pacífico, en tránsito para Europa, porque será más
corta, más rápida y más agradable.

Ahora bien, ¿se hará el canal, con el presupuesto sancionado y en el tiempo indicado en el
programa de M. de Lesseps? Avanzo con profunda convicción mi opinión negativa. No se trata
aquí, y M. de Lesseps empieza a comprenderlo ya, de una obra como la de Suez. Falta el Khedive,
faltan los centenares de miles de fellahs, que morían en la tarea, como sus antepasados de
ahora cuarenta siglos en la construcción de las pirámides que quedan fijas sobre las arenas,
como monumentos de esas insensatas hecatombes humanas.

El pasajero que hoy cruza el Canal de Suez, bostezando ante el monótono paisaje de arenas y
palos de telégrafo, no piensa nunca--y hace bien, porque no hay motivo para agitarse la sangre
en un sentimentalismo retrospectivo--en los cadáveres que quedaron tendidos a lo largo de esos
áridos malecones. Eran fellahs, esclavos sin voz ni derecho, y nadie habló de ellos.

Pero en Panamá no hay khedives ni fellahs y las condiciones generales de salubridad son aún
inferiores a las de Suez. Basta conocer el nombre de algunos puntos del trayecto del Istmo,
nombres que vienen de la conquista, como el de «Mata cristianos», para darse cuenta del ameno
clima de esas localidades. No resiste el europeo a ese sol abrasador que inflama el cráneo,
no puede luchar contra la emanación que exhala la tierra removida, tierra húmeda, pantanosa,
lacustre. ¿Cuántos han muerto hasta hoy de los que fueron contratados, desde el comienzo de
la empresa? No busquéis en las estadísticas oficiales, que ocultan esas cosas, sin duda para
no turbar la digestión de los accionistas europeos. Buscadlos en las cruces de los cementerios,
en las fosas comunes repletas, y formaos una idea del número de bajas en ese pequeño ejército
de trabajadores, recordando que muchos ingenieros, con el principal a la cabeza, gente toda
cuya higiene personal les servía de preservativo, han sido de los primeros en caer bajo las
fiebres del Istmo.

Se ha detenido ya la corriente de europeos, y un momento se ha pensado en los chinos. Pero,
como éstos son más hábiles que fuertes, y como, a pesar de chinos, son mortales, creo que se
ha desistido de ese proyecto. Hay además una razón económica, en todas esas grandes empresas:
el dinero de los peones, en sus tres cuartas partes, reingresa en la caja, por conducto de
las cantinas numerosas y provisiones de todo género que se establecen sobre el terreno. Los
chinos no consumen nada, lo que no los hace por cierto muy simpáticos a la empresa.

Por fin, se ha echado mano de los nativos, eso es, de los que, estando habituados al clima,
podrían resistirlo, y se ha contratado un gran número de panameños, samarios, cartageneros,
costarriquenses, buscando reclutas hasta en las Antillas próximas. Pero toda esa gente sin
necesidades, habituada a vivir un día con un plátano, no es ni fuerte, ni laboriosa, ni se
somete a la disciplina militar indispensable en compañías de esa magnitud.

Falto de hombres, M. de Lesseps apeló a la industria y contrató la construcción en Estados
Unidos de enormes máquinas de excavación, cuyos dientes de hierro debían reemplazar el brazo
humano. Es necesario ver trabajar esos monstruos para saber hasta dónde puede llegar la potencia
mecánica. El ingeniero constructor del motor fijo que daba movimiento a las infinitas poleas
de la Exposición Universal de Filadelfia, decía que, si tuviera un punto fuera del mundo para
colocar su máquina, sacaría a la Tierra de su órbita.

Tenía razón, como la tenía Arquimedes.

Pero no hay máquina que pueda luchar contra las lluvias torrenciales que en Panamá se suceden
casi sin interrupción durante nueve meses del año. Abierto un foso, en cualquier punto de la
línea, cavado hasta tres y cuatro metros de profundidad, viene un aguacero, lo colma y derrumba
dentro la tierra laboriosamente extraída un momento antes.

Es inútil pensar en agotarlo, porque cinco minutos después estará de nuevo lleno. Viene el
sol al día siguiente, abrasador, inflamado, se remueve el barro para continuar los trabajos,
y los miasmas deletéreos infeccionan la atmósfera.

¿Se hará el canal? Sin duda alguna, porque no es una obra imposible y los recursos con que
hoy cuenta la industria humana son inagotables. Pero, en vista de las dificultades que he apuntado
y que me es permitido creer no se tuvieran en vista al plantear los lineamientos generales
de la obra, me es lícito pensar, de acuerdo con todas las personas que han visitado los trabajos,
observando imparcialmente, que el canal no estará abierto al comercio universal antes de 10
años y después de haber consumido algo más del doble de la suma presupuesta (seiscientos millones
de francos).

No veo sino a M. de Lesseps capaz de llevar a cabo la empresa que tan dignamente coronará su
vida. ¡Quiera el cielo prolongar los días del ilustre anciano para su gloria propia y para
el beneficio del mundo entero!

Son conocidas las dificultades suscitadas por los Estados Unidos a la empresa del Canal de
Panamá, los ardientes debates a que esta cuestión dio origen en el Congreso de Wáshington y
la idea, un momento acariciada, de proteger con todo el poder de la gran nación, el proyecto
rival de practicar el canal interoceánico a través de Nicaragua. La entereza y tenacidad de
M. de Lesseps triunfaron una vez más contra el nuevo inconveniente; pero los Estados Unidos,
lejos de declararse vencidos, reanimaron la cuestión bajo la forma diplomática, tocando el
papel primordial en el memorable debate que en el momento de escribir estas líneas aun no se
ha agotado, a M. Blaine, cuyo rápido paso por el Gobierno de la Unión ha marcado una huella
tan profunda, y cuya reputación, después de la caída, ha sido desgarrada tan sin piedad por
sus adversarios. Para éstos, M. Blaine no ha sido sino un político aventurero e impuro, que
ha pretendido variar la corriente de vida internacional que durante un siglo había conducido
sin tropiezo la nave de la Unión. Los asuntos del Pacífico; el engaño inexcusable de un pueblo
en agonía que tiende sus brazos desesperados a una promesa falaz; los misterios de la Peruvian
Guano Company; la palinodia vergonzosa de los señores Trescott y Blaine en Santiago de Chile,
han suministrado no escasos elementos de acusación contra el primer ministro del presidente
Garfield. Paréceme, sin embargo, que si un extranjero imparcial estudia un poco el pueblo americano
actual, encontrará que es muy posible que el juicio del momento sobre M. Blaine no sea corroborado
por la opinión pública dentro de diez años. Es innegable que hay hoy en Estados Unidos una
corriente de poderosa reacción contra la política de aislamiento, que ha sido la base del sistema
americano y tal vez de su prosperidad. Sueños y ambiciones patrióticas de un lado, vistas profundas
sobre el porvenir, del otro, y en el centro, la ponderación, siempre grave, de intereses mezquinos,
de lucro rápido y fácil, han determinado la iniciación de la propaganda de que M. Blaine se
hizo eco en el Gobierno. Una nación compacta de más de cincuenta millones de almas, con elementos
de riqueza, ingenio, cultura, iguales por lo menos a las primeras naciones de Europa, no puede
ni debe, dicen, permanecer indiferente a la política europea.

Por de pronto, los asuntos todos de la América deben ser de su exclusivo resorte, ejerciendo
la legítima hegemonía a que su importancia le da derecho. Desde el Cabo de Hornos a los límites
del Canadá no debe existir otra influencia que la de los Estados Unidos, ni escucharse otra
voz que la que se levante en Wáshington.

Tal es la idea fundamental, que pronto dará vida y servirá de lábaro a un partido, a cuyo frente
no dudo ver aún a M. Blaine, a pesar del estruendo de su caída. Y tal es la influencia que
ejerce sobre el espíritu colectivo, que a ella se debe el último recrudecimiento de la doctrina
de Monroe, que en estos momentos sostiene M. Frelinghysen con igual perseverancia que su antecesor.
El debate iniciado entre lord Grenwille y M. Blaine se continúa en el día, sin que se vea hasta
ahora probabilidades de que ninguna de las dos partes ceda.

No historiaré el tratado Clayton-Bulwer, conocido por todos los que en estas cuestiones se
interesan; recordaré solamente que fue una transacción, un modus vivendi mejor dicho, que permitiese
extenderse las influencias inglesa y americana en las Antillas y las costas de Centro América,
de una manera paralela que no diese lugar a conflictos.

Pero, si los americanos encontraban cómodo el tratado cuando se trataba de factorías insignificantes
o islotes diminutos, no juzgaron lo mismo respecto al futuro Canal de Panamá y denunciaron
listamente el tratado, reclamando la garantía exclusiva de la libre navegación y neutralidad
del Istmo, para sí mismos. Los ingleses, como es natural, rechazaron la denuncia y propusieron,
en vez de esa garantía exclusiva, la de todas las potencias de Europa, en unión con los Estados
Unidos. Tal es la cuestión; volúmenes de notas se han cambiado, sin que aun se vea un paso
positivo.

Entretanto, ¿cuál es la opinión de Colombia, que al fin y al cabo, teniendo la soberanía territorial
y la jurisdicción directa, paréceme que puede reclamar algún derecho a ser oída? Desde luego,
es bueno recordar que Colombia ha tenido más de una vez que interponer reclamaciones serias
contra los avances de los Estados Unidos en las costas atlánticas del Istmo. A veces ha necesitado
gritar muy fuerte para ser oída en Europa, y sólo así, los americanos han largado la presa
de que perentoriamente, con el derecho del león, se habían apoderado, saltando sobre el tratado
Clayton-Bulwer mismo. Pero un ministro colombiano, de paso para Europa, pues ni aun en Wáshington
estaba acreditado, tuvo la ocurrencia de firmar con el Gabinete americano, un protocolo, por
el cual Colombia declaraba satisfacerse y preferir la garantía exclusiva de los Estados Unidos.
Esa convención fue solemnemente desaprobada en Bogotá; pero Colombia, comprendiendo, a mi juicio
bien, sus conveniencias, tira son épingle du jeu, y dejó frente a frente a la Inglaterra y
a la Unión, manifestando, por lo demás, merced a la voz de su prensa y a la palabra de sus
oradores en el Congreso, sus simpatías indudables por la garantía unida, propuesta por la Inglaterra.

En el fondo, la doctrina Monroe no es sino una opinión, un desideratum, el anhelo de un pueblo,
que formula así sus intereses generales. Pero de ahí a convertir esa opinión en un principio
de derecho público, hay distancia y mucha. Además de que los principios de derecho, no sólo
en nuestro siglo, sino en todos los tiempos, han influido muy débilmente en la solución de
las cuestiones de hecho, los americanos ni aun pueden pretender que la doctrina Monroe sea
admitida por el consenso universal. Lejos de eso; desde el presidente que le dio su nombre
hasta el actual, ninguno la ha formulado con sus variantes en el tiempo, sin que la Inglaterra,
y en muchos casos la Europa, haya dejado de protestar. ¡El pobre Monroe ha hecho muchas veces
el papel del lobo! ¡el lobo! de la fábula; pero, como los americanos jamás mostraron la garra,
ni cuando la expedición de Méjico, ni cuando el bombardeo de Valparaíso, en el que las balas
españolas pasaban casi sobre buques que llevaban la bandera estrellada, nadie cree ya en eso
espantajo.

La Inglaterra contesta que, teniendo indiscutibles intereses en el Pacífico, y siendo el Canal
de Panamá una ruta para la India, es natural que quiera tomar parte en la garantía. Entonces
reclamo mi parte también, contestan los Estados Unidos, en la garantía del canal de Suez. La
Inglaterra sonríe... e insiste.

Es seguro que la intención de M. Blaine, al convocar el Congreso americano, que debía reunirse
en Wáshington en noviembre de 1882, con el pretexto de buscar medios para evitar la guerra
entre las naciones americanas (sic), era simplemente echar sobre el tapete la cuestión de la
garantía del Istmo, y tal vez, ante la perseverancia de la Inglaterra, que no cede, proponer,
en lugar de su garantía exclusiva, la de todos los Estados que componen ambas Américas. ¿Qué
actitud aconsejaba a éstas la inteligencia clara de sus intereses? ¿Qué habría dicho la Europa
a semejante proposición?

Vamos por partes. Noto que salgo por un momento del tono general de este libro de impresiones,
en el que sólo he querido consignar lo que he visto y sentido en países casi desconocidos para
nosotros. Pero como la cuestión en primer lugar, refiriéndose a Colombia, entra en mi cuadro,
y toca por otra parte, no ya a un interés del momento, sino a la marcha constante de la política
americana, no creo inoportuno consignar aquí las ideas que un estudio detenido me permite considerar
como las más sanas y convenientes para todos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04193</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>185552</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20765</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The distinguished Mr. Céspedes, Argentine Consul
Colon, who is there to make his fortune incomparable heroism, is, by my misfortune, in bed.
What to do? "Visiting the city? Twenty minutes, c'est fait. Barro and wooden houses, nothing.
Get to read ... "In my room? I prefer death! And here I am you, as we hear, set in a bar-room
table of my hotel, with a cocktail pro forma, ahead, studying for six consecutive hours, the
sailors played pool and the many patrons of the counter. One of them, a merchant captain Yankee
came to a slightly stippled and absorbed half a glass of a drink that had to go around burnt sugar
edges to avoid contact of the lips. For four hours, Yankee came regularly every twenty minutes and
a dose of identical engorged proportions. Under the unbearable heat of the day and in the struggle
with internal vapors were about to make him explode, the eyes of the U.S. leaping red ... At four
in the afternoon fell drunk dead, two sailors dragged him into a corner and stood there.

In one corner of the room, taking at most a space five feet square,
a young Swiss had set up his window and watch your table.

I had it before me, during half hour rubbed with a cloth a clock spring, then dropped his head
in his hands, that at the end of the day was observed (not one customer had come!) saw him run two
tears streaming down her cheeks. More than once I had the urge to go and talk to the poor watchmaker;
but in my turn, I was so nervous and irritable, which I finally bother me to the unhappy before
him.

Those who have not traveled or have done only in major European centers
can not exact realization of a state of mind as one in which I was.

The spirit forms the chimera that it is impossible to leave it, that martyrdom will be prolonged
indefinitely. At every moment, and take courage, it is necessary to take his wallet (I never
care as there), said that there are ways to go at any time, the vapors expect and finally, that if one is
in the center, is a book and premeditated act of will.

At last night came, and when I remember, I declare that I feel a great satisfaction for having
referred to this table and unique.

I have said that Columbus is composed almost entirely in one street, but I forgot to mention that
over the same runs a Recoba kind of entries to protect against frequent rain. I walked under
her to drop the first shadows and I noticed that in front of every hotel, every bar-room, every
door, a man pulled a small folding table, was installed before she lit a lamp, arranged in
a semicircle a few dozen art piastres silver, and began to beat thundered a huge horn dice
provided. Ship moored to the shore, once gave seven, began dating a cloud of sailors and officers,
foremen, etc., soon blocked the road, forming compact groups before each table. As if a blow had
driven the mud and formed with the female body, sprang from the ground in an instant hundreds
of black, mulatto, quadroon livid, barefoot mostly, drunken, filthy, in turn, attracted by
the fascination of the game, crowded around the tables, gnashed their teeth when they were down and
jumped to the sailors shaky, asking, in a language other than English or French, or Spanish,
or anything known one of these real coins to the Americans call a dime.

The bar-rooms were full, no sound was hoarse and guttural voice of Black people in Jamaica, blasphemous
eternal sailor speak English and some foul Cadiz. Out and the first table threw a coin, then another
and, once exhausted, he entered the neighbor, the gleaming blades
and effort was only possible to separate.

One was rolling in the mud two or three drunken women dancing to an organ in which an Italian face
on Mars, played a wild cancan. Sweltering heat and unbearable atmosphere, such as noise, curses,
sarcasm, the eternal fight with the banker who was quicker as parishioners saw more point ...
and I reclined in my column, wondering what he was doing between that world, modern and very real
Sabbath to convince me I was not dreaming. I Columbus then, a license, an absolute freedom to all
the vices and human degradation. He who pays a small tax has the right to establish their outdoor
table, and what mat! Exploitation, theft more outrageous the sailor as a beast ignorant that
under the fumes of liquor, leaving a strip of the award year of work, playing their lives in
storms. These women, especially those women, filthy harpies, black and angular, spreading the
mixture around your innate odor and patchouli makes a turn the stomach! ... Pouah! ...

Come to my room, suffocating, without being able to strip out of disgust to bed, I sat in a
chair and I called to account. Had resolved to spend ten days in the Isthmus and that day was
almost held my ticket in the City of Para, who came to New York in the period indicated. There
same, in all seriousness, I imposed an oath to leave Columbus, renouncing Panama, channel, the
whole world, the first ship that will sail, no matter to where.

How I Spent that night, what say? At dawn I was standing, I put in the field and knew that two days
left for New York after the steam Alene, company Atlas. I took my ticket on the spot and I
carry my luggage on board, congratulating me on having enough time to go to a forthcoming Channel
stations and to see with my own eyes the progress of work and the future of the company. I
paid my account of the infamous mulatto, and when I came on board, vapor in a small and uncomfortable,
I thought solemnly entered paradise.

A glance at the geographical map of the land has given birth in the minds of men the idea of
??correcting certain vagaries of nature at the time of the geological formation the world. The
Isthmus of Corinth, the Suez and Panama, have been successively in time and space, of concern to
all those who sought ways to increase the welfare of mankind.

The Greeks, with their religious beliefs that impelled the personification of all items considered
a sacrilege to attempt to change aspects of the known world, and Aeschylus Xerxes attributed the
disaster to divine retribution, by the haughty manner in which the Persian monarch treated
the Hellespont. The Romans, some browsers even fixed their gaze on the Isthmus of Suez, for his
legions were accustomed to go the whole earth with his step-martial.

Was necessary commercial development wondrous world of the West, so that dream of opening new shipping
routes and economical to become a reality. The old land that led to the East, was abandoned when
Basque Gama rounded the Cape of Storms, and in turn the route of the famous Portuguese gave way
to that outlined so wonderfully modern wit personified in the "Great
French", as it's called M. de Lesseps.

What commands respect in the work of this man, not the concept of idea, which ran many years
ago in the intellectual field. It is the perseverance to habituate the public mind to deal
with a company of this magnitude with serenity, with positive views a quick and easy business,
is the tenacity of their fight against England, he believes see she committed their interests.
The experience of Suez is against the relentless dull British resistance, and in ten years with
incredible read the book just amazed published, in which the most remarkable men of England
declared a threat to drilling independence Channel Tunnel! Maybe so, today we see sarcastic The
Times, mocking intended Stephenson locomotive traveling with a distance twenty miles per hour!

The Isthmus of Panama is one of those geographical points, such as Constantinople, are called
the importance of all time. Central point of two continents, a must for European trade with five
or six American nations, it is natural to have dialed the attention of the big punch. The Americans,
built the railroad that passes through and establishing the lowest rates leonine known on earth
[28], believed unnecessary the excavation of the canal, which, worthy sons of the English,
never looked with favor.

Lesseps's perseverance triumphed once again, and the new route received his elementary stroke
[29].

What is the economic result of the Panama Canal? Since then, the approach, by cheapness of
transportation, of all the lands washed by the Pacific from the Bering Strait to Chile itself,
with the major European centers. Magellan's route will be abandoned by the same identical
result to that of the Basque left Gama, and the commercial importance
the strait has been on the verge of starting the war in the far south
of America, will have disappeared completely.

Even in the day, the whole trade of Peru and the movement of passengers, is made by Panama
despite the inconveniences and delays of transshipment and the enormity of the rail freight Isthmian.
Chileans tend to prefer them that way, they avoid the rough seas of the South and tired of this
monotonous navigation, while the northern route has calm seas and
frequent stops to lighten the heaviness of the trip.

After opening the canal, rare will therefore be the vessel to search for the Strait of Magellan
into the Pacific. For Chileans, and perhaps for Peruvians, just one path to lead fight against
via Panama, is the rail that attaches to Buenos Aires to Chile. That will be the required path
of most Americans of the Pacific, in transit to Europe, because it will be shorter, faster and
more enjoyable.

Now, will the channel, with the sanctioned budget and time specified in M. Program de Lesseps?
I move with deep conviction my negative opinion. It is not here, and M. de Lesseps begins to understand
and, in a work like that of Suez. Missing Khedive, missing hundreds of thousands of fellahs,
who died in the task, as their ancestors now forty centuries in the
construction of the pyramids that are still on the sands, monuments
of these senseless slaughters human.

The passenger is now crossing the Suez Canal, yawning at the monotonous landscape of sand and telegraph
poles, never thinks about - and does well, because there is no reason to stir the blood in
a retrospective sentimentality - in the bodies were left lying along these aggregate piers.
Were fellahs, slaves without a voice or right, and nobody talked
about them.

But in Panama there is no fellahs Khedive and sanitation conditions are still lower than those
of Suez.

Just know the name of some points along the route of the Isthmus names coming from the conquest,
such as "Kill Christians", to realize the fun climate of those locations. Europe does not stand
the blazing sun to that which inflames the skull can not fight the emanation exhaled disturbed
soil, moist, marshy lake. How many have died to date from which they were hired, since the
beginning of the company? Do not seek official statistics, they hide these things, no doubt
not to disturb the digestion of European shareholders. Look for them in the crosses of cemeteries
in mass graves filled, and train yourselves an idea of ??the number of casualties in this small
army workers, noting that many engineers, with the main head, people all which served as their
personal hygiene condom, have been among the first to fall under the fever of the Isthmus.

Has stopped and the flow of Europeans, and a moment thought of the Chinese. But as they are
more skilled than strengths, and how, despite the Chinese, are deadly,
I think has withdrawn the project.

There is also an economic reason, in all these great companies: money from the laborers, in
their three-quarters re-enters the box through numerous canteens and supplies of all kinds down
on the ground. The Chinese do not consume anything, which certainly does not make very sympathetic
to the company.

Finally, it has seized from the natives, that is, those who are accustomed
to the climate, could be longer, and he has hired a large number of
Panamanians, Samaria, Cartagena, costarriquenses, looking for recruits
to the West Indies next.

But all those people without needs, used to live one day with a banana, is neither strong nor
industrious, nor subject to military discipline essential for companies of that magnitude.

Lacking
men, M. de Lesseps appealed to the construction industry contracted in the United enormous
excavation machines, which had iron teeth to replace the arm human. Work is necessary to see
these monsters to know how far power mechanics.

The motor construction engineer was fixed to the endless movement pulleys Universal Exhibition
in Philadelphia, said that if I had a point outside the world place your machine, pull out the
Earth from its orbit.

He was right, as Archimedes did.

But there is no machine that can combat the torrential rains that
occur in Panama almost without interruption for nine months.

Open a trench at any point line, dug up three to four meters deep, has a shower, it fills and
collapses laboriously extracted into the ground a moment before.

It is useless to think of exhausted, because five minutes later be
full again.

Come sun the next day, hot, swollen, mud is removed for further work, and deleterious miasma
infects the atmosphere.

Will there be any channel? Without a doubt, because it is a work impossible and the resources
today by human industry are endless. But in view of the difficulties I have pointed and that I am
allowed to believe were not taken into view in raising the general guidelines of the work,
I think it is legitimate, according to all the people who have visited the work impartial observer,
that the channel is not open to universal trade within 10 years and after having consumed more
than twice the budgeted amount (six hundred million francs).

But I do not see M. de Lesseps able to carry out the company that will crown her as gently life.
Heaven grant to extend the days of the illustrious old man for his own glory and the benefit
of the whole world!

The difficulties are raised by the United States to the Canal Company Panama, the fiery debates
that this matter originated in Washington and Congress the idea, cherished moment, to protect
all the power of the great nation, the project practice rival canal through Nicaragua. The
strength and toughness M. de Lesseps succeeded once again against the new problem, but the United
States far from the maturity, the issue was revived in the form diplomatic, playing the role
in the memorable debate at the time of writing, not yet exhausted, M. Blaine, whose rapid passage
through the Union Government has made a mark so deep, and the reputation, after the fall, has
been torn apart so ruthlessly by their opponents. For these, M. Blaine has been nothing but
a political adventurer and impure, that has sought to vary the flow of international life for
a century had led without tripping the ship of the Union. Pacific affairs, the inexcusable cheating
people in agony he stretches his arms in desperation to a false promise, the mysteries of the
Peruvian Guano Company, the shameful recantation of Messrs. Trescott and Blaine in Santiago de
Chile, few elements have provided no indictment against Prime Minister President Garfield. It
seems, however, that if a study abroad fair a little the American people now find that it is
possible that the time trial on M. Blaine is not corroborated public opinion within ten years. It is
undeniable that the U.S. is now a powerful stream of reaction against the policy of isolation has
been the basis of the system American and perhaps prosperity. Patriotic dreams and ambitions
aside, deep view about the future, the other, and in the middle, pondering, always serious, narrow
interests, quick and easy profit, have determined the initiation of the propaganda that M. Blaine echoed
in the Government. A compact nation of over fifty million souls, with elements wealth, wit, culture,
equal to at least the first nations of Europe, can not should not, say, indifferent to the
European policy.

For the moment, the issues all of America should be his sole spring,
exerting legitimate hegemony that entitles its importance.

From Cape Horn to the limits Canada should not be another influence that the United States,
or hear other voice that rises in Washington.

This is the fundamental idea that life will soon serve as a party
labarum, headed no doubt see even M. Blaine, despite the sound of
his fall.

And such is the influence exerts on the collective spirit, that she should be the last resurgence
of the doctrine Monroe, which currently holds M. Frelinghysen with equal perseverance than
its predecessor. The debate started between Lord and M. Grenwille Blaine continues in the day,
without showing up now likely to either party subsides.

No historiaré the Clayton-Bulwer treaty, known to all that these issues
are interest, remember only that it was a compromise, a modus vivendi
rather than allow extended English and American influences in the
West Indies and the coasts of Central America in a parallel manner
that does not lead to conflict.

But if Americans were comfortable the treaty when it was insignificant factories tiny islets, not
tried the same thing about the future Panama Canal and reported cleverly
the treaty, claiming the exclusive guarantee of free navigation and
neutrality Isthmus, for themselves.

The British, of course, rejected the complaint and proposed, instead of that guarantee exclusive, all
the powers of Europe, together with States Together. That is the question; volumes of notes
have been changed, but still see a step positive.

Meanwhile, what is the view of Colombia, that after all, taking the territorial sovereignty and
the direct jurisdiction, it seems to me that you can claim a right to be heard? Since then,
is worth remembering that Colombia has had more than once that bring
serious complaints against the inroads of the United States on the
Atlantic coasts of the Isthmus.

Sometimes it's needed shout very loudly to be heard in Europe, and only then, Americans have quit the
dam that peremptorily, with the right of the lion, had taken over, jumping on the treaty Clayton-Bulwer
himself. But a Colombian minister, on his way to Europe, because even in Washington was accredited,
had the idea of ??signing with the American Office, a protocol, which Colombia declared satisfied
and prefer the security of the United States exclusively. This convention was formally disapproved
in Bogota, but Colombia, including, to my mind However, their convenience, are épingle du jeu strip,
and left face to face England and the Union, stating, moreover, through the voice of the press and
word of their Speakers at the Congress, its undoubted sympathy for the guarantee attached, proposed
by England.

At bottom, the Monroe Doctrine is nothing but an opinion, a desideratum, the longing of a people
that formula and their general interests. But then to turn that opinion at first public law,
there is much distance.

In addition to the principles of law, not only In our century, but at all times, have had very
weakly in solution questions of fact, Americans can not even claim that the Monroe Doctrine
is supported by the universal consensus. Far from it, from the president who gave his name
until now, none has made with its variations in time, without England, and in many cases,
Europe has ceased to protest. Poor Monroe has done many times the role of the wolf! Wolf!
of the fable, but, like the Americans never showed the claw, or if the issue of Mexico, or
when the bombardment of Valparaiso, where bullets spent most of Spanish ships carrying the flag
of stars, no longer believes in it scarecrow.

England replied that, having indisputable interest in the Pacific, and being the Canal Panama
a route to India, it is natural to want to take part in the warranty. Then claim I, too, answered
the United States in the security of the Suez Canal.

The England smiles ... and stresses.

Surely the intention of M. Blaine, when he called the American Congress, which was to meet in
Washington in November 1882, under the pretext of seeking the means
to avert war among the American nations (sic) was just lay on the
table the question of guarantee the Isthmus, and perhaps, to the perseverance
of England, not giving up, propose, rather than its exclusive warranty,
of all the states comprising the two Americas.

What attitude intelligence advised them clear of their interests? What would he say Europe such
a proposition?

We split. I notice that I leave for a moment the general tone of this book of impressions where
I just wanted to record what I have seen and felt almost unknown in countries us. But since
the question first, referring to Colombia, come into my box, and touches on the other hand, not
a current interest, but the steady march of politics American, I
do not enter inappropriate ideas here that a comprehensive study to
suggest me as healthier and more convenient for everyone.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>