<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04261</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>314768</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22927</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> No dejó de haber
alguna turbacion entre los mesmos incas, porque algunos hijos de Tupac Inca, habidos en otras
mujeres que la Coya, quisieron ponerse á pretender[191] la dignidad real, mas el pueblo, que
vian estaba con Guayna Capac, no lo consintió, mas estorbó el castigo que se hizo. Acabado
el ayuno, Guayna Capac salió con la borla muy galano y aderezado, y hizo las cirimonias usadas
por sus pasados, con el fin de las cuales el nombre de rey le pusieron, y así, á grandes voces
decian[192]: Guayna Capac Inca Zapalla tucuillacta uya; que quiere decir; "Guayna Capac solo
es rey; á él oyan todos los pueblos."

Era Guayna Capac, segun dicen muchos indios que le vieron y conocieron, de no muy grand cuerpo,
pero doblado y bien hecho; de buen rostro y muy grave; de pocas palabras, de muchos hechos;
era justiciero y castigaba sin templanza. Queria ser tan temido, que de noche le soñaran los
indios. Comia como ellos usan, y así vivia vicioso de mujeres, si así se le puede decir; oía
á los que le hablaban bien, y creíase muy de ligero: privaron con él mucho los aduladores y
lisonjeros, que entre ellos no faltaban, ni hoy deja de haber; y daba oidos á mentiras, que
fué causa que muchos murieron sin culpa. A los mancebos que tentados de la carne dormian con
sus mujeres ó mancebas, ó con las que estaban en el templo del sol, luego los mandaba matar
á ellos, y á ellas castigo igual. A los que él castigó por alborotos y motines, privó de las
haciendas, dándolas á otros; por otras causas, era el castigo en las personas solamente.--Mucho
desto disimulaba su padre, especial lo de las mujeres, que cuando se tomaba alguno con ellas,
decia que eran mancebos.--Su madre de Guayna Capac, señora principal, mujer y hermana que fué
de Tupac Inca Yupanqui, llamada Mama Ocllo, dicen que fué de mucha prudencia, y que avisó á
su hijo de muchas cosas que ella vió hacer á Tupac Inca, y que le queria tanto, que le rogó
no se fuese á Quito ni á Chile, hasta que ella fuese muerta; y así, cuentan que por le hacer
placer y obedecer á su mandado, estuvo en el Cuzco sin salir hasta que ella murió y fué enterrada
con grand pompa, metiéndose en su sepultura muchos tesoros y ropa fina y de sus mujeres y servidores.
Los más tesoros de los Incas muertos y heredades, que llaman chácaras, todo estaba entero desde
el primero, sin que ninguno osase gastarlo ni tocarlo, porque entre ellos no tenian guerras
ni necesidades que el dinero hobiese de las remediar; por donde creemos que hay grandes tesoros
en las entrañas de la tierra perdidos; y así estarán para siempre, si de ventura, alguno, edificando
ó haciendo otra cosa, no topare con algo de lo mucho que hay.

CAP. LXII.--Cómo Guayna Capac salió del Cuzco y lo que hizo.

Guayna Capac habia mandado parescer delante de sí á los principales señores de los naturales
de las provincias, y estando su Córte llena dellos, tomó por mujer á su hermana Chimbo Ocllo,
y por ello se hicieron grandes fiestas, dejando los lloros que por la muerte de Tupac Inca
se hacian. Y acabadas, mandó que se saliesen con él hasta cincuenta mill hombres de guerra,
con los cuales queria ir acompañado para ir á visitar las provincias de su reino. Como lo mandó,
se puso por obra, y salió del Cuzco con más pompa y autoridad que su padre; porque las andas
serian tan ricas, á lo que afirman los que llevaron el rey en sus hombros, que no tuvieran
precio las piedras preciosas tan grandes y muchas que iban en ellas, sin el oro de que heran
hechas. Y fué por las provincias de Xaquixaguana y Andaguaylas, y allegó á los Soras y Lucanas[193],
donde envió embajadas á muchas partes de los llanos y sierras, y tuvo respuesta dellos y de
otras, con grandes presentes y ofrecimientos.

Volvió desde aquellos lugares al Cuzco, donde estuvo entendiendo en hacer grandes sacrificios
al sol y á los que más tenian por dioses, para que le fuesen favorables en la jornada que queria
hacer, y dió grandes dones á los ídolos de los guacas; y supo de los adivinos, por los dichos
de los demonios, ó porque ellos lo inventaron, que le habia de suceder prósperamente en las
jornadas que hacer queria, y que volveria al Cuzco con grande honra y provecho. Esto acabado,
de muchas partes vinieron gentes con sus armas y capitanes, por su mandado, y alojados, de
la ciudad eran proveidos.

En el edificio de la fortaleza se entendia, sin dejar de labrar dia ninguno los para ello señalados.
En la plaza del Cuzco se puso la grand maroma de oro, y se hicieron grandes bailes y borracheras,
y, junto á la piedra de la guerra, se nombraron capitanes y mandones, conforme á su costumbre;
y ordenándoles, hizo un parlamento Guayna Capac, bien ordenado y dicho con palabras vehementes,
sobre que le fuesen leales así los que iban con él, como los que quedaban. Respondieron que
de su servicio no se partirian, el cual dicho loó y dió esperanzas de les hacer mercedes largas.
Y estando aparejado lo que para la jornada era menester, salió del Cuzco con toda la gente
de guerra que se habia juntado, y por un camino grande, tan soberbio como hoy dia paresce,
pues todos los de acá lo vemos y andamos por él, anduvo hácia el Collao, mostrando por las
provincias donde pasaba tener en poco los grandes servicios que le hacian; porque dicen que
decia que á los Incas todo se les debia. Entendia en saber lo que le daban de tributo, y la
posibilidad de la provincia; recogió muchas mujeres, las más hermosas que se podian hallar;
dellas tomaba para sí, y otras daba á sus capitanes y privados; las demás eran puestas en el
templo del sol y allí guardadas.

Entrando en el Collao, le trajeron cuenta de las grandes manadas que tenia de ganados, y cuántas
mill cargas de lana fina se llevaban por año á los que hacian la ropa para su casa y servicio.
En la isla de Titicaca entró y mandó hacer grandes sacrificios. En Chuquiabo[194], mandó que
estuviesen indios estantes con sus veedores á sacar metal de oro con la órden y regimiento
que se ha escripto. Pasando adelante, mandó que los Charcas y otras naciones hasta los Chichas,
sacasen cantidad grande de pastas de plata, que se llevasen al Cuzco por su cuenta, sin que
nada faltase; trasportó algunos mitimaes de una parte en otra, aunque habia dias que estaban
alojados; mandaba que todos trabajasen y ninguno holgase, porque decia que la tierra donde
habia holgazanes, no pensaban otra cosa sinó cómo buscar escándalos y corromper la honestidad
de las mujeres. Por donde pasaba, mandaba edificar tambos y plazas, dando con su mano la traza;
repartió los términos á muchas provincias y límite conocido, para que, por aventajallo, no
viniesen á las manos. Su gente de guerra, aunque era tanta, iba tan corregida, que no salia
de los reales un paso; por donde pasaban, los naturales proveian de lo necesario tan cumplidamente,
que era más lo que sobraba que lo que se gastaba. En algunos lugares edificaron baños, y en
otros cotos, y por los desiertos se hicieron grandes casas. Por todas partes quel Inca pasaba,
dejaba hechas tales cosas, que es admiracion contarlas. Al que erraba castigaba sin dejar pasar
por alto nada, y gratificaba á quien bien le servia.

Ordenado estas cosas y otras, pasó de las provincias subjetas agora á la Villa de la Plata,
y por lo de Tucuman[195] envió capitanes con gente de guerra á los Chiriguanaes; mas no les
fue bien, porque volvieron huyendo. Por otra parte, hácia la mar del Sur, envió más gente con
otros capitanes, á que señoreasen los valles y pueblos que del todo su padre no pudo conquistar.
El fué caminando con toda su gente hácia Chile, acabando de domar, por donde pasaba, las gentes
que habia. Pasó gran trabajo por los despoblados, y fué mucha la nieve que sobre ellos cayó;
llevaban toldos con que se guarescer y muchos yanaconas y mujeres de servicio. Por todas estas
nieves se iba haciendo el camino, ó ya estaba hecho, y bien limpio, y postas puestas por él.

Allegó á lo que llamaban Chile, á donde estuvo más de un año entendiendo en refrenar aquellas
naciones y asentarlas de todo punto; mandó que le sacasen la cantidad que señaló de tejuelos
de oro; y los mitimaes fueron puestos, y trasportadas muchas gentes de aquellas de Chile de
unas partes en otras. Hizo, en algunos lugares, fuertes y cercas á su uso, que llaman pucaraes,
para la guerra que con algunos tuvo. Anduvo mucho más por la tierra que su padre, hasta que
dijo que habia visto el fin della, y mandó hacer memorias por muchos lugares para que en lo
futuro se entendiese su grandeza, y formas de hombres crecidos[196].

Puesto en razon lo de Chile, y hecho lo que convino, puso sus delegados y gobernadores, y mandó
que siempre avisasen en la córte del Cuzco lo que pasara en aquella provincia. Encargóles que
hiciesen justicia y que no consintiesen motin ni alboroto que no matasen los movedores sin
dar la vida á ninguno.

Volvió al Cuzco, á donde fué recebido de la ciudad honradamente y los sacerdotes del templo
de Curicancha le dieron muchas bendiciones, y él alegró al pueblo con grandes fiestas que se
hicieron. Y nacíanle muchos hijos, los cuales criaban sus madres, entre los cuales nació Atahuallpa,
segund la opinion de todos los indios del Cuzco, que dicen ser así, y llamábase su madre Tuta
Palla, natural de Quillaco, aunque otros dicen ser del linaje de los Orencuzcos; y siempre,
desde que se crió, anduvo Atahuallpa con su padre, y era de más edad que Guascar.

Como Guayna Capac se hobiese holgado algunos meses en el Cuzco, y en él se hobiesen juntado
los sacerdotes de los templos y adivinos de los oráculos, mandó hacer sacrificios, y la ofrenda
de la capacocha se hizo bien grande y rica, y volvieron bien llenos de oro los burladores de
los hechiceros. A cada uno daban respuesta como les parescia que el rey sería más contento.
Lo cual con otras cosas pasado, mandó Guayna Capac que se entendiese en hacer un camino más
real, mayor y más ancho que por donde fué su padre, que llegase hasta Quito, á donde tenia
pensado de ir; y que los aposentos ordinarios y depósitos de las postas se pasasen á él. Para
que por todas las tierras se supiese ser esto su voluntad, salieron correos á lo avisar, y
luego fueron orejones á lo mandar cumplir, y se hizo un camino el más soberbio y de ver que
hay en el mundo, y más largo, porque salia del Cuzco y allegaba á Quito y se juntaba con el
que iba á Chile. Igual á él, creo yo que desde que hay memoria de gente, no se ha leido de
tanta grandeza como tuvo este camino, hecho por valles hondos y por sierras altas, por montes
de nieve, por tremedales de agua y por peña viva y junto á rios furiosos; por estas partes
iba llano y empedrado, por las laderas bien sacado, por las sierras deshechado, por las peñas
socavado, por junto á los rios sus paredes, entre nieves con escalones y descansos; por todas
partes limpio, barrido, descombrado, lleno de aposentos, de depósitos de tesoros, de templos
del sol, de postas que habia en este camino. ¡Oh! ¿Qué grandeza se puede decir de Alexandre,
ni de ninguno de los poderosos reyes que el mundo mandaron que tal camino hiciesen, ni inventasen
el proveimiento que en él habia? No fué nada la calzada que los romanos hicieron, que pasa
por España, ni los otros que leemos, para que con este se comparen. Y hízose hasta en más poco
tiempo de lo que se puede imaginar; porque los Incas, más tardaban ellos en mandarlo, que sus
gentes en ponerlo por obra.

Hízose llamamiento general en todas las provincias de su señorío, y vinieron de todas partes
tantas gentes, que hinchian los campos; y despues de haber hecho banquetes y borracheras generales,
y puesto en órden las cosas de la ciudad, salió della Guayna Capac con iscaypachaguaranga runas,
que quiere decir, con "doscientos mill hombres de guerra," sin los yanaconas y mujeres de servicio,
que no tenia cuento el número dellos. Llevaba consigo dos mill mujeres y dejaba en el Cuzco
más de cuatro mill.

Habian proveido los delegados y gobernadores que asistian en las cabeceras de las provincias,
que de todas las partes acudiesen [con] bastimentos y armas, y todo lo demás que siempre se
recogia y guardaba para cuando se hacia guerra; y así hincheron todos los grandes aposentos
y depósitos de todo ello, de manera, que de cuatro á cuatro leguas, que era la jornada, estaba
entendido que se habia de hallar proveimiento para toda esta multitud de gente, sin que faltase,
sino que sobrase más de lo que ellos gastasen y las mujeres, y muchachos y hombres que servian
personalmente de lo que les era mandado, y que llevaban el repuesto del Inca y el bagaje de
la gente de guerra de un tambo á otro, donde estaba el proveimiento que en el pasado.

Como saliese Guayna Capac, por el camino que por su mandado se habia mandado hacer, del Cuzco,
anduvo hasta que llegó á lo de Vilcas, donde paró algunos dias en los aposentos que le habian
hecho pegados con los de su padre; y holgóse de ver que estaba el templo del sol acabado, y
dejó cantidad de oro y pastas de plata para joyas y vasos; mandó que se tuviese grand cuidado
del proveimiento de las mamaconas y sacerdotes. Sobióse á hacer oracion en un terrado galano
y primo que para ello se habia hecho; sacrificaron, conforme á su ceguedad, lo que usaban,
y mataron muchos animales y aves, con algunos niños y hombres, para aplacar á sus dioses.

Esto hecho, salió de aquel lugar con su gente el rey, y no paró hasta el valle de Xauxa, donde
habia alguna controversia y division sobre los límites y campos del valle, entre los mismos
que dél eran señores. Como Guayna Capac lo entendió, despues de haber hecho sacrificios, como
en Vilcas, mandó juntar los señores Alaya, Cucichuca, Guacaropa[197] y entre ellos con equidad
repartió los campos de la manera que hoy dia lo tienen. A los Yauyos envió embajadas; lo mismo
hizo á los Yuncas, y á Bonbon envió algunos dones á los señores naturales de aquella tierra;
porque, como tenian fuerza en la laguna, en partes que nadaban, hablaban sueltamente, y por
rigor no quiso hablar con ellos hasta ver la suya. Los señores de Xauxa le hicieron grandes
servicios, y algunos de los capitanes y gente de guerra le fueron acompañando; y anduvo hasta
Bonbon, donde paró poco, porque quiso ir á Caxamalca, más aparejado lugar para descansar y
comarcano con provincias grandes y muy altas. Y por el camino siempre le venian gentes con
grandes embajadas y presentes.

Como llegó á Caxamalca, paró algunos dias para descansar del camino, y mandó que su gente de
guerra se alojase á la redonda de aquella tierra, y que comiese lo que recogido en los depósitos
estaba; y con la gente que le paresció entró por los Guancachupachos, y tuvo récia guerra,
porque no del todo quedaron los naturales de allí en gracia de su padre y conformidad; mas,
tanto pudo, que lo allanó y sojuzgó, poniendo gobernadores y capitanes, y eligiendo de los
naturales señores, para que mandasen las tierras, los que más les paresció; porque ellos, de
antigüedad, no conocian señores á otros que los que, siendo más poderosos, se levantaban y
acaudillaban para hacer guerra, y otorgaban paz cuando ellos querian. En los Chachapoyas halló
Guayna Capac gran resistencia; tanto, que por dos veces volvió huyendo desbaratado á los fuertes
que para su defensa se hacian; y con favores que le vinieron, se revolvió sobre los Chachapoyanos
y los quebrantó de tal manera, que pidieron paz, cesando por su parte la guerra. Dióse con
condiciones provechosas al Inca, que mandó pasar muchos dellos á que residiesen en el mesmo
Cuzco, cuyos descendientes hoy viven en la mesma ciudad; tomó muchas mujeres, porque son hermosas
y agraciadas y muy blancas; puso guarniciones ordinarias con soldados mitimaes, para que estuviesen
por frontera; dejó gobernador en lo principal de la comarca; proveyó lo que más ellos usaban;
castigó á muchos de los principales, porque le dieron guerra; lo cual hecho, á Caxamalca se
volvió, donde prosiguió su viaje, y puso en órden las provincias de Caxas, Ayahuaca, Guancabanba[198]
y las demás que con ellas confinan.

Público es entre muchos naturales de estas partes que Guayna Capac entró por la tierra que
llamamos Bracamoros, y que volvió huyendo de la furia de los hombres que en ella moran; los
cuales se habian acaudillado y juntado para defender á quien los fuese á enojar; y, sin los
orejones del Cuzco, cuenta esto el señor de Chincha, y algunos principales del Collao y los
de Xauxa. Y dicen todos, que yendo Guayna Capac acabando de asentar aquellas tierras por donde
su padre pasó y que habia sojuzgado, supo de cómo en los Bracamoros habia muchos hombres y
mujeres que tenian tierras fértiles, y que bien adentro de la tierra habia una laguna y muchos
rios, llenos de grandes poblaciones. Cobdicioso de descubrir y ganoso de señorear, tomando
la gente que le paresció, con poco bagaje, mandó caminar para allá, dejando el campo alojado
por los tambos reales, y encomendado á su capitan general. Entrando en la tierra, iban abriendo[199]
el camino con asaz trabajo, porque pasada la cordillera de los promontorios nevados, dieron
en la montaña de los Andes y hallaron rios furiosos que pasar, y caian muchas aguas del cielo.
Todo no fué parte para que el Inca dejase de llegar á donde los naturales por muchas partes
puestos en sus fuertes le estaban aguardando, desde donde le mostraban sus vergüenzas, afeándole
su venida; y comenzaron la guerra unos y otros, y tantos de los bárbaros se juntaron, los más
desnudos sin traer ropas, á lo que se afirmaba, que el Inca determinó de se retirar, y lo hizo
sin ganar nada en aquella tierra. Y los naturales que lo sintieron, le dieron tal priesa, que
á paso largo, á veces haciendo rostro, á veces enviando presentes, se descabulló dellos y volvió
huyendo á su reino, afirmando que se habia de vengar de los rabudos; lo cual decia, porque
algunos traian las maures[200] largas que les colgaban por encima de las piernas.

Desde estas tierras, donde ya habia reformado, se afirma tambien que envió capitanes con gente
la que bastó, á que viesen la costa de la mar lo que habia á la parte del Norte, y que procurasen
de atraer á su servicio los naturales de Guayaquil y Puerto Viejo; y que estos anduvieron por
aquellas comarcas, en las cuales tuvieron guerra y algunas batallas, y en unos casos quedaban
vencedores, y en otros no del todo; y ansí anduvieron hasta Collique, donde toparon con gentes
que andaban desnudas y comian carne humana, y tenian las costumbres que hoy tienen y usan los
comarcanos al rio de Sant Juan; de donde dieron la vuelta, sin querer pasar adelante, á dar
aviso á su rey, que con toda su gente habia llegado á los Cañares; á donde se holgó en estremo,
porque dicen nacer[201] allí, y que halló hechos grandes aposentos y tambos, y mucho proveimiento,
y envio embajadas á que le viniesen á ver de las comarcas; y de muchos lugares le vinieron
embajadores con presentes.

Tengo entendido que, por cierto alboroto que intentaron ciertos pueblos de la comarca del Cuzco,
lo sintió tanto, que, despues de haber quitado las cabezas á los principales, mandó expresamente
que los indios de aquellos lugares trajiesen de las piedras del Cuzco la cantidad que señaló,
para hacer en Tomebamba unos aposentos de mucho primor, y que con maromas las trujiesen; y
se cumplió su mandamiento. Y decia muchas veces Guayna Capac, que las gentes destos reinos,
para tenellos bien sojuzgados, convenia, cuando no tuviesen que hacer ni que entender, hacerles
pasar un monte de un lugar á otro; y áun del Cuzco mandó llevar piedras y losas para edificios
del Quito, que hoy dia tienen en los edificios que las pusieron.

De Tomebamba salió Guayna Capac y pasó por los Puruaes, y descansó algunos dias en Riobamba,
y en Mocha y en La Tacunga descansaron sus gentes y tuvieron bien que beber del mucho brebaje
que para ellos estaba aparejado y recogido de todas partes. Aquí fué saludado y visitado de
muchos señores y capitanes de la comarca, y envió orejones fué el de su linaje[202] á que fuesen
por la costa de Los Llanos y por la serranía á tomar cuenta de los quiposcamayos, que son sus
contadores, de lo que habia en los depósitos, y á que supiesen cómo se habian con los naturales
los quel tenia puestos por gobernadores, y si eran bien proveidos los templos del sol y los
oráculos y guacas que habia en todo lugar; y al Cuzco envió sus mensajeros para que ordenasen
las cosas que dejaba mandadas y en todo se cumpliese su voluntad. Y no habia dia que no le
venian correos, no uno ni pocos, sino muchos, del Cuzco, del Collao, de Chile y de todo su reino.

De La Tacunga anduvo hasta que allegó á Quito, donde fué recebido, á su modo y usanza, con
grandes fiestas, y le entregó el gobernador de su padre los tesoros, que eran muchos, con la
ropa fina y cosas más que á su cargo eran; y honróle con palabras, loando su fidelidad, llamándole
padre y que siempre le estimaria conforme á lo mucho que á su padre y á él habia servido. Los
pueblos comarcanos á Quito enviaron muchos presentes y bastimento para el rey, y mandó que
en el Quito se hiciesen más aposentos y más fuertes de los que habia; y púsose luego por obra,
y fueron hechos los que los nuestros hallaron cuando aquella tierra ganaron.

Unos de los orejones afirman, que Guayna Capac desde el Quito volvió al Cuzco por Los Llanos
hasta Pachacama, y otros que no, pues quedó en el Quito hasta que murió. En esto, inquerido
lo que es más cierto, lo porné conforme á como lo oí á algunos principales que se hallaron
por sus personas con él en esta guerra; que dicen, que estando en el Quito, le vinieron de
muchas partes embajadores á congratularse con él en nombre de sus tierras; que teniendo, y
habiendo tomado [de] seguro y por muy pacífico [modo] á las provincias de la serranía, pensó
que sería bien hacer jornada á las provincias de Puerto Viejo y á lo que llamamos Guayaquil,
y á los Yuncas, y tomando su consejo con sus capitanes y principales, aprobaron su pensamiento
y aconsejaron que lo pusiera por obra. Quedaron en el Quito muchas de sus gentes; con la que
convino salió, y entró por aquellas tierras, en donde tuvo con algunos moradores dellas algunas
refriegas; pero, al fin, unos y otros quedaron en su servicio y puestos en ellas gobernadores
y mitimaes.

La Puná tenia recia guerra con Túmbez, y el Inca habia mandado cesar las contiendas y que le
recebiesen en la Puná, lo cual Tumbalá sintió mucho, porque era Señor della; mas, no se atrevió
á ponerse contra el Inca, ántes lo recebió y hizo presentes con fingida paz; porque, como salió,
procurándolo con los naturales de la tierra firme, trataron de matar muchos orejones con sus
capitanes que con unas balsas iban á salir á un rio para tomar la tierra firme; mas Guayna
Capac lo supo y sobre ello hizo lo que yo tengo escripto en la Primera parte en el capítulo
LIII; y hecho grand castigo, y mandando hacer la calzada, ó paso fuerte, que llaman de Guayna
Capac[203], volvió y paró en Túmbez, donde estaban hechos edificios y templo del sol; y vinieron
de las comarcas á le hacer reverencia con mucha humildad. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10629</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>60550</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21177</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Have not stopped some
confusion among the Incas mesmos, because some children of Tupac Inca, have occurred in other
Coya women, wanted to pretend to be [191] the kingship, but the people who Vian was with Huayna
Capac, not consent, but interfered with the punishment that was done. Finish fasting, Huayna
Capac went with tassel very gallant and dressed, and made the cirimonias used by their past, to
which the name of king wore, and so loud voices they said [192]: Inca Huayna Capac Zapalla tucuillacta
Uya, which means, "Huayna Capac only is king Øyan unto him all peoples. "

Huayna Capac was, as they say many Indians saw him and knew of no very great body but bent and well
done, good and very serious face, a few words, many facts was righteous and punished without
restraint. I wanted to be as feared, that night I dreamed of Indians. Ate as they use, and so
lived cycle of women, if you can tell, hear to those who spoke well, and believed very light:
long deprived him of flatterers and flattering, that among them there were plenty, and today
there is no longer, and gave ear to lies, was the reason that many died without guilt. For
the young men who slept meat tempted to their wives or concubines, or with which they were in
the temple of the sun, then sent them to kill to them, and to punish them equally. For those
who punished him by riots and mutinies, deprived of estates, giving them to others, from other
causes, was punishment .-- Many people only desto conceal his father, especially the women, that
when he took one with them, young men said they were .-- His mother of Huayna Capac, leading
lady, wife and sister who was Inca Tupac Yupanqui, called Mama Ocllo say that was of great prudence,
and warned her son that she saw many things to do to Tupac Inca, and loved him so much that
he begged not to go to Quito and to Chile, until she was dead, and so, do you have that pleasure
and obey his command, was at Cuzco without leave until she died and was buried with grand pomp,
getting in his grave many treasures and fine clothes and their wives and servants. The treasures
of the Incas more deaths and estates, which called Chaco, everything was entirely from the first, and
none dared to spend and do not touch because they did not have wars between and needs the money
hobiese of remedy, for where we believe there are great treasures in the bowels of the earth
lost, and so will be forever, if perchance, one, building or doing something else, do not bump
into something much there.

CAP. LXII .-- How Huayna Capac left Cuzco and what he did.

Huayna Capac had ordered Paresce before him to the chief lords of natural provinces, and while
his court full of them, he married his sister Chimbo Ocllo and therefore were big parties,
leaving the crying for the death of Tupac Inca were done. And finished, he ordered him to go
aside up to fifty thousand men of war with whom I wanted to go together to visit the provinces of
his kingdom. As commanded, stood by the work, and left Cuzco with more pomp and authority than
his father, for the litter would be so rich, to the assertions of those who carried the king
on his shoulders, had not price of the precious stones so large and many who were in them, without
the gold that Heran made. And it was through the provinces of Xaquixaguana and Andaguaylas, and associates
of the Soras and Lucanas [193] where embassies sent to many parts of the plains and mountains,
and was answered Dell and others, with great presents and offerings.

He returned from those places to Cuzco, where he was understood to make big sacrifices the sun
and those who had more gods, which were favorable to the day I wanted do, and gave great gifts
to the idols of the buried treasures, and knew of the liars, by the said of demons, or because
they invented it, it had to happen prosperously in days I wanted to do, and would return to
Cuzco with great honor and profit.

This finish in many parts of people came with their guns and captains, by his order, and housed in the
city were provided.

In the building of the fortress was understood, while the styling for this day none reported. In
the plaza of Cuzco was the grand chain of gold, and there was great dancing and drinking; and,
next to the stone of the war, were named captains and bossy, as his custom; and ordering, Huayna
Capac had a parliament, well ordered and said with vehement words, on it were loyal and those
who were with him, as those who remained. Responded that of service not be leaving, which
gave the loo and I hope to make large grants. And being rigged for the day what was needed,
left Cuzco with everyone of war who had gathered, and a big road, so proud as today Paresce,
all here because of what we see and walk by him, walked towards the Collao, showing the provinces
have passed in just the great services rendered him, for they say that It said that the Incas
everything they owe. Understood to know what gave him tribute, and possibility of the province
collected many women, the most beautiful that could be found; Dellas
took for himself, and others gave to his captains and private, the
others were placed on the temple of the sun and stored there.

Entering the Collao, brought him realize that he had large herds of cattle, and how many loads
of fine wool mill were taking a year to those that made the clothes for your home and service.
On the island of Titicaca came in and ordered great sacrifices. In Chuquiabo [194], ordered Indians
were shelves with their suppliers to take gold metal with the order and regiment has been eScript.
Going forward, he ordered the Charcas and other nations to the Chichas bring forth out large
amount of silver pastes, which are taken to Cuzco on your own, without nothing missing; transport
some mitimaes of a party to another, although there were days that were accommodated; ordered
that all work and no loose, because they said the land where there were lazy, did not think anything
but how to find scandals and corrupt honesty women. He went, ordered to build inns and places,
giving his hand the trace; terms distributed to many provinces and known limit, so that, for
aventajallo not should come to blows. His warriors, though much, was so adjusted, that did not come
out the real one step, as they went, the natives provided what is necessary so dutifully, that
was what was left to what was spent. In some places built bathing and other reserves, and the
deserts were great houses. Inca quel everywhere wrong, he had done such things, it is admiration
count.

When they wandered punished without missing ignore anything and pander to those who served
him well.

Sort these things and went from the provinces subjective agora to the Villa de la Plata, and at Tucuman
[195] sent people to war captains to the Chiriguanos, but do not was good, because turned and fled.
Moreover, towards the South Sea, sent more people other captains, to that dominated the valleys
and villages of all his father could not conquer. He was walking with all his people towards Chile,
putting an end to tame, he went, people he had.

He spent much work for the wilds and the snow was a lot of them fell; awnings had to be guarescer
and many yanaconas and women of service. For all these snow was becoming the way, or was done,
and very clean, and posts made by him.

Alleg to what they called Chile, where he spent more than a year in restraining those understanding
nations and entering them in every way, sent to save him the amount stated in ingots gold,
and the mitimaes were laid, and transported many of those people
of Chile some parts in others.

He did, in some places, strong and close to its use, calling pucaraes, for the war that some had.
He walked the earth more than his father, until said he had seen the end of it, and sent to memory
in many places so that in the future understand his greatness, and ways of grown men [196].

Placed
on the reason for Chile, and done what was agreed, put her delegates
and governors, and sent I always notice in the courthouse of Cuzco
what happened in that province.

Encargóles that hiciesen justice and not agree to riot or not to kill clutter free movers give
life to none.

He returned to Cuzco, where he was honorably received any of the city and the temple priests of
Curicancha gave many blessings, and he delighted the people with big festivals made. And nacíanle
many children, who kept their mothers, among whom was born Atahuallpa
second the opinion of all the Indians of Cuzco, who claim to be so,
and his mother was called Tuta Palla, Quillacas natural, while others
claim to be the lineage of the Orencuzcos, and always since he grew
up, went Atahuallpa with his father, and was older than Huascar.

As Huayna Capac hobiese loose a few months in Cuzco, and he coupled hobiesen the priests of the
temples of the oracles and soothsayers, ordered to make sacrifices, and offering of capacocha
was very big and rich, and became well filled with gold of the mockers sorcerers. Each one
gave answer as parescia them that the king would be more happy. Which with other things past,
Huayna Capac ordered it to be understood to make a path real, bigger and wider than where it
was his father, who came to Quito, where he had intended to go, and that the regular rooms
and deposits the posts from switching to it. To that all this land was known to be his will,
left the post to advise and apricots were then sent to meet him, and made a most magnificent
way and seeing that in the world, and longer, because it came out of Cuzco and associates
of Quito and was coupled with I was going to Chile. Like him, I think that since no memory of
people, has not been read from such grandeur as was this road, made by deep valleys and high
mountains, by forests of snow, quagmires of water and live rock and beside raging rivers, for
these parts was flat and paved, well out on the slopes, through the mountains discarded, on the
rocks undermined by the rivers beside the walls, between snow with steps and landings, for all
parts clean, sweeping debris, filled with apartments, deposits of treasures, temples the sun,
he had coaching in this way. Oh! What is true greatness of Alexander, or any of the powerful kings
who sent the world that such a way did, or invent the proveimiento that he had? There was
no road that the Romans did, that passes Spain, nor the others who read, so that with this being
compared. And more recently made himself up time than you can imagine, for the Incas, it took
them to send more than their put people in for work.

General appeal made himself in all the provinces of his kingdom, and came from all over many people,
and filled the fields, and after making drunken banquets and general and put in order the things of
the city, went della Huayna Capac iscaypachaguaranga runes meaning, with "two hundred thousand
men of war," without the yanaconas and women of service had not count
the number of reach.

Mill was carrying two women and left in Cuzco more than four miles.

Had provided the delegates and governors who attended at the heads of provinces, that all parties
to come [with] supplies and weapons, and everything else that is always collected and saved for
when to war, and so all large buildings hincheron and deposits of all this, so that four to four
leagues, the day was understood that they had to find proveimiento for this whole crowd, without
missing, but on more than what they spent and women, and boys and men who served personally
what I was commanded, and carrying the parts of the Inca and the
baggage of the warriors of an inn to another, where was the proveimiento
than in the past.

As Huayna Capac come out on the road by his command had been commanded to do, of Cuzco, walked
until he came to the Vilcas, where stood a few days in the chambers that had been stuck with
his father, and rejoiced to see the sun temple was finished and left quantity of gold and silver
jewelry pastas and glasses, ordered that great care had proveimiento of the virgins and priests.
Sobióse to pray in a gallant roof and cousin that this had been done,
sacrificed, according to his blindness, which used, and killed many
animals and birds, with some children and men, to appease their gods.

This done, he left the place with his people the king, and did not stop until Xauxa Valley, where
there was some controversy and division over the limits and fields of the valley between them
were lords of it thou. Understood as Huayna Capac, after having made sacrifices, as in Vilcas,
sent along the lords Alaya, Cucichuca, Guacaropa [197] and between them fairly divided the fields
the way you are today. At Yauyos sent embassies, the same made to the Yuncas, and to Bonbon
sent some gifts to the natural lords of the land; because, as they had strength in the lake,
swimming parties, speaking loosely, and rigor would not talk with them to see yours. Xauxa lords
made him great services, and some of the captains and warriors were accompanying him, and
walked up Bonbon, where it stopped short, because he wanted to go to Cajamarca, more rigged
place to rest and provinces neighboring towns with large and very
high.

And by the way people always came to major embassies and present.

As he arrived at Cajamarca, stopped a few days to rest from the road, and commanded that his
people War will host the round of that land, and eat what they collected in the tanks was,
and with the people who entered the Guancachupachos paresció, and had a fierce war, because
they were not quite there in the natural grace of his father and compliance, but, both could,
raided and subjugated it, putting governors and captains, and choosing the natural gentlemen,
to send in the land, the ones they paresció, for them, old masters knew not to others which, being
more powerful, rising and acaudillaban to make war, and gave peace when they wanted. Found in Chachapoyas
Huayna Capac high resistance, so much so that twice thwarted fleeing back to the strong that they
made their defense, and favors that came before turning on Chachapoyanos and so broke, they
asked for peace, stopping the war on their part. God conditions helpful to the Inca, who sent
many of them to pass that he himself resided in Cuzco, whose descendants now live in the same city
took many women, because they are beautiful and graceful and very white; put garrisons of soldiers
mitimaes ordinary men, to be by border, left in the main governor of the region, provided what
more they used; punished to many leading, because they gave war, which indeed is to Cajamarca
again, where he continued his journey, and put in order Caxas provinces, Ayahuacas, Guancabanba [198]
and others that confine them.

Public is among many natives of these parts that Huayna Capac went by land Bracamoros call,
and turned to escape the fury of men who dwell therein; the leaded whom had gathered to defend
and who the angry to be, and, without Cuzco apricots, consider this the lord of Chincha, and
some major and Collao Xauxa. And they say all that going Huayna Capac finishing settle those lands
where his father passed and he had subdued, he knew how in many men and had Bracamoros women
who had fertile land, and deep inside the earth had a pond and many rivers, full of large populations.
Covetous of discovering and willing ladies, taking paresció the people who, with little baggage,
he had to walk away, leaving the field stay by real drums, and entrusted to the captain general.
Entering the earth, were opening [199] Asaz the road with work, because after the snow-capped mountains
of the promontories, gave in the mountains of the Andes and found raging rivers to go, and
fell from the sky many waters. All was not party to the Inca cease to arrive at where the natives
of many parts positions were waiting for her strong will, where he showed his nakedness, afeándole
His coming, and started the war each other, and many of the barbarians were combined, the most bring
naked without clothes, to what was stated, that the Inca were determined to withdraw, and did
without gaining anything in that land. And the natives who felt it gave him such a hurry that
in stride, sometimes making the face, sending sometimes present, descabulló them and set back
fleeing to his kingdom, saying it was to avenge the pintail; which he said, because Some wore the
maures [200] long they hung down over her legs.

From these lands, which had already renovated, also says that people sent captains which is sufficient,
for them to see the coast of the sea that had to the North, and to endeavor to his service to attract
the natives of Guayaquil and Puerto Viejo, and that they walked by those regions, where war had
some battles, and in some cases were winners, and others not at all, and so he walked up Collique
where people encountered who were naked and ate human flesh, and had the habits that have and
use today the neighboring towns of San Juan river, from where they turned, not wanting to move
on, to give notice to their king, who with all his men had arrived at the Cañar; whither he
was thankful in the extreme, they say birth [201] there, and you have made great buildings and
drums, and much provision, and sent ambassadors to him should come and see the regions, and many more
will come ambassadors with presents.

I have understood that, for some noise that tried to certain towns in the region of Cuzco, I felt
so much that, after having removed the heads to the principal, expressly commanded the Indians in
those parts of the stones brought from Cuzco the amount stated, to do in some quarters Tomebamba
much delicacy, which he brought to the ropes, and His commandment was fulfilled. And he said
many times Huayna Capac, the people of these kingdoms, for keeping him well subdued, proper,
when they had to do or to understand them a mountain pass from one place to another and even from
Cuzco carry stones and slabs sent to buildings of Quito, which today are in buildings that put.

Huayna
Capac Tomebamba came and went through the Puru, and rested a few
days in Riobamba, and Mocha and The Tacunga rested his men and had
much good to drink the concoction that was rigged and collected them
everywhere.

Here was greeted and visited many lords and masters of the region, and apricots sent was that
of his lineage [202] to which they were along the coast of Los Llanos and the mountains to take
account of quiposcamayos, which are its accountants, in what was in the tanks, and to which
they knew how they had with the natives the nickel had made governor, and if they were well supplied
with the temples of the sun and guacas oracles and that was in every place, and sent messengers
to Cuzco in the ordering the things you sent and left everything to fulfill his will. And there
was no day that does not e came, not one or a few, but many, of Cuzco, the Collao, Chile and
all his kingdom.

De La Tacunga walked until he go to Quito, where he was received,
in his own way and style, with big parties, and gave the governor
of his father's treasures, which were many, with fine clothes and
other things that were under his charge, and honróle with words, praising
his loyalty, calling father and always according to estimate how much
his father and he had served.

The Quito to neighboring towns sent many presents and provisions for the king, and ordered
in Quito be made more and more strong quarters that had, and then stood by work and there were
those who found when the land our won.

Some of the dried state, which Huayna Capac returned from Quito to Cuzco by Los Llanos to Pachacamac,
and others not, it was in Quito to death. In this, inquerido What is more certain, according to
the porn as I heard, some principal that is found for his people
with him in this war, they say, that while in Quito, we came from
many parts ambassadors to congratulate him on behalf of their lands,
that have, and having taken [the] very safe and peaceful [so] to the
provinces of the mountains, he thought it would be okay to do day
to the provinces of Puerto Viejo and Guayaquil to what we call, and
to the Yuncas, and taking counsel with his captains and main, approved
of his thought and advised to put him to work.

Quito were in many of its people, with which agreed and departed, and went through those lands,
where some residents had with some Dellas skirmishes, but in the end, both groups were in his
service and made them Governors and mitimaes.

Puna had a fierce war with Túmbez, and the Inca had ordered an end to the strife and to receive
him in the Puna, which Tumbalá felt much, because he was lord of it, but he dared not to stand
against the Inca, before it was engaged or present with false peace, because, as it came, procuring
the land natural, tried to kill many apricots with with a raft captains were going to go to a
river to take the mainland, but Huayna Capac it knew and what I have done in Part eScript chapter
LIII, and great wrath, and sending to the road, or safe passage, that is called Huayna Capac [203],
turned and stopped at Tumbes, where buildings were made of the sun temple and they came the counties
to do him reverence with humility.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>