<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08503</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>445378</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20870</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Finalmente, á los once dias de marcha se hace alto sobre la ribera izquierda, y echando pié
á tierra se caminan tres leguas por entre el bosque mas hermoso del mundo, siguiendo el rumbo
de un estrecho sendero que conduce al pueblecillo de la Ascension de Isiboro, perteneciente
al pais de los Yuracarees.

Camino de Yuracáres á Moxos, por el rio Securi.

Cuando en el año de 1832 me propuse abrir una nueva via de comunicacion entre el pais de los
Yuracarees y la provincia de Moxos, emprendí mi viage por el siguiente itenerario. Bajé primeramente
al rio Moleto, donde me embarqué en una canoa que habia yo mandado construir para el efecto.
Las aguas de este rio estaban muy bajas, y á cada paso tropezábamos ademas con las cachuelas
de que está lleno; por cuya razon empleamos tres dias para llegar á la confluencia del rio
Icho que solo dista tres leguas. Metidos casi siempre en el agua para arrastrar la canoa y
enteramente descalzos, durante el dia nos veiamos atormentados por las picaduras ponzoñosas
de los jejenes á los que reemplazaban por la noche enjambres de mosquitos mas encarnizados
todavía. Mis compañeros de viage se quejaban con mucha razon, y solamente el ejemplo de mi
resignacion y mi constante cooperacion á sus trabajos podian darles el ánimo suficiente para
seguir adelante. En este intervalo, el rio Moleto recibe por la parte de oriente las aguas
del Ipuchi, y por la de occidente las de los rios Solotosama y Eñesama[1], que corren por entre
colinas bajas, mas prominentes hácia el oeste. Estas colinas no son otra cosa que las últimas
faldas de la Cordillera.

En la confluencia de los dos rios que forman el rio Securi, las aguas se ensanchan y su hondura
es mayor; sin embargo, para poder navegar en grandes barcas, es menester que sean estas de
poco fondo. Encontramos en este punto algunos indios ocupados en la pesca, y que se determinaron
á seguirnos: bien pronto aconsejándonos hacer alto, nos mostraron detras de unas zarzales de
la ribera izquierda un sendero que no hubiéramos podido descubrir desde el rio. Encaminándonos
por él, encontramos en medio de un bosque, á un cuarto de legua de distancia, unas cuantas
casas que tenian un piso alto, construccion propia para el lugar que me pareció muy húmedo.
Con la esperanza de conseguir algunos plátanos y raices de mandioca, únicas provisiones que
se encuentran en aquellos lugares salvages, me instalé desde luego en una de esas casas, recientemente
abandonadas por sus habitantes, quienes se habian transferido diez leguas al oeste, huyendo
de una enfermedad que segun ellos existia en el lugarejo. Al siguiente dia, á poco mas de las
once, viendo que aun no volvian los comisionados que habian salido en busca de víveres, resolví
regresar al rio para embarcarme y proseguir mi viage; pero no tardaron mis tres indios en llegar
tras de mi con algunas provisiones. Inmediatamente nos pusimos en marcha, dejando el pais de
los Yuracarees y vogando resueltamente hácia regiones desconocidas.

En el espacio de una legua tuvimos que salvar algunos encalladeros, y despues de haber dejado
atras un islote guarnecido de árboles, encontramos el rio ya franco y totalmente desembarazado.
Entónces llegué á conocer que seria muy fácil la navegacion de esta corriente, aun para las
embarcaciones de vapor. Este punto, cuyos terrenos son los mas feraces que pudieran encontrarse,
me ha parecido muy conveniente para el establecimiento de un puerto cuando lleguen á entablerse
las comunicaciones comerciales con la provincia de Moxos. El rio es abundantísimo en pescados:
cada vez que echábamos nuestros anzuelos, sin pérdida de tiempo sacábamos de á pares enormes
pescados, entre los que se distinguian principalmente los pertenecientes á la familia de los
siluroides, y tambien los numerosos pacus, pez de los mas esquisitos de América[1]. Al dia
siguiente, despues de haber evitado algunos hacinamientos de troncos que obstruian el paso
en algunos parages, el rio fué ensanchándose poco á poco, y su profundidad llegó á ser mayor:
los jejenes desaparecieron, las palmas viñas eran mas raras, hasta que fueron reemplazadas
por las palmas motacúes. Cada banco de arena se veia cubierto de rayadores, de gaviotas y de
caprimulgus, que anidan en las playas, depositando simplemente sus huevos sobre la arena.

Las jornadas se sucedian lentamente por las frecuentes paradas que hacian mis remeros, los
que á pesar del ascendiente que yo habia llegado á tomar sobre ellos, saltaban muchas veces
á tierra, sin querer obedecerme, para perseguir por entre los bosques, ya las bandadas de pavas
del monte, ya los javalíes, ya una tropa de grandes marimonos, que agenos de conocer el daño
parecian salir á nuestro encuentro brincando alegremente por sobre los árboles, hasta que una
tardía y dolorosa esperiencia les enseñaba á desconfiar del hombre.

Entretanto, las riberas se veian constantemente animadas por toda especie de animales selváticos,
que salian de los bosques á retozar sobre la playa ó sobre los árboles de los ribazos. Muy
á menudo un gran-bestia, sorprendido de improviso con nuestra llegada, se ponia precipitadamente
en fuga; otras veces un carpincho, deslizándose con presteza de la barranca, se escondia en
el agua; mas léjos, un ciervo dormido, despertando de pronto, echaba á correr por entre el
bosque volviendo de tiempo en tiempo la cabeza para examinarnos de nuevo. De vez en cuando
oiamos tambien á la distancia el bramido del tigre.

Al cabo de algunas jornadas de marcha por la corriente profunda, pero poco rápida del rio Securi,
llegamos á la confluencia del rio que los Yuracarees llaman Yaniyuta, el cual, bajando del
este, viene á dar mas ensanche al Securi. La abundancia de víveres que habia reinado hasta
entónces, gracias á la buena pesca y á la caza, nos fué abandonando poco á poco; pues la selva
iba siendo cada vez mas desierta, y por otra parte, la pólvora que yo llevaba alterada sin
duda por la humedad, se habia puesto inservible; por manera que bien pronto la falta de caza
nos redujo al pescado sin sal por todo alimento, y mas tarde á unas pocas espigas de maiz que
nos proporcionaron los Yuracarees, y á los palmitos que pudieron derribar mis indios.

Lo largo del camino y la monotonía de esta navegacion empezaban ya á desalentarme cuando el
8 de agosto, á eso de las once de la mañana, llegamos por fin á la confluencia de un rio que
baja del oeste, y es mucho mas considerable que el Securi. Los Yuracarees le dan el nombre
de Isiboro, y segun el decir de los que me acompañaban, esta caudalosa corriente, formada de
los rios Isiboro, Samucebeté y Chipiriri, recibe todas las aguas del vertiente oriental de
la cadena del Iterama ó del Paracti, comprendidas entre el rio San-Mateo, y el rio Yaniyuta,
por delante del cual habiamos pasado tres dias ántes. Viendo pues que el rio Securi tomba ya
un ensanche igual al que habia yo notado en el punto de su confluencia con el Mamoré, recobré
el ánimo, esperando llegar bien pronto á encontrarme con este rio.

Al siguiente dia se deslizaba tranquilamente nuestra canoa por entre islas guarnecidas de bosques,
cuando se presentó derrepente, posada sobre un árbol del ribazo, la mas hermosa, la mas corpulenta,
la mas noble de todas las aves de rapiña, una verdadera harpía[1], que levantaba su bello copete,
mirándonos detenidamente sin parecer inquietarse de nuestra presencia. No pudiendo hacer uso
de mi escopeta por falta de buena pólvora, dejé á la destreza de mis Yuracarees, que saltaron
inmediatamente á tierra, la gloria de capturar aquel soberbio animal. Uno de ellos le asertó
desde luego un flechazo: á pesar de este golpe, echóse á volar el pájaro; pero embarazado con
la flecha que llevaba clavada, (la cual tenia como dos varas de largo) cayó bien pronto dentro
del bosque á donde la siguieron mis cazadores. Me regocijaba ya con la idea de poder llevar
á Francia esta rara presa, cuando vi regresar á mis indios trayendo el pájaro con la cola y
las alas enteramente desplumadas, y el cuerpo casi pelado. Los Yuracarees estiman en mucho
las plumas de este pájaro; ya para empenar sus flechas, ya para adornarse en los dias de gala[2];
así es que sin perder tiempo se habian apoderado de ellas, dejando burladas mis esperanzas.
Despues de haberlos reñido asperamente por esta conducta, ordené que me tragesen al animal,
que creiamos muerto; y sentado en la canoa lo coloqué delante de mí. Aturdido solamente por
los golpes que habia recibido en la cabeza, volvió en sí poco á poco sin que nos apercibiésemos
de ello, y cuando yo ménos lo pensaba, se arrojó sobre mí, haciéndome de un solo golpe ocho
heridas con sus enormes garras, una de las cuales, de mas de tres pulgadas de largo, me atravesó
el brazo de parte á parte, entre el cubitus y el radius, desgarrándome uno de los tendones.
A los gritos que dí, acudieron mis compañeros de viage, y lograron con muchísimo trabajo quitarme
de encima al furioso animal. Bañado en sangre y sin medicamentos para curar mis heridas, mi
estado no dejaba de ser peligroso. Entretanto, continuamente espuesto al calor del dia ó á
la nociva humedad de la noche, la fiebre se apoderó bien pronto de mí. Por otra parte el temor
de que me atacase un pasmo, y la duda de si quedaria estropeado por causa de la adherencia
de la piel al tendon, aumentaban sobremanera mis sufrimientos. Gracias á la Providencia el
solo mal positivo que me resultó de todo esto, fué la imposibilidad de servirme de mi brazo
durante algun tiempo.

En la noche de ese mismo dia llegamos á la confluencia del rio Sinuta, último tributario occidental
del Securi. Saliendo de este punto, hicimos todavía dos jornadas mas, y mis inquietudes ya
tocaban á su colmo, cuando se presentó por fin el rio Mamoré, desplegando á nuestra vista toda
su grandeza. Inmediatamente dí al olvido mis padecimientos, pues me encontraba en Moxos, blanco
de mis afanes, y al dia siguiente, despues de haber remado toda la noche vogando rio abajo,
desembarcamos en Trinidad, capital de la provincia.

Habiendo hecho el plano de este itinerario, resultó claramente, como yo lo esperaba, que el
nuevo tránsito practicado por mí era mucho mas corto, y no tan peligroso como el de Palta-Cueva.

Camino de Moxos á Santa-Cruz de la Sierra por el rio Grande y el rio Piray.

Para encaminarse de Loreto, último punto habitado de la provincia de Moxos, hácia Santa-Cruz
de la Sierra, es necesario hacer primero, lo mismo que para ir á Cochabamba, un tránsito de
tres dias hasta la confluencia de los rios Sara y Mamoré. Se sigue luego por el primero de
estos rios, que no es otro que el rio Grande cuyo numbre cambia momentáneamente en la confluencia
del rio Piray hasta el punto de su reunion con el Mamoré. Sus aguas rogizas forman un contraste
con las cristalinas de este último: por lo demas, las riberas del rio Sara presentan, aunque
con ménos terrenos bajos, absolutamente el mismo aspecto; pues se hallan cubiertas de igual
modo que las del Mamoré, de bosques muy variados por la diversidad de árboles de que se componen,
y entre los que sobresalen las palmas motacúes. Solo en la estacion de seca se ven á descubierto
los altos ribazos de esta corriente; entretanto, la línea del nivel á que alcanzan las inundaciones,
queda siempre marcada sobre los troncos de los árboles inmediatos, como á una vara de altura
desde su pié.

Al fin de la quinta jornada, se presenta la confluencia del riachuelo, llamado Maravo, que
baja por la izquierda, de las llanuras inundadas. En la mañana de la sesta jornada se pasa
la confluencia del rio Ibabo, cuyas fuentes se encuentran en Tasajos, en Pampa-Grande y en
Vilca, puntos de las montañas de la provincia de Valle-Grande. Esta corriente formada de los
rios Surutú y Yapacani, toma el nombre de Ibabo cuando baja á serpentear por la llanura, siendo
navegable hasta el pié de las montañas. Al cabo de una jornada de navegacion por el rio Sara,
se llega á la confluencia del rio Piray. En tiempo de los Jesuitas se subia por el rio Sara
ó rio Grande hasta el lugarejo de Payla, situado al este de Santa-Cruz; pero este camino, que
obligaba á los viageros á dar una vuelta considerable, siendo al mismo tiempo no poco peligroso
en tiempo de crecientes por causa de las avenidas que ocultan enteramente el álveo del rio,
ha sido abandonado, harán como cincuenta años, para dirigirse mas bien por el Piray, el cual,
aunque mucho mas angosto que el rio Grande, es ménos propenso á las crecientes devastadoras;
razon por la que se le prefiere aun á pesar de los saltos que suele tener en tiempo de seca.
Es probable que cuando las endebles canoas sean reemplazadas por barcos de vapor, se volverá
á tomar el rio Grande, abandonando el Piray, ménos conviente para la navegacion de grandes
embarcaciones.

En los dias séptimo y octavo del viage se sube el Piray, con muchísimo trabajo si la estacion
es de seca: el álveo de este rio, bastante profundo desde luego, se halla de trecho en trecho
obstruido por árboles que las corrientes amontonan, ó por espigones permanentes en el fondo
del rio, contra los que tropiezan á menudo las canoas; lo que ocasiona no pocos desastres.
Sobre el espacio que se recorre en estas dos jornadas se ven ademas algunos puentes construidos
por los salvages Sirionos[1], que moran en las selvas circunvecinas, sin jamas inquietar á
los naturales de Moxos. Hasta llegar á la undécima jornada se tienen que salvar sucesivamente
muchas cachuelas, formadas por una especie de saltos de arcilla amarilleja endurecida; esto
obliga á perder un tiempo considerable por la necesidad que hay de descargar las canoas, para
hacerlas subir por en medio de la corriente, tirándolas con sogas. Al ejecutar esta maniobra,
algunos de los indios que tienen precision de caminar por entre el agua, suelen ser gravemente
heridos por el punzante aguijon de las rayas armadas[2]. Tienen estos pescados en la cola,
como las pastinacas de las costas marítimas de Francia, una lanceta de cuatro pulgadas, muy
filosa, y guarnecida de dientes retorcidos para adentro con los que desgarran las carnes, causando
dolores agudísimos y muchas veces ataques de tétano: por desgracia estos accidentes son muy
comunes, sobre todo en las cabeceras de los rios. En tiempo de crecientes, cinco ó seis varas
de agua cubren estos puntos salientes, y se pasa entónces por encima de ellos sin que se les
eche de ver.

A la duodécima jornada, los bosques de las riberas del Piray cesan de pronto, y son reemplazados
por unos pantanos á donde vienen á perderse dos riachuelos, el de Palacios y el Palometas,
que nacen en la llanura de Santa-Cruz de la Sierra. Estos pantanos ó bañados anuncian que ya
no dista mucho el término del viage.

Al décimocuarto dia se pasan de seguida, una tras otra, cuatro cachuelas, no léjos de las cuales
se presenta el puerto situado sobre la ribera izquierda, y que no tiene mas habitacion que
un espacioso rancho techado con hojas de palma: desde este puerto, separado del lugarejo de
los Cuatro-Ojos por un hondo pantano que tiene como una legua de largo, hay que andar todavía
treinta leguas para llegar á Santa-Cruz de la Sierra. En la estacion lluviosa se emplean solamente
diez dias para hacer este camino, subiendo por el Piray; y seis dias, yendo rio abajo desde
Cuatro-Ojos hasta Loreto.

POBLACION.

Si comparativamente á lo que dije en la primera época de la historia de Moxos ántes de la llegada
de los Españoles, trato de saber en lo que han venido á parar las naciones primitivas de aquellas
comarcas, hallaré los resultados siguientes.

La nacion de los Moxos ocupa todavía los lugares que ántes habitaba, con la sola diferencia
de encontrarse reunidos en las misiones de la provincia de la manera que sigue.

Muchojeones del Cármen.                         230

Baures del Cármen de Moxos.           362
  "    de Concepcion de Moxos.      3,126
  "    de San-Joaquin de Moxos.       690
  "    todavía salvages.            1,000
                                   ------
                                              5,178

Moxos de Loreto de Moxos.           2,145
  "   de Trinidad.                  2,604
  "   de San Xavier.                1,515
  "   de San Ignacio.               1,948
                                   ------
                                              8,212
                                             ------
Total.                                       13,620

Se ve pues por esta esposicion que si la cuasi totalidad de los Moxos se halla sometida al
cristianismo, todavía existen algunos en el estado salvage: estos (de lo cuales un pequeño
número perteneció á las misiones, en tiempo de los Jesuitas) viven divididos en familias establecidas
no léjos del rio Guaporé, y al este de las misiones de Concepcion y del Cármen, sin comunicarse
jamas con sus compatriotas convertidos. Se ve tambien el número relativo de las diferentes
tribus de los Moxos, Baures y Muchojeones, y puede calcularse la importancia que debe tener,
en el seno de un pais anegado, una nacion cuyos habitantes aun pasan de trece mil, hablando
todos ellos el dialecto moxo.

Acostumbrados á la obediencia, los Moxos tienen un carácter bondadoso, sociable, alegre, y
mas que todo paciente; pero así como están siempre en disposicion de reír por la menor fruslería
cuando se hallan entregados á sí mismos, de igual modo la servidumbre los ha hecho tímidos
y taciturnos en presencia de los superiores.

Estos naturales tienen una aficion particular por el dibujo, la que no deja de estar acompañada
de bastante habilidad: sus pinturas representan animales y plantas regularmente copiadas. Escultores,
torneros , carpinteros, tejedores prácticos, fabrican infinidad de objetos curiosos que se
llevan para vender en algunas ciudades del Perú. Muchos de entre ellos han aprendido el español
y saben escribirlo muy correctamente: en una palabra, la nacion de los Moxos es quizas la mas
susceptible de civilizacion. Entre todos los indios de la provincia, los Moxos son en la actualidad,
no solamente los católicos mas decididos, sino que llevan el fanatismo á tanto, que todos los
años, en la semana santa, se les ve regar las plazas públicas con la sangre que se sacan á
fuerza de azotes. Son igualmente supersticiosos en sumo grado.

La nacion de los Itonamas se encuentra totalmente sometida, y no queda un solo salvage. En
1830 se contaban:

En Magdalena.      2,831 En San-Ramon.      1,984

       Total.      4,815

Estos indios, de cuyo carácter he hablado ya mas de una vez en los capítulos anteriores, conservan
todavía sus inclinaciones y costumbres primitivas, que la religion católica no ha podido desarraigar.
Los tegidos que ellos fabrican son los mejores de la provincia. La lengua itonama está siempre
en uso en ámbas misiones.

La nacion de los Canichanas, enteramente cristiana, forma hoy en dia la mision de San-Pedro.
El número de su poblacion alcanzaba en 1830 á mil novecientos treinta y nueve individuos[1].

Estos naturales han conservado hasta hoy, en el seno mismo de las misiones, muchas de sus antiguas
costumbres, y son todavía el terror de las otras naciones, cuyos campos devastan robándoles
todos sus frutos, sin que se atrevan estas á aventurar una sola queja por el miedo estramado
que les tienen. Los Canichanas son bruscos, y jamas usan de cortesía con los estrangeros. Actualmente
su poblacion es la ménos industriosa de la provincia, y la sola que se alimenta con la carne
del caiman, para cuya caza se vale de mil ardides.

Profesando el catolicismo, no han podido desprenderse de una infinidad de supersticiones de
su condicion salvage: son por otra parte muy malos cristianos. El lenguage de que hacen uso
es el mismo de su estado primitivo.

La nacion de los Movimos ha sido reunida por los Jesuitas en la mision de Santa-Ana: no queda
de ella un solo salvage. Segun el padrón del año de 1830, su poblacion ascendia á mil docientos
treinta y ocho individuos. Estos indios se egercitan en la caza, la pesca, la navegacion y
la agricultura. Su industria, poco mas ó ménos igual á la de los Moxos, aun no ha llegado al
mismo grado de adelanto, á escepcion solamente de los tegidos.

Rastro ninguno queda ya hoy en dia de su religion primitiva; no obstante, suelen manifestar
de vez en cuando que no han olvidado todas las supersticiones de que estaban imbuidos ántes
de su conversion. Su idioma nacional no ha cambiado.

La nacion de los Cayuvavas, convertida totalmente al cristianismo, se halla reunida al presente
en la mision de Exaltacion. En 1830 el total de su poblacion llegaba á dosmil sesenta individuos[1].

Francos y leales los Cayuvavas, se hacen querer de todos los que se relacionan con ellos. En
toda la provincia no hay otros que conozcan la navegacion mejor que estos indios, remeros hábiles
y pilotos los mas esperimentados en el rio Mamoré. Respecto de su industria, en nada se dejan
aventajar por los Moxos, siendo quizas superiores á estos en el ramo de agricultura.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05529</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>353308</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18156</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Finally,
the eleven days of travel is high on the left bank, and throwing foot earth to walk three miles
through the woods more beautiful in the world, following the course a narrow path leading to
the small town of Ascension Isiboro belonging the country of the Yuracares.

Yuracares Road to Moxos, by the river Securi.

When in the year 1832 I decided to open a new way of communication between the country of Yuracares and
Moxos province, began my journey by following ITINERARY. First lower Moleto the river, where
I embarked in a canoe which I had had built for this purpose. The waters of this river were
very low, and stumbled at every step in addition to the rapids it is full, for which reason
we use three days to arrive at the confluence of the rivers Icho far only three leagues. Tucked
almost always in the water to drag the canoe and entirely bare during the day we were tormented
by venomous bites the gnats who were displaced by swarms of mosquitoes at night bitterest
yet. My journey companions complained with good reason, and only the example of my resignation
and my constant cooperation could work to give the mind to forward. In this interval, the river
receives Moleto the eastern waters the Ipuchi, and by those of western rivers and Eñesama
Solotosama [1], which run between low hills, most prominent towards the west. These hills are but
the latest slopes of the Cordillera.

At the confluence of two rivers that form the river Securi, water depth and widen is greater, however,
to navigate in large boats, they need to be they of shallow. We find here some Indians engaged
in fishing, which were determined to watch: soon advising us to stop, they showed us behind some
brambles the left bank of a path that we could not discover from the stream. Encaminándonos
by him, are in the middle of a forest, a quarter of a mile away, a few houses that had a high
floor, building for the place itself seemed very wet. Hoping to get some bananas and cassava
roots, the only provisions that found in uncivilized places, I moved since then into one of
those houses recently abandoned by their inhabitants, who had transferred ten miles to the
west, fleeing a disease that according to them existed in the hamlet. The next day, at little more than
the eleven, seeing that even the commissioners did not return had gone in search of food, I
decided return to the river to embark and continue my journey, but soon my three Indians to reach
after me with some supplies. Immediately we started leaving the country of vogando the Yuracarés
and resolutely towards unknown regions.

In the space of a league we had to save some shoals, and after leaving
trim back a tree island, we found the river and completely open and
unencumbered.

Then I came to know it would be very easy navigation of this current, even for steam vessels.
This point, which are the most fertile land that could be found, I found very helpful for the establishment
of a port to open on arrival commercial communications with the province of Moxos. The river
abounds in fish: increasingly casting our hooks, without losing time in pairs took out huge fish,
among which were distinguished mainly belonging to the family of siluroides, and also the many
pacus, fish of the most exquisite of America [1]. Day Next, after having avoided some piles of
logs blocking the road in some spot, the river was widened gradually, and its depth became greater:
gnats disappeared, the palms vines were more rare, until they were replaced by palms palm fronds.
Each bank of sand covered saw skimmers, gulls and Caprimulgus, which nest on the beaches,
simply by depositing their eggs on the sand.

Slowly the days succeeded each by frequent stops to my rowers, the that in spite of the influence
that I had come to take upon them, often jumping to the ground, not wanting to obey, to chase
through the woods, and flocks of turkeys the mountain, and the boar,
and a troop of large Marimon, who understand the damage Agen our meeting
seemed to go merrily jumping over the trees, until a EXPERIENCE late
and painful taught to distrust the man.

Meanwhile, the banks were constantly encouraged by all sorts of wild animals, that came out of the
woods to frolic on the beach or on the trees of the hillsides. Very Often a large beast, suddenly
surprised with our arrival, he would abruptly in flight, sometimes a capybara, sliding with alacrity
to the gorge, was hiding in the water further, a deer asleep, waking
up early, ran about among the forest from time to time turning his
head to examine it again.

Occasionally also heard at the distance the roar of the tiger.

After several days of walking through the deep stream, but not very fast Securi river, we reached
the confluence of the rivers that Yuracares Yaniyuta call, which came down from the this, is
to give more expansion to Securi. The abundance of food that had reigned until Then, thanks
to the good fishing and hunting, was leaving us little by little, as the forest was becoming
more deserted, and on the other hand, the powder that I had altered
without moisture doubt, had as useless, for so soon after the lack
of game we reduced the salt fish without any food, and later to a
few ears of corn that Yuracares provided us, and to the palms that
could shoot down my Indians.

Along the way, and the monotony of the voyage were beginning to get discouraged when August
8, at about eleven o'clock, we finally arrived at the confluence of a river low in the west, and
is much more significant that the Securi. The Yuracaré give the name of Isiboro, and according
to the saying of those who accompanied me, this mighty stream, consisting of Isiboro rivers,
Chipiriri Samucebeté and receives all the waters of the eastern slope of Iterama chain or the
Paracti, between the river San-Mateo, and the river Yaniyuta, ahead
of which we had spent three days earlier.

Seeing as that the river and tomba Securi an expansion equal to that which I had noticed at
the point of its junction with the Mamore, recovered mood, hoping to arrive soon to meet this
river.

The next day quietly slid our canoe manned by between forest islands, when presented derrepente,
perched on a tree bank, the most beautiful, the most corpulent the most noble of all birds of
prey, a real harpy [1], which raised its beautiful crest, watching closely without seeming anxious
of our presence. Unable to use of my gun for lack of good powder, left to the skill of my Yuracares,
who jumped immediately to the ground, capturing the glory of that
proud animal.

One of them assertion certainly a crush: in spite of this blow, fell at the bird fly, but pregnant
with the arrow had stuck, (which was about two yards long) soon fell into the forest where the follow
my hunter. I rejoiced because the idea of ??being able to carry to France this rare prey, when I
return to my Indians bringing the bird with the tail and wings entirely plucked, and the body
almost bare. The estimated Yuracares much the feathers of this bird, and to pawn his arrows,
and to adorn the gala days [2]; so that no time had taken possession of them, leaving my hopes
mocked. After having fought harshly for this behavior, I ordered the animal Trageser, we thought
dead, and seated in the canoe put it before me. Stunned only he had received blows to the head,
he came to himself, little by little without being apercibiésemos this, and when I least expected
it, he threw himself on me, making me one stroke eight wounds with their huge claws, one of
which, more than three inches long, I went through the arm from side to side, between the
cubitus and radius, rending one tendon. A screaming that I gave, my colleagues went voyage, and succeeded
with great difficulty to take off off the furious animal. Bathed in blood and no medicines
to cure my wounds, my state it was still dangerous. Meanwhile, heat continuously esponse of
the day or at the harmful dampness of the night, the fever took hold of me soon. On the other
hand fear that attacked me a fright, and doubt whether it would be damaged due to adhesion the
skin to the tendon, greatly increased my sufferings. Thanks to the Providence only positive
that I was wrong all this, was the inability to turn my arm for some time.

On the evening of that day we reached the confluence of the river Sinuta, last western tributary the
Securi. Leaving this point, we still have two more days, and my concerns and played at its
height, when finally presented Mamore river, unfolding before our eyes all his greatness.
Immediately I gave to forget my sufferings, for I was in Moxos, white of my labors, and the next
day, after having rowed all night vogando downstream, landed in Trinidad, capital of the province.

Having
made the plane on this route, was clearly, as I expected, the new transit practiced by me
was much shorter, and not as dangerous as the Avocado-Cave.

Moxos Road to Santa Cruz de la Sierra on the Rio Grande and the Rio Piray.

To aim of Loreto, last inhabited point Moxos province, towards Santa-Cruz de la Sierra, you need
to do first, like to go to Cochabamba, a transit three days until the confluence of the rivers
Sara and Mamore. It follows then by the first these rivers, which is none other than the Rio
Grande which numbres change momentarily at the confluence Piray River
to the point of their reunion with the Mamore.

Its waters are a contrast rogizas with the crystal of the latter: at rest, the banks of the
river will be present, although lowlands with less, quite the same
light; for they are covered as so that the Mamore Forest varied by
the diversity of trees that are composed and among which the palms
palm fronds.

Only in the dry season are found to high steep banks of this stream,
meanwhile, the line reached the level to which flood is always marked
on the trunks of the trees near, like unto a rod height from his foot.

At the end of the fifth day, shows the confluence of the creek, called Maraven, which down
the left from the flood plain. On the morning of the sixth day passed the confluence of the river
Ibaba sources are found in beef, in Pampa Grande and Vilches, points to the mountains of the province
of Valle Grande. This current consists of Yapacani Surutú rivers and takes the name of Ibaba
when winding down to the plain, being navigable to the foot of the mountains. After a day of
sailing on the river Sara you get to the confluence of the river Piray. In time the Jesuits were
raised by the river Sara or Rio Grande to the hamlet of payload, located east of Santa Cruz, but
this path, forcing the travelers to give a considerable return, while being not a little dangerous increasing
time because of the floods that completely hide the riverbed of the river, has been abandoned,
will make about fifty years to go but well for the Piray which, but
much more narrow than the Rio Grande, is less prone to devastating
floods; reason I prefer it even in spite of the leaps that often take
time to dry.

It is likely that when the flimsy canoes are replaced by steamships, will become to take the
Rio Grande, leaving the Piray, less convient for navigation of large vessels.

In the seventh and eighth days of the journey is the Piray up with a lot of work if the station
is dry, the riverbed of the river, deep enough, of course, is at intervals obstructed by trees
that crowd flows, or by standing at the bottom piers the river, against the often encountered
canoes causing not a few disasters. On the space that is covered in these two days are also
some bridges built by the savages Sirionos [1], who dwell in the surrounding forests, without
ever disturb Moxos natives. To arrive at the eleventh day must be saved on many rapids, formed
by a kind of breaks amarilleja hardened clay, this requires considerable time to lose the need
is to download the canoes so them up in the middle of the stream, pulling them with ropes. Executing
this maneuver, some of the Indians with precision to walk between the water, are often severely
hurt by the sharp sting of armed stripes [2]. These fish are in the queue, parsnips and the
sea coasts of France, a lancet than four inches, very sharp, crooked teeth and trimmed for that
tear in with the meat, causing excruciating pain and often attacks of tetanus: unfortunately
these accidents are common, especially in the headwaters of the rivers.

Increasing time, five or six yards water cover these salient points, and is then passed over them
without being I could see.

In the twelfth day, the forests on the banks of Piray stop suddenly, and are replaced for a
swamp to where two creeks come to be lost, the palace and the pompano, born on the plains of Santa
Cruz de la Sierra. These swamps or marshes to announce that not far from the end of the journey.

The
fourteenth day are passed followed, one after another, four rapids, not far from where port is
presented on the left bank, and has no more room to a spacious roofed hut of palm leaves from
this port, separate from the hamlet of Four-Eyes by a deep swamp that is a mile long, you have
to walk yet thirty leagues to get to Santa Cruz de la Sierra. In the rainy season are used only
ten days to make this road, up the Piray, and six days, moving downstream from Four-Eyes to Loreto.

POPULATION.

If
we compare what I said in the first period of history before the arrival Moxos of the Spanish,
trying to find out what they have come to stop those primitive nations districts, shall find
the following results.

The nation of Moxos still occupies the places you lived before, with the only difference meeting
to meet the missions of the province as follows.

Muchojeones del Carmen. 230

Moxos Baures del Carmen. 362 "Concepcion Moxos. 3.126 "San-Joaquin Moxos. 690 "Still savages.
1.000 ------ 5,178

Moxos Moxos of Loreto. 2,145 "Trinidad. 2.604 "San Xavier. 1.515 "San Ignacio. 1.948 ------
8,212 ------ Total. 13,620

It looks as if this exposition that almost all of the Moxos is subject to Christianity, there are still
some in the savage state: these (of which a small number belonged to the missions of the Jesuits
time) live set divided into families Guaporé river not far, and east
of the missions and Carmen Concepcion, without communicating their
compatriots never converted.

It is also the relative number of different Moxos tribes, and Muchojeones
Baures, and can calculate the importance that should be, within a
country flooded, a nation whose people still spend thirteen thousand,
speaking all Moxo dialect.

Accustomed to obedience, Moxos have a kind nature, sociable, cheerful,
and but that all patients, but the way they are always ready to laugh
at the smallest trifle when they are delivered to themselves, just
as slavery has made them shy and silent in the presence of superiors.

These natives have a particular fondness for drawing, which continues
to be accompanied with enough skill: his paintings of animals and
plants regularly copied.

Sculptors turners, carpenters, weavers workshops,
  produced countless curios that have to
  sell in some cities of Peru. Many of them
  have learned Spanish and can write very
                                   well:
                                              in a word, the nation of the Moxos is perhaps the most susceptible
of civilization.

Among all the Indians of the province, the
  Moxos are currently Catholics not only
  more determined, but that lead to fanaticism
  so that all years, during Holy Week, they
                                   were seen
                                              watering
                                             public
spaces that draw blood to force lashes.

They are also superstitious in the extreme.

The nation of Itonama is totally subdued, and there is not a savage. In 1830, included:

In Magdalena. 2.831 In San-Ramon. 1,984

Total. 4,815

These Indians, whose character I have already spoken more than once in the previous chapters,
preserved inclinations and customs still primitive, that the Catholic religion could not uproot.
The tissues they make are the best in the province. The language is always Itonama used in
both missions.

The nation of Canichana entirely Christian, today is the mission of St. Peter. The number of its population
in 1830 amounted to 1939 individuals [1].

These natives have survived until today, in the very heart of the missions, many of its former
customs, and are still the terror of other nations, whose devastated fields stealing bear fruit, but
those to dare to venture a single complaint for fear estramado they have. The Canichana are rude,
and never use a courtesy to strangers. Today its population is less industrious in the province,
and one that feeds on the flesh caiman, for whose capture is worth
a thousand tricks.

Profess Catholicism, they could not dispose of countless superstitions
salvage their condition: they are otherwise very bad Christians.

       The language of that use is the same as their original state.

We moved the nation of has been assembled by the Jesuits in the mission of Santa Ana: it is not
one salvage it.

According to the census of year 1830, its population was two hundred thousand thirty-eight individuals.
These Indians are egercitan in hunting, fishing, navigation and agriculture.

Industry, little more or less equal to that of the Moxos, has not yet reached same degree of advancement,
only exception to the tissues.

No trace remains today because of their primitive religion, however, often report occasionally they have
not forgotten all the superstitions that were infused before of his conversion. National language
has not changed.

The nation of Cayuvava, fully converted to Christianity, is meeting this Exaltation in the mission.
In 1830 the total population reached two thousand sixty individuals
[1].

Cayuvava frank and loyal to be made of all who want to interact with them. In throughout the
province who know no other better navigation that these Indians, rowers working more experiments
and pilots in the Mamore River.

Regarding its industry, nothing is left Moxos excel by being perhaps superior to those in the
field of agriculture.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>