<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07766</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>535674</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20247</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Don Marcelo les miró uno á uno. Las fatigas de la guerra, especialmente la marcha acelerada
de los últimos días, estaban visibles en sus personas. Unos eran altos, delgados, con una esbeltez
angulosa; otros, cuadrados y fornidos, con el cuello corto y la cabeza hundida entre los hombros.
Estos últimos habían perdido sus adiposidades en un mes de campaña, colgándoles la piel arrugada
y flácida en varias partes del rostro. Todos llevaban la cabeza rapada, lo mismo que los soldados.
En torno de la mesa brillaban dos filas de esferas craneales sonrosadas ó morenas. Las orejas
sobresalían grotescamente; las mandíbulas se marcaban con el óseo relieve del enflaquecimiento.
Algunos habían conservado el mostacho enhiesto, á la moda del emperador; los más iban afeitados
ó con bigotes cortos en forma de cepillo.

Un brazalete de oro brillaba á continuación de una mano del conde puesta sobre la mesa. Era
el más viejo de todos y el único que conservaba sus cabellos, de un rubio obscuro y canoso,
peinados cuidadosamente y brillantes de pomada. Próximo á los cincuenta años, mantenía un vigor
femenil, cultivado por los ejercicios violentos. Enjuto, huesudo y fuerte, procuraba disimular
su rudeza de hombre de pelea con una negligencia suave y perezosa. Los oficiales le trataban
con gran respeto. Hartrott había hablado de él á su tío como de un gran artista, músico y poeta.
El emperador era su amigo: se conocían desde la juventud. Antes de la guerra, ciertos escándalos
de su vida privada le habían alejado de la corte: vociferaciones de folicularios y de socialistas.
Pero el soberano le mantenía en secreto su afecto de antiguo condiscípulo. Todos recordaban
un baile suyo, Los caprichos de Schahrazada, representado con gran lujo en Berlín por recomendación
del poderoso compañero. Había vivido algunos años en Oriente. En suma, un gran señor y un artista
de exquisita sensibilidad, al mismo tiempo que un soldado.

El conde no podía admitir el silencio de Desnoyers. Era su comensal, y creyó del caso hacerle
hablar para que interviniese en la conversación. Cuando don Marcelo explicó que sólo hacía
tres días que había salido de París, todos se animaron, queriendo saber noticias.

«¿Vió usted algunas de las sublevaciones?...» «¿Tuvo la tropa que matar mucha gente?» «¿Cómo
fué el asesinato de Poincaré?»

Le hicieron estas preguntas á la vez, y don Marcelo, desorientado por su inverosimilitud, no
supo qué contestar. Creyó haber caído en una reunión de locos. Luego sospechó que se burlaban
de él. ¿Sublevaciones? ¿Asesinato del Presidente?... Unos le miraban con lástima por su ignorancia;
otros con recelo, al ver que fingía no conocer unos sucesos que se habían desarrollado junto
á él. Su sobrino insistió.

--Los diarios de Alemania hablan mucho de eso. El pueblo de París se ha sublevado hace quince
días contra el gobierno, asaltando el Elíseo y asesinando al Presidente. El ejército tuvo que
emplear las ametralladoras para imponer el orden... Todo el mundo lo sabe.

Pero Desnoyers insistía en no saberlo: nada había visto. Y como sus palabras eran acogidas
con un gesto de maliciosa duda, prefirió callarse. Su Excelencia, espíritu superior, incapaz
de incurrir en las credulidades del vulgo, intervino para restablecer los hechos. Lo del asesinato
tal vez no era cierto: los periódicos alemanes podían exagerar con la mejor buena fe. Precisamente
pocas horas antes le había hecho saber el Estado Mayor General la retirada del gobierno francés
á Burdeos. Pero lo de la sublevación del pueblo de París y su pelea con la tropa era indiscutible.
«El señor lo ha visto sin duda, pero no quiere decirlo.» Desnoyers tuvo que contradecir al
personaje, pero su negativa ya no fué escuchada. ¡París! Este nombre había hecho brillar los
ojos, excitando la verbosidad de todos. Deseaban llegar cuanto antes á la vista de la torre
Eiffel, entrar victoriosos en la ciudad, para saciarse de las privaciones y fatigas de un mes
de campaña. Eran adoradores de la gloria militar, consideraban la guerra necesaria para la
vida, y sin embargo se lamentaban de los sufrimientos que les proporcionaba. El conde exhaló
una queja de artista.

--¡Lo que me ha perjudicado la guerra!--dijo con languidez--. Este invierno iban á estrenar
en París un baile mío.

Todos protestaron de su tristeza: su obra sería impuesta después del triunfo, y los franceses
tendrían que aplaudirla.

--No es lo mismo--continuó el conde--. Confieso que amo á París... ¡Lástima que esas gentes
no hayan querido nunca entenderse con nosotros!...

Y se sumió en su melancolía de hombre no comprendido.

A uno de los oficiales que hablaba de las riquezas de París con ojos de codicia, lo reconoció
de pronto Desnoyers por el brazal que ostentaba en una manga. Era el que había saqueado el
castillo. Como si adivinase sus pensamientos, el comisario se excusó.

--Es la guerra, señor...

¡Lo mismo que los otros!... La guerra había que pagarla con los bienes de los vencidos. Era
el nuevo sistema alemán; la vuelta saludable á la guerra de los tiempos remotos: tributos impuestos
á las ciudades y saqueo aislado de las casas. De este modo se vencían las resistencias del
enemigo y la guerra terminaba antes. No debía entristecerse por el despojo. Sus muebles y alhajas
serían vendidos en Alemania. Podía hacer una reclamación al gobierno francés para que le indemnizase
después de la derrota: sus parientes de Berlín apoyarían la demanda.

Desnoyers oyó con espanto tales consejos. ¡Qué mentalidad la de aquellos hombres! ¿Estaban
locos ó querían reirse de él?...

Al terminar el almuerzo, algunos oficiales se levantaron, requiriendo sus sables para cumplir
actos del servicio. El capitán von Hartrott también se levantó: necesitaba volver al lado de
su general; había dedicado bastante tiempo á las expansiones de familia. El tío le acompañó
hasta el automóvil. Moltkecito se excusaba una vez más de los desperfectos y despojos sufridos
por el castillo.

--Es la guerra... Debemos ser duros para que resulte breve. La verdadera bondad consiste en
ser crueles, porque así, el enemigo, aterrorizado, se entrega más pronto y el mundo sufre menos.

Don Marcelo levantó los hombros ante el sofisma. Estaban en la puerta del edificio. El capitán
dió órdenes á un soldado, y éste volvió poco después con un pedazo de tiza que servía para
marcar las señales de alojamiento. Von Hartrott deseaba proteger á su tío. Y empezó á trazar
una inscripción en la pared, junto á la puerta: «Bitte, nicht plündern. Es sind freundliche
Leute...»

Luego la tradujo, en vista de las repetidas preguntas del viejo.

--Quiere decir: «Se ruega no saquear. Los habitantes de esta casa son gente amable... gente amiga.»

¡Ah, no!... Desnoyers repelió con vehemencia esta protección. El no quería ser amable. Callaba
porque no podía hacer otra cosa... ¡pero amigo de los invasores de su país!...

El sobrino borró parte del letrero y sólo dejó el principio: «Bitte, nicht plündern.» «Se ruega
no saquear.» Luego, en la entrada del parque repitió la inscripción. Consideraba necesario
este aviso; podía irse Su Excelencia, podían instalarse en el castillo otros oficiales. Von
Hartrott había visto mucho, y su sonrisa daba á entender que nada llegaría á sorprenderle,
por enorme que fuese. Pero el viejo siguió despreciando su protección y riéndose con tristeza
del rótulo. ¿Qué más podían saquear?... Ya se habían llevado lo mejor.

--Adiós, tío. Pronto nos veremos en París.

El capitán montó en su automóvil, luego de estrechar una mano fría y blanda que parecía repelerle
con su inercia.

Al volver hacia su casa vió á la sombra de un grupo de árboles una mesa y sillas. Su Excelencia
tomaba el café al aire libre, y le obligó á sentarse á su lado. Sólo tres oficiales le acompañaban...
Gran consumo de licores procedentes de su bodega. Hablaban en alemán entre ellos, y así permaneció
don Marcelo cerca de una hora inmóvil, deseando marcharse y no encontrando el momento oportuno
para abandonar su asiento y desaparecer.

Se adivinaba fuera del parque un gran movimiento de tropas. Pasaba otro cuerpo de ejército
con sordo rodar de marea. Las cortinas de árboles ocultaban este desfile incesante que se dirigía
hacia el Sur. Un fenómeno inexplicable conmovió la luminosa calma de la tarde. Sonaba á lo
lejos un trueno continuo, como si rodase por el horizonte azul una tormenta invisible.

El conde interrumpió su conversación en alemán para hablar á Desnoyers, que parecía interesado
por el estrépito.

--Es el cañón. Se ha entablado una batalla. Pronto entraremos en danza.

La posibilidad de tener que abandonar su alojamiento, el más cómodo que había encontrado en
toda su campaña, le puso de mal humor.

--¡La guerra!--continuó--. Una vida gloriosa, pero sucia y embrutecedora. En todo un mes, hoy
es el primer día que vivo como un hombre.

Y como si le atrajesen las comodidades que habría de abandonar en breve, se levantó, dirigiéndose
al castillo. Dos alemanes se marcharon hacia el pueblo, y Desnoyers quedó con el otro, ocupado
en paladear admirativamente sus licores. Era el jefe del batallón acantonado en Villeblanche.

--¡Triste guerra, señor!--dijo en francés.

De todo el grupo de enemigos, éste era el único que había inspirado á don Marcelo un sentimiento
vago de atracción. «Aunque es un alemán, parece buena persona», pensaba viéndole. Debía haber
sido obeso en tiempo de paz, pero ahora ofrecía el exterior suelto y lacio de un organismo
que acaba de sufrir una pérdida de volumen. Se adivinaba en él una existencia anterior de tranquila
y vulgar sensualidad, una dicha burguesa que la guerra había cortado rudamente.

--¡Qué vida, señor!--siguió diciendo--. Que Dios castigue á los que han provocado esta catástrofe.

Desnoyers casi estaba conmovido. Vió la Alemania que se había imaginado muchas veces: una Alemania
tranquila, dulce, de burgueses un poco torpes y pesados, pero que compensaban su rudeza originaria
con un sentimentalismo inocente y poético. Este Blumhardt, al que sus compañeros llamaban Bataillon-Kommandeur,
era un buen padre de familia. Se lo representó paseando con su mujer y sus hijos bajo los tilos
de una plaza de provincia, escuchando todos con religiosa unción las melodías de una banda
militar. Luego lo vió en la cervecería con sus amigos, hablando de problemas metafísicos entre
dos conversaciones de negocios. Era el hombre de la vieja Alemania, un personaje de novela
de Goethe. Tal vez las glorias del Imperio habían modificado su existencia, y en vez de ir
á la cervecería frecuentaba el casino de los oficiales, mientras su familia se mantenía aparte,
aislada de los civiles, por el orgullo de la casta militar; pero en el fondo era siempre el
alemán bueno, de costumbres patriarcales, pronto á derramar lágrimas ante una escena de familia
ó un fragmento de buena música.

El comandante Blumhardt se acordaba de los suyos, que vivían en Cassel.

--Ocho hijos, señor--dijo con un esfuerzo visible para contener su emoción--. Los dos mayores
se preparan para ser oficiales. El menor va á la escuela desde este año... Es así.

Y señalaba con una mano la altura de sus botas. Temblaba nerviosamente de risa y de pena al
recordar á su pequeño. Luego hizo el elogio de su esposa, excelente directora de hogar, madre
que se sacrificaba con modestia por sus hijos, por su esposo. ¡Ay, la dulce Augusta!... Veinte
años de matrimonio iban transcurridos, y la adoraba como el día en que se vieron por primera
vez. Guardaba en un bolsillo de su uniforme todas las cartas que ella le había escrito desde
el principio de la campaña.

--Véala, señor... Estos son mis hijos.

Sacó del pecho un medallón de plata con adornos de arte de Munich, y tocando un resorte lo
hizo abrirse en redondeles, como las hojas de un libro, dejando ver los rostros de toda la
familia: la Frau Kommandeur, de una belleza austera y rígida, imitando el gesto y el peinado
de la emperatriz; luego las hijas, las Fraulin Kommandeur, vestidas de blanco, los ojos en
alto como si cantasen una romanza; y al final los niños, con uniformes de escuelas del ejército
ó de instituciones particulares. ¡Y pensar que podía perder á estos seres queridos con sólo
que un pedazo de hierro le tocase!... ¡Y había de vivir lejos de ellos ahora que era la buena
estación, la época de los paseos en el campo!...

--¡Triste guerra!--volvió á repetir--. Que Dios castigue á los ingleses.

Con una solicitud que conmovió á don Marcelo, le hizo preguntas á su vez acerca de su familia.
Se apiadó al enterarse de lo escasa que era su prole; sonrió un poco ante el entusiasmo con
que el viejo hablaba de su hija, saludando á Fraulin Chichí como un diablillo gracioso; puso
el gesto compungido al saber que el hijo le había dado grandes disgustos con su conducta.

¡Simpático comandante!... Era el primer hombre dulce y humano que encontraba en el infierno
de la invasión. «En todas partes hay buenas personas», se dijo. Deseó que no se moviese del
castillo. Si habían de continuar allí los alemanes, mejor era tenerle á él que á otros.

Un ordenanza vino á llamar á don Marcelo de parte de Su Excelencia. Encontró al conde en su
propio dormitorio, luego de pasar por los salones con los ojos cerrados para evitarse el dolor
de una cólera inútil. Las puertas estaban forzadas, los suelos sin alfombras, los huecos sin
cortinajes. Sólo los muebles rotos en los primeros momentos ocupaban sus antiguos lugares.
Los dormitorios habían sido saqueados con más método, desapareciendo únicamente lo que no era
de utilidad inmediata. El haberse alojado en ellos el día antes el general con todo su séquito
les había librado de una destrucción caprichosa.

El conde lo recibió con la cortesía de un gran señor que desea atender á sus invitados. No
podía consentir que Herr Desnoyers, pariente de un von Hartrott--al que recordaba vagamente
haber visto en la corte--, viviese en la habitación de los porteros. Debía ocupar su dormitorio,
aquella cama solemne como un catafalco, con penachos y columnas, que había tenido el honor
de servir horas antes á un ilustre general del Imperio.

--Yo prefiero dormir aquí. Esta otra habitación va mejor con mis gustos.

Había entrado en el dormitorio de la señora Desnoyers, admirando su mueblaje Luis XV, de una
autenticidad preciosa, con los oros apagados y los paisajes de sus tapicerías obscurecidos
por el tiempo. Era una de las mejores compras de don Marcelo. El conde sonrió con un menosprecio
de artista al recordar al jefe de la Intendencia encargado del saqueo oficial.

«¡Qué asno!... Pensar que esto lo ha dejado por viejo y feo...»

Luego miró de frente al dueño del castillo.

--Señor Desnoyers: creo no cometer ninguna incorrección, y hasta me imagino que interpreto
sus deseos, al manifestarle que estos muebles me los llevo yo. Serán un recuerdo de nuestro
conocimiento, un testimonio de nuestra amistad que ahora empieza... Si esto queda aquí corre
peligro de ser destruído. Los guerreros no están obligados á ser artistas. Yo guardaré estas
preciosidades en Alemania, y usted podrá verlas cuando quiera. Ahora todos vamos á ser unos...
Mi amigo el emperador se proclamará soberano de los franceses.

Desnoyers permaneció silencioso. ¿Qué podía contestar al gesto de ironía cruel, á la mirada
con que el gran señor iba subrayando sus palabras?...

--Cuando termine la guerra le enviaré un regalo de Berlín--añadió con tono protector.

Tampoco contestó el viejo. Miraba en las paredes el vacío que habían dejado varios cuadros
pequeños. Eran de maestros famosos del siglo XVIII. También debía haberlos despreciado el comisario
por insignificantes. Una ligera sonrisa del conde le reveló su verdadero paradero.

Había escudriñado toda la pieza, el dormitorio inmediato, que era el de Chichí, el cuarto de
baño, hasta el guardarropa femenino de la familia, que conservaba, unos vestidos de la señorita
Desnoyers. Las manos del guerrero se perdieron con delectación en los finos bullones de las
telas, apreciando su blanda frescura.

Este contacto le hizo pensar en París, en las modas, en las casas de los grandes modistos.
La rue de la Paix era el lugar más admirado por él en sus visitas á la ciudad enemiga.

Don Marcelo percibió la fuerte mezcla de perfumes que exhalaban su cabeza, sus bigotes, todo
su cuerpo. Varios frascos del tocador de las señoras estaban sobre la chimenea.

--¡Qué suciedad la guerra!--dijo el alemán---. Esta mañana he podido tomar un baño, después
de una semana de abstinencia; á media tarde tomaré otro... A propósito, querido señor: estos
perfumes son buenos, pero no son elegantes. Cuando tenga el gusto de ser presentado á las señoras,
les daré las señas de mis proveedores... Yo uso en mi casa esencias de Turquía: tengo muchos
amigos allá... Al terminar la guerra haré un envío á la familia.

Sus ojos se habían fijado en algunos retratos colocados sobre una mesa. El conde adivinó á
Madama Desnoyers viendo la fotografía de doña Luisa. Luego sonrió ante el retrato de Chichí.
Muy graciosa: lo que más admiraba en ella era su aire resuelto de muchacho. Posó una mirada
amplia y profunda en la fotografía de Julio.

--Excelente mozo--dijo--. Una cabeza interesante... artística. En un baile de trajes obtendría
un éxito. ¡Qué príncipe persa!... Una aigrette blanca en la cabeza sujeta con un joyel, el
pecho desnudo, una túnica negra con pavos de oro...

Y siguió vistiendo imaginariamente al primogénito de Desnoyers con todos los esplendores de
un monarca oriental. El viejo sintió un principio de simpatía hacia aquel hombre por el interés
que le inspiraba su hijo. ¡Lástima que escogiese con tanta habilidad las cosas preciosas y
se las apropiase!...

Junto á la cabecera de la cama, sobre un libro de oraciones olvidado por su esposa, vió un
medallón con otra fotografía. Esta no era de la casa. El conde, que había seguido la dirección
de sus ojos, quiso mostrársela. Temblaron las manos del guerrero... Su altivez desdeñosa é
irónica desapareció de golpe. Un oficial de Húsares de la Muerte sonreía en el retrato, contrayendo
su perfil enjuto y curvo de pájaro de pelea bajo el gorro adornado con un cráneo y dos fémurs.

--Mi mejor amigo--dijo con voz algo temblorosa--. El ser que más amo en el mundo... ¡Y pensar
que tal vez se bate en estos momentos y pueden matarlo!... ¡Pensar que yo también puedo morir!...

Don Marcelo creyó entrever una novela del pasado del conde. Aquel húsar era indudablemente
un hijo natural. Su simplicidad no podía concebir otra cosa. Sólo en su ternura era un padre
capaz de hablar así... Y casi se sintió contagiado por esta ternura.

Aquí dió fin la entrevista. El guerrero le había vuelto la espalda, saliendo del dormitorio,
como si desease ocultar sus emociones. A los pocos minutos sonó en el piso bajo un magnífico
piano de cola que el comisario no había podido llevarse por la oposición del general. La voz
de éste se elevó sobre el sonido de las cuerdas. Era una voz de barítono algo opaca, pero que
comunicaba un temblor apasionado á su romanza. El viejo se sintió conmovido; no entendía las
palabras, pero las lágrimas se agolparon á sus ojos. Pensó en su familia, en las desgracias
y peligros que le rodeaban, en la dificultad de volver á encontrar á los suyos... Como si la
música tirase de él, descendió poco á poco al piso bajo. ¡Qué artista aquel hombre altivamente
burlón! ¡Qué alma la suya!... Los alemanes engañaban á primera vista con su exterior rudo y
su disciplina, que les hacía cometer sin escrúpulo las mayores atrocidades. Había que vivir
en intimidad con ellos para apreciarlos tales como eran.

Cuando cesó la música estaba en el puente del castillo. Un suboficial contemplaba las evoluciones
de los cisnes en las aguas del foso. Era un joven doctor en Derecho que desempeñaba la función
de secretario cerca de Su Excelencia; un hombre de Universidad movilizado por la guerra.

Al hablar con don Marcelo reveló inmediatamente su origen. Le había sorprendido la orden de
partida estando de profesor en un colegio privado y en vísperas de casarse. Todos sus planes
habían quedado deshechos.

--¡Qué calamidad, señor!... ¡Qué trastorno para el mundo!... Y sin embargo, éramos muchos los
que veíamos llegar la catástrofe. Forzosamente debía sobrevenir un día ú otro. El capitalismo:
el maldito capitalismo tiene la culpa.

El suboficial era socialista. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09257</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>444951</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18490</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Don Marcelo looked at them one by one. The hardships of war, especially the accelerated speed
in recent days, were visible on their persons. Some were tall, thin, with a slender angular, others
square and chunky, with short neck and his head sunk between his shoulders. The latter had lost their
adiposity in a month of campaigning, wrinkled skin hanging and flabby in various parts of the face.
All had their heads shaved, just like soldiers. Around the table two rows of spheres glowed pink or
brown head. Ears protruded grotesquely, the jaw bone is marked with the relief of emaciation.
Some had kept the mustache, erect, to fashion the emperor, the most were shaved short whiskers
or with a brush.

A shining gold bracelet following a count's hand placed on the table. Was the oldest of all
and the only one who kept her hair a dark blond and gray carefully and shiny hair pomade. Near
fifty years, maintaining a force female, grown by strenuous exercise. Thin, bony and strong, he
tried to hide his rudeness of a man fighting with a soft and lazy negligence. The officers treated
him with great respect. Hartrott he had spoken to his uncle as a great artist, musician and
poet. The emperor was his friend, were known since youth. Before the war, some scandals of his private
life had been away from the court, shouts of folicularios and socialists. But the sovereign he kept
secret his affection for former classmate. Everyone remembered him a dance, The vagaries of Shahrazade,
represented in great luxury in Berlin on the recommendation the powerful partner. He had spent
some years in the East. In short, a great man and artist of exquisite sensitivity, while a soldier.

The
count could not accept the silence of Desnoyers. It was his guest, and believed the case to make
speak to intervene in the conversation.

When Don Marcelo was explained that only three days he had left Paris, they all cheered, wanting
to know news.

"Did you see some of the uprisings ?...»" Did the troops to kill many people? "How Poincaré was
the murder? "

I did these questions at once, and Don Marcelo, misled by its implausibility, not know what to
say. He thought he had fallen into a crazy meeting. Then laughed suspected him. "Uprisings? "Assassination
of President? ... Some looked at him with pity for his ignorance; other with suspicion, seeing
that pretended not to know about events that had developed along
to him.

His nephew said.

- The German newspapers talk a lot about that.

The people of Paris has risen fifteen days against the government, the Elysee assaulting and
murdering the president. The army had to used machine guns to impose order ... Everybody knows
it.

But Desnoyers insisted on not knowing, nothing had ever seen. And as his words were greeted with
a wave of malicious certainly preferred to be silent. His Excellency, higher spirit, unable from engaging
in the credulity of the vulgar, intervened to restore the facts. It's murder maybe it was
not true: the German newspapers were exaggerating with the utmost good faith. Precisely few
hours earlier he had made known the General Staff of the French government's withdrawal to
Bordeaux. But the uprising of the people of Paris and his fight with the troops was indisputable.
"The gentleman has seen no doubt, but do not want to say." Desnoyers had to contradict the
character, but his refusal was no longer heard. Paris! This name had done shine eyes, exciting
all the verbiage.

Wanted to reach as soon as the sight of the tower Eiffel, entering the city victorious, to
be fed with the deprivations and hardships of a month campaign.

They were worshipers of military glory, considered necessary for the war life, and yet complained
of the suffering that they provided.

The count uttered a complaint of an artist.

- What the war has hurt me! - Said languidly -.

This winter was to be premiered mine a ball in Paris.

All complained of his sadness, his work would be imposed after the
victory, and the French should applaud.

- It is not the same - continued
the count -.

I confess that I love Paris ... Too bad that these people have not
ever wanted to get along with us!

...

And he sank into his melancholy man understood.

One of the officers who spoke of the riches of Paris through the eyes of greed, recognized Desnoyers
suddenly he held the armband on one sleeve. It was he who had looted
castle.

As if divining his thoughts, the commissioner is excused.

- It's war, sir ...

Like the others! ... The war had to be paid to the property of the vanquished. Was the new German
system, the healthy return to war from ancient times: tax charges to isolated cities and looting
of houses.

In this way, overcame the resistance of enemy before the war ended. Should not be saddened
by the looting. Their furniture and jewelry would be sold in Germany.

Could make a claim to the French government to indemnify him after the defeat: his relatives in
Berlin would support demand.

Desnoyers listened with horror such advice. What mentality of these men! Were mad or wanted
to laugh at him?

...

After lunch, some officers were lifted, requiring their sabers to meet official duties. Captain
von Hartrott also rose: he needed to return to the side the general
had spent considerable time to the expansion of the family.

The uncle accompanied to the car. Moltkecito once again apologized for any damage suffered and
waste the castle.

- It's war ... We must be hard to make it brief. True goodness is be cruel, because then the
enemy, terrified, is delivered more quickly, and the world is less.

Don Marcelo shrugged his shoulders with the sophistry.

Were at the door of the building. Captain gave orders to a soldier, and he returned shortly afterwards
with a piece of chalk that was used to signs mark the property.

Von Hartrott wanted to protect his uncle. And he began to draw an inscription on the wall next
to the door: "Bitte, nicht plündern. It sind freundliche Leute ... "

Then translated, in view of the repeated questions of the old.

- It means: 'Please do not loot. The inhabitants of this house are nice people ... friendly
people. "

Ah, no! ... Desnoyers vehemently repelled protection. He did not want
to be nice.

Silent because I could not do anything ... But a friend of the invaders of their country! ...

The
nephew erased part of the sign and left only the beginning: "Bitte,
nicht plündern."

"Please not to plunder. "Then at the park entrance repeated registration.

Considered necessary this notice could leave His Excellency, the castle could be installed on
other officers.

Von Hartrott had seen much, and his smile implied that nothing would surprise him, by huge it
was.

But the old man continued ignoring their protection and laughing with sadness the label. What more
could loot? ... Had already been the best.

- Bye, uncle. Soon we will be in Paris.

The captain got into his car, after shaking a cold hand seemed to repel soft with its inertia.

Returning
to his house he saw the shadow of a clump of trees a table and chairs. His Excellency my coffee
outside, and forced him to sit beside her. Only three officers with him ... Greater consumption of
spirits from the cellar.

Speak German among themselves, and remained so Don Marcelo still
about an hour, anxious to leave and not finding the right time to
leave his seat and disappear.

Guessed out of the park is a great movement of troops. He spent another corps with deaf rolling tide. The curtain
of trees hid the incessant parade headed south. An inexplicable phenomenon shook the calm of the
afternoon light. It sounded to him far continuous thunder, as if the blue horizon rodase by
invisible storm.

The count broke off his conversation in German to speak to Desnoyers, who seemed interested
by the noise.

- Is the barrel. Has been engaged in a battle. Soon go into dance.

The possibility of having to abandon their property, the more comfortable
he had found in Throughout his campaign, put in a bad mood.

- War!
- Continued -.

A glorious life, but dirty and brutish. In a month, today is the first day I live as a man.

And as if he would appeal the amenities that would leave soon, he rose, turning the castle.
Two Germans marched into town, and Desnoyers was with the other, busy admired his taste in liquor.
It was the battalion commander stationed in Villeblanche.

- Sad war, sir! "- Said in French.

The entire group of enemies, this was the only one who had inspired
a feeling Don Marcelo vague attraction.

"While it is a German, looks good person", I thought seeing him. Should have been obese in
peacetime, but now offered outside of a loose, straight body who has just suffered a loss
of volume. Hinted at in a previous life of quiet and vulgar sensuality, a bourgeois that the
war had cut roughly.

- What a life, sir - he went -. May God punish those who caused this catastrophe.

Desnoyers was almost moved.

Germany saw that he had imagined many times: Germany quiet, sweet,
clumsy burghers and heavy, but they compensated for their original
rudeness with an innocent and poetic sentiment.

This Blumhardt, whom his fellows termed "Bataillon Kommandeur, was a good father. It represented
him walking with his wife and children under the linden trees a provincial square, listening
to all religious anointing with the melodies of a band military. Then I saw the beer with friends,
discussing metaphysical problems between two business conversations.

He was the man of old Germany, a character in a novel Goethe. Perhaps the glories of the Empire
had modified his existence, and instead of going Brewery to frequent the casino of the officers,
while his family stood apart isolated from civilians, the pride of
the military caste, but in the background was always Good German,
of patriarchal, ready to shed tears at a family scene or a piece of
good music.

Blumhardt commander remembered his people, who lived in Cassel.

- Eight children, sir - he said with a visible effort to contain his excitement -. The two major
prepare to be official. The child goes to school from this year ... So.

And he pointed with one hand the height of his boots. He trembled nervously laughing and grief
to remind your child. He then made a compliment to his wife, excellent head of household, mother
modesty is sacrificed for her children, her husband. Oh, the sweet Augusta! ... Twenty years of
marriage were passed, and worshiped as the day they were first time. Kept in a pocket of his
uniform all the letters she had written from the beginning of the
campaign.

- See it, sir ... These are my children.

He took from his breast a silver medallion adorned with art of Munich, and touching a spring
the was opened in rounds, like the leaves of a book, revealing the faces of all family: Kommandeur
Frau, a rigid, austere beauty, imitating the gesture and hair the
Empress, then daughters, Fraulin Kommandeur, dressed in white, eyes
sing high like a romance, and eventually the children with school
uniforms army or private institutions.

And to think he could lose to these loved ones with only a piece
of iron touch him!

... And had to live away from them now that was good season, the
time of the walks in the countryside!

...

- Sad war! - He repeated -. May God punish the English.

In an application moved by Don Marcelo made him turn to questions about his family. It is pity
to learn what their offspring was little, smiled a little at the
enthusiasm with the old man spoke of his daughter, Chichi saluted
like an imp Fraulin funny, put apologetic gesture knowing that the
son had taken great trouble with his behavior.

Nice Commander! ... It was the first man that was sweet man in hell
of the invasion.

"Everywhere there are good people," he said. He wished not to move the castle. If they were
to continue there the Germans had better have him than to others.

An orderly came to call Don Marcelo from His Excellency. Earl found in own room, after passing
through the rooms with closed eyes to avoid the pain a useless anger. The doors were forced, non-carpeted
floors, the holes without curtains. Only the broken furniture at first took their old places.
The bedrooms had been ransacked more methodically, disappearing only
what was not immediately useful.

The have stayed in them the day before the general with his entourage had escaped a wanton
destruction.

The count received him with the courtesy of a gentleman who wishes
to attend to your guests.

No Desnoyers could consent to Herr, parent of a von Hartrott - who vaguely remembered have
seen in court - he lived in a room with the porters. Should take their bedroom, that bed solemn
as a coffin, with plumes and columns, which had the honor hours prior to serving a famous general
of the Empire.

- I'd rather sleep here. The other room goes better with my tastes.

He entered the bedroom of Ms. Desnoyers, admiring his unfurnished Louis XV, a authenticity beautiful,
with muted golds and landscapes of his upholstery obscured by time.

It was one of the best buys of Don Marcelo. The Count smiled with contempt artist to remind the
head of the Administration official in charge of plunder.

"What an ass! ... To think that this has been left by old and ugly ... "

Then he looked in front of the owner of the castle.

- Mr Desnoyers: I did not commit any impropriety, and I even imagine that I play their wishes,
to express that I'll take the furniture myself. Will be a reminder of our knowledge, a testament
to our friendship that begins now ... If this is here runs danger of being destroyed. Warriors
are not required to be artists. I will keep these Prices in Germany, and you can see them anytime.
Now we're all going to be some ... My friend proclaimed emperor of the French sovereign.

Desnoyers was silent. What could respond to the gesture of cruel irony,
to look that the great lord was emphasizing his words?

...

- When the war will send a gift of Berlin - patronizing tone he added.

Neither answered the old man. I looked on the walls the void left several paintings small. They
were famous masters of the eighteenth century. He also despised the commissioner ought to have
by insignificant. Count a slight smile revealed his true whereabouts.

He had searched the entire piece, the room immediately, which was to Chichi, the fourth bathroom,
to the female wardrobe of the family, who retained, some dressed as Miss Desnoyers. The warrior's
hands were lost in the fine pleasure of studs fabrics, soft appreciating their freshness.

This contact made him think of Paris, in fashion, in the homes of
the great couturiers.

Rue de la Paix was the most admired by him in his visits to the enemy city.

Don Marcelo felt a strong mixture of perfumes that exhaled his head,
his mustache, all your body.

Several bottles of toiletries for ladies were on fire.

- What dirty war! - --- German said.

This morning I could take a bath, after a week of abstinence afternoon to take another ... By
the way, dear sir, these perfumes are good, but not elegant. When you have the pleasure of being
introduced to the ladies, I will give the address of my vendors ...
I use in my house essences of Turkey: I have many friends there ...
After the war I will make a delivery to the family.

His eyes were fixed on some portraits placed on a table. The count
guesses Madame Desnoyers saw the picture of Dona Luisa. Then he smiled
at the portrait of Chichi. Very funny: what he most admired about
her was her air of determination as a boy. Posed a glance broader
and deeper picture of July.

- Excellent waiter - he said -. An interesting
head ... art. In a costume ball would a success. What Persian prince!
... A white aigrette subject's head with a jewel, the bare chest,
a black tunic with gold turkeys ...

He continued wearing the eldest
son of Desnoyers imagination with all the splendors of an Eastern
monarch. The old man felt a principle of sympathy for the man by the
interest he felt for his son. Too bad they chose with such skill and
precious things they are appropriate! ...

At the head of the bed,
on a prayer book forgotten by his wife, saw a medallion with another
picture. This was not the house. The count, who had followed the direction
his eyes, wanted to show it. Shook the hands of the warrior ... His
haughty disdain é ironic suddenly disappeared. An officer of Hussars
of Death was smiling in the picture, collapsing thin and curved profile
of a fighting bird under his cap adorned with a skull and two femurs.

-
My best friend - "His voice was somewhat shaky -. Being that I love
in the world ... And to think that perhaps bat at the moment and can
kill you! ... I also think I can die! ...

Don Marcelo felt a novel
of the last glimpse of the count. He was undoubtedly Hussar an illegitimate
child. Its simplicity could not conceive otherwise. Only in his tenderness
was a father able to speak well ... And he was almost caught by this
tenderness.

Here the interview ended. The warrior was turned away,
leaving the bedroom, as if to hide his emotions. A few minutes sounded
on the floor beneath a magnificent grand piano that the commissioner
had not been carried by the opposing general. The voice of it rose
over the sound of the strings. Baritone voice was somewhat opaque,
but tremor communicated his passionate romance. The old man was shocked,
did not understand words, but the Tears welled in his eyes. He thought
of his family, misfortune and dangers that surrounded him, the difficulty
of finding his men ... As if Pulling music from him, dropped little
by little on the ground floor. Which artist man haughtily mockery!
What his soul! ... The Germans were deceiving at first sight with
its rough exterior and their discipline, they did not scruple committing
the worst atrocities. Had to live intimately with them to appreciate
such as they were. 

When the music stopped on the bridge of the castle.
An officer watching developments of swans in the waters of the moat.
He was a young doctor in law who acted as secretary about His Excellency,
a University man mobilized for war.

In talking with Don Marcelo immediately
revealed their origin. I was surprised by the order of starting to
be a teacher at a private school and before marriage. All plans had
been undone.

- What a calamity, sir ... What disorder to the world!
... And yet, we were many we saw reach the disaster. Must inevitably
occur some day or other. Capitalism: damn capitalism is to blame.

The
officer was a socialist</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>