<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09665</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>82382</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20970</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Tomó entonces unas tierras cerca de Sagunto: campos de secano, rojos y eternamente sedientos,
en los cuales retorcían sus troncos huecos algarrobos centenarios ó alzaban los olivos sus
redondas y empolvadas cabezas.

Fué su vida una continua batalla con la sequía, un incesante mirar al cielo, temblando de emoción
cada vez que una nubecilla negra asomaba en el horizonte.

Llovió poco, las cosechas fueron malas durante cuatro años, y Batiste no sabía ya qué hacer
ni adónde dirigirse, cuando en un viaje á Valencia conoció á los hijos de don Salvador, unos
excelentes señores (Dios les bendiga), que le dieron aquella hermosura de campos, libres de
arrendamiento por dos años, hasta que recobrasen por completo su estado de otros tiempos.

Algo oyó él de lo que había sucedido en la barraca, de las causas que obligaban á los dueños
á conservar improductivas tan hermosas tierras; pero ¡iba transcurrido tanto tiempo!... Además,
la miseria no tiene oídos; á él le convenían los campos, y en ellos se quedaba. ¿Qué le importaban
las historias viejas de don Salvador y el tío Barret?...

Todo lo despreciaba y olvidaba contemplando sus tierras. Y Batiste sentíase poseído de un dulce
éxtasis al verse cultivador en la huerta feraz que tantas veces había envidiado cuando pasaba
por la carretera de Valencia á Sagunto.

Aquello eran tierras: siempre verdes, con las entrañas incansables engendrando una cosecha
tras otra, circulando el agua roja á todas horas como vivificante sangre por las innumerables
acequias y regadoras que surcaban su superficie como una complicada red de venas y arterias;
fecundas hasta alimentar familias enteras con cuadros que, por lo pequeños, parecían pañuelos
de follaje. Los campos secos de Sagunto recordábalos como un infierno de sed, del que afortunadamente
se había librado.

Ahora se veía de veras en el buen camino. ¡A trabajar! Los campos estaban perdidos; había allí
mucho que hacer; pero ¡cuando se tiene buena voluntad!... Y desperezándose, este hombretón
recio, musculoso, de espaldas de gigante, redonda cabeza trasquilada y rostro bondadoso sostenido
por un grueso cuello de fraile, extendía sus poderosos brazos, habituados á levantar en vilo
los sacos de harina y los pesados pellejos de la carretería.

Tan preocupado estaba con sus tierras, que apenas si se fijó en la curiosidad de los vecinos.

Asomando las inquietas cabezas por entre los cañares ó tendidos sobre el vientre en los ribazos,
le contemplaban hombres, chicuelos y hasta mujeres de las inmediatas barracas. Batiste no hacía
caso de ellos. Era la curiosidad, la expectación hostil que inspiran siempre los recién llegados.
Bien sabía él lo que era aquello; ya se irían acostumbrando. Además, tal vez les interesaba
ver cómo ardía la miseria que diez años de abandono habían amontonado sobre los campos de Barret.

Y ayudado por su mujer y los chicos, empezó á quemar al día siguiente de su llegada toda la
vegetación parásita.

Los arbustos, después de retorcerse entre las llamas, caían hechos brasas, escapando de sus
cenizas asquerosos bichos chamuscados. La barraca aparecía como esfumada entre las nubes de
humo de estas luminarias, que despertaban sorda cólera en toda la huerta.

Una vez limpias las tierras, Batiste, sin perder tiempo, procedió á su cultivo. Muy duras estaban;
pero él, como labriego experto, quería trabajarlas poco á poco, por secciones; y marcando un
cuadro cerca de su barraca, empezó á remover la tierra ayudado por su familia.

Los vecinos burlábanse de todos ellos con una ironía que delataba su sorda irritación. ¡Vaya
una familia! Eran gitanos como los que duermen debajo de los puentes. Vivían en la vieja barraca
lo mismo que los náufragos que se aguantan sobre un buque destrozado: tapando un agujero aquí,
apuntalando allá, haciendo verdaderos prodigios para que se sostuviera la techumbre de paja,
distribuyendo sus pobres muebles, cuidadosamente fregoteados, en todos los cuartos, que eran
antes madriguera de ratones y sabandijas.

En punto á laboriosos, eran como un tropel de ardillas, no pudiendo permanecer quietos mientras
el padre trabajaba. Teresa la mujer y Roseta la hija mayor, con las faldas recogidas entre
las piernas y azadón en mano, cavaban con más ardor que un jornalero, descansando solamente
para echarse atrás las greñas caídas sobre la sudorosa y roja frente. El hijo mayor hacía continuos
viajes á Valencia con la espuerta al hombro, trayendo estiércol y escombros, que colocaba en
dos montones, como columnas de honor, á la entrada de la barraca. Los tres pequeñuelos, graves
y laboriosos, como si comprendiesen la grave situación de la familia, iban á gatas tras los
cavadores, arrancando de los terrones las duras raíces de los arbustos quemados.

Duró esta faena preparatoria más de una semana, sudando y jadeando la familia desde el alba
á la noche.

La mitad de las tierras estaban removidas. Batiste las entabló y labró con ayuda del viejo
y animoso rocín, que parecía de la familia.

Había que proceder á su cultivo; estaban en San Martín, la época de la siembra, y el labrador
dividió la tierra roturada en tres partes. La mayor para el trigo, un cuadro más pequeño para
plantar habas y otro para el forraje, pues no era cosa de olvidar al Morrut, el viejo y querido
rocín. Bien se lo había ganado.

Y con la alegría del que después de una penosa navegación descubre el puerto, la familia procedió
á la siembra. Era el porvenir asegurado. Las tierras de la huerta no engañaban; de allí saldría
el pan para todo el año.

La tarde en que se terminó la siembra vieron avanzar por el inmediato camino unas cuantas ovejas
de sucios vellones, que se detuvieron medrosas en el límite del campo.

Tras ellas apareció un viejo apergaminado, amarillento, con los ojos hundidos en las profundas
órbitas y la boca circundada por una aureola de arrugas. Iba avanzando lentamente, con pasos
firmes, pero con el cayado por delante tanteando el terreno.

La familia le miró con atención. Era el único que en las dos semanas que allí estaban se atrevía
á aproximarse á las tierras. Al notar la vacilación de sus ovejas, gritó para que pasasen adelante.

Batiste salió al encuentro del viejo. No se podía pasar: las tierras estaban ahora cultivadas.
¿No lo sabía?...

Algo de ello había oído el tío Tomba; pero en las dos semanas anteriores había llevado su rebaño
á pastar los hierbajos del barranco de Carraixet, sin preocuparse de estos campos.... ¿De veras
que ahora estaban cultivados?

Y el anciano pastor avanzaba la cabeza haciendo esfuerzos para ver con sus ojos casi muertos
al hombre audaz que osaba realizar lo que toda la huerta tenía por imposible.

Calló un buen rato, y al fin comenzó á murmurar tristemente:

«Muy mal; él también, en su juventud, había sido atrevido: le gustaba llevar á todos la contraria.
¡Pero cuando son muchos los enemigos!... Muy mal; se había metido en un paso difícil. Aquellas
tierras, después de lo del pobre Barret, estaban malditas. Podía creerle á él, que era viejo
y experimentado: le traerían desgracia.»

Y el pastor llamó á su rebaño, le hizo emprender la marcha por el camino, y antes de alejarse
se echó la manta atrás, alzando sus descarnados brazos, y con cierta entonación de hechicero
que augura el porvenir ó de profeta que husmea la ruina, le gritó á Batiste:

--Creume, fill meu: ¡te portarán desgrasia!...[4]

[4]--Créeme, hijo mío: ¡te traerán desgracia!...

De este encuentro surgió un motivo más de cólera para toda la huerta. El tío Tomba ya no podía
meter sus ovejas en aquellas tierras, después de diez años de pacífico disfrute de sus pastos.

Nadie decía una palabra sobre la legitimidad de la negativa de su ocupante al estar el terreno
cultivado. Todos hablaban únicamente de los respetos que merecía el anciano pastor, un hombre
que en sus mocedades se comía los franceses crudos, que había visto mucho mundo, y cuya sabiduría,
demostrada con medias palabras y consejos incoherentes, inspiraba un respeto supersticioso
á la gente de las barracas.

Cuando Batiste y su familia vieron henchidas de fecunda simiente las entrañas de sus tierras,
pensaron en la vivienda, á falta de trabajo más urgente.

El campo haría su deber. Ya era hora de pensar en ellos mismos.

Y por primera vez desde su llegada á la huerta, salió Batiste de las tierras para ir á Valencia
á cargar en su carro todos los desperdicios de la ciudad que pudieran serle útiles.

Aquel hombre era una hormiga infatigable para la rebusca. Los montones formados por Batistet
se agrandaron considerablemente con las expediciones del padre. La giba de estiércol, que formaba
una cortina defensiva ante la barraca, creció rápidamente, y más allá amontonáronse centenares
de ladrillos rotos, maderos carcomidos, puertas destrozadas, ventanas hechas astillas, todos
los desperdicios de los derribos de la ciudad.

Contempló con asombro la gente de la huerta la prontitud y buena maña de los laboriosos intrusos
para arreglarse su vivienda.

La cubierta de paja de la barraca apareció de pronto enderezada; las costillas de la techumbre,
carcomidas por las lluvias, fueron reforzadas unas y sustituídas otras; una capa de paja nueva
cubrió los dos planos pendientes del exterior. Hasta las crucecitas de sus extremos fueron
sustituídas por otras que la navaja de Batiste trabajó cucamente, adornando sus aristas con
dentelladas muescas; y no hubo en todo el contorno techumbre que se irguiera más gallarda.

Los vecinos, al ver cómo se reformaba la barraca de Barret, colocándose recta la montera, veían
en esto algo de burla y de reto.

Después empezó la obra de abajo. ¡Qué modo de utilizar los escombros de Valencia!... Las grietas
desaparecieron, y terminado el enlucido de las paredes, la mujer y la hija las enjalbegaron
de un blanco deslumbrante. La puerta nueva y pintada de azul, parecía madre de todas las ventanillas,
que asomaban por los huecos de las paredes sus cuadradas caras del mismo color. Bajo la parra
hizo Batiste una plazoleta, pavimentada con ladrillos rojos, para que las mujeres cosieran
allí en las horas de la tarde. El pozo, después de una semana de descensos y penosos acarreos,
quedó limpio de todas las piedras y la basura con que la pillería huertana lo había atiborrado
durante diez años, y otra vez su agua limpia y fresca volvió á subir en musgoso pozal, con
alegres chirridos de la garrucha, que parecía reirse de las gentes del contorno con una estridente
carcajada de vieja maliciosa.

Devoraban los vecinos su rabia en silencio. ¡Ladrón, más que ladrón! ¡Vaya un modo de trabajar!...
Aquel hombre parecía poseer con sus membrudos brazos dos varitas mágicas que lo transformaban
todo al tocarlo.

Diez semanas después de su llegada, aún no había salido de sus tierras media docena de veces.
Siempre en ellas, la cabeza metida entre los hombros y el espinazo doblegado, embriagándose
en su labor; y la barraca de Barret presentaba un aspecto coquetón y risueño, como jamás lo
había tenido en poder de su antiguo ocupante.

El corral, cercado antes con podridos cañizos, tenía ahora paredes de estacas y barro, pintadas
de blanco, sobre cuyos bordes correteaban las rubias gallinas y se inflamaba el gallo, irguiendo
su cabeza purpúrea.... En la plazoleta, frente á la barraca, florecían macizos de dompedros
y plantas trepadoras. Una fila de pucheros desportillados pintados de azul servían de macetas
sobre el banco de rojos ladrillos, y por la puerta entreabierta--ah, fanfarrón--veíase la cantarera
nueva, con sus chapas de blancos azulejos y sus cántaros verdes de charolada panza: un conjunto
de reflejos insolentes que quitaban la vista al que pasaba por el inmediato camino.

Todos, en su furia creciente, acudían á Pimentó. ¿Podía esto consentirse? ¿Qué pensaba hacer
el temible marido de Pepeta?

Y Pimentó se rascaba la frente oyéndoles, con cierta confusión.

¿Qué iba á hacer?... Su propósito era decirle dos palabritas á aquel advenedizo que se metía
á cultivar lo que no era suyo; una indicación muy seria para que «no fuese tonto» y se volviera
á su tierra, pues allí nada tenía que hacer. Pero el tal sujeto no salía de sus campos, y no
era cosa de ir á amenazarle en su propia casa. Esto sería «dar el cuerpo» demasiado, teniendo
en cuenta lo que podría ocurrir luego. Había que ser cauto y guardar la salida. En fin... un
poco de paciencia. Él, lo único que podía asegurar es que el tal sujeto no cosecharía el trigo,
ni las habas, ni todo lo que había plantado en los campos de Barret. Aquello sería para el demonio.

Las palabras de Pimentó tranquilizaban á los vecinos, y éstos seguían con mirada atenta los
progresos de la maldita familia, deseando en silencio que llegase pronto la hora de su ruina.

Una tarde volvió Batiste de Valencia, muy contento del resultado de su viaje. No quería en
su casa brazos inútiles. Batistet, cuando no había labor en el campo, buscaba ocupación yendo
á la ciudad á recoger estiércol. Quedaba la chica, una mocetona que, terminado el arreglo de
la barraca, no servía para gran cosa, y gracias á la protección de los hijos de don Salvador,
que se mostraban contentísimos con el nuevo arrendatario, acababa de conseguir que la admitiesen
en una fábrica de sedas.

Desde el día siguiente, Roseta formaría parte del rosario de muchachas que, despertando con
la aurora, iban por todas las sendas con la falda ondeante y la cestita al brazo camino de
la ciudad, para hilar el sedoso capullo entre sus gruesos dedos de hijas de la huerta.

Al llegar Batiste á las inmediaciones de la taberna de Copa, un hombre apareció en el camino
saliendo de una senda inmediata y marchó hacia él lentamente, dando á entender su deseo de
hablarle.

Batiste se detuvo, lamentando en su interior no llevar consigo ni una mala navaja, ni una hoz,
pero sereno, tranquilo, irguiendo su cabeza redonda con la expresión imperiosa tan temida por
su familia y cruzando sobre el pecho los forzudos brazos de antiguo mozo de molino.

Conocía á aquel hombre, aunque jamás había hablado con él. Era Pimentó.

Al fin ocurría el encuentro que tanto había temido.

El valentón midió con una mirada al odiado intruso, y le habló con voz melosa, esforzándose
por dar á su ferocidad y mala intención un acento de bondadoso consejo.

Quería decirle dos razones: hacía tiempo que lo deseaba; pero ¿cómo hacerlo, si nunca salía
de sus tierras?

--Dos rahonetes no més...[5]

[5]--Dos razoncitas nada más...

Y soltó el par de razones, aconsejándole que dejase cuanto antes las tierras del tío Barret.
Debía creer á los hombres que le querían bien, á los conocedores de las costumbres de la huerta.
Su presencia allí era una ofensa, y la barraca casi nueva un insulto á la pobre gente. Había
que seguir su consejo, é irse á otra parte con su familia.

Batiste sonreía irónicamente mientras hablaba Pimentó, y éste, al fin, pareció confundido por
la serenidad del intruso, anonadado al encontrar un hombre que no sentía miedo en su presencia.

«¿Marcharse él?... No había guapo que le hiciera abandonar lo que era suyo, lo que estaba regado
con su sudor y había de dar el pan á su familia. Él era un hombre pacífico, ¿estamos? pero
si le buscaban las cosquillas, era tan valiente como el que más. Cada cual que se meta en su
negocio, y él haría bastante cumpliendo con el suyo sin faltar á nadie.»

Luego, pasando ante el matón, continuó su camino, volviéndole la espalda con una confianza
despectiva.

Pimentó, acostumbrado á que le temblase toda la huerta, se mostraba cada vez más desconcertado
por la serenidad de Batiste.

--¿Es la darrera paraula?[6]--le gritó cuando estaba ya á cierta distancia.

[6]--¿Es la última palabra?

--Sí; la darrera--contestó Batiste sin volverse.

Y siguió adelante, desapareciendo en una revuelta del camino. A lo lejos, en la antigua barraca
de Barret, ladraba el perro olfateando la proximidad de su amo.

Al quedar solo, Pimentó recobró su soberbia. «¡Cristo! ¡Y cómo se había burlado de él aquel
tío!» Masculló algunas maldiciones, y cerrando el puño señaló amenazante la curva del camino
por donde había desaparecido Batiste.

--Tú me les pagarás.... ¡Me les pagarás, morral!

En su voz, trémula de rabia, vibraban condensados todos los odios de la huerta.

IV

Era jueves, y según una costumbre que databa de cinco siglos, el Tribunal de las Aguas iba
á reunirse en la puerta de los Apóstoles de la Catedral de Valencia.

El reloj de la torre llamada el Miguelete señalaba poco más de las diez, y los huertanos juntábanse
en corrillos ó tomaban asiento en los bordes del tazón de la fuente que adorna la plaza, formando
en torno al vaso una animada guirnalda de mantas azules y blancas, pañuelos rojos y amarillos
ó faldas de indiana de colores claros.

Llegaban unos tirando de sus caballejos con el serón cargado de estiércol, contentos de la
colecta hecha en las calles; otros en sus carros vacíos, procurando enternecer á los guardias
municipales para que les dejasen permanecer allí; y mientras los viejos conversaban con las
mujeres, los jóvenes se metían en el cafetín cercano, para matar el tiempo ante la copa de
aguardiente, mascullando su cigarro de tres céntimos.

Toda la huerta que tenía agravios que vengar estaba allí, gesticulante y ceñuda, hablando de
sus derechos, impaciente por soltar ante los síndicos ó jueces de las siete acequias el interminable
rosario de sus quejas.

El alguacil del tribunal, que llevaba más de cincuenta años de lucha con esta tropa insolente
y agresiva, colocaba á la sombra de la portada ojival las piezas de un sofá de viejo damasco,
y tendía después una verja baja, cerrando el espacio de acera que había de servir de sala de
audiencia.

La puerta de los Apóstoles, vieja, rojiza, carcomida por los siglos, extendiendo sus roídas
bellezas á la luz del sol, formaba un fondo digno del antiguo tribunal: era como un dosel de
piedra fabricado para cobijar una institución de cinco siglos.

En el tímpano aparecía la Virgen con seis ángeles de rígidas albas y alas de menudo plumaje,
mofletudos, con llameante tupé y pesados tirabuzones, tocando violas y flautas, caramillos
y tambores. Corrían por los tres arcos superpuestos de la portada tres guirnaldas de figurillas,
ángeles, reyes y santos, cobijándose en calados doseletes. Sobre robustos pedestales exhibíanse
los doce apóstoles; pero tan desfigurados, tan maltrechos, que no los hubiera conocido Jesús:
los pies roídos, las narices rotas, las manos cortadas; una fila de figurones, que más que
apóstoles parecían enfermos escapados de una clínica mostrando dolorosamente sus informes muñones.
Arriba, al final de la portada, abríase, como gigantesca flor cubierta de alambrado, el rosetón
de colores que daba luz á la iglesia, y en la parte baja, en la base de las columnas adornadas
con escudos de Aragón, la piedra estaba gastada, las aristas y los follajes borrosos por el
frote de innumerables generaciones.

En este desgaste de la portada adivinábase el paso de la revuelta y el motín. Junto á estas
piedras se había aglomerado y confundido todo un pueblo; allí se había agitado en otros siglos,
vociferante y rojo de rabia, el valencianismo levantisco, y los santos de la portada, mutilados
y lisos como momias egipcias, al mirar al cielo con sus rotas cabezas, parecían estar oyendo
aún la revolucionaria campana de la Unión ó los arcabuzazos de la Germanías.

Terminó el alguacil de arreglar el tribunal y plantóse á la entrada de la verja, esperando
á los jueces.

Iban llegando, solemnes, con una majestad de labriegos ricos, vestidos de negro, con blancas
alpargatas y pañuelo de seda bajo el ancho sombrero. Cada uno llevaba tras sí un cortejo de
guardas de acequia, de pedigüeños que antes de la hora de la justicia buscaban predisponer
el ánimo del tribunal en su favor.

La gente labradora miraba con respeto á estos jueces salidos de su clase, cuyas deliberaciones
no admitían apelación. Eran los amos del agua; en sus manos estaba la vida de las familias,
el alimento de los campos, el riego oportuno, cuya carencia mata una cosecha. Y los habitantes
de la extensa vega cortada por el río nutridor, como una espina erizada de púas que eran sus
canales, designaban á los jueces por el nombre de las acequias que representaban.

Un vejete seco, encorvado, cuyas manos rojas y cubiertas de escamas temblaban al apoyarse en
el grueso cayado, era Cuart de Faitanar; el otro, grueso y majestuoso, con ojillos que apenas
si se veían bajo los dos puñados de pelo blanco de sus cejas, era Mislata; poco después llegaba
Rascaña, un mocetón de planchada blusa y redonda cabeza de lego; y tras ellos iban presentándose
los demás, hasta siete: Favara, Robella, Tormos y Mestalla.

Ya estaba allí la representación de las dos vegas: la de la izquierda del río, la de las cuatro
acequias, la que encierra la huerta de Ruzafa con sus caminos de frondoso follaje que van á
extinguirse en los límites del lago de la Albufera, y la vega de la derecha del Turia, la poética,
la de las fresas de Benimaclet, las chufas de Alboraya y los jardines siempre exuberantes de
flores.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06029</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>168136</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18572</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

He took some land near Sagunto: dry fields, red and eternally thirsty in which twisted its ancient
carob hollow trees or olive trees raised their powdered round heads.

His life was a continuous battle with drought, a continuing look at the sky, trembling with emotion
whenever a small black cloud looming on the horizon.

Little rain, the crops were bad for four years, and Batiste did not know what to do or where
to go, when on a trip to Valencia met the sons of Don Salvador, a great masters (God bless),
who gave that beauty of fields, free lease for two years until they
completely regain their status of other times.

Something he heard what had happened in the cabin, the causes that force the owners so beautiful to
keep unproductive land, but after going so long!

... In addition, misery has no ears, he suited to the fields, and they left. What mattered old
stories of Don Salvador and Barret? ...

Forgot everything despised and contemplating their land. And Batiste felt himself possessed
of a sweet Ecstasy to be fertile orchard grower had so often envied when he passed the road from
Valencia to Sagunto.

That was land, evergreen, with the entrails of a crop breeding tireless after another, circling the red
water at all hours as life-giving blood for the many ditches and
sprinklers that plied its surface as a complex network of veins and
arteries fertile to feed whole families with tables, so small, they
seemed scarves foliage.

Sagunto dry fields recordábalos thirsty as hell, which fortunately had escaped.

Now he was really on track. Business The fields were lost, was there much to do, but when you have
good will ... And stretching, the big man strong, muscular back of a giant, round head and a
kindly face sustained sheared by a thick neck, a monk, extending
his powerful arms, lifted her accustomed to sacks of flour and the
heavy skins of the cart.

So concerned was their land, who barely noticed the curious neighbors.

The restless heads poking among cañares or lying on his stomach on the slopes, Men stared at
him, little boys and even women of the barracks immediately. Batiste
did ignore them.

It was the curiosity, expectation always inspire hostile newcomers. He knew what that was,
and would be accustomed.

Also, maybe they were interested see how poverty burned ten years of neglect had heaped upon
the fields of Barret.

And helped by his wife and children, began to burn a day after his arrival the whole parasitic vegetation.

Shrubs,
after writhing in the flames, embers fell facts, escaping from their nasty bugs charred ashes.
The hut appeared to be blurred between the clouds smoke of lamps,
which aroused anger deaf throughout the garden.

Once clean the land, Batiste, without wasting time, proceeded to its cultivation. Were harsh; but
he, as an expert farmer, wanted to work slowly, in sections, and setting a box near his hut,
he began to remove the help of his family land.

Neighbors burlábanse them all with an irony that betrayed his irritation. Go a family! They were
gypsies and those who sleep under bridges. They lived in the old barracks the same as shipwrecked
on a ship wrecked endure: plugging a hole here shoring up there, doing real wonders that would
hold up the thatch, distributing its poor furniture, carefully fregoteados in all rooms, which were
before burrowing mice and bugs.

In point of time-consuming, were like a herd of squirrels, unable to sit still while the father
worked.

Teresa Rosetta women and the eldest daughter, with her skirts gathered between legs and spade
in hand, digging more ardently than a laborer, resting only to turn
back by the hair falling on the red sweaty face.

The eldest son was continuous Valencia travel to the basket on his shoulder, carrying manure
and debris, placed in two piles, like columns of honor, at the entrance
of the building.

The three little ones, serious and laborious, as if they understood the plight of the family,
went to all fours after diggers, tearing lumps of hard burned shrub roots.

This preparatory task lasted more than a week, sweating and panting
family from dawn till night.

Half of the land was removed.

Batiste filed and styled with the help of the old and spirited horse, which seemed to the family.

Had
to come to his crop, were in San Martin, the time of sowing and the
farmer cleared land divided into three parts.

The higher in wheat, a smaller frame for beans and other plant for fodder, it was not something
to forget the Morrut, the good old nag. Well it had won.

And with the joy of that after a laborious navigation discover the port, the family proceeded to
planting. The future was assured. The lands of the garden did not
deceive, hence would bread for the whole year.

The afternoon saw the planting was completed by the immediate way forward a few sheep of dirty fleece,
fearful that they stopped at the edge of the field.

Behind them came an old parchment, yellow, eyes sunken in the deep orbits and mouth surrounded
by a halo of wrinkles. Progressed slowly, with steps firm, but with
the staff ahead of testing the waters.

The family looked at him intently. Was the only one in the two weeks that there were dared to approach
the land. Noting the hesitation of his sheep, he shouted for them to go forward.

Batiste went to meet the old. Could not happen: the lands are now cultivated. Did not you know?
...

Some of it had heard the old Tomba, but in the past two weeks had
led his flock to graze the weeds in the cliff of Carraixet, without
worrying about these fields .... Really now they were grown?

And the old shepherd moved his head to make efforts to see with their
eyes almost dead bold man who dared to do what all the garden was
as impossible.

He paused a while, and finally began to murmur sadly

"Too bad, he also, in his youth he had been dared: he liked to wear
them all the opposite.

But when too many enemies ... Too bad, she had gone into a difficult step. Those land, after
the poor Barret, were cursed.

I could believe him, that was old and experienced, would bring misfortune.

"

And the pastor called his herd, to march him down the road, and before leaving threw the blanket
back, raising his emaciated arms, and some chanting wizard that predicts the future or a prophet
who sniffs the ruin, he shouted to Batiste:

- Creume, fill meu: desgrasia will carry you !...[ 4]

[4] - Believe
me, my son will bring disgrace!

...

From this meeting arose another reason for anger to the entire garden. Tomba's uncle could no longer
put the sheep on that land, after ten years of peaceful enjoyment of their pastures.

Nobody said a word about the legitimacy of the refusal of the occupant to be the ground cultivated.
All spoke only of the respect he deserved the old minister, a man
that in his youth, the French ate raw, who had seen much of the world,
and whose wisdom, demonstrated average incoherent words and advice,
inspired a superstitious respect to the people of the barracks.

When Batiste and his family were drenched fertile seed the bowels of their land, thought of housing,
lack of work more urgent.

The field would do his duty. It was time to think about themselves.

And for the first time since his arrival in the orchard, land Batiste left to go to Valencia to
charge your car every scrap of the city that might be useful.

The man was a tireless ant to search for it. The mounds formed by Batistet widened considerably with
the father's expeditions.

The hump of manure, which was a shade defensively to the hut, grew rapidly, and beyond hundreds amontonáronse
of bricks, rotting timbers, broken doors, windows made chips, all demolition waste in the city.

People
watched in amazement how quickly the garden and good skill of industrious
hackers to fix your home.

The thatched roof of the cabin was suddenly straightened, the ribs of the roof eaten away by
the rains, were reinforced and substituted some other, a layer of
fresh straw covered the remaining two planes abroad.

Even the little crosses on the ends were substituted by others that worked cucamente Batiste knife,
decorating its edges with jagged notches, and there was all round roof that they stood more graceful.

The
neighbors, seeing how reformed Barrett's cabin, standing straight cap, saw in this bit of fun
and challenge.

Then began the work below. What a way to use the rubble of Valencia! ... Cracks disappeared, and
finished plaster walls, the wife and daughter the whitewashed dazzling
white.

The new door and painted blue, it seemed the mother of all windows, poking through the holes
in the walls its square faces of the same color.

Under the vine Batiste made a square, paved with red bricks, for
women to sew there in the afternoon.

Well, after a grueling week of declines and carries, was cleared of all stones and rubbish that
the rascals had crowded orchard for ten years, and again its clean, fresh water rose again in mossy
pail with cheerful chirps of the wheel, which seemed to laugh at people with a raucous contour
old mischievous laugh.

Neighbors devouring rage in silence. Thief, rather than a thief! What a way to work! ... The man
seemed to have with their brawny arms two magic wands that transform all at the touch.

Ten weeks after his arrival, had not yet left their lands half a dozen
times.

Always on them, his head between his shoulders and his spine bent, intoxicated in their work,
and Barrett's cabin had a flirtatious and cheerful appearance, as never had been held by its
former occupier.

The yard, surrounded with rotten hurdles before, now had poles and mud walls, painted white on the
edges of chickens running around the blonde and inflamed the rooster,
straightening purple head .... In the square, opposite the barracks,
beds blooming dompedro and vines.

A row of pots painted blue chipped pots served on the bank of red bricks, and through the open
door - ah, blowhard - there was the Cantarera new white sheets with tiles and green jars belly
pan, a set insolent glare and took the view that once ran through the road.

All in his fury rising, went to Pimento. Could this be pampered? What did make Pepeta the terrible
husband?

And Pimento scratched his face listening to them, with some confusion.

What was I going to do?

... Its purpose was to say two little words to that upstart that was brought to cultivate what
was not theirs, a very serious indication that "it was not stupid"
and again his land, because there had nothing to do.

But this subject did not come out of their fields, and not thing was going to threaten him
at home.

This would "give the body" too, taking consider what might happen
next.

Had to be cautious and save the output.

Anyway ... a little patience. Him, all I could say is that this subject would not reap the wheat,
and beans, and all that was planted in the fields of Barret. That would be for the devil.

Pimento reassuring words to the neighbors, and they continued with
the watchful eye Progress of the goddam family, wishing silently that
soon came when his ruin.

One afternoon he returned Batiste of Valencia, very happy with the results of his trip. I did not
want to arm home pointless. Batistet, when there was work in the field, sought occupation
going into the city to collect manure. There was the girl, a Bouncers that arrangement ended
the cabin, no good for much, and thanks to the protection of the
children of Don Salvador showed that thrilled with the new tenant
just to get that support it in a silk factory.

From the next day, Rosetta would be part of the string of girls, waking up dawn, going through
all the paths with flowing skirt and the basket to the arm path the
city, to spin the silken cocoon between his thick fingers of daughters
of the garden.

Batiste Arriving to the vicinity of the tavern Cup, a man appeared
on the road leaving a trail immediately and marched him slowly, giving
to understand their desire talk.

Batiste was stopped inside regretting not carrying not a bad knife or a sickle, but serene,
tranquil, rearing its head round the expression so feared by pressing his family and across
the chest the arms of former strongman mill boy.

Known to man, although he had never spoken with him.

Pimento was.

At last the encounter occurred had feared.

The bully was measured with a look at the hated intruder, and spoke with honeyed voice, striving
to give his ferocity and malice in a tone of kindly advice.

I wanted to tell you two reasons: it had long wanted, but how to do it, if you never left from
their land?

- Two rahonetes not més ... [5]

[5] - Two razoncitas nothing more ...

And let the couple of reasons,
advising him to leave as soon as the land of Barret.

Must believe the men who loved him well, to those familiar with the customs of the garden. His
presence there was an offense, and the cabin almost new an insult to the poor people. There to
follow his advice and go elsewhere with his family.

Batiste Pimento smiled ironically as he spoke, and he, at last, seemed confused by the serenity
of the intruder, shocked to find a man who felt no fear in his presence.

"" Leaving it? ... There was cute to make him abandon what was his, which was watered with their
sweat and had to give bread to his family. He was a peaceful man, are we? but if you seek
out tickles, was as brave as they come. Everyone that gets into your business, and he would rather
meet with him without offending anyone. "

Then, past the bully, went his way, turning away with a confidence derogatory.

Pimento, accustomed to him tremble all the garden, looked increasingly puzzled by the serenity of
Batiste.

- Is the Darrera paraula [6] - he cried when he was already at a distance.

[6]

- Is the last word?

- Yes, the Darrera - Batiste replied without turning.

And went ahead, disappearing around a turn of the road.

Far away, in the former barracks Barrett, sniffing dog barked near his master.

When left alone, Pimento regained its pride. "Christ! And how he had taunted him Uncle! "muttered
some curses and threatening a fist pointed curve of the road where he had gone Batiste.

- You will pay me .... I will pay, backpack!

In his voice trembling with anger, hatred vibrated condensed all of the garden.

IV

It was Thursday, and according to a custom dating back five centuries, the Tribunal de las Aguas
was to meet at the door of the Apostles of the Cathedral of Valencia.

The clock tower pointing Miguelete called a little after ten, and
juntábanse huertanos in little groups or were seated on the edge of
the bowl of the font that adorns the plaza, forming around the glass
a vibrant garland of blue and white blankets, scarves red and yellow
calico skirts or light colors.

Came about pulling his nag with pannier full of manure, content of sampling on the streets, others
in their empty cars, trying to soften the guards municipal dejasen them stay there, and while
conversing with the old women, young people went into the nearest
cafe to kill time before the cup brandy, mumbling his cigar three
cents.

All orchard that avenge wrongs had was there, grinning and
frowning, talking their rights, eager to drop to the trustees or judges
of the seven judges the endless litany of complaints.

Court bailiffs,
who had more than fifty years of struggle with this troop insolent
and aggressive, placed under the shade of the arched cover parts of
old damask sofa, and tended then a low fence, closing the sidewalk
space was to serve as room hearing.

The door of the Apostles, old,
red, eaten for centuries, spreading their gnawed beauties to sunlight,
was a fund worth of the old court was like a canopy stone shelter
built for an institution than five centuries.

In the tympanum the
Virgin appeared six angels with rigid wings often dawns and plumage
chubby, with flaming toupee and heavy curls, playing viola and flutes,
reeds and drums. Running through the three arches superimposed on
the cover three wreaths of figurines, angels, kings and saints, canopies
sheltering in drafts. On sturdy pedestals exhibíanse the twelve apostles,
but so disfigured, so battered, that I had not known Jesus foot gnawed,
broken noses, hands cut off, a row of dummies, which more than apostles
seemed ill escaped from a clinic reports showing painfully dies. Above,
at the end of the cover, opened, like a gigantic flower wire cover,
escutcheon of colors that gave light to the church, and on the floor
at the base of the columns adorned with coats of Aragon, the stone
was worn edges and blurred by the foliage friction of countless generations.

In
this wear on the cover guessed the passage of the revolt and mutiny.
Alongside these had gathered stones and confused an entire people
there were busy in other centuries, screaming and red with rage, the
Valencianism rebellious, and the saints of the cover, mutilated and
smooth as Egyptian mummies, to look at the sky with broken heads,
seemed to be listening even revolutionary union campaign or the gunshot
of the Germanies.

He finished the sheriff court and plantóse fix
at the entrance of the gate, waiting to the judges.

Iban came and
solemn, with the majesty of rich peasants, dressed in black, white
sandals and silk handkerchief under the broad hat. Each carried behind
a procession of ditch guards of beggars before the time of seeking
justice bias the mind of the court in their favor.

The peasant folk
look with respect to these judges come out of his class, whose deliberations
admitted no appeal. They were the masters of water in his hands was
the life of families, the food of the fields, irrigation, timely,
lack of which kills the harvest. And the people the extensive river
valley cut by the nurturer, as a bristling barbed spine were his channels
to the judges designated by the name of the canals they represented.

A
dry old man, hunched, whose red hands trembling and covered with scales
to rely on arch thickness was Faitanar room, the other large and majestic,
with eyes that just if they were under the two handfuls of white hair
of his eyebrows, was Mislata, shortly after arriving Rascaño, a young
man of ironed shirt and lay round head, and behind them were performing
others, up to seven: Favara, Robella, Tormos and Mestalla.

Was there
representing the two valleys: the left of the river, the four ditches,
which encloses the garden paths Ruzafa with lush foliage that go to
extinct within the limits of the Albufera lake and the valley to the
right of the Turia, the poetic the Benimaclet strawberries, groundnuts
Alboraya and lush gardens are always flowers</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>