<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10990</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>377215</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>738</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Y esta juventud ruidosa,
alegre, exuberante en jugos, sufría un suplicio tantalesco al hablar de las muchachas más hermosas
de la ciudad. Las admiraban y vivían aparte de ellas, a pesar de moverse en un estrecho espacio
que les obligaba a continuos encuentros. Toda su ilusión era conseguir una licencia para vivir
varios días en Mallorca o en la Península, lejos de la isla virtuosa y huraña, que sólo admitía
al forastero como marido; embarcarse en busca de otras tierras, donde era fácil dar expansión
a sus deseos exacerbados, iguales a los del colegial y el presidiario.

¡Las mujeres!... Aquellos jóvenes no hablaban de otra cosa; y Febrer, sentado a la gran mesa
de la fonda, aprobaba en silencio sus palabras y sus lamentaciones. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>534340</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>701</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> And these young noisy joyful,
exuberant juices, suffered an ordeal tantalesco talking about the most beautiful girls of the city.
The admired and lived apart from them, despite moving in a narrow space which forced them to continuous
games. His whole dream was to get a license to live several days in Mallorca or on the Peninsula,
off the island virtuous and shy, which only supported the stranger as husband embark in search
of other lands, where it was easy to expand exacerbated their desires, like those of the college
and the inmate.

Women! ... Those young people did not talk about something else, and
Febrer, sitting at the large table of the Fund approved quietly his
words and lamentations</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>