<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09773</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>167783</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23740</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

En suma, para no cansar más a mis lectores, acabaré por decir que don Acisclo recogió al fin
el premio de sus fatigas.

Las elecciones llegaron, y D. Acisclo venció en las elecciones. Don Jaime Pimentel salió diputado
por una gran mayoría.

Algunos quieren dar a entender que D. Acisclo hizo mil tramoyas y falsedades; pero nada se
pudo probar, y por consiguiente no debemos creerlo.

Don Jaime Pimentel, sin abandonar la corte, sin escribir apenas carta alguna, con el mayor
sosiego, tuvo el gusto de recibir su acta, casi limpia, pues sólo llevaba dos protestas insignificantes
y mal fundadas.

El júbilo de D. Acisclo fue grande después de la victoria. ¡Qué lauro el suyo! ¡Qué muestra
de poder la que acababa de dar! Con un candidato invisible, descuidado, flojo; con un enemigo
tan fuerte, tan único, tan modelo y tan fénix entre los representantes del pueblo, había logrado
vencer, y vencer por una gran mayoría. Después de admirarse de su propia capacidad para la
política, sólo se reconocía deudor a D. Juan Fresco y a la copiosa turba de bermejinos que
le siguieron en el día de la elección como a caudillo respetado.

Durante todo este largo período electoral, las relaciones amistosas de doña Luz y del P. Enrique
se fueron estrechando más cada día. Hasta doña Manolita, dejándose llevar del entusiasmo de
su marido, o bien compartiéndole, no había pensado más que en las elecciones.

Doña Luz y el padre eran sin duda las dos únicas personas de cierta posición en todo el distrito,
que no habían pensado en éste ni en el otro candidato, y que no se habían afanado por el triunfo
de cualquiera de ellos.

En medio de aquella agitación política, habían hallado retraimiento dulcísimo en la misma casa
de quien la promovía; y allí eran las pláticas suaves y encumbradas, y las conversaciones amenas,
en que siempre aprendía algo doña Luz, en que siempre hallaba nuevas excelencias en el entendimiento
y en el corazón del padre, y en que el padre, a su vez, no dejaba nunca de pasmarse del despejo,
de la agudeza, de la notable discreción, de la fantasía poética y de la sensibilidad exquisita
de su bella interlocutora.

Don Anselmo había terciado en los debates, aunque ya no tanto, por haberle tenido también D.
Acisclo muy interesado en las elecciones. Y el cura don Miguel había seguido yendo con constancia
a la tertulia, si bien los diálogos sabios del Padre y de doña Luz le magnetizaban y embelesaban
de tal suerte, que a los pocos minutos de empezar a oírlos, solía quedarse profundamente dormido,
acompañándolos y animándolos a veces con una música de ronquidos interminables y sonoros.

Resultaba de todo ello que la única persona, que era en verdad constante e inteligente testigo
del mutuo afecto y de los íntimos coloquios de doña Luz y del Padre, era doña Manolita. Yo
no quiero hacer a ésta, ni a ninguno de mis héroes, mejor de lo que son o de lo que fueron.
Doña Manolita no era una paloma sin hiel; y no porque odiase a alguien, sino porque no dejaba
de tener malicia. Más bien se podía tildar a doña Manolita de tenerla. Más bien se la podía
acusar de que, sin envidia ni encono, y sólo por amor al arte, gustaba algo de la murmuración,
y seguía demasiado, como regla para sus juicios, aquella terrible sentencia de piensa mal y
acertarás. Sin embargo, merced a la veneración cariñosa que doña Luz le infundía, ella interpretaba
siempre por el lado más benévolo todos sus actos y discursos. Por esto, aunque a la perspicacia
de doña Manolita no pudo ocultarse largo tiempo aquella inclinación irresistible de dos almas,
doña Manolita no dejó nunca de hacer justicia a doña Luz, y reconoció y declaró, allá en el
fondo de su pecho, que en el de su amiga no había la más leve intención de perturbar el ánimo
del Padre ni de atraerle con coqueterías culpadas.

El respeto y el cariño de la hija del médico al P. Enrique eran grandes también; pero no tanto
que le impidiesen por completo todo fallo algo contrario sobre su conducta. Doña Manolita,
pues, sin pensar que doña Luz hubiese dado para ello ni ocasión ni motivo, empezó a sospechar
que el Padre, más o menos confusa y vagamente, estaba enamorado. Por respeto a su amiga, y
porque en los lugares no anda la gente con sutilezas etéreas o pasadas por alambique, y porque
con decir ella algo hubiera dado pie para que se añadiese mucho, doña Manolita ni a su padre
confió el resultado de sus observaciones. Sólo le confió a Pepe Güeto, a quien nada ocultaba;
pero exigiéndole el más profundo sigilo.

La gravedad de doña Luz y del Padre cortaba los vuelos a todas las audacias de doña Manolita,
quien jamás se propasó a dirigir al Padre, ni en broma y con rodeos y perífrasis, la indirecta
más oscura sobre la pasión que en él imaginaba. Doña Manolita siguió, no obstante, observando.
Pepe Güeto observó también. Ambos esposos se comunicaban luego lo que habían observado. De
esta suerte venían los dos a corroborarse en la idea de que el Padre, quizá sin saberlo, amaba
a doña Luz por estilo místico y sutil, y que doña Luz se dejaba adorar sin presumir ningún
término disgustoso, sin reflexionar en toda la trascendencia que aquella adoración podría tener,
y sin ver en ella más que una amistad tierna, sencilla e impecable, como la que ella profesaba
al convaleciente y poético misionero.

Ocurrió en esto un suceso que no se esperaba ya. De pronto, y cuando D. Acisclo se había resignado
a que su diputado fuese invisible para el distrito, éste le escribió anunciándole que inmediatamente
venía a visitarle. El primer pueblo en que se presentaría había de ser Villafría, desde donde,
a caballo, y con la pompa correspondiente, había de pasar a recorrer y visitar los otros pueblos.

Don Acisclo se alegró mucho de esta venida, que iba a darle la mayor importancia; pero tuvo
que afanarse para disponer bien las cosas, a fin de hacer a D. Jaime Pimentel una brillante
recepción. Para hospedarle con decoro y hasta con lujo, acudió a doña Luz pidiéndole las mejores
habitaciones de su casa solariega, no ocupadas por su sobrino; y para ofrecer a D. Jaime un
buen caballo en que montar e ir de pueblo en pueblo, acudió asimismo a doña Luz, pidiéndole
prestado su hermoso caballo negro. Doña Luz tuvo que acceder a todo.

La víspera del día en que debía llegar D. Jaime, todos estaban alborotados en el lugar con
la gran fiesta de la recepción que iba a haber. Hasta doña Manolita estaba más alegre que lo
de costumbre y muy parlanchina. En la tertulia diaria sólo asistían ella, doña Luz y el Padre,
porque los demás andaban aún ocupados en los preparativos de la fiesta, o descansando del ajetreo
de aquel día.

Entonces tuvo doña Manolita una ocurrencia algo maliciosa, y que, en su sentir, había de darle
mucha luz en sus investigaciones. ¿Por qué no había de embromar a doña Luz, pronosticando que
D. Jaime, de quien la fama decía maravillosos encomios, y que era libre y soltero, iba a enamorarse
de ella, apenas la viese, con el gustoso asombro de hallar en una villa pequeña tan completo
dechado de elegancia, distinción y hermosura? ¿Por qué, al embromar así a doña Luz, con algo
que la halagaría, no había de dar solapadamente una broma bastante pesada al Padre, cuyo amor,
enmarañado y turbio en el centro de la conciencia, se vendría a aclarar con el reactivo de
los celos? Doña Manolita, al dar la broma, miraría al Padre, a ver si se inmutaba o si permanecía
impasible, en apariencia al menos.

Como lo pensó, lo hizo. Doña Manolita dijo a doña Luz que D. Jaime iba a prendarse de ella,
apenas la viese; que D. Jaime no podía sospechar que, en un lugar tan arrinconado como Villafría,
estuviese oculto tanto tesoro; y que, a su ver, era evidente el amor futuro de D. Jaime.

--¿Qué forastero--prosiguió--, no se ha enamorado de ti, de cuantos han venido a Villafría,
jóvenes, libres y en estado de merecer? Prepara, pues, el almíbar con que sueles propinar las
calabazas, si es que también piensas dárselas a éste. Pero, ¿quién sabe? El pretendiente, que
ya columbro, no es rústico, ni lugareño, como los que has tenido hasta ahora. Dicen que es
la flor y nata de los elegantes de Madrid, y además un bizarro militar y un hombre de gran
porvenir y de extraordinario talento. ¿Serás tan fiera que también le desdeñes?

Doña Luz, sin enojarse, antes bien algo lisonjeada, contestó negando la validez del pronóstico,
y asegurando, con modestia un poco fingida, que don Jaime, acostumbrado a ver en la corte tantas
bellas mujeres, no repararía en ella ni le haría caso.

--Además--dijo doña Luz--, no haya miedo de que me pretenda ese caballero. Yo no soy lo que
se llama un buen partido. Para él se necesita una rica heredera, que dé alas a su ambición,
y no una señorita pobre que le encadene y le sirva de rémora y estorbo. Créeme, Manuela; ya
te lo he dicho mil veces: yo no me casaré nunca... ni quiero casarme. No hablemos de esas tonterías,
ni en broma.

Doña Manolita, durante estas frases que entre su amiga y ella se cruzaban, miró de soslayo
al Padre y creyó ver que se había puesto más pálido que de costumbre. Por lo demás el Padre
permaneció silencioso, y no dio su parecer ni sobre el enamoramiento posible de D. Jaime, ni
sobre el constante propósito de doña Luz de permanecer soltera.

A las diez se retiró a su casa, y las dos amigas quedaron solas.

Alentada entonces doña Manolita con lo bien que su primera broma había sido tolerada, y tal
vez agradecida como lisonja, en el fondo del alma de la hija del marqués, cayó en la tentación
de aventurarse a dar otra broma bastante menos ligera.

Sin reflexionarlo mucho, dijo, pues, de este modo:

--¡Ay! ¡Hija! Me arrepiento de haberte dicho lo de D. Jaime.

--¿Y por qué te arrepientes?--preguntó con sencillez doña Luz--. Yo no creo probable que ese
caballero cortesano se enamore de mí, en tres o cuatro días que ha de estar por aquí; pero
como ni eso es imposible, ni me ofende el que tú, estimándome en más de lo que merezco, me
vaticines tal triunfo, no tienes para qué arrepentirte, a no ser por el temor de exaltar demasiado
mi amor propio.

--No es ese temor--replicó la hija del médico--, lo que me induce al arrepentimiento, sino
el temor de haber lastimado un corazón sensible, de haberle hecho una profunda herida.

--No te comprendo--dijo doña Luz--; ¿qué quieres dar a entender? ¿Qué corazón sensible es ese?

--El del P. Enrique--respondió en mala hora doña Manolita.

Doña Luz se puso roja como la grana. Toda la sangre de su cuerpo se diría que se le subió a
la cabeza. Todo el orgullo de su casta se agolpó y amontonó en su corazón. No vio más que ridiculez
indigna en que la creyesen objeto de la pasión de un fraile. Ella creía que un fraile la podía
admirar por su talento, estimar por sus virtudes, venerar por su conducta intachable, y gustar
de su trato y conversación, y complacerse en ser su amigo; pero enamorarse de ella le parecía
tan absurdo, tan contrario a todas las conveniencias y leyes sociales y religiosas, tan monstruosamente
feo y chocante, que no quería, ni podía, ni debía sospecharlo en persona del juicio, de la
circunspección y hasta de la santidad que en el P. Enrique notaba. Doña Luz miró, pues, como
una malicia villana y ruin el pensamiento de doña Manolita, y como una insolencia la expresión
de dicho pensamiento por medio de la palabra.

--Lo que acabas de proferir--exclamó con la voz balbuciente de cólera--, es un insulto, es
una dura acusación contra el P. Enrique y contra mí. Ni el padre delira, ni yo le he dado ocasión
para que delire. A fin de que mi limpia fama esté al abrigo de la maledicencia, me he encerrado
en este lugar, me he apartado casi de todo trato humano, he huido de la juventud, mientras
he sido joven; siéndolo todavía, como lo soy, no he admitido en mi intimidad sino a viejos
de sesenta años como tu padre, el cura y don Acisclo, y nada de esto me ha valido. Porque yo,
de cerca de treinta años, me he abandonado, me he confiado con gusto, lo declaro francamente,
en la amistad honrada de un siervo de Dios, probado en mil fatigas, quebrantado por ellas,
lleno de ciencia y de virtud, no se concibe esta amistad, no se explica este trato, sino por
motivos viles e impuros. Y no son los rústicos del lugar, no son los que no me conocen, sino
mi mejor amiga la que me sospecha y me injuria.

La pobre doña Manolita se quedó aterrada: se compungió, y al cabo se le saltaron las lágrimas.

--Pero, mujer--dijo--; no te enojes por amor de Dios. Yo, sin duda, me he explicado mal. Yo
no digo que sea impuro el amor del Padre....

--¿Qué disparates son los tuyos?--interrumpió doña Luz--. ¿Qué extravío de ideas? ¿Qué necias
distinciones pretendes hacer? ¿Cómo cohonestar el amor de un fraile a una doncella honrada?
Tal amor es impuro siempre; es infame; es sacrílego.

Viendo doña Manolita que no había manera de remediar su torpeza, y apuradísima de haber irritado
tanto a doña Luz, a quien quería de todo corazón, no pronunció una sola palabra más; pero lloró
y sollozó como si le hubiese sobrevenido la más cruel desgracia.

Entonces doña Luz, que tenía buen fondo, a pesar de su soberbia, sintió que había estado dura
y áspera en demasía, y pidió perdón a doña Manolita, besándola y poco menos que llorando también.

Las dos amigas vinieron a quedar de resultas mucho más amigas que antes. Doña Luz se convenció
de que doña Manolita no había tenido intención de deslustrar en lo más mínimo la pureza de
sus relaciones amistosas con el P. Enrique; y doña Manolita hizo por convencerse y hasta se
convenció por el momento de que el P. Enrique, ni siquiera como Dante amó a Beatriz, como Petrarca
amó a Laura, o como don Quijote amó a Dulcinea, era capaz de amar a doña Luz; porque, siendo
él un fraile y ella una señorita muy bien educada y honestísima, tal amor, por alambicado,
espiritual e incorpóreo que fuese, tenía un no sé qué de indecorosamente plebeyo y de grotescamente
pecaminoso que con la condición de su bella y soberbia amiga se ajustaba muy mal.

No bien acabadas de hacer las paces, llegó don Acisclo con Pepe Güeto, quienes no advirtieron
las huellas de la pasada tempestad. Cenaron los cuatro en amistosa compañía, y con buen apetito,
y se fueron luego a dormir.

Al día siguiente se celebró con pompa y estruendo la entrada triunfal de D. Jaime en Villafría.
Cuantos tenían caballo, y no pocos que sólo tenían mulo o burro, fueron de madrugada a recibirle
en la estación, con D. Acisclo al frente, y a eso de las once volvieron todos con el diputado,
caballero éste en el hermoso caballo negro de doña Luz.

A las puertas del lugar salieron los muchachos y los hombres de a pie a recibir la lucida cabalgata,
y todos entraron por aquellas calles al son de las campanas que se habían echado a vuelo, entre
vivas y aclamaciones, y atronando el aire a tiros de cuantas escopetas estaban servibles en
Villafría.

-XIII-

Crisis

Después de haber rechazado con tan cruel desabrimiento las palabras de doña Manolita y después
de hechas las paces, doña Luz pensó a sus solas en el valor y motivo de aquellas palabras;
y, como si una claridad nueva y extraña iluminase los más oscuros laberintos de su cerebro,
creyó percibir la verdad de todo y reconoció que su amiga tenía algunos visos de razón al decir
lo que dijo.

Doña Luz se había enojado quizá porque su propia conciencia, aprovechándose de las palabras
de doña Manolita, había formulado una acusación mucho más severa. ¿Qué diferencia radical e
importante se da entre la amistad más tierna y exclusiva, entre la predilección más marcada
de un hombre por una mujer y de una mujer por un hombre, ninguno de los dos viejo aún, y el
amor más puro, más platónico y más sublime? Doña Luz se ponía a sí misma esta cuestión; y,
no acertando a resolverla sino en el sentido de que no se da diferencia, o que, si se da, apenas
es perceptible y se quiebra de puro sutil, decidía que no era absurdo ni insolencia suponer
y afirmar que estuviese enamorado de ella el P. Enrique. El Padre, encadenado por el respeto,
teniendo en cuenta su estado, sus votos y su posición, se había guardado bien de manifestar
su cariño de un modo que hiciese sospechar ni remotamente que no era legítimo y sin tacha;
pero, sin duda, que en el fondo de su alma le sentía.

Luego que doña Luz dejaba esto como sentado y evidente, se preguntaba también: «¿Y yo qué he
hecho para inspirar esta pasión? ¿Qué culpa adquiero de que él me ame? ¿Hasta qué punto he
dado y sigo dando pábulo a su afecto?». La contestación que doña Luz se daba era contradictoria
y confusa. Ora se condenaba; ora se absolvía. Se condenaba al reconocer que ella había disimulado
mucho menos que él la complacencia con que le oía, el contento que su vista le causaba, el
deleite que su conversación le traía siempre, y que ella por instinto irreflexivo, pero depravado,
gustaba de parecer hermosa y elegante a todos, y particularmente a las personas a quienes quería,
entre las cuales no podía menos de incluir al Padre.

Otra serie de consideraciones acudía luego a su mente para absolverla. Pues qué, ¿no era lícito
amar la ciencia, la virtud y el ingenio que en el Padre resplandecían? ¿Qué mal había en mostrarlo?
Y en cuanto al esmero en el adorno de su persona, ¿qué ley divina ni humana podía imponerle
la obligación de ocultar las prendas que el cielo le había dado y de no lucirlas hasta donde
esto es compatible con el más rígido decoro? De esta suerte se absolvía doña Luz; pero, prosiguiendo
en sus cavilaciones, añadía en su pensamiento: «Y si yo supongo que él me ama, ¿por qué no
ha de suponer él que le amo yo? Si yo no tengo motivo para suponerlo, si es mi vanidad quien
lo supone, bien puede él ser tan vanidoso como yo y suponerlo del mismo modo. Y si yo lo supongo
con motivo ¿el motivo que yo le he dado para que haga suposición idéntica es menor acaso?».
Doña Luz tenía entonces que confesarse que, atendidas la natural reserva que deben tener las
mujeres, y la modestia y timidez con que deben velar y mitigar los movimientos e inclinaciones
del corazón, ella había dado mayor motivo al Padre para que él la creyese enamorada que el
que él le había dado a ella para que de su parte lo creyese.

El proverbio dice que quien prueba mucho no prueba nada, y esto ocurría a doña Luz no bien
demostraba que, no sólo el Padre estaba enamorado de ella, sino que ella estaba enamorada del
Padre. Se examinaba el alma, se interrogaba el corazón, y como le respondían que no amaban
al Padre, volvía a creer que sólo su presunción podía hacerle imaginar que el Padre la amase
a ella. Lo único que, después de tantos rodeos, sacaba en claro doña Luz era que en aquella
convivencia e intimidad afectuosa y en aquellos coloquios tan sabios de ella con él, había
algo de ocasionado a perversas interpretaciones, algo de mal gusto, algo de pedantesco y lugareño
a la vez, que la parecía cómico, y cuya ridiculez se atenuaba sólo pensando que su vida en
un lugar no podía llevarla a menos necio extravío.

Doña Luz resolvió, pues, ser más cauta y menos expansiva en lo venidero, y no menudear tanto
las discusiones filosóficas y teológicas, y las confianzas y el trato con el venerable sobrino
del antiguo administrador de su casa.

«Si no hay--concluía ella--mutua y peligrosa inclinación en nuestras almas, pudiera suponerse,
y esto me ofendería, y si la hay, como la inclinación sería por todos estilos abominable, conviene
cortarla de raíz».

En cualquiera de ambos supuestos, reconoció doña Luz la necesidad de cambiar de conducta; la
conveniencia, valiéndonos de una frase española, algo anticuada, pero gráfica, de poner su
descuido en reparo.

La llegada a Villafría del triunfante y flamante diputado D. Jaime Pimentel y Moncada coincidió
casi con esta prudentísima, aunque algo tardía resolución.

Doña Luz, acompañada de su benigna amiga, estaba en una ventana baja, aguardando la aparición
de la pompa y del triunfo, que se anunciaba ya por el resonar de los tiros y de los vivas.

Don Jaime, cabalgando en medio de D. Acisclo y Pepe Güeto, precedido de una turba de muchachos
y de hombres a pie, y seguido de buen golpe de gente a caballo y aun de más gente pedestre,
se mostró al cabo a los ojos de nuestra heroína.

La fama no había mentido. Era D. Jaime todo un galán caballero. Montaba con gracia y firmeza.
Aunque tenía cerca de cuarenta años, parecía que apenas tenía treinta. Su traje sencillo dejaba
ver, en los pormenores todos, la elegancia y el buen gusto.

La cabalgata se paró a la puerta de D. Acisclo, y éste, seguido de su ahijado y huésped, se
halló pronto en la sala, donde aguardaban doña Luz y doña Manolita.

--Aquí tiene V. a nuestro diputado el Sr. D. Jaime--dijo D. Acisclo, presentándole a doña Luz--;
y luego añadió, dirigiéndose a D. Jaime:

--La señorita doña Luz, hija del difunto marqués de Villafría.

El recuerdo lejano y confuso de la alta sociedad madrileña, que doña Luz no había hecho sino
entrever hacía más de doce años, la idea vaga de un medio más culto y más aristocrático, las
formas y el ser soñados de damas y galanes, sus usos, discreteos, aventuras y amoríos, tales
cuales ella los había fantaseado o columbrado, sin llegarlos a ver ni a gozar, obligada, en
la aurora de su vida, a retirarse a un pueblo pequeño, todo acudió de súbito a la mente de
doña Luz, al mirar a D. Jaime Pimentel, al notar la soltura y naturalidad de sus distinguidos
modales, y al oír su acento y las pocas y atinadas palabras que le dirigió, las cuales ni pecaron
de frías y secas, ni se extremaron por lo galantes, sino que se encerraron dentro de los límites
de la más respetuosa discreción. Porque no era el inferior quien sintió doña Luz que le hablaba,
ni el cortesano insolente tampoco, cuya superioridad se revela al través de su fingida cortesía,
sino el hombre de la misma clase que ella, que habla como igual, pero con las atenciones delicadas
que a una señora principal se deben siempre. Doña Luz lo comprendió así, se complació en ello,
y lo agradeció todo. Harto advirtió el tono diverso que empleó don Jaime, al hablar con doña
Manolita, no bien a ella también le presentaron.

Dos días estuvo D. Jaime en Villafría, al cabo de los cuales fue menester proseguir la comenzada
tarea de visitar todos los lugares del distrito.

Durante estos dos días, D. Acisclo desplegó la más prodigiosa magnificencia. Tuvo, por decirlo
así, mesa de Estado. Toda su parentela, el médico, su hija y su yerno, y el cura D. Miguel,
almorzaron, comieron y hasta cenaron con él y con el agasajado D. Jaime. Éste se sentó siempre
a la derecha de doña Luz, y tuvo siempre a doña Manolita del otro lado.

Petra, el ama de llaves, hizo milagros en aquellos dos días. ¿Qué pavos rellenos, qué cocido
con morcilla, chorizo, embuchados y morcones, qué tortillas con espárragos trigueros, qué platazos
de pepitoria, qué menestras de cardos, morrillas y guisantes, qué jamón con huevos hilados,
qué tortas maimones, y qué deliciosas alboronías, picantes salmorejos, frescos gazpachos y
ensaladas, y variados arropes y almíbares, no condimentó o presentó en la mesa de su amo?

Los cinco mejores músicos del lugar vinieron por la noche con sus acordes y sonoros instrumentos,
y se bailó en la cuadra alta, porque la baja estaba como santificada por la Santa Cena.

Don Jaime bailó rigodón con doña Manolita y con una de las hijas de D. Acisclo; y con doña
Luz, no sólo bailó rigodón, sino también valsó.

Con doña Luz estuvo muy fino y amable, y doña Luz asimismo lo estuvo con él.

Los chistes urbanos, las anecdotillas picantes, sin rayar en libres, las pinturas de las intrigas
y lances de Madrid, referidos con ligereza y primor por don Jaime, divirtieron mucho a doña
Luz y la hicieron reír; cosa que le agradó y pasmó, porque no era fácil para la risa. Siempre
que la conversación era general, cuanto decía D. Jaime encantaba al auditorio, y todos le aplaudían.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>77189</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21824</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

In sum, not to tire my readers, I'll end by saying that Don finally picked Acisclo the reward
of his labors.

The elections came, and D. Acisclo won the election.

Congressman Don Jaime Pimentel left by a large majority.

Some want to imply that D. Acisclo did a thousand stage machinery and falsehoods, but nothing
could prove, and therefore should not believe.

Don Jaime Pimentel, without leaving the court, not just write a letter, with the highest calm,
was pleased to receive your certificate, almost clean, they only had two minor protests and ill-founded.

The
joy of D. Acisclo was great after the win. Lauro yours! Which shows of power that had just given!
With an invisible candidate, careless, lazy, with an enemy so strong, so unique, so as phoenix
pattern and the representatives of the people, had achieved win and win by a landslide. After
marveling at his own capacity for policy, only acknowledged debtor
D. Juan Fresco and abundant peat bermejinos that followed on the day
of the election as a respected leader.

Throughout this long election period, the friendly relations and Dona
Luz P. Enrique it was closing more every day.

To Dona Manolita, drifting of the enthusiasm of her husband, or share it, I never thought more than
in elections.

Doña Luz and father were certainly the only two people in a certain position in the whole district,
had not thought of this or the other candidate, and who had not toiled for victory any of them.

In the midst of political turmoil, had been found in the same withdrawal sweet home of those who
promoted, and there were talks soft and lofty, and pleasant conversations, you always learn something
Dona Luz, which was always new excellence in understanding and in
the heart of the father and the father, in turn, never failed to amaze
the clearance, sharpness, the remarkable discretion of poetic fantasy
and exquisite sensitivity its fine interlocutor.

Don Anselmo was third in the debates, although not as much, for having been too D. Acisclo very interested
in the election. And the priest Don Miguel had kept going to record to socialize, while Father's
wise dialogue and Dona Luz magnetized and enthralled him in such
a way, that within minutes of beginning to hear, he would stay asleep,
sometimes accompanied and animated with music and endless sound of
snoring.

It was from this that the only person who was really consistent and intelligent control of mutual
affection and intimate conversation of Mrs. Light and the Father, was Dona Manolita. I I do not
want to do this, or any of my heroes, better than they are or what they were. Doña Manolita
was not a dove without gall, and not because they hated someone, but because he kept have malice.
Rather, it could tick Dona Manolita have it. Rather it could be acknowledge that without envy
or bitterness, and just for the sake of art, like some gossip, and still too much, as a rule for his
judgments, that terrible sentence wrong and think be right. However, thanks to the loving devotion
that inspired him Dona Luz, she played always more benevolent side all his acts and speeches.
Therefore, although insight Dona Manolita long time could not hide that irresistible inclination
of two souls, Dona Manolita never failed to do justice to Dona Luz, and acknowledged and declared,
back in bottom of his chest, in her friend had not the slightest
intention of disrupting the mood Father's lure with flirting or blamed.

The

respect and affection of the doctor's daughter Fr Enrique were great too, but not both that any
failure would prevent something completely opposite of their behavior. Doña Manolita then,
without thinking that Dona Luz had given no occasion for it or why he began to suspect the Father,
more or less confused and vaguely, was in love. Respect for his friend and because in the
places people do not walk the ethereal subtleties or passed over still, and because to say something
she had given rise to be added much, Donna and her father Manolita entrusted with the results
of his observations. Entrusted only to Güeto Pepe, who was hiding anything; but demanding the
deepest secrecy.

The severity of the Father Dona Luz and cut flights to all the boldness of Dona Manolita who never
molested directing the Father, even as a joke and rodeos and circumlocution, indirect darker on
the passion that he imagined. Doña Manolita continued, however, watching. Pepe Güeto also
observed. Both spouses are then communicated what they had observed. Of Thus came the two to corroborate
the idea that the Father, perhaps without knowing it, loved Dona Luz by mystical and subtle
style, and that Dona Luz worship was left without assuming any disgusting term, without reflecting
on all the significance that this worship might have, and seeing in it more than a tender friendship,
friendly and impeccable, as she professed the convalescent and poetic
mission.

It happened in an incident that was not expected now. Suddenly, when D. Acisclo had resigned to
his deputy were invisible to the district, he immediately wrote him
telling him that came to visit.

The first town that was to be presented Villafría, whence horse, and the corresponding bubble,
was to pass to travel and visit other towns.

Don Acisclo was glad of this coming, which would give the greatest importance, but had to strive
to have good things to do D. Jaime Pimentel brilliant reception. To accommodate you with dignity
and even luxury, came to asking the best Dona Luz rooms of his ancestral
home, not occupied by his nephew, and to offer D. Jaime a good horse
to ride and go from village to village, also went to Dona Luz, asking
lent her beautiful black horse.

Luz had to agree to everything.

The day before they had to reach D. Jaime, everyone was abuzz in place with the great feast of
the reception would be. To Dona Manolita was more cheerful than usual and very talkative. In the
daily gatherings she attended only Dona Luz and the Father because
the rest were still busy with the preparations for the party, or relaxing
from the hustle that day.

Donna then had an occurrence Manolita something malicious, and that his feelings had to give much light
on their research. Why was not to tease Dona Luz, predicting that D. Jaime, who said fame wonderful
praise, and he was free and single, would love it, just to see her with the happy surprise of
finding in a small village as complete paragon of elegance, distinction and beauty? Why, to tease
and Dona Luz, with some the flatter, could not make a joke rather heavy covertly to the Father,
whose love, tangled and murky in the center of consciousness, it would clarify with the reagent jealousy?
Doña Manolita, after making a joke, I would look to the Father, to
see if they budge or remained impassive, seemingly at least.

As I said than done.

Manolita said Dona Dona Luz D. Jaime was going to fall in love with her, just saw her, that
D. Jaime did not suspect that in a place so cornered as Villafria much treasure was hidden, and
that, in his view, it was clear the future of D. Love Jaime.

- What stranger - he continued - not in love with you, who have come to Villafria young, free
and in a state of merit? Prepare, therefore, the syrup with you usually
tip the pumpkins, if you think also give to it.

But who knows? The suitor, which Columbro and is not rustic, or local, as you've had so far. They
say it the cream of the elegant Madrid, and also a brave soldier and a man of great future and extraordinary
talent. Will you be so fierce that also despise?

Doña Luz, without anger, but rather something flattered, responded by denying the validity of
the forecast, and ensuring, with a little mock modesty, that Don Jaime, accustomed to seeing
on the court so beautiful women, it would notice it or would ignore.

- In addition - "Dona Luz - no fear that I intend to that gentleman. I'm not what is called
a good game. For him it needs a rich heiress, to give wings to his ambition, and not a poor
girl that string and will serve as a burden and nuisance. Believe me, Manuela, and I've said
a thousand times, I never will marry me ... I do not want to marry.

Let's not talk nonsense, even in jest.

Doña Manolita during these sentences between her friend and she crossed, glanced Father and thought
he saw had been paler than usual.

Otherwise the Father remained silent and did not give their opinion
or possible crush on D. Jaime, no the constant aim of Dona Luz to
stay single.

At ten o'clock he retired to his home, and the two friends were left alone.

Dona Manolita then encouraged with how well his first joke was tolerated, and such Once grateful as
flattery, in the depths of the soul of the daughter of the Marquis,
was tempted venturing to make another joke a lot less light.

Without thinking much, he said, because, as follows:

- Ay! Daughter! I regret having said what's D. Jaime.

- Why do you regret? - Simply asked Dona Luz -. I do not think probable that courtly knight falls
in love with me, in three or four days you have to be here, but and even that is impossible, or
you are offended me, estimated at more than I deserve, I foretell such a triumph, you have to
do to repent, but for the fear of too exalted my pride.

- It's not that fear - said the doctor's daughter - which leads me to repentance, but fear of
having hurt a sensitive heart, of having made a deep wound.

- I do not understand - "Dona Luz -, what do you mean? What is this tender heart?

- The P. Enrique - said in an evil hour Mrs. Manolita.

Luz blushed scarlet. All the blood in his body would be turned up to head. All the pride of
caste was gathered and piled in his heart. Saw nothing but ridiculous indignant they believed
that the object of the passion of a friar. She believed that a friar could admired for their
talent, estimated by his virtues revered for its impeccable behavior, and taste their intercourse
and conversation, and pleased to be your friend, but seemed to fall in love so absurd, so contrary
to all the conveniences and social and religious laws, so monstrously ugly and shocking, I did
not want, or could, or should suspect it in person the trial, the
circumspection and even sanctity in the P. Enrique showed.

Luz looked for, as an evil villain and mean Manolita Dona thought
and expression as an insult of that thinking through the floor.

-
What you have just uttered - said in a voice stammering with rage
- is an insult, it a harsh accusation against Fr Henry and me.

Neither the father is delirious, and I have given occasion to rave. A clean so that my fame
is protected from slander, I've enclosed in this place, I have separated
almost everything humanely, I fled the youth, while I was young, be
so still, as I am, I have admitted my privacy but old sixty years
as your father, the priest, Don Acisclo, and none of this has earned
me.

For me, about thirty years I have left, I have trusted with pleasure, I declare frankly in friendship
honored servant of God, tested in a thousand hardships, broken by them, full of science and
virtue, not conceived this friendship, this treatment is not explained,
but vile and impure motives.

And there are the rustic place, not that I do not know, but my best friend and me I suspect injury.

Poor
Donna was terrified Manolita: is pricked, and after he burst into tears.

- But, my dear - he said -, do not get mad for love of God. I certainly have explained me wrong.
I I'm not saying that is impure the Father's love ....

- What nonsense are yours? - Interrupted Dona Luz -. What loss of ideas? What foolish distinctions
intend to do? How do you explain away the love of a brother to a girl honored? Such love is
always impure, is infamous, it is sacrilegious.

Viewing Dona Manolita there was no way to remedy his clumsiness, and have irritated apuradísima
both Dona Luz, whom he loved with all my heart, did not utter a single word, but cried and sobbed as
if he had come upon the most cruel misfortune.

Then Dona Luz, who had a good background, despite his pride, he felt he had been hard rough and too
much, and apologized to Mrs. Manolita, kissing and all but crying
too.

The two friends came to get a result much more friendly than before. Luz was convinced Dona Manolita
that he had not intended to tarnish in the least purity friendly
relations with the P. Henry, and Mrs. Manolita made by convincing
and even convinced by the time that P. Henry, even as Dante loved
Beatrice, like Petrarch Laura loved, or loved Dulcinea Don Quixote,
was able to doña Luz love, because, being him a monk and she a highly
educated lady and honestísima, such love, convoluted, spiritual and
incorporeal as it was, had a something unseemly and grotesque commoner
the sinful condition of your beautiful and superb fitted very bad
friend.

No well-finished to make peace, came Don Pepe Güeto Acisclo who did not notice last traces of
the storm.

They dined in the four friendly company, and with good appetite,
and then went to sleep.

The next day was celebrated with pomp and din the triumphal entry of D. Jaime in Villafría.
Few had horses, and not a few who had only mule or donkey, went at dawn to greet at the station,
with D. Acisclo the front, and about eleven o'clock they all returned to the deputy, Knight him
in the beautiful black horse Dona Luz.

At the gates of the place came the boys and men on foot to receive the ride lucida, and they
all went through the streets to the sound of the bells that were cast in flight between live
and cheers, and thunderous shot from air guns were serviceable in many Villafría.

-XIII-

Crisis

Having rejected as cruel despondency Manolita Dona words and then
of made peace, Dona Luz thought to their own in the value and purpose
of those words; and, as if a strange new light illuminate the darkest
labyrinths of his brain, thought he heard the whole truth and acknowledged
that his friend had some show of reason to say he said.

Luz was angry perhaps because his own conscience, taking advantage of the words Dona Manolita had
entered a more severe charge. What difference is radical and important is between the tender and
exclusive friendship between the most marked predilection a man for a woman and a woman by
a man, neither old yet, and love purest, most sublime Platonic? Luz itself is put this matter, and
not conceive resolve but in the sense that no difference occurs, or, if given, only is obvious and
subtle cigar breaks, I decided it was not absurd or insolence to
assume and claim that she was in love with Fr Enrique.

Father, chained by respect, taking into account their state, their votes and positions, he had
kept well to state their love in a way that would make even remotely suspect that it was not legitimate
and unblemished; but certainly in the bottom of his soul he felt.

Dona Luz after leaving this as sitting and obvious, he asked again: "What about me I done to inspire
this passion? What acquire fault that he loves me? To what extent have given and continue
to give fuel to his affection? ". The answer was that Dona Luz was contradictory and confusing.
Ora was condemned, now is absolved. Was condemned to recognize that she had concealed much less
than the complacency with which he heard him, the glad sight caused him, the delight in his
conversation he always brought, and she instinctively reckless, but depraved, liked to look
beautiful and elegant at all, and particularly people who wanted among which could not fail to
include the Father.

Another set of considerations came into his mind then to acquit her. Why, do not lawful love
science, virtue and wit that sparkled in the Father? What wrong had to show it? And as for care
in the adornment of her person, what divine or human law could impose the obligation to conceal
the clothes that heaven had given him and not show them off to where this is consistent with
the most rigid decorum? Thus Dona Luz was acquitted, but continuing in thought, he added in
his thinking: "If I guess he loves me, why not must suppose him that I love? If I have no
reason to suppose, if my vanity who it is, well can he be so vain as me and guess the same way. And
if I guess with "the reason why I have given to make the same assumption is less chance?".
Luz then had to confess that, having regard to the natural reserve
that should have women, and the modesty and timidity should ensure
that mitigate the movements and inclinations heart, she had more reason
to the Father so that he believed that love that he had given her
for on his part, believe.

The proverb says that whoever proves much proves nothing, and this
occurred not well Dona Luz showed that not only the Father was in
love with her, but she was in love Fr.

Examined the soul, the heart was questioned, and as he answered that they did not love Father,
again believe that the presumption could only imagine that the Father do love her to it. All that,
after so many detours, drew Dona Luz was clear at that loving and
living and privacy in those conversations so wise of her to him was
led to some perverse interpretations, some tacky, some pedantic and
local at a time, that seemed funny, and ridiculous as thinking that
was attenuated only his life could not take place unless foolish error.

Luz

decided, therefore, be more cautious and less expansive in the future, not often both philosophical
and theological discussions, and trusts and dealing with the venerable nephew the former manager
of his home.

"If there is - she concluded - and dangerous mutual inclination in
our souls, could be expected, and this offended me, and if so, as
the inclination would be abhorrent in every way, it root cutting.

"

In either event, Dona Luz recognized the need for change of behavior, the convenience, availing
of a Spanish phrase, somewhat dated, but graphic, put your neglect in repair.

The arrival of the triumphant and newly Villafría MP D. Jaime Pimentel and coincided Moncada almost
to the prudent, if somewhat belated resolution.

Doña Luz, accompanied by her friend benign, was on a low window, waiting for the appearance
the pomp and triumph, which was foreshadowed by the ringing of the
dead and alive.

Don Jaime, riding through D. Pepe Güeto Acisclo and preceded by a
mob of boys and men on foot, and followed by a good crowd of people
on horseback and even more people walking, was after all in the eyes
of our heroine.

Fame had not lied. Was D. Jaime all a gallant gentleman. He rode with grace and determination.
Although he was nearly forty years, it seemed that he was only thirty. Her simple dress left
see in details all the elegance and good taste.

The cavalcade stopped at the door D. Acisclo, and this, followed by his godson and guest, soon found
in the room, where waiting and Dona Dona Luz Manolita.

- Here is V. our MEP Mr D. Jaime - said D. Acisclo, presenting Dona Luz -; and then he said to D.
Jaime:

- Miss Dona Luz, daughter of the late Marquis of Villafría.

The distant memory and confusion of Madrid's high society that Dona Luz had only interviews for more
than twelve years, the vague idea of ??a more educated and aristocratic,
the forms and be dreamed of ladies and gallants, their uses, discreteos,
adventure and romance, such which she had fantasized or discerned,
without seeing or enjoy, bound, the dawn of life, to retire to a small
town, everything suddenly came to mind Dona Luz, looking at D. Jaime
Pimentel, noting the ease and naturalness of his distinguished manners,
and to hear his accent and the few and sensible words addressed to
you, which neither sinned of cold and dry, or end by the gallant,
but are locked within more respectful of discretion.

Because there was less Dona Luz who felt that he was speaking, nor the insolent courtier either,
which reveals the superiority through their feigned politeness, but the man of the same class
as her, speaking as an equal, but with the attentions than a leading lady should be provided.
Luz understood this, was pleased about it, and thanked him for everything.

Harto said different tone he used Don Jaime, speaking with Dona Manolita, no sooner had she too.

Two
days were D. Jaime in Villafría, after which it was necessary to continue the started task of visiting
all parts of the district.

During these two days, D. Acisclo deployed the most prodigious magnificence.

Had, so to speak and table of state. All her relatives, the doctor, his daughter and her husband,
and the priest D. Miguel, lunch, ate and even had dinner with him
and Pacino D. Jaime.

He always sat right of Doña Luz, Doña Manolita always had the other side.

Petra, the housekeeper, performed miracles in those two days.

What stuffed turkeys, which cooked with sausage, chorizo, sausage and morcones, what tortillas with
green asparagus, which platazos the fricassee, which stews thistles, Morrill and peas, ham
and eggs which yarn what maimones cakes, and what delicious alboronía, salmorejos spicy, fresh
gazpacho and salads, and various syrup and syrup, not flavored or
presented in the table of his master?

The five best musicians in
the place came at night with its sonorous chords and instruments,
and danced at the high block, because the floor was as sanctified
by the sacrament.

Don Jaime and Dona Manolita quadrille danced with
one of the daughters of D. Acisclo and Dona Light not only quadrille
danced, but also the waltz.

Dona Luz was very fine and friendly,
and the Dona Luz was also with him. 

Urban jokes, the anecdotillas
spicy, without bordering on free paintings intrigue and sets of Madrid,
in relation with lightness and delicacy by Don Jaime, had a great
time to Dona Light and made her laugh, something that pleased him
and stunned, because it was easy to laugh. Always that the conversation
was general, the said D. Jaime loved the audience, and everyone applauded.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>