<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03750</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>25</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24211</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

FEDERICO DI ROBERTO

ESPASMO

BUENOS AIRES

1909

INDICE

   I.--El hecho
  II.--Las primeras indagaciones
 III.--Los recuerdos de Roberto Vérod
  IV.--Historia de una alma
   V.--Duelo
  VI.--La investigación
 VII.--La confesión
VIII.--La carta
  IX.--Espasmo

Para hacer conocer la literatura romántica italiana, en sus elementos más modernos y en sus
tendencias más recientes, difícilmente podríamos haber encontrado algo más a propósito que
un autor como Federico di Roberto y un libro como Espasmo.

Federico di Roberto tendrá ahora treinta y seis años. Es siciliano, como Verga, el autor de
Cavalleria rusticana, con el cual su talento literario presenta algún parecido. Como Verga,
también es un realista, de un realismo que ostenta el color luminoso de la isla nativa. Sus
novelas son de una gran intensidad dramática--aun cuando conservan en sus lineamientos una
elegancia impecable,--algo de aristocrático en la concepción y en la forma, que se revela en
todas sus páginas y que caracterizan al joven escritor de una manera feliz. Con Arabeseos e
Historias breves inició brillantemente su carrera literaria, en la que, a pesar de estar en
sus comienzos, ha logrado éxitos de resonancia con I Viceré y con este Espasmo que hoy ofrecemos
a los lectores argentinos, y cuya traducción directa del idioma en que fue escrito mereció
de nuestra parte especial cuidado.

En el drama que se desarrolla en este libro intervienen pasiones intensas y opuestas. Su ambiente
es una ciudad de Suiza; el drama se desarrolla entre refugiados nihilistas, y es la lucha ardiente
del deber impuesto por la fe política contra una pasión violenta y arrebatadora. Sobre tal
contraste, que da lugar a escenas emocionantes y en que se mueven personajes intensamente humanos,
se funda el argumento de esta novela, acerca de la cual no diremos nada más para no malograr
la conmoción honda y sincera que ella produce en el ánimo del lector.

Como se podrá notar fácilmente, Federico di Roberto representa en la moderna literatura de
Italia una nota nueva para nosotros, diferenciándose completamente de D'Annunzio, Fogazzaro
y D'Amicis, que son los novelistas italianos más conocidos en el exterior. Y, al leer Espasmo,
estamos seguros de que los lectores de buen gusto nos tendrán en cuenta el haberles hecho conocer
un vigoroso talento que encarna, puede decirse, la nueva forma de la literatura romántica italiana
en esta época.

ESPASMO

I

EL HECHO

Todos los que pasaron el otoño de 1894 en las orillas del lago de Ginebra, recuerdan sin duda
todavía el trágico suceso de Ouchy, que produjo tanta impresión y proporcionó tan abundante
alimento a la curiosidad, no sólo de las colonias de gente en vacaciones esparcidas en todas
las estaciones del lago, sino también del gran público cosmopolita, al que los diarios lo refirieron.

El 5 de octubre, pocos minutos antes de mediodía, el estampido de un arma de fuego y gritos
confusos salidos de la villa Cyclamens, situada en mitad del camino de Lausana a Ouchy, interrumpieron
violentamente la habitual tranquilidad del lugar y atrajeron a los vecinos y transeúntes. La
villa Cyclamens estaba alquilada a una señora milanesa, la Condesa d'Arda, que la ocupaba todos
los años, de junio a noviembre. La amistad de la Condesa con el Príncipe Alejo Zakunine, revolucionario
ruso que había sido condenado primero en su país, expulsado en seguida de todos los Estados
de Europa y refugiado últimamente en el territorio de la Confederación, era conocida desde
tiempo atrás.

Los dos amantes se encontraban en la villa el día de la tragedia; y los gritos, del mismo Príncipe
Zakunine, junto con la detonación del arma, hicieron acudir a los sirvientes despavoridos,
a cuyos ojos apareció un tremendo espectáculo: la Condesa yacía exánime al pie de la cama,
la sien derecha perforada por un proyectil, y un revólver cerca de su mano. Y por más que la
vista de la muerte, de la muerte repentina y violenta, sea tal que ninguna otra la aventaje
en horror, la presencia de ese cadáver no era, sin embargo, lo que producía una emoción más
fuerte, sino el aspecto del sobreviviente. Semejante a una pálida azalea cruzada por rayas
rojas, el frío rostro de la infeliz, manchado parcialmente de sangre, tenía el color de la
cera, pero nada en él revelaba las contracciones de la agonía: por el contrario, una serena
confianza y algo como una sonrisa todavía viviente le animaban; Levemente apartados los violáceos
labios, detrás de los cuales asomaba apenas la perlada línea de los dientes; abiertos los párpados,
las pupilas vueltas hacia el cielo, la muerta parecía estar en éxtasis, como si aún no hubiese
abandonado la existencia del todo, deseosa de poder atestiguar que fuera de la vida humana,
en el silencio y en la sombra, había por fin hallado el bienestar y la alegría. Lívido, desencajadas
las facciones, los cabellos en desorden sobre la frente empapada en sudor glacial, loca la
mirada, temblorosos los labios, las manos, todo el cuerpo, como si fuera presa de la fiebre,
el Príncipe Alejo infundía pavor. Después de haber pedido auxilio con voz ronca y a gritos,
se había arrodillado junto al cadáver y lo abrazaba, ensangrentándose todo, y de su convulsa
boca no salían más que dos palabras breves y monótonas:

--¡Se acabó!... ¡Se acabó!...

En aquellas palabras, en el desgarrado acento con que las repetía, había un desconsuelo, una
amargura, una desesperación tan grande, que la muerta no parecía ya merecer tanta compasión
como el vivo, como aquel hombre inconsolable, abrumado por el dolor, que parecía, él también,
próximo a perder el aliento. Y a ratos, cuando sus manos se cansaban de acariciar las manos,
los cabellos, las ropas de la muerta, se las llevaba al cuello con ademán violento, cual si
quisiera estrangularse: entonces los criados, todas las personas que habían acudido, trataban
de consolarle, de arrancarle a ese espectáculo cruel; pero él, con ímpetu salvaje, rechazaba
a todos lejos de sí, extendía los brazos, se paraba, y después de recorrer con paso inseguro,
cual si estuviera ebrio, el cuarto mortuorio, volvía a desplomarse junto al cadáver.

La villa estaba abierta para todos; nadie pensaba en impedirles su acceso. De la cercana Casa
de Salud había acudido prontamente el doctor Bérard, quien sólo había podido comprobar la muerte
instantánea. La noticia se iba propagando rápidamente entre la colonia de extranjeros, y los
curiosos afluían a la villa, en especial los que conocían a la Condesa y al Príncipe; pero
ninguno podía obtener noticias de lo acontecido, a no ser de los sirvientes. Zakunine parecía
sordo y ciego, no reconocía a las personas que se le acercaban, que intentaban estrecharle
la mano, ni oía las palabras de pésame, las frases de dolorida simpatía que le dirigían.

Tampoco las respuestas de los criados arrojaban mucha luz sobre el suceso. Refiriéndose solamente
a las circunstancias exteriores de la catástrofe, contaban todos que el Príncipe había vuelto
a la villa dos días antes, después de una ausencia de algunas semanas; que la señora se había
levantado esa mañana más temprano que de costumbre y había permanecido como una hora en el
terrado, mientras su compañero trabajaba en el escritorio, con una dama que había llegado como
a las nueve; que antes del almuerzo la Condesa había enviado a la ciudad, con unos encargos,
a Julia, la doncella italiana que tenía desde hacía largo tiempo; que, cuando ya iba el almuerzo
a ser servido, el disparo había hecho estremecer a todos: que del segundo piso, donde estaban
las habitaciones de los patrones, se había lanzado el Príncipe al piso bajo como un loco, pidiendo
que se llamara a un médico, y que todos habían subido precipitadamente al cuarto de la Condesa,
donde la extranjera, después de intentar en vano socorrer a aquélla, había tratado, igualmente
en vano, consolar al desesperado Príncipe.

En medio de la confusión pocos habían notado la presencia de la extranjera. Era ésta una joven
de veinte años apenas; cabellos de un rubio azafranado, cortos, peinados como los de un hombre;
ojos claros y mirada fría; estatura más bien pequeña: estaba vestida de negro de pies a cabeza.
Se mantenía derecha e inmóvil en el ángulo de una ventana, los brazos cruzados, la cabeza inclinada,
y casi no se daba cuenta de la curiosidad que su presencia comenzaba a excitar.

En el círculo que formaban los más curiosos de los presentes, estaba la Baronesa de Börne,
dama austriaca, gruesa y de baja estatura, la única de su sexo que había acudido a la villa,
y que miraba fijamente a la extranjera, abrumando al mismo tiempo con sus preguntas a los criados,
quienes no sabiendo qué contestar se mezclaban en los grupos a comentar lo ocurrido.

--¡Pobre mujer!... ¡Pobre amiga!...--exclamaba la Baronesa.--Pero ¿por qué?... ¿Cómo ha podido?...
¿Y no ha escrito nada? ¿No han encontrado algo dejado por ella?... Tiene que haber algo...
buscando... ¿Murió en el instante?... Sufría, es cierto; ¡pero no tanto que no pudiera resistir!...
Era fuerte, una mujer muy fuerte, a pesar de su cuerpecito tenue y delicado... Los dolores
morales...

Y en voz más baja, dirigiendo la palabra a un joven inglés de bigotes colorados, ojos azules
y frente calva, le insinuó:

--¿Cree usted que fuera feliz?

El interrogado respondió con un ademán ambiguo, que tanto podía significar asentimiento como
duda o ignorancia.

--¡Y ese pobre Príncipe!...--continuó la Baronesa, siempre mirando por lo bajo, continuamente,
a la extranjera.--Es un dolor verle sufrir así... Sería necesario que alguien le persuadiera
de que se alejara...--Y estas palabras iban encaminadas directamente a la joven desconocida;
pero como ésta no contestara, la Baronesa propuso:--¿Por qué no ponen por lo menos el cadáver
sobre la cama?

Hablaba desde el grupo formado en torno del cadáver, y, al ver que los circunstantes, aprobaban
sus observaciones, pidió y obtuvo que la dejaran pasar. Entonces se acercó al Príncipe, que
estaba en ese momento apoyado contra la cama, los brazos colgando, contraídas las manos y los
extraviados ojos todavía vueltos hacia la muerta.

--No podemos dejarla así... deseamos ponerla sobre la cama... ¿Quiere usted?

Pero él no contestó, ni pareció siquiera haber oído, y al ponerle la Baronesa una mano en el
hombro, tembló como sacudido por una corriente magnética: su mirada extraviada, perdida, desconsolada
expresaba una angustia tan pavorosa, que la locuaz señora se encontró por un momento con que
le faltaban las palabras.

--¡Qué desgracia!... ¡Qué dolor!...--dijo turbada.--¡Pero hay, sin embargo, que tener fuerza
suficiente para resignarse al destino!... Doctor--agregó, volviéndose hacia Bérard, que se
acercaba en ese momento al Príncipe.--Desearíamos retirar de allí el cadáver... ¡Me figuro
a ratos que la pobrecilla sufre en el suelo!... Y a toda esta gente, ¿no se la podría pedir
que se alejara?

--Sí... cierto...--contestó el doctor vacilante y sin saber qué hacer.--Pero antes de resolver
nada, hay que esperar la llegada de los magistrados...

--¿Se les ha avisado?

--Aquí llegan.

Efectivamente, el murmullo de las voces acababa de extinguirse en la sala contigua, y en ese
instante entraba el juez de paz del circuito Lausana, el comisario de policía, un médico y
dos gendarmes.

Lo primero que hizo el juez fue ordenar que se alejara a los indiscretos del cuarto mortuorio
y de la sala, y cumplida esta orden, los gendarmes se colocaron en la puerta que comunicaba
aquella sala con el otro saloncito, para impedir que la gente volviera. Sólo quedaron con el
cadáver, la extranjera, el doctor Bérard, y su colega de la policía, a quien explicaba la inutilidad
de toda curación y la rapidez de la muerte; la Baronesa de Börne, que sin que nadie se lo pidiera,
informaba de lo sucedido al juez; éste, el Príncipe y el comisario.

--¿A qué se atribuye su funesta resolución? ¿No había algo que la hiciese prever?--preguntó
el juez; y la Baronesa, no obstante ser incapaz de callarse, por esa vez se limitó a encogerse
de hombros y mirar al Príncipe, para significar que éste era el único que podía contestar.

Zakunine se pasó una mano por la frente, como si se despertara de un profundo sueño, y dijo:

--Sí, había que preverlo... Yo he debido preverlo...

--¿Sufría mucho?

--¡Sufría tanto... tanto!...--respondió el Príncipe, con una entonación de tristeza tan profunda,
que el mismo magistrado se sintió conmovido.

--¿Estaba enferma?--preguntó el juez al doctor, después de un breve silencio.

--Sí: de una afección del pecho.

--¿Sabía lo que tenía?

--Sin duda. No era posible ocultarle nada. Era tan inteligente y valerosa, que las mentiras
compasivas eran inútiles con ella.

--¿No se podía tener esperanzas de salvarla?

--Su enfermedad era de aquellas sobre el desenlace de las cuales no cabe engaño, pero que mediante
un régimen apropiado permiten vivir aún largos años.

--¿Entonces no es la enfermedad lo único que la ha impulsado a matarse?

--No es lo único--repitió como un eco el Príncipe Alejo.

Muy curiosa, casi cómica, era durante aquel triste interrogatorio la actitud de la Baronesa
de Börne, la cual, ya que no podía hablar apretaba los labios, movía los ojos, sacudía la cabeza,
inclinaba todo el cuerpo, como si sucesivamente repitiera las preguntas del juez y confirmara
las respuestas del médico y del Príncipe, para hacer ver que ella había previsto las unas y
las otras, y advertir por señas que también ella tenía una observación que hacer. Y de vez
en cuando interrumpía:

--¡Eso es!... ¡Asimismo!... ¡Exactamente!... Y teniendo los sentimientos religiosos que tenía...

--¿Cuáles eran?--preguntó el juez.

--Pocas mujeres he conocido de una fe tan sólida y ardiente--contestó el doctor.

--¿Es cierto?...--interrumpió otra vez la Baronesa.--¡Parece increíble lo grande que era su
fervor! Yo tengo motivos para saberlo. No daba un paseo sin que su término no fuera una iglesia.
Sus excursiones preferidas eran en el distrito de Echallens, a Bretigny, a Assens, a Villars-le-Terroir,
a causa de las iglesias católicas que encontraba por allí.

Los domingos y fiestas pasaba largas horas aquí, en San Luis, arrodillada hasta que le faltaban
las fuerzas... Y esa era la observación que yo quería hacer a usted: que es por demás increíble
cómo, con tanta fe, ha podido hacer lo que ha hecho.

El Príncipe no hablaba. El temblor nervioso que al principio le sacudía iba calmándose; la
convulsa, violenta, pavorosa expresión de su rostro lívido y de sus ojos enrojecidos se iba
transformando: pálido, agotado, sin fuerzas, parecía él también próximo a caer.

--¿Estaba sola cuando se mató?

--Sola.

--¿Habló usted con ella esta mañana?

--Sí; habló con ella.

--¿Estaba triste?

--Mortalmente.

--Podríamos ver si ha dejado algo escrito.

La Baronesa dio una palmada y exclamó:

--¡Eso es lo que yo he dicho desde el principio!

El comisario, a una señal del juez, se puso a buscar.

Pocos muebles había en el cuarto de la muerta. La cama, un ropero con espejo, una cómoda, un
pequeño escritorio colocado contra la ventana, en plena luz, y en un ángulo una mesita de trabajo,
era todo lo que formaba el menaje. Sobre el escritorio había dos pilas de libros ingleses con
cubiertas blancas; una caja de papel de cartas; una bombonera antigua, y un saco de viaje.
En la mesita de trabajo y en el velador había más libros. El comisario los registraba uno por
uno, abría los cajones de los muebles, ninguno de los cuales estaba cerrado con llave, y después
de echar una ojeada a los objetos de elegancia femenina de que estaban llenos, los volvía a
cerrar. En el escritorio estaba la correspondencia de la difunta, en cajas de cartón bastante
viejas y una cartera llena de valores italianos y franceses así como algunos miles de pesos
en monedas de oro y plata. En el fondo de la gaveta de la derecha encontró el comisario un
estuche en forma de libro forrado en terciopelo negro, y cerrado con una minúscula llave: ya
iba a abrirlo, cuando el Príncipe dio un paso hacia él, diciendo:

--Ese es un libro de memorias... el diario de su vida...

Por el tono en que hacía esa indicación, por la actitud de toda su persona, parecía que quisiera
defender contra las miradas indiscretas el pensamiento íntimo de su pobre amiga; pero la Baronesa
de Börne exclamó, aproximándose al juez, que ya había tomado de las manos del comisario el
libro extraído por éste de su negra caja:

--¡Allí precisamente se puede encontrar algo!...

También la cubierta del libro era negra, con broches de plata, como un libro mortuorio y su
sola vista expresaba la tristeza y el dolor que debían haber amargado la vida de aquella desventurada.
El juez recorrió rápidamente las tapas: la letra era más bien grande, delgada, poco acentuada,
elegante y de una nitidez admirable. Casi las tres cuartas partes del libro estaban escritas.
El juez consagró su mayor atención a las últimas páginas; pero después de haber leído, dejó
caer la cabeza y:

--No se entiende--dijo--no es una confesión...

Mientras tanto, el comisario continuaba sus investigaciones en una pequeña habitación contigua
al cuarto de vestirse, donde otro ropero, el lavatorio y los baúles ocupaban todo el lugar
disponible. Pero tampoco allí encontró ninguna carta. Entonces volvió al dormitorio, lo atravesó,
y entró en la sala: allí el registro fue aún más breve o inútil, pues aparte del diván y los
sillones, sólo había una mesa llena de menudos objetos de uso, y luego el piano, sobre el cual
se veía un cuaderno con composiciones de Pessard. Ya el comisario volvía sobre sus propios
pasos, cuando un ruido de voces, exclamaciones de angustia le hicieron regresar; los gendarmes,
obedientes a las órdenes que habían recibido, impedían la entrada a una mujer vestida de obscuro,
que llevaba en la cabeza el velo negro de la gente del pueblo lombardo.

--¡Ah, señor! ¡Ah, señor!...--exclamaba la mujer, juntando las manos, el flaco rostro surcado
por ardientes lágrimas.--¡Quiero verla!... ¡Verla una vez más!... ¡Mi patrona... mi buena patrona!
¡Ah, señor, verla!...

Era Julia, que en ese momento volvía de la ciudad. Bajita y delgada, algo entrada en años,
parecía anonadada por la angustia.

--Dejadla pasar--ordenó el magistrado, a quien la Baronesa explicaba que, sirvienta de la Condesa
durante muchos años, esa mujer había gozado de toda su confianza.

Y cuando entró, sollozante y lacrimosa, juntas las manos, y se adelantó hacia el cadáver, el
mismo estremecimiento nervioso de antes volvió a sacudir el cuerpo del Príncipe; en su rostro
volvieron a leerse aquel desfallecimiento de terror, aquel pavoroso dolor, como si la vista
de una persona cara a la muerta, su presencia allí, hicieran recrudecer su tormento. Ya no
miraba al cadáver sino a la desconsolada mujer, y parecía querer acercársela, juntarse con
ella, como para unir los dolores de ambos, para hablarla de la muerta, para oírla hablar de
ella. Todos, hombres de justicia, médicos, hasta la misma Baronesa se sentían impresionados
por la ansiosa actitud de aquel desdichado: sólo la extranjera permanecía inmóvil y rígida,
impasible y casi sin mirar a nadie.

--¡Lo decía y lo ha hecho!... ¡Ha hecho lo que decía!...--gemía la mujer junto al cadáver.--Deseaba
la muerte, la llamaba... ¡Ah, pobrecilla!... ¡Ah, señores!... Y me mandó afuera, me mandó...
para estar libre... ¡para que no se lo leyese en la cara! ¡Ah, si hubiera estado junto a ella!...
¡Cuántas veces, pobrecita, cuántas veces, rogó a Dios que la hiciera morir!... ¡Y se ha matado!...--repetía
con voz aún más afligida, como si hasta ese momento hubiera podido dudar y esperar, y de repente
recibiera la confirmación indudable de semejante desgracia. ¡Se ha matado!... ¡Está muerta!
¡Señor! ¡Señor!...

La Baronesa se pasó la mano por los ojos, suspiró y atrajo hacia su pecho a la criada.

--¡Basta, basta, pobre mujer!... ¡No hay más remedio que conformarse!... ¡Cálmese usted!....
¡Basta!... Lo mejor es que diga usted a estos señores, a la justicia, ¿adonde la mandó, a usted?
¿A qué la mandó?

--A la ciudad, a pagar unas cuentas... a comprar cosas... Yo no sé más... Parecía, cuando se
levantó de la cama, como si quisiera ir conmigo... después cambió de opinión, y me mandó...

--¿La dio a usted alguna carta? ¿Sabe usted si escribió alguna carta, anoche o esta mañana?

--Anoche no: esta mañana. Esta mañana escribió una carta.

--¿A quién estaba dirigida?

--A sor Ana.

--¿Quién es sor Ana?--preguntó el magistrado, que había dejado pacientemente a la verbosa señora
formular el interrogatorio.

--Sor Ana Brighton, su antigua maestra inglesa.

--¿Dónde está?

--No sé. En el sobre estaba el nombre del lugar, un nombre extranjero.

--¿Usted tampoco sabe esa dirección?--preguntó el juez, volviéndose hacia el Príncipe Alejo.

--La ignoro, pero...

Su ansiedad parecía ir calmándose. Ya iba a decir algo, cuando se volvió a oír en el fondo
de la sala a los agentes de policía que impedían la entrada a alguien. Pero esa vez la inesperada
persona no se lamentaba, no lloraba; con voz vibrante, irritada y casi imperiosa, decía:

--¡Déjenme pasar!... ¡necesito entrar, les digo!...

Al mismo tiempo que el comisario iba a ver quién era, Bérard y la Baronesa de Börne se acercaban
a la puerta.

--¡Vérod!--exclamó la Baronesa al ver a un joven alto, corpulento, de cabellos negros y bigote
rubio, que decidido a forzar la consigna, entró a prisa cuando los guardias, a una seña de
su superior, se hicieron a un lado. Pero después de haber realizado su intento y avanzar rápidamente
los primeros pasos, el recién venido pareció de pronto titubear, vacilante: la irritación que
le encendía el rostro fue cediendo ante la confusión y la angustia. Al llegar al umbral y ver
al cadáver se llevó una mano al corazón, se recostó contra el marco de la puerta, intensamente
pálido, a punto casi de desmayarse.

--¡Nuestra pobre amiga!--exclamó otra vez la Baronesa, tendiéndole la diestra, cual si quisiera
confortarle, infundirle valor.--¡Quién lo habría dicho!... ¿No parece un sueño?... ¡Pobre,
pobre amiga!... Matarse así...

Pero el joven se repuso, y avanzando un paso más dijo con fuerte voz:

--No.

Un movimiento de inquietud y estupor pasó por entre los presentes.

--¿Qué dice usted?--preguntó el juez, acercándose a Vérod y mirándole fijamente en los ojos.

--Digo que esta señora no se ha matado. Digo que ha sido asesinada.

Su voz resonaba de manera extraña, parecía que hablara en un lugar vacío, tan glacial era el
silencio que reinaba en torno suyo, tan suspensos y sorprendidos se encontraban los ánimos
de todos los presentes. El Príncipe Alejo, erguido, inmóvil, alta la frente, miraba también
fijamente a su inesperado acusador.

--¿Cómo puede usted asegurarlo?--preguntó aún el juez.

--Lo sé.

--¿Cuáles son las pruebas que tiene usted?

--Ninguna prueba material. Todas las certidumbres morales.

--¿Quién cree usted que la ha muerto?

El joven extendió el brazo, señaló con el índice al Príncipe y la extranjera, y dijo:

Todos los presentes volvieron las atónitas miradas hacia los acusados.

En el primer momento la fisonomía del Príncipe Zakunine había permanecido sin expresión; parecía
que éste no hubiera oído, o que no hubiera comprendido; pero, poco a poco, una amarga e irónica
contracción de los labios, un encogimiento de las cejas sobre los ojos de pronto hundidos y
casi risueños, animados por una risa casi dolorosa, revelaron la sensación de estupor, de incredulidad
y en cierto modo de diversión, que tan inopinado cargo despertaba en su ánimo. En cuanto a
la desconocida, seguía con los brazos cruzados sobre el pecho, mirando al acusador, sin que
su rostro de estatua despertara desdén ni estupor.

Antes de decir nada contra alguien--repuso el juez en tono de amonestación--es preciso estar
cierto de lo que se dice.

--Si no estuviera cierto no habría hablado.

--¿Qué interés puede haber armado el brazo de estas personas?

El joven rompió a hablar con una violencia que en vano trataba de contener.

--La maldad del alma de uno y otro, el placer salvaje de hacer mal, de destruir una vida, de
derramar sangre. La voluptuosidad de poner fin con la muerte al largo martirio que han infligido
a esa infeliz.

La voz le temblaba, sus manos también estaban trémulas, sus ojos estaban preñados de lágrimas.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>373471</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21593</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

ROBERTO DI FEDERICO

SPASM

BUENOS AIRES

1909

INDEX

I. - The fact
II .-- The first investigations III .-- The memories of Roberto candle
plant IV .-- Story of a Soul V. - Duel VI .-- Research VII .-- Confession
VIII .-- The letter IX .-- Spasm

To raise awareness of the Italian
romantic literature, in its most modern in recent trends, we could
hardly have found something more to the point that authors like Federico
di Roberto and a book like spasm.

Federico di Roberto have now thirty-six years.

Is Sicilian, as Dick, the author of Cavalleria rusticana, with which
his literary talent presents some resemblance.

   As Dick, also
  is a realist, the realist who
 holds the light color native island.
  Its novels are of great dramatic
   intensity
  - even when kept in its
 guidelines a impeccable
elegance - something
  aristocratic in the design and shape, as revealed in all pages that
characterize the young writer a happy way.

With Arabeseos e Short stories brilliantly began his literary career, in which, despite being
in its inception has achieved success in resonance with I Vicera and we offer today this spasm
Argentine readers, whose direct translation of the language in which
it was written deserved special care from us.

In the drama that unfolds in this book involves intense and conflicting passions. Your environment
is a city in Switzerland, the refugee drama unfolds between nihilists, and the ardent struggle
the duty imposed by the political faith against a violent passion and captivating. Upon such
contrast, resulting in exciting scenes and characters intensely moving human underlying the
plot of this novel, about which we will say no more to not spoil the deep and sincere emotion
it produces in the reader's mind.

As you can easily notice, Federico di Roberto represented in modern
literature Italy a new note for us to fully differentiated D'Annunzio,
Fogazzaro and D'Amicis, who are the best known Italian novelist abroad.

And, reading Spasm we are confident that readers of good taste we shall have made them known account
embodies a strong talent that can be said, the new way of romantic Italian literature at this time.

SPASM

I

THE
FACT

Everyone who spent the fall of 1894 on the shores of Lake Geneva, no doubt remember yet the tragic
event of Ouchy, which was so impressive and so abundantly provided
food for curiosity, not just the people on holiday camps scattered
in all stations in the lake, but also the cosmopolitan public, which
the newspapers reported it.

On October 5, few minutes before noon, the sound of a gunshot and screams confused coming out of
the village Cyclamens, located in the middle of the road to Lausanne Ouchy, interrupted violently
usual tranquility of the place and attracted the neighbors and passersby. The Cyclamens villa was
rented to a Milanese lady, the Countess d'Arda, who had charge of
all the years, from June to November.

Countess friendship with Prince Alexius Zakunine, revolutionary Russian
who had been sentenced first in his country, expelled at once from
all States refugee Europe and recently in the territory of the Confederation,
was known from time ago.

The two lovers were in the village the day of the tragedy and the shouting, the same Prince Zakunine,
along with the detonation of the weapon, they go to the terrified servants, whose eyes appeared
a tremendous spectacle: the Countess lay lifeless at the foot of the bed perforated the right
temple by a bullet and a gun near his hand.

And even though the view of death, sudden and violent death, is such that no other the outdo
in horror, the presence of that body was not, however, which produced a thrill strong, but the appearance
of the survivor. Like a pale striped azalea crusade red, cold face of the unhappy, partially
stained with blood, was the color of wax, but it revealed nothing of the agony of contractions:
on the contrary, a serene confidence and something like a smile encouraged him still alive, slightly apart
the purple lips, behind which loomed just line the pearly teeth, open eyelids, the eyes turned
toward the sky, the dead appeared to be ecstatic, as if it had not abandoned the existence
of all, willing to testify that out of human life in silence and
in shade, had finally found the well-being and happiness.

Pale, haggard factions, hair in disarray over his forehead drenched in icy sweat, mad the eyes, trembling
lips, hands, whole body, as if it were a prey to fever, Alejo Prince instilled fear. After
asking for help and shouting hoarsely, had knelt beside the body and hugged him, all bloody,
and his troubled face no more than two words out short and boring:

- It's over! ... It's over! ...

In those words, the accent torn repeated that there was a breakdown, a bitterness, despair
so great that the dead no longer seemed to deserve such compassion as alive as inconsolable
man, overwhelmed by grief, it seemed, he also close to losing his breath. And sometimes, when his
hands got tired of caressing hands the hair, the clothes of the dead, carried them around the neck
with violent gesture, as if I would like to strangle, then the servants, all who had come, sought
to comfort, to wrest this cruel spectacle, but he, with wild momentum, rejected all from him,
stretched out his arms, stopped, and after walking unsteadily, if he were drunk, the fourth mortuary,
I fell back beside the body.

The villa was open to all, no one thought to prevent access. In the nearby House of Health had
come promptly Dr. Berard, who had only been able to verify death instant. The news was spreading
rapidly among the foreign colony, and curious flocked to the village,
especially those who knew the Countess and Prince, but no one could
get news of what happened, unless the servants.

Seemed Zakunine deaf and blind, unable to recognize people who approached
him, trying to shake hand, or hear the words of condolence, sympathy
sore phrases addressed to him.

Nor are the responses of the servants threw much light on the incident. Referring only to external
circumstances of the disaster, told everyone that the Prince had become to the town two days
earlier, after an absence of several weeks, that the lady had up this morning earlier than
usual and had remained an hour in the roof, while his partner worked at the desk, with a lady
who had arrived as at nine, that lunch before the countess had been sent to the city, with orders,
Julia, the Italian girl who had long-standing, that, when it was lunch to be served, the shot
had made everyone shudder: that the second floor, where they were
rooms at patterns, had launched the Prince on the ground floor like
a madman, asking to call a doctor, and that all had gone headlong
into the room of the Countess, where the foreigner, after trying in
vain to rescue it, had treated equally in vain, to console the despairing
prince.

Amid the confusion, few had noticed the presence of the foreign. This was a young just twenty
years, blond hair saffron, short, hair like a man clear eyes and look cool, rather small stature,
was dressed in black from head to toe. Right remained motionless in the corner of a window, arms
folded, head bowed, and hardly realized his presence curiosity began to stir.

In the circle that formed the most curious of these was the Baroness de Born Austrian woman, thick
and short, the only sex who had come to the village, and stared at the stranger, overwhelming
at the same time with your questions to the servants, those not knowing what to say in mixed
groups to discuss what happened.

- Poor girl ... Poor !...-- friend Baroness exclaimed .-- But why? ... How could he? ... What
has not written anything? Have not found anything left for her? ... There must be something ...
looking for ... Did he die at the moment? ... Suffered, it is true, but not so much that I could
not resist! ... He was strong, a very strong woman, despite her body thin and delicate ... Pains moral
...

And in a lower voice, addressed the young Englishman a red mustache,
blue eyes and bald forehead, he suggested:

- Do you believe that
to be happy?

The questioned responded with a vague gesture, which could mean both consent and doubt or ignorance.

-
And that poor Prince !...-- continued the Baroness, always looking for the low, continuous, foreign
to him .-- It is a pain and suffering ... Would need to persuade
someone that moved away ...-- And these words were aimed directly
at the young stranger; but as this did not answer, Baroness proposed:
- Why not put the body at least on the bed?

Speaking from the group around the corpse, and, seeing that the bystanders, approved their comments
sought and obtained to be allowed to pass.

Then came the Prince, which was currently leaning against the bed, arms hanging, hands and contracted
lost eyes still turned towards the dead.

- We can not leave her like this ... we want to put it on the bed ... Do you?

But he did not answer, or even seemed to have heard, and the Baroness put a hand on shoulder,
trembled as if shaken by a magnetic current, his gaze lost, lost,
disconsolate expressed an anxiety so awful that the loquacious lady
found that for a moment lacked the words.

- What a disgrace ... What
pain troubled !...-- said .-- There are, however, to have power enough
to resign themselves to fate!

... Doctor - he added, turning to Berard, who approached at that
time the Prince .-- We would remove the body there ... I suppose at
times that the poor little suffering on the ground!

... And all these people, do not it could ask to go away?

- Yes ... ...-- a doctor replied hesitantly, not knowing what to do .-- But before solving all,
we must wait for the judges ...

- Have they been notified?

- Here they come.

Indeed, the murmur of voices had become extinct in the next room, and in that instantly entered
the circuit magistrate in Lausanne, the police commissioner, a physician
and two gendarmes.

The first thing the judge did was to order him away to the mortuary of the room indiscreet and the room,
and complete this order, the police were placed in the door between that room with the other
little room, to keep people back.

Only kept the body, foreign, Dr. Berard, and his colleague from the police, who explained the
futility of all healing and rapid death, the Baroness de Born, that without anyone being asked,
reported what happened to the judge it, Prince and the commissioner.

- What do you attribute his fatal decision?

Was not there some were that he should expect? - Asked the judge, and the Baroness, despite being
unable to shut up, by that time simply shrugged shoulders and look
to the Prince, to signify that this was the only one who could answer.

Zakunine ran a hand across his forehead, as if waking from a deep sleep and said:

- Yes, you had to foresee ... Because I foresee ...

- Did he suffer
much?

- I suffered so much ... !...-- both said the Prince, with
a tone of deep sadness, that the same judge was shocked.

- Was he
sick? - Asked the court to the doctor, after a brief silence.

- Yes,
from a chest condition.

- Did what he had?

- Certainly.

It was impossible to hide anything. He was so intelligent and courageous, which lies were useless
with her compassionate.

- You could not hope to save her?

- His illness was one of those on the outcome of which can not be
cheating, but that by appropriate arrangements can live many years
yet.

- So it is not the only disease that has driven to kill?

-
It's not all - echoed Prince Alexius.

Very curious, almost comical, it was during interrogation that sad
attitude Baroness Borne, which, since he could not speak pursed her
lips, moving his eyes, shook his head, bent around the body, as if
repeated on the judge's questions and confirm the doctor's answers
and Prince, to see that she had provided the one and the other, and
also noted by signs that she had one observation.

And once then interrupted:

- That's it ... Also!

... Exactly! ... And with the religious feelings I had ...

- What were they? - Asked the judge.

- Few women I have known such strong faith and ardent - said the doctor.

-
Is it true ?...-- Baroness interrupted again .-- It seems incredible
how big it was his fervor!

I have a reason to know. There was a walk without an end not a church. His favorite trips were
Echallens district to Bretigny to Assens, Villars-le-Terroir, because
of the churches there was Catholic.

Sundays and holidays we spent hours here in San Luis, kneeling to
her missing forces ... And that was the point that I wanted to ask
you: who else is amazing how, with so much faith, was able to do what
he has done.

The prince did not speak. Nervous tremor shook him at first was calming down, the turbulent,
violent, terrifying expression on his face pale and his eyes went red transforming: pale, exhausted,
powerless, he also appeared next to fall.

- She was alone when he killed himself?

- Sola.

- Did you speak to her this morning?

- Yes, spoke to her.

- Were you sad?

- Mortality.

- We could see if something has stopped writing.

Baroness clapped his hands and exclaimed:

- That's what I have said from the beginning!

The commissioner, a judge's signal, began to search.

There was little furniture in the room of the dead.

The bed, a wardrobe with mirror, a dresser, a small desk placed against
the window, in broad daylight, and at an angle a work table, was all
that was the household.

On the desk were two stacks of books in English white covers, a box
of paper; an old candy box, and a travel bag.

Working on the coffee table and nightstand were more books. The commissioner was recording one
one, opened the drawers of furniture, none of which was locked, and then to take a look at the feminine
elegance objects that were full, returned to the close. On the desk was the correspondence of
the deceased, in cardboard boxes rather old and a bag of Italian and French values ??and a
few thousand pesos in gold and silver. At the bottom of the drawer on the right found the commissioner
a as a book case lined in black velvet, and closed with a tiny key, and going to open it, when the
Prince took a step toward him, saying:

- This is a book of memories ... the day of your life ...

From the tone that made such an indication, by the attitude of his whole person, it seemed like
defend against prying eyes thinking of her poor intimate friend,
but the Baroness Borne said, approaching the court, which had been
in the hands of the Commissioner extracted by this book of his black
box:

- Sinovac can find something!

...

Also the book's cover was black, with silver clasps, like a book and mortuary single view expressed
sadness and pain that must have embittered the life of that unhappy. The judge quickly ran
Covers: the letter was rather large, thin, very striking, elegant
and admirable clarity.

Almost three quarters of the book were written.

The judge devoted the most attention to the last pages, but after reading this, let hung his
head and:

- It is not clear - he said - not a confession ...

Meanwhile, the Commissioner continued his research in a small adjoining
room the dressing room, where another closet, the lavatory and chests
all over the place occupied available.

But even there he found no letter.

Then returned to the bedroom, through him, and entered the room: there the record was even shorter
or useless, because apart from the couch and chairs, only had a table full of small objects
of use, and then the piano, on which looked a notebook Pessard compositions. And the sheriff returned
on their own steps, when the sound of voices, cries of anguish he turned back, the police, obedient
to the orders they had received, preventing the entrance of a woman dressed in dark, head wearing
the black veil of the Lombard Village People.

- Ah, sir! Ah, sir !...-- exclaimed the woman, clasping her hands, skinny face, furrowed by hot tears
.-- I see it! ... Seeing it again! ... My employer ... my good mistress!

Ah, sir, to see it! ...

It was Julia, who at that time returning from the city.

Short and thin, somewhat advanced in years, seemed overwhelmed by anxiety.

- Let her go - ordered the judge, whom the Baroness explained that the Countess's maid for many years,
this woman had enjoyed his confidence.

And when he came, sobbing and tearful, hands together, and advanced to the corpse, nervous shudder
before it turned to move the body of the Prince on his face re-read that fainting with terror,
that awful pain, as if the view a person facing death, his presence there, did intensify their
torment. No looked at the corpse, but the weeping woman, and seemed to approach, together
with her to join the pains of the two to talk about death, to hear her talk it. All men of
justice, doctors, even to the Baroness were impressed anxious for that unfortunate attitude:
only foreign motionless and rigid, impassive and almost without looking at anyone.

- She said and done! ... He has done what he said !...-- women wailed beside the body .-- wanted death,
called ... Ah, poor thing! ... Ah, gentlemen ... And I sent out, sent me ... to be free ...
Not to read it in the face! Ah, if I had been with her! ... Many times, poor thing, how many times
prayed to God to make her die! ... And they have killed repeated !...-- even more distressed voice, as if until
that time has been doubt and wait, and suddenly undoubtedly received confirmation of such misfortune.
Have been killed! ... She's dead! Lord! Lord ...

Baroness ran a hand across his eyes, sighed and pulled her to his chest to the maid.

- Enough, enough, poor woman ... There is no choice but to comply! ... Calm down you !.... Basta!
... It is best that you tell these gentlemen, justice, where are
the commanded you?

What sent her?

- In the city, to pay some bills ... to buy things ... I do not know
anymore ... It seemed, when got out of bed, as if to go with me ...
then changed his mind and sent me ...

- Given to you a letter?

Do you know if he wrote a letter last night or this morning?

- Last
night, no: this morning.

This morning I wrote a letter.

- Who was targeted?

- A Sister Anne

-
Who is Sister Ann? - Asked the judge, who had left the verbose lady
patiently make the interrogation.

- Sister Anne Brighton, his former
English teacher.

- Where?

- Do not know.

In the envelope was the name of the place, a foreign name.

- Do
you not know that address? - Asked the judge, turning to Prince Alexis.

-
The know, but ...

His anxiety seemed to be calming down.

I was about to say something, when he heard in the background room to the police officers who prevented
anyone from entering.

But this time the unexpected person never complained, not crying,
vibrant voice, irritated and almost imperative, said:

- Let me go!

... I need to go, I say!

...

While the commissioner would see who he was, and Baroness Bérard approached
Borne at the door.

- Candle plant! - Baroness cried when she saw
a tall, burly, black hair and mustache blonde, who decided to force
the slogan, came in a hurry when the guards, a sign of his superior,
is pushed aside.

But after making his attempt and move quickly the first steps, the newcomer seemed suddenly
hesitated, uncertain: the irritation he lit his face was giving way to confusion and distress. When
you reach the threshold and see the body was hand over his heart,
leaned against the doorframe, intense pale, almost about to faint.

-
Our poor friend! - Baroness cried again, holding out his right hand
as if to to comfort, inspire courage .-- Who would have thought!

... Does not seem like a dream? ... Poor poor friend!

... And kill ...

But the young man said, advancing one step in a loud voice said:

- No.

A movement of concern and shock went through the present.

- What do you say? - Asked the judge, approaching candle plant and
staring eyes.

- I say that this lady was not killed.

I say that has been murdered.

His voice echoed strangely, seemed to speak in a vacuum, so ice was
silence that reigned around him, so bewildered and tempers were surprised
of all present.

Prince Alexis, erect, motionless, high forehead, looked also stared
at his unexpected accuser.

- How can you sure? - Even the judge asked.

-
I know.

- What evidence do you have?

- No test material.

All moral certainties.

- Who do you think is dead?

The young man extended his arm, pointed his index and foreign Prince,
and said:

All present turned their astonished gaze toward the defendants.

At

first the Prince's face remained expressionless Zakunine had, it seemed that he had not heard
or had not understood, but little by little, a bitter and ironic contraction of the lips,
a shrug of the eyebrows over his eyes suddenly sunk almost smiling, animated by an almost painful
laugh, showed a sense of amazement, disbelief and in a sense of fun,
so unexpected by awakened in his mind.

As the unknown, still with his arms folded across his chest, looking
at the accuser, without the statue's face and awakening from stupor.

Before you say anything against anyone - the judge said in a tone
of warning - it must be some of what is said.

- If it were true would
not have spoken.

- What interest can be armed arm these people?

The young man began to speak with a violence that vainly tried to
hold.

- The evil of the soul of each other, the savage pleasure to
do evil, to destroy a life, bloodshed.

The pleasure of ending with the death of the long martyrdom inflicted to that unhappy.

Her voice trembled, his hands were trembling too, his eyes were fraught with tears.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>