<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10370</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>279796</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>14988</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Jacobo Melín examinó con curiosidad a su presuntuoso contrincante. Quizá sabía que estaba predestinado
a perder el dinero, y prefería que refluyese en sus propios cofres a que entrase en los de
cualquier forastero; así es que asintió con un gesto, y acercó su silla a la mesa. En aquel
mismo momento, llamaron a la puerta.

--Es Lina--dijo Moreno.

Jacobo descorrió el cerrojo, y la puerta se abrió; pero por vez primera en su vida perdió el
aplomo, se levantó bamboleando, y una oleada de sangre enrojeció hasta la frente su pálida
cara. Allí mismo, en su cuarto, estaba la señora de la diligencia de Wingdam, a quien Moreno,
dejando caer las cartas, saludó, exclamando con ojos de asombro.

--¡Mi mujer!... ¡Cielos!

Se dice que la señora Moreno prorrumpió en llanto y reproches contra su marido; pero yo que
le vi en 1857 en Marysville, no lo he creído jamás. La Crónica de Wingdam de la semana siguiente,
bajo el título de «Escena conmovedora», decía:

     «En nuestra ciudad, donde tan frecuentes son hechos e incidentes de
     todo género, ha tenido lugar ayer uno de los más tiernos y
     conmovedores que registra la historia de California. La esposa de
     uno de los más eminentes pionners de Wingdam, cansada de la
     caduca civilización del Este y de su ingrato clima, resolvió
     reunirse con su noble esposo en estas playas de oro, y sin
     noticiarle su intención, emprendió el largo viaje, llegando hará
     cosa de unos ocho días. El júbilo del marido más es para imaginado
     que para descrito. Dícese que el encuentro fue indescriptiblemente
     dramático. Esperamos que este ejemplo tendrá imitadores.»

Desde este hecho, sea por la influencia de la señora de Moreno o por especulaciones afortunadas,
la situación financiera de Moreno mejoró notablemente. Al cabo de poco tiempo, compró la participación
de sus socios en la mina Nip-y-Tack, con dinero, que se decía ganado al poker una semana o
dos después de la llegada de su mujer, pero que los maldicientes, adoptando el criterio de
la señora Moreno sobre la conversión de su marido, atribuían a Melín. Edificó y amuebló también
la Wingdam House, que los atractivos de su esposa mantuvieron siempre rebosando de huéspedes;
fue elegido miembro de la asamblea, hizo donativos a iglesias y se dio su nombre a una calle
del pueblo.

Su carácter no participó, sin embargo, de tal prosperidad. Notose que a medida que se enriquecía
tornábase pálido, flaco y malhumorado, y su recelo e inquietud crecían cuanto más aumentó la
popularidad de su mujer. Él, el más mujeriego de los hombres, era celoso hasta lo absurdo.
Según se cuchicheaba, si no se entrometía en la libertad social de su mujer, era porque, su
primero y único ensayo de este género, había tenido por resultado una grave disputa con su
señora, que le impuso el silencio, quieras que no. El bello sexo era el que tomaba parte más
activa en estos chismes y se comprende, pues aquélla las había suplantado en las galantes atenciones
de Wingdam, que, como todas las aficiones populares rendían culto de admiración al poder de
la fuerza masculina o de la beldad femenina. Recordaré en su descargo, que desde su llegada
había sido la inconsciente sacerdotisa objeto de un culto mitológico que no ennoblece más a
su sexo que el peculiar de la antigua Grecia. Moreno sospechaba vagamente esto, y su único
confidente era Jacobo Melín, cuya mala reputación le prohibía una amistad íntima con la familia
y cuyas visitas no se repetían muy a menudo.

El verano enviaba todos sus rigores, y en una noche de luna, la señora Moreno, con sus rasgados
ojos, sonrosada y bonita como siempre, estaba sentada en la plaza disfrutando el perfumado
incienso de la brisa de la montaña, y de otro incienso no tan puro ni tan inocente, pues a
su lado estaban sentados el coronel Estrella y el juez Roberto Bob, y un turista recién agregado
a la reunión.

--¿Qué ve usted a lo lejos, en el camino?--preguntó el galante coronel, observando que desde
hacía algunos minutos la atención de la señora Moreno se fijaba hacia aquel punto.

--Una nube de polvo--dijo con un suspiro la interpelada.--Veo el rebaño de la hermana Ana.

Los recuerdos literarios del militar no se remontaban más allá del periódico de la semana anterior,
así es que lo comprendió al pie de la letra.

--No son ovejas--continuó,--es un jinete. Juez, ¿no es aquél el tordo de Jacobo Melín?

Pero el juez no lo sabía, y según indicó la señora Moreno, el aire era demasiado fuerte para
más averiguaciones; de manera que tuvieron que retirarse.

El celoso marido estaba en la cuadra, donde generalmente se retiraba después de cenar. Quizá
lo hacía para demostrar su desagrado a los compañeros de su esposa; tal vez a semejanza de
tantas débiles naturalezas, encontraba un placer en el ejercicio del poder absoluto sobre animales
inferiores. Experimentaba cierta satisfacción en amaestrar una yegua pía, a la cual podía pegar
o acariciar a su antojo, lo que no podía hacer con su señora. Al penetrar en la cuadra, reconoció
a cierto caballo tordo que acababan de entrar, y mirando un poco más allá vio a su dueño. Saludole
cordial y sinceramente, correspondiendo Melín bastante hoscamente. Sin embargo, accediendo
al importuno empeño de Moreno, le siguió por una escalera excusada, hasta un estrecho corredor,
y de allí a un pequeño cuarto con ventana interior, sencillamente amueblado con una cama, una
mesa, algunas sillas, látigos y un escaparate para escopetas.

--Ahí tienes mi casa--dijo Moreno, suspirando, echándose sobre la cama y haciendo seña a su
compañero de que tomase asiento.--Su habitación está al otro extremo del edificio. Hace más
de seis meses que no hemos vivido juntos ni nos hemos visto, fuera de las horas de comer. ¡Qué
triste papel para el cabeza de familia! ¿verdad?--dijo con forzada risa;--pero me alegro de
verte, Jacobo, me alegro inmensamente de verte.

E inclinose sobre el borde de la cama, para estrechar la mano de Melín, que permanecía mudo.

--He querido que subieses aquí, porque no quería hablarte en la cuadra; aunque eso lo sabe
toda la ciudad. No enciendas la vela. Podemos hablar así, a la luz de la luna. Apoya tus pies
en este sofá y siéntate aquí a mi vera. En ese jarro hay buen anís.

Jacobo no utilizó el aviso. Moreno de Calaveras volvió la cara hacia la pared y continuó:

--Nada me importaría si no la amase, Jacobo. Pero amarla y verla un día tras otro día seguir
en este talante, como lo está haciendo, y que yo no ponga la más leve cortapisa... ¡esto es
lo que me mata! Pero me alegro de verte, Jacobo, me alegro infinitamente.

Y tentó en la oscuridad, hasta que pudo estrechar la mano de su confidente. La hubiera retenido
consigo, pero Jacobo la deslizó en su abrochada levita y preguntó con indiferencia cuánto tiempo
hacía que aquello duraba.

--Desde que llegó, desde el mismo día en que entró en la Magnolia. Yo a la sazón fui un torpe,
Juan, y ahora soy un torpe también; pero no supe cuánto la amaba hasta el presente. Y ya no
es la misma mujer.

Mas no es esto todo; de otra cosa quería hablarte, y me alegro de que hayas venido. No se trata
tan sólo de que no me ame, y coquetee con el primero que se presenta, pues tal vez jugué su
amor y lo perdí, como hice con todo lo demás en la Magnolia, y acaso la coquetería es natural
en ciertas mujeres; esto no sería grave, sino para los bobos que se dejaran seducir. Pero,
amigo... creo que ama a otro. No me dejes, Jacobo, no me dejes; si tu pistola te molesta, tírala.

Hace cosa de seis meses que la veo inquieta y triste, y como nerviosa y taciturna. Y a veces,
la he sorprendido mirándome tímida y compasiva. Se comunica con alguien. He observado que ha
recogido sus cosas... vestidos, dijes y joyas. Jacobo, yo creo que prepara una fuga. Y te juro
que eso no lo soportaría. Todo, menos que se escurra como un alevoso ladrón.

Apoyó fuertemente su cara en la almohada, y por algunos momentos no se oyó otro ruido que el
tic-tac del reloj, encima de la mesa. Melín encendió un puro y se acercó a la abierta ventana.
La luna ya no iluminaba el cuarto, y la cama y el que la ocupaba quedaron en las tinieblas.

--¿Qué resolver, Jacobo?--dijo una voz profunda.

La contestación centelleó pronta y claramente.

--Buscar al hombre y matarlo en el acto.

--¡Jacobo!

--¡Quien ama el peligro, perecerá en él!

--¿Pero esto me la devolverá?

Jacobo no contestó, pero se alejó de la ventana, con ánimo de retirarse.

--No te vayas aún, Jacobo; enciende la vela y siéntate a la mesa. Cuando menos, será un placer
para mí no verte ocupar este sitio.

El confidente titubeó y consintió al cabo, sacando del bolsillo una baraja. Revolviola, mirando
de soslayo a la cama. Pero Moreno tenía la cara vuelta hacia la pared. Cuando Melín hubo barajado,
cortó y puso una carta al lado opuesto de la mesa, hacia la cama, y otra a su lado en la mesa
destinada a él. La primera era un as; la suya un rey. Barajó y cortó. Esta vez al dummy[11]
le tocó una sota y a él un cuatro. Animose para la tercera vuelta. Le tocó a su adversario
un as y sacó otra vez un rey para sí.

--De tres, dos--dijo Jacobo en alta voz.

--¿Qué es eso, Melín?--preguntó Moreno.

--Nada.

Probó después Melín la suerte con los dados, pero siempre tiró a seises y su supuesto adversario
a ases.

--Esto es sorprendente--exclamó el autojugador.

Mientras tanto, alguna influencia magnética latente en la presencia de Jacobo, o el anodino
de la bebida, o acaso ambas cosas a la vez, mitigaron el dolor de Moreno, que quedó dormido.
Acercó entonces Melín su silla a la ventana, y contempló la ciudad de Wingdam, a la sazón pacíficamente
dormida bajo sus duras siluetas y chillones colores, armonizados por la luz que la luna derramaba
sobre el panorama. En medio del nocturno silencio, oíase el murmullo del agua en los canales
y el suspiro del aire en los pinos de la selva vecina. Alzó los ojos al firmamento, en el momento
que una estrella se corría a través del negro cielo, tras de ella otra, y otra cruzó rauda
después, dejando tras sí un rastro luminoso. El fenómeno sugirió a Jacobo un nuevo augurio.

--Si dentro de unos quince minutos cayese otra estrella...

Reloj en mano permaneció en aquella posición el doble de aquel intervalo de tiempo, pero el
fenómeno no se repitió. En el campanario dieron las dos y Moreno dormía todavía. Melín se acercó
a la mesa y sacó de su bolsillo un billete que leyó a la luz vacilante de la vela. No contenía
más que una sola línea, escrita en lápiz con letra femenina.

«Espera en el corral con el boghey a las tres.»

Moreno se agitó desasosegado y por fin despertó.

--¡Jacobo! ¿Estás ahí?

--Sí.

Te suplico no te marches aún. Soñaba ahora, soñaba en los pasados tiempos; Susana y yo nos
casábamos otra vez y el sacerdote, Jacobo, era... ¿Sabes quién era? ¡Tú!

Melín se rió y sentose sobre la cama, con el papel en los dedos.

--¿Es buena señal?--preguntó Moreno.

--Ya lo creo: di, compadre, ¿no sería mejor que te levantases?

Moreno de Calaveras se levantó con la ayuda de la mano que Melín le ofrecía.

--Creo que fumas.

Moreno tomó maquinalmente el cigarro que le alargaba.

--¿Fuego?

Jacobo arrolló la carta en espiral, la encendió y ofreciola a su amigo. Quedose con ella entre
los dedos, hasta que se hubo consumido, y tiró el cabo que como fulgurante estrella, cayó ventana
abajo. Siguiolo con la vista y se volvió luego hacia Moreno.

--Compadre--dijo poniendo sus manos sobre los hombros de su amigo,--en seis minutos me planto
en el camino y me desvanezco como esa llama. No volveremos a vernos, pero antes de que me marche
toma el consejo de un loco. Liquida todo cuanto tengas y llévate a tu mujer lejos de este sitio.
No es lugar para ti ni para ella. Anúnciale que debe partir: oblígala a que se vaya, si no
quiere de buen grado. No te lamentes de no ser un Sócrates ni ella un ángel. Acuérdate de que
eres hombre y trátala como a una mujer. No seas torpe. Abur.

Desprendiose de los brazos de Moreno y saltó por las escaleras abajo como un gamo. Una vez
en la cuadra tomó por el cuello al medio dormido mozo y le empujó contra el muro.

--Pon la silla al instante a mi caballo, o te...

La disyuntiva era terrible y fácil de entender.

--La señora dijo que enganchase el boghey para usted--tartamudeó el infeliz.

--¡Al diablo el boghey!

El tordo fue ensillado tan rápidamente como las nerviosas manos del asombrado mozo pudieron
manejar las correas y hebillas.

El mozo, quien, como todos los de su clase, admiraba el empuje de su fogoso patrón, y realmente
se interesaba en su suerte, no pudo menos de preguntar:

--¿Ocurre algo, señor?

--¡Quítate de ahí!

El mozo se apartó tímidamente. Sonó un latigazo y una blasfemia, pateó el caballo y Jacobo
caminaba ya a trote tendido.

Un momento después, a los ojos somnolientos del mozo no era más que una movediza nubecilla
de polvo en el horizonte hacia donde una estrella, separándose de sus hermanas, dejaba un rastro
luminoso.

Los moradores a orillas del camino de Wingdam, oyeron, al amanecer, una voz vibrante como la
de la alondra, cantando por la llanura. Los que dormían se revolvieron en sus toscos lechos
para soñar en la juventud, en el amor y en la vida. Campesinos de tosca cara y ansiosos buscadores
de oro, ya en el trabajo, cesaron en sus faenas y se apoyaron en sus picos para escuchar a
este romántico aventurero que, destacando a la luz de la rosada aurora, cabalgaba al paso castellano.

CAROLINA

(EPISODIO DE FIDDLETOWN)

I

En la población de Fiddletown se la consideraba por todo el mundo como una mujer bonita. Su
buena figura, realzada por una espléndida mata de cabello castaño se caracterizaba por un hermoso
color y cierta gracia lánguida que le prestaban un no sé qué interesante y distinguido. Vestía
siempre con gusto y para Fiddletown era la última moda. No tenía más que dos defectos: uno
de sus aterciopelados ojos, examinado de cerca, se desviaba ligeramente, y manchaba su mejilla
izquierda una pequeña cicatriz causada por una gota de vitriolo, felizmente la única de un
frasco entero que le había arrojado una celosa rival, con la aviesa intención de desfigurar
tan bonito jeme. Sin embargo, cuando el observador alcanzaba a notar la irregularidad de su
mirada, quedaba por lo general incapacitado para criticarla y no faltaba quien pretendía que
la mancha de su mejilla le añadía mayor seducción y donaire. El joven editor de El Alud, de
Fiddletown, sostenía reservadamente que era un hoyuelo disimulado y al coronel Roberto le recordaba
las tentadoras pecas de los tiempos de la reina Ana, y más especialmente a una de las más hermosas
y malditas mujeres, sí, ¡malditas sean! en que jamás se hayan podido fijar ojos humanos. Era
una criolla de Nueva Orleáns. Dicha mujer tenía una cicatriz, un costurón que le cruzaba (a
fe que es verdad), desde el ojo derecho a la boca. Y esta mujer, amigo, le penetraba a uno...
amigo, le enloquecía... verdaderamente le condenaba el alma con su maldita fascinación. Un
día le dije:

--Celeste, ¿cómo demonio se te hizo esa maldita cicatriz? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09914</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>15939</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>13688</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

James Melin looked curiously at his presumptuous opponent. Maybe he knew he was destined to lose money,
and preferred refluyese in their own coffers to enter into those an outsider, so I nodded,
and drew his chair to the table. At that Right now, knock on the door.

- It's Lina - Moreno said.

James pulled back the bolt, and the door opened, but for the first time in his life lost aplomb,
got up wobbling, and a rush of blood to the face reddened her pale
face.

Right there in his room, was the mistress of the diligence of Wingdam,
whom Moreno dropping the letters, greeting, exclaiming with wondering
eyes.

- My wife!

... Heavens!

It is said that Mrs. Moreno burst into tears and reproaches against
her husband, but I that I saw him in 1857 in Marysville, I have not
ever believed.

     Wingdam Chronicle the following week, under the title "poignant scene,"
     said
     
     "In our city, where frequent are events and incidents every
     kind, took place yesterday one of the most tender poignant in
     the history of California. The wife one of the most eminent
     of Wingdam pionners, tired of expires Eastern civilization and its
     unpleasant weather, resolved join her noble husband in these golden
     beaches, and no news of his intention, made the long journey, arriving
     will thing about eight days.

The joy of the husband is to imagine more that described. It is said that the meeting was indescribably
dramatic. We hope this example will have imitators. "

From this fact, whether by the influence of Madame de Moreno or lucky speculation, Moreno's
financial situation improved dramatically. After a short time, bought the stake its partners in
the mine Nip-and-Tack, with money, who won the poker said a week or two after the arrival of
his wife, but the cursing, taking the view Ms. Moreno on the conversion of her husband, attributed
to Melin.

Also built and furnished the Wingdam House, that the attractions of his wife always kept overflowing
with guests; was elected to the assembly, made donations to churches and gave his name to a
street Village.

His character did not participate, however, this prosperity. Notos that was enriched as Tornabe
pale, gaunt and moody, and his fear and concern grew the more increased popularity of his wife.
Him, the philandering of men, was jealous to the absurd. As whispered, if not meddled in the social
freedom of his wife, was because their first and only trial of its kind, had resulted in a
serious dispute with lady, who imposed silence, willy-nilly. The fair sex was the one who took
part active in these gossip and understood, as it had been supplanted in the amorous attentions
of Wingdam, which, like all popular hobbies of admiration worshiped the power of male strength
or feminine beauty. Remember in his defense, that since coming had been the unconscious priestess
of a cult object that ennobles the mythological most that the peculiar
sex in ancient Greece.

Moreno vaguely suspected this, and his only James was confident Melin, whose bad reputation forbade
a close friendship with the family whose visits are not repeated very often.

Summer sent all its rigors, and a moonlit night, Ms. Moreno, with her wide eyes, rosy and pretty
as always, sat in the square enjoying the perfumed incense of the
mountain breeze, incense and other not so pure nor so innocent, because
sat beside Colonel Roberto Estrella and Judge Bob, and a tourist newly
added the meeting.

- What do you see in the distance, on the way?
- The gallant colonel said, noting that since few minutes ago the
attention of Ms. Moreno was set to that point.

- A cloud of dust
- said with a sigh the challenged .-- I see the flock of Sister Anne

The
military's literary memories no deeper than the previous week's newspaper,
so I got it at face value.

- There are sheep - continued - a rider.

Judge, is not one of James Melin thrush?

But the judge did not know, and according to Ms. Moreno, the air was
too strong for further investigation, so that had to withdraw.

The jealous husband was on the block, where generally retired after
dinner.

Perhaps I did it to show their displeasure at his wife's colleagues, perhaps along the lines
of many weak natures, he found a pleasure in the exercise of power
over animals lower.

Felt a certain satisfaction in taming a horse pious, which could hit or caress at will, which
could do with his wife. On entering the stable, recognized a certain gray horse which had
just come in, and looking a little further he saw his owner. Saluted cordial and sincere, rather sullenly
corresponding Melin. However, accessing the importunate efforts of Moreno, followed by a staircase
excused, to a narrow corridor and thence to a small interior room with window, simply furnished with
a bed, table, some chairs, whips and a showcase for shotguns.

- That's my house - Moreno said with a sigh, leaning over the bed and beckoned her partner to take
seat .-- Your room is on the other end of the building. More six months since we lived together
and we have seen, outside mealtimes. What sad role for the head of
the family!

Right? - Said with a forced laugh, - but I'm glad see James, I'm glad to see you immensely.

I
leaned over the edge of the bed to shake hands with Melin, who remained silent.

- I wanted subieses here, not wanting to speak on the block, although he knows that throughout
the city. Do not light the candle.

We can talk like that, in light of the moon. Support your feet on
this couch and sit here by my side.

In this jar is good anise.

James did not use the notice.

Calaveras Moreno turned to face the wall and continued:

- No matter if I love her, James. But love her and seeing her one day after another day to follow
in this ethos, as it is doing, and I do not put the slightest cortapisa
... Ie what kills me!

But I'm glad to see you, James, me infinitely happy.

And tempted in the dark, until he could shake hands with his confidant.

Had retained the him, but James slipped it into his coat buttoned and casually asked how long was
that this lasted.

- Since coming from the same day he entered the Magnolia. At the time I was a clumsy, John, and
now I'm a clumsy too, but I did not know how much he loved so far. And no is the same woman.

But
this is not everything I wanted to talk about something else, and I'm glad you came. It is not
just that I love, and flirt with the first show, they played perhaps their love and lost,
as I did with everything else in the Magnolia, and is perhaps the
coquetry natural in some women, this would not be serious, but for
the fools who are seduced.

But Friend ... I think he loves another. Do not leave me, James, do not leave me, if your gun
bothers you, throw it away.

Thing six months ago that I worried and sad, and as nervous and moody.

And sometimes I've caught looking shy and compassionate. Communicate with someone. I have observed
has collected his things ... dresses, trinkets and jewels. James, I think preparing for a flight.
And I swear that does not stand for it. Everything, except to drain
as a treacherous thief.

Strongly supported her face in the pillow, and for a few moments there
was no noise but the ticking clock on the table.

Melin lit a cigar and walked to the open window.

The moon did not illuminate the room, and bed and which were occupied
in the dark.

- What to solve, Jacob? - Said a deep voice.

The answer flashed early and clearly.

- Find the man and kill him instantly.

- James!

- He who loves danger shall perish in it!

- But this I shall return?

James did not answer, but away from the window, intending to retire.

-
Do not go yet, James, light the candle and sit down at the table.

At the very least, be happy for me not to see you occupy this site.

The informant hesitated and agreed to out of pocket, pulling out a
deck.

Revolviola looking glanced at the bed. But Moreno had his face turned toward the wall. When
Melin were shuffled, cut and put a letter on the opposite side of the table to the bed, and
another at his side at the table intended for him. The first was an ace, his king. Shuffled and cut. This
time the dummy [11] touched a jack and him a four. Animose for the third round. It fell to his opponent
an ace and a king took over for himself.

- Three, two - James said loudly.

- What is it, Melin? - Asked Moreno.

- Nothing.

Melin tested after luck with the dice, but always threw sixes and
his supposed adversary to aces.

- This is amazing - said the auto
playable.

Meanwhile, a latent magnetic influence in the presence of James, or
bland beverage, or perhaps both at the same time ease the pain of
Moreno, who was asleep.

Melin then approached his chair to the window, and looked Wingdam
City, at the time peacefully asleep under their harsh outlines and
garish colors, harmonized by the moon shed light about the outlook.

In the midst of silent night, could hear the murmur of the water in the canals and the breath
of air in the nearby pine forest.

He raised his eyes to the sky, at the time that a star running through
the black sky behind her again, and again crossed swiftly later, leaving
behind a trail of light.

The phenomenon suggested to James a new sign.

- If within fifteen
minutes another star should fall ...

Watch in hand remained in that
position twice that interval, but phenomenon was not repeated.

The bell struck two and Moreno was still sleeping.

Melin came to the table and took from his pocket a note that read
in the flickering light of the candle.

It contained more than a single line, written in pencil with feminine
handwriting.

"Wait for the corral with boghey at three."

Moreno was stirred restlessly and finally woke up.

- James! Are you there?

- Yes.

I beg do not leave yet.

Now dreaming, dreaming of times past, Susan and I got married again and the priest, James,
was ... Do you know who it was? You!

Melin laughed and sat on the bed, with the paper in the toes.

- Is
it a good sign? - Asked Moreno.

- I think: Say, man, would not it
be better to get up?

Calaveras Moreno rose with the help of the hand that offered Melin.

- I think you smoke.

Moreno took the cigar which mechanically stretched.

- Fire?

James rolled the letter spiral, lit it and offered him his friend.

He remained with her in fingers, until he had consumed, and pulled out that as the shining
star, fell window below. Followed him by sight and then turned to Moreno.

- My friend - said putting his hands on the shoulders of his friend, - I stand in six minutes
on the road and I fade away as the flame. Not meet again, but before I leave take the advice
of a madman. Have settled everything and take your wife away from this site. Not the place for you
or for her. Tidings that must go: to compel them to leave, if not you willingly. Do not regret
not being a Socrates or her an angel. Remember that If you treat
her like a man and a woman.

Do not be stupid.

Abur.

Desprendiose Moreno's arms and jumped down the stairs like a deer. Once on the block took the
boy asleep in the middle neck and pushed him against the wall.

- Put the saddle my horse instantly, or you ...

The dilemma was terrible and easy to understand.

- The woman said she hooked boghey for you - stammered the unhappy.

- To hell with boghey!

The thrush was saddled as fast as the nervous hands of the astonished boy could drive belts and buckles.

The
boy, who, like all his class, admired the thrust of his fiery patron, and really was interested
in their fate could not but ask:

- Is there anything, sir?

- Get out of there!

The waiter turned away shyly. There was a whip
and a blasphemy, James kicked the horse and walking and tended to
trot.

A moment later, the sleepy eyes of the young man was only a
small cloud shifting dust on the horizon to where a star, separated
from her sisters, leaving a trail bright.

The inhabitants on the
banks Wingdam Road, heard at dawn as a vibrant voice the lark singing
over the plain. Those who slept rough were stirred in their beds to
dream of youth, love and life. Rough peasants face and eager seekers
gold, already at work, ceased their labors and leaned upon their picks
to listen to this romantic adventurer, noting in light of the rosy
dawn, he rode to step Castilian.

CAROLINA

(Episode of Fiddletown)

I

In
the town of Fiddletown was regarded worldwide as a beautiful woman.
His good figure, highlighted by a mop of brown hair splendid characterized
by a beautiful color and a certain languid grace which lent him a
something interesting and distinguished. Dressed Always taste and
Fiddletown was the rage. He had only two flaws: a its velvety eyes,
examined closely, deviating slightly, and stained his cheek left a
small scar caused by a drop of vitriol, a happily single whole bottle
that had cast a jealous rival, with the malicious intent to disfigure
Jerne so beautiful. However, when the observer reached to notice the
irregularity of look, it was usually unable to criticize it and there
were some who claimed that the stain on his cheek he added more charm
and grace. The young editor of The Avalanche, of Fiddletown, argued
privately that it was a hidden dimple and Colonel Roberto reminded
freckles tempting time of Queen Anne, and especially to one of the
most beautiful damn women and, yes, damn them! they never have been
fixed in human eyes. Was a native of New Orleans. This woman had a
scar, one that crossed seams (a faith that is true), from the right
eye to mouth. And this woman, friend, we penetrated to a ... friend,
you crazy ... actually condemned him with his damn soul fascination.
A day I said:

- Celeste, how the hell you did that damn scar</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>