<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document06464</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>131926</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>1459</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Son, replicó el ermitaño, los vientos
que hinchen las velas del navío; algunas veces le sumergen, pero sin ellas no es posible navegar.
La bílis hace iracundo, y causa enfermedades; mas sin bílis no pudiera uno vivir. En la tierra
todo es peligroso, y todo necesario.

Tratóse del deleyte, y probó el ermitaño que era una dádiva de la divinidad; porque el hombre,
dixo, por sí propio no puede tener sensaciones ni ideas: todo en él es prestado, y la pena
y el deleyte le vienen de otro, como su mismo ser.

Pasmábase Zadig de que un hombre que tantos desatinos habia cometido, discurriese con tanto
acierto. Finalmente despues de una conversacion no ménos grata que instructiva, llevó su huésped
á los dos caminantes á un aposento, dando gracias al cielo que le habia enviado dos hombres
tan sabios y virtuosos. Brindóles con dinero de un modo ingenuo y noble que no podia disgustar:
rehusóle el ermitaño, y le dixo que se despedia de él, porque hacia ánimo de partirse para
Babilonia ántes del amanecer. Fué afectuosa su separacion, y con especialidad Zadig se quedó
penetrado de estimacion y cariño á tan amable huésped.

Quando estuvo con el ermitaño en su aposento, hiciéron ámbos un pomposo elogio de su huésped.
Al rayar el alba, despertó el anciano á su camarada. Vámonos, le dixo; quiero empero, miéntras
que duerme todo el mundo, dexar á este buen hombre una prueba de mi estimacion y mi cariño.
Diciendo esto, cogió una tea, y pegó fuego á la casa. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06700</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>76825</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>1372</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Son, "replied the hermit, winds to swell
the sails of the ship, sometimes you are immersed, but without them you can not navigate. The bile
makes angry, and causes disease, but no one could not live bile. On earth everything is dangerous,
and all necessary.

Tratóse of Deleyte, and tested the hermit that was a gift of divinity, because man, he said,
for himself can not have feelings or ideas: everything in it is borrowed,
and the penalty and the delight will come from another, as their very
being.

Zadig Pasmábase that a man who had committed so many blunders, runs with both success. Finally
after a conversation no less pleasant than instructive, led his guest to the two walking into a
room, giving thanks to heaven that he had sent two men so wise and virtuous. Brindóles with
money from a naive and noble so that he could not upset: rehusóle the hermit, and told him that
he said goodbye to him, because to be assumed to mind Babylon before
dawn.

Their separation was affectionate, and specialty Zadig remained esteem and affection penetrated
so kind to host.

Quando was with the hermit in his place, did both a pompous eulogy
of his guest. At daybreak, awakened his old comrade. Come on, told
him, I however, whilst sleeping around the world, to this good man
dexar proof of my esteem and my affection. Saying this, he took a
torch and set fire to the house</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>