<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09773</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>161792</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22861</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Cerca
de este lugar posee unas sesenta aranzadas de olivar, que su padre, militar como él, compró
con dinero ganado al juego. Este es el único lazo, que yo sepa, que a este distrito le une.
Repito, pues, que no me explico su empeño en ser nuestro diputado; pero doy por evidente que,
una vez logrado su empeño, nos volverá la espalda, nos mandará a paseo, y no nos dará ni pizca
de turrón. Como en esto precisamente consiste mi sueño dorado, callándome la razón para no
espantar a los secuaces de V., me decido a ser uno de ellos. Cuente V., pues, conmigo para
elegir diputado a D. Jaime Pimentel, y créame su afectísimo amigo».

Tal era la carta de D. Juan Fresco que tanto alegró el corazón de D. Acisclo. Lo esencial era
que D. Juan apoyase su empresa, fuese por lo que fuese. Lo que don Acisclo quería era aquella
alianza, y poco le asustaban las enrevesadas razones y fatídicos pronósticos en que se fundaba
y que él se guardó bien de confiar a nadie. Sólo de cuando en cuando, si bien haciendo desmedidos
encomios de la entereza, discreción, honradez y sabiduría de D. Juan Fresco, afirmaba D. Acisclo
que era un ente.

--¿Y por qué dice V. que ese D. Juan es un ente?--le preguntó una vez doña Manolita.

--¿Por qué lo he de decir?--contestó don Acisclo--; porque es un ente; porque es el bicho más
raro que he conocido en mi vida.

-XII-

El triunfo

Ente o no ente, D. Juan Fresco valió de mucho a D. Acisclo, el cual, mientras más esperanzas
tenía, más se afanaba y desvelaba porque no se frustrasen.

Los informes que le había dado D. Juan acerca de la condición poco servicial de D. Jaime Pimentel,
no dejaban de mortificarle. Ya, sin embargo, no había modo de retroceder, y lo que convenía
por lo pronto era derrotar a D. Paco, aunque para ello fuese menester valerse del candidato
menos buscador de turrones, más distraído y peor cultivador de distritos que hubiese en todo
el reino.

Don Acisclo solía echar cálculos alegres, y este mismo descuido de su futuro diputado, que
para cualquiera otro hubiera sido un mal, se mostraba a veces con colores risueños y brillantes
a los ojos de su esperanza ambiciosa.

«Si el diputado no hace nada--decía don Acisclo para sí--, si no cumple sus promesas, si no
recompensa los afanes de los electores, yo tendré que volver por ellos, lo cual me dará motivo
para entenderme por mí mismo con el Gobernador de la provincia y hasta con el Ministro, y ser
yo aquí real y directamente el amo, sin ese intermedio enojoso del diputadito. Lo esencial,
pues, es lograr la victoria con gran mayoría, y hacer ver que D. Paco es un trasto a mi lado».

A este fin no quedó medio que D. Acisclo no emplease.

Las elecciones debían ser en el otoño, y durante el verano vivió D. Acisclo en una fiebre de
actividad. Recorrió a caballo todos los pueblos del distrito, que eran siete, ganando votos
para su protegido y quitando parciales a D. Paco. Hasta a la capital del distrito fue varias
veces, y no sin éxito, con el referido objeto.

A no pocos electores de influjo, a quienes D. Paco tenía amarrados, los desamarró D. Acisclo,
exponiendo gallardamente sus capitales. Por estar amarrados, se entiende en lenguaje electoral
de por allí, deber dinero al grande elector. D. Acisclo estuvo rumboso. Lo menos repartió ocho
mil duros al diez por ciento, sin más garantías que pagarés sencillos, libertando así a gentes
amarradas por D. Paco, con escritura pública y dinero prestado al quince.

Todo elector de Villafría iba antes a votar a un lugar cercano, porque en Villafría no había
mesa. Don Acisclo consiguió que se quitase la mesa de dicho lugar y que se diese a Villafría,
población más céntrica y cómoda, según él demostró.

En Villafría estaba seguro don Acisclo de que volcaría el puchero en favor de D. Jaime.

Volcar el puchero significa poner o colgar todos los votos posibles al candidato a quien se
quiere favorecer. Los votos posibles son los de cuantos electores están en las listas, a no
hallarse a mil leguas de distancia o en la sepultura. Y aun ha habido ocasiones en que los
ausentes y hasta los difuntos han votado.

Cuentan las crónicas electorales de aquel distrito que, no bien supo D. Paco la que D. Acisclo
le estaba urdiendo, empezó a trabajar en contra, saliendo del letargo, o mejor diremos del
tranquilo y descuidado reposo en que su confianza y seguridad hasta allí le habían tenido.
Esto, naturalmente, hizo que don Acisclo tuviese que redoblar cada vez más su actividad. Así
es que no paraba. Su vida era un tejido incesante de conferencias, excursiones a este o al
otro pueblo, tratos y cartas que escribir y que leer. Pepe Güeto se hizo el ayudante y el secretario
de D. Acisclo, y también escribía, viajaba y conferenciaba.

Doña Luz y doña Manolita se hacían compañía mutuamente, abandonadas por D. Acisclo y Pepe Güeto.
Y a las dos servía también de acompañante el P. Enrique, único varón quizá de todo el distrito
que no intervenía en el asunto electoral.

El padre había intervenido sólo en los primeros días para tratar de disuadir a D. Acisclo de
que se mezclase en elecciones; pero D. Acisclo no se dejaba convencer por nadie, y cuando lo
reconoció así su sobrino, se retrajo, se calló, y no volvió a dar a entender ni siquiera que
sabía en qué maremágnum andaba engolfado su tío.

A éste le molestaba ya bastante la flojera y falta de formalidad del candidato. El candidato
había prometido visitar el distrito; las elecciones se venían encima, y el tal D. Jaime no
llegaba. Su contrario estaba, ya instalado en casa de D. Paco, prometiendo empleos para cuando
volviese al poder, que sería pronto, vendiendo protección, y conquistando voluntades.

Don Jaime, entre tanto, no sólo no venía, sino que apenas sí se dignaba escribir, salvo a D.
Acisclo, y esto de tarde en tarde y por estilo lacónico y seco.

Pero fuese como fuese, el lance estaba ya empeñado; para D. Acisclo era cuestión de amor propio;
y aunque D. Jaime hubiera sido el mismo diablo, D. Acisclo hubiera echado el resto por sacarle
triunfante.

En suma, para no cansar más a mis lectores, acabaré por decir que don Acisclo recogió al fin
el premio de sus fatigas.

Las elecciones llegaron, y D. Acisclo venció en las elecciones. Don Jaime Pimentel salió diputado
por una gran mayoría.

Algunos quieren dar a entender que D. Acisclo hizo mil tramoyas y falsedades; pero nada se
pudo probar, y por consiguiente no debemos creerlo.

Don Jaime Pimentel, sin abandonar la corte, sin escribir apenas carta alguna, con el mayor
sosiego, tuvo el gusto de recibir su acta, casi limpia, pues sólo llevaba dos protestas insignificantes
y mal fundadas.

El júbilo de D. Acisclo fue grande después de la victoria. ¡Qué lauro el suyo! ¡Qué muestra
de poder la que acababa de dar! Con un candidato invisible, descuidado, flojo; con un enemigo
tan fuerte, tan único, tan modelo y tan fénix entre los representantes del pueblo, había logrado
vencer, y vencer por una gran mayoría. Después de admirarse de su propia capacidad para la
política, sólo se reconocía deudor a D. Juan Fresco y a la copiosa turba de bermejinos que
le siguieron en el día de la elección como a caudillo respetado.

Durante todo este largo período electoral, las relaciones amistosas de doña Luz y del P. Enrique
se fueron estrechando más cada día. Hasta doña Manolita, dejándose llevar del entusiasmo de
su marido, o bien compartiéndole, no había pensado más que en las elecciones.

Doña Luz y el padre eran sin duda las dos únicas personas de cierta posición en todo el distrito,
que no habían pensado en éste ni en el otro candidato, y que no se habían afanado por el triunfo
de cualquiera de ellos.

En medio de aquella agitación política, habían hallado retraimiento dulcísimo en la misma casa
de quien la promovía; y allí eran las pláticas suaves y encumbradas, y las conversaciones amenas,
en que siempre aprendía algo doña Luz, en que siempre hallaba nuevas excelencias en el entendimiento
y en el corazón del padre, y en que el padre, a su vez, no dejaba nunca de pasmarse del despejo,
de la agudeza, de la notable discreción, de la fantasía poética y de la sensibilidad exquisita
de su bella interlocutora.

Don Anselmo había terciado en los debates, aunque ya no tanto, por haberle tenido también D.
Acisclo muy interesado en las elecciones. Y el cura don Miguel había seguido yendo con constancia
a la tertulia, si bien los diálogos sabios del Padre y de doña Luz le magnetizaban y embelesaban
de tal suerte, que a los pocos minutos de empezar a oírlos, solía quedarse profundamente dormido,
acompañándolos y animándolos a veces con una música de ronquidos interminables y sonoros.

Resultaba de todo ello que la única persona, que era en verdad constante e inteligente testigo
del mutuo afecto y de los íntimos coloquios de doña Luz y del Padre, era doña Manolita. Yo
no quiero hacer a ésta, ni a ninguno de mis héroes, mejor de lo que son o de lo que fueron.
Doña Manolita no era una paloma sin hiel; y no porque odiase a alguien, sino porque no dejaba
de tener malicia. Más bien se podía tildar a doña Manolita de tenerla. Más bien se la podía
acusar de que, sin envidia ni encono, y sólo por amor al arte, gustaba algo de la murmuración,
y seguía demasiado, como regla para sus juicios, aquella terrible sentencia de piensa mal y
acertarás. Sin embargo, merced a la veneración cariñosa que doña Luz le infundía, ella interpretaba
siempre por el lado más benévolo todos sus actos y discursos. Por esto, aunque a la perspicacia
de doña Manolita no pudo ocultarse largo tiempo aquella inclinación irresistible de dos almas,
doña Manolita no dejó nunca de hacer justicia a doña Luz, y reconoció y declaró, allá en el
fondo de su pecho, que en el de su amiga no había la más leve intención de perturbar el ánimo
del Padre ni de atraerle con coqueterías culpadas.

El respeto y el cariño de la hija del médico al P. Enrique eran grandes también; pero no tanto
que le impidiesen por completo todo fallo algo contrario sobre su conducta. Doña Manolita,
pues, sin pensar que doña Luz hubiese dado para ello ni ocasión ni motivo, empezó a sospechar
que el Padre, más o menos confusa y vagamente, estaba enamorado. Por respeto a su amiga, y
porque en los lugares no anda la gente con sutilezas etéreas o pasadas por alambique, y porque
con decir ella algo hubiera dado pie para que se añadiese mucho, doña Manolita ni a su padre
confió el resultado de sus observaciones. Sólo le confió a Pepe Güeto, a quien nada ocultaba;
pero exigiéndole el más profundo sigilo.

La gravedad de doña Luz y del Padre cortaba los vuelos a todas las audacias de doña Manolita,
quien jamás se propasó a dirigir al Padre, ni en broma y con rodeos y perífrasis, la indirecta
más oscura sobre la pasión que en él imaginaba. Doña Manolita siguió, no obstante, observando.
Pepe Güeto observó también. Ambos esposos se comunicaban luego lo que habían observado. De
esta suerte venían los dos a corroborarse en la idea de que el Padre, quizá sin saberlo, amaba
a doña Luz por estilo místico y sutil, y que doña Luz se dejaba adorar sin presumir ningún
término disgustoso, sin reflexionar en toda la trascendencia que aquella adoración podría tener,
y sin ver en ella más que una amistad tierna, sencilla e impecable, como la que ella profesaba
al convaleciente y poético misionero.

Ocurrió en esto un suceso que no se esperaba ya. De pronto, y cuando D. Acisclo se había resignado
a que su diputado fuese invisible para el distrito, éste le escribió anunciándole que inmediatamente
venía a visitarle. El primer pueblo en que se presentaría había de ser Villafría, desde donde,
a caballo, y con la pompa correspondiente, había de pasar a recorrer y visitar los otros pueblos.

Don Acisclo se alegró mucho de esta venida, que iba a darle la mayor importancia; pero tuvo
que afanarse para disponer bien las cosas, a fin de hacer a D. Jaime Pimentel una brillante
recepción. Para hospedarle con decoro y hasta con lujo, acudió a doña Luz pidiéndole las mejores
habitaciones de su casa solariega, no ocupadas por su sobrino; y para ofrecer a D. Jaime un
buen caballo en que montar e ir de pueblo en pueblo, acudió asimismo a doña Luz, pidiéndole
prestado su hermoso caballo negro. Doña Luz tuvo que acceder a todo.

La víspera del día en que debía llegar D. Jaime, todos estaban alborotados en el lugar con
la gran fiesta de la recepción que iba a haber. Hasta doña Manolita estaba más alegre que lo
de costumbre y muy parlanchina. En la tertulia diaria sólo asistían ella, doña Luz y el Padre,
porque los demás andaban aún ocupados en los preparativos de la fiesta, o descansando del ajetreo
de aquel día.

Entonces tuvo doña Manolita una ocurrencia algo maliciosa, y que, en su sentir, había de darle
mucha luz en sus investigaciones. ¿Por qué no había de embromar a doña Luz, pronosticando que
D. Jaime, de quien la fama decía maravillosos encomios, y que era libre y soltero, iba a enamorarse
de ella, apenas la viese, con el gustoso asombro de hallar en una villa pequeña tan completo
dechado de elegancia, distinción y hermosura? ¿Por qué, al embromar así a doña Luz, con algo
que la halagaría, no había de dar solapadamente una broma bastante pesada al Padre, cuyo amor,
enmarañado y turbio en el centro de la conciencia, se vendría a aclarar con el reactivo de
los celos? Doña Manolita, al dar la broma, miraría al Padre, a ver si se inmutaba o si permanecía
impasible, en apariencia al menos.

Como lo pensó, lo hizo. Doña Manolita dijo a doña Luz que D. Jaime iba a prendarse de ella,
apenas la viese; que D. Jaime no podía sospechar que, en un lugar tan arrinconado como Villafría,
estuviese oculto tanto tesoro; y que, a su ver, era evidente el amor futuro de D. Jaime.

--¿Qué forastero--prosiguió--, no se ha enamorado de ti, de cuantos han venido a Villafría,
jóvenes, libres y en estado de merecer? Prepara, pues, el almíbar con que sueles propinar las
calabazas, si es que también piensas dárselas a éste. Pero, ¿quién sabe? El pretendiente, que
ya columbro, no es rústico, ni lugareño, como los que has tenido hasta ahora. Dicen que es
la flor y nata de los elegantes de Madrid, y además un bizarro militar y un hombre de gran
porvenir y de extraordinario talento. ¿Serás tan fiera que también le desdeñes?

Doña Luz, sin enojarse, antes bien algo lisonjeada, contestó negando la validez del pronóstico,
y asegurando, con modestia un poco fingida, que don Jaime, acostumbrado a ver en la corte tantas
bellas mujeres, no repararía en ella ni le haría caso.

--Además--dijo doña Luz--, no haya miedo de que me pretenda ese caballero. Yo no soy lo que
se llama un buen partido. Para él se necesita una rica heredera, que dé alas a su ambición,
y no una señorita pobre que le encadene y le sirva de rémora y estorbo. Créeme, Manuela; ya
te lo he dicho mil veces: yo no me casaré nunca... ni quiero casarme. No hablemos de esas tonterías,
ni en broma.

Doña Manolita, durante estas frases que entre su amiga y ella se cruzaban, miró de soslayo
al Padre y creyó ver que se había puesto más pálido que de costumbre. Por lo demás el Padre
permaneció silencioso, y no dio su parecer ni sobre el enamoramiento posible de D. Jaime, ni
sobre el constante propósito de doña Luz de permanecer soltera.

A las diez se retiró a su casa, y las dos amigas quedaron solas.

Alentada entonces doña Manolita con lo bien que su primera broma había sido tolerada, y tal
vez agradecida como lisonja, en el fondo del alma de la hija del marqués, cayó en la tentación
de aventurarse a dar otra broma bastante menos ligera.

Sin reflexionarlo mucho, dijo, pues, de este modo:

--¡Ay! ¡Hija! Me arrepiento de haberte dicho lo de D. Jaime.

--¿Y por qué te arrepientes?--preguntó con sencillez doña Luz--. Yo no creo probable que ese
caballero cortesano se enamore de mí, en tres o cuatro días que ha de estar por aquí; pero
como ni eso es imposible, ni me ofende el que tú, estimándome en más de lo que merezco, me
vaticines tal triunfo, no tienes para qué arrepentirte, a no ser por el temor de exaltar demasiado
mi amor propio.

--No es ese temor--replicó la hija del médico--, lo que me induce al arrepentimiento, sino
el temor de haber lastimado un corazón sensible, de haberle hecho una profunda herida.

--No te comprendo--dijo doña Luz--; ¿qué quieres dar a entender? ¿Qué corazón sensible es ese?

--El del P. Enrique--respondió en mala hora doña Manolita.

Doña Luz se puso roja como la grana. Toda la sangre de su cuerpo se diría que se le subió a
la cabeza. Todo el orgullo de su casta se agolpó y amontonó en su corazón. No vio más que ridiculez
indigna en que la creyesen objeto de la pasión de un fraile. Ella creía que un fraile la podía
admirar por su talento, estimar por sus virtudes, venerar por su conducta intachable, y gustar
de su trato y conversación, y complacerse en ser su amigo; pero enamorarse de ella le parecía
tan absurdo, tan contrario a todas las conveniencias y leyes sociales y religiosas, tan monstruosamente
feo y chocante, que no quería, ni podía, ni debía sospecharlo en persona del juicio, de la
circunspección y hasta de la santidad que en el P. Enrique notaba. Doña Luz miró, pues, como
una malicia villana y ruin el pensamiento de doña Manolita, y como una insolencia la expresión
de dicho pensamiento por medio de la palabra.

--Lo que acabas de proferir--exclamó con la voz balbuciente de cólera--, es un insulto, es
una dura acusación contra el P. Enrique y contra mí. Ni el padre delira, ni yo le he dado ocasión
para que delire. A fin de que mi limpia fama esté al abrigo de la maledicencia, me he encerrado
en este lugar, me he apartado casi de todo trato humano, he huido de la juventud, mientras
he sido joven; siéndolo todavía, como lo soy, no he admitido en mi intimidad sino a viejos
de sesenta años como tu padre, el cura y don Acisclo, y nada de esto me ha valido. Porque yo,
de cerca de treinta años, me he abandonado, me he confiado con gusto, lo declaro francamente,
en la amistad honrada de un siervo de Dios, probado en mil fatigas, quebrantado por ellas,
lleno de ciencia y de virtud, no se concibe esta amistad, no se explica este trato, sino por
motivos viles e impuros. Y no son los rústicos del lugar, no son los que no me conocen, sino
mi mejor amiga la que me sospecha y me injuria.

La pobre doña Manolita se quedó aterrada: se compungió, y al cabo se le saltaron las lágrimas.

--Pero, mujer--dijo--; no te enojes por amor de Dios. Yo, sin duda, me he explicado mal. Yo
no digo que sea impuro el amor del Padre....

--¿Qué disparates son los tuyos?--interrumpió doña Luz--. ¿Qué extravío de ideas? ¿Qué necias
distinciones pretendes hacer? ¿Cómo cohonestar el amor de un fraile a una doncella honrada?
Tal amor es impuro siempre; es infame; es sacrílego.

Viendo doña Manolita que no había manera de remediar su torpeza, y apuradísima de haber irritado
tanto a doña Luz, a quien quería de todo corazón, no pronunció una sola palabra más; pero lloró
y sollozó como si le hubiese sobrevenido la más cruel desgracia.

Entonces doña Luz, que tenía buen fondo, a pesar de su soberbia, sintió que había estado dura
y áspera en demasía, y pidió perdón a doña Manolita, besándola y poco menos que llorando también.

Las dos amigas vinieron a quedar de resultas mucho más amigas que antes. Doña Luz se convenció
de que doña Manolita no había tenido intención de deslustrar en lo más mínimo la pureza de
sus relaciones amistosas con el P. Enrique; y doña Manolita hizo por convencerse y hasta se
convenció por el momento de que el P. Enrique, ni siquiera como Dante amó a Beatriz, como Petrarca
amó a Laura, o como don Quijote amó a Dulcinea, era capaz de amar a doña Luz; porque, siendo
él un fraile y ella una señorita muy bien educada y honestísima, tal amor, por alambicado,
espiritual e incorpóreo que fuese, tenía un no sé qué de indecorosamente plebeyo y de grotescamente
pecaminoso que con la condición de su bella y soberbia amiga se ajustaba muy mal.

No bien acabadas de hacer las paces, llegó don Acisclo con Pepe Güeto, quienes no advirtieron
las huellas de la pasada tempestad. Cenaron los cuatro en amistosa compañía, y con buen apetito,
y se fueron luego a dormir.

Al día siguiente se celebró con pompa y estruendo la entrada triunfal de D. Jaime en Villafría.
Cuantos tenían caballo, y no pocos que sólo tenían mulo o burro, fueron de madrugada a recibirle
en la estación, con D. Acisclo al frente, y a eso de las once volvieron todos con el diputado,
caballero éste en el hermoso caballo negro de doña Luz.

A las puertas del lugar salieron los muchachos y los hombres de a pie a recibir la lucida cabalgata,
y todos entraron por aquellas calles al son de las campanas que se habían echado a vuelo, entre
vivas y aclamaciones, y atronando el aire a tiros de cuantas escopetas estaban servibles en
Villafría.

-XIII-

Crisis

Después de haber rechazado con tan cruel desabrimiento las palabras de doña Manolita y después
de hechas las paces, doña Luz pensó a sus solas en el valor y motivo de aquellas palabras;
y, como si una claridad nueva y extraña iluminase los más oscuros laberintos de su cerebro,
creyó percibir la verdad de todo y reconoció que su amiga tenía algunos visos de razón al decir
lo que dijo.

Doña Luz se había enojado quizá porque su propia conciencia, aprovechándose de las palabras
de doña Manolita, había formulado una acusación mucho más severa. ¿Qué diferencia radical e
importante se da entre la amistad más tierna y exclusiva, entre la predilección más marcada
de un hombre por una mujer y de una mujer por un hombre, ninguno de los dos viejo aún, y el
amor más puro, más platónico y más sublime? Doña Luz se ponía a sí misma esta cuestión; y,
no acertando a resolverla sino en el sentido de que no se da diferencia, o que, si se da, apenas
es perceptible y se quiebra de puro sutil, decidía que no era absurdo ni insolencia suponer
y afirmar que estuviese enamorado de ella el P. Enrique. El Padre, encadenado por el respeto,
teniendo en cuenta su estado, sus votos y su posición, se había guardado bien de manifestar
su cariño de un modo que hiciese sospechar ni remotamente que no era legítimo y sin tacha;
pero, sin duda, que en el fondo de su alma le sentía.

Luego que doña Luz dejaba esto como sentado y evidente, se preguntaba también: «¿Y yo qué he
hecho para inspirar esta pasión? ¿Qué culpa adquiero de que él me ame? ¿Hasta qué punto he
dado y sigo dando pábulo a su afecto?». La contestación que doña Luz se daba era contradictoria
y confusa. Ora se condenaba; ora se absolvía. Se condenaba al reconocer que ella había disimulado
mucho menos que él la complacencia con que le oía, el contento que su vista le causaba, el
deleite que su conversación le traía siempre, y que ella por instinto irreflexivo, pero depravado,
gustaba de parecer hermosa y elegante a todos, y particularmente a las personas a quienes quería,
entre las cuales no podía menos de incluir al Padre.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07997</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>314552</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20978</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Close this
place has some sixty olive aranzadas that his father, military as he bought with money earned
in the game. This is the only link that I know, that binds him to this district. I repeat,
therefore, I do not understand their commitment to be our congressman, but I for granted that,
once achieved its best efforts, we will return back, send us a walk, and we will not pinch nougat.
As this is precisely my golden dream, silencing the reason for not scare the minions V., I
decided to be one of them. Count V, then, with me D. choose deputy Jaime Pimentel, and believe
me your affectionate friend. "

Such was the letter D. Juan Fresco so glad the heart of D. Acisclo. It was essential that D. John
supported his business, so it would be. What we wanted was that Don Acisclo alliance, and little
he scared the convoluted reasons and ominous forecasts on which it was based and he was careful not
to trust anyone. Only occasionally, while making intemperate praise of integrity, discretion, honesty
and wisdom of D. John Fresco, said D. Acisclo it was an entity.

-
"Why says V. that D. John is an entity? - Once asked Mrs. Manolita.

-
Why do I say? - Said Don Acisclo - for it is an entity, because the
bug is more I have rarely met in my life.

-XII-

Triumph

Being or
not being, D. Juan Fresco worth a lot to D. Acisclo, which, while
more hope had, the more he toiled and sleepless because they are frustrated.

The

reports had given D. Juan about the condition of D. unhelpful Jaime
Pimentel, did not fail to mortify.

Already, however, there was no way back, and what suited for now was to defeat D. Paco, even
if this were necessary to make use of the candidate less search nougat,
more distracted and worst grower districts have all the kingdom.

Don used to throw stones Acisclo happy, and this neglect of his future deputy, for anyone else
would have been a bad, appeared sometimes bright and cheerful colors
in the eyes of his ambitious hopes.

"If the deputy does nothing - said Don Acisclo for themselves - if not keep your promises, if
not reward the labors of the voters, I will come back for them, which will give me reason to
understand for myself with the Governor of the province and to the
Minister, and be I hereby direct the master real and without that
annoying middle of diputadito.

Essentially therefore, is to win a large majority, and show that D. Paco is a junk to me.
"

To this end it was not medium D. Acisclo not employees.

The elections were to be in the fall, and during the summer lived D. Acisclo in a fever activity.
He traveled on horseback all the villages in the district, who were seven, winning votes for
his protege and removing partial D. Paco. Up to the district capital
was several times, and not unsuccessfully, with the said object.

A few do not influence voters, whom D. Paco had tied, the untied D. Acisclo gallantly exposing
their capital. Being tied up, language is understood in electoral over there, owing money to
the great elector. D. Acisclo was pompous.

Distributed at least eight thousand dollars to ten percent, with no guarantees that simple notes,
thus freeing people tied by D. Paco, with deed and money lent to fifteen.

Every voter was Villafría before voting in a place nearby, because there was Villafría table. Don
Acisclo got to take off the table of the area and to be given to
Villafria population most central and convenient, as he demonstrated.

In Villafría Acisclo Don was sure that would overturn the pot in favor
of D. Jaime.

Tilt the pot or hanging means putting all possible votes to the candidate who is wants to favor.
The voting power of those voters are are on the lists, not be a thousand miles away or in
the grave.

And yet there have been occasions when absent and even the dead voted.

The chronicles of that electoral district, when he found D. Paco, D. Acisclo I was weaving,
began to work against, out of lethargy, or better say the careless quiet repose in which their
confidence had been up there. This, of course, was that Don had to redouble Acisclo increasing
its activity. So is not stopped. His life was a relentless tissue lectures, excursions to the east or
other people, treatment and letters to write and read.

Güeto Pepe became the assistant and secretary D. Acisclo, and also writing, traveling and in conference.

Manolita
Dona Luz and another company were made, abandoned by D. Güeto Acisclo and Pepe. And both also
served as accompanist Fr Henry, only son perhaps the entire district
not intervene in the election issue.

The father had intervened only in the early days to try to dissuade D. Acisclo of to meddle in
elections, but D. Acisclo not let anyone convince anyone, and when
recognized and his nephew, retreated, paused, and did not even imply
that knew which engulfed his uncle walked welter.

To him pretty upset and laziness and lack of formality of the candidate. The candidate had promised
to visit the district, elections are coming up, and that D. Jaime
no arrived.

His opponent was already installed in the house of D. Paco, promising jobs for when return to
power, it would be soon, selling protection, and conquering minds.

Don Jaime, meanwhile, not only coming, but scarcely deigned to write,
except for D. Acisclo, and that from time to time and laconic style,
dry place.

But be that as it may, the set was already committed, to D. Acisclo was a matter of pride; and although
D. Jaime had been the devil, D. Acisclo had thrown the rest to get
triumphant.

In sum, not to tire my readers, I'll end by saying that Don finally picked Acisclo the reward
of his labors.

The elections came, and D. Acisclo won the election. Congressman Don Jaime Pimentel left by
a large majority.

Some want to imply that D. Acisclo did a thousand stage machinery and falsehoods, but nothing
could prove, and therefore should not believe.

Don Jaime Pimentel, without leaving the court, not just write a letter, with the highest calm, was
pleased to receive your certificate, almost clean, they only had two minor protests and ill-founded.

The
joy of D. Acisclo was great after the win. Lauro yours! Which shows
of power that had just given!

With an invisible candidate, careless, lazy, with an enemy so strong, so unique, so as phoenix pattern
and the representatives of the people, had achieved win and win by a landslide. After marveling
at his own capacity for policy, only acknowledged debtor D. Juan
Fresco and abundant peat bermejinos that followed on the day of the
election as a respected leader.

Throughout this long election period, the friendly relations and Dona Luz P. Enrique it was closing more
every day. To Dona Manolita, drifting of the enthusiasm of her husband, or share it, I never thought
more than in elections.

Doña Luz and father were certainly the only two people in a certain position in the whole district,
had not thought of this or the other candidate, and who had not toiled for victory any of them. 

In
the midst of political turmoil, had been found in the same withdrawal sweet home of those who promoted,
and there were talks soft and lofty, and pleasant conversations, you always learn something Dona
Luz, which was always new excellence in understanding and in the
heart of the father and the father, in turn, never failed to amaze
the clearance, sharpness, the remarkable discretion of poetic fantasy
and exquisite sensitivity its fine interlocutor.

Don Anselmo was third in the debates, although not as much, for having been too D. Acisclo very
interested in the election. And the priest Don Miguel had kept going to record to socialize,
while Father's wise dialogue and Dona Luz magnetized and enthralled him in such a way, that
within minutes of beginning to hear, he would stay asleep, sometimes accompanied and animated
with music and endless sound of snoring.

It was from this that the only person who was really consistent and intelligent control of mutual
affection and intimate conversation of Mrs. Light and the Father, was Dona Manolita. I I do not
want to do this, or any of my heroes, better than they are or what they were. Doña Manolita
was not a dove without gall, and not because they hated someone, but because he kept have malice.
Rather, it could tick Dona Manolita have it.

Rather it could be acknowledge that without envy or bitterness, and just for the sake of art,
like some gossip, and still too much, as a rule for his judgments, that terrible sentence
wrong and think be right. However, thanks to the loving devotion that inspired him Dona Luz,
she played always more benevolent side all his acts and speeches. Therefore, although insight
Dona Manolita long time could not hide that irresistible inclination of two souls, Dona Manolita
never failed to do justice to Dona Luz, and acknowledged and declared, back in bottom of his
chest, in her friend had not the slightest intention of disrupting the mood Father's lure with
flirting or blamed.

The respect and affection of the doctor's daughter Fr Enrique were great too, but not both that
any failure would prevent something completely opposite of their behavior. Doña Manolita then,
without thinking that Dona Luz had given no occasion for it or why he began to suspect the
Father, more or less confused and vaguely, was in love. Respect for his friend and because in
the places people do not walk the ethereal subtleties or passed over still, and because to
say something she had given rise to be added much, Donna and her father Manolita entrusted with
the results of his observations. Entrusted only to Güeto Pepe, who was hiding anything; but demanding
the deepest secrecy.

The severity of the Father Dona Luz and cut flights to all the boldness of Dona Manolita who never molested
directing the Father, even as a joke and rodeos and circumlocution, indirect darker on the passion
that he imagined. Doña Manolita continued, however, watching. Pepe
Güeto also observed.

Both spouses are then communicated what they had observed. Of Thus came the two to corroborate
the idea that the Father, perhaps without knowing it, loved Dona Luz by mystical and subtle
style, and that Dona Luz worship was left without assuming any disgusting term, without reflecting
on all the significance that this worship might have, and seeing in it more than a tender friendship,
friendly and impeccable, as she professed the convalescent and poetic mission.

It happened in an incident that was not expected now. Suddenly, when D. Acisclo had resigned
to his deputy were invisible to the district, he immediately wrote him telling him that came
to visit. The first town that was to be presented Villafría, whence horse, and the corresponding
bubble, was to pass to travel and visit other towns.

Don Acisclo was glad of this coming, which would give the greatest importance, but had to strive
to have good things to do D. Jaime Pimentel brilliant reception. To accommodate you with dignity
and even luxury, came to asking the best Dona Luz rooms of his ancestral home, not occupied by his
nephew, and to offer D. Jaime a good horse to ride and go from village to village, also went
to Dona Luz, asking lent her beautiful black horse. Luz had to agree to everything.

The day before they had to reach D. Jaime, everyone was abuzz in place with the great feast
of the reception would be. To Dona Manolita was more cheerful than usual and very talkative. In the
daily gatherings she attended only Dona Luz and the Father because
the rest were still busy with the preparations for the party, or relaxing
from the hustle that day.

Donna then had an occurrence Manolita something malicious, and that
his feelings had to give much light on their research.

Why was not to tease Dona Luz, predicting that D. Jaime, who said fame wonderful praise, and
he was free and single, would love it, just to see her with the happy surprise of finding in
a small village as complete paragon of elegance, distinction and beauty? Why, to tease and Dona
Luz, with some the flatter, could not make a joke rather heavy covertly to the Father, whose
love, tangled and murky in the center of consciousness, it would clarify with the reagent
jealousy? Doña Manolita, after making a joke, I would look to the
Father, to see if they budge or remained impassive, seemingly at least.

As

I said than done. Manolita said Dona Dona Luz D. Jaime was going to fall in love with her, just
saw her, that D. Jaime did not suspect that in a place so cornered as Villafria much treasure was
hidden, and that, in his view, it was clear the future of D. Love
Jaime.

- What stranger - he continued - not in love with you, who
have come to Villafria young, free and in a state of merit?

Prepare, therefore, the syrup with you usually tip the pumpkins, if you think also give to
it. But who knows? The suitor, which Columbro and is not rustic, or local, as you've had so
far. They say it the cream of the elegant Madrid, and also a brave soldier and a man of great
future and extraordinary talent. Will you be so fierce that also despise?

Doña Luz, without anger, but rather something flattered, responded by denying the validity
of the forecast, and ensuring, with a little mock modesty, that Don Jaime, accustomed to seeing
on the court so beautiful women, it would notice it or would ignore.

- In addition - "Dona Luz - no fear that I intend to that gentleman.

I'm not what is called a good game. For him it needs a rich heiress, to give wings to his ambition,
and not a poor girl that string and will serve as a burden and nuisance. Believe me, Manuela,
and I've said a thousand times, I never will marry me ... I do not
want to marry.

Let's not talk nonsense, even in jest.

Doña Manolita during these sentences between her friend and she crossed, glanced Father and thought
he saw had been paler than usual. Otherwise the Father remained silent and did not give their
opinion or possible crush on D. Jaime, no the constant aim of Dona Luz to stay single.

At ten o'clock he retired to his home, and the two friends were left
alone.

Dona Manolita then encouraged with how well his first joke was tolerated,
and such Once grateful as flattery, in the depths of the soul of the
daughter of the Marquis, was tempted venturing to make another joke
a lot less light.

Without thinking much, he said, because, as follows:

- Ay! Daughter! I regret having said what's D. Jaime.

- Why do you regret? - Simply asked Dona Luz -. I do not think probable that courtly knight falls in love
with me, in three or four days you have to be here, but and even that is impossible, or you
are offended me, estimated at more than I deserve, I foretell such a triumph, you have to do
to repent, but for the fear of too exalted my pride.

- It's not that fear - said the doctor's daughter - which leads me to repentance, but fear
of having hurt a sensitive heart, of having made a deep wound.

- I do not understand - "Dona Luz -, what do you mean? What is this tender heart?

- The P. Enrique - said in an evil hour Mrs. Manolita.

Luz blushed scarlet. All the blood in his body would be turned up to head. All the pride of
caste was gathered and piled in his heart. Saw nothing but ridiculous indignant they believed
that the object of the passion of a friar. She believed that a friar could admired for their
talent, estimated by his virtues revered for its impeccable behavior,
and taste their intercourse and conversation, and pleased to be your
friend, but seemed to fall in love so absurd, so contrary to all the
conveniences and social and religious laws, so monstrously ugly and
shocking, I did not want, or could, or should suspect it in person
the trial, the circumspection and even sanctity in the P. Enrique
showed.

Luz looked for, as an evil villain and mean Manolita Dona thought
and expression as an insult of that thinking through the floor.

-
What you have just uttered - said in a voice stammering with rage
- is an insult, it a harsh accusation against Fr Henry and me.

Neither the father is delirious, and I have given occasion to rave. A clean so that my fame
is protected from slander, I've enclosed in this place, I have separated
almost everything humanely, I fled the youth, while I was young, be
so still, as I am, I have admitted my privacy but old sixty years
as your father, the priest, Don Acisclo, and none of this has earned
me.

For me, about thirty years I have left, I have trusted with pleasure, I declare frankly in friendship
honored servant of God, tested in a thousand hardships, broken by them, full of science and
virtue, not conceived this friendship, this treatment is not explained,
but vile and impure motives.

And there are the rustic place, not that I do not know, but my best friend and me I suspect injury.

Poor
Donna was terrified Manolita: is pricked, and after he burst into tears.

- But, my dear - he said -, do not get mad for love of God. I certainly have explained me wrong.
I I'm not saying that is impure the Father's love ....

- What nonsense are yours? - Interrupted Dona Luz -. What loss of ideas? What foolish distinctions
intend to do? How do you explain away the love of a brother to a girl honored? Such love is
always impure, is infamous, it is sacrilegious.

Viewing Dona Manolita there was no way to remedy his clumsiness, and have irritated apuradísima
both Dona Luz, whom he loved with all my heart, did not utter a single word, but cried and sobbed as
if he had come upon the most cruel misfortune.

Then Dona Luz, who had a good background, despite his pride, he felt he had been hard rough and too
much, and apologized to Mrs. Manolita, kissing and all but crying
too.

The two friends came to get a result much more friendly than before. Luz was convinced Dona Manolita
that he had not intended to tarnish in the least purity friendly
relations with the P. Henry, and Mrs. Manolita made by convincing
and even convinced by the time that P. Henry, even as Dante loved
Beatrice, like Petrarch Laura loved, or loved Dulcinea Don Quixote,
was able to doña Luz love, because, being him a monk and she a highly
educated lady and honestísima, such love, convoluted, spiritual and
incorporeal as it was, had a something unseemly and grotesque commoner
the sinful condition of your beautiful and superb fitted very bad
friend.

No well-finished to make peace, came Don Pepe Güeto Acisclo who did not notice last traces of
the storm.

They dined in the four friendly company, and with good appetite,
and then went to sleep.

The next day was celebrated with pomp and din the triumphal entry of D. Jaime in Villafría.
Few had horses, and not a few who had only mule or donkey, went at dawn to greet at the station,
with D. Acisclo the front, and about eleven o'clock they all returned to the deputy, Knight him
in the beautiful black horse Dona Luz.

At the gates of the place came the boys and men on foot to receive the ride lucida, and they
all went through the streets to the sound of the bells that were cast in flight between live
and cheers, and thunderous shot from air guns were serviceable in many Villafría.

-XIII-

Crisis

Having rejected as cruel despondency Manolita Dona words and then
of made peace, Dona Luz thought to their own in the value and purpose
of those words; and, as if a strange new light illuminate the darkest
labyrinths of his brain, thought he heard the whole truth and acknowledged
that his friend had some show of reason to say he said.

Luz was angry perhaps because his own conscience, taking advantage of the words Dona Manolita had
entered a more severe charge. What difference is radical and important is between the tender and
exclusive friendship between the most marked predilection a man for a woman and a woman by
a man, neither old yet, and love purest, most sublime Platonic? Luz itself is put this matter, and
not conceive resolve but in the sense that no difference occurs, or, if given, only is obvious and
subtle cigar breaks, I decided it was not absurd or insolence to
assume and claim that she was in love with Fr Enrique. Father, chained
by respect, taking into account their state, their votes and positions,
he had kept well to state their love in a way that would make even
remotely suspect that it was not legitimate and unblemished; but certainly
in the bottom of his soul he felt.

Dona Luz after leaving this as
sitting and obvious, he asked again: "What about me I done to inspire
this passion? What acquire fault that he loves me? To what extent
have given and continue to give fuel to his affection? ". The answer
was that Dona Luz was contradictory and confusing. Ora was condemned,
now is absolved. Was condemned to recognize that she had concealed
much less than the complacency with which he heard him, the glad sight
caused him, the delight in his conversation he always brought, and
she instinctively reckless, but depraved, liked to look beautiful
and elegant at all, and particularly people who wanted among which
could not fail to include the Father</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>