<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07766</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>513592</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22508</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> «Adiós, hijos míos...
Adiós, vida... Yo no quiero morir... ¡no quiero morir!...»

Los dos hombres sintieron la necesidad de decir algo, de cerrar la página de su existencia
con una afirmación.

--¡Viva la República!--gritó el alcalde.

--¡Viva Francia!--dijo el cura.

Desnoyers creyó que ambos habían gritado lo mismo.

Se alzaron dos verticales sobre las cabezas: el brazo del sacerdote trazó en el aire un signo,
el sable del jefe del piquete relampagueó al mismo tiempo lívidamente... Un trueno seco, rotundo,
seguido de varias explosiones tardías.

Sintió lástima don Marcelo por la pobre humanidad al ver las formas grotescas que adopta en
el momento de morir. Unos se desplomaron como sacos medio vacíos; otros rebotaron en el suelo
lo mismo que pelotas; algunos dieron un salto de gimnasta, con los brazos en alto, cayendo
de espaldas ó de bruces, en una actitud de nadador. Vió cómo salían del montón humano piernas
contorsionadas por los estremecimientos de la agonía... Unos soldados avanzaron con el mismo
gesto de los cazadores que van á cobrar sus piezas. De la palpitación de los miembros revueltos
se elevaron unas melenas blancas y una mano débil que se esforzaba por repetir su signo. Varios
tiros y culatazos en el lívido montón chorreante de sangre... Y los últimos temblores de vida
quedaron borrados para siempre.

El oficial había encendido un cigarro.

--Cuando usted guste--dijo á Desnoyers con irónica cortesía.

Montaron en el automóvil para atravesar Villeblanche, regresando al castillo. Los incendios
cada vez más numerosos y los cadáveres tendidos en las calles ya no impresionaron al viejo.
¡Había visto tanto! ¿Qué podía alterar ya su sensibilidad?... Deseaba salir del pueblo cuanto
antes, en busca de la paz de los campos. Pero los campos habían desaparecido bajo la invasión:
por todas partes soldados, caballos, cañones. Los grupos en descanso destruían con su contacto
lo que les rodeaba. Los batallones en marcha habían invadido todos los caminos, rumorosos y
automáticos como una máquina, precedidos por los pífanos y los tambores, lanzando de vez en
cuando, para animarse, su grito de alegría: «¡Nach París!»

El castillo también estaba desfigurado por la invasión. Había aumentado mucho el número de
sus guardianes durante la ausencia del dueño. Vió todo un regimiento de infantería acampado
en el parque. Miles de hombres se agitaban bajo les árboles preparando su comida en las cocinas
rodantes. Los arriates de su jardín, las plantas exóticas, las avenidas cuidadosamente enarenadas
y barridas, todo roto y ajado por la avalancha de hombres, bestias y vehículos.

Un jefe ostentando en una manga el brazal distintivo de la Administración militar daba órdenes
como si fuese el propietario. Ni se dignó fijar sus ojos en este civil que marchaba al lado
de un teniente con encogimiento de prisionero. Los establos estaban vacíos. Desnoyers vió sus
últimas vacas que salían conducidas á palos por los pastores con casco. Los reproductores costosos
eran degollados todos en el parque como simples bestias de carnicería. En los gallineros y
palomares no quedaba una sola ave. Las cuadras estaban llenas de caballos enjutos que se daban
un hartazgo ante el pesebre repleto. El pasto almacenado se esparcía pródigamente por las avenidas,
perdiéndose en gran parte antes de ser aprovechado. La caballada de varios escuadrones iba
suelta por los prados, destruyendo bajo su pateo los canales, los bordes de los taludes, el
alisamiento del suelo, todo un trabajo de largos meses. La leña seca ardía en el parque con
un llameo inútil. Por descuido ó por maldad, alguien había aplicado el fuego á sus montones.
Los árboles, con la corteza reseca por los ardores del verano, crujían al ser lamidos por las
llamas.

El edificio estaba ocupado igualmente por una multitud de hombres que obedecían á este jefe.
Sus ventanas abiertas dejaban ver un continuo tránsito por las habitaciones. Desnoyers oyó
golpes que resonaron dentro de su pecho. ¡Ay, su mansión histórica!... El general iba á instalarse
en ella, luego de haber examinado en la orilla del Marne los trabajos de los pontoneros, que
establecían varios pasos para las tropas. Su miedo de propietario le hizo hablar. Temía que
rompiesen las puertas de las habitaciones cerradas; quiso ir en busca de las llaves para entregarlas.
El comisario no le escuchó: seguía ignorando su existencia. El teniente repuso con una amabilidad
cortante:

--No es necesario; no se moleste.

Y se fué para incorporarse á su regimiento. Pero antes de que Desnoyers le perdiese de vista
quiso el oficial darle un consejo. Quieto en su castillo; fuera de él podían tomarle por un
espía, y ya estaba enterado de la prontitud con que solucionaban sus asuntos los soldados del
emperador.

No pudo permanecer en el jardín contemplando de lejos su vivienda. Los alemanes que iban y
venían se burlaban de él. Algunos marchaban á su encuentro en línea recta, como si no le viesen,
y tenía que apartarse para no ser volteado por este avance mecánico y rígido.

Al fin se refugió en el pabellón del conserje. La mujer le veía con asombro, caído en un asiento
de su cocina, desalentado, la mirada en el suelo, súbitamente envejecido al perder las energías
que animaban su robusta ancianidad.

--¡Ah, señor!... ¡Pobre señor!

De todos los atentados de la invasión, el más inaudito para la pobre mujer era contemplar al
dueño refugiado en su vivienda.

--¡Qué va á ser de nosotros!--gemía.

Su marido era llamado con frecuencia por los invasores. Los asistentes de Su Excelencia, instalados
en los sótanos del castillo, lo reclamaban para inquirir el paradero de las cosas que no podían
encontrar. De estos viajes volvía humillado, con los ojos llenos de lágrimas. Tenía en la frente
la huella negra de un golpe; su chaqueta estaba desgarrada. Eran rastros de un débil intento
de oposición durante la ausencia del dueño al iniciar los alemanes el despojo de establos y
salones.

El millonario se sintió ligado por el infortunio á unas gentes consideradas hasta entonces
con indiferencia. Agradecía mucho la fidelidad de este hombre enfermo y humilde. Le conmovió
el interés de la pobre mujer, que miraba el castillo como si fuese propio. La presencia de
la hija trajo á su memoria la imagen de Chichí. Había pasado junto á ella sin fijarse en su
transformación, viéndola lo mismo que cuando acompañaba, con trote de gozquecillo, á la señorita
Desnoyers en sus excursiones por el parque y los alrededores. Ahora era una mujer, con la delgadez
del último crecimiento, apuntando las primeras gracias femeniles en su cuerpo de catorce años.
La madre no la dejaba salir del pabellón, temiendo á la soldadesca, que lo invadía todo con
su corriente desbordada, filtrándose en los lugares abiertos, rompiendo los obstáculos que
estorbaban su paso.

Desnoyers abandonó su desesperado mutismo para confesar que sentía hambre. Le avergonzaba esta
exigencia material, pero las emociones del día, la muerte vista de cerca, el peligro todavía
amenazante, despertaron en él un apetito nervioso. La consideración de que era un miserable
en medio de sus riquezas y no podía disponer de nada en su dominio aumentó todavía más su necesidad.

--¡Pobre señor!--dijo otra vez la mujer.

Y contempló con asombro al millonario devorando un pedazo de pan y un triángulo de queso, lo
único que pudo encontrar en su vivienda. La certeza de que no conseguiría otro alimento por
más que buscase, hizo que don Marcelo siguiese atormentado por su apetito. ¡Haber conquistado
una fortuna enorme, para sufrir hambre al final de su existencia!... La mujer, como si adivinase
sus pensamientos, gemía, elevando los ojos. Desde las primeras horas de la mañana el mundo
había cambiado su curso: todas las cosas parecían al revés. ¡Ay, la guerra!...

En el resto de la tarde y una parte de la noche fué recibiendo el propietario las noticias
que le traía el conserje después de sus visitas al castillo. El general y numerosos oficiales
ocupaban las habitaciones. No quedaba cerrada una sola puerta: todas estaban de par en par,
á culatazos y hachazos. Habían desaparecido muchas cosas; el portero no sabía cómo, pero habían
desaparecido, tal vez rotas, tal vez arrebatadas por los que entraban y salían. El jefe del
brazal iba de habitación en habitación examinándolo todo, dictando en alemán á un soldado que
escribía. Mientras tanto, el general y los suyos estaban en el comedor. Bebían abundantemente
y consultaban mapas extendidos en el suelo. El pobre hombre había tenido que bajar á las cuevas
en busca de los mejores vinos.

Al anochecer se marcó un movimiento de flujo en aquella marea humana que cubría los campos
hasta perderse de vista. Habían quedado establecidos varios puentes sobre el Marne y la invasión
reanudó su avance. Los regimientos se ponían en marcha lanzando su grito de entusiasmo: «¡Nach
Paris!» Los que se quedaban para continuar al día siguiente iban instalándose en las casas
arruinadas ó al aire libre. Desnoyers oyó cánticos. Bajo el fulgor de las primeras estrellas
los soldados se agrupaban como orfeonistas, formando con sus voces un coral solemne y dulce,
de religiosa gravedad. Encima de los árboles flotaba una nube roja que la sombra hacía más
intensa. Era el reflejo del pueblo, que aún llameaba. A lo lejos, otras hogueras de granjas
y caseríos cortaban la noche con sus parpadeos sangrientos.

El viejo acabó por dormirse en la cama de sus conserjes, con el sueño pesado y embrutecedor
del cansancio, sin sobresaltos ni pesadillas. Caía y caía en un agujero lóbrego y sin término.
Al despertar, se imaginó que sólo había dormido unos minutos. El sol coloreaba de naranja las
cortinillas de la ventana. A través de su tejido vió unas ramas de árbol y pájaros que saltaban
piando entre las hojas. Sintió la misma alegría de los frescos amaneceres del verano. ¡Hermosa
mañana! Pero ¿qué habitación era aquella?... Miró con extrañeza el lecho y cuanto le rodeaba.
De pronto la realidad asaltó su cerebro, paralizado dulcemente por los primeros esplendores
del día. Fué surgiendo de esta bruma mental la larga escalera de su memoria, con un último
peldaño negro y rojo: el bloque de emociones que representaba el día anterior. ¡Y él había
dormido tranquilamente rodeado de enemigos, sometido á una fuerza arbitraria que podía destruirle
en uno de sus caprichos!...

Al entrar en la cocina, su conserje le dió noticias. Los alemanes se iban. El regimiento acampado
en el parque había salido al amanecer, y tras de él, otros y otros. En el pueblo quedaba un
batallón, ocupando las pocas casas enteras y las ruinas de las incendiadas. El general había
partido también con su numeroso Estado Mayor. Sólo quedaba en el castillo el jefe de una brigada,
al que llamaban sus asistentes «el conde», y varios oficiales.

Después de estas noticias se atrevió á salir del pabellón. Vió su jardín destrozado, pero hermoso.
Los árboles guardaban impasibles los ultrajes sufridos en sus troncos. Los pájaros aleteaban
con sorpresa y regocijo al verse dueños otra vez del espacio abandonado por la inundación humana.

Pronto se arrepintió Desnoyers de su salida. Cinco camiones estaban formados junto á los fosos,
ante el puente del castillo. Varios grupos de soldados salían llevando á hombros muebles enormes,
como peones que efectúan una mudanza. Un objeto voluminoso envuelto en cortinas de seda, que
suplían á la lona de embalaje, era empujado por cuatro hombres hasta uno de los automóviles.
El propietario adivinó. ¡Su baño: la famosa tina de oro!... Luego, con un brusco cambio de
opinión, no sintió dolor por esta pérdida. Odiaba ahora la ostentosa pieza, atribuyéndole una
influencia fatal. Por su culpa se veía él allí. Pero ¡ay!... ¡los otros muebles amontonados
en los camiones!... En este momento pudo abarcar toda la extensión de su miseria y su impotencia.
Le era imposible defender su propiedad; no podía discutir con aquel jefe que saqueaba el castillo
tranquilamente, ignorando la presencia del dueño. «¡Ladrones! ¡ladrones!» Y volvió á meterse
en el pabellón.

Pasó toda la mañana con el codo en una mesa y la mandíbula apoyada en la mano, lo mismo que
el día anterior, dejando que las horas se desgranasen lentamente, no queriendo oir el sordo
rodar de los vehículos que se llevaban las muestras de su opulencia.

Cerca de mediodía le anunció el conserje que un oficial llegado una hora antes en automóvil
deseaba verle.

Al salir del pabellón encontró á un capitán igual á los otros, con el casco puntiagudo y enfundado,
el uniforme color de mostaza, botas de cuero rojo, sable, revólver, gemelos y la carta geográfica
en un estuche pendiente del cinturón. Parecía joven; ostentaba en una manga el brazal del Estado
Mayor.

--¿Me conoce?... No he querido pasar por aquí sin verle.

Dijo esto en castellano, y Desnoyers experimentó una sorpresa más grande que todas las que
había sentido en sus largas horas de angustia á partir de la mañana anterior.

--¿De veras que no me conoce?--prosiguió el alemán, siempre en español--. Soy Otto... el capitán
Otto von Hartrott.

El viejo descendió, ó más bien rodó por la escalera de su memoria, para detenerse en un peldaño
lejano. Vió la estancia, vió á sus cuñados que tenían el segundo hijo. «Le pondré el nombre
de Bismarck», decía Karl. Luego, remontando muchos escalones, se veía en Berlín durante su
visita á los Hartrott. Hablaban con orgullo de Otto, casi tan sabio como el hermano mayor,
pero que aplicaba su talento á la guerra. Era teniente y continuaba sus estudios para ingresar
en el Estado Mayor. «¿Quién sabe si llegará á ser otro Moltke?», decía el padre. Y la bulliciosa
Chichí lo bautizó con un apodo, aceptado por la familia. Otto fué en adelante Moltkecito para
sus parientes de París.

Desnoyers se admiró de las transformaciones realizadas por los años. Aquel capitán vigoroso
y de aire insolente, que podía fusilarle, era el mismo pequeñín que había visto corretear en
la estancia, el Moltkecito imberbe del que reía su hija...

Mientras tanto, el militar explicaba su presencia allí. Pertenecía á otra división. Eran muchas...
¡muchas! las que avanzaban formando un muro extenso y profundo desde Verdún á París. Su general
le había enviado para mantener el contacto con la división inmediata, pero al verse en las
cercanías del castillo, había querido visitarlo. La familia no es una simple palabra. El se
acordaba de los días que había pasado en Villeblanche, cuando la familia Hartrott fué á vivir
por algún tiempo con sus parientes de Francia. Los oficiales que ocupaban el edificio le habían
retenido para que almorzase en su compañía. Uno de ellos mencionó casualmente al dueño de la
propiedad, dando á entender que andaba cerca, aunque nadie se fijaba en su persona. Una gran
sorpresa para el capitán von Hartrott. Y había hecho averiguaciones hasta dar con él, doliéndose
de verle refugiado en la habitación de sus porteros.

--Debe usted salir de ahí: usted es mi tío--dijo con orgullo--. Vuelva á su casa, donde le
corresponde estar. Mis camaradas tendrán mucho gusto en conocerle; son hombres muy distinguidos.

Se lamentó luego de lo que el viejo hubiese podido sufrir. No sabía con certeza en qué consistían
tales sufrimientos, pero adivinaba que los primeros instantes de la invasión habrían sido crueles
para él.

--¡Qué quiere usted!--repitió varias veces--. Es la guerra.

Al mismo tiempo celebraba que hubiese permanecido en su propiedad. Tenían la orden de castigar
con predilección los bienes de los fugitivos. Alemania deseaba que los habitantes permaneciesen
en sus viviendas, como si no ocurriese nada extraordinario. Desnoyers protestó... ¡Pero si
los invasores fusilaban á los inocentes y quemaban sus casas!... El sobrino se opuso á que
siguiese hablando. Palideció, como si detrás de su epidermis se esparciese una ola de ceniza;
le brillaron los ojos, le temblaron las mejillas, lo mismo que al teniente que se había posesionado
del castillo.

--Se refiere usted al fusilamiento del alcalde y los otros... Me lo acaban de contar los camaradas.
Aún ha sido flojo el castigo; debían haber arrasado el pueblo entero: debían haber matado hasta
á los niños y las mujeres. Hay que acabar con los franco-tiradores.

El viejo le miró con asombro. Su Moltkecito era tan peligroso y feroz como los otros... Pero
el capitán cortó la conversación, repitiendo una vez más la eterna y monstruosa excusa:

--Muy horrible, pero ¡qué quiere usted!... Así es la guerra.

Luego pidió noticias de su madre, alegrándose al saber que estaba en el Sur. Le había inquietado
mucho la idea de que permaneciese en París. ¡Con las revoluciones que habían ocurrido allá
en los últimos tiempos!... Desnoyers quedó dudando, como si hubiese oído mal. ¿Qué revoluciones
eran esas?... Pero el oficial había pasado sin más explicación á hablar de los suyos, creyendo
que Desnoyers sentiría impaciencia por conocer la suerte de la parentela germánica.

Todos estaban en una situación magnífica. Su ilustre padre era presidente de varias sociedades
patrióticas--ya que sus años no le permitían ir á la guerra--y organizaba además futuras empresas
industriales para explotar los países conquistados. Su hermano «el sabio» daba conferencias
acerca de los pueblos que debía anexionarse el Imperio victorioso, tronando contra los malos
patriotas que se mostraban débiles y mezquinos en sus pretensiones. Los tres hermanos restantes
figuraban en el ejército: á uno de ellos lo habían condecorado en Lorena. Las dos hermanas,
algo tristes por la ausencia de sus prometidos, tenientes de húsares, se entretenían en visitar
los hospitales y pedir á Dios que castigase á la traidora Inglaterra.

El capitán von Hartrott llevó lentamente á su tío hacia el castillo. Los soldados grises y
rígidos, que habían ignorado hasta entonces la existencia de don Marcelo, le seguían con interés
viéndole en amistosa conversación con un oficial del Estado Mayor. Adivinó que estos hombres
iban á humanizarse para él, perdiendo su automatismo inexorable y agresivo.

Al entrar en el edificio, algo se contrajo en su pecho con estremecimientos de angustia. Vió
por todas partes dolorosos vacíos que le hicieron recordar los objetos que ocupaban antes el
mismo espacio. Manchas rectangulares de color más fuerte delataban en el empapelado el emplazamiento
de los muebles y cuadros desaparecidos. ¡Con qué prontitud y buen método trabajaba aquel señor
del brazal en la manga!... A la tristeza que le produjo el despojo frío y ordenado vino á unirse
su indignación de hombre económico, viendo cortinas con desgarrones, alfombras manchadas, objetos
rotos de porcelana y cristal, todos los vestigios de una ocupación ruda y sin escrúpulos.

El sobrino, adivinando lo que pensaba, repitió la eterna excusa: «¡Qué hacer!... Es la guerra.»

Pero con Moltkecito no tenía por qué guardar los miramientos del miedo.

--Esto no es guerra--dijo con acento rencoroso--. Es una expedición de bandidos... Tus camaradas
son unos ladrones.

El capitán von Hartrott creció de pronto con violento estirón. Se separó del viejo, mirándole
fijamente, mientras hablaba en voz baja, algo silbante por el temblor de la cólera. ¡Atención,
tío! Afortunadamente, se había expresado en español y no podían entenderle los que estaban
cerca de ellos. Si se permitía insistir en tales apreciaciones, corría el peligro de recibir
una bala como respuesta. Los oficiales del emperador no se dejan insultar. Y todo en su persona
demostraba la facilidad con que podía olvidarse de su parentesco si recibía la orden de proceder
contra don Marcelo.

Calló éste, bajando la cabeza. ¡Qué iba á hacer!... El capitán reanudó sus amabilidades, como
si hubiese olvidado lo que acababa de decir. Quería presentarle á sus camaradas. Su Excelencia
el conde Meinbourg, Mayor General, al enterarse de que era pariente de los Hartrott, le dispensaba
el honor de convidarle á su mesa.

Invitado en su propia vivienda, entró en el comedor, donde estaban muchos hombres vestidos
de color mostaza y con botas altas. Instintivamente apreció con rápida ojeada el estado de
la habitación. Todo en buen orden, nada roto: paredes, cortinajes y muebles seguían intactos.
Pero al mirar al interior de los aparadores monumentales experimentó otra vez una sensación
dolorosa. Por todas partes la obscuridad del roble. Habían desaparecido dos vajillas de plata
y otra de porcelana antigua, sin dejar como rastro la más insignificante de sus piezas. Tuvo
que responder con graves saludos á las presentaciones que iba haciendo su sobrino, y estrechó
la mano que le tendía el conde con aristocrática dejadez. Los enemigos le consideraban con
benevolencia y cierta admiración al saber que era un millonario procedente de la tierra lejana
donde los hombres se enriquecen rápidamente.

Se vió de pronto sentado como un extraño ante su propia mesa, comiendo en los mismos platos
que empleaba su familia, servido por unos hombres de cabeza esquilada al rape que llevaban
sobre el uniforme un mandil á rayas. Lo que comía era suyo, el vino procedía de su bodega,
todo lo que adornaba aquella habitación lo había comprado él, los árboles que extendían su
ramaje más allá de la ventana le pertenecían igualmente... Y sin embargo, creyó hallarse en
este sitio por primera vez, sufriendo el malestar de la extrañeza y la desconfianza. Comió
porque sentía hambre, pero alimentos y vinos le parecían de otro planeta.

Iba examinando con asombro á estos enemigos que ocupaban los mismos lugares de su esposa, de
sus hijos, de los Lacour... Hablaban en alemán entre ellos, pero los que conocían el francés
se valían con frecuencia de este idioma para que les entendiese el invitado. Los que sólo chapurreaban
unas palabras las repetían con acompañamiento de sonrisas amables. Se notaba en todos ellos
un deseo de agradar al dueño del castillo.

--Va usted á almorzar con los bárbaros--dijo el conde al ofrecerle un asiento á su lado--.
¿No tiene usted miedo de que le coman vivo?...

Los alemanes rieron con gran estrépito la gracia de Su Excelencia. Todos hacían esfuerzos por
demostrar con sus palabras y ademanes que era falsa la barbarie que les atribuían los enemigos.

Don Marcelo les miró uno á uno. Las fatigas de la guerra, especialmente la marcha acelerada
de los últimos días, estaban visibles en sus personas. Unos eran altos, delgados, con una esbeltez
angulosa; otros, cuadrados y fornidos, con el cuello corto y la cabeza hundida entre los hombros.
Estos últimos habían perdido sus adiposidades en un mes de campaña, colgándoles la piel arrugada
y flácida en varias partes del rostro. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07720</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>392329</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20276</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> "Farewell, my children
... Goodbye, life ... I do not want to die ... !...»

Not want to die

The two men felt the need to say something, you close the page of
its existence with a statement.

- Viva la Republica! - Shouted the
mayor.

- Vive la France! - Said the priest.

Desnoyers believed that both had shouted the same thing.

Two vertical rose above their heads: the priest's arm in the air drew
a sign the saber squad leader flashed while livid ... Dry thunder,
resounding later followed by several explosions.

Don Marcelo felt sorry for poor humanity to see the grotesque forms it takes in the moment
of death. Some collapsed as half-empty bags, others bounced on the ground as well as balls, some
gymnast jumped with his arms held high, falling back or face down, in an attitude of swimmer.
Leaving the lot saw how human legs contorted by the tremors of agony ... Soldiers moved with the
same gesture of hunters who go to collect their pieces. In the throb of the members scrambled rose
a white mane and a weak hand that was trying to repeat his sign. Several throws and kicks in
the livid lot of blood dripping ... And the last tremor of life were
erased forever.

The officer had lit a cigarette.

- When you like - said to Desnoyers with ironical politeness.

Mounted on the car to cross Villeblanche, returning to the castle. Fires increasingly numerous
and the corpses lying in the streets and the old was not impressed. He had seen so much! What
could alter and their sensitivity? ... I wanted to leave the village as before, in search of
peace of the fields.

But the fields had disappeared in the invasion: soldiers everywhere, horses, guns. Groups
at rest destroyed his contact their surroundings. The battalions had invaded up all the roads,
noisy and automatic like a machine, preceded by the fifes and drums, tossing from time to when
to cheer, his cry of joy: "Nach Paris!"

The castle was also marred by the invasion. Had greatly increased the number of their guardians
during the owner's absence. He saw a regiment of infantry encamped in the park. Thousands of
men under them trees waved their food prepared in kitchens trailers. The beds in his garden,
exotic plants, carefully sanded Avenues and swept, all broken and worn by the flood of men and beasts
and vehicles.

A chief boasting a distinctive sleeve cuff of the military administration issued orders as if he were
the owner. Neither deigned to fix his eyes on the next civil marching a lieutenant with shrinking
of prisoner. The stables were empty. Desnoyers saw her conducted last cows out to the shepherds
sticks with helmet. Expensive players were slaughtered everyone in the park as mere beasts
of slaughter. In poultry and pigeon was not a single bird. The stables were full of emaciated
horses that were given a weariness before the manger full. The grass is sprinkled liberally stored
by the floods, largely lost before being used.

The horses of several squadrons would released through the fields, destroying at your kick channel,
the edges of the slopes, smoothing of the soil, all work of many months. The dry wood burning
in the park a flared useless. Carelessness or mischief, someone had applied the fire to their stacks.
The trees, the bark dry by the heat of summer, rustling when licked by the flames.

The building was also occupied by a crowd of men who were due to this boss. Left their windows open to
see a continuous flow through the rooms. Desnoyers heard shock that reverberated in his chest. Oh,
the historic mansion!

... The general was about to be installed in it, after having examined
the banks of the Marne the work of the pontoon, which established
several steps for the troops.

His owner afraid of him speaking. Feared breaks up the bedroom doors closed, she wanted to go
in search of keys for delivery. The commissioner did not listen: it was ignoring its existence.
The lieutenant said with a kindness shear:

- No need, no bother.

And he went to join his regiment. But before he lost sight Desnoyers
the officer wanted to give him advice.

Stay in the castle, outside of it could take a spy, and was already aware of how quickly solved
their affairs soldiers emperor.

He could not stay in the garden watching from afar his home.

The Germans who came and mocked him coming. Some marched to meet him in a straight line, as
if he saw it, and had to be turned away for not by the mechanical
feed and rigid.

Finally took refuge in the flag of the concierge. The woman watched in amazement, dropped into a
seat your kitchen, discouraged, look at the floor, suddenly aged to lose energy that encouraged
a robust old age.

- Ah, sir ... Poor lord!

Of all the attacks of the invasion, the most unheard of for the poor woman was contemplating
the refugee in his own home.

- What will become of us! - Moaned.

Her husband was often called by the invaders. Attendees of His Excellency, installed in the
basement of the castle, claiming to inquire the whereabouts of the things they could not find.
Of these trips became humiliated, his eyes filled with tears.

His forehead the black mark of a blow, his jacket was torn. Were traces of a feeble attempt opposition
during the absence of the owner to start stripping the Germans stables classrooms.

Millionaire felt bound by misfortune to a people hitherto perceived
with indifference.

Much appreciated the loyalty of this sick man and humble.

He moved the interest of the poor woman, who looked as if the castle itself. The presence of
The daughter brought to his memory the image of Chichi. Had passed it without regard to its
transformation, seeing the same thing when accompanied with little dog trot, Mademoiselle Desnoyers
on excursions through the park and surrounding area. Now she was a woman, thinness the last boom,
noting the first through feminine in his body for fourteen years. The mother would not let
go of the flag, fearing the soldiers, who invaded everything with
its current overflowing, seeping into the open places, breaking the
barriers hindered in its path.

Desnoyers silence left her desperate to confess that he was hungry. He was ashamed of this material
requirement, but the emotions of the day, death, close-up, the woods yet threatening, awakened
in him a nervous appetite. The fact that it was a miserable in the midst of their wealth and
could not have anything in his domain further increased their need.

- Poor sir - said the woman again.

And watched with amazement the millionaire eating a piece of bread and a triangle of cheese,
All he could find in your home. The certainty would not get other food for more searching, made
Don Marcelo continue tormented by his appetite. Having conquered an enormous fortune, to go hungry
at the end of his life! ... The woman, as though divining their thoughts, moaning, raising
her eyes. From early morning the world had changed its course, everything seemed upside down.
Oh, war! ...

In the rest of the afternoon and part of the night was getting the news owner the concierge
brought him after his visits to the castle.

The general and numerous officers occupied rooms. There was only one door closed, they were
all wide, with rifle butts and axes. Gone were many things, the doorman did not know how, but
had disappeared, perhaps broken, perhaps stolen by those who came and went. The head of Cuff
went from room to room examining everything, dictating in German to a soldier writing. Meanwhile,
the general and his men were in the dining room. Drink plenty and consulted maps spread out on
the floor. The poor man had to descend into the caves in search of the best wines.

At nightfall, it was a movement of this human tide flow fields covering out of sight. Had been
established several bridges over the Marne and the invasion resumed their advance. The regiments
were put up by throwing her scream with excitement: "Nach Paris! "Those who stayed to continue the
next day were settled in houses ruined or outdoors.

Desnoyers heard singing. Under the glare of the first stars soldiers were grouped as choruses, their
voices form a choral solemn and sweet of religious gravity. Floating above the trees a red
cloud in the shade for more intense. It was the reflection of the people, still aflame. In the
distance, other farm fires and villages cut off the night with their blinking bloody.

The old man ended up falling asleep in the bed of their caretakers, with heavy, brutalizing sleep Fatigue,
smooth or nightmares. Fell and fell into a dark hole and never ending. Upon awakening, he imagined
that he had slept only a few minutes. The orange sun colored the
window blinds.

Through its fabric saw some tree branches and birds that flew twittering among the leaves. He felt
the same joy of the cool summer mornings. Hermosa tomorrow! But what room was that? ... He looked
strange bed and everything around him. Reality suddenly assaulted his brain, paralyzed by the
first splendor sweetly the day. Was emerging from the mental haze the long staircase of his
memory, with a final black and red step: emotions block representing the previous day. And
he had sleep peacefully surrounded by enemies, subjected to an arbitrary power that could destroy
in one of his whims! ...

Upon entering the kitchen, concierge gave news. The Germans were. The regiment encamped in the park
had left at dawn, and after him, others and others. In the village was a battalion occupying
the entire few houses and the ruins of the fire.

The general had also match with his numerous staff. Only the castle was the head of a brigade
they called his aides 'Count', and several officers.

After this news dared to leave the pavilion. He saw his garden destroyed, but beautiful. The
trees bore unmoved the outrages suffered in their trunks.

The birds fluttered with surprise and joy at being masters of space left over by the human flood.

Desnoyers soon regretted his departure. Five trucks were lined up beside the moat to the castle bridge.
Several groups of soldiers carrying out furniture to shoulder huge
as laborers who made a move.

A large object wrapped in silk curtains that Canvas was supplying
the packaging, was pushed by four men to one of the cars.

The owner guessed. Your bathroom: the famous gold tub! ... Then with an abrupt change opinion
felt no sorrow for this loss. Now hated the ostentatious piece, attributing
a fatal influence.

Because of him looked him there. But alas ... Other furniture piled in the truck! ... At this point
could cover the entire extent of their poverty and powerlessness.

He was unable to defend his property, he could not argue with that boss who plundered the castle
quietly, ignoring the presence of the owner. "Thieves! Thieves! "And again he get in the pavilion.

He
spent all morning with his elbow on a table and jaw resting on his hand, like the day before,
leaving you pluck the hours slowly, not wanting to hear the muffled rolling of the vehicles
had samples of his wealth.

Around noon the concierge told him that an officer arrived an hour before drive wanted to see
him.

When leaving the hall he found a captain like the others, with pointed helmet and sheathed, the
uniform color of mustard, red leather boots, sword, pistol, binoculars
and geographical map in a case pending belt.

He looked young, wore a sleeve cuff of the State Mayor.

- Do you know me? ... I did not want to go through here without him.

He said this in Castilian, and Desnoyers experienced a big surprise that all that had in their
long hours of anguish from the previous morning.

- You really do not know me? - German continued, always in Spanish -. I'm Otto ... Captain Otto
von Hartrott.

The old man fell, or rather rolled down the stairs of his memory, to stop at a step distant.
He saw the room, saw his brothers who had the second child. "We put
the name Bismarck, "said Karl.

Then, going back many steps, looked in Berlin during visit to the Hartrott. Otto spoke with pride,
almost as wise as the older brother but he applied his talent to the war. Was a lieutenant and continued
his studies to enter on the staff.

"Who knows if there will be another Moltke?" Said the father.

And the heavy traffic Chichi was baptized with a nickname, accepted by the family. Otto was henceforth
to Moltkecito relatives in Paris.

Desnoyers was surprised at the changes made over the years. Strong that captain and insolent
air, which could shoot him, was the same little boy he had seen running around stay, the beardless
Moltkecito of her daughter laughing ...

Meanwhile, the officer explained his presence there. Belonged to another division. There were many ...
Many! the advancing wall forming a wide and deep from Verdun to Paris. His general had sent him
to maintain contact with the division immediately, but when viewed
in the near the castle, had wanted to visit.

The family is not just a word. He remembered the days he had spent in Villeblanche, when the
family went to live Hartrott for some time with relatives in France.

The officers who had occupied the building retained for lunch at
your company.

One of them casually mentioned to the owner property, implying that he was nearby, but nobody noticed
him. A large Surprise for Captain von Hartrott. And he had made inquiries to find him, grieving
to see him refuge in the room of their goalkeepers.

- You should get out of it: you are my uncle - he said proudly -.

Return to his home where he belongs. My comrades will be pleased to know, are very distinguished
men.

He lamented that after the old man would have suffered. Was not sure what they were such suffering,
but guessed that the first moments of the invasion would have been cruel for him.

- What do you want! - Repeated several times -. It's war.

At the same time that had been held on their property. They had the order to punish with a
preference the assets of the fugitives. Germany wanted the inhabitants remained in their homes,
as if nothing extraordinary occurred. Desnoyers protested ... But if the invaders shot the innocent
and burn their houses! ... The nephew was opposed to that continue
speaking.

He turned pale, as if behind your epidermis spread a wave of ash; his eyes shone, his cheeks
quivered, as well as the lieutenant who had taken possession the castle.

- Are you referring to the shooting of the mayor and others ... I just had to tell the comrades.
Even the punishment has been sluggish, should have destroyed the whole village: they should have
killed as little children and women. We must end the sharp-shooters.

The old man looked at him in amazement.

Your Moltkecito was so dangerous and ferocious as the others ...
But Captain cut the conversation, repeating once again the eternal
and monstrous excuse

- Very horrible, but what you want!

... That's war.

After news of his mother asked, glad to know he was in the South. Had disturbed much the idea
that remained in Paris. With the revolutions that occurred beyond in recent times! ... Desnoyers
hesitated as if he had heard wrong. What revolutions were these? ... But the officer had passed
without further explanation to speak of their own, believing Desnoyers feel impatient to know
the fate of the kindred Germanic.

Everyone was in a great situation.

His illustrious father was president of several companies patriotic - as their years are not
allowed to go to war - and also organized future endeavors industry to exploit the conquered countries.
His brother 'the wise' lecturing about the people that had annex the victorious empire, thundering
against evil patriots who showed weak and narrow in its claims.

The three remaining brothers included in the army to one of them had decorated in Lorraine.
The two sisters, something sad about the absence of their promised, lieutenant of hussars,
were entertained to visit hospitals and ask God to punish the traitor England.

Captain von Hartrott her uncle drove slowly towards the castle. Gray soldiers rigid, which had
hitherto ignored the existence of Don Marcelo, followed him with interest seeing him in friendly
conversation with a staff officer. Guessed that these men went to humanize to him losing his
relentless and aggressive automation.

Upon entering the building, something in his chest contracted with
shudders of anxiety.

Saw empty painful everywhere they did remember the objects they held before the same space.
Rectangular stains betrayed deeper color in the wallpaper site furniture and paintings disappeared.
Which promptly and that man worked good method armband on the sleeve! ... A sadness that he
was cold and ordered the theft came to join outrage of economic man, seeing shades with tears,
stained carpets, objects broken porcelain and glass, all traces of a rude and ruthless occupation.

The
nephew, guessing what he thought, he repeated the eternal excuse: "What to do! ... It's war.
"

But Moltkecito store did not have the regard of fear.

- This is not war - said in a spiteful tone -. It is an expedition of bandits ... Your comrades
are thieves.

Captain von Hartrott soon grew violent stretch.

Separated from the old, looking intently as he spoke softly, whistling something by shaking with
anger. Attention Uncle! Fortunately, he had expressed in Spanish
and could not understand those who were near them.

If allowed to insist on such assessments, was in danger of receiving a bullet in response.
The officers of the emperor not leave insulting. And all in his person demonstrated the ease with
which he could forget about their relationship if he received the order to proceed against Don Marcelo.

He
paused, looking down. What was going to do! ... The captain resumed his kindness, as if he had forgotten
what he had said. Wanted to introduce his comrades. His Excellency
Count Meinbourg, Major General, upon learning that a relative of Hartrott,
relieved it the honor of inviting me to his table.

Guest in his own
house, entered the room, where were many men dressed and mustard-colored
boots. Instinctively appreciated with a quick look at the state the
room. All in good order, nothing broken, walls, curtains and furniture
were still intact. But looking inside the windows monumental again
experienced a feeling painful. Everywhere the dark oak. Had disappeared
two silverware and other ancient porcelain without leaving the slightest
trace as its parts. Had Greetings to respond to serious presentations
was by his nephew, and shook proffered hand with aristocratic Count
neglect. The enemies thought he was with benevolence and a certain
admiration to know he was a millionaire from the distant land where
men get rich quickly.

Suddenly found himself sitting like a stranger
to his own table, eating the same dishes he used his family, served
by men shorn head carrying a crew on even a striped apron. What we
ate was his, the wine came from her store all that adorned the room
had bought him, the trees spread their branches beyond the window
belonged to him also ... And yet, believed to be in this site for
the first time, suffering the discomfort of strangeness and suspicion.
Ate because he was hungry, but food and wine seemed from another planet.

He
was looking with astonishment to these enemies who occupied the same
places of his wife, their children, the Lacour ... Speak German among
themselves, but those who knew the French frequently made use of this
language so that they understood the guest. Those who only speak broken
some words are repeated to the accompaniment of friendly smiles. You
could tell all a desire to please the owner of the castle.

- Are
you going to lunch with the barbarians - said the count to provide
a seat at his side -. Are not you afraid of being eaten alive? ...

The
Germans laughed noisily the grace of His Excellency. All efforts were
demonstrate by their words and gestures that it was false barbarism
attributed to them by the enemies.

Don Marcelo looked at them one
by one. The hardships of war, especially the accelerated speed in
recent days, were visible on their persons. Some were tall, thin,
with a slender angular, others square and chunky, with short neck
and his head sunk between his shoulders. The latter had lost their
adiposity in a month of campaigning, wrinkled skin hanging and flabby
in various parts of the face</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>