<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07766</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>667416</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18738</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Y tenía que hacer un esfuerzo, recordar la dignidad de sus años, para no pedir á Argensola
que le presentase á las fugitivas, cuya presencia adivinaba en las habitaciones interiores.
Habían sido tal vez amigas de su hijo, representaban una parte de su pasado, y esto le bastaba
para suponer en ellas grandes cualidades que las hacían interesantes.

Estas sorpresas, con sus correspondientes inquietudes, acabaron por conseguir que el pintor
se lamentase un poco de su nueva amistad. Le molestaba además la invitación á comer que continuamente
formulaba el viejo. Encontraba muy buena, pero demasiado aburrida, la mesa de los Desnoyers.
El padre y la madre sólo hablaban del ausente. Chichí apenas prestaba atención al amigo de
su hermano. Tenía el pensamiento fijo en la guerra; le preocupaba el funcionamiento del correo,
formulando protestas contra el gobierno cuando transcurrían varios días sin recibir carta del
subteniente Lacour.

Argensola se excusó con diversos pretextos de seguir comiendo en la avenida Víctor Hugo. Le
placía más ir á los restoranes baratos con su séquito femenino. El viejo aceptaba las negativas
con un gesto de enamorado que se resigna.

--¿Tampoco hoy?...

Y para compensarse de tales ausencias, iba al día siguiente al estudio con gran anticipación.

Representaba para él un placer exquisito dejar que se deslizase el tiempo sentado en un diván
que aún parecía guardar la huella del cuerpo de Julio, viendo aquellos lienzos cubiertos de
colores por su pincel, acariciado por el calor de una estufa que roncaba dulcemente en un silencio
profundo, conventual. Era un refugio agradable, lleno de recuerdos, en medio del París monótono
y entristecido de la guerra, en el que no encontraba amigos, pues todos necesitaban pensar
en las propias preocupaciones.

Los placeres de su pasado habían perdido todo encanto. El Hotel Drouot ya no le tentaba. Se
estaban subastando en aquellos momentos los bienes de los alemanes residentes en Francia, embargados
por el gobierno. Era como una respuesta al viaje forzoso que habían hecho los muebles del castillo
de Villeblanche tomando el camino de Berlín. En vano le hablaban los corredores del escaso
público que asistía á las subastas. No sentía la atracción de estas ocasiones extraordinarias.
¿Para qué hacer más compras?... ¿De qué servía tanto objeto inútil? Al pensar en la existencia
dura que llevaban millones de hombres á campo raso, le asaltaban deseos de una vida ascética.
Había empezado á odiar los esplendores ostentosos de su casa de la avenida Víctor Hugo. Recordaba
sin pena la destrucción del castillo. Sentía, una pereza irresistible cuando sus aficiones
pretendían empujarle, como en otros tiempos, á las compras incesantes. No; mejor estaba allí...
Y allí, era siempre el estudio de Julio.

Argensola trabajaba en presencia de don Marcelo. Sabía que el viejo abominaba de las gentes
inactivas, y había emprendido varias obras, sintiendo el contagio de esta voluntad inclinada
á la acción. Desnoyers seguía con interés los trazos del pincel y aceptaba todas las explicaciones
del retratista de almas. El era partidario de los antiguos; en sus compras, sólo había adquirido
obras de pintores muertos; pero le bastaba saber que Julio pensaba como su amigo, para admitir
humildemente todas las teorías de éste.

La laboriosidad del artista era otra. A los pocos minutos prefería hablar con el viejo, sentándose
en el mismo diván.

El primer motivo de conversación era el ausente. Repetían fragmentos de las cartas que llevaban
recibidas; hablaban del pasado con discretas alusiones. El pintor describía la vida de Julio
antes de la guerra como una existencia dedicada por completo á las preocupaciones del arte.
El padre no ignoraba la inexactitud de tales palabras, pero agradecía la mentira como una gran
muestra de amistad. Argensola era un compañero bueno y discreto; jamás, en sus mayores desenfados
verbales, había hecho alusión á Madama Laurier.

En aquellos días preocupaba al viejo el recuerdo de ésta. La había encontrado en la calle dando
el brazo á su esposo, que ya estaba restablecido de sus heridas. El ilustre Lacour contaba
satisfecho la reconciliación del matrimonio. El ingeniero sólo había perdido un ojo. Ahora
estaba al frente de su fábrica, requisada por el gobierno para la fabricación de obuses. Era
capitán y ostentaba dos condecoraciones. No sabía ciertamente el senador cómo se había realizado
la inesperada reconciliación. Les había visto llegar un día á su casa juntos, mirándose con
ternura, olvidados completamente del pasado.

--¿Quién se acuerda de las cosas de antes de la guerra?--había dicho el personaje--. Ellos
y sus amigos han olvidado completamente lo del divorcio. Vivimos todos una nueva existencia...
Yo creo que los dos son ahora más felices que antes.

Esta felicidad la había presentido Desnoyers al verles. Y el hombre de rígida moral, que anatematizaba
el año anterior la conducta de su hijo con Laurier, teniéndola por la más nociva de las calaveradas,
sintió cierto despecho al contemplar á Margarita pegada á su marido, hablándole con amoroso
interés. Le pareció una ingratitud esta felicidad matrimonial. ¡Una mujer que había influido
tanto en la vida de Julio!... ¿Así pueden olvidarse los amores?...

Los dos habían pasado como si no le conociesen. Tal vez el capitán Laurier no veía con claridad;
pero ella le había mirado con sus ojos cándidos, volviendo la vista precipitadamente para evitar
su saludo... El viejo se entristeció ante tal indiferencia, no por él, sino por el otro. ¡Pobre
Julio!... El inflexible señor, en plena inmoralidad mental, lamentaba este olvido como algo
monstruoso.

La guerra era otro objeto de conversación durante las tardes pasadas en el estudio. Argensola
ya no llevaba los bolsillos repletos de impresos, como al principio de las hostilidades. Una
calma resignada y serena había sucedido á la excitación del primer momento, cuando las gentes
esperaban intervenciones extraordinarias y maravillosas. Todos los periódicos decían lo mismo.
Le bastaba con leer el comunicado oficial, y este documento sabía esperarlo sin impaciencia,
presintiendo que, poco más ó menos, diría lo mismo que el anterior.

La fiebre de los primeros meses, con sus ilusiones y optimismos, le parecía ahora algo quimérico.
Los que no estaban en la guerra habían vuelto poco á poco á las ocupaciones habituales. La
existencia recobraba su ritmo ordinario. «Hay que vivir», decían las gentes. Y la necesidad
de continuar la vida llenaba el pensamiento con sus exigencias inmediatas. Los que tenían individuos
armados en el ejército se acordaban de ellos, pero sus ocupaciones amortiguaban la violencia
del recuerdo, acabando por aceptar la ausencia, como algo que de extraordinario pasaba á ser
normal. Al principio, la guerra cortaba el sueño, hacía intragable la comida, amargaba el placer,
dándole una palidez fúnebre. Todos hablaban de lo mismo. Ahora, se abrían lentamente los teatros,
circulaba el dinero, reían las gentes, hablaban de la gran calamidad, pero sólo á determinadas
horas, como algo que iba á ser largo, muy largo, y exigía con su fatalismo inevitable una gran
resignación.

--La humanidad se acostumbra fácilmente á la desgracia--decía Argensola--, siempre que la desgracia
sea larga... Esa es nuestra fuerza; por eso vivimos.

Don Marcelo no aceptaba su resignación. La guerra iba á ser más corta de lo que se imaginaban
todos. Su entusiasmo le fijaba un término inmediato: dentro de tres meses, en la primavera
próxima. Y si la paz no era en la primavera, sería en el verano.

Un nuevo interlocutor tomó parte en sus conversaciones. Desnoyers conoció al vecino ruso, del
que le hablaba Argensola. También este personaje raro había tratado á su hijo, y esto bastó
para que Tchernoff le inspirase gran interés.

En tiempo normal, lo habría mantenido á distancia. El millonario era partidario del orden.
Abominaba de los revolucionarios, con el miedo instintivo de todos los ricos que han creado
su fortuna y recuerdan la modestia de su origen. El socialismo de Tchernoff y su nacionalidad
habrían provocado forzosamente en su pensamiento una serie de imágenes horripilantes: bombas,
puñaladas, justas expiaciones en la horca, envíos á Siberia. No, no era un amigo recomendable...
Pero ahora don Marcelo experimentaba un profundo trastorno en la apreciación de las ideas ajenas.
¡Había visto tanto!... Los procedimientos terroríficos de la invasión, la falta de escrúpulos
de los jefes alemanes, la tranquilidad con que los submarinos echaban á pique buques pacíficos
cargados de viajeros indefensos, las hazañas de los aviadores, que á dos mil metros de altura
arrojaban bombas sobre las ciudades abiertas, destrozando mujeres y niños, le hacían recordar
como sucesos sin importancia los atentados del terrorismo revolucionario que años antes provocaban
su indignación.

--¡Y pensar--decía--que nos enfurecíamos, como si el mundo fuese á deshacerse, porque alguien
arrojaba una bomba contra un personaje!

Estos exaltados ofrecían para él una cualidad que atenuaba sus crímenes. Morían víctimas de
sus propios actos ó se entregaban sabiendo cuál iba á ser su castigo. Se sacrificaban sin buscar
la salida: rara vez se habían salvado valiéndose de las precauciones de la impunidad. ¡Mientras
que los terroristas de la guerra!...

Con la violencia de su carácter imperioso, el viejo efectuaba una reversión absoluta de valores.

--Los verdaderos anarquistas están ahora en lo alto--decía con risa irónica--. Todos los que
nos asustaban antes eran unos infelices... En un segundo matan los de nuestra época más inocentes
que los otros en treinta años.

La dulzura de Tchernoff, sus ideas originales, sus incoherencias de pensador acostumbrado á
saltar de la reflexión á la palabra sin preparación alguna, acabaron por seducir á don Marcelo.
Todas sus dudas las consultaba con él. Su admiración le hacía pasar por alto la procedencia
de ciertas botellas con que Argensola obsequiaba algunas veces á su vecino. Aceptó con gusto
que Tchernoff consumiese estos recuerdos de la época en que vivía él luchando con su hijo.

Después de saborear el vino de la avenida Víctor Hugo, sentía el ruso una locuacidad visionaria
semejante á la de la noche en que evocó la fantástica cabalgada de los cuatro jinetes apocalípticos.

Lo que más admiraba Desnoyers era su facilidad para exponer las cosas, fijándolas por medio
de imágenes. La batalla del Marne con los combates subsiguientes y la carrera de ambos ejércitos
hacia la orilla del mar eran para él hechos de fácil explicación... ¡Si los franceses no hubiesen
estado fatigados después de su triunfo en el Marne!...

--...Pero las fuerzas humanas--continuaba Tchernoff--tienen un límite, y el francés, con todo
su entusiasmo, es un hombre como los demás. Primeramente la marcha rapidísima del Este al Norte
para hacer frente á la invasión por Bélgica; luego los combates; á continuación una retirada
veloz para no verse envueltos; finalmente una batalla de siete días; y todo esto en un período
de tres semanas nada más... En el momento del triunfo faltaron piernas á los vencedores para
ir adelante y faltó caballería para perseguir á los fugitivos. Las bestias estaban más extenuadas
aún que los hombres. Al verse acosados con poca tenacidad, los que se retiraban, cayéndose
de fatiga, se tendieron y excavaron la tierra, creándose un refugio. Los franceses también
se acostaron, arañando el suelo para no perder lo recuperado... Y empezó de este modo la guerra
de trincheras.

Luego, cada línea, con el intento de envolver á la línea enemiga, había ido prolongándose hacia
el Noroeste, y de los estiramientos sucesivos resultó la carrera hacia el mar de unos y otros,
formando el frente de combate más grande que se conocía en la Historia.

Cuando don Marcelo, en su optimismo entusiasta, anunciaba la terminación de la guerra para
la primavera siguiente... para el verano, siempre con cuatro meses de plazo á lo más, el ruso
movía la cabeza.

--Esto será largo... muy largo. Es una guerra nueva, la verdadera guerra moderna. Los alemanes
iniciaron las hostilidades á estilo antiguo, como si no hubiesen observado nada después de
1870: una guerra de movimientos envolventes, de batallas á campo raso, lo mismo que podía discurrirla
Moltke imitando á Napoleón. Deseaban terminar pronto y estaban seguros del triunfo. ¿Para qué
hacer uso de procedimientos nuevos?... Pero lo del Marne torció sus planes: de agresores tuvieron
que pasar á la defensiva, y entonces emplearon todo lo que su Estado Mayor había aprendido
en las campañas de japoneses y rusos, iniciándose la guerra de trincheras, la lucha subterránea,
que es lógica, por el alcance y la cantidad de disparos del armamento moderno. La conquista
de un kilómetro de terreno representa ahora más que hace un siglo el asalto de una fortaleza
de piedra... Ni unos ni otros van á avanzar en mucho tiempo. Tal vez no avancen nunca definitivamente.
Esto va á ser largo y aburrido, como las peleas entre atletas de fuerzas equilibradas.

--Pero alguna vez tendrá fin--dijo Desnoyers.

--Indudablemente; pero ¿quién sabe cuándo?... ¿Y cómo quedarán unos y otros cuando todo termine?...

El creía en un final rápido, cuando menos lo esperase la gente, por la fatiga de uno de los
dos luchadores, cuidadosamente disimulada hasta el último momento.

--Alemania será la derrotada--añadió con firme convicción--. No sé cuándo ni cómo, pero caerá
lógicamente. Su golpe maestro le falló en Septiembre, al no entrar en París deshaciendo al
ejército enemigo. Todos los triunfos de su baraja los echó entonces sobre la mesa. No ganó,
y continúa prolongando el juego porque tiene muchas cartas, y lo prolongará todavía largo tiempo...
Pero lo que no pudo hacer en el primer momento no lo hará nunca.

Para Tchernoff, la derrota final no significaba la destrucción de Alemania ni el aniquilamiento
del pueblo alemán.

--A mí me indignan--continuó--los patriotismos excesivos. Oyendo á ciertas gentes que formulan
planes para la supresión definitiva de Alemania, me parece estar escuchando á los pangermanistas
de Berlín cuando repartían los continentes.

Luego concretó su opinión.

--Hay que derrotar al Imperio, para tranquilidad del mundo: suprimir la gran máquina de guerra
que perturba la paz de las naciones... Desde 1870 todos vivimos pésimamente. Durante cuarenta
y cuatro años se ha conjurado el peligro, pero en todo este tiempo ¡qué de angustias!...

Lo que más irritaba á Tchernoff era la enseñanza inmoral nacida de esta situación y que había
acabado por apoderarse del mundo: la glorificación de la fuerza, la santificación del éxito,
el triunfo del materialismo, el respeto al hecho consumado, la mofa de los más nobles sentimientos,
como si fuesen simples frases sonoras y ridículas, el trastorno de los valores morales, una
filosofía de bandidos que pretendía ser la última palabra del progreso y no era mas que la
vuelta al despotismo, la violencia, la barbarie de las épocas más primitivas de la Historia.

Deseaba la supresión de los representantes de esta tendencia, pero no por esto pedía el exterminio
del pueblo alemán.

--Ese pueblo tiene grandes méritos confundidos con malas condiciones, que son herencia de un
pasado de barbarie demasiado próximo. Posee el instinto de la organización y del trabajo, y
puede prestar buenos servicios á la humanidad... Pero antes es necesario administrarle una
ducha: la ducha del fracaso. Los alemanes están locos de orgullo, y su locura resulta peligrosa
para el mundo. Cuando hayan desaparecido los que les envenenaron con ilusiones de hegemonía
mundial, cuando la desgracia haya refrescado su imaginación y se conformen con ser un grupo
humano ni superior ni inferior á los otros, formarán un pueblo tolerante, útil... y quién sabe
si hasta simpático.

No había en la hora presente, para Tchernoff, pueblo más peligroso. Su organización política
lo convertía en una horda guerrera educada á puntapiés y sometida á continuas humillaciones
para anular la voluntad, que se resiste siempre á la disciplina.

--Es una nación donde todos reciben golpes y desean darlos al que está más abajo. El puntapié
que suelta el emperador se transmite de dorso en dorso hasta las últimas capas sociales. Los
golpes empiezan en la escuela y se continúan en el cuartel, formando parte de la educación.
El aprendizaje de los príncipes herederos de Prusia consistió siempre en recibir bofetadas
y palos de su progenitor el rey. El kaiser pega á sus retoños, el oficial á sus soldados, el
padre á sus hijos y á la mujer, el maestro á los alumnos; y cuando el superior no puede dar
golpes, impone á los que tiene debajo el tormento del ultraje moral.

Por eso cuando abandonaban su vida ordinaria, tomando las armas para caer sobre otro grupo
humano, eran de una ferocidad implacable.

--Cada uno de ellos--continuó el ruso--lleva debajo de la espalda un depósito de patadas recibidas,
y desea consolarse dándolas á su vez á los infelices que coloca la guerra bajo su dominación.
Este pueblo de «señores», como él mismo se llama, aspira á serlo... pero fuera de su casa.
Dentro de ella, es el que menos conoce la dignidad humana. Por eso siente con tanta vehemencia
el deseo de esparcirse por el mundo, pasando de lacayo á patrón.

Repentinamente, don Marcelo dejó de ir con frecuencia al estudio. Buscaba ahora á su amigo
el senador. Una promesa de éste había trastornado su tranquila resignación.

El personaje estaba triste desde que el heredero de las glorias de su familia se había ido
á la guerra, rompiendo la red protectora de recomendaciones en que le había envuelto.

Una noche, comiendo en casa de Desnoyers, apuntó una idea que hizo estremecer á éste. «¿No
le gustaría ver á su hijo?...» El senador estaba gestionando una autorización del Cuartel General
para ir al frente. Necesitaba ver á René. Pertenecía al mismo cuerpo de ejército que Julio;
tal vez estaban en lugares algo lejanos, pero un automóvil puede dar muchos rodeos antes de
llegar al término de su viaje.

No necesitó decir más. Desnoyers sintió de pronto un deseo vehemente de ver á su hijo. Llevaba
muchos meses teniendo que contentarse con la lectura de sus cartas y la contemplación de una
fotografía hecha por uno de sus camaradas...

Desde entonces asedió á Lacour como si fuese uno de sus electores deseoso de un empleo. Le
visitaba por las mañanas en su casa, lo invitaba á comer todas las noches, iba á buscarle por
las tardes en los salones del Luxemburgo. Antes de la primera palabra de saludo, sus ojos formulaban
siempre la misma interrogación... «¿Cuándo conseguiría el permiso?»

El grande hombre lamentaba la indiferencia de los militares con el elemento civil. Siempre
habían sido enemigos del parlamentarismo.

--Además, Joffre se muestra intratable. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07720</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>172240</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16694</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

And I had to make an effort to remember the dignity of their years, not to seek to Argensola
to submit to the fugitive, whose presence glimpsed in the inner rooms. They were perhaps friends
of his son, were a part of his past, and this was enough to believe in these great qualities that
made them interesting.

These surprises, with their concerns, they finally get the painter lamented a bit of their new friendship.
Also bothered him the invitation to eat continuously formulated the old. Was very good, but
too boring, the table of Desnoyers. The father and mother spoke only absentee. Chichi just
paying attention to friends his brother. He fixed thought the war was concerned about the operation
of the mail, making anti-government protests when several days passed without receiving letter
Lieutenant Lacour.

Argensola excused himself on various pretexts to continue eating in
the avenue Victor Hugo.

Le happy to go to the restaurants more flights with his female entourage.

The old accepted the negative with a gesture of love who is resigned.

- Have not today? ...

To compensate for such absences, leaving the following day to study with great anticipation.

Represented for him an exquisite pleasure to let slip the time sitting
on a couch still seemed to hold the imprint of the body of Julio,
seeing those canvases covered colors for your brush, caressed by the
warmth of a stove that was snoring softly in the silence deeper, monastery.

It was a pleasant retreat, full of memories, amid the drab Paris and saddened by the war, which
was not friends, we all need to think in their own concerns.

The pleasures of the past had lost all charm. The Hotel Drouot no longer tempted. It were auctioned
at the time the assets of the Germans in France, seized by the government. It was as a response
to the trip had forced castle furniture Villeblanche taking the path of Berlin. In vain the riders
spoke little public who attended the auction. Did not feel the attraction of these extraordinary
times. Why do more shopping? ... What was so useless object? When thinking about the existence hard
worn million men in the open, I attacked an ascetic life wishes. Had begun to hate the ostentatious
splendor of his house in the avenue Victor Hugo. Remembered not worth the destruction of the castle.
I felt an irresistible when their hobbies laziness tried to push,
as in other times, purchases constant.

No, maybe he was there ... And there was always the study of July.

Argensola worked in the presence of Don Marcelo. I knew that old people abhorred inactive, and had
undertaken several works, feeling the contagion of this angle will to the action. Desnoyers noted
with interest the brush strokes and accepted all the explanations the portrait of souls. He was
in favor of the ancients in their shop, had only acquired works by
dead artists, but it was enough to know that Jules thought as his
friend, to support humbly all theories of it.

The artist's hard work was another. A few minutes later he preferred to speak with the old, sitting
on the same couch.

The first topic of conversation was absent. Repeated fragments of the letters had received, talked
about the past with subtle allusions. The painter depicted the life of Julius before the war as a
life dedicated entirely to the concerns of art.

The father was aware of the inaccuracy of such words, but appreciated as a big lie token of friendship.
Argensola was a good companion, discreet, never to abandon its greatest verbal, had alluded
to Madame Laurier.

In those days, worried about the old memories of it. Had met in the street giving his arm to her
husband, who was now recovered from his wounds. The illustrious Lacour had happy marriage reconciliation.
The engineer had only lost one eye.

Now was in charge of his factory requisitioned by the government for making bombs. Was captain
and wore two medals. Senator certainly did not know how it was done an unexpected reconciliation.
I had seen them arrive a day to his home together, looking with tenderness,
completely forgotten the past.

- Who remembers things before the
war? - Had said the character -.

They and his friends have forgotten all about the divorce. We all live a new life ... I think the two
are now happier than before.

This happiness I had sensed Desnoyers to see them. And the man of strong moral values, which
anathematized the year before your child's behavior with Laurier,
holding for the most harmful of the skulls, felt some vexation at
the sight Marguerite glued to her husband, speaking with love interest.

It seemed an act of ingratitude is happiness in marriage. A woman who had influenced both in the
life of Julio! ... So you can forget the love? ...

The two had gone as if he knew. Perhaps the captain was not clear Laurier; but she had looked
at her candid eyes, looking back abruptly to avoid your greeting
... The old man grieved at such indifference, not by him but on the
other.

Poor Julio! ... The inflexible sir, full mental immorality, lamented this oversight as something
monstrous.

The war was another subject of conversation during the evenings spent in the study. Argensola no
longer had his pockets full of paper, as at the beginning of hostilities. A quiet and serene
resignation had happened to the excitement the first time, when people
extraordinary and wonderful interventions expected.

All the newspapers said the same. He had only to read the official statement, and this document wise
to wait without impatience, feeling that, more or less say the same as above.

The fever of the first months with their hopes and optimism, now seemed somewhat unrealistic. Those who
were not in the war had gradually become habitual occupations. The existence resumed its regular
pace. "We must live," people said. And the need to continue thinking life filled with immediate
demands. Those with individuals The army armed remembered them, but their occupations muffled violence
of memory, running to accept the absence, as something that was going to be special normal. At first,
the war cut the dream, the food was inedible, bitter pleasure, giving it a funereal pallor. Everyone
was talking about the same. Now, slowly opened the theater circulating money, people laughed,
talked about the great calamity, but only to certain hours, as something
that was going to be long, lengthy, and demanding with inevitable
fatalism great resignation.

- Humankind can easily get used to misfortune
- Argensola said - as long as misfortune is long ... That is our strength,
which is why we live.

Don Marcelo would not accept his resignation. The war was going to be shorter than you imagined
all. His enthusiasm will immediately set a term: within three months in the spring next. And
if peace was not in the spring, would be in the summer.

A new participant took part in conversations. Desnoyers knew the neighboring Russian, Argensola
speaking to him.

Also this weird character had treated his son, and this was enough Tchernoff inspire you to
great interest.

In normal times, he was kept at a distance. The millionaire was in favor of order. Detested the
revolutionaries, with the instinctive fear of all the rich who have created his fortune and remember
the modesty of its origins. Tchernoff socialism and nationality would have necessarily resulted in
his mind a series of horrifying images, pumps, stabbing, just by hanging atonement, sent to Siberia.
No, it was a friend recommended ... But now Don Marcelo felt a profound disorder in the appreciation
of others' ideas. He had seen so much! ... The procedures terrifying invasion, lack of scruples
German heads, the ease with which the ships sunk submarines peaceful cast full of helpless passengers,
the exploits of the airmen, that two thousand feet throwing bombs on open towns, destroying women
and children, made him remember as unimportant events of revolutionary
terrorism attacks that caused years before outrage.

- And to think
- he said - that we are angry, as if the world were to fall apart,
because someone threw a bomb at a character!

These exalted offered to him a quality that dimmed his crimes. Victims died their own acts or
gave themselves knowing what would be his punishment. Sacrificed without seeking Output: rarely
had saved using the precautions of impunity. While The terrorist war! ...

With the violence of its urgent nature, the old effected a complete reversal of values.

- The real anarchists are now at the top - he said with an ironic laugh -. All that We were frightened
by some unhappy ... In a second killing the most innocent of our
time the other in thirty years.

The sweetness of Tchernoff, original ideas, and inconsistencies of thinker accustomed to reflection
jump to the word without any preparation, eventually seduce Don Marcelo. All doubts of consulting
with him. His admiration made him overlook the provenance of certain
bottles that sometimes Argensola regaled his neighbor.

Gladly accepted Tchernoff that consume these memories of the time when he lived fighting with your
child.

After tasting the wine of the avenue Victor Hugo, was a loquacious visionary Russian similar to that
of the night raised the fantastic ride of the four apocalyptic horsemen.

What I admired most was the ease Desnoyers putting things, fixing them through image. The Battle
of the Marne to the fighting that followed, and the race of both armies towards the sea were to
him made easy explanation ... If the French had not been tired after his triumph at the Marne!
...

--... But human forces - continued Tchernoff - are limited, and French, with all enthusiasm, is a
man like others. First, very rapid progress in the North East to deal with the invasion of
Belgium and then the fighting, and then withdrawal fast to avoid being enveloped, and finally
a battle of seven days and all this in a period just three weeks ... In the moment of triumph to
the victors legs were missing for go ahead and cavalry failed to
pursue the fugitives.

The beasts were more exhausted even men. To be harassed with little tenacity, which retreated,
falling fatigue, lay down and dug the earth, creating a shelter. The French also went to bed,
scratching the ground to keep the recovered ... And thus began the
war trenches.

Then, every line, in an attempt to envelop the enemy line had been
extending towards North West, and successive stretching was the race
to the sea each other, forming the largest battlefront was known in
history.

When Don Marcelo, in his enthusiastic optimism, announcing the termination of war next spring ... for
the summer, always within four months at the most, Russian shook his head.

- This will be long ... long. It's a new war, the true modern war. The Germans initiated hostilities
to the old style, as if they had not seen anything after 1870: outflanking war, battles in the open,
as he could devise Moltke imitating Napoleon. Wished to end soon and they were sure of victory.
What make use of new procedures? ... But what of the Marne twisted his plans were aggressors
to go on the defensive, and then used all that his staff had learned in Japanese and Russian campaigns,
beginning of trench warfare, the fight underground that is logical,
for the scope and quantity of fire of modern weapons.

The conquest a mile of land now accounts for more than a century
ago the assault of a fortress stone ... Neither are going to move
in a long time.

Maybe not ever move permanently.

This is going to be long and boring, like fights between athletes of balanced forces.

- But have you ever have an end - said Desnoyers.

- Certainly, but who knows when? ... And how will each other when it's over? ...

He believed in a quick end when people least expect it, with the fatigue
of one of the two wrestlers, carefully concealed until the last minute.

-
Germany will be defeated - he said with firm conviction -.

I do not know when or how, but fall logically. His coup failed him in September, not undoing to
enter Paris enemy.

All wins from their deck then threw them on the table. She did not win and continues to prolong
the game because it has many letters, and extend long time yet ... But what we could do at first,
never will.

To Tchernoff final defeat did not mean the destruction of Germany or the annihilation the German
people.

- Me, I am outraged - continued - the excessive patriotism. Listening to some people who made
plans for the final elimination of Germany, I seem to be listening to the Pangerman Berlin when
the continents divided.

Then clarified its opinion.

- We must defeat the Empire, for the peace of the world: eliminate the vast war machine which disturbs
the peace of nations ... Since 1870 all live badly.

For forty and four years have averted the danger, but in all this time which of anguish! ...

What
most irritated Tchernoff was born immoral teaching of this situation and had ended up taking
over the world: the glorification of force, the sanctification of success the triumph of materialism,
respect for the fait accompli, the mockery of the noblest sentiments, as if they were simple and
ridiculous sound bites, the disruption of moral values, a philosophy of bandits pretending
to be the last word of progress and was not more than back to despotism, violence, barbarism
of earlier epochs of history.

He wanted the removal of the representatives of this trend, but not this called for the extermination
the German people.

- This town has great merits confused with poor conditions, which are inherited from a barbaric
past too close. Has the instinct of the organization and work, and can provide good service
to humanity ... However, prior to administering a Shower: Shower failure. The Germans are mad
with pride, and his madness is dangerous for the world. When they are gone poisoned with illusions
of hegemony world when misfortune has cooled their imagination and be content with being a group
Human neither superior nor inferior to others, form a tolerant people, useful ... and who knows
if even sympathetic.

There was at the present time to Tchernoff most dangerous people.

His political organization made it an educated warrior horde kicked and subjected to continuous humiliation
to override the will, which always refuses to discipline.

- It is a nation where all are beaten and they want to give them to the one below. The kick releasing
the emperor is transmitted back to back to the last strata.

The shock start school and continue in the barracks as part of education. Learning the Crown
Prince of Prussia was always receive slaps and sticks to his father
the king.

The Kaiser stick to their offspring, the officer to his soldiers, father to his children and
the woman, the teacher to the students, and when the top can not
shock, which imposes upon it under the torment of moral outrage.

So they left their ordinary life, taking up arms to fall into another group human, were relentless
ferocity.

- Each one of them - continued Russian - brings back under a deposit of kicks received and want
to turn giving comfort to those unfortunate people who put the war under his domination. The
village of "gentlemen" as he calls himself, wants to be ... but outside
their home.

Within it is the least known human dignity. So feel so strongly the desire to spread throughout
the world, from servant to master.

Suddenly, Don Marcelo frequently stopped going to the studio.

Now looking to his friend Senator. A promise he had upset his quiet resignation.

The character was sad since the heir to the glories of his family
had gone to war, breaking the protective net of recommendations that
had been wrapped.

One night, eating at home Desnoyers, said one idea
that made it shudder. "Is not would like to see his son was handling
?...» Senator authorization Headquarters for the front. Needed to
see to René. Belonged to the same corps that July; were perhaps slightly
distant places, but a car can take many detours before reach the end
of your trip.

No need to say more. Desnoyers suddenly felt a strong
desire to see his son. Wearing many months have to be content with
reading his letters and the contemplation of a photograph taken by
a comrade ...

Since then laid siege to Lacour as if one of his constituents
eager for employment. Le visited in the morning at home, inviting
him to dinner every night, went to look for evening in the halls of
Luxembourg. Before the first word of greeting, his eyes formulated
always the same question ... "When get the permit?"

The great man
lamented the indifference of the military against the civilian component.
Always parliamentarism had been enemies.

- In addition, Joffre shown
intractable</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>