<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07122</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>32460</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>733</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> De «lo de ayer»,
se habló mucho más, y también con cierto cuidado para que no fuera oído desde la alcoba lo
que podía impresionarle nuevamente. Y fue un milagro de Dios que no nos oyera lo más de ello,
porque con el obstinado empeño que yo tenía en que había de haber algo entre Lita y el médico,
estuve verdaderamente pesado y machacón en ciertos pasajes del diálogo; particularmente durante
las escapadas de Mari Pepa a la alcoba, porque había tosido mi tío o se creía que había llamado...
o para ver si necesitaba alguna cosa, sin que tosiera ni llamara. En casa de don Pedro Nolasco
se había sabido todo, poco antes de pasar «la nube» que los había aterrado. Habían vivido en
la misma angustia que yo hasta muy entrada la noche. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04738</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>44975</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>677</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Of "what happened
yesterday," there was much more, and with some care to not heard from the bedroom as I could
impress again. It was a miracle of God that we do not hear most of it, because with the stubborn
determination I had in that there should be something between Lita and physician I was really
heavy and insistent in certain passages of dialogue, particularly during Mari Pepa getaway to the
bedroom, because my uncle had coughed or believed that he had called ... or to see if I needed something,
but coughed or call. At Don Pedro Nolasco had known all, shortly before going on "the cloud" that
had terrified. They had lived in the same anguish I late into the night.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>