<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document06096</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>224683</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22788</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Todo anunciaba que íbamos a tener un encuentro formal con el ejército francés.

Según nuestras noticias, Dupont continuaba en Andújar, reforzado por la división de Vedel.
¿Habían trabado acción con nuestro tercer cuerpo y el de reserva, que, pasando el río por Marmolejo,
estaban situados en la orilla derecha? Nosotros creíamos que sí, a menos que Castaños no aguardase
para atacar enérgicamente a que la primera y segunda división cayeran sobre la espalda del
ejército de Dupont, bajando desde Bailén. ¿Era éste el objeto que nos guiaba en nuestra marcha?
Parecíanos que sí.

Mientras llegaba el momento del drama, lejos de nosotros y en los flancos del ejército imperial,
mil dramáticas peripecias debían precipitar la catástrofe, irritando paulatinamente al enemigo.
Los cuerpos y columnas de guerrilleros, mandados por D. Juan de la Cruz, el conde de Valdecañas
y el clérigo Argote, se habían desparramado como enjambre mortífero por los pueblos y caseríos
que dominaba el Cuartel General francés en las primeras estribaciones de la sierra, al Norte
de Andújar. De tal modo perseguían aquellos ardorosos paisanos a los franceses, y con tanta
rapidez se dispersaban para evitar ser atacados, que a los invasores les era de todo punto
imposible estar tranquilos un solo momento. El poderoso gigante sacudía de una manotada aquellos
moscones venenosos; pero éstos volvían a zumbar en derredor suyo, le molestaban con sus terribles
picaduras, y huían incólumes, sin temer la espada ni el cañón, pues estas armas no se han hecho
para mosquitos.

No podían los franceses apartarse de su Cuartel General como no fuera en grandes destacamentos.
Frecuentemente iban mil hombres a llenar en la fuente próxima unas cuantas alcarrazas de agua.
Si por acaso salían a merodear pelotones de poca fuerza, eran despachados por los guerrilleros
en menos que canta un gallo. Antes que consentir que se apoderasen de una panera, la quemaban;
las fuentes eran enturbiadas con lodo y estiércol, para que no pudieran beber; los molinos,
desmontados y enterradas sus piedras para que no molieran un solo grano. ¡Ay de aquel francés
que se rezagara en las marchas de su destacamento! Sentíase de improviso asido por mil coléricas
manos; sentíase arrastrado por las mujeres, pellizcado por los chicos y acuchillado por los
hombres, hasta que su existencia se apagaba con horrible choque en la fría profundidad de un
pozo. El invasor no encontraba asilo en ninguna parte, y forzosamente encerrado en los límites
del Cuartel General, veía conjurados contra sí hombres y Naturaleza. Por esto, rabioso y desesperado,
anhelaba batirse en función campal, seguro de su destreza y costumbre de guerrear; y lamentando
la estupefacción del General en Jefe, exclamaba: «Demos una batalla, y, aunque muera la mitad
del ejército, la otra mitad conquistará un charco en que beber y un puñado de trigo seco que
llevar a la boca.»

Habían dejado los franceses en Montoro un destacamento de setenta hombres para custodiar un
molino donde fabricaban con dificultad harina malísima. El alcalde de aquella villa, donde
no había quedado ni una sola arma de fuego, se atreve, sin embargo, a dar cuenta de los setenta
franceses, para lo cual era preciso despachar primero a los veinticinco que a todas horas estaban
de guardia en el puente. Reúne, pues, algunos paisanos decididos, y usando la arma blanca,
ataca con furia a la guardia; los veinticinco son exterminados; apodérase de sus fusiles la
valiente cuadrilla, sorprende el resto del destacamento en la casa donde se albergaba, hace
prisioneros a soldados y jefes, y les manda a la isla de León. El parte en que se notificó
este suceso a la Junta Suprema decía que todo se hizo con las varas de los harrieros (conservo
la ortografía del original); pero esto ha de ser una hipérbole andaluza.

Sintiéndose llamado a mas grandes acciones, D. José de la Torre (que así se nombraba aquel
alcaldito) sale al encuentro de un convoy que venía de Córdoba, y de los cincuenta y nueve
franceses que custodiaban éste, los cincuenta quedan tendidos en el camino, y los nueve restantes
corren a contar a Dupont lo que ha pasado. Entonces Dupont envía mil hombres a Montoro con
encargo de que incendien el pueblo y lleven vivo o muerto al alcalde. Arde Montoro, y La Torre,
conducido vivo, va a ser pasado por las armas; pero un general francés, a quien poco antes
había dado hospitalidad, intercede por él; es puesto en libertad, y aquel petit caporal de
las guerrillas marcha a Sevilla y recibe de la Junta los galones de capitán de ejército.

Pues bien: lo que pasaba en Montoro ocurría en todos los pueblos de la carretera de Andalucía,
desde Córdoba hasta Santa Elena. El gigante que incendiaba lugares y destrozaba ejércitos no
podía dar un paso sin encontrar un avispero, y frenético con aquel zumbido, envenenado por
los aguijones, maldecía la hora de la invasión. El águila, devorada por los insectos, graznaba
a orillas del Guadalquivir con hambre y calentura, afilando sus garras en el tronco de los
olivos, con el ansia de que llegara pronto la ocasión de destrozar alguna cosa.

XXI

Cuando entramos en Bailén, ya muy avanzada la noche, nos sorprendió mucho el no ver ninguna
fuerza francesa a la entrada del pueblo para disputarnos el paso. ¿Adónde habían ido los franceses?
¿Qué les pasaba, cuando ni por precaución dejaron allí un par de batallones para guardar punto
tan importante? Pronto salimos de dudas, porque de boca de los habitantes de Bailén, que salieron
en masa a recibirnos, supimos que la división Vedel había pasado por allí en dirección a La
Carolina.

--Nosotros les hacíamos a ustedes en Linares--dijo D. Paco, que también salió a nuestro encuentro,
rebosando de júbilo--. ¡Oh!, Sr. Conde, niño mío... ¿Está por ventura herido Vuestra Excelencia?
Vamos un rato a casa, donde la Sra. Condesa y las niñas están rezando por el buen éxito de
la guerra. ¿No darán un descanso a las tropas?

Nuestro General había determinado salir en seguida para Andújar; pero como ocupábamos todo
el pueblo, pudimos llegarnos a la casa de nuestro amo, en cuya sala baja se nos dió un tentempié
muy confortante.

--Es un milagro que podamos daros estos cuantos panes y estas onzas de chocolate crudo--nos
dijo D. Paco al ofrecernos aquellos artículos--. Los franceses no han dejado nada. ¡Qué horroroso
saqueo! Y gracias que quedamos con vida. ¡Ay!, la Sra. Condesa salió a recibirlos con una serenidad
que me espantó. Yo temblaba, y tuve que esconderme en el oratorio, porque delante de ellos
hubiera perdido la dignidad de mi carácter. ¡Qué modo de saquear!...; en una palabra, la paja
de los caballos, las gallinas del corral, los huevos, hasta unos tomates que tenía yo guardaditos
en mi escritorio para hacer un gazpachito..., todo, todo se lo llevaron. El pueblo está muerto
de miseria, y yo sé de mucha gente que hechó la harina en los muladares para que ellos no se
la llevaran. ¿No lo creéis? ¿Pues y el Sr. Salvador, que sacó al campo los doscientos pellejos
de aceite y ciento de vino que tenía en su cueva, y destapándolos dejó correr aquel precioso
caldo hasta que todo se lo chupó la tierra? Otros hicieron una grande hoguera con los carros
y la paja. Las alhajas de las imágenes y la plata de las iglesias están todas enterradas, porque
esto parece que es lo que más les abre el ojo a esos señores. Así estaban ellos de rabiosos
cuando vieron que no sacaban de aquí gran cosa. El día 16, después de haber pasado un gran
miedo, gozamos lo indecible cuando les vimos llegar de la barca de Menjíbar, derrotados y con
su General muerto. ¡Cómo corrían por esas calles, y qué gritos daban, y qué cosas tan atroces
e indecentes echaron por aquellas bocazas! ¡Así se vengaban los muy perros! ¿Pues qué creéis?
Dieron muerte a muchas personas que no les hacían daño, lo cual creo yo que no se vió en ninguna
de las guerras de Alejandro. Pero también se les molió de firme. Unos cuantos pasaron por la
calle de enfrente hechando bravatas, y detuviéronse en la puerta de la posada de Gil, donde
tenían encendido el horno para cocer la loza. ¡Ay! Mis francesitos se ponen a decir no sé qué
insolencias obscenas a la mujer de Gil, cuando salen los mozos, me les agarran, y con morriones
y todo..., ¡plaf!..., al horno... Pero ahí viene la Sra. Condesa, que estaba en el oratorio
con las niñas.

En efecto; vimos desfilar gravemente, cubierta de negro manto, a la señora de la casa, seguida
de los dos tiernos pimpollitos de sus hijas, las cuales arrojáronse llorando en los brazos
de su hermano. Doña María abrazó a su hijo sin perder ni por un instante su solemne y estirado
empaque, y luego saludónos a todos con mucho afecto, nombrándonos uno por uno. Cuantos componían
la cuadrilla estaban presentes, menos Santorcaz, el cual desde nuestra llegada había pedido
con mucha prisa a D. Paco recado de escribir y puéstose a trazar unas cartas en el despacho
de éste.

La Condesa, después de saludarnos, tomó asiento y dirigió a D. Diego estas palabras dignas
de la Historia:

--Hijo mío, sé todo lo que pasó en la acción del 16, y nadie me ha dicho que hicieras algo
notable. ¿Has tenido miedo?

--¡Miedo!--exclamó el muchacho, riendo--No, señora. He cumplido con mi deber en las filas,
y nada más hasta ahora; pero su merced no se impaciente, porque aunque no soy más que soldado,
espero lucirme.

--¡Nada más que soldado!--dijo la Condesa--. Tú no eres soldado, aunque así parezca. Cualquiera
que sea el puesto que se ocupe, cada cual debe obrar conforme a su nombre y a la posición que
tiene en el mundo. ¿Qué se diría de ti, de mí, de esta casa, de tu difunto padre, si en estas
guerras no hicieras algo superior a lo que corresponde a un simple soldado?

--Señora--repuso el mozo con un desenfado que sorprendió a su familia--, yo haré lo que pueda,
y según lo que haga, así seré más o menos que los demás. Y ya que hablo de esto, señora madre,
yo quiero seguir en el ejército, yo quiero que su merced pida al Rey, ¿qué digo al Rey?, a
la Junta, una bandolera.

--Tú no estás destinado a ser militar sino en esta ocasión suprema, en que la patria necesita
de todos sus hijos, desde el más alto al más bajo.

--Pero, señora madre, no soy nada y quiero ser algo--insistió el joven, mostrando una energía
que nadie hasta entonces le había conocido.

--¡Que no eres nada!--exclamó la madre, con sorpresa primero, después con cólera, y mirándonos
a todos como para preguntarnos si su hijo se había vuelto loco durante la campaña.

--Yo no soy nada, no soy más que un papamoscas--repuso el chico--. ¿De qué me valen esos papeluchos
viejos y esos escudos de armas, si todos se ríen de mi desde que abro la boca, porque no digo
más que necedades?

La Condesa se puso encendida como la grana, y, sin decir palabra, miró a D. Paco, el cual,
confuso, absorto, aterrado, por lo que acababa de oír, revolvía sus espantados ojos de un lado
para otro.

--Este joven--dijo al fin el ayo--parece que ha perdido el juicio. Señora, cuando vuelva de
cumplir sus deberes de caballero en los campos de batalla, le haremos que se penetre bien de
las máximas contenidas en la historia de Alejandro el Grande.

Doña María, cuya dignidad no podía consentir que semejante asunto se tratara delante de personas
extrañas, hizo callar a D. Paco, y también impuso silencio a su hijo con gesto aterrador. Asunción
y Presentación, después de registrar los bolsillos de su hermano, examinaban las polainas,
el sombrero y la charpa, por ver, según dijeron, si aquellas prendas estaban agujereadas por
alguna bala de cañón.

Pero el D. Diego, sintiendo sin duda en su cabeza un hervidero de palabras, que atropelladamente
se le ocurrían conforme a la repentina fecundidad de su entender, no pudo estar callado mucho
tiempo, y habló para poner en mayores cuidados a la Sra. de Rumblar. Estábamos, como he dicho,
en una sala baja, donde la Condesa había hecho traer, para nuestro regalo, un par de zaques,
milagrosamente salvados de la rapacidad francesa. Don Diego, luego que tal vió, volvióse a
nosotros, que permanecíamos respetuosamente detenidos en la puerta, y con gesto de campechana
confianza nos dijo:

--Ea, muchachos, entrad todos aquí ¿Por qué estáis en la puerta? Vaya, poneos los sombreros,
que aquí todos somos iguales, todos somos compañeros de armas, y lo mismo puede matarme a mí
una bala que a vosotros. Ea, bebamos juntos. ¿Tenéis vergüenza porque soy noble y mayorazgo,
y vosotros unos pobres hambrones? Fuera necedades; que hoy o mañana las Juntas quitarán todas
esas antiguallas, y entonces cada cual valdrá según lo que tenga y lo que sepa.

Don Paco se puso verde al oír tales despropósitos, y llevándose la mano al corazón, miró a
la Condesa con semblante dolorido y contristado, como para manifestarle, en la sola elocuencia
de una mirada, que él no había enseñado tales cosas al joven discípulo. Doña María encerraba
su enojo en lo más hondo del pecho, y aunque harto se le conocían la inquietud y la ira en
el furtivo centellear de sus negros ojos, nada dijo que comprometiera su dignidad, y deseando
que su hijo variase de conversación, le preguntó si había hecho en Córdoba las visitas a la
Sra. Marquesa de Leiva y su sobrina.

--Sí, señora--contestó el rapaz--. Las vi: la Sra. Condesa me dió muchos dulces, y la Marquesa
me preguntó si sabía ayudar a misa. Una y otra me dijeron que la joven con quien está concertado
mi matrimonio se obstina en no salir del convento, asegurando que antes se casará con Jesucristo
que conmigo. ¡Qué ranciedades, señora madre!--añadió con nuevo arrebato--. Yo quiero seguir
en el ejército, yo quiero ir a Madrid para tratar a la gente que sabe, y a los filósofos, y
leer la Enciclopedia, y ver las sociedades secretas, si las hay para entonces, y aprender lo
que no sé, pues D. Paco no me ha enseñado más que esa sandez de Por el barandal del cielo.

El ayo volvió a mirar compungidamente a la Condesa, pintando en sus húmedos ojos la persuasión
de que no había instruído al mayorazgo en tales iniquidades, y D.ª María reprendió a su hijo
con majestad verdaderamente regia, diciéndole con pausa y aplomo estas amargas palabras:

--Hijo mío, recordarás que te entregué una espada que fué de tus abuelos. Honra da al que la
ciñe ese acero antiguo; pero también ella la recibe de las manos de su poseedor, si éste es
persona que sabe adquirirla en los campos de batalla. ¿Deshonrarás tú esa espada que llevó
el tatarabuelo de tu padre en el sitio de Maestrich, cuando medio mundo se llamaba España?

--¡La espada!--exclamó el chico con sorpresa--. Ya no me acordaba de la dichosa espada. Si
ya no la tengo.

--¿Que no la tienes?--preguntó D.ª María ton estupefacción.

--No, señora. ¡Si no sirve para nada! Cuando dimos el primer ataque en Menjíbar, saqué yo mi
espadita, y a los primeros golpes que di en unas hierbas observé que no cortaba.

--¡Que no cortaba!

--No, señora. Era una hoja mellada, llena de garabatos, letreros, sapos por aquí, culebras
por allí, y cubierta de moho desde la punta a la empuñadura. ¿Para qué me servía? Como no tenía
filo, la cambié por un sable nuevo que me dió un sargento.

--¡Y diste la espada, la espada!...--exclamó la Condesa, levantándose de su asiento.

La señora estaba sublime en su indignación. Parecía la imagen de la Historia levantándose de
su sepulcro a pedir cuentas a la generación contemporánea.

--Sí, señora: se la di al sargento--añadió el mozo, sacando de la vaina un sable nuevo, reluciente
y de agudísimo filo--. ¡Si aquello no servía más que de estorbo! Muy bonita, eso si, toda llena
de dibujos de plata y oro; pero, señora madre, si no cortaba..., si estaba llena de orín...
Vea usted este sable: no tiene letrero, ni cabecitas, ni garrapatos, ni nada; pero corta que
es un gusto.

Observamos que la Condesa dió un paso hacia su hijo; que su semblante hermoso y venerable se
contrajo, desfigurado por la ira; que extendió sus brazos; que comenzó a balbucir con locución
atropellada, cual si su indignada lengua no acertara a encontrar una palabra bastante dura,
bastante enérgica para tal situación; la vimos después llevarse ambas manos a la cabeza, retroceder,
vacilar, apoyarse en el hombro de D. Paco, y por último, reponerse, erguirse, serenarse, mirar
a su hijo con desdén, señalar a la calle, donde de improviso empezaba a oírse fuerte redoblar
de tambores, y decir:

--El ejército se va. Marcha, corre. Cuando se acabe la guerra, ajustaremos cuentas. Si eres
valiente y vuelves vivo, a palmetazos te enseñaré a respetar tu nombre. Pero si eres cobarde,
no vuelvas acá.

Salimos a toda prisa, y montando en nuestras cabalgaduras, ocupamos las filas. Al punto se
nos unió Santorcaz. Don Paco no quiso salir a despedirnos, porque estaba traspasado de dolor,
al ver--según dijo después--cómo en una semana se torciera, al soplo de las malas compañías,
el derecho arbolito criado con tanto esmero en el apacible huerto de sus lecciones.

Las dos señoritas salieron a las ventanas, y nos despedían agitando los mismos pañuelos con
que secaban sus lágrimas. Ninguna de las dos, ni la destinada al matrimonio, que era, por tanto,
ignorante, ni la consagrada al claustro, que era ya medio doctora, habían entendido la conversación
que acabo de referir.

Las pobrecillas veían desaparecer un mundo y nacer otro nuevo sin darse cuenta de ello.

XXII

Era la madrugada cuando las columnas de vanguardia comenzaron a salir de Bailén. Mi regimiento
debía salir de los últimos, y mientras se pusieron en movimiento la artillería y los cuerpos
de a pie, estuvimos más de media hora formados a la salida del pueblo, a mano derecha del camino,
esperando la orden de la marcha. Íbamos a Andújar, resueltos a tomar la ofensiva contra el
ejército francés, que al mismo tiempo debía ser atacado por Castaños, del lado de Marmolejo.
¿Y la división de Vedel, cuyos movimientos eran la clave de aquel problema estratégico? La
división de Vedel estaba en Andújar el día 16, cuando ocurrió la acción de Menjíbar, que antes
he descrito. Al saber Dupont la derrota de Ligier-Belair y la muerte de Gobert, dispuso que
Vedel marchase sobre Bailén, con intención de seguirle él al día siguiente.

Mientras éste iba sobre Andújar, Ligier-Belair, al vernos retirar y pasar el río, creyó que
las tropas de Reding, unidas con las de Coupigny, intentaban extenderse cautelosamente por
la orilla izquierda, río arriba, tomando el camino de Linares a Guarromán, para ocupar luego
La Carolina y cortar el paso de la sierra. Persuadido de esto, y sin hacer averiguaciones,
emprendió la marcha hacia el Norte, creyendo anticiparse a lo que creía un rasgo de ingenio
estratégico del general Reding. Llega Vedel a Bailén creyendo encontrarnos, y los franceses
que quedaron allí le dicen: «Quía, los insurgentes han repasado el río y van por Linares a
ocupar el paso de la sierra; pero el general Ligier-Belair, que ha comprendido el juego, ha
marchado en seguida a ocupar La Carolina, de modo que cuando lleguen los españoles, creyendo
haber hecho un movimiento de primer orden, se lo encontrarán allí.» Vedel oye esto y dice:
«Han ido a cortar el paso de la sierra para impedirnos la retirada y matarnos aquí de hambre
y sed. Pues corramos a La Carolina. Vamos; en marcha.» Manda un emisario a Dupont, diciéndole:
«Sr. General en Jefe, los insurgentes han ido a cortar el paso de la sierra. Corro a La Carolina;
venga usted tras mí, y acabaremos con ellos.»

Esto pasaba en los días 17 y 18. En tanto, los insurgentes, replegados a la orilla izquierda,
como he dicho, fingíamos un movimiento hacia Linares; pero en cuanto cerró la noche, los insurgentes
caminamos a marchas forzadas hacia Bailén. Por eso en este pueblo nos decían: «Por aquí pasó
Vedel esta mañana en dirección a La Carolina, para impedirles a ustedes que cortasen el paso
de la sierra. ¿No ibais hacia Linares?»

No; nosotros íbamos a Andújar, con objeto de atacar a Dupont. Por causa de los torpísimos movimientos
de los generales franceses, una gran parte de la fuerza imperial corría hacia la sierra, buscando
un fantasma. Los insurgentes, a quien ellos suponían en marcha hacia La Carolina, estaban en
Bailén, en marcha para Andújar. He aquí la verdadera y exacta situación de las divisiones españolas
y francesas en la noche del 18 al 19 de julio.

Íbamos a luchar con Dupont, sólo con Dupont. Pero ¿y si Vedel, conociendo a tiempo su error,
retrocedía velozmente para caer de improviso sobre nuestra espalda durante el combate? Esta
funesta probabilidad estaba compensada con el hecho seguro de que el ejército francés de Andújar
tendría que defenderse al mismo tiempo de nosotros y de la reserva, que le amenazaba del lado
de Poniente. De todos modos, nuestra posición era arriesgada; por lo cual, deseando Reding
cerciorarse de la verdadera distancia a que se hallaba Vedel, había despachado camino arriba,
desde Menjíbar, al teniente de ingenieros D. José Jiménez, con encargo de averiguarlo.

Este valiente oficial, cuyo nombre no está en la Historia, se disfrazó de arriero, y en una
fatigosa jornada supo desempeñar muy bien su comisión, volviendo por la noche a decir que Vedel
había pasado ya más allá de La Carolina.

Así andaban las cosas cuando nos preparábamos a salir de Bailén al amanecer del 19. Pero no
lo habíamos previsto todo: no habíamos previsto que Dupont, muy receloso de aquella ilusoria
ocupación de la sierra por los insurgentes, había levantado su campo en la misma noche, y silenciosamente,
sofocando los ruidos de su tropa, abandonaba la funesta y para ellos maldita ciudad de Andújar.

Cerca de la madrugada, nuestros jefes disponían las columnas para la marcha. Si al comienzo
de aquella misma noche, que ya se iba a extinguir, una mirada humana hubiera podido escudriñar
desde la altura de los cielos lo que pasaba en aquella larga faja de sementeras y olivares
que se extiende a la vera de los montes, entre éstos y el Guadalquivir, habría visto que del
obscuro caserío de Andújar se destacaba cautelosamente, escurriéndose por detrás de las casas,
una hilera de hombres y caballos; que esta hilera se iba alargando por la carretera en interminable
procesión, y serpenteaba con lento paso, sin ruido y sin luces; habría visto cómo se iba extendiendo
la negra raya, destacándose a ratos sobre la tierra blanquecina, a ratos confundiéndose con
los obscuros olivos, sin dejar de seguir paso a paso, como si no quisiera ser vista y anhelara
apagar en el polvo el ruido de las cureñas; habría visto que iban delante unos tres mil hombres
de infantería, después un escuadrón de caballos, después seis cañones, después un número inmenso
de carros, tantos, tantos carros, que ocupaban dos leguas; detrás de los carros nuevos grupos
de infantería y muchos generales; después otros seis cañones, dos regimientos de coraceros;
luego cuatro cañones, y al fin otro grupo de jefes, seguidos de quinientos hombres de a pie.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04050</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>603909</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20187</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> All announced we were going to have a formal meeting with the French army.

To our knowledge, Dupont continued in Andújar, reinforced by the division of Vedel. Had they stuck with
our third body action and the reserve, which, crossing the river by Marmolejo were located on the
right bank? We thought so, unless Brown does not wait to attack vigorously the first and second
divisions fell on the back of Dupont's army, down from Bailen. Was this the purpose that guided
us in our journey?

Parecíanos yes.

While the drama was time away from us and on the flanks of the imperial army, thousand dramatic
incidents were precipitated the catastrophe, gradually angering the enemy. The bodies and columns
of guerrillas, led by D. Juan de la Cruz, Count Valdecañas Argote and the cleric had been scattered
like deadly swarm through the villages and hamlets which dominated the French headquarters
in the foothills of the mountains, north Andujar. So those ardent pursuit of the French peasants,
and so dispersed quickly to avoid being attacked, that the raiders was quite impossible to be quiet
for a moment. The mighty giant who shook a handful moscones poisonous, but they returned to buzz
around him, annoyed him with its terrible bites, and escaped unscathed, without fear of the sword
or the gun, because these weapons have not been made mosquito.

The French could not deviate from its headquarters and not in large detachments. Thousand men often
went to fill in a few alcarrazas next source of water. If by chance squads out to roam a little
strength, were released by guerrillas at the drop of a hat. Before consenting to get the best
of a breadbox, the burning; sources were clouded with mud and manure, so they could not drink
the mills, disassembled and buried the stones to grind not a single grain. French unto him that
linger in his detachment marches! He felt himself suddenly seized by a thousand angry hands,
he felt drawn by women, pinched by the boys and stabbed by men, until their existence was extinguished
with hideous crash into the cold depths of a well. The invader was no asylum anywhere, and necessarily
confined within the limits Headquarters, I saw other men conspired against Nature. Therefore, angry and
desperate, longed to fight a pitched role, sure of his skills and customs of war, and mourning
the astonishment of the Commander in Chief, exclaimed: "Let us fight, and although half die army,
conquer half a puddle to drink and a handful of dry wheat lead to the mouth. "

They had left the French in Montoro a detachment of seventy men to guard a mill where they made
with flour terrible difficulty. The mayor of that town, where had not been not a single firearm,
dare, however, to account for the seventy French, for which it was necessary to send twenty-first
at all times that were guarding the bridge. Thus encompasses some countrymen determined, and using
knives, furiously attacked the guard, the twenty-five are killed, grab their rifles the brave
crew, surprised the rest of the garrison in the house which housed ago prisoners, soldiers
and commanders, and sends them to the island of Leon. The party was notified this event to
the Supreme Board said that everything was done with the rods of the harrieros (retain the
original spelling), but this must be a hyperbole Andalusia.

Feeling called to larger stocks, D. José de la Torre (for so he was appointed alcaldito) goes
to meet a convoy that came from Cordoba, and fifty-nine French guarding it, fifty are lying
on the road, and the remaining nine Dupont are to tell what happened. Dupont then send a thousand
men with Montoro Custom ignite and carry the people living or dead the mayor. Arde Montoro,
and Torre conducted live, will be spent for weapons, but a French general, who shortly before had
given hospitality to intercede for him, he is released, and that petit foreman Sevilla guerrillas
and get up to the Board of gallons of army captain.

Well, what happened in Montoro occurred in all the peoples of the road to Andalusia from Cordoba
to Santa Elena. The giant fire to and destroyed more armies could take a step without finding
a nest, and furious with that buzz, poisoned stings, cursing the time of the invasion. The
eagle, eaten by insects, squawked the banks of the Guadalquivir in hunger and fever, sharpening
his claws on the trunk of olive trees, with the desire to come soon destroy the chance of
something.

XXI

When we go into dance, and late at night, we was very surprised to see no French force at the entrance
of town to dispute the passage. Where had been the French? What happened to them, as a precaution
and left there a couple of battalions to save point so important? Soon we doubt, because the
mouth of the inhabitants of Bailen, who left en masse to welcome
us, we knew that the division Vedel had passed through in the direction
of Carolina.

- We did them to you in Linares - said D. Paco, who
also came to meet us and joyful -.

Oh, Mr. Earl, my child ... Does Your Excellency hurt perchance? Come a little home, where Mrs. Countess
and girls are praying for the success of war. Do not give the troops a break?

Our General had determined to leave at once for Andújar, but as we
occupied all the village, we arrived at the house of our master, whose
floor room gave us a snack very comforting.

- It's a miracle that
we can give these few loaves and these ounces of raw chocolate - we
D. said Paco by offering those items -.

The French have left anything. Tut plunder! And thank you to stay alive. Alas, Ms. Countess
came out to meet with a serenity I freaked. I was shaking, and I had to hide in the oratory, because
in front of them had lost the dignity of my character.

What a way to loot !...; in short, straw horses, barnyard chickens, eggs, until I had some
tomatoes that stash on my desk to make a gazpachito ..., everything was taken away. The town is dead
misery, and I know many people who made the flour in the dumps so that they do not ride. Do not you
think? Why, and Mr. Salvador, who took the field two hundred skins percent oil and wine he
had in his cave, and uncovered that precious left running broth until it sucked all the earth?
Others made a bonfire with cars and straw. The jewelry and silver images of the churches are all
buried, because this seems to be what they are most open eye on these gentlemen. So furious were
they from when they saw it taken out of here much. On day 16, after having spent a great fear,
enjoy the unspeakable when I saw the boat arrive Menjíbar, defeated and the General died. I ran
through the streets, and what screams gave, and what things so heinous and indecent cast by
those loudmouth! So the very dogs would take revenge! Well, what do you think? They killed many
people who did them no harm, which I think is not seen in any of the wars of Alexander. But they
are also hard ground. A few passed through the By taking street from bluster, and stopped at
the door of the inn Gil, where had turned the oven to cook the dishes. Ay! My Frenchies are
made that do not know what obscene insolence Gil's wife when the boys leave, I grab them, and
helmets and all ..., slap ... !..., baked But here comes Mrs. Countess, who was in the oratory
with girls.

Indeed, we saw parading seriously, covered in black cloak, the lady of the house, followed of
the two tender pimpollitos their daughters, who cried in the arms arrojáronse of his brother.
Dona Maria hugged his son without losing his solemn for a moment and stretched packing, and then
saluted them all with great affection, names one by one. Composed many the crew were present except
Santorcaz, which since our arrival had requested in a hurry to D. Paco puéstose writing materials
and to draw some letters in the office it.

The countess, after greeting us, sat down and went to D. Diego worthy words History:

- My son, I know everything that happened in the action of 16, and no one has told me to do
something remarkable. Have you been afraid?

- Fear! - Said the boy, laughing - No, ma'am. I have done my duty in the ranks, and nothing
else so far, but his mercy do not be impatient, because although
I am only a soldier I hope to show off.

- Nothing more than a soldier!
- Said the Countess -.

You are no soldier, even if this appears. Any that is the position occupied, each must act
according to his name and position has in the world.

What say you, me, this house of your deceased father if, in these Wars do not do something
more than what corresponds to a simple soldier?

- Lady - said the young man with an ease that surprised his family - I do what I can, and as I do,
so I will be more or less than others. And I talk about this, mother, I want to go in the army,
I want to ask your worship the King, what do I say to the King?, a the Board, a shoulder strap.

-
You are not meant to be military but this time supreme, where the
country needs of all children, from highest to lowest.

- But, mother,
I am nothing and I want to be something - insisted the young man,
showing an energy no one had hitherto known.

- You are nothing! -
Said the mother, first with surprise, then anger, and looking everyone
like to ask if his son had gone mad during the campaign.

- I am nothing,
I am a pied - said the boy -.

What are you worth these vile papers old and these coats of arms, if all laugh at me since I open
my mouth because I say no rather than nonsense?

La Condesa reddened like scarlet, and without saying a word, looked
at D. Paco, who, confused, lost, terrified by what had just heard,
rolled their eyes back frightened for another.

- This young man -
he said at last ayo - seems to have lost his mind.

Lady, when he returns from fulfill his duties as a gentleman in the fields of battle, we will
be entering either the maximum contained in the story of Alexander
the Great.

Dona Maria, whose dignity could not allow such a case is tried in front of people strange silenced
D. Paco, and silenced his son with a look scary.

Assumption and Presentation, after the pockets of his brother, studied leggings, Charpa hat and, to
be seen, they said, if those clothes were pierced by a cannonball.

But D. Diego, feeling no doubt in his mind a seething mass of words, hastily occurred to him
as to the sudden fertility of their knowledge, could not be silent long time, and spoke to give
more care to Mrs. Rumble.

We were, as I said, in a lower room, where the Countess had been brought to our gift, a pair
of wine-skin, miraculously saved from the rapacity of France. Don Diego, after he saw this,
he turned to us, we stayed respectfully held at the door, and hearty
gesture Trust told us:

- Hey, guys, come all here Why are you in
the door?

Go, put on hats, here we are all equal, all are comrades in arms, and the same can kill me a bullet
to you. Come, drink together. Do you shame because I am noble and primogeniture, wolverine and you
are poor? Outside nonsense, that today or tomorrow the Boards remove all these antiquities,
and then everyone will be worth as you have and what you know.

Don Paco turned green when he heard such nonsense, and touching his heart, looked at Countess to
face hurt and grieved, as if to express, in the sole eloquence a look, he had not taught these
things to the young disciple. Doña María enclosed anger in the depths of the chest and knew he
was sick but the concern and anger the furtive glitter of his dark eyes, said nothing that would
compromise their dignity, and wishing your child more of conversation, asked if he had done
on visits to Cordoba Ms. Marquesa de Leiva and his niece.

- Yes, madam - said the boy -. I saw them: Mrs. Countess gave me lots of candy, and the Marquesa
I asked if he could help mass. Over and over they told me the girl who is entered my marriage
persists in refusing to leave the convent, ensuring that previously married to Jesus Christ
to me. What ranciedades, dear mother! - Added to new outburst -. I want to keep in the army,
I want to go to Madrid to treat people who know, and philosophers,
and read the Encyclopedia, and see the secret societies, if any then,
and learn what I do not know, because D. Paco not only taught me the
folly of On the railing of the sky.

The schoolmaster looked back compungidamente the Countess, painting in his eyes wet persuasion
that he had not instructed of the estate in such wickedness, and Ms Mary scolded his son with
truly royal majesty, telling him to pause and poise these bitter words:

- My son, remember that I gave you a sword that had belonged to your
grandparents.

Honor gives that steel sticks that old, but she also receives from the hands of the holder, whichever
is person who can acquire them in the battlefields. Disgrace "that brought you this sword your father's
great-grandfather on the site of Maastricht, when half the world was called Spain?

- The sword! - Said the boy with surprise -. I do not remember the blessed sword. If and I have
not.

- What do not you? - Asked Ms Maria ton amazement.

- No, ma'am. If no avail!

When we made the first attack in Menjíbar, I brought my little sword, and the first shots I
gave in a saw that cut herbs.

- Do not cut!

- No, ma'am.

It was a dull blade, full of graffiti, signs, here toads, snakes
there, and covered with mold from tip to handle.

What I used? Having no edged sword exchanged my back gave me a sergeant.

- And gave the sword, the sword !...-- said the Countess, rising from
his seat.

The lady was sublime in its indignation.

It seemed the picture of history, rising from his grave to demand
accountability from the contemporary generation.

- Yes, ma'am, I
gave the sergeant - said the boy, pulling a sword sheath bright, new,
and very sharp edge -.

If that did not serve more than a hindrance! Very nice, that if all full drawings of silver
and gold, but, mother, if not cut ... if it was full of rust ...
You see this sword: it has no sign, or heads, or ticks, or anything,
but shorter than is a pleasure.

We note that the Countess took a step toward his son, that her face is beautiful and venerable
contracted, distorted by anger, which extended his arms began to stammer with voiceover hit,
as if his tongue angrily hitting pretty hard to find a word, quite
strong for such a situation, we saw then bring both hands to his head,
back, hesitation, leaning on the shoulder of D. Paco, and finally
recover, stand up, calm down, look his son with contempt, pointing
to the street, where suddenly began to hear strong step drums, and
say:

- The army goes.

Run, run. When the war is over, reckoning. If you brave and come back alive, slapping will teach
you to respect your name. But if you are a coward, do not come back here.

We left in haste, and riding our horses, we occupy the ranks. At the point Santorcaz joined us. Don Paco
would not come out to say goodbye, because I was pierced with pain, to see - he said later - in
a week how twisted, the blow of bad company, the right tree so carefully raised in the peaceful
garden of his lessons.

The two ladies took to the windows and waving goodbye to us with the
same tissue they dried their tears.

Neither, nor the intended marriage, which was therefore ignorant, or devoted to the cloister,
which was already half a doctor, had understood the conversation I have just mentioned.

The poor things looked a world away and a new birth without realizing it.

XXII

It was dawn when the columns began to edge out of Bailen.

My regiment should leave the past, and while the artillery set in
motion and bodies foot, more than half an hour were formed out of
town, to the right of way waiting for the order of the march.

We went to Andujar, determined to take the offensive against French
army at the same time Brown was being attacked by the side of Marmolejo.

What Vedel's division, whose movements were key to this strategic problem? The Vedel's division
was in Andújar day 16, when the action occurred Menjíbar, previously I have described. Dupont
Knowing the Ligier-Belair defeat and death of Gobert, provided that Vedel Bailén march on, intending
to follow him the next day.

While this was going on Andújar, Ligier-Belair, to see us withdraw and cross the river, believed
that Reding's troops, together with those of Coupigny, trying to expand cautiously the left bank,
upstream, taking the road to Linares Guarromán to occupy after The Carolina and cutting in
front of the saw.

Confident of this, without making inquiries, pushed toward the North, thinking ahead to what
you thought was a stroke of genius general strategic Reding. Bailen comes to believing Vedel
find, and French who were there say to him: "Quia, insurgents have gone over the river and go
for Linares take the step of the mountain, but the general Ligier-Belair, who has understood
the game, has gone at once to occupy La Carolina, so that when the Spanish arrived, believing
have done a first-order motion, I find there. "Vedel hears this and says: "They have been to
cut off the saw to prevent removal and hunger kill us here and thirst. Then run to La Carolina.
Come, on. "Send a messenger to Dupont, saying: "Mr. Commander in Chief, the insurgents have
been to cut off the mountains. I run to La Carolina; you come after me and kill them. "

This happened at 17 and 18. Meanwhile, the insurgents retreated to the left bank as I said, faked
a move to Linares, but as night fell, the insurgents walk in a rush to Bailen. So in this village
told us, "passed by here Vedel this morning in the direction of Carolina, to prevent you to hew step
of the saw. Do not you went to Linares? "

No, we went to Andujar, to attack Dupont. Because of the movements torpísimos French generals, a large
part of the imperial power ran to the mountains, looking for a ghost. The insurgents, whom they
supposed to march towards La Carolina, were Bailen, up to Andújar. This is the true and accurate
situation of Spanish divisions and French on the night of 18 to 19
July.

We were going to fight with Dupont, Dupont only. But what if Vedel, knowing his time error, quickly
retreated to fall suddenly on our back during combat? This dire was likely offset by the fact that
certain French army Andújar would have to defend both of us and reserve,
which was threatening side Poniente.

Anyway, our position was risky so, wishing Reding ensure that the true distance that was Vedel,
had sent up the road from Menjíbar, the lieutenant of engineers D. José Jiménez, with instructions
to find out.

This brave officer, whose name is in history, was disguised as carrier, and a exhausting day
playing very well knew his commission, returning at night to say that Vedel had passed beyond
La Carolina.

So things were when we were preparing to leave at dawn Bailen 19. But we had planned everything
we had not planned to Dupont, very wary of that illusory occupation
of the mountains by the insurgents, had raised his country on the
same night, and silently stifling the sounds of his troops, leaving
the unfortunate and they cursed city of Andújar.

Near dawn, our heads available for the march column. If at first that evening, which was to extinguish a human
eye could scan from the heights of heaven what was going on that
long stretch of fields and olive groves extending to the edge of the
mountains, between them and the Guadalquivir, would have seen that
the Andujar obscure hamlet stood cautiously, slipping behind the houses,
a line of men and horses, that this row was going on the road stretching
in endless procession, and wound with a slow pace, with no noise and
no lights, would have seen how it was spreading the black stripe,
standing out at times on the white ground, sometimes confused with
the dark olive trees, while step by step, as if unwilling to be seen
and longed Dust off the noise of the carriages, would have seen that
going forward about three thousand men infantry, then a squad of horses,
after six guns, then a huge number cars, many, many cars, which occupied
two leagues behind the new car groups infantry and many generals,
after six guns, two regiments of armed horsemen; then four guns, and
finally another group of heads, followed by five hundred men on foot.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>