<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04113</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>203924</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21766</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Pero, ¿cómo?

Tras pensarlo mucho, después de haber intentado en vano desarrugar el periódico con las manos,
se lo llevó a la cocina y lo alisó con una plancha caliente, dejándolo luego donde su hermano
lo encontrara, sin que Tirso lo viese. Al caer la tarde volvió Pepe con Millán, que acostumbraba
a comer allí los domingos, quedándose gran parte de la noche acompañando a don José, por estar
cerca de Leocadia. Hízole el padre la presentación de su hijo mayor, comieron todos alegremente
y de sobremesa hablaron de política, única conversación que tenía el privilegio de distraer
al pobre viejo, quien a cada instante hallaba medio de relacionar los sucesos de entonces con
los de su juventud, estableciendo comparaciones entre hombres y épocas distintas.

Pepe se había puesto a leer La Libertad Española, que pidió a Leocadia y que ella le trajo
sin una sola arruga, con gran sorpresa de Tirso; mas este permaneció callado, deseoso de escuchar
a Millán que, mirando de vez en cuando a la chica, sostenía el diálogo con don José. Decía
el viejo:

--Aquí no se hacen más que torpezas; si el partido liberal se divide, vamos a ver cosas muy
tristes.

--Ya las estamos viendo. ¿Le parece a usted poco el desarrollo que dejan tomar a la guerra?

--¡Si hubieran hecho ahora lo que Prim el 69!... Por supuesto que, tarde o temprano, tendrán
que hacerlo: con los convenios no se adelanta nada. Yo recuerdo que, cuando el de Vergara,
en realidad quienes perdimos fuimos nosotros: luego que el partido liberal aseguró la corona
a la Reina, le trataron como a un negro; a Espartero le arrinconaron en seguida; a los oficiales
carlistas les favorecieron mucho; decían que todos éramos hermanos, y los nuestros, que se
habían batido en invierno con pantalón de dril... iban a Filipinas o a Fernando Póo en cuanto
parecían sospechosos.

--Por eso y por cosas análogas hay tantos republicanos en la generación nueva; porque nos hemos
convencido de que no queda otro remedio.

--Eso es muy peligroso: el pueblo no está preparado.

--Y como nadie le enseña nada, tiene él que aprenderlo a su costa.

--Es que hoy no hay virtudes cívicas. Si hubierais conocido vosotros a Mendizábal, y luego
a Olózaga, que ahora está tan caído...: él fue quien llamó progresistas a los que decían antes
exaltados. Siempre ha habido más entusiasmo liberal que ahora. ¡Si vierais qué indignación
se desencadenó el año 40 contra Toreno y Martínez de la Rosa, porque pidieron la prórroga del
medio diezmo, y aun el diezmo entero y la primicia! Pues ¡y cuando Espartero no quiso aprobar
la famosa Ley de Ayuntamientos!

--Entusiasmos estériles, y que muchas veces han sido ahogados en sangre.

--En eso tenéis razón. Se condenaba a muerte por cualquier cosa. Desde el fusilamiento de los
sesenta compañeros de Manzanares y los veinticuatro de Alicante, el 8 de Mayo, hasta el de
los sargentos del 22 de Junio, no ha pasado año sin alguna brutalidad semejante: exceptuando
a los Zurbanos, y la muerte de Mariana de Pineda, para quien fue preciso hacer un garrote nuevo,
porque tenía el cuello muy delgadito...

--A pesar de lo cual--interrumpió Pepe--hay quien mira con buenos ojos a la Restauración y
quien se bate por don Carlos. Si en España quedan monárquicos, y sobre todo borbónicos, es
porque nadie lee historia contemporánea.

--En fin, hijos míos, ya sabéis que yo tengo buena memoria: pues bien, desde Diciembre del
43 hasta la Noche Buena del 44, fueron fusiladas doscientas catorce personas, la mayor parte
por liberales.

--Tiene Vd. razón, don José; así pagó la corona al partido liberal que, primero por el padre
y luego por la hija, había hecho tantos sacrificios...

--Pues si llega a tener espíritu santo la familia--añadió Pepe--nos quedamos sin una gota de
sangre.

Al oír este chiste impío, Tirso no pudo aguantar más. El elogio a Mendizábal, la alusión al
diezmo y la primicia, el horror a los fusilamientos de revolucionarios, el espíritu liberal
que palpitaba en la conversación, le hicieron daño; pero aquello de explotar para una gracia
la tercera persona de la Santísima Trinidad, puso el colmo a su indignación. Entonces, levantándose
de su asiento, se acercó al grupo que formaban Pepe y Millán junto a don José y, puesto delante
del balcón, sobre cuyo hueco claro se destacó su figura negra y espigada, dijo severamente:

--¡Parece mentira que hombres de juicio hablen así!

Millán calló por deferencia a su amigo, y don José porque se arrepintió de haber dicho tales
cosas, dando margen al enojo de Tirso: Pepe, más fogoso, se encaró con éste y, aunque hablando
moderadamente, le repuso:

--Es natural que tengas simpatías por los partidos reaccionarios; son los que os protegen;
pero, ¿negarás que nosotros no podemos mirar bien a la Iglesia? Siempre, y renegando de su
origen, ha sido enemiga de la libertad y de la democracia.

--¡La libertad! ¡la libertad! ¿y para qué sirve? Y ¿qué es la democracia? el permitir que manden
los pillos. ¡La democracia! ¿Cuántas libras de patatas se compran con eso?

--¡No! la libertad es lo que os mandó Cristo que predicarais; la democracia es eso que os ha
permitido a vosotros, clérigos y frailes, nacidos entre los más humildes, escalar los puestos
más altos del mundo.

--Pues Mendizábal fue un ladrón.

--Esa es una majadería que no tiene nada que ver con lo que hablamos. Y, mira, no te irrites;
pero por lo que me gusta Mendizábal, es por haber sido quien ha hecho más daño a la Iglesia.

--¡Callad, hijos míos, callad!--gritó don José:--¿Vais a reñir ahora? Yo no diré tanto; pero
Mendizábal fue un gran hombre. ¡Cuidado si tuvo mérito sacar la quinta de los 100.000 hombres!

Tirso hacía inútiles esfuerzos por disimular su disgusto. En vano afectaba oír en calma aquellas
cosas. Su desagrado no era pena, sino ira, viendo que no se había equivocado cuando, a poco
de poner el pie en la casa, imaginó que allí no había devoción ni creencias.

Su padre era un progresista ridículo, que se entusiasmaba hablando de Espartero; su hermano
un demagogo ateo, de los que hacen burla de Dios y la Divina Providencia; su madre una pobre
señora, a quien se le figuraba ser santa porque era hacendosa, y Leocadia una chicuela presumida,
que se pasaba la mañana embandolinándose el pelo. Allí nadie iba a misa, ni ayunaba, ni rezaba;
no había bula, se comía carne los viernes y el padre toleraba los chistes impíos de Pepe. Estuvo
a punto de descargar su indignación en apóstrofes violentos, de los que tantas veces oyó a
los señores que frecuentaban la casa de don Tadeo; pero se limitó a mirar a su hermano con
lástima, diciéndole:

--¡Parecéis judíos!

No concebía mayor insulto.

Las mujeres se miraron al oír las últimas palabras del diálogo, dichas ásperamente, sorprendiéndoles
la novedad de que allí se riñese por cosas de política; Millán fue a ponerse al lado de Leocadia;
don José calló, tratando de hallar medio de variar la conversación, y Tirso permaneció de pie
ante el balcón, como desafiándoles a todos y dispuesto a reanudar la disputa. Su figura resultaba
arrogante: más parecía soldado pronto a pelear, que hombre ansioso de convencer Al cabo de
un rato, como paladín que ha esperado en vano a su adversario, salió tranquilamente del comedor.
Pepe y Millán se fueron a dar una vuelta por las calles. En el portal, aquél preguntó a éste,
aludiendo a la escena pasada:

--¿Has oído?

--Vais a tener muchos disgustos.

--¿Creerás que esta es la hora en que no sabemos a qué ha venido?

--¿Tenía él en el pueblo relaciones con gente carlista?

--¿Por qué lo preguntas?

--Mucho cuidado... no sea que haya venido con algún encargo. Ahora se revuelven mucho. A ver
si os da un susto la policía. Para tu padre sería una impresión desastrosa.

       *       *       *       *       *

A la tarde siguiente se presentó en la casa un caballero de aspecto muy respetable, preguntando
por Tirso. Leocadia le acompañó hasta el comedor y avisó a su hermano; pero éste, apenas oyó
el nombre del recién llegado, se le llevó a su cuarto, permaneciendo largo rato encerrado con
él. La visita fue larga, y Tirso despidió al desconocido con grandes muestras de respeto.

A partir de aquella entrevista, el cura salió a la calle casi todas las noches, pero sin decir
nunca dónde ni a qué iba.

XIV

Menudeaban tanto por aquel tiempo los presbíteros que, fugados de sus curatos, aparecían luego
como cabecillas en el campo o eran sorprendidos en las ciudades sirviendo de auxiliares y emisarios
cerca de las juntas del partido faccioso, que nada tenía de absurdo la sospecha de Millán:
justificábala, además, el empeño de Tirso en callar el objeto de su viaje. ¿No podían haber
convertido el fanatismo de aquel hombre en instrumento suyo las mismas gentes que le hicieron
clérigo a espaldas de sus padres? La probabilidad de que en el momento menos pensado se presentara
la policía en la casa buscando a su hermano, asustó a Pepe, temeroso de la impresión que tal
lance pudiera causar en el ánimo del pobre viejo. Respecto a que Tirso diese margen a disgustos
de otra índole, por proponerse la conversión de la familia o emprender campaña para despertar
su fervor religioso, nada receló: antes era de temer, según el carácter que el cura demostraba,
algún rasgo de intolerancia, exceso de celo o frase áspera que turbara la tranquilidad del
hogar, porque la falsa circunspección que Tirso observaba oyendo comentar noticias de la guerra
se parecía mucho al disimulo.

Desde el día de la disputa en que llamó ladrón a Mendizábal, hacía la vista gorda tocante al
indiferentismo religioso que le rodeaba; pero claramente se notaba que en él no era todo prudencia,
sino falta de arrojo. Pepe, deseoso de no dar pábulo a la irritabilidad de su hermano, se abstenía
de chistes impíos y frases burlescas, aunque a veces se le venían a los labios, oyéndole desplegar
ingenuamente la más arraigada superstición; de suerte que ambos comenzaron a fingir cierto
comedimiento, a pesar del cual Pepe comprendía que la situación no era para prolongada y que
la menor cosa que proporcionase a Tirso ocasión de mostrar su enojo bastaría a desencadenar
una tormenta. Por su parte, el cura iba convenciéndose de que había venido a ser entre sus
padres y hermanos como árbol trasplantado de pronto a distinta tierra de la en que nació. Difícil
era que él arraigase allí ni pudiera vivir en paz con los suyos. Si fueran tibios en la devoción
o sólo tardos en cumplir las prácticas religiosas, aún habría remedio; pero no se trataba de
gente en cuyo pecho se hubiera amortiguado la fe, sino de individuos que, a juzgar por lo que
Tirso veía, no la sintieron nunca. El padre carecía de creencias, tal vez a consecuencia de
su simpatía hacia aquel partido progresista que siempre mintió respeto a la religión, sin ocultar
mala voluntad al clero; Leocadia y doña Manuela eran mujeres mal dirigidas, o mejor dicho,
descuidadas. En cuanto a Pepe, su incredulidad, su alejamiento de todo lo divino y sagrado
resultaban más graves, por ser fruto, no del olvido de las santas verdades, sino de un profundo
desprecio de ellas: le empujaban al descreimiento las corrientes de la época, los estudios
modernos, la atmósfera cortesana y una indudable predisposición personal. En esto no se equivocó
Tirso: los padres y la hermana se ofrecieron a su observación como realmente eran: indiferentes;
Pepe, como un impenitente convencido con quien la lucha había de ser más trabajosa, porque
la lucha era inevitable. No vino él al hogar con ánimo de provocarla, mas tampoco le parecía
razonable ni conforme a su ministerio mirar en calma aquel estado de honda perturbación que
le hizo prorrumpir en un momento de ira: «parecéis judíos.» Su entusiasmo religioso era sincero:
la conciencia le dijo que, si los azares de la vida le hubiesen colocado junto a gentes extrañas,
empecatadas como sus padres y hermanos, habría puesto tenaz empeño en convertirlas, y que mal
podía contemplar fríamente la perdición de su propia viña. Cuando resolvió su viaje a la corte,
no imaginó tener que consagrarse a esta obra: otros eran sus propósitos y él solo los sabía;
mas ya que la Providencia le mostraba la mala yerba en su camino, debía arrancarla, aunque
fuera al paso y sin distraerse de su objeto principal. ¡Deber juntamente grato y penoso el
salvar a sus padres y hermanos de la condenación eterna! Algo análogo leyó en sus libros devotos,
pero no tan en grande. Tal santo convirtió a su cónyuge, otro a su padre, alguno a su hermano:
él tenía que habérselas con toda su familia, en la cual antes jamás pensó, de la que vivió
apartado voluntariamente, pero que de pronto se le antojaba rebaño disperso al borde de un
abismo, y al cual había de guiar hasta recogerlo en el redil bendito de la Iglesia. Trájole
a la corte el servir a empresa más alta, por tratarse de la patria entera y no de unos cuantos
individuos; mas ya que Dios ponía la llaga al alcance de sus manos y la herida estaba como
en su mismo cuerpo, justo era que la sanara.

Comenzó en esto a agravarse la enfermedad del padre, fueron precisos mayores gastos, vinieron
para la familia días tristes y afligiose sobremanera doña Manuela; por todo lo cual determinó
Tirso empezar a cumplir su propósito, imaginando que en medio de la tribulación es cuando más
fácilmente se avasallan los corazones. Su madre y su hermana fueron las primeras a quienes
pensó atraerse. No alcanzó a más su sagacidad, y aun esto le repugnó sobremanera, pues toda
tardanza se le antojaba complicidad en el mal y todo fingimiento le parecía indigno del noble
fin a que enderezó la voluntad. Era fogoso, arriscado; mas adivinando en su hermano un terrible
adversario, comprendió que las circunstancias ponían trabas a su celo. Hubiera preferido combatir
cara a cara los obstáculos, congregar repentinamente la familia y convencerla de su error;
pero no se aventuró a tanto y, mal de su grado, como no pudo ser violento, se hizo astuto:
soñó con desempeñar papel de apóstol batallador, y hubo de limitarse a obrar como jesuita de
novela, pero de buena fe, con limpia intención, seguro de poner el ánimo en una empresa honrada.

Resuelto a extirpar la impiedad que se había enseñoreado de su casa, no quiso demorarlo, y
una mañana, como observase que doña Manuela estaba desdoblando el mantón para ir a comprar
unos medicamentos, se anticipó a ella y la esperó en una esquina próxima: luego la fue siguiendo
por la calle Imperial abajo, y cuando iba a entrar en una botica de la de Toledo, la llamó
de cerca:

--¡Madre, madre!

--Hijo, ¿cómo tú por aquí?

--Quiero hablar con Vd. ¿Tiene Vd. que esperar en la botica?

--Un ratito.

--Pues vamos primero por las drogas; luego aguardaremos juntos, y le diré a usted lo que deseo.

Tirso hablaba con acento severo: su madre le oía con una curiosidad mezclada de temor.

--Pero hombre, ¿qué es ello? ¿Pasa algo malo en casa?

--No: ¡si he salido yo casi al mismo tiempo que Vd.! Nada ocurre; pero quiero que hablemos.

Entró doña Manuela en la botica, esperola él a la puerta, y apenas la vio salir, continuó de
este modo, mientras ella le seguía dócilmente:

--Vámonos ahí al lado, al pórtico de San Isidro.--Y subieron las escaleras de la iglesia.

--Mire Vd., madre, yo no quiero callarme: estoy disgustadísimo. Desde que llegué a Madrid tengo
el alma llena de tristeza...

--Lo comprendo, hijo: nuestra situación no es para menos. ¡Si vieras la crujía que hemos pasado!...
¡Y lo que queda!...

--No es nada de eso.

--Pues no te entiendo.

--Ahora me comprenderá Vd. Mi obligación era decir a mi padre lo que voy a decirle a Vd., pero
creo que con Vd. me entenderé mejor: además, su carácter y su estado... Más adelante veré lo
que he de hacer.

--¿Carácter, dices? ¡Si el pobre no molesta a nadie ni se enfada nunca!...

--Quizá por esa bondad tengamos mucho que llorar.

--¡Explícate, por Dios, hijo mío!

--Sí, madre; mucho que llorar y que sentir. Vaya, clarito; en casa no hay religión, y donde
falta la religión todo está perdido. Así les castiga a ustedes Dios.

--¡Castigarnos Dios!

--¡Le parecen a Vd. pocas penas esa enfermedad, esa escasez, esos sufrimientos!...

--¿Y qué le hemos de hacer? Todos trabajamos. ¿No has visto la vida que llevan tus hermanos
y lo que yo me afano?

--¡Pregunta Vd. lo que pueden hacer! ¡Parece mentira! Es imposible que Dios ayude a ustedes.

En vano pretendía dar dulzura a sus frases: la extraordinaria viveza de los ojos acusaba una
resolución enérgica.

--No, madre; no esperen ustedes alivio ni amparo. En casa no hay religión, no se reza, no se
practica una sola devoción... Da grima pensarlo. Desde hace cerca de un mes que estoy en Madrid,
¡cuántas cosas tristes he visto! ¡Ni una oración, ni un acto de piedad! Comprendo que padre
no vaya a misa, aunque bien pudiera sustituirla con algunos actos de recogimiento y penitencia;
pero, ¿y Vd.? ¿y Leocadia? ¿y Pepe? ¡Vivís como herejes! Lo confieso, madre; he dudado mucho
antes de dar este paso, pero mi deber es antes que todo. ¿No siente usted miedo... vergüenza
por vivir así?

--Y ¿qué quieres que haga? Yo no mando... yo cuido de la casa... y nada más: la limpieza...
trabajar y más trabajar... ¡qué sé yo!

--¡Limpieza y trabajo! ¡Con eso piensa usted que ha cumplido! Cuando el Señor la lleve de este
mundo, que la llevará... desgraciadamente, ¿se salvará Vd. con haber tenido aseada la casa?
¡La casa limpia y el alma negra por el pecado! ¡Toda la pulcritud para uno mismo, todo el trabajo
para lo propio, y ni una visita a la casa de Dios, ni un pensamiento para su divina Madre!
¡Da ira el verlo!

Doña Manuela oía en silencio, sobrecogida con aquel inesperado disgusto, que aun para su escasa
inteligencia era señal de otros mayores. La vehemencia de Tirso llegó a exacerbarse tanto,
que la pobre vieja no pudo menos de decirle, casi con enojo:

--¡Hijo, no manotees, que nos ve la gente!

Él estaba ya poseído de su papel, y no hacía caso.

--¡Aquí no hay hijo! No hay sino un sacerdote que ha visto esa lepra asquerosa del ateismo
y quiere curarla. ¿Lo oye Vd., madre? Si Vd. no me ayuda, lo haré yo solo... lo intentaré yo
solo; y si no puedo lograrlo, se lo diré a todos ustedes, cara a cara, sacudiré en la puerta
el polvo de mis zapatos, como los patriarcas de Israel cuando salían de la casa de los impíos,
y no volverán ustedes a verme nunca.

--Y del escándalo y del disgusto se morirá tu padre.

--¿Qué más muerte que la que tenemos encima? El corazón cerrado a la piedad... ¡Si basta entrar
allí para convencerse!... Estampas de reos liberales en las paredes, periódicos perversos de
los que venden por las calles, comedias o noveluchas que lleva ese Millán de la imprenta y
que permitís leer a Leocadia, libros malos... y en toda la casa no hay una imagen de la Virgen
ni una cruz de palo...

--Yo no mando...

--Pues es necesario que mande Vd. A falta de padre, y estamos como si faltara, usted es quien
debe gobernar: yo la ayudaré... y elija Vd., madre: poner remedio al mal, o dejar que lo remedie
yo solo, contra mi padre, contra Pepe, contra todos.

--¡No, hijo de mi alma, por Dios, eso no, a Pepe no le hables de estas cosas!

--¡Ah! ¿Tiene Vd. miedo? Pues yo no.

Hablaban en voz baja, solos en un rincón del atrio de la iglesia, mientras les miraba curiosamente
una mujer que en la escalinata vendía estampas, caras de Dios con marco de estaño, chufas,
majuelas y torraos. Tirso intimidaba a su madre accionando con ademanes descompuestos: ella,
ya ansiosa de cortar el diálogo, miraba alternativamente hacia el suelo y hacia la acera opuesta,
donde estaba la botica. Las acusaciones de impiedad no la hicieron en un principio gran efecto;
pero cuando Tirso las presentó como causa de los males sufridos y promesa de castigos eternos,
su debilidad mujeril cedió al empuje del creyente. Lo que peor la sentó, fue la amenaza de
que hablaría con Pepe.

Guardaron silencio unos instantes: él, dudoso del éxito de su empresa; ella, turbada, deseosa
de sustraerse al influjo violento de aquel hijo que, para sojuzgarla mejor, acababa de decirla:
«no soy sino sacerdote.»

--¿Vamos a la botica?--se atrevió por fin a preguntar la madre.

--Espere Vd.; no quiero que nos separemos así. Tiene Vd. que prometerme antes su auxilio. ¿Trabajará
Vd. conmigo para que seamos todos cristianos, o me entiendo yo con Pepe y con mi padre? ¿Imagina
usted vivir santamente no haciendo daño al prójimo? ¡Qué ceguedad! ¿Y Vd. misma? ¿Y su salvación?
Rece Vd., madre, esto es lo primero, y Dios la iluminará y borrará de su alma esa apatía; venga
Vd. a misa, y a poco que despierten los buenos sentimientos, cesará Vd. de reír las bufonadas
sacrílegas de mi hermano, y arderá Vd. en deseo de auxiliarme. ¿Lo promete Vd.?

--Sí, hijo--contestó azorada--pero a Pepe no le cuentes nada de esto.

--¡Ya comprendía yo que él es quien tiene la culpa de lo que ocurre! Quedamos en que Vd. es
mía, es decir, de Dios; si no, me marcharé para siempre, después de declarar francamente ante
todos que no quiero vivir entre judíos.

Bajaron lentamente las escaleras del atrio, esperó Tirso a la puerta de la botica y, al ver
salir a su madre con un frasquito en la mano, dijo:

--¡Tanto esmero, tanta solicitud para buscar remedio a los males del cuerpo, que no importan
nada, y ni un pensamiento para la salud del alma! Acuérdese Vd. de lo que acabamos de hablar.

En seguida se separó de ella, dejándola confusa y asustada, como mujer a quien acaban de sorprender
cometiendo un delito. El pecado, la condenación, la impiedad, habían sonado en sus oídos a
modo de palabras vacías de sentido; las amonestaciones de un Bossuet no hubiesen ejercido en
ella más imperio. Lo que la dejó amilanada fue la amenaza de hablar a su marido y a Pepe, segura
de que la menor reconvención de Tirso provocaría una escena agria, quizá un rompimiento y un
disgusto gravísimo. ¿Qué podía hacer ella para evitarlo? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09139</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>120208</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20119</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> But how?

After much thought, after trying in vain unwrinkle the newspaper with his hands, took him to the
kitchen and straightened with a hot iron, leaving it to his brother after find him without seeing
him Tirso. When evening came Pepe Millan, who used to eat there on Sunday, leaving much of the
night with Don Jose, for being near Leocadia. Presentation made him the father of his eldest son
happily ate all desktop and talked about politics, the only conversation I had the privilege
of diverting the poor old man, who was every moment means to relate the events of that time with
those of his youth, drawing comparisons between men and different times.

Pepe had begun to read Spanish La Libertad, which asked Leocadia and she brought without a single
wrinkle, to the surprise of Tirso, but this remained silent, willing to listen Miller that,
looking from time to time to the girl, holding a dialogue with Don
José.

Said old:

- Here are not only clumsy, if the liberal party is divided, we will see things sad.

- Already we are seeing. Does it seem to you little development left to take to war?

- If what you have done now for 69 Prim! ... Of course, sooner or later, will to do: with no progress
Conventions anything. I remember that when the de Vergara, who were actually lost us after
the Liberal Party said the crown the Queen, he was treated like a black-Espartero cornered him
at once, to official Carlist favored them much, they said we were
all brothers, and ours, which winter had beaten in denim pants ...
went to the Philippines or as Fernando Poo looked suspicious.

- That
and similar things so many Republicans in the new generation, because
we convinced that there is no alternative.

- That is very dangerous:
people are not ready.

- And since no one teaches anything, does he
have to learn at their own expense.

- Is that today there is no civic
virtues.

If you had known Mendizabal, then to Olózaga, now so fallen ...: it was he who called progressives
who said before exalted.

It has always been more liberal enthusiasm now.

If you only saw what indignation 40 year unfolded against Toreno
and Martinez de la Rosa, requested the extension because of half tithe,
and even the whole tithe and the scoop!

Well they would not approve Espartero the famous Councils Act!

- Enthusiasm sterile, and have often been drowned in blood.

- In that you are right. Was condemned to death for anything. Since the execution of Manzanares
sixty partners and twenty of Alicante, May 8, until the Sergeants
June 22, has last year without any such brutality, except to Zurbano,
and the death of Mariana de Pineda, for whom it was necessary to make
a new club, because my neck was very skinny ...

- In spite of this
- broke Pepe - there are those who look favorably upon the Restoration
and who fights for Don Carlos.

If Spain are monarchists, and especially Bourbon is because nobody
reads contemporary history.

- Finally, my children, you know that
I have a good memory: well, since December 43 to Christmas Eve of
44, two hundred and fourteen people were shot, most by liberals.

-
Have you right, Don Jose, and paid the crown to the Liberal Party,
first by the father and then the daughter, had made so many sacrifices
...

- Well if you do have family holy spirit - Pepe said - we were
without a drop of blood.

Upon hearing this joke wicked Tirso could not take it anymore. Praise Mendizabal, the reference
to tithing and the scoop, the horror of the executions of revolutionaries, the liberal spirit throbbing
in the conversation, made him harm, but to exploit what a grace the
third person of the Holy Trinity, set the height to their outrage.

Then, rising from his seat, approached the group formed by Pepe and Miller with Don José and,
as before the balcony, on which stood clear opening its slender black figure and said sternly:

-
It seems incredible that men talk and opinion!

Miller stopped in deference to his friend, and Don Jose because he
repented of having said such things, leaving room for the wrath of
Tirso: Pepe, more passionate, he faced it, and while talking moderately,
he said:

- It is natural to have sympathy for the reactionary parties,
are those that protect you; but do you deny that we can not look good
for the Church?

Always, and renege on their origin, has been the enemy of freedom and democracy.

- Freedom! Freedom! What for? " And what is democracy? allowing them to send crooks. Democracy!
How many pounds of potatoes are bought with that?

- No! freedom
is what Christ commanded you to preach democracy is that which hath
allowed you, clerics and monks, born among the most humble, climbing
posts highest in the world.

- For Mendizabal was a thief.

- That
is a nonsense that has nothing to do with what we say.

And look, do not fret; but what I like Mendizabal, is for being who has done more harm to the
Church.

- Hush, my children, hush! - Shouted Don José: - Are you going to fight now? I will not say much, but
Mendizabal was a great man. Take care if you have had merit a fifth of the 100,000 men!

Tirso made futile efforts to hide his disgust.

In vain to calm those affected hear things. His displeasure was not grief, but anger, seeing
that he was wrong when, shortly set foot in the house, he imagined that there was no devotion
or belief.

His father was a progressive ridiculous that Espartero excited talking, and his brother a demagogue
atheist, of which make a mockery of God and Divine Providence, his
mother a poor lady, whom he imagined to be a saint because he was
industrious, and a little girl presumed Leocadia, who spent the morning
embandolinándose hair.

There was no mass, or fasting, or praying; there was no bull, ate meat on Fridays and father tolerated
Pepe wicked jokes.

Was to vent their anger about violence in apostrophes, of which so often heard the gentlemen
who frequented the house of Mr. Thaddeus, but just looked at her brother pity, saying:

- You seem like Jews!

No greater insult conceived.

The women looked at the last words of dialogue, said gruffly, surprising
the news that there Wheels by political matters, Miller went to stand
beside Leocadia; Don Jose was silent, trying to find means of changing
the conversation, stood Tirso to the balcony, as challenging them
to all and ready to resume the dispute.

His figure was arrogant, more like soldiers ready to fight, that man eager to convince After a while,
as a champion who has waited in vain for his adversary, left the room quietly. Pepe and Miller
went for a walk through the streets.

In the portal, that he asked, referring to the last scene:

- Have you heard?

- You are going to have much trouble.

- Would you believe that this is the time we do not know why you came?

- Was he in town Carlist relationships with people?

- Why do you
ask?

- Be careful ... lest there come with some commission.

Now stir a lot.

Let's see if you give the police a scare. To print your father would be a disaster.

* * * * *

The next afternoon went to the home a very respectable-looking gentleman, asking by Tirso.
Leocadia accompanied him to the kitchen and told her brother, but he barely heard the name of the
newcomer, he was carried to his room and remained locked up with long time him. The visit was
long, and fired Tirso unknown with a great show of respect.

Since that interview, the priest went out almost every night, but
said or where ever he went.

XIV

       Often both at that time the priests who escaped from their parishes,
then appeared as leaders in the field or were caught in the cities
serving as assistants and messengers near the fractious party together,
that there was nothing absurd suspicion Millán: justificábala also
Tirso's commitment to remain silent for the purpose of your trip.

Could not they have become fanaticism that man in his instrument the same people that made him
cleric backs of their parents? The probability that in the present when you least expect it
police in the house looking for his brother, Pepe scared, fearful of the impression that such
release could cause in the mind of poor old man.

Regarding to give room for disappointment Tirso otherwise, for the proposed conversion of the
family or take campaign to raise their religious fervor, nothing
suspicious: was once feared, according to the character that the priest
showed, some feature of intolerance, excessive heat or harsh sentence
to disturb the tranquility of home, because false circumspection watched
Tirso hearing news of the war comment resembled the sly.

From the day of the dispute that thief called Mendizabal, turned a blind eye with respect to religious
indifference that surrounded him, but clearly felt that it was not all prudence, but lack
of courage. Pepe, anxious not to fuel the irritability of his brother, abstained wicked jokes
and mocking phrases, but sometimes he came to his lips, hearing deploy more naively rooted superstition
so that both began to pretend certain restraint, despite that Pepe knew that the situation was not
for long and the slightest thing to Tirso provide an opportunity to show their anger would be
enough to trigger a storm. For its part, the priest was convinced that he had come to be among
parents and siblings as tree suddenly transplanted to other land of his birth. Difficult was
that he could take root there or live in peace with their own. If they were lukewarm in their devotion
or just slow to meet the religious practices still have choice, but it was not people whose
heart had cushioned the faith, but of individuals who, judging by what Tirso seen, not felt before.
The father had no beliefs, perhaps a result of sympathy progressive
party that lied always respect for religion, not hide unwillingness
of the clergy Leocadia and doña Manuela women were misdirected, or
rather, neglected.

As for Pepe, their unbelief, their absence of all divine and sacred were more serious, because
the fruit, not forgetting the holy truths, but a deep contempt for them: he pushed the disbelief currents
of the time, studies modern courtly atmosphere and a definite predisposition. In this he was right
Tirso: parents and sister gave their comments as they really were: indifferent Pepe, as an unrepentant
confident with whom the struggle had to be more laborious, because the fight was inevitable.
He did not come home with the intention to provoke, but neither seemed unreasonable under his
ministry to look into that state of deep calm disturbance made him break out in a moment of
anger, "you seem to Jews." His enthusiasm was sincere religious: conscience told him that
if the hazards of life he had placed next to strangers, empecatadas as their parents and siblings,
would have dogged efforts to convert them, and that bad could look coldly destruction of his own
vineyard. When solved your trip to the court, not imagine having to devote to this work: some
were his purposes and he only knew; but since Providence showed him the weeds in its path, was
starting, but to step outside without being distracted from its main object. Duty along the
pleasant and painful save her parents and siblings of eternal damnation! Some read books analog devotees
but not so big. This saint became a spouse, another to his father, one to his brother: he
was dealing with his family, which never before thought, which lived paragraph voluntarily,
but suddenly it seemed scattered flock to the edge of a deep, and which was to be guided to pick
in the fold of the Church blessed. Brought him to cut the company to serve higher, because
it is the entire nation and not a few individuals, but since God put the sore at your hands and
the wound was as in the same body just was to heal her.

It began to worsen in the parent's illness, it took higher expenses came sad day for the family
and Dona Manuela greatly dismayed, for all of which determined Tirso start fulfilling its purpose,
imagining that in the midst of trouble is when most easily overwhelm our hearts. His mother and
sister were the first who attract thought. Not reach more sagacity, and even this will greatly disgusted,
as all delay seemed to her complicity in evil and all pretense seemed unworthy of the noble straightened
so that the will. It was fiery, Arriscado, but guessing at his brother a terrible opponent, he
realized that the circumstances put obstacles to his zeal. Would have preferred to fight face
to face obstacles, suddenly gather family and convince them of their error; but did not venture
much and, against his will, as there could be violent, it was clever: dreamed of playing the
role of apostle is combative, and had to be limited to acting as a Jesuit novel, but in good faith,
with a clear intention, make sure the mood in a company honest.

Determined to eradicate the wickedness which had dominion over his home, he would not delay
it, and one morning, and finds that Dona Manuela was unfolding the shawl to go shopping some
medications, anticipated it and waited in a corner next: then he followed Imperial down the street,
and when he would enter a drug store in the Toledo, called closely:

- Mother, Mother!

- Son, how are you doing here?

- I want to talk with you Do you have to wait in the pharmacy?

- A little bit.

- Well, let us first by drugs, then we will wait together, and I'll tell you what I want.

Tirso severe spoke with an accent, his mother heard him with a curiosity mixed with fear.

- But man, what is it? Is something wrong at home?

- No: if I left I was almost at the same time as you! Nothing happens, but I want to talk.

Dona Manuela entered in the pharmacy, esperola him outside, and just
saw her leave, continued to Thus, while she obediently followed him:

-
Let's go there next, the portico of San Isidro .-- And they went up
the stairs of the church.

- Look at you, mother, I will not shut
up: I disgustadísimo.

Since I have arrived in Madrid a heart full of sadness ...

- I understand,
son, our situation is not without reason.

If you saw the bay ever!

... And what's left! ...

- There's nothing like that.

- I do not understand you.

- Now you understand me My duty was to tell my father that I will tell you, but I think that
you will understand me better, also his character and state ... Later
I'll see what I have to do.

- Character, you say?

If the poor are not upset or annoyed anyone ever! ...

- Maybe that goodness we have much to mourn.

- Explain, by God, my
son!

- Yes, mother, much to mourn and to feel.

Well, Clarita, at home no religion, and where takes religion all is lost. So God punished you.

- God punish!

- I seem to you a few sentences that disease, the scarcity of such suffering! ...

- And what did we do?

We all work. Have not you seen the life they lead your brothers and
what I labors?

- Ask what you can do!

It seems impossible! It is impossible for God to help you.

Vainly sought to provide sweetness to his phrases, the extraordinary
vividness of an accused eyes strong resolution.

- No, mother, do
not expect you relief or protection.

At home there is no religion, no praying, no practice a single devotion
... Da creeps thinking.

For almost a month since I'm in Madrid I have seen many sad things!

Not a prayer, nor an act of mercy! I understand that father not go to church, although it may
well replace it with some acts of devotion and penance; But what
about you?

Leocadia what? What about Pepe? You live as heretics!

I confess, mother, I doubted much before taking this step, but my duty is first and foremost.
Do not you feel afraid ... shame to live well?

- And what do you
want?

I do not control ... I take care of the house ... and nothing more: cleaning ... work and more
work ... I do not know!

- Clean and working! With that you think has been accomplished! When the Lord takes this world,
that will ... unfortunately, is save you to have had the house neat? The house clean and the
black soul by sin! All neatly for oneself, all work for the same, and not a visit to the house
of God, not a thought for Mother Divine!

Da anger to see him!

Doña Manuela heard in silence, overwhelmed with this unexpected disappointment, that even for low
intelligence was a sign of bigger ones. The vehemence of Tirso became exacerbated therefore
the poor old woman could not help but say, almost angrily:

- Son, no slapping, people see us!

He was already possessed of his role, and would not listen.

- There is no son!

There is but one priest who had seen the foul leprosy of atheism and wants to heal. Did you
hear, mother? If you do not help me, I will just ... I will try alone, and if I can not do,
I'll tell you all face to face, shake at the door the dust off my shoes, like the patriarchs
of Israel as they left the house of the wicked, and you will not see me ever again.

- And the scandal and disgust your father will die.

- What more death than we have up? The heart closed to pity ... If you simply enter there to
be convinced! ... Pictures of prisoners liberals on the walls, newspapers perverse those selling
in the streets, carrying noveluchas comedies of the press that Miller and that you allow to read
Leocadia, bad books ... and throughout the house there is an image
of the Virgin or a wooden cross ...

- I do not control ...

- Well,
you have to send the absence of a father, and we as missing, you are
the should govern: I'll help ... and choose you, mother to remedy
the evil, or let the remedy myself, against my father, against Pepe,
against all.

- No, son of my soul, my God, why not, Pepe did not
talk about these things!

- Ah!

Do you have fear?

I have not.

They spoke quietly, alone in a corner of the churchyard, while looking
at them curiously a woman on the steps of selling prints, framed faces
of God tin, groundnuts, hawthorn and torrao.

Tirso intimidating gestures gesticulating with his mother broken-she,
and eager to cut the dialogue, looked alternately at the floor and
onto the sidewalk opposite where was the pharmacy.

The charges of impiety did not at first impressive; Tirso but when
presented as the cause of the evils suffered and promise of eternal
punishment, womanly weakness gave the thrust of the believer.

What set her worst, was the threat of would talk to Pepe.

They kept silent for a moment: he, doubtful of the success of your business, she, embarrassed,
anxious to escape the violent influence of his son, to subdue it better, just say it: "I am but a
priest."

- Are we going to the pharmacy? - Finally dared to ask the mother.

- Wait for you, do not want us to separate well. You have to promise before the rescue. Will it
work You with me so that we are all Christians, and I understand I with Pepe and my father? Can
you imagine you live holy by not doing harm to others?

What blindness! What about yourself? What about your salvation?

Pray you, mother, this is the first, and God's light and remove them from your soul that apathy come
You to church, and little to awaken the good feelings, you will stop laughing antics sacrilegious
my brother, you shall burn with desire for help. Did you promise?

- Yes, my son - said embarrassed - but Pepe did not tell any of this.

- As I understand it is him who is to blame for what happens!

We agreed that you are mine, ie God, otherwise I will leave for good, after declaring openly
to all I do not want to live among Jews.

Slowly descended the stairs of the court, Tirso waited at the door of the shop and saw leaving
his mother with a bottle in his hand, said:

- Both care, such request to seek remedy for the ills of the body
that do not matter nothing and no one thought to the health of the
soul!

Remember what you just mentioned.

Then he left her, leaving her confused and frightened, a woman who's just been amazing committing
a crime. Sin, condemnation, impiety, had sounded in their ears how empty words, the warnings of
a Bossuet had not exercised in she most empire. What was left unnerved about the threat of her
husband and Pepe, safe that reduced Tirso counterclaim sour cause
a scene, perhaps a break and a grave disappointment. What could she
do about it</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>