<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>392546</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16357</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Aquella
señora daba las cosas por hechas discretamente, hablándole como á un yerno. Su mirada de bondad
tenía una expresión melancólica. Era la dulce tristeza de las personas maduras que ven monótono
el presente, medido el porvenir, y se refugian en los recuerdos del pasado, envidiando á las
jóvenes porque pueden gozar en la realidad lo que ellas sólo paladean con la memoria.

--¡Felices ustedes!... ¡Amense mucho!... Únicamente por el amor vale la vida la pena de ser vivida.

Y Freya, como si le enterneciesen de un modo irresistible estos consejos, avanzó un brazo sobre
los globos encorsetados de la doctora, apretando convulsivamente la diestra de Ulises.

Los lentes de oro, con su brillo protector, parecían incitarles á mayores intimidades. «Podían
besarse...» La imponente señora, para facilitar sus expansiones, iba á salir, alegando un pretexto
insignificante, cuando se levantó el cortinaje de la puerta que comunicaba el salón con la oficina.

Entró un hombre de la edad de Ferragut, pero más bajo de estatura, menos endurecido el rostro
por el curtimiento de la intemperie. Iba vestido á la inglesa, con escrupulosa corrección.
Se adivinaban en él las preocupaciones más nimias y pueriles en todo lo referente al adorno
de su persona. El traje, de lanilla gris, aparecía realzado por la unidad de la corbata, los
calcetines y el pañuelo asomado al bolsillo del pecho. Las tres prendas eran azules, sin la
más leve variación en su tono, escogidas con exactitud, como si este hombre pudiese sufrir
crueles molestias saliendo á la calle con la corbata de un color y los calcetines de otro.
Sus guantes tenían el mismo amarillo obscuro de sus zapatos.

Ferragut pensó que este gentleman, para ser completo, debía llevar el rostro afeitado. Y sin
embargo, usaba barba, una barba recortada á flor de piel en las mejillas y formando sobre el
mentón una punta corta y aguda. El capitán presintió que era un marino. En la flota alemana,
en la rusa, en todas las marinas del Norte, los oficiales que no iban rasurados á la inglesa
usaban esta barbilla tradicional.

Se inclinó, ó más bien dicho, se dobló en ángulo, con brusca rigidez, al besar las manos de
las dos señoras. Luego se llevó un monóculo de impertinente fijeza á uno de sus ojos, mientras
la doctora hacía las presentaciones.

--El conde Kaledine... El capitán Ferragut.

Dió la mano el conde al marino, una mano dura, bien cuidada y forzuda, que se mantuvo largo
rato sobre la de Ulises, queriendo dominarla con una presión sin afecto.

La conversación continuó en inglés, que era el idioma empleado por la doctora en sus relaciones
con Ulises.

--¿El señor es marino?--preguntó éste para aclarar sus dudas.

No se movió el monóculo de su órbita, pero un temblor ligero de sorpresa parecía rizar su luminosa
convexidad. La doctora se apresuró á responder:

--El conde es un diplomático ilustre que está ahora con licencia, cuidando su salud. Ha viajado
mucho, pero no es marino.

Y continuó sus explicaciones. Los Kaledine eran una noble familia rusa de tiempos de la gran
Catalina. La doctora, por ser polaca, estaba relacionada con ellos hacía muchos años... Y cesó
de hablar, dando entrada á Kaledine en la conversación.

Al principio el conde se mostró frío y algo desdeñoso en sus palabras, como si no pudiera despojarse
de su altivez diplomática. Pero lentamente esta altivez se fué fundiendo.

Conocía por su «distinguida amiga la señora Talberg» muchas de las aventuras náuticas de Ferragut.
A él le interesaban los hombres de acción, los héroes del Océano.

Ulises notó de pronto en su noble interlocutor un afecto caluroso, un deseo de agradar semejante
al de la doctora. ¡Hermosa casa aquella, en la que todos se esforzaban por hacerse simpáticos
al capitán Ferragut!

El conde, sonriendo amablemente, dejó de valerse del inglés, y le habló de pronto en español,
como si hubiese reservado este golpe final para acabar de captarse su afecto con el más irresistible
de los halagos.

--He vivido en Méjico--dijo para explicar su conocimiento de esta lengua--. He hecho un largo
viaje por las Filipinas cuando vivía en el Japón.

Los mares del Extremo Oriente eran los menos frecuentados por Ulises. Sólo dos veces había
navegado hacia los puertos chinos y nipones, pero conocía lo suficiente para mantener la conversación
con este viajero que mostraba en sus gustos cierto refinamiento de artista. Durante media hora
desfilaron por el vulgar ambiente del salón imágenes de enormes pagodas de techos superpuestos,
vibrantes á la brisa, como un arpa, con sus filas de campanillas; ídolos monstruosos tallados
en oro, en bronce ó en marfil; casas de papel, tronos de bambú, muebles de nacaradas incrustaciones,
biombos con filas de cigüeñas volantes.

Desapareció la doctora, aturdida por este diálogo, del que sólo podía adivinar algunas palabras.
Freya, inmóvil, con los ojos adormecidos y una rodilla entre sus manos cruzadas, se mantuvo
aparte, entendiendo la conversación, pero sin intervenir en ella, como si le ofendiese el olvido
en que la dejaban los dos hombres. Al fin se deslizó discretamente, siguiendo el llamamiento
de una mano asomada á un cortinaje. La doctora preparaba el té y pedía auxilio.

La conversación continuó, sin hacer alto en estas ausencias. Kaledine había abandonado los
mares asiáticos para pasar al Mediterráneo, y se anclaba en él con una insistencia admirativa.
Un motivo más de afecto para Ferragut, que lo encontraba cada vez más simpático, á pesar de
su trato un poco glacial.

Se dió cuenta repentinamente de que ya no era el conde ruso el que hablaba, pues con breves
y certeras preguntas le hacía hablar á él, lo mismo que si lo sometiese á un examen.

Agradeció las muestras de interés que este gran viajero daba por el pequeño mare nostrum, y
especialmente por las particularidades de su cuenca occidental, que deseaba conocer minuciosamente.

Podía preguntar cuanto quisiera. Ferragut poseía milla por milla todo el litoral español, el
francés y el italiano, así en la superficie como en sus fondos.

Kaledine, tal vez por vivir en Nápoles, insistió con predilección en la parte mediterránea
comprendida entre la Cerdeña, la Italia del Sur y la Sicilia, ó sea lo que los antiguos habían
llamado el mar Tirreno... ¿Conocía el capitán Ferragut las islas poco frecuentadas y casi perdidas
enfrente de Sicilia?

--Yo lo conozco todo--afirmó éste con orgullo.

Y sin discernir completamente si era curiosidad del conde ó si quería someterle á un examen
interesado, habló y habló.

Conocía el archipiélago de las islas Lípari, con sus minas de azufre y de piedra pómez, grupo
de cimas volcánicas que emergen de las profundidades del Mediterráneo. En ellas habían colocado
los antiguos á Eolo, señor de los vientos; en ellas está el Stromboli vomitando enormes bolas
de lava, que estallan con un estrépito de trueno. Las escorias volcánicas vuelven á caer en
las chimeneas del cráter ó ruedan por la pendiente de la montaña, sumiéndose en las olas.

Más al Oeste, aislada y solitaria en un mar limpio de escollos, está Ustica, una isla volcánica
y abrupta que colonizaron los fenicios y sirvió de refugio á los piratas sarracenos. Su población
es escasa y pobre. Nada hay que ver en ella, aparte de ciertas conchas fósiles que interesan
á los hombres de ciencia...

Pero el conde se sintió interesado por este cráter muerto y solitario en medio de un mar que
sólo frecuentan las barcas de pesca.

Ferragut había visto igualmente, aunque de lejos, al entrar en el puerto de Trápani, el archipiélago
de las Egades, donde existen grandes pesquerías de atunes. Había desembarcado una vez en la
isla Pantelaria, situada á medio camino entre Sicilia y África. Era un cono volcánico altísimo
que emergía en mitad del estrecho, y á cuyo pie existían lagos alcalinos, humaredas sulfurosas,
aguas termales y construcciones prehistóricas de grandes bloques, semejantes á las de Cerdeña
y las Baleares. Los buques que iban á Túnez y Trípoli tomaban cargamento de pasas, única exportación
de esta antigua colonia fenicia.

Entre la Panteleria y Sicilia, el suelo submarino se elevaba considerablemente, guardando sobre
su dorso una capa acuática que en algunos puntos sólo tenía doce metros de espesor. Era el
extenso banco llamado de la Aventura, hinchazón volcánica, doble isla anegada, pedestal submarino
de Sicilia.

También el banco de la Aventura pareció interesar al conde.

--Conoce usted bien su mar--dijo con tono de aprobación.

Ferragut iba á seguir hablando, pero entraron las dos señoras con una bandeja que contenía
el servicio de té y varios platos de pasteles. El capitán no extrañó esta falta de servidumbre.
La doctora y su amiga eran para él unas mujeres de costumbres extraordinarias, y todos sus
actos los encontraba lógicos y naturales. Freya sirvió el té con una gracia púdica, como si
fuese la hija de la casa.

Pasaron el resto de la tarde conversando sobre lejanos viajes. Nadie aludió á la guerra ni
á las preocupaciones de Italia en aquel momento por mantener su neutralidad ó salir de ella.
Parecían vivir en un lugar inaccesible, á miles de leguas de todo tropel humano.

Las dos mujeres trataban al conde con una familiaridad de buen tono, como personas de su mismo
mundo; pero el marino creyó notar en ciertos momentos que le tenían miedo.

Al terminar la tarde, este personaje abandonó su asiento, y Ferragut hizo lo mismo, comprendiendo
que debía poner fin á su visita. El conde se ofreció á acompañarle. Mientras se despedía de
la doctora, agradeciendo con extremos corteses que le hubiese hecho conocer al capitán, éste
sintió que Freya le apretaba la mano de modo significativo.

--Hasta la noche--murmuró levemente, sin mover apenas los labios--. Volveré tarde... Espérame.

¡Oh, dicha!... Los ojos, la sonrisa, la presión de la mano, decían para él mucho más.

Nunca dió un paseo tan agradable como al marchar al lado de Kaledine por las calles de Chiaia
hacia la ribera. ¿Qué decía aquel hombre?... Cosas insignificantes para evitar el silencio,
pero á él le parecieron observaciones de profunda sabiduría. Su voz era, según él, armoniosa
y acariciadora. Todo lo encontraba igualmente amable, la gente que transitaba por las calles,
el ruido napolitano del anochecer, el mar obscuro, la vida entera.

Se despidieron ante la puerta del hotel. El conde, á pesar de sus ofrecimientos de amistad,
se fué sin decirle cuál era su domicilio.

«No importa--pensó Ferragut--. Volveremos á encontrarnos en casa de la doctora.»

El resto de la velada lo pasó agitado alternativamente por la esperanza y la impaciencia. No
quería comer; la emoción había paralizado su apetito... Y una vez sentado á la mesa, comió
más que nunca, con una avidez maquinal y distraída.

Necesitaba pasear, hablar con alguien, para que transcurriese el tiempo con mayor rapidez,
engañando su inquieta espera. Ella no volvería al hotel hasta muy tarde... Y precisamente se
retiró á su habitación más temprano que de costumbre, creyendo, con un ilogismo supersticioso,
que de este modo llegaría antes Freya.

Su primer movimiento al verse en su cuarto fué de orgullo. Miró al techo, apiadándose del marino
enamorado que una semana antes habitaba el piso superior. ¡Pobre hombre! ¡Cómo se habían reído
de él!... Ulises se admiró á sí mismo como una personalidad completamente nueva, feliz y triunfadora,
separado de la otra por un período doloroso de humillaciones y fracasos que no quería recordar.

¡Las horas larguísimas del que aguarda con ansiedad!... Se paseó fumando, encendiendo un cigarro
en el resto del anterior. Luego abrió la ventana, queriendo borrar este perfume de tabaco fuerte.
Ella sólo gustaba de los cigarrillos orientales... Y como persistiese el acre olor del cigarro
habano, jugoso y bravío, rebuscó en su maletín de aseo, derramando sobre la cama el fondo de
varios frascos de esencia largo tiempo olvidados.

Una repentina inquietud amargó su espera. La que iba á llegar ignoraba tal vez cuál era su
habitación. El no estaba seguro de haberle dado las señas con suficiente claridad. Era posible
que se hubiese equivocado... Empezó á creer que, efectivamente, se había equivocado.

El miedo y la impaciencia le hicieron abrir su puerta, plantándose en el corredor para mirar
de lejos el cerrado cuarto de Freya. Cada vez que sonaban pasos en la escalera ó chirriaba
la verja del ascensor, el barbudo marino se estremecía con una inquietud infantil. Deseaba
esconderse y al mismo tiempo quería mirar, por si era ella la que llegaba.

Los huéspedes que vivían en el mismo piso le fueron viendo, al retirarse á sus cuartos, en
las más inexplicables actitudes. Unas veces permanecía firme en el corredor, como el que espera
á los domésticos, fatigado por inútiles llamamientos. Otras veces le sorprendían con la cabeza
asomada á la puerta entreabierta, retirándola precipitadamente. Un viejo conde italiano le
dirigió al pasar una sonrisa de inteligencia y compañerismo... ¡Estaba en el secreto! Aguardaba,
indudablemente, á una de las doncellas del hotel.

Acabó por meterse en la habitación, pero dejando la puerta abierta... Un rectángulo de viva
luz que se marcaba en el suelo y la pared de enfrente guiaría á Freya, indicándole el camino.

Tampoco pudo mantener mucho tiempo esta señal. Damas mal tapadas con un kimono, señores en
pijama, se deslizaban por el pasillo discretamente sobre la suavidad silenciosa de sus pantuflas,
todos en la misma dirección, lanzando una ojeada de cólera hacia la puerta luminosa que sorprendía
el secreto de sus miserias corporales.

Por fin tuvo que cerrar la puerta. Abrió un libro, y le fué imposible leer dos párrafos seguidos.
Su reloj marcaba las doce.

--¡No vendrá!... ¡no vendrá!--dijo con desesperación.

Una idea nueva le sirvió de alivio. Era imposible que una persona discreta como Freya se atreviese
á avanzar hasta su cuarto viendo luz por debajo de la puerta. El amor necesita obscuridad y
misterio. Además, esta espera visible podía atraer el espionaje de algún curioso.

Dió vuelta al conmutador eléctrico y buscó en la obscuridad su lecho, tendiéndose con un ruido
exagerado, para que nadie pudiese dudar de que se acostaba. Esta lobreguez reanimó su esperanza.

--Va á venir... Llegará de un momento á otro.

Otra vez se levantó cautelosamente, sin ningún ruido, yendo de puntillas. Había que facilitar
las dificultades de la entrada. Dejó la puerta entreabierta levemente, para evitar el ruido
giratorio del picaporte. Una silla mantuvo su hoja apoyada con suavidad en el marco del quicio.

Todavía se levantó varias veces, despojándose en cada uno de estos saltos de una parte de sus
vestidos. Así aguardaría mejor.

Se estiró sobre el lecho, dispuesto á permanecer en vela toda la coche si era preciso. No debía
dormir; no quería dormir; lo ordenaba su voluntad... Y media hora después dormía profundamente,
sin saber en qué momento se había dejado rodar por las blandas laderas del sueño.

Despertó de pronto, como si le hubiesen asestado un mazazo en el cráneo. Los oídos le zumbaban...
Era la brusca impresión del que se duerme sin deseo de dormir y se siente sacudido por la inquietud
resucitadora. Tardó unos instantes en darse cuenta de su situación. Luego lo recordó todo de
golpe... ¡Solo!... ¡Ella no había llegado!... Ignoraba si iban transcurridos minutos ú horas.

Otra cosa, además de la inquietud, le había vuelto á la vida. Adivinó en la silenciosa obscuridad
algo real que se acercaba. Un pequeño ratón parecía moverse en el corredor. Los zapatos colocados
ante una de las puertas resbalaron con leve chirrido. Ferragut percibió una vaga impresión
de aire que se desplaza con el lento avance de un cuerpo.

Se movió la puerta; la silla retrocedió poco á poco, suavemente empujada. En la obscuridad
fué marcándose una sombra móvil, mucho más negra y densa. El hizo un movimiento.

--¡Quieto!--suspiró una voz tenue, de fantasma, una voz del otro mundo--. Soy yo.

Pero Ferragut había saltado cama abajo, avanzando las manos en la sombra. Tropezó con unos
brazos desnudos y mórbidos, luego con la frescura suave de una carne envuelta en velos.

Instintivamente llevó su diestra á la pared, y se hizo la luz.

Bajo la lámpara eléctrica estaba ella, una Freya distinta á la que había visto siempre, con
los cabellos opulentos cayendo en sierpes sobre sus hombros, completamente desnuda en el interior
de una túnica asiática que la envolvía como una nube.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07947</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>490779</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14590</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> That lady
was quietly made things, speaking as a son. His look of kindness had a melancholy expression. It
was the sweet sadness of older people that are monotonous This measured the future, and take refuge
in the memories of the past, I envy the young people because they can enjoy in reality what
they savored only in memory.

- Blessed are you! ... Love one a lot! ... Only love is worth the life is worth living.

And Freya, as if irresistibly softened to the above, and moved an arm corseted balloons to the
doctor, pressing convulsively the right hand of Ulysses.

The lenses of gold, with its brightness protector, seemed to encourage them to greater intimacy.
"They could kissing ... "The impressive lady, to facilitate its expansion, was about to leave,
citing a pretext insignificant, when it lifted the curtain of the door between the room with
the office.

A man entered the age of Ferragut, but lower in height, less hardened face tanning by the weather.
He was dressed to the English with scrupulous correctness. Hinted at in the most trivial and
childish concerns at all about the trim of person.

The suit, gray flannel, appeared enhanced by the unity of the tie, socks and handkerchief overlooking
the breast pocket. The three pieces were blue, with no slightest variation in tone, chosen with
precision, as if this man could suffer cruel now out into the street with a color tie and socks
in another. Her gloves had the same dark yellow of his shoes.

Ferragut felt that this gentleman, to be complete, should bring his face shaved. And however,
wore a beard, a beard to the surface of the cheeks and forming the chin short and sharp tip. The
captain felt he was a sailor.

In the German fleet in Russian, in all North Sea, the officers were
not shaved to the English used this traditional chin.

He bowed, or better said, bent at an angle, with sudden stiffness, kissing hands the two ladies.
Then he took a monocle impertinent fixity to one of his eyes, while
Dr. made the presentations.

- Count Kaledine ... Captain Ferragut.

Count shook hands with the sailor, a tough, well maintained and strong
that remained long while on the Ulysses, wanting to dominate with
a pressure no affection.

The conversation continued in English, which was the language used by the doctor in their relations
with Ulysses.

- "The Lord is ocean? - He asked for clarification.

Monocle not moved in its orbit, but a slight tremor of surprise seemed to ruffle his luminous convexity.
The doctor was quick to respond:

- The Count is a distinguished diplomat who is now on leave, caring for your health. He has traveled
much, but it is not marine.

He continued his explanation.

The Kaledine were a noble Russian family of great times Catalina. The doctor, being Polish, I
was connected with them for many years ... And stopped speak, giving
entrance to Kaledine in the conversation.

At first the count was cold and somewhat cavalier in his words, as if he could shed of diplomatic
arrogance. But this pride went slowly melting.

Known for his "distinguished friend Mrs. Talberg" many of the nautical adventures Ferragut. He wanted
to know the men of action, the heroes of the ocean.

Ulises suddenly noticed his noble interlocutor warm affection, such a desire to please to the doctor.
Beautiful home that, in which all strove to be sympathetic Captain Ferragut!

The count, smiling graciously, left to fend English, and he suddenly spoke in Spanish, as if
he had booked this final blow to finish captured his affection with the most irresistible of flattery.

-
I lived in Mexico - said to explain his knowledge of the language -. I made a long trip to
the Philippines when I lived in Japan.

The seas of the Far East were the least frequented by Ulysses. Only twice had Chinese sailed
to ports and Nipponese, but knew enough to keep the conversation
with this flyer showing some sophistication in his tastes as an artist.

For half an hour paraded through the lounge atmosphere of vulgar images of huge roof pagodas
overlapping vibrating in the breeze, like a harp, with its rows of
bells, idols carved monstrous in gold, bronze or ivory paper houses,
bamboo thrones, furniture inlaid mother of pearl, screens with rows
of cranes flying.

Dr. disappeared, stunned by this dialogue, which could only guess at some words. Freya, still, with
the sleepy eyes and a knee between his hands crossed, he kept addition,
understanding the conversation, but without intervening in it, as
if offended oblivion in which the two men left.

Finally he slipped quietly, following the call leaning a hand to
a curtain.

The doctor prepared the tea and asked for help.

The conversation continued without a halt in these absences. Kaledine had abandoned the Asian
seas to go to the Mediterranean, it was anchored to an insistence admiration. Another reason of
affection for Ferragut, who was increasingly sympathetic, notwithstanding her try a little ice
age.

Suddenly realized that was not the Russian count who spoke, as with brief and accurate questions
made him speak to him, as if he is subjected to review.

Appreciated the expressions of interest that this great traveler gave
the small mare nostrum, and especially by the particularities of its
western basin, which wanted to know thoroughly.

Could ask how I wanted. Ferragut had mile by mile all the Spanish coast, the French and Italian, and
on the surface and in its funds.

Kaledine, perhaps to live in Naples, insisted on the Mediterranean predilection between Sardinia,
Southern Italy and Sicily, or is what the ancients called the Tyrrhenian Sea ... Did you know
Captain Ferragut islands unfrequented and almost forgotten across from Sicily?

- I know everything - he said proudly.

And fully discern whether it was curiosity or if the count would be subject to a review concerned,
talked and talked.

He knew the Lipari archipelago, with its mining of sulfur and pumice, group of volcanic peaks
rising from the depths of the Mediterranean. They were placed the former to Aeolus, god of the
winds in them is throwing huge balls Stromboli lava, bursting with a roar of thunder. The
volcanic scoria fall back into the chimneys of the crater or roll down the slope of the mountain
sinking into the waves.

Further west, isolated and lonely in a sea clear of obstacles, is Ustica, a volcanic island and
abrupt that the Phoenicians settled and served as a refuge for pirates
Saracen.

Its population is scarce and poor. Nothing to do with it, apart from some fossil shells of interest
to men of science ...

But the count was interested in this crater, dead and alone in the middle of a sea only frequent
the fishing boats.

Ferragut had seen also, although by far, entering the port of Trapani,
the archipelago of Egadi where large tuna fisheries.

Once he landed in Pantelleria island, midway between Sicily and Africa.

He was a towering volcanic cone emerging in the middle of the strait, and at whose feet were alkaline
lakes, sulphurous smoke, hot springs and prehistoric building blocks, like those of Sardinia
and the Balearics. Ships to Tunis and Tripoli were taking shipment of raisins, only export of
this ancient Phoenician colony.

Between Pantelleria and Sicily, the sea floor rose considerably, saving on its back a water
layer at some points was only twelve feet thick.

Was extensive bank called the Adventure, swelling volcanic island
flooded twice, submarine pedestal Sicily.

Also, the bank appeared to interest the Count Aventura.

- Well you
know the sea - said in a tone of approval.

Ferragut was going to keep talking, but the two ladies entered with a tray containing service area
and various dishes of cakes.

The captain was no surprise that lack of bondage. The doctor and his friend were to him a women
of extraordinary ways, and all the actions was logical and natural. Freya served tea with modest
grace, as if was the daughter of the house.

They spent the rest of the afternoon talking on distant voyages. No one mentioned the war or to the
concerns of Italy at that time to maintain their neutrality or leave it. Seemed to live in a place
inaccessible to thousands of miles around the human throng.

The two women tried to count, with a familiarity of tone, as persons
of the same world, but the sailor thought he noticed at times that
you were afraid.

By late afternoon, this person left his seat, and Ferragut did the
same, comprising that would put an end to his visit.

The count offered to accompany him. While saying goodbye the doctor, thanking him with extreme
courtesy would have made known to the captain, he Freya felt squeezed his hand significantly.

-
After Dark - mumbled slightly, without moving his lips barely -. Come back later ... Wait.

Oh,
joy! ... The eyes, the smile, the pressure of the hand, saying to
him more.

Never got a ride as nice as they marched alongside Kaledine through the streets of Chiaia toward
the shore. What did this man? ... Little things to keep silence, but he seemed to observations
of deep wisdom. His voice was, he said, harmonious and caressing. Everything was just lovely, the
people walking the streets, Neapolitan noise dark, dark sea, the
whole life.

They parted at the door of the hotel. The count, in spite of his offers of friendship, went
without saying what their home.

"No matter - thought Ferragut -.

Return home to find the doctor. "

The rest of the evening was spent alternately agitated by hope and
impatience.

No I wanted to eat, the emotion had paralyzed his appetite ... And once seated at table, ate More
than ever, with an eagerness mechanical and distracted.

I needed to walk, talk to someone, for the passage of time more quickly, deceiving his restless
waiting.

She did not return to the hotel until very late ... And precisely
retired to his room earlier than usual, thinking, with an illogical
superstitious that this would come before Freya.

His first movement was seen in his room with pride. Looked at the
ceiling, pitying the ocean love that one week before lived upstairs.

Poor man! How they had laughed it! ... Odysseus himself was admired as a completely new personality,
happy and successful, separated from each other by a painful period
of humiliations and failures did not want to remember.

Very long hours of anxiously awaiting! ... Paced smoking, lighting
a cigarette in the rest of the former.

He opened the window, wanting to erase the scent of strong snuff. She just liked oriental cigarettes
... And the acrid smell persists cigar Tan, juicy and brave, reached into his bag of toiletries, spilling
onto the bed fund several bottles of essence long forgotten.

A sudden concern bitter waiting. Which was about to reach what was perhaps unaware of their room.
He was not sure giving him the address with sufficient clarity. It was possible that would have been
wrong ... Began to believe that indeed he was wrong.

The fear and impatience made him open his door, standing on the porch to watch by far the closed
room Freya. Every time I sounded on the stairs creaked or lift gate,
the bearded sailor shook a child concern.

Wanted hide and at the same time wanted to look, if she was coming.

Guests who lived on the same floor you were seeing, to retire to their
quarters, the most inexplicable attitudes.

Sometimes he stood firm in the corridor, such as waiting to the home,
tired of futile appeals.

Other times I caught his head appear at the door ajar, withdrawing abruptly. An elderly Italian
count him went to pass a smile of intelligence and companionship ... I was in the secret! Waiting,
Undoubtedly, one of the maids of the hotel.

Finally get into the
room, but leaving the door open ... A rectangle of deep light that
is marked on the ground and the opposite wall would lead to Freya,
indicating the road.

Nor could he long maintain this signal. Ladies
badly covered with a kimono, lords pajamas, slipped quietly down the
hall on the quiet softness of her slippers, all in the same direction,
casting a look of anger toward the door, surprising light the secret
of their bodily misery.

Finally had to close the door. Opened a book,
and it was impossible to read two paragraphs in a row. Your clock
struck twelve.

- Do not come! ... Will not come! - Said in despair.

A
new idea served as a relief. It was impossible for one person dared
discreet as Freya to advance to his room watching light under the
door. Love needs dark and mystery. In addition, the expected visible
espionage could attract some curious.

He turned the power switch
in the dark and sought his bed, lying with a noise exaggerated, so
that nobody could doubt that he slept. This gloom revived their hopes.

-
Is coming ... Come from one moment to another.

Again got up cautiously,
without noise, tiptoeing. Had to provide difficulties in the entrance.
He left the door slightly ajar to prevent noise rotary knob. A chair
held his blade gently supported under the doorway.

Still got up several
times, shedding in each of these jumps from one part of their dresses.
So await better.

He stretched on the bed, ready to stay awake all
car if necessary. Should not sleeping, not wanting to sleep so ordered
his will ... Half an hour later asleep, without knowing what time
was left by the soft rolling hills of sleep.

He awoke suddenly, as
if he had been dealt a blow to the skull. His ears were ringing ...
It was a sharp impression of that desire to sleep without sleeping
and feel shaken by concerns resuscitator. It took a while to realize
their situation. Then I remembered all of blow ... Solo! ... She had
not come! ... Knew if they went after minutes or hours.

Another thing,
besides the concern, had returned to life. Guessed in the silent darkness
something approaching real. A little mouse seemed to move in the corridor.
Shoes positioned at one of the doors slid with a slight squeak. Ferragut
felt a vague impression air that moves with the slow progress of a
body.

Moved the door, the seat back gradually, gently pushed. In
the dark Moving Shadow was making a much more black and dense. He
made a movement.

- Stop! - Sighed a faint voice, a ghost, a voice
from another world -. Me.

But Ferragut had jumped down bed, moving
his hands in the shade. He stumbled over some morbid bare arms, then
with the soft freshness of meat wrapped in veils.

Instinctively brought
his right hand to the wall, and there was light.

Under the electric
lamp she was, a different Freya he had ever seen, with opulent hair
falling into serpents on his shoulders, completely naked inside an
Asian robe enveloped in a cloud</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>