<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03750</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>367524</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24050</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Y no sabía ya lo que en él podía ver, o lo que es peor, temía saber demasiado.
¡Florencia se había dado la muerte! ¡No había tenido miedo del juicio de Dios! No había pensado
en la salvación de su alma, no había creído en su vida futura: se había matado porque todo
acaba en la muerte.

«Entonces, ¿nada existe, nada?...»

La pregunta de la muerta quedaba sin respuesta, desoída.

Por la sola virtud de la vista de su amada, Vérod había mirado, había oído, comprendido el
alma del mundo: voces misteriosas le habían dicho cosas memorables; todo vivía, palpitaba y
relucía. Pero, después el silencio y la obscuridad volvían a aglomerarse en torno suyo. Lo
que antes tenía un sentido evidente o recóndito permanecía mudo.

Tan profunda y sincera había sido su conversión, que a veces se sentía iluminado por lampos
de la antigua fe; pero luego lo rodeaban nuevamente las tinieblas más espesas. Y en la alternativa
de la duda, encontraba otra vez con mudo y desesperado terror, a su otro yo, al hombre de tiempos
pasados que creía haber sepultado ya dentro de sí mismo. Como antes de haber conocido a la
Condesa, su pensamiento era obscuro, confuso, se perdía. La milagrosa florescencia que había
brotado de todos los pliegues de su alma se marchitaba y deshacía. En otros tiempos, su corazón,
cerrado a todos se complacía en su propia avidez; pero una vez que ya había recibido la simiente,
se sentía amargado por un rencor infinito.

El joven resolvió viajar. Vio otras tierras, otros hombres, esperando dejar su dolor a lo largo
de los caminos del mundo; pero nada fue suficiente para calmarlo. En Niza, delante de la tumba
de su hermana, lloró ardientes lágrimas que lejos de extinguir el fuego lo reanimaron. Al lago
no había vuelto: un mortal pavor lo invadía al pensar que iba a ver otra vez los únicos lugares
donde pudiera decir que realmente hubiera vivido. Temía morir ahogado por la pena al ver las
playas de Ouchy, las cuestas de Lausana, la villa Cyclamens, el bosque de Comte, las humildes
capillas, el panorama del Leman velado por las nubes y sonriente a, la luz del sol.

Por fin, un día fue. Encontró esos lugares tal cual los había dejado. La impasibilidad de la
eterna Naturaleza lo lastimó como un insulto: si al menos algo hubiera sido destruido en la
tierra; si al menos hubiera visto en su derredor los rastros de una devastación parecida a
la que él sentía en su interior.

Los montes seculares, las aguas perennes, voraces sepulcros de seres vivientes, permanecían
inmutables. El joven iba reconociendo cada punto del camino, cada pormenor de la perspectiva.
Tenía la desesperada certidumbre de que ningún poder habría podido jamás realizar el milagro
de devolverle lo que había perdido, y sin embargo volvía en torno suyo la mirada, y aguzaba
el oído, como si una aparición, una voz, pudieran de improviso evocar el bien perdido.

Y una tarde que desde una ventana de su cuarto contemplaba las cumbres del Dôle, detrás de
las cuales descendía radiosamente el sol, se estremeció al oír una voz que hablaba detrás de él.

¿Era una alucinación? ¿No soñaba despierto?

El Príncipe Alejo Zakunine estaba en su presencia.

--Roberto Vérod--decía la voz--¿no me reconoce usted?

Una especie de escalofrío le sacudió los nervios: creía estar viendo un espectro.

¿Qué quería con él ese hombre? ¿Por qué iba a buscarle?

--¿Sabe usted quién soy? ¡Pero no me esperaba usted! He venido a verle porque tengo algo que
decirle.

Hablaba con la cabeza baja, humildemente. Vista de arriba, desde la frente en extremo espaciosa
hasta la punta de la barba, la cara parecía toda surcada de profundas arrugas. Los cabellos,
ya muy raros, estaban blancos junto a las sienes. Toda su persona llevaba impresa las señales
de una rápida decadencia.

Vérod le contemplaba como fascinado, incapaz de contestarle una sola palabra, de ver claro
en el tumulto de sentimientos que se desencadenaban en su alma.

--Tengo que decir a usted una cosa. Quería decirla al juez Ferpierre; pero he pensado que mejor
era dirigirme primero a usted...

Y después de una pausa, añadió:

--Óigame usted, Vérod: Florencia d'Arda no se mató. Yo la asesiné.

El joven se pasó una mano por la frente, por los ojos. Otra vez, más aún que en el primer instante,
estaba inseguro de hallarse despierto.

--¿No me cree, usted? ¡Y, sin embargo, usted estuvo tan cerca de la verdad! Yo sé que usted
la afirmó contra todo y todos, y poco faltó para que consiguiera demostrarla. Cierto es que
muchas circunstancias, una principalmente, estuvieron, en contra de usted. La carta de sor
Ana, parecía decir la última palabra sobre la suerte de la Condesa. Lo que engañó a la justicia
fue que cuando yo la maté se hallaba verdaderamente decidida a darse la muerte. Voy a decir
a usted cómo la maté...

Vérod temblaba como sacudido por la fiebre.

--Voy a referir a usted mi infamia: éste será el principio del castigo. Nunca conocí lo que
valía. Jamás, mientras vivió, comprendí la hermosura de su alma. Ninguna belleza era comprensible
para mí: el mundo y la vida me parecían desprovistos de esa cualidad. Tenía dentro de mí un
infierno, nada podía apagar la llama que me devoraba. Todo cuanto yo tocaba quedaba reducido
a cenizas. Ella me amó por compasión: el instinto, la necesidad, la voluptuosidad del sacrificio
me la entregaron. Y aunque no la comprendí, por un momento me sentí deslumbrado por su luz.
No pude soportar su claridad, y aparté la vista. Y me burlé de ella y la ofendí.

Se calló un momento, la vista fija delante de sí, cual si estuviera ciego, y luego prosiguió:

--Óigame usted. Cuando le haya dicho todo, comprenderá usted que mis palabras merecen fe. En
los primeros tiempos de mi dicha me sentí otro. La Naturaleza y la vida habían hecho que fuera
condición mía el pasar de un sentimiento al otro con fulmínea violencia. Los que saben lo que
yo he hecho en el mundo podrán pensar que a veces me guió quizá la voz del bien. Pero yo no
tenía conciencia. Si dentro de mí juzgaba mis acciones y las de los demás, todo se reducía
a un mecanismo, a un juego de impulsos ciegos y fatales. Yo no podía, por lo tanto, creer en
el cambio que se había operado en mí por su virtud. No me burlé solamente de ella, también
me reí de mí mismo...

Debería decir a usted cual fue, día por día, hora, por hora, mi obra espantosa; cómo, a su
constante, infatigable, divina prédica de amor y su bondad opuse el desprecio, el insulto,
la traición. Pero usted sabe todo esto. Y luego, y luego...

Todo cuanto sugería a usted su odio hacia mí era demasiado poco: lo que yo le hice es increíble.
A veces, cuando con palabras envenenadas y corrosivas profanaba, vilipendiaba, destruía su
fe; cuando le demostraba que nada existe fuera del mal; que los únicos remedios son el hierro,
el fuego, la muerte; cuando la incitaba a dejarme, a traicionarme, a perderse, sentía operarse
en mi interior una reacción violenta, y el llanto me acudía a los ojos. Pero yo ocultaba mis
lágrimas.

Cuando usted la conoció, cuando comprendí que ella comenzaba a amarle, mi pecho se dilató de
gozo. Ver que su decantada eternidad de sentimientos flaqueaba; prever que iba a caer como
caen todas; poder decirla:--¿Ya ves? ¿Dónde están tus leyes morales? ¡Tú también haces como
las demás, lo que te place!--era algo que me colmaba de júbilo...

Mientras tanto yo me entregaba completamente, había incitado a la acción a los pusilánimes,
a en mi país y en los demás. La última tentativa me parecía destinada a prosperar; ya saboreaba
el triunfo. Todo lo había preparado detenidamente, había incitado a la acción a los pusilánimes,
a los vacilantes, a los miedosos, y entregado casi todo cuanto quedaba de mis bienes sin pensar
en las dificultades que encontraría más tarde.

Mi deber era entrar yo también en acción, y hube de partir con ese objeto, pero me vi obligado
a quedarme a preparar una nueva acción para el caso de un revés. Y un día supe que mis hermanos
habían sido muertos, pendían de las horcas que caían en los caminos que conducen a los destierros,
bajo la férula de los esbirros; supe que las mujeres, que las niños subían al patíbulo; que
tantos inocentes sufrían en mi lugar; que el temor reinaba sobre toda la gente de mi raza...

Ese día me encontré, en presencia de tanta ruina, con el temor de haber equivocado el camino,
solo y casi pobre. Entonces, de improviso, surgió dentro de mi corazón algo como una necesidad,
como una ansia, como una sed ardiente de socorro; entonces llegué casi a extender la mano para
encontrar a mi lado un apoyo, casi me prosterné a escuchar una palabra de consuelo...

El ser que podía consolarme existía: no habría tenido otra cosa que hacer que ir en su busca,
que abrirle mi corazón. Quizás habría sido aún tiempo. O quizás no: ya era demasiado tarde...

¡Demasiado tarde! ¿Sabe usted lo que estas palabras significan?... Un impulso de soberbia me
detuvo. ¿Habría yo de suplicar? Y, sin embargo, me daba cuenta de que nada en aquella crisis
de mi vida habría podido curarme como el amor de una criatura como esa.

Volví a su lado, pero nada le dije. Mi actitud debía demostrar, sin embargo, lo que ocurría
en mi interior. ¡Demasiado tarde!... Podemos sufrir y aceptar el sufrimiento; podemos desesperar
y vivir en la desesperación, pero ante la idea de que la felicidad hubiera sido para nosotros;
de que la fortuna ha pasado a nuestro lado; de que para obtenerla sólo teníamos que extender
la mano, que decir una palabra, y que hemos retirado la mano, y proferido--¡demasiado tarde!--la
palabra; ante esa idea el corazón cesó de latir...

Ya ella no era mía: era de usted, y cuando adquirí esta certidumbre, comencé nuevamente a reír
y a burlarme. Huí de ella, pero tuve que volver a su lado; aun cuando me mostraba arrepentido
y convertido, no me pesaba la sujeción: lejos de ella no podía vivir. Así transcurrieron los
últimos meses, alternando mis huidas con breves regresos. A Zurich iba para hablar de ella
a otra infeliz, a Alejandra. Alejandra Natzichet ha muerto...

Vérod estaba aturdido. No, no soñaba; pero la realidad tenía todos los caracteres del sueño.
El hombre que hablaba en su presencia se parecía a aquel orgulloso revolucionario como las
pálidas imágenes de una pesadilla se parecen a las personas vivas. ¿Muerta la Natzichet? ¿Cómo,
por qué había muerto? Hasta la hora y la luz eran poco naturales: el amarillento crepúsculo
alumbraba de manera extraña la habitación, las cosas, el rostro escuálido del Príncipe.

--Confiaba mi tormento a Alejandra, ¡y Alejandra me amaba, sin que yo lo notara siquiera! La
vida lo ha querido así: ¡que nuestras almas, que estos cuatro seres se hayan encontrado para
sufrir un dolor inefable, y que ninguno supiera lo que el otro sufría, o lo supiera siempre
demasiado tarde! Yo profesaba a Alejandra un afecto fraternal: la soledad en que se encontraba
sumida, su entereza, que la hacía capaz de soportar y vencer las dificultades de la vida, me
inclinaron a protegerla, a sostenerla como a una hermana, como a una hija; ¡pero ella me quiso
con un afecto más ardiente! Y aunque yo me hubiera dado cuenta de su amor, ¿habría podido hacerla
feliz? ¡Sólo a ella podía confiar mi pasión por la otra!...

Alejandra trató de curarme llamándome al deber de servir la causa: quise escucharla, pero en
vano. La idea de reconquistar el amor que antes desdeñara, embargaba y dirigía mi vida entera.
Después de haberlo desdeñado, atribuía a ese amor un precio inestimable. ¡Era justo!...

Nada de esto decía a Florencia: las veces que venía a verla, me pasaba los días temblando de
descubrir que, así como había dejado de ser mía en el alma, se hubiera entregado ya a usted.
Para no creer en esa horrible cosa, me decía: «¡Piensa con tanta elevación, que nunca lo hará!»
Y una voz interior me contestaba: «¿Ahora crees en aquella altura moral de que antes te reías?»
Sí, antes me reía. ¡Y todavía no creía en ella!

Mi confianza en que no me traicionara no se fundaba tanto en la estima en que tenía su carácter,
cuanto en la imposibilidad de creer que todo hubiera terminado irremediablemente entre nosotros.
Veía que mi vuelta y mi arrepentimiento la producían una ansiedad mortal, y me halagaba la
esperanza de recuperarla...

¡Estar a su lado y no poder tomarle la mano! ¡Recordar lo pasado y desesperar de vivir otra
vez una sola de sus horas!... ¡Tanto como pasaba por mí, y nada podía decir! La soberbia me
contenía aún y también otro motivo menos mezquino. Yo me encontraba ya en la pobreza, ella
era rica: ¿hablarle de mi amor, no podía ser una mentira sugerida por el cálculo?...

Un día hablé. La dije:

--Te he perdido, he querido perderte: siento que mi culpa es irreparable. ¡Pero si tú supieras
lo que pasa dentro de mí! Te pido por favor que no me abandones en este momento en que todo
se derrumba en torno mío. Más tarde harás lo que quieras...

Ese mismo día, el día de la tempestad había hablado usted también. Estrechada entre nuestras
dos pasiones, resolvió morir. La respuesta que me dio fue:

--Nunca le abandonaré porque soy su esposa; pero acuérdese usted de que nuestro amor ha muerto.

Su acento era frío, su mirada evitaba encontrarse con la mía.

Cuando comprendí que también usted había hablado, se me ocurrió que no era sincera, pensé que
me ocultaba algo. Pero lo que temía era que hubiera resuelto huir; no creía que tuviera la
decisión de morir: ¡aun no la conocía!...

Pasé una noche tremenda. Ella también la pasó en vela. Cien veces, mil, quise ir a buscarla,
pero su puerta me estaba vedada. Por la mañana vino Alejandra a buscarme, a llamarme, con la
intuición de una catástrofe. La prometí partir, pero antes quise ver por última vez a Florencia.

Al oírme entrar en su cuarto escondió precipitadamente algo. Vi que era el arma.

Al tal punto se sentía oprimida entre nuestras dos pasiones, que quería morir para libertarse...
Comprendí que yo no tenía derecho de hablar, de haberme introducido en su habitación; que debía
dejarla entregada a su destino, a la libertad, a la muerte, pero no podía. La idea de que entre
dos seres que habían sido el uno del otro no existiera ya nada, nada; de que yo era peor que
un extraño para ella, no encontraba cabida en mi mente. Y la voz secreta me decía: «Antes,
tú creías que el amor fuera el encuentro fugaz de dos caprichos, antes te reías de los lazos
indisolubles...»

Yo no podía admitir que perteneciera a otro, aun cuando no fuera más que con el pensamiento.
Yo, que la había traicionado, no podía admitir el ser traicionado a mi vez. Mi soberbia era
ilimitada, no toleraba que alguien valiese más que yo. Y como comprendía que usted habría sabido
hacerla feliz, la soberbia, el amor, los celos, todas las pasiones, todos los instintos de
mi raza, de mi naturaleza, se sublevaban amenazadores.

--¡Tú me prometiste ayer--la dije con acento amargo--que no me dejarías, porque eres mi esposa,
y ahora quieres matarte!...

Ella no lo negó.

--Déjame morir--fue su respuesta;--eso será mejor para todos.

En su voz había algo que no conocía: su amor por usted, el rencor de tener que abandonar la
felicidad que se prometía con usted.

--¿De modo que ya no puedes tolerar mi vista? ¿Tanto te horrorizo?

La dije estas palabras, y muchas, muchas otras.

Ella me respondió únicamente:.

--¿De quién es la culpa?

--Óigame usted: este era el primer reproche que me dirigía después de tantos meses de dolor.

--Pues bien--la repliqué,--yo desapareceré: partiré hoy mismo, dentro de un momento y nunca
volverás a verme. ¿Quieres morir, sin embargo?

--Sí--me dijo.

Tuve miedo de comprender, pero, no obstante, la pregunté:

--¿Por qué?

Sus palabras, nada me dijeron que yo no supiera ya.

--Porque si vivo seré suya.

¡Suya, de usted, de otro!...

Una llamarada me subió a los ojos y a la frente.

--¡Eso no es posible, no sucederá!...

Ella movió la cabeza.

--¡No digas que no!--insistí.--¡No digas que no!... Ya sé que no me amas, que me odias, que
me execras; pero no me digas, que amas a otro, porque... porque...

--Le amo--dijo.

Entonces la supliqué, hasta lloré. Ella repitió:

--Le amo. No se debe mentir. Yo no sé fingir. Le amo; y porque este amor me está vedado, muero.

Yo me eché entonces a reír, la escarnecí:

--¡La persona que quiere morir no lo dice!... ¡Bien desempeñas tu papel!...

Todavía creo ver su mirada asombrada.

--¿No me cree usted? ¿No cree cuando ya me he despedido de la única persona que me llorará
sinceramente?...

--¿De él?...--exclamé.

A sor Ana era a quien había escrito; pero no manifestó indignación de mi sospecha, del tono
de ironía con que la expresé. Se limitó a corregirme:

--De sor Ana.

Yo repuse siempre en tono de burla:

--¿Y la salud del alma?

Al oír estas palabras se ocultó el rostro entre las manos. Yo se las tomé de repente, y traté
de atraerla hacia mi pecho.

--¡No, no morirás; tú vivirás para mí, conmigo...

Ella se levantó de un salto y se echó para atrás:

--¡No me toque usted!

Yo sentí que mi inmenso amor chocaba contra un odio implacable.

--¡Bueno! ¿La causo horror?--la dije.--¡Y lo ama usted a él! Y aun cuando en realidad quisiera
usted matarse, no lo haría, porque teme el juicio de su Dios. Yo quiero librarla a usted de
esa pena!...

Y antes de que siquiera tuviese el tiempo de sospechar mi intención, me apoderé del arma, que
tenía oculta entre varios libros.

--Ahora no se matará usted, no afrontará la ira de Dios, y podrá usted también correr en busca
de nuevas caricias.

Desde ese momento ya no la reconocí. Miró en su derredor, como si se sintiera presa de una
gran congoja, como si se creyera perdida, como si se viera envuelta en una tromba voraz y absorbente.

Luego me miró: sus ojos estaban iluminados por un fulgor de gozo, por una sonrisa burlona.

--¡Ah! ¿Cree usted?... ¿Hasta usted cree que yo quiero morir?... ¿Cómo lo ha creído usted?...
¡Llévese esa arma! No es la muerte la que me espera, sino la vida y el placer... ¡Váyase usted:
déjeme sola: él va a venir ahora!...

Yo también miré entonces en torno mío, desconcertado: mi mano armada temblaba. Y como en mi
mirada había una pregunta, ella la comprendió:

--¡Va a venir: soy suya!...

La roja llamarada me subió otra vez, más furiosa, a los ojos y a la frente.

--¡Cállese usted!--la grité.

--¡No, no quiero callarme! ¡No puedo!... ¡Le amo, soy suya!

--¡Cállese!--la ordené una vez más.

--¡No, no quiero callarme! ¡Le amo, y a ti te odio y te desprecio! ¡Tú me has hecho tanto mal,
que tengo derecho de desquitarme por fin! ¡Nadie puede condenarme!...

--¡Cállate!...--la intimé por tercera vez.

--¡No, no puedo callarme! Aunque me condenen, ¿qué me importa? Todo mi ser necesita respirar
la felicidad de que por fin se siente saturado. ¡Quiero gritar a todos, a todos quiero hacer
ver la felicidad que me inunda el alma!...

--¡Estás loca!--grité.

--¡Sí, desde que soy tuya!

No; eso no era posible. Si hubiera sido cierto, si yo hubiera debido creerlo, yo también me
hubiera vuelto loco.

--¡No es cierto! ¡No te creo!--exclamé.

Ella me contestó, atónita, riéndose:

--¿No lo crees? ¿Cómo te lo haré creer?... Escucha: si no fuera verdad, ¿yo habría querido
morir? Tú me has encontrado con el arma en la mano; he escrito ya una carta de postrer adiós;
iba a escribir mi testamento: después le habría escrito a él. ¿Crees que yo habría querido,
habría podido dejarlo de esa manera? Sin el remordimiento de la culpa, ¿habría pensado en la
muerte? ¡A no haber sido mi caída, habría continuado viviendo como hasta ahora! Deseaba morir,
porque creía haber pecado; ¡pero ahora ya no, ya no, ya no!...

--¿Tú has hecho eso?

--Lo he hecho y lo volveré a hacer. Le amo, es mío, para siempre. ¿Quieres saber desde cuándo?
¿Quieres saber cómo?

--¡Cállate! ¡No me provoques!

--No, no te provoco. ¿Qué me importas tú? ¿Quién eres tú? ¿Qué haces aquí? ¿Quién te ha dado
el derecho de entrar aquí? ¡Vete, déjame! Él me espera, te lo repito... ¿Quieres darme miedo?...
¡Ah, ah!...

Mis miradas debían ser espantosas: ¡y ella se reía e insistía!

--¡No te temo! ¿Qué puedes hacerme?

Yo prorrumpí:

--¡Matarte!

Ella abrió los brazos, alzó la cabeza, presentó el pecho.

--¡Mátame! ¡Seré suya hasta la tumba!

--¡Cállate, o te mato!

--¡Hasta la tumba! No hay uno solo de mis pensamientos, ni un latido de mi corazón, ni un movimiento
de mi alma, ni una fibra de mis carnes, que no sea suya...

Yo alcé el arma. La mirada fulguraba, su voz cantaba:

--En la vida, hasta más allá de la muerte, de él solo...

El tiro partió...

Roberto Vérod había temblado durante el relato, de dolor, de horror, de compasión, de remordimiento
impotente, de odio mal contenido. Al oír la última palabra dio un paso adelante, y alzando
el puño gritó:

--¡Asesino!

El Príncipe sostuvo su mirada, y dijo:

--Pegue usted.

Así permanecieron los dos, frente a frente, durante un tiempo que ni uno ni otro habría podido
después apreciar. Vérod volvió a dejar caer el brazo, y con voz sorda, trémula, repitió:

--¡Asesino!

--He venido para que usted cumpla justicia. Lo que usted haga será justo. Pero escúcheme usted
todavía un instante. Cuando la vi caer, cuando vi su sangre brotar de su horrible herida, un
rugido se escapó de mi pecho. Todavía estaba viva. Vivió para decirme sus últimas palabras.
Óigalas usted:

--He mentido, para morir... Yo no podía... Gracias... Perdón...

Esas fueron, sus postreras palabras. Yo quise morir con ella. Tenía en la mano el arma, y la
volví contra mí mismo; pero alguien me apretó en ese momento el brazo como con una tenaza.
Alejandra estaba delante de mí:

--¡Tú tienes que vivir! ¡Debes vivir! ¡Debes salvarte! ¡Déjame hacer!...

Yo no comprendía.

Alejandra colocaba el arma junto al cadáver, estudiaba la manera de ponerla, le extrajo una
cápsula.

--Se habrá matado, como lo había anunciado: todos lo creerán...

Ya se acercaban las voces, los rumores de pasos:

--Óyeme. Si sospechan, déjame contestar a mí; confirma en todo caso mis respuestas. ¡Piensa
en el deber! ¡Piensa en la causa! ¡Piensa en mí, que te amo, que te quiero para mí, que sabré
hacerte feliz!...

Yo no comprendía. Corrí a pedir socorro, con la esperanza que todavía estuviera viva. ¿Por
qué ocultar la verdad? Decirla fue mi primer impulso. Si no la dije inmediatamente fue porque
todavía no comprendía nada: no oía las preguntas que me hacían, contestaba a ellas mecánicamente,
como en sueños. Pero después, cuando usted me arrojó a la cara la acusación, yo me sublevé.
Todavía era esa mi condición. Mi pensamiento, mis sentimientos, obedecían ciegamente a esa
clase de reacciones repentinas. Acusado por usted, me defendí. Dije todo cuanto podía decir
en mi contra, reconocí haber sido yo quien la empujó a la muerte, pero negué el acto extremo.
Varias veces en el curso de los interrogatorios estuvo por confesar; pero al oír el nombre
de usted, al ver la dureza del juez, me contenía. De la necesidad de destrozarme, de morir,
de expiar mi culpa, que me dominaba en los primeros momentos, pasé a la ansiedad de la deliberación:
como una fiera aprisionada, no tuve ya otro empeño que el de romper mis cadenas, de correr
en campo abierto, de ser otra vez dueño de mí mismo. Y, sin comprenderlas, confirmé las declaraciones
de Alejandra; y cuando ella se acusó, cuando por fin la comprendí, cuando vi que se perdía
por amor a mí, entonces, naturalmente, acepté el sacrificio... Ambos fuimos dejados en libertad,
y entonces, en el momento en que me vi libre, en que la mentira triunfaba, me propuse decir
la verdad. Todavía me callé durante algún tiempo, porque dentro de mí, en la prolongada noche
de mi mente, el alba de un nuevo día aparecía ya. Alejandra creía velar sobre mí porque estábamos
juntos, porque me hablaba. Yo no la veía, no la oía: una alma, muda e invisible, gobernaba
ya mi vida...

Se interrumpió un momento, alzando los ojos al firmamento. El cielo se había calmado, los amarillos
nubarrones habían desaparecido: coloraciones rosadas, y verdes, purísimas, iluminaban el occidente.

El Príncipe continuó:

--El rencor, el odio, la envidia, la concuspicencia, todas las miserias que habían formado
mi vida, se me aparecieron por fin bajo su luz sombría. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>118768</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21594</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> And no longer knew what it could see, or worse, afraid to know too. Florence had
been death! No trial had been afraid of God! I had not thought in the salvation of his soul he
did not believe in their future life, because everything had been killed ends in death.

"So there is nothing, nothing ?...»

The question of the dead remained unanswered, unheard.

By sole virtue of sight of his beloved candle plant had looked, I
had heard, including the soul of the world: mysterious voices had
told him memorabilia, all living, throbbing and glistened.

But, then again silence and darkness to gather around him. The with previously evident or hidden
meaning remained mute.

So deep and sincere was his conversion, which is sometimes felt under electric of the ancient
faith, but then again the darkness around him thicker. And in the alternative of course, was
silent again with terror and despair, his alter ego, the man Time I thought I had buried past and
into himself. As before having met the Countess, his thinking was dark, confused, lost. The miraculous
flowering had sprouted from every crevice of your soul withered and
crumbled.

At other times, his heart, be closed to all pleasure in their own greed, but once they had received
the seed he was embittered by rancor infinity.

The young man decided to go. He saw other lands, other men, hoping to leave his pain over the ways
of the world, but nothing was enough to calm him down. In Nice, in front of the tomb his sister,
wept hot tears that far from extinguishing the fire revived. Lake had become: a mortal dread
came over him at the thought of seeing again the only places where
I could tell he really had lived.

Feared drowned with grief to see Ouchy beaches, hills of Lausanne, the town Cyclamens, the forest
of Comte, the humble chapels, the panorama of Lake Geneva veiled by clouds and smiling, sunlight.

Finally,
one day went. Found these places as they had left. The passivity of the Nature eternal hurt
him as an insult: if at least something had been destroyed in the
land, if only I had seen around him traces of devastation similar
to which he felt inside.

Secular forests, perennial waters, ravenous beasts graves, remained immutable. The young man
was acknowledging each point along the way, every detail of perspective. His desperate certainty
that no power could have never perform the miracle to give back what
was lost and turned around but his eyes, and sharpened ear, as if
an apparition, a voice suddenly could evoke the lost asset.

And one afternoon from a window in his room watching Dôle summits
behind down which the sun rays, shuddered when he heard a voice behind
him spoke.

Was it a hallucination? Is not daydreaming?

Alejo Zakunine Prince was in his presence.

- Roberto candle plant - said the voice - can not you recognize me?

A kind of shiver shook the nerves, believed to be seeing a ghost.

What he wanted with this man? Why would fetch?

- Do you know who I am? But I was not expecting you! I come to you because I have something say.

He
spoke with his head bowed, humbly.

Seen from above, from the spacious front end to the tip of the beard,
the face was all furrowed with deep wrinkles.

Hair, very rare, were white with temples.

His whole person was printed signs a rapid decline.

Candle plant looked at him as if fascinated, unable to answer a single word, to see clearly
in the tumult of feelings that raged in his soul.

- I have to tell you one thing. Ferpierre want to give it to the judge, but I thought it best was
first to address you ...

And after a pause he added:

- Listen, candle plant, Florence d'Arda not killed. I murdered.

The young man ran a hand across his forehead, eyes. Again, more so than in the first instant
was unsure of being awake.

- Do not believe me, you? Yet, you were so close to the truth!

I know you the asserted against everything and everyone, and very
nearly got to prove it.

True many circumstances, especially, were, against you. Sister's letter Ana, seemed to have
the last word on the fate of the Countess. What cheated justice was that when I killed was indeed
determined to be death. I will say you how I killed her ...

Candle plant trembled as if shaken by fever.

- I will refer you to my shame: this is the beginning of the punishment. I never knew what
worth.

Never, while he lived, I realized the beauty of her soul. No beauty was understandable to
me: the world and life seemed devoid of that quality. I had within me a Hell, nothing could
extinguish the flame which devoured me.

Everything I touched was reduced to ashes. She loved me for compassion: the instinct, need, lust
of slaughter gave me. And although I did not understand, for a moment I was blinded by her
light. I could not bear the light, and looked away. And I teased her and offended.

He paused a moment, staring before him as if he were blind, and then continued:

- Listen you. When he has said everything, you will understand my words deserve faith. In the
first time I said I was next. Nature and life had to go provided me with a feeling passing
another with fulmineo violence. Those who know what I have done in the world may sometimes
think that perhaps the voice guided me the right. But I do not was
aware.

If within me judging my actions and those of others, all came down a mechanism, a game of blind
drives and fatal. I could not, therefore, believe the change had come over me by virtue. I only
made fun of it, too I laughed at myself ...

Should tell you which was, day by day, hour by hour, my awful work,
how to constant, tireless preaching of divine love and goodness opposed
contempt, insult, betrayal.

But you know all this. And then, then ...

Everything you suggested to his hatred towards me was not enough: what I did is incredible. Sometimes
when words poison and corrosive desecrated, vilified, destroyed their faith, when he showed
that nothing exists outside of evil, that the only remedies are iron,
fire, death, when urged to leave me, to betray, to lose, was operated
inside me a backlash, and tears came to my eyes.

But I hid my tears.

When you met her, I realized that she began to love him, my heart was dilated to joy. View your
feelings wavered decanted eternity; provide that would fall as all
fall, to say it: - You see?

Where are your moral laws? You also do as others, what you please! - was something that filled
me with joy ...

Meanwhile, I gave myself completely, had prompted the action to the fainthearted to my country
and others. The last attempt seemed destined to prosper and savored
success.

Everything was carefully prepared, had prompted the action to the fainthearted the wavering,
to the fearful, and delivered almost all that remained of my property without thinking encounter
difficulties in later.

My duty was to get me also in action, and I had to leave for that purpose, but I was obliged to stay
to prepare a new action in the case of a setback.

And one day I learned that my brothers were dead, hanging from the gallows that fell on roads
leading to the exile, under the rule of the thugs, and I knew that women, the children went to
the gallows, that many innocents suffered in my place that fear reigned over all the people
of my race ...

That day I found myself in the presence of such ruin, with the fear of having the wrong road,
alone and almost poor. Then suddenly arose in my heart something like a necessity, as a forward,
like a burning thirst for relief, then I almost reach out and find support me, almost prostrated
me to hear a word of comfort ...

The consolation being that could exist, would have had nothing else to do to go after her, to
open my heart. Might have been still long. Or maybe not: it was too late ...

Too late! Do you know what these words mean? ... Me a boost of pride stopped. Would I have to beg?
And yet, I realized that nothing in this crisis My life could have been heal as the love of
a creature like this.

I went back to his side, but nothing I said.

My attitude was to demonstrate, however, what happened within me. Too late! ... We suffer and
accept suffering, we can despair and live in despair, but at the thought that happiness would
have been for us; that fortune has come to our side to get it that
we only had to extend hand, to say a word, and we've taken her hand,
and uttered - too late! - the word at the idea the heart stopped beating
...

And it was not mine: it was you, and when I acquired this certainty,
I started to laugh again and mock.

I ran it, but I had to return to his side, even when I showed repentant and converted, I weighed
the subject, far from it could not live. Thus passed the recent months, alternating with brief
escapes my returns. A Zurich going to talk about it another unhappy, Alejandra. Alejandra Natzichet
is dead ...

Candle plant was stunned. No, not dreaming, but the reality was all the dream characters. The man
who spoke in his presence seemed to him as proud revolutionary pale images of a nightmare look like
living people. Dead, the Natzichet? How, why he died? Until the time and light are unnatural:
the yellow twilight oddly lit room, the things the Prince's emaciated
face.

- I trusted my torment Alejandra, Alejandra and loved me, without
me even noticing!

The Life has so dear: our souls, that these four creatures have been found to suffer unspeakable
pain, and none knew what the other suffering, or always know too late! Alejandra I professed
brotherly affection: the solitude in which he was sunk, her integrity, which made her able
to withstand and overcome the difficulties of life, I inclined to
protect her, to hold her like a sister, as a daughter, but she wanted
me with a more ardent affection!

And even if I had realized his love, what could have made it happy?

Only she could trust with my passion for the other! ...

Alejandra tried to cure me call of duty to serve the cause: I wanted
to hear, but vain.

The idea of ??winning back the love that before disdained, to seize and running my whole life.
After being overlooked and attributed to the love an inestimable
price.

It was fair! ...

None of this is said to Florence: the time had come to see, I spent days shaking discover and
mine was no longer in the soul, had already handed over to you. To not believe in this horrible
thing, I say, "Think so elevated, it never will!"

And an inner voice answered: "Now do you believe in that moral high ground that before you laugh?"
Yes, before I laughed. And still did not believe it!

My confidence that I would betray not based on both the esteem in
which he had his character, as unable to believe it was all over between
us irretrievably.

I saw that my back and my repentance produced a mortal anxiety, and I flattered the hope to recover
...

Being at his side and unable to hold his hand! Remember the past and the despair of living another
After one of his hours! ... As much as happened to me, and nothing could say! I pride and
still contained another reason less petty. I was already in poverty, she was rich: speaking
of my love, could not be a lie suggested by the calculation?

...

One day I spoke. The said

- I've lost, I wanted to lose, I feel that my guilt is irreparable.

But if you knew what happens inside me! I ask you please not leave me this time around collapses
around me.

Later you will do what you want ...

That same day, the day the storm
had spoken to you too.

Narrowed between our two passions, he resolved to die.

The answer he gave me was:

- Never leave him because I'm his wife, but you remember that our
love is dead.

His tone was cold, her eyes meet mine avoided.

When I realized that you also had spoken, I thought it was not sincere,
I thought I was hiding something.

But the fear was that had decided to flee, did not believe that had
the decision to die: not even know!

...

I spent quite a night. She also spent awake.

A hundred times a thousand, I wanted to go look, but his door was
closed me.

Alejandra morning came for me, calling me with intuition of a disaster.

As I promised, but first I wanted a last look at Florence.

Hearing me into his room hurriedly hid something. I saw it was the gun.

At this point he was squeezed between our two passions, he wanted
to die to free ... I realized that I had no right to speak, introducing
me to his room, which was given leave to your destination, freedom,
death, but could not.

The idea that among two people who had been on each other did not
exist, nothing, nothing that I was worse than a stranger to her, she
found no place in my mind.

And the secret voice told me: "Before, you thought that love was
fleeting encounter of two whims, before you laugh ties indissoluble
... "

I could not admit that he belonged to another, even if it were only
in thought.

I, who had betrayed her, could not accept being betrayed my time. My pride was unlimited,
would not tolerate someone were worth more than me.

And understand that you would have known make her happy, pride, love,
jealousy, all passions, all the instincts of my race, my nature revolted
threatening.

- You promised me yesterday - I said with bitter emphasis
- let me not because you're my wife, and now want to kill you ...

She
did not deny it.

- Let me die - was his answer, - it will be better
for everyone.

In his voice there was something I did not know: his love for you,
the bitterness of having to abandon happiness that was promised to
you.

- "So you can no longer tolerate my sight?

So much you cringe?

The said these words, and many, many others.

She replied only:.

- Whose fault is it?

- Listen you: this was the first complaint that I was going after so many months of pain.

- Well - the "I replied, - I will disappear, will depart today, in
a moment and never see me again.

You want to die, though?

- Yes - I said.

I was afraid to understand, but, however, asked

- Why?

His words, nothing I said I did not already know.

- Because if I live I will be yours.

His, for you, otherwise ...!

A flare up to my eyes and forehead.

- That's not possible, will not happen! ...

She shook her head.

- Do not say no! - Insisted .-- Do not say no! ... I know you do not love me you hate me, that
defy me but do not tell me you love another, because ... because
...

- I love him - he said.

Then I begged, I cried. She repeated:

- I love him. Do not lie. I do not pretend to know.

I love him, and because this love is forbidden me, I die.

Then I fell down laughing, derided:

- The person who wants to die does not say! ... Well performing your role! ...

I still see his eyes in amazement.

- Are not you think?

Do not believe me when I fired the only person I will cry honestly? ...

- How he cried ?...--.

A Sister Ana was who had written, but no outrage expressed my suspicion, tone of irony to express
it.

Merely corrected:

- Sister Anne

I always said I facetiously:

- What about the health
of the soul?

At these words he hid his face in his hands.

I know I took them suddenly, and tried draw it into my chest.

-
No, not die, you live for me, me ...

She jumped up and leaned back:

-
Do not you touch me!

I felt that my great love crashed into implacable hatred.

- Well!

Is caused horror? - The said .-- And you love him!

And though it actually would you kill, would not, because he fears
the trial of his God.

I want you free from that penalty! ...

And before I even had the time to suspect my intention, I seized the
weapon, had hidden in several books.

- Now do not kill you, will
not face the wrath of God, and you may also run for new strokes.

Since then no longer recognized.

He looked around him, as if she were prey to a terrified, as if he thought lost, like become engaged
in a whirlwind voracious and absorbing.

Then she looked: her eyes were lit by a glow of joy, a grin.

- Ah! Do you? ... How you think I want to die? ... How have you believe ...? Take that gun!
It is death that awaits me, but life and pleasure ... Go you: leave
me alone: ??he is coming now!

...

I also then looked around me, puzzled: my hand shaking armed. And as in my eyes had a question,
she realized:

- It's going to come: I am yours!

...

I climbed the red flare again, more furious, eyes and forehead.

-
Shut up you! - The screamed.

- No, I will shut up!

I can not! ... I love him, I'm yours!

- Shut up! - The computer again.

- No, I will shut up! I love you, and you will hate and despise you! You have made me so ill,
I have the right to retaliate at last! No one can condemn! ...

- Shut !...-- privacy for the third time.

- No, I can not shut up! Although I condemn, what do I care? My whole being needs to breathe
happiness that finally feels saturated. I want to scream at all, all I want to do I see the happiness
that fills the soul ...

- You're crazy! - I cried.

- Yes, I'm yours!

No, that was not possible. If it were true, if I'd believe it because I too had gone mad.

- Not true! Do not believe it! - I cried.

She replied, astonished, laughing:

- Do not you think? How do you believe it? ... Listen: if it were not true, what I would have liked
die? You've found me with the gun in his hand, I have already written
a letter last farewell; I would write my will, then I would have written
it.

Do you think I would have liked, might have to leave that way?

Without the remorse of guilt, would have thought in death? Had it not been my downfall, would
have continued living as now! Wanted to die, because he believed
they have sinned, but now no, no, no! ...

- You have done that?

-
I have done and do it again. I love him, is mine forever. Want to
know how long? Want to know how?

- Shut up! Do not tease me!

- No,
do not provoke. What I care about you? Who are you? What are you doing
here? Who has given you the right to come here? Go, leave me! He waits
for me, I repeat ... Do you want me so scared? ... Ah, ah ...

My
eyes had to be frightening, and she laughed and insisted!

- Do not
be afraid! What can you do to me?

I burst out:

- Kill!

She opened
her arms, looked up, introduced the chest.

- Kill me! I'll keep him
until the grave!

- Shut up or I'll kill you!

- To the grave! There
is not one of my thoughts, not a beat of my heart, not a movement
of my soul, not a fiber of my flesh, that is not yours ...

I raised
the gun. The eyes flashed, his voice sang:

- In life, even beyond
death, it just ...

The fire broke ...

Roberto candle plant had trembled
in the tale, of pain, horror, compassion, remorse impotent, hate bad
content. Upon hearing the shots came forward, and lifting fist shouted

-
Murderer!

The Prince held his gaze and said:

- Paste you.

So the
two stood face to face for a while neither could have then appreciate.
Candle plant again dropping the arm, and a hollow voice, tremulous,
he repeated:

- Murderer!

- I have come that you meet justice. What
you do will be fair. But listen to me still an instant. When I saw
her fall, when I saw the blood flow from his horrible wound, a roar
escaped from my chest. She was still alive. He lived to tell me his
last words. You hear them:

- He lied to die ... I could not ... Thanks
... Sorry ...

Those were his last words. I wanted to die with her.
He was holding the gun, and I went against myself, but someone pushed
me in that moment his arm as with pliers. Alejandra was before me:

-
You must live! You live! You save! Let me do! ...

I do not understand.

Alejandra
placed the gun near the body, was studying how to put it, he drew
a capsule.

- Will have been killed, as he said: we all believe ...

And
voices approaching, rumors of steps:

- Listen. If suspect, let me
answer me in any case confirms my answers. Think on duty! Think about
the cause! Think of me, I love you, I love you for me, I know make
you happy! ...

I do not understand. I ran to call for help, hoping
to still be alive. Why Why hide the truth? Say it was my first impulse.
If not I immediately said it was because still did not understand:
I could not hear the questions I did, answered them mechanically as
dreams. But then, when you threw me face the charge, I rebelled. Still
was that my condition. My thoughts, my feelings, blindly obeying the
kind of sudden reactions. Charged with you, I defended myself. I said
all he could say against me, I recognized it was me who pushed her
to death, but denied the extreme act. Several times during the interrogation
was to confess, but hearing the name you, to see the harshness of
the judge, I contained. The need to tear, dying, to atone for my fault
that I overlooked at first, I went to the anxiety of the discussion:
imprisoned like a wild beast, and I had no other commitment than to
break my chains, running open field again be master of myself. And
without understanding, confirmed the statements Alejandra, and when
she was accused, when he finally realized when I saw that was lost
for my sake, then, naturally, I accepted the sacrifice ... Both were
released, and then, at the time that I was free, which lie succeeded,
I wanted to say truth. Still I was silent for some time, because within
me, in the long night of my mind, the dawn of a new day was already
included. Alejandra believed to watch over me because we were together,
because I spoke. I could not see, not heard: a soul, silent and invisible,
ruled and my life ...

He paused, looking up at the sky. The sky was
calm, yellow clouds were gone, colors pink and green, pure, illuminating
the west.

The Prince continued:

- The bitterness, hatred, envy,
concuspicencia all the misery that had formed my life, I finally came
under the dim light</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>