<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>147049</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16489</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Parecía que hubiese
llovido ceniza sobre la inmovilidad de las cosas.

Las personas ofrecían igual aspecto de abandono y decadencia. Ulises encontró al poeta flaco
y amarillento, sumido en un sillón, con la barba luenga y blanca, un ojo casi cerrado y el
otro enormemente abierto. Al ver al marino, ancho de pecho, forzudo, bronceado, Labarta se
echó á llorar con un hipo infantil, como si llorase sobre la miseria de las ilusiones humanas,
sobre la brevedad de una vida engañosa que necesita el oleaje de la continua renovación.

Más trabajo le costó todavía á Ferragut reconocer á una señora pequeña y encogida que estaba
junto al poeta. Colgaban de su esqueleto flácidas adiposidades, como harapos de un pasado esplendor.
La cabeza era exigua; su rostro tenía el arrugamiento de las manzanas invernizas, de las ciruelas,
de todas las frutas que se contraen y momifican, perdiendo su líquido. «¡Doña Pepa!...» Los
dos viejos se tuteaban ahora en presencia de Ulises, con la tranquila amoralidad de los que
se ven próximos á la muerte y olvidan los temores y escrúpulos de una vida que se va derrumbando
á sus espaldas.

El marino vió en esta miseria física el triste final de un régimen alimenticio absurdo, alegre
y pueril: los dulces sirviendo de base de nutrición, los grandes arroces como plato diario,
las sandías y melones llenando el intermedio entre las comidas, los helados servidos en copas
enormes, esparciendo el perfume de su nieve melosa.

Los dos le hablaron suspirando de sus enfermedades, que juzgaban incomprensibles, atribuyéndolas
á ignorancia de los médicos. Era la consunción que ataca de pronto á las gentes de los países
abundantes. Su vida se fundía en un chorreo de azúcar líquido... Y todavía adivinaba Ferragut
las desobediencias de los dos viejos á las disciplinas del régimen, sus ocultamientos infantiles,
sus astucias para gustar á solas las frutas y los jarabes, encanto de su existencia.

Fué corta la entrevista. El capitán debía volver al Grao, donde le esperaba su trasatlántico,
pronto á zarpar para la América del Sur.

El poeta lloró otra vez, besando á su ahijado. Ya no vería más á este coloso que parecía repeler
sus débiles abrazos con el fuelle de su respiración.

--Ulises, ¡hijo mío!... piensa siempre en Valencia... Haz por ella todo lo que puedas... Ya
lo sabes. ¡Siempre Valencia!

Juró todo lo que quiso el poeta, sin comprender qué es lo que Valencia podía esperar de él,
simple marino errante por todos los mares. Labarta quiso acompañarle hasta la puerta, pero
se hundió en su asiento, obediente al cariñoso despotismo de su compañera, que temía para él
las mayores catástrofes.

¡Pobre doña Pepa!... Ferragut sintió deseos de reír y de llorar al recibir un beso de su boca
arrugada, cuyo vello se había convertido en púas. Fué un beso de beldad vieja que se recuerda
al contacto de un buen mozo; un beso de mujer infecunda que acaricia al hijo que pudo tener.

--¡El infeliz Carmelo!... Ya no escribe; ya no lee... ¡Ay! ¿qué será de mí?...

Hablaba de la decadencia de su poeta con la conmiseración de un ser fuerte y sano. Se aterraba
al pensar en los años que podría sobrevivir á su señor. Ocupada en cuidarle, no se miraba á
ella misma.

Un año después, el capitán encontró en Port-Said, á la vuelta de las Filipinas, una carta de
su padrino. Doña Pepa había muerto, y Labarta, sacudiendo la modorra lacrimosa de su abatimiento,
la despedía con un largo cántico. Ulises pasó los ojos por el recorte de periódico que iba
dentro de la carta conteniendo los últimos versos del poeta. Eran versos en castellano. ¡Malo!...
Después de esto, resultaba indudable su próximo fin.

No tuvo ocasión de verle otra vez: murió estando él de viaje. Al desembarcar en Barcelona,
su madre le entregó una carta escrita casi en su agonía. «Valencia, hijo mío; ¡siempre Valencia!»
Y luego de repetir varias veces esta recomendación, le hacía saber que era su heredero.

Los libros, las estatuas, todos los recuerdos gloriosos de Labarta, pasaron á Barcelona para
adornar la casa del marino. El pequeño Telémaco pudo entretenerse rompiendo las viejas coronas
del trovador, arrancando estampas á los volúmenes, con la inconsciencia de un niño fogoso que
tiene á su padre muy lejos y vive sometido á dos señoras que le adoran. Además, el poeta dejó
á su ahijado una casa vieja en Valencia, varias tierras y cierta cantidad en valores cotizables.
Total: treinta mil duros.

El otro tutor de su infancia, el vigoroso Tritón, permanecía insensible al paso de los años.
Ferragut le encontró varias veces, al llegar á Barcelona, instalado en su casa, en sorda hostilidad
con doña Cristina, dedicando á Cinta y á su hijo una parte del cariño que antes era sólo para
Ulises.

Deseaba que el pequeño Esteban conociese la casa de los bisabuelos.

--¿Me lo dejarás?... Ya sabes que allá en la Marina los hombres se hacen fuertes como el bronce.
¿De veras que me lo dejarás?...

Dudaba de su influencia ante el gesto indignado de la suave doña Cristina. ¿Confiar su nieto
al Tritón, para que le infundiese el amor á las aventuras marítimas, lo mismo que á Ulises?...
¡Atrás, demonio azul!

El médico vagaba desorientado por el puerto de Barcelona... Demasiado ruido, demasiado movimiento.
Marchaba al lado de Ulises orgullosamente, haciéndole relatar las aventuras de sus años de
marino vagabundo y cosmopolita. Veía en él al más grande de los Ferragut: hombre de mar como
sus abuelos, pero con título de capitán; aventurero de todos los océanos como él lo había sido,
pero con un sitio en el puente, revestido del mando absoluto que confieren la responsabilidad
y el peligro.

Al reembarcarse Ulises, se alejaba el Tritón hacia sus dominios.

--Será la próxima vez--decía para consolarse al partir sin el hijo de su sobrino.

Y pasados unos meses reaparecía, cada vez más grande, más feo, más curtido, con una sonrisa
silenciosa que estallaba en palabras ante Ulises, lo mismo que una nube tempestuosa estalla
en truenos.

A la vuelta de un viaje al mar Negro, doña Cristina anunció á su hijo:

--Tu tío ha muerto.

La piadosa señora lamentaba cristianamente la desaparición de su cuñado, dedicándole una parte
de sus rezos, pero insistió con cierta crueldad en el relato de su triste fin. No podía perdonarle
su fatal intervención en el destino de Ulises. Había muerto como había vivido, en el mar, víctima
de su temeridad, sin confesión, lo mismo que un pagano.

Otra herencia que caía sobre Ferragut... Su tío se había lanzado á nadar en una mañana asoleada
de invierno, y no había vuelto. Los viejos de la costa explicaban á su modo el accidente: un
desmayo, un choque con las rocas. El Dotor era aún vigoroso, pero los años no pasan sin dejar
huella. Algunos creían en una lucha con un «cabeza de olla» ú otro pez carnívoro de los que
cazan en las aguas mediterráneas. En vano los pescadores llevaron sus barcas por todas las
angulosidades entrantes y salientes del promontorio, explorando las cuevas sombrías y los bajos
fondos de cristalina transparencia. Nadie pudo encontrar el cadáver del Tritón.

Ferragut recordó el cortejo de Afrodita que el médico le había descrito tantas veces en las
noches estivales, viendo á lo lejos las luces de los faros. Tal vez había tropezado con la
alegre comitiva de las nereidas, uniéndose á ella para siempre.

Esta suposición absurda que Ulises formuló mentalmente, con incrédula y triste sonrisa, se
repitió al mismo tiempo en el pensamiento simple de muchas gentes de la Marina.

Se negaban á creer en su muerte. Un brujo no se ahoga. Habría encontrado abajo algo muy interesante,
y cuando se cansase de vivir en las verdes profundidades volvería nadando á su casa.

No; el Dotor no había muerto.

Y durante muchos años, las mujeres que seguían la costa al anochecer apresuraron el paso, persignándose,
al distinguir en las aguas obscuras un madero ó un paquete de algas. Temían que surgiese de
pronto el Tritón, barbudo, lúbrico, chorreante, volviendo de su correría por las misteriosas
entrañas del mar.

IV

FREYA

El nombre de Ulises Ferragut empezó á ser famoso entre los capitanes de los puertos españoles.
Las aventuras náuticas de su primera época entraban por muy poco en esta popularidad. Los más
de ellos habían arrostrado mayores peligros, y si le apreciaban, era por el instintivo respeto
que sienten los hombres enérgicos y simples ante una inteligencia que consideran superior.
Sin otras lecturas que las de su carrera, hablaban con asombro de los numerosos libros que
llenaban el camarote de Ferragut, muchos de ellos sobre materias que les parecían misteriosas.
Algunos hasta hacían afirmaciones inexactas para completar el prestigio de su camarada:

--Sabe mucho... Además de marino, es abogado.

La consideración de su fortuna contribuía igualmente al aprecio general. Era accionista importante
de la compañía naviera á la que prestaba sus servicios. Los compañeros calculaban con orgullosa
exageración la riqueza de su madre, tasándola en millones.

Encontraba amigos en todo buque que ostentase á popa la bandera española, fuese cual fuese
su puerto de origen y el regionalismo de sus tripulantes.

Todos le querían: los capitanes vascos, sobrios en palabras, rudos y de tuteo confianzudo;
los capitanes asturianos y gallegos, enamoradizos y derrochadores, que desmienten con su carácter
la avaricia y la tristeza de tierra adentro; los capitanes andaluces, que parecen llevar en
su gracioso lenguaje un reflejo de la blanca Cádiz y sus vinos luminosos; los capitanes valencianos,
que hablan de política en el puente, imaginando lo que podrá ser la marina de la futura República;
los capitanes de Cataluña y de Mallorca, conocedores de los negocios tan á fondo como sus armadores.
Siempre que les unía la necesidad de defender sus derechos, pensaban inmediatamente en Ulises.
Ninguno escribía como él.

Los viejos pilotos venidos de abajo, hombres de mar que habían empezado su carrera en las barcas
de cabotaje y á duras penas ajustaban sus conocimientos prácticos al manejo de los libros,
hablaban de Ferragut con orgullo:

--Dicen que los del mar somos gente bruta... Ahí tienen á don Luis, que es de los nuestros.
Pueden preguntarle lo que quieran... ¡Un sabio!

El nombre de Ulises les hacía titubear. Lo creían apodo, y no queriendo incurrir en una falta
de respeto, habían acabado por transformarlo en don Luis. Para algunos de ellos, el único defecto
de Ferragut era su buena suerte. Aún no se había perdido un buque mandado por él. Y todo buen
marino que navega sin descanso debe tener en su historia una de estas desgracias para ser un
capitán completo. Solamente los labradores no pierden barcos.

Cuando murió su madre, Ulises quedó indeciso ante el porvenir, no sabiendo si continuar su
vida de navegante ó emprender otra completamente nueva. Sus parientes de Barcelona, mercaderes
de ágil entendimiento para la evaluación de una fortuna, sumaban lo que habían dejado el notario
y su esposa, y añadiendo lo de Labarta y el médico, casi llegaban á un millón de pesetas...
¿Y un hombre con tanto dinero iba á seguir viviendo lo mismo que un pobre capitán que necesita
el sueldo para mantener á su familia?...

Su primo Joaquín Blanes, dueño de una fábrica de géneros de punto, le instó repetidas veces
á que siguiese su ejemplo. Debía quedarse en tierra y emplear su capital en la industria catalana.
Ulises era del país, por su madre y por haber nacido en la vecina tierra de Valencia. Se necesitaban
hombres de fortuna y energía para que interviniesen en el gobierno. Blanes hacía política regionalista
con el entusiasmo de un burgués que se lanza en aventuras novelescas.

Cinta no dijo una palabra para decidir á su esposo. Era hija de un marino y había aceptado
ser la esposa de otro. Además, entendía el matrimonio con arreglo á la tradición familiar:
la mujer dueña absoluta del interior de la casa, pero confiada en los asuntos exteriores á
la voluntad del señor, del guerrero, del jefe del hogar, sin permitirse pensamientos ni objeciones
sobre sus actos.

Fué Ulises el que adoptó por sí mismo la decisión de abandonar la vida de navegante. Trabajado
por las sugestiones de sus primos, le bastó una pequeña disputa con uno de los directores de
la casa armadora para ofrecer su renuncia, sin que lograsen hacerle retroceder los ruegos y
explicaciones de los otros consocios.

En los primeros meses de su existencia terrestre, extrañó la inmovilidad desesperante de las
cosas. El mundo era de una rigidez y una dureza antipáticas. Sintió algo semejante á un principio
de mareo al ver que todo permanecía allí donde él lo dejaba, sin permitirse el menor vaivén,
la más leve fantasía dinámica.

Por las mañanas, al entreabrir sus ojos, experimentaba la dulce sensación de la libertad irresponsable.
Nada le importaba la suerte de aquella casa. Las vidas de los que dormían en los otros pisos,
encima y debajo de él, no estaban confiadas á su vigilancia... Pero á los pocos días sintió
que le faltaba algo que era una de las mayores satisfacciones de su existencia: la voluntad
del poder, el gusto del mando.

Dos criadas de aire azorado acudían á sus voces y sus repiqueteos de timbre. Esto era todo
para él, que había mandado docenas de hombres de áspera dureza que infundían terror al bajar
en los puertos.

Nadie le consultaba ahora, mientras que en el mar todos buscaban su consejo y muchas veces
necesitaban interrumpir su sueño. La casa podía existir sin que él la visitase diariamente
desde las cuevas al tejado, revisando hasta el último grifo. Las mujeres que hacían la limpieza
por las mañanas le obligaban á refugiarse en el despacho con sus terrestres escobazos. No le
era permitido formular observaciones, no podía extender un brazo galoneado, lo mismo que cuando
reñía á la grumetería descalza y despechugada, exigiendo que la cubierta quedase limpia como
un salón. Se sentía empequeñecido, exonerado. Pensaba en Hércules vestido de mujer, hilando
su rueca. El amor á la familia le había hecho renunciar á su vida de varón poderoso.

Sólo el trato de su esposa, que le rodeaba de asiduos cuidados, como si quisiera compensarse
con esto de las largas separaciones, le hizo llevadera la situación. Además, sentía satisfecha
su conciencia al hacer de padre «terrestre», preocupándose de su hijo, que empezaba á prepararse
para ingresar en el Instituto, repasando sus libros, ayudándole en la comprensión de los textos.

Pero tampoco estos placeres fueron de larga duración. Le aburrían las tertulias de familia
en su casa y en la de sus parientes; las conversaciones con tíos, primos y sobrinos sobre ganancias
y negocios ó sobre los defectos de la tiranía centralista. Según ellos, todas las calamidades
del cielo y de la tierra procedían de Madrid. El gobernador de la provincia era el «cónsul
de España».

Estos mercaderes sólo interrumpían sus críticas para oír con religioso silencio la música de
Wágner golpeada en el piano por las niñas de la familia. Un amigo con voz de tenor cantaba
Lohengrin en catalán. El entusiasmo hacía rugir á los más exaltados: «¡El himno... el himno!»
No era posible equivocarse. Para ellos sólo existía un himno. Y acompañaban con una canturria
á media voz la música litúrgica de Los segadores.

Ulises recordaba con nostalgia su vida de comandante de trasatlántico: una vida amplia, mundial,
de incesantes y variados horizontes, de muchedumbres cosmopolitas. Se veía detenido en las
cubiertas por grupos de muchachas elegantes que le pedían nuevos bailes en la semana. Salían
á su paso faldas de blanco revoloteo, velos que ondulaban como nubes de colores, risas y trinos
parlantes en un español que parecía puesto en música; todo el estrépito juguetón de una jaula
de pájaros del Trópico.

Los ex presidentes de República--generales ó doctores que iban á descansar á Europa--le contaban
en el puente, con una gravedad napoleónica, los principales hechos de su historia. Los hombres
de negocios, al dirigirse á América, le confiaban sus planes estupendos: ríos cambiados de
cauce, ferrocarriles á través de la selva virgen, monstruosas fuerzas eléctricas extraídas
de cascadas de varios kilómetros de anchura, ciudades vomitadas por el desierto en unas semanas;
todas las maravillas de un mundo en la pubertad, que desea realizar cuanto concibe su joven
imaginación. Era el demiurgo del pequeño mundo flotante; disponía á su antojo de la alegría
y del amor.

En las tardes calurosas de la Línea, le bastaba dar una orden para sacudir la embrutecida modorra
de las cosas y los seres. «Que suba la música y que sirvan refrescos.» </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01154</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>453601</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14879</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> It seemed there was rained
ash on the immobility of things.

People offered the same aspect of neglect and decay. Ulysses met the poet skinny and yellow,
deep in an armchair, his beard white luenga, one eye almost closed and Another huge open.
Upon seeing the ocean, broad chest, strong man, tan, Labarta is began to mourn a child hiccups,
as if crying on the misery of human illusions, on the deceptive brevity
of life that needs the waves of constant renewal.

More work still cost Ferragut recognize a lady that was small and cramped with the poet. His skeleton
hung flaccid fat tissues, like rags of past luxury. The head was small, her face wrinkling
had the wintry apples, plums, of all fruits that contract and mummified, losing their liquid.
"Doña Pepa !...» The tuteaban old couple now in the presence of Ulysses, with the quiet amorality
of those who are close to death and forget the fears and scruples
of a life that is crumbling behind him.

The ocean seen in this physical misery the sad end of an absurd diet, happy and childish candy
serve as the basis of nutrition, the major rice-dish daily watermelon
and melon filling in between meals, ice cream served in cups enormous,
spreading the perfume of honeyed snow.

They both spoke sigh of illnesses, who judged incomprehensible, attributing to ignorance of doctors.
Consumption was suddenly attacking the people of the countries abundant. His life was smelted in
a blast of liquid sugar ... And yet guessed Ferragut the disobedience
of the old couple to the disciplines of the regime, its concealment
Child tricks to please their own fruits and syrups, the charm of its
existence.

The interview was short. The captain had to return to Grao, where he waited his transatlantic soon
to sail for South America.

The poet cried again, kissing his godson.

I would not see more to this giant that seemed to repel their weak hugs with the bellows of
his breath.

- Odysseus, my son ... Valencia always thinking ... Make for it all
you can ... And you know.

Always Valencia!

What he vowed all the poet, not understanding what was expected of
him Valencia, ocean simple wandering the seas.

Labarta wanted to accompany him to the door, but sank into his chair,
obedient to the despotism of his loving companion, who feared for
him major catastrophes.

Poor Dona Pepa!

... Ferragut felt like to laugh and to mourn when receiving a kiss from his mouth wrinkled,
whose hair had become spikes. It was a kiss that recalls old beauty in contact with a handsome, a
barren woman kiss caressing the child might have.

- The unfortunate Carmelo!

... Do not write, and do not read ... Ay! What will become of me? ...

He spoke of the decline of his poet with pity of a strong and healthy.

Is terrified to think about the years he could survive his master. Who look, not looked upon
herself.

A year later, the captain found in Port Said, at the back of the Philippines, a letter his godfather.
Doña Pepa had died, and Labarta, shaking his tearful stupor of its doldrums, the long goodbye with
a song.

Ulysses spent the eyes of the newspaper clipping was within the letter containing the last verses
of the poet. They were verses in Castilian. Bad! ... After that, it was undoubtedly his approaching
end.

He had no opportunity to see him again: he died while traveling.

Upon landing in Barcelona his mother gave him a letter written almost in agony. "Valencia, my son
always Valencia!"

And after repeating several times this recommendation, let him know it was his heir.

The books, statues, all the glorious memories Labarta, went to Barcelona
for decorate the house of the sailor.

Telemachus could entertain the small breaking the old crowns troubadour, tearing pictures of volumes,
with the unconsciousness of a spirited child who his father is far away and was exposed to
two ladies who adore him. Furthermore, the poet left his godson an old house in Valencia, more
land and a certain amount in marketable securities. Total: thirty thousand dollars.

The other guardian of his childhood, the strong Triton, remained insensitive
to the passage of time.

Ferragut met him several times, on arriving at Barcelona, ??installed
in your home, in dull hostility Dona Cristina, dedicating to Ribbon
and her son a part of the care that was previously only Ulysses.

Steven wanted the little house knew the great-grandparents.

- Did I leave it? ... You know that back in the Navy men are strong
as bronze.

You really leave me?

...

He doubted his influence with the angry gesture of soft Dona Cristina. "Trusting his grandson the
Triton, that instills the love of maritime adventure, like Ulysses?

... Behind blue devil!

The doctor wandered bewildered through the port of Barcelona ... Too much noise, too much movement.
He walked proudly beside Odysseus, making the adventures of his years of ocean tramp and cosmopolitan.
Saw in him the greatest Ferragut: sea man his grandparents, but with capacity; adventurous
of all the oceans as he had been but with a place on the bridge, coated conferring absolute command
responsibility and danger.

To re-embark Ulysses Triton retreating to their domains.

- Next time - said to console to leave without the child of his nephew.

And a few months later he reappeared, bigger and bigger, uglier, more tanned, with a smile silent words
before exploding in Ulysses, the same as a thundercloud burst in thunder.

Back from a trip to the Black Sea, Mrs Cristina said her son:

- Your uncle is dead.

The pious Christian lady lamented the disappearance of his brother,
spend their prayers, but he insisted with some cruelty in the story
of his sad end.

I could not forgive its fatal intervention in the fate of Ulysses.

Had died as he lived, at sea, victim for his temerity, without confession, as well as a pagan.

Another
legacy that fell on Ferragut ... His uncle had been released to swim on a sunny morning winter,
and had not returned. The older of the coastline explained to her how the accident: a fainting,
a collision with the rocks. The Dotor was still strong, but the years do not pass without
leaving footprint. Some believed in a fight with a "pot head" or other carnivorous fish which
hunt in the Mediterranean waters. In vain the fishermen took their boats for all incoming and
outgoing angularity of the promontory, exploring the dark caves and
low funds crystalline transparency.

Nobody could find the corpse of Triton.

Ferragut remembered the procession of Aphrodite that the doctor had described so often in the summer
nights in the distance watching the headlights.

Perhaps he had encountered the joyous procession of the Nereids, by binding to it forever.

This
absurd assumption that Ulysses made mentally, incredulous, sad smile,
repeated at the same time just thinking of many people from the Navy.

They refused to believe in his death. A sorcerer does not drown. Down would have found something
very interesting and when tired of living in the green depths swam back to his house.

No, the Dotor not dead.

And for many years, women who followed the coast at dusk quickened
their pace, crossing to distinguish in the dark waters a tree or a
package of seaweed.

They feared that arise from Triton soon, bearded, lewd, dripping, returning from his foray by the
mysterious depths of the sea.

IV

FREYA

The name of Ulises Ferragut began to be famous among the captains of the Spanish ports. Nautical
adventures from the time it came through very little in this popularity. Most of them had braved
greatest dangers, and if he liked, was the instinctive respect Men
who feel strong and simple with an intelligence that considered superior.

No other reading than his career, spoke with awe of the many books Ferragut filled the cabin,
many of them on matters that seemed mysterious. Some even made inaccurate statements to complement
the prestige of his comrade:

- He knows a lot ... In addition to ocean, is a lawyer.

The consideration of his fortune contributed equally to the appreciation. It was a major shareholder
to the shipping company that provided services. Calculated with proud peers exaggerated the wealth
of his mother, tasándola in millions.

Find friends all vessel flying the Spanish flag at the stern, no matter
what its port of origin and the regionalism of his crew.

All he wanted: the Basque captains, sober words, rude and familiarity confianzudo; Asturian
and Galician masters, lovesick and wasteful, that belie its character greed and sadness inland, the
masters in Andalusia, which seem to lead in its funny language reflects
the white light Cádiz and its wines, the captain of Valencia, to talk
politics on the bridge, imagining what could be the future Marine
Republic; Masters of Catalonia and Mallorca, who know the business
as thoroughly as their owners.

Whenever I connected the need to defend their rights, immediately thought Ulysses. None wrote
like him.

The old drivers coming from below, seamen who began his career in
the boats Coastal and barely fit their expertise to the handling of
books, Ferragut spoke proudly

- They say that people are gross sea
... There you have to Don Luis, who is one of us.

They can ask whatever they want ... A wise!

The name of Odysseus made them hesitate. I thought nickname, and not wanting to incur a lack
respect, had finally transformed into Don Luis.

For some, the only defect Ferragut was his good luck. He still had not lost a ship commanded by him. And
all good sailing ocean without rest should be history of these misfortunes to be a full captain.
Only the farmers do not lose ships.

When his mother died, Odysseus was undecided about the future, not
knowing whether to continue his seafaring life or take a brand new
one.

His relatives in Barcelona, ??merchants agile understanding for evaluation of a fortune, which
amounted to the notary had left and his wife, and adding Labarta and the doctor, just shy of
one million pesetas ... And a man with so much money going to continue
living the same as a poor captain needs salary to maintain his family?

...

His cousin Joaquin Blanes, owner of a knitwear factory, he repeatedly urged to follow their example.
Should stay on the ground and use their capital in Catalan industry. Ulysses was in the country,
by his mother and being born in the neighboring land of Valencia. Needed men of wealth and power
to intervene in government. Blanes was regionalist policy with the enthusiasm of a bourgeois
who is released into fictional adventures.

Tape did not say a word as to her spouse. She was the daughter of a sailor and had accepted be
the wife of another. Also, understand marriage according to family tradition: absolute mistress
women inside the house, but reliant on foreign affairs Lord's will, the warrior, household head,
not allowing thoughts or objections on their actions.

Ulysses was adopted for himself the decision to leave the seafaring life. Worked by the suggestions
of his cousins, he needed only a little dispute with one of the directors shipowner's house to
offer his resignation, no one could get him to back the requests and explanations of the other
associates.

In the first months of his earthly existence, missed the despairing immobility things. The world
was a disagreeable stiffness and hardness. He felt something akin to a principle faint to see
that everything was still where he left him, without allowing the
lower back and forth, the slightest fantasy dynamics.

In the morning, the half-opening his eyes, he felt the sweet sensation of freedom irresponsibly.
Nothing with the fate of the house. The lives of those who slept on the other floors, above and
below it, were not entrusted to their supervision ... But a few days did he needed something
that was one of the greatest satisfactions of his life: the will
of power, like remote.

Two maids came embarrassed to air their voices and peals of ringing. This was all for he who
had sent dozens of hard rough men that instilled terror down ports.

No one consulted him now, while at sea all sought his advice and often needed to disrupt your
sleep. The house could exist without his daily visit from the caves to the roof, going to the
last tap.

Women who did the cleaning in the morning he was forced to take refuge in the office with their land
broom. Not was allowed to comment, could not extend an arm gallon,
same as when scolded the barefoot and bare-chested grumetería, demanding
that the cover is clean as lounge. He felt dwarfed, exonerated. I
thought of Hercules dressed as a woman, spinning her distaff. The
love of family had made him renounce his life of a mighty man.

Only
the treatment of his wife, who surrounded himself with assiduous care,
as if to compensate with that of the long separation, he made the
situation bearable. And she was satisfied his conscience by making
father "earth", worrying about her son, who began to prepare to join
the Institute, reviewing their books, helping in the understanding
of texts.

But these pleasures were not long lasting. Bored him family
gatherings at home and in their relatives, conversations with uncles,
cousins ??and nephews on earnings and businesses or on the defects
of centralized tyranny. According to them, all the calamities of heaven
and earth came from Madrid. The governor of the province was the "consul
of Spain. "

These merchants only interrupted their criticism in religious
silence to hear the music Wagner struck on the piano by the children
of the family. A friend sang tenor Lohengrin in Catalan. The enthusiasm
was the most excited to roar: "The hymn ... the anthem! " There was
no mistaking. For them there was only one hymn. And accompanied with
a Canturri softly to the liturgical music of The Harvesters.

Ulises
recalled with nostalgia his life transatlantic commander: a life wide,
worldwide, incessant and varied horizons, cosmopolitan crowd. It looked
stopped on covered by groups of smart girls who asked new dances in
the week. Out his passage fluttering white skirts, veils that flowed
like colored clouds, laughter and trills Spanish speakers in a music
that seemed to set in, all the playful noise of a cage Tropic bird.
Former presidents of the Republic - general or doctors who came
to rest to Europe - we had on the bridge, with a serious Napoleon,
the main facts of his story. Men business, to go to America, he hoped
his great plans: rivers changed from river, rail through the jungle,
learned monstrous electric forces cascades of several kilometers wide,
the desert cities vomited in a few weeks; all the wonders of a world
in puberty, you want to conceive as her young imagination. It was
the demiurge of small floating world, provided he pleases of joy and
love.

In the hot afternoons of the Line, was enough to give an order
to shake the torpor brutish of things and beings. "Let the music up
and serve refreshments.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>