<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10370</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>30511</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>780</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Interrogada Sofía sobre el asunto, dijo que habían salido juntas hacia la escuela,
pero que la voluntariosa Melisa había tomado otro sendero. Por la tarde el mismo misterio,
y al llegar la noche vio el maestro a la señora Morfeo, cuyo corazón maternal estaba realmente
sobresaltado. La señora Morfeo había pasado todo el día buscándola, sin hallar traza que pudiera
ayudar al descubrimiento de la fugitiva. Arístides fue llamado como presunto cómplice, pero
aquel honrado muchacho consiguió convencer a la familia de su inmaculada inocencia. La señora
Morfeo alimentaba la viva esperanza de que aún hallaría a la niña ahogada en una zanja, o lo
que casi era tan terrible, cubierta de lodo, manchada y sin esperanza de que por medio de jabón
y agua volviera a su primitivo estado. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03289</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>530</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>870</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Sofia had some questions on the matter, she was sure that Aristedes had something to
do with the disappearance of Melissa even though they had gone their separate ways. All afternoon
they tried to solve the mystery, and when night came, Mrs. Morpheo, soft-heartedly worried about the
girl. She had spent the entire day searching for her but had found no clues to her disappearance that
could help in discovering the run-away. Even though Aristedes was at first thought to be an accomplice,
the honest boy was soon able to convince her family that he was innocent. Mrs. Morfeo feared that
there was a possiblily that the girl had drowned in a ditch, or, which seemed almost as tragic
to her way of thinking, that she would be found muddy, her cloting
stained so badly that there would be no hope that soap and water would
be able to bring them back to the original state</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>