<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05565</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>8812</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19605</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

PROEMIO.

Mi intento es escribir la memorable Expedicion y Jornada, que los Catalanes y Aragoneses hicieron
á las Provincias de Levante, cuando su fortuna y valor andaban compitiendo en el aumento de
su poder y estimacion, llamados por Andronico Paleologo Emperador de Griegos, en socorro y
defensa de su imperio y casa. Favorecidos y estimados en tanto que las armas de los Turcos
le tuvieron casi oprimido, y temió su perdicion y ruina; pero despues que por el esfuerzo de
los nuestros quedó libre de ellas, mal tratados y perseguidos con gran crueldad y fiereza bárbara;
de que nació la obligacion natural de mirar por su defensa y conservacion, y la causa de volver
sus fuerzas invencibles contra los mismos Griegos, y su Príncipe Andronico; las cuales fueron
tan formidables, que causaron temor y asombro á los mayores Príncipes de Asia y Europa, perdicion
y total ruina á muchas naciones y Provincias, y admiracion á todo el mundo. Obra será esta,
aunque pequeña por el descuido de los antiguos, largos en hazañas, cortos en escribirlas, llena
de varios y estraños casos, de guerras continuas en regiones remotas y apartadas con varios
Pueblos y gentes belicosas, de sangrientas batallas y victorias no esperadas, de peligrosas
conquistas acabadas con dichoso fin por tan pocos y divididos Catalanes y Aragoneses, que al
principio fueron burla de aquellas Naciones, y despues instrumento de los grandes castigos
que Dios hizo en ellas. Vencidos los Turcos en el primer aumento de su grandeza Othomana, desposeidos
de grandes y ricas Provincias de la Asia menor, y á viva fuerza y rigor de nuestras espadas
encerrados en lo mas áspero y desierto de los montes de Armenia. Después vueltas las armas
contra los Griegos, en cuyo favor pasaron, por librarse de una afrentosa muerte, y vengar agravios
que no se pudieran disimular sin gran mengua de su estimacion y afrenta de su nombre. Ganados
por fuerza muchos Pueblos y Ciudades, desbaratados y rotos poderosos ejércitos, vencidos y
muertos en campo Reyes y Príncipes, grandes Provincias destruidas y desiertas, muertos, cautivos,
ó desterrados sus moradores; venganzas merecidas mas que licitas. Thracia, Macedonia, Tesalia,
y Beocia penetradas y pisada á pesar de todos los Príncipes y fuerzas del Oriente, y últimamente
muerto á sus manos el Duque de Athenas con toda la nobleza de sus vasallos, y de los socorros
de Franceses y Griegos ocupado su estado, y en él fundado un nuevo señorío. En todos estos
sucesos no faltaron traiciones, crueldades, robos, violencias, y sediciones, pestilencia comun,
no solo de un ejército colecticio y débil por el corto poder de la suprema cabeza, pero de
grandes y poderosas Monarquias. Si como vencieron los Catalanes á sus enemigos, vencieran su
ambicion y codicia, no excediendo los límites de lo justo, y se conservarán unidos, dilataran
sus armas hasta los últimos fines del Oriente, y viera Palestina y Jerusalen, segunda vez las
banderas cruzadas. Porque su valor y disciplina militar, su constancia en las adversidades,
sufrimiento en los trabajos, seguridad en los peligros, presteza en las ejecuciones, y otras
virtudes militares las tuvieron en sumo grado, en tanto que la ira no las pervirtió. Pero el
mismo poder que Dios les entregó para castigar y oprimir tantas naciones, quiso que fuese el
instrumento de su propio castigo. Con la soberbia de los buenos sucesos, desvanecidos con su
prosperidad, llegaron á dividirse en la competencia del gobierno; divididos á matarse, con
que se encendió una guerra civil, tan terrible y cruel, que causó sin comparacion mayores daños
y muertes, que las que tuvieron con los extraños.

CAPITULO I.

Estado de los Reinos y Reyes de la casa de Aragon por este tiempo.

Antes de dar principio á nuestra historia, importa para su entera noticia decir el estado en
que se hallaban las provincias y Reyes de Aragon, sus ejércitos y armadas, sus amigos y enemigos;
principios necesarios para conocer donde se funda la principal causa de esta expedicion. El
Rey Don Pedro de Aragon, á quien la grandeza de sus hechos dió renombre de Grande, hijo de
Don Jaime el Conquistador fué casado con Gostanza hija de Manfredo Rey de Sicilia, á quien
Cárlos de Anjou con ayuda del Pontífice Romano, enemigo de la sangre de Federico Emperador,
quitó el Reino y la vida. Quedo Cárlos con su muerte Príncipe y Rey de las dos Sicilias, y
más después que el infeliz Coradino, último Príncipe de la casa de Suevia, roto y deshecho,
vino preso á sus manos, y por su órden y sentencia, se le cortó la cabeza en público cadahalso,
para eterna memoria de una vil venganza, y ejemplo grande de la variedad humana. Don Pedro
Rey de Aragon no se hallaba entónces con fuerzas para poder tomar satisfacion de la muerte
de Manfredo y Coradino, ni después de ser Rey le dieron lugar las guerras civiles, porque los
Moros de Valencia andaban levantados, y los Barones y Ricos hombres d Cataluña estaban desavenidos
y mal contentos; y tambien porque mostrándose enemigo declarado de Cárlos, provocaba contra
sí las armas de Francia, y las de la Iglesia, formidables por lo que tienen de divinas; los
Reinos de Sicilia y Nápoles lejos de los suyos, sus armas ocupadas en defenderse de los enemigos
mas vecinos. Todas estas dificultades detenian el ofendido ánimo del Rey, pero no de manera,
que borrasen la memoria del agravio. En unas vistas que tuvo con el Rey de Francia Filipe su
cuñado, entrevino Cárlos hijo del Rey de Nápoles, y deseando el Rey de Francia que fuesen amigos
y se hablasen, siempre Don Pedro se escusó, y mostró en el semblante el pesar y el disgusto
que tenia en el corazon, de que todos quedaron mal satisfechos y desabridos, y sin duda entónces
Cárlos se previniera y armara, si creyera que las fuerzas del Rey de Aragon fueran iguales
á su ánimo y pensamiento. Pero el cielo se las dió bastantes para tomar entera y justa satisfacion
de la sangre inocente de Coradino por medios tan ocultos, que no se supieron hasta que la misma
ejecucion los publicó.

Los míseros Sicilianos incitados de la insolencia Francesa, desenfrenada en su afrenta y deshonor,
tomaron las armas, y con aquel famoso hecho que comunmente llaman Vísperas Sicilianas, sacudieron
de la cerviz pública el insufrible yugo de los Franceses, y de Cárlos, que injustamente los
opremia, dejándoles al arbitrio y sujecion de ministros injustos; causa que las mas veces produce
mudanzas en los estados, y casos miserables en sus Príncipes. Acudió luego Cárlos con poderoso
ejército á castigar el atrevimiento y rebeldía de los súbditos. Ellos viendo cerrada la puerta
á toda piedad y clemencia, pusieron la esperanza de su remedio y amparo en Don Pedro Rey de
Aragon, que en esta sazon se hallaba en Africa, como verdadero Príncipe Christiano, con ejército
victoriso y triunfante de muchos Jeques y Reyes de Berbería, asistidos de la mayor parte de
la nobleza y soldados de sus Reinos. Llegaron ante su presencia los Embajadores de Sicilia,
llenos de lagrimas, luto y sentimiento; bastantes con esta triste demostracion á mover no solo
el ánimo de un Rey ofendido por particular agravio, pero el de cualquier otro que como hombre
sintiera. Acordaronle la muerte desdichada de Manfredo, y la afrentosa de Coradino, facilitaronle
la venganza con ayuda de los pueblos de Sicilia, tan aficionados á su nombre y enemigos del
de Francia. Ultimamente le propusieron el estado peligroso de su libertad, vidas y haciendas,
si no les amparaba su valor; por que ya Cárlos estaba sobre Mecina, y amenazaba el rigor de
su castigo un lastimoso fin á todo el Reino. Movido de estas razones y de las que su venganza
le ofrecia, acudió antes que su fama á Trapana con todo su poder, y fué con tanta presteza
sobre su enemigo, que apenas supo Cárlos que venia, cuando vió sus armas, y se halló forzado
á levantar el sitio y retirarse afrentosamente á Calabria.

Con este hecho el Pontifice como amigo, y el Rey de Francia como deudo, descubiertamente se
mostraron favorecedores de Cárlos, y enemigos de Don Pedro, y tomaron contra él las armas.
El Rey de Castilla que por el deudo y amistad debiera ayudarle, se salió á fuera, y se inclinó
á seguir el mayor poder. Don Jaime Rey de Mallorca, su hermano, tambien le desamparó, dando
ayuda y paso por sus estados á sus contrarios, aunque se escusó con las débiles fuerzas de
su Reino, desiguales á la defensa y oposicion de tan poderoso enemigo; disculpa con que muchas
veces los Príncipes pequeños, encubren lo mal hecho, atribuyendo á la necesidad lo que es ambicion.
Don Pedro con esto se halló sin amigos, solo acompañado de su valor, fortuna, y razon de satisfacer
el ultraje y afrenta de su casa. Al tiempo que le juzgaron todos por perdido, venció á sus
enemigos varias veces, reforzados de nuevas ligas y socorros, todo los deshizo y humilló en
mar, en tierra. Mantuvo el nombre de Aragon en gran reputacion y fama, y fué el primer Rey
de España, que puso sus banderas vencedoras en los Reinos de Italia, sobre cuyo fundamento
hoy se mira levantada su Monarquía. Hechado Cárlos de Sicilia, intentó con mayor poder reducirla
á su obediencia, y en esta hubo grandes y notables acontecimientos; pero siempre la casa de
Aragon, se aseguró en el Reino con victorias, no solo contra el poder de Cárlos, pero de todos
los mayores Príncipes de Europa que le ayudaban.

Murieron ambos Reyes competidores en la mayor furia y rigor de la guerra, y por derecho de
sucesion heredó á Cárlos Rey de Nápoles, su hijo primogénito del mismo nombre, que en este
tiempo se hallaba preso en Cataluña. A Don Pedro Rey de Aragon sucedieron sus dos hijos, Alfonso
mayor en los Reinos de España, Jaime en el de Sicilia. Prosiguiose la guerra hasta la muerte
de Alfonso, que por morir sin hijos fué Don Jaime llamado á la sucesion, y hubo de venir á
estos Reinos, dejando en Sicilia á Don Fadrique su hermano, para que la gobernase y defendiese
en su nombre. Después de su vuelta á España Don Jaime, recuperadas algunas fuerzas de sus Reinos,
renunció el de Sicilia á la Iglesia, temiendo que las armas Castellanas, Francesas y Eclesiásticas
á un mismo tiempo no le acometiesen, y persuadido de su madre Gostanza, que como mujer de singular
santidad, quiso más que su hijo perdiese el Reino, que alargar más tiempo el reconciliarse
con la Iglesia. Enviaronse á Sicilia para poner en efecto la renunciacion Embajadores de parte
de Don Jaime y de Gostanza, y entregar el Reino á los Legados del Pontífice Romano. Pero la
gente de guerra y los naturales indignados de la facilidad, con que su Rey renunciaba lo que
con tanto trabajo y sangre se habia adquirido y sustentado, y les entregaba tan sin piedad
á sus enemigos, de quien forzosamente habian de temer servidumbre y muerte; pareciéndoles á
los Sicilianos cierto el peligro, y á los Catalanes y Aragoneses mengua de reputacion, que
lo que no pudieron las armas de sus contrarios alcanzar en tantos años, se alcanzase por una
resolucion de un Rey mal aconsejado, volvieron á tomar las armas, y oponiéndose á los Legados,
persuadieron á Don Fadrique como verdadero sucesor del padre y del hermano, que se llamase
Rey, y tomase á su cargo la defensa comun.

Fué facil de persuadir un Príncipe de ánimo levantado, en lo mas florido de su juventud, y
que por otro medio no podia dejar ser vasallo y sujeto á las leyes del hermano: ocasion bastante,
cuando no fuera ayudada de tanta razon, á precipitar los pocos años de Don Fadrique. Llamose
Rey, y como á tal le admitieron y coronaron. Prevínose para la guerra cruel que le amenazaba,
asistido de buenos soldados, y del Pueblo fiel y pronto á su conservacion, teniéndole por segundo
libertador de la Patria. Opusose luego á Cárlos su mayor y mas vecino enemigo, al Papa que
amparaba y defendia su causa, y al Rey Don Jaime, que de hermano se le declaró enemigo, cuyas
fuerzas juntas le acometieron y vencieron en batalla naval, con que la guerra se tuvo por acabada,
y Don Fadrique por perdido. Pero la oculta disposicion de la providencia Divina, que algunas
veces fuera de las comunes esperanzas muda los sucesos para que conozcamos que sola ella gobierna
y rige, Don Fadrique se mantuvo en su Reino, con universal contento de los buenos, asombro
y terror de sus enemigos, y gloria de su nombre.

Deshizose poco después la liga, por apartarse de ella Don Jaime Rey de Aragon, con gran sentimiento
y quejas de sus aliados, porque sin las fuerzas de Aragon parecia cosa fatal y casi imposible
vencer un rey de su misma casa, y la experiencia lo mostró, pues apartado Don Jaime de la liga,
siempre los enemigos de Don Fadrique fueron perdiendo, y él acreditándose con victorias, hasta
forzarles á tratar de paces quedándose con el Reino; cosa que de solo pensarla se ofendian.
Concluyéronse después de algunas contradicciones, y se establecieron con mayor firmeza con
el casamiento, que luego se hizo de Leonor hija de Cárlos con Don Fadrique, con que el Reino
quedó libre y sin recelo de volver á la servidumbre antigua, y el Rey pacífico señor del estado
que defendió con tanto valor. El Rey Don Jaime su hermano sustentaba sus Reinos de Aragon,
Cataluña, y Valencia con suma paz y reputacion, amado de los súbditos, temido de los infieles,
poderoso en la mar, servido de famosos capitanes, aguardando ocasion de engrandecer su corona
á imitacion d sus pasados. El Rey de Mallorca Príncipe el menor de la casa de Aragon gozaba
pacíficamente el señorío de Mompeller, Condados de Rocellon, Cerdaña, y Conflent, difíciles
de conservar, por esta divididos, y tener vecinos mas poderosos, entre quien siempre fueron
fluctuando sus pequeños Reyes; pero por este tiempo vivia con reputacion, y con igual fortuna
que los otros Reyes de su casa.

CAPITULO II.

Eleccion de General.

Tenian los Reinos de Aragon, Mallorca y Sicilia el estado que habemos referido, cuando los
soldados viejos, y Capitanes de opinion, que sirvieron al gran Rey Don Pedro, á Don Jaime su
hijo, y últimamente á Don Fadrique en esta guerra de Sicilia, juzgándola ya por acabada, hechas
las paces mas seguras por el nuevo casamiento de Leonor con Fadrique, vínculo de mayor amistad
entre los poderosos, en tanto que el interés y la ambicion no le disuelven y deshacen, deshecho
causa de mas viva enemistad y odios implacables, pareciéndoles que no se podia esperar por
entónces ocasion de rompimiento y guerra, trataron de emprender otra nueva contra infieles
y enemigos del nombre cristiano en Provincias remotas y apartadas. Porque era tanto el esfuerzo
y valor de aquella milicia, y tanto el deseo de alcanzar nuevas glorias y triunfos, que tenian
á Sicilia por un estrecho campo para dilatar engrandecer su fama; y así, determinaron de buscar
ocasiones arduas, trances peligrosos, para que esta fuese mayor y mas ilustre.

Ayudaban á poner en ejecucion tan grandes pensamientos dos motivos, fundados en razón de su
conservacion. El primero fué la poca seguridad que habia de volver á España su patria, y vivir
con reputacion ella, por haber seguido las partes de Don Fadrique con tanta obstinacion contra
Don Jaime su Rey y señor natural; que auque Don Jaime no era Príncipe de ánimo vengativo, y
se tenía por cierto, que pues en la furia de la guerra contra su hermano no consintió que se
diesen por traidores los que le siguieron, menos quisiera castigar á sangre fria lo que pudo,
y no quiso en el tiempo que actualmente le estaban ofendiendo, siguiendo las banderas de su
hermano contra las suyas. Pero la Majestad ofendida del Príncipe natural, aunque remita el
castigo, queda siempre viva en el ánimo la memoria de la ofensa; y aunque no fuera bastante
para hacerles agravios, por lo menos impidiera el no servirse de ellos en los cargos supremos:
cosa indigna de lo que merecían sus servicios, nobleza y cargos administrados en paz y guerra.
El segundo motivo, y el que mas le obligó á salir de Sicilia, fué ver al Rey imposibilitado
de poderles sustentar con la largueza que antes, por estar la hacienda Real y Reino destruidos
por una guerra de veinte años, y ellos acostumbrados á gastar con exceso la hacienda ajena
como la propia cuando les faltaban despojos de pueblos y ciudades vencidas. Como entre ambas
cosas cesaron hechas las paces, y fenecida la guerra, juzgaron por cosa imposible reducirse
á vivir con moderacion.

El Rey Don Fadrique, y su padre y hermano, con su asistencia en la guerra, y como testigos
de las hazañas, industria y valor de los súbditos, pocas veces se engañaron en repartir las
mercedes; porque dieron más crédito á sus ojos, que á sus oidos, y siempre el premio á los
servicios, y no al favor. Con esto faltaban en sus Reinos quejosos y mal contentos, pero no
pudieron dar á todos los que le sirvieron estados y haciendas, con que algunos quedaron con
menos comodidad que sus servicios merecian. Pero como vieron que los Reyes dieron con suma
liberalidad y grandeza lo que lícitamente pudieron á los mas señalados Capitanes, atribuyeron
solo á su desdicha, y á la virtud, y valor incomparable de los que fueron preferidos, el hallarse
inferiores.

Estas fueron las causas que movían los ánimos en comun para tratar de engrandecer en nuevas
empresas y conquistas. Los más principales Capitanes que animaban y alentaban á los demás,
fueron cuatro, debajo de cuyas banderas, sirvieron Roger de Flor Vicealmirante de Sicilia,
Berenguer de Entenza, Ferran Jimenez de Arenós, ambos ricos hombres, y Berenguer de Rocafort;
todos conocidos y estimados por soldados de grande opinion. Comunicaron sus pensamientos entre
sus valedores y amigos, y hallándoles con buena disposicion y ánimo de seguirles en cualquier
jornada, se resolvieron de emprender la que pareciese más útil y honrosa. Para la conclusion
de este trato se juntaron en secreto, y antes de discutir sobre su expedicion, quisieron darle
cabeza; porque sin ella fuera inútil cualquier consejo y determinacion, faltando quien puede
y debe mandar. Con acuerdo comun de los que para esto se juntaron, fué nombrado por General
Roger de Flor Vicealmirante, poderoso en la mar, valiente y estimado soldado, práctico y bien
afortunado marinero, persona que en riquezas y dinero excedia á todos los demas Capitanes;
causa principal de ser preferido.

CAPITULO III.

Quien fué Roger de Flor.

Nació Roger de Flor, á quien los nuestros eligieron pro General y suprema cabeza, en Brindiz
de padres nobles, su padre fué Alemán, llamado Ricardo de Flor, cazador del Emperador Federico
su madre Italiana, y natural del mismo lugar. Murió Ricardo en la batalla que Cárlos de Anjou
tuvo con Coradino, cuyas partes seguia, por ser nieto de Federico su Príncipe y señor. Cárlos
insolente con la victoria, después de haber cortado la cabeza á Coradino, confiscó las haciendas
de todos los que tomaron las armas en su ayuda. Con esta pérdida quedó Roger y su madre con
suma pobreza, y con la misma se crió hasta la edad de quince años, que un caballero Francés,
religioso del Temple, llamado Yassaill, se le aficionó con ocasion de asistir en Brindiz, con
el Alcon nave del Temple, cuyo Capitan era. Navegó juntamente con él Roger algunos años, y
ganó tan buena opinion en el ejercicio que profesaba, que la Religion le recibió por suyo,
dándole el hábito de fray sargento, en aquel tiempo casi igual al de caballero. Con el Roger
comenzó á ser conocido y temido en todo el mar de Levante, al tiempo que Prolemayde, dicha
por otro nombre Acre, se rendió á las armas de Melech Taseraf Sultan de Egipto, Roger, como
refiere Pachimerio, era uno de los asistian en un Convento del Temple; y viendo que la ciudad
no se podia defender, recogió muchos Cristianos en un navío, con la hacienda que pudieron escapar
de la crueldad y furia de los Bárbaros.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09586</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>269391</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18202</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Proem.

My intent is to write the memorable Shipping and Day, which the Catalans and Aragonese made
to the provinces of East, when his fortune and went competing value in increasing power and
esteem, called by Andronico Paleologo Greek Emperor in relief and defense of his government
and home. Favored and esteemed as the weapons of the Turks I had almost depressed, and feared
his perdition and ruin, but after that effort ours was free of them, mistreated and persecuted with
great cruelty and barbaric ferocity; was born the natural obligation to look for their defense
and preservation, and the cause of back invincible forces against the Greeks themselves, and
Prince Andronico, which were formidable, causing fear and awe to the greatest princes of Asia and
Europe, perdition and total destruction to many nations and provinces, and admiration to all
the world. Will this work, though small by the neglect of the old, long in deeds, write short,
full various and strange cases of continuous warfare in remote and isolated several Towns and
warlike people, of bloody battles and unexpected victories of dangerous finished with gains
so happy by so few and divided Catalans and Aragonese, that were initially mockery of those
nations, and after the great instrument of punishment God made them. Defeated the Turks in
the first increase of its greatness Othomana, dispossessed large and wealthy provinces of Asia Minor,
and by main strength and rigor of our swords locked in the most harsh and desert mountains
of Armenia. After the weapons around against the Greeks, on whose behalf they passed, to get
rid of an ignominious death, and avenge wrongs not without great disgrace could hide their esteem
and disgrace of his name. Won by force many towns and cities, powerful armies routed and broken,
defeated and field dead kings and princes, great Provinces destroyed and deserted, dead, captive,
or exiled its inhabitants, more than deserved revenge lawful. Thracia, Macedonia, Thessaly, and Boeotia
tread penetrated and in spite of all the princes and forces of the East, and lately died at his
hands the Duke of Athens with all the nobility of his subjects, and the relief of French and Greeks
held their state, and he formed a new dominion. In all these events not without treachery, cruelty,
theft, violence and sedition, pestilence common, not only an army colecticio and weak for
the short head of the supreme power, but great and powerful monarchies. If, as the Catalans defeated
his enemies, overcome their ambition and greed, not to exceed the limits of right, and kept
together, dilating their weapons until the final end of East, and see Palestine and Jerusalem,
the second time crossed flags. For his courage and military discipline, his constancy in adversity,
suffering in the work, safety hazards, alacrity in executions, and other the military virtues
were in the highest degree, while the anger is not perverted. But same power that God gave
them to punish and oppress many nations wanted it to be the instrument of his own punishment.
With the pride of the good events, faded with prosperity, came to be divided into the competence
of government, divided to kill, with which ignited a civil war, terrible and cruel, which caused
no major damage comparison and deaths, that they had with strangers.

CHAPTER I.

State of the Kingdoms and Kings of Aragon's house by this time.

Before beginning to our story, it is important for whole words, the state news who were the provinces
and Kings of Aragon, his armies and navies, their friends and enemies; principles necessary
to know which is founded the main cause of this expedition. The Rey Don Pedro of Aragon, whom
the greatness of his works gave renown Great, son of Don Jaime el Conquistador Gostanza was
married to the daughter of King Manfred of Sicily, whom Charles of Anjou with the help of the
Roman Pontiff, the blood enemy of Emperor Frederick, removed the Kingdom and life. Charles
stayed with his death Prince and King of the Two Sicilies, and more after the unfortunate Coradin,
last Prince of the house of Swabia, broken and destroyed, prisoner came into his hands, and by
his order and sentence, he was beheaded in public scaffold, for eternal memory of a vicious
revenge, and great example of the human variety. Don Pedro King of Aragon was not then strong
enough to take the death satisfacion Manfredo and Coradin, or later to be King he led the civil
wars, because Valencia went Moors raised, and the Barons and rich men were quarreling d Catalonia
and malcontents, and also because they were declared enemy of Charles, provoked against yes
the arms of France, and the Church, so formidable are the divine, the Kingdoms of Sicily and
Naples out of his house, his arms employed in defense against enemies more neighbors. All these
difficulties stopped the mood offended the King, but not in any way, erasing the memory of the
grievance. In some views he had with the King of France Filipe its brother, Charles Entreviñas
son of King of Naples, King of France wanting to be friends and talk, always excused Don Pedro and
his face showed sorrow and disgust I had in my heart, that they were all satisfied and bland
bad, and certainly then Charles was prevented and arm, if he believed that the forces of King of
Aragon were equal his mind and thought. But the sky gave them enough to take full and fair
satisfacion of the innocent blood of so-hidden Coradin means, not learned until it the published execution.

Sicilianos
Outrageous insolence prompted the French, unbridled in their shame and dishonor took up arms, and
made the famous Sicilian Vespers commonly called, shook the public
cervix insufferable yoke of the French, and Charles, which unfairly
opremia, leaving to the discretion and restraint of ministers unjust
cause the most often occurs removals in the states and their princes
miserable cases.

Charles then went to powerful army to punish the bold and rebellious subjects. They closed the door
watching to all piety and mercy, hoping to put their medicine and shelter in King Don Pedro Aragon,
which at this juncture was in Africa, as a true Prince Christiano, with army victoriso and
successful in many Sheikhs and Kings of Barbary, assisted by the majority of the nobility and soldiers
in their kingdoms. Came before him Ambassadors Sicily filled with tears, mourning and feeling,
enough with this sad demonstration to move not only the mind of a King offended by particular
grievance, but that of any man other than as felt. Acordaronle unfortunate death of Manfred,
and the insulting of Coradin, facilitaronle revenge with the help of the people of Sicily, to his
name as fans and foes France. Recently I proposed a dangerous state of liberty, life and property,
if they do not maintain their value, for that and Charles was on Mecina, and threatened the
rigor of his punishment a pitiful end to the Kingdom. Moved by these reasons and that his vengeance
offered him, his reputation went before them Trapana with all his might, and went so quickly
on his enemy, who hardly knew Charles was coming, when he saw their weapons, and found himself forced
to raise the siege and withdraw folly to Calabria.

This made the pontiff as a friend, and the King of France and deed, the bare Charles showed
favoring and enemies of Don Pedro, and took arms against him. The King of Castile and friendship
for bereaved should help, it came to be, and bent to follow the most power. Don Jaime King
of Mallorca, his brother, also forsook him, giving help and step by their states to their opponents,
even if excused with the weak forces His Kingdom, uneven and opposition
to the defense of such a powerful enemy, apologize to many Sometimes
the young princes, conceal it wrong, attributing to the need that
is ambition.

Don Pedro with friends this was found not only with his courage, fortune, and reason to meet
The outrage and disgrace of his house. While he tried all lost, defeated his enemies repeatedly
reinforced new leagues and relief, all the broke and humiliated in sea, on land. Aragon kept the
name of a great reputation and fame, and was the first King of Spain, who placed his winning
flags in the Kingdom of Italy, on whose basis Today we look raised his monarchy. By taking
Charles of Sicily, he tried to reduce it further his obedience, and this was great and notable
events, but always home Aragon, secured in the Kingdom with victories, not only against the power of
Charles, but all the greatest Princes of Europe to help him.

Reyes died two largest competitors in the rage and rigor of the war, and right inherited succession
to Charles King of Naples, his eldest son the same name, which in this time was a prisoner
in Catalonia. A Don Pedro King of Aragon succeeded by his two sons, Alfonso greatest in the
Kingdom of Spain, Jaime in Sicily. Prosiguiose war to the death Alfonso, who die without children
was Don Jaime called to the succession, and had to come to these realms, leaving Sicily to
his brother Don Frederic, to govern and defend the on their behalf. After his return to Spain,
Don Jaime, recovered some of their forces Kingdoms Sicilian resigned
to the Church, fearing that the weapons Spanish, French and Church
at the same time not rushed, and his mother Gostanza convinced that
as a woman of singular holiness, wanted more than his son lost the
kingdom, which extend over time reconciled with the Church.

Enviaronse to Sicily to give effect to the renunciation Ambassadors from Don Jaime and Gostanza,
and provide the kingdom with the legacies of the Roman Pontiff. But people from war and natural
indignation of the facility, with its King resigned as with so much blood work and had acquired
and sustained, and gave them so mercilessly his enemies, who had feared forced servitude and
death, it seems to Sicilians true danger, and to the Catalans and Aragonese decline in reputation,
which what weapons they could not reach their opponents in so many years, was reached by a resolution
of a misguided King, returned to take up arms and oppose the Legacies, Don persuaded Frederic as
a true successor to the father and brother, whose name was King, and to take charge of common defense.

It
was easy to persuade a prince of spirits lifted, the flower of his youth, and which otherwise could
not fail to be a vassal and subject to the laws of brother occasion enough, if it was not
helped so many reasons, to precipitate the few years of Don Frederic. Llamosa King, and as such
he was admitted and crowned. Prevínose for the cruel war that threatened him, assisted by good
soldiers, and the faithful and soon to their preservation, holding him for the second liberator
of the country. Opusose to Charles after its largest and most neighboring enemy, the Pope
protected and defended their cause, and Rey Don Jaime, who was declared enemy brother, whose
joint forces attacked and defeated him in battle naval war that was to complete, and Don Frederic
lost. But the hidden disposition of Divine Providence, that some sometimes out of the common
hopes to move the events we know that it alone governs and governed, Don Frederic remained in
his Kingdom, with universal content of the good, wonder and terror of their enemies, and glory
of his name.

Deshizose shortly after the league, away from her Don Jaime King of Aragon, with great feeling and
complaints of their allies, because without the forces of Aragon seemed something fatal and
almost impossible conquer a king of her home, and experience showed, as Don Jaime paragraph League,
always the enemies of Don Frederic were losing, and he credited with victories, even to try to force
peace by staying with the Kingdom, something that's just thinking it was offended. Concluyéronse
after some contradictions, and more firmly established with marriage, which later became Eleanor
daughter of Charles, with Don Frederic, with which the United was free and without any danger of returning
to the old easement, and Mr. King peaceful state so valiantly defended. El Rey Don Jaime his
brother sustained their kingdoms of Aragon Catalonia, and Valencia with great peace and reputation,
beloved of his subjects, dreaded by the infidels, powerful at sea, served as celebrity captains,
awaiting an opportunity of enlarging his crown imitation d their
pasts.

El Rey de Mallorca au-Prince under the house of Aragon enjoyed the lordship of Montpellier peacefully,
Rocellon Counties, Cerdanya, and Conflent, difficult to preserve, for this split, and have more
powerful neighbors, among whom were always Reyes fluctuating their small, but by this time lived
with reputation, and fortune as the other kings of his house.

CHAPTER II.

General Election.

They had the Realms of Aragon, Majorca and Sicily the state of which we have referred, when old
soldiers, and captains of opinion, who served the great King Don Pedro, Don Jaime their son,
Don Frederic lately in this war in Sicily, judging and for finished, done peace more secure
by the remarriage of Leonor Fadrique greater friendship link among the powerful, while the
interest and ambition will not dissolve and break down, broken more alive because of enmity
and hatred implacable, thinking that he could not wait then chances of war breaking and tried
to start a new one against infidels and enemies of Christianity in
remote and isolated provinces.

Because it was so much effort and the value of that militia, and
both the desire to achieve new glories and victories, they had to
Sicily by a narrow field to dilate to increase his fame, and so they
decided to seek sometimes arduous, dangerous trances, for this is
greater and more illustrious.

Helped to give effect to such large thoughts two reasons, based on grounds of conservation. The
first was the lack of security which had to return to Spain, his homeland, and live with her reputation
for having followed the parts of Don Frederic with such obstinacy against Rey Don Jaime and his
natural lord, that Don Jaime auque Prince of mind was not vindictive, and was held to be true,
that as in the fury of a war against his brother consented to should give them as traitors
those who followed him, less punishing in cold blood like he could, and refused at the time
you were offended now, following the flags of against his brother. But the offended Majesty natural
Prince, but refer the punishment is always alive in the mind the memory of the offense, and although
not enough grievances for them, at least not impede the use of them in the highest positions: unworthy
of their service they deserved, nobility and administrative positions
in peace and war.

The second reason, and the one you forced to leave Sicily, was unable to see the King poderles
support of the largesse that before, being the property Real and United destroyed by a war of
twenty years, and they used to spend in excess the property of others as your own when they lacked
spoils of conquered cities and towns. As between the two ceased things made peace, and war
defunct, judged by reduced impossible thing to live in moderation.

Don King Frederic, and his father and brother, his assistance in the war, and as witnesses of
the deeds, industry and courage of his subjects, rarely deceived in dealing the grants, because
they gave more credit to his eyes, his ears, and always the prize to the services, not to favor.
With this missing from your complainers and malcontents Kingdoms, but not could give to all who
served states and estates, with some left with less comfort that his services deserved. But they
saw that the Kings were to sum generosity and greatness which could lawfully Captains to the
most signal, attributed only to his misery, and virtue, and incomparable value of which were preferred,
the found lower.

These were the reasons that moved the minds together to try to enlarge in new companies and
conquests.

Most major Captains who cheered and encouraged others were four, under whose flags, Vice Admiral
Roger de Flor served in Sicily Berenguer de Entenza, Ferran Jimenez Arenas, both rich men,
and Berenguer de Rocafort; all known and appreciated by soldiers of great reviews. Shared
their thoughts between its supporters and friends, and being with good disposition and courage
to follow them in any day, resolved to undertake that seem more useful and honorable. For the
conclusion This deal came together in secret, and before discussing his expedition, wanted
to give head because she was useless without any advice and determination, who can missing and
must be controlled. With the common understanding that this came together, was appointed General
Vice Admiral Roger de Flor, powerful at sea, brave and respected
soldier, practical and well lucky sailor, who in wealth and money
exceeded all other captains; primary cause to be preferred.

CHAPTER III.

Who was Roger de Flor.

Roger de Flor was born, whom the General and our elected supreme head pro at Brindiz noble parents,
his father was German, called Ricardo de Flor, Emperor Frederick Hunter his mother Italian, and
natural place. Ricardo died in the battle that Charles of Anjou had with Coradin, whose party
continued, being grandson of Frederick the Prince and Lord. Charles insolent victory, after
having cut the head to Coradin, confiscated the estates of all those who took up arms to help.
With this loss was Roger and his mother extreme poverty, and it was raised until the age of
fifteen, a French knight, Temple religious, called Yassaill, is fond
on the occasion of Brindiz assist with Alcon ship the Temple, whose
Captain was.

Roger sailed with him a few years and won such a good opinion in
the year professed that he received for his Religion, Brother giving
the habit of sergeant at that time almost equal to that gentleman.

With Roger began to be known and feared throughout the Levantine
Sea, while Prolemayde Said Acre by another name, surrendered to the
arms of Melech Taseraf Sultan of Egypt, Roger, as Pachymeres referred,
was one of those attending a convent of the Temple, and seeing that
the city could not defend, collected many Christians in a ship, with
the cattle that escaped of cruelty and rage of the Barbarians.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>