<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document06376</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>19015</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24292</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Me has servido, me has acompañado, me has
sostenido en mi adversidad. Eres buena, buenísima; pero no abuses, hija; no me digas que venías
a casa con el moro de los dátiles, porque creeré que te has vuelto loca.

--A casa le traía, sí, señora, como traje a Frasquito Ponte, por caridad... Si hubo misericordia
con el otro, ¿por qué no ha de haberla con este? ¿O es que la caridad es una para el caballero
de levita, y otra para el pobre desnudo? Yo no lo entiendo así, yo no distingo... Por eso le
traía; y si a él no le admite, será lo mismo que si a mí no me admitiera.

--A ti siempre... digo, siempre no... quiero decir... es que no tenemos hueco en casa... Somos
cuatro mujeres, ya ves... ¿Volverás mañana? Coloca a ese desdichado en una buena fonda... no,
¡qué disparate! en el Hospital... No tienes más que dirigirte a D. Romualdo... Dile de mi parte
que yo le recomiendo... que lo mire como cosa mía... ¡ay, no sé lo que digo!... como cosa tuya,
y tan tuya... En fin, hija, tú verás... Puede que os alberguen en la casa del Sr. de Cedrón,
que debe ser muy grande... tú me has dicho que es un casetón enorme que parece un convento...
Yo, bien lo sabes, como criatura imperfecta, no tengo la virtud en el grado heroico que se
necesita para alternar con la pobretería sucia y apestosa... No, hija, no: es cuestión de estómago
y de nervios... De asco me moriría, bien lo sabes. ¡Pues digo, con la miseria que traerás sobre
ti!... Yo te quiero, Nina; pero ya conoces mi estómago... Veo una mota en la comida, y ya me
revuelvo toda, y estoy mala tres días... Llévate tu ropa, si quieres mudarte... Juliana te
dará lo que necesites... ¿Oyes lo que te digo? ¿Por qué callas? Ya, ya te entiendo. Te haces
la humilde para disimular mejor tu soberbia... Todo te lo perdono; ya sabes que te quiero,
que soy buena para ti... En fin, tú me conoces... ¿Qué dices?

--Nada, señora, no he dicho nada, ni tengo nada que decir--murmuró Nina entre dos suspiros
hondos--. Quédese con Dios.

--Pero no te irás enojada conmigo--añadió con trémula voz Doña Paca, siguiéndola a distancia
en su lenta marcha por el pasillo.

--No, señora... ya sabe que yo no me enfado...--replicó la anciana mirándola más compasiva
que enojada--. Adiós, adiós».

Obdulia condujo a su madre al comedor diciéndole: «¡Pobre Nina!... Se va. Pues mira, a mí me
habría gustado ver a ese moro Muza y hablar con él... ¡Esta Juliana, que en todo quiere meterse!...».

Atontada por crueles dudas que desconcertaban su espíritu, Doña Francisca no pudo expresar
ninguna idea, y siguió revisando los cubiertos desempeñados. En tanto, Juliana, conduciendo
a la Nina hasta la puerta con suave opresión de su mano en la espalda de la mendiga, la despidió
con estas afectuosas palabras: «No se apure, señá Benina, que nada ha de faltarle... Le perdono
el duro que le presté la semana pasada, ¿no se acuerda?

--Señora Juliana, sí que me acuerdo. Gracias.

--Pues bien: tome además este otro duro para que se acomode esta noche... Váyase mañana por
casa, que allí encontrará su ropa...

--Señora Juliana, Dios se lo pague.

--En ninguna parte estará usted mejor que en la Misericordia, y si quiere, yo misma le hablaré
a D. Romualdo, si a usted le da vergüenza. Doña Paca y yo la recomendaremos... Porque mi señora
madre política ha puesto en mí toda su confianza, y me ha dado su dinero para que se lo guarde...
y le gobierne la casa, y le suministre cuanto pueda necesitar. Mucho tiene que agradecer a
Dios por haber caído en estas manos...

--Buenas manos son, señora Juliana.

--Vaya por casa, y le diré lo que tiene que hacer.

--Puede que yo lo sepa sin necesidad de que usted me lo diga.

--Eso usted verá... Si no quiere ir por casa...

--Iré.

--Pues, señá Benina, hasta mañana.

--Señora Juliana, servidora de usted».

Bajó de prisa los gastados escalones, ansiosa de verse pronto en la calle. Cuando llegó junto
al ciego, que en lugar próximo le esperaba, la pena inmensa que oprimía el corazón de la pobre
anciana reventó en un llorar ardiente, angustioso, y golpeándose la frente con el puño cerrado,
exclamó: «¡Ingrata, ingrata, ingrata!

--No yorar ti, amri--le dijo el ciego cariñoso, con habla sollozante--. Señora tuya mala ser,
tú ángela.

--¡Qué ingratitud, Señor!... ¡Oh mundo... oh miseria!... Afrenta de Dios es hacer bien...

--Dir nosotros luejos... dirnos, amri... Dispreciar ti mondo malo.

--Dios ve los corazones de todos; el mío también lo ve... Véalo, Señor de los cielos y la tierra,
véalo pronto».

XXXIX

Dicho lo que antecede, se limpió las lágrimas con mano temblorosa, y pensó en tomar las resoluciones
de orden práctico que las circunstancias exigían.

«Dirnos, dirnos--replicó Almudena cogiéndola del brazo.

--¿A dónde?--dijo Nina con aturdimiento--. ¡Ah! lo primero a casa de D. Romualdo».

Y al pronunciar este nombre se quedó un instante lela, enteramente idiota.

--«R'maldo mentira--declaró el ciego.

--Sí, sí, invención mía fue. El que ha llevado tantas riquezas a la señora será otro, algún
D. Romualdo de pega... hechura del demonio... No, no, el de pega es el mío... No sé, no sé.
Vámonos, Almudena. Pensemos en que tú estás malo, que necesitas pasar la noche bien abrigadito.
La señá Juliana, que es la que ahora corta el queso en la casa de mi señora, y todo lo suministra...
en buen hora sea... me ha dado este duro. Te llevaré a los palacios de Bernarda, y mañana veremos.

--Mañana, dir nosotros Hierusalaim.

--¿A dónde has dicho? ¿A Jerusalén? ¿Y dónde está eso? ¡Vaya, que querer llevarme a ese punto,
como si fuera, un suponer, Jetafe o Carabanchel de Abajo!

--Luejos, luejos... tú casar migo y ser tigo migo uno. Dirnos Marsella por caminos pidiendo...
En Marsella vapora... pim, pam... Jaffa... ¡Hierusalaim!... Casarnos por arreligión tuya, por
arreligión mía... quierer tú... Veder tú sepolcro; entrar tú S'nagoga rezar Adonai...

--Espérate, hijo, ten un poco de calma, y no me marees con las invenciones de tu cabeza deliriosa.
Lo primero es que te pongas bueno.

--Mí estar bueno... mí no c'lentura ya... mí contentada. Tú viener migo siempre, por mondo
grande, caminas mochas, libertanza, mar, terra, legría mocha...

--Muy bonito; pero ahora caigo en la cuenta de que tú y yo tenemos hambre, y entraremos a cenar
en cualquier taberna. Si te parece, aquí en la Cava Baja...

--Onde quierer tú, yo quierer...».

Cenaron con relativo contento, y Almudena no cesaba de ponderar las delicias de irse juntitos
a Jerusalén, pidiendo limosna por tierra y por mar, sin prisa, sin cuidados. Tardarían meses,
medio año quizás; pero al fin darían con sus cuerpos en la Palestina, aunque la emprendiesen
por la vía terrestre hasta Constantinopla. ¡Pues no había pocos países bonitos que recorrer!
Objetaba Nina que ella tenía ya los huesos duros para correría tan larga, y el africano, no
sabiendo ya cómo convencerla, le decía: «Ispania terra n'gratituda... Correr luejos, juyando
de n'gratos ellos».

En cuanto cenaron se recogieron en casa de Bernarda, dormitorios de abajo, a dos reales cama.
Muy tranquilo estuvo Almudena toda la noche, sin poder coger el sueño, delirando con el viajecito
a Jerusalén; y Benina, por ver de calmarle, mostrábase dispuesta a emprender tan larga peregrinación.
Inquieto y dolorido, cual si la cama fuera de zarzas punzadoras, Mordejai no hacía más que
volverse de un lado para otro, quejándose de ardores en la piel y de picazones molestísimas,
las cuales no eran motivadas, dicha sea la verdad, por cosa alguna tocante a la miseria que
se combate con polvos insecticidas. Ello provenía quizás de un extraño giro que la fiebre tomaba,
y que se manifestó a la mañana siguiente en un rojo sarpullo en brazos y piernas. El infeliz
se rascaba con desesperación, y Benina le llevó a la calle, con la esperanza de que el aire
libre y el ejercicio le servirían de alivio. Después de vagar pidiendo, por no perder la costumbre,
fueron a la calle de San Carlos, y subió Benina a ver a Juliana, que allí le tenía su ropa,
y se la dio en un lío, diciéndole que mientras gestionaban para que fuese recogida en la Misericordia,
se albergara en cualquier casa barata, con o sin el hombre, aunque mejor le estaba, para su
decoro, dejarse de compañía y tratos tan indecentes. Añadió que en cuanto se limpiara bien
de toda la inmundicia que había traído del Pardo, podía ir a visitar a Doña Paca, que gozosa
la recibiría; pero que no pensase en volver a su lado, porque los hijos se oponían a ello,
atentos a que su mamá estuviese bien servida, y suministrada con regularidad. Con todo se mostró
conforme la buena mujer, que en ello veía una voluntad superior incontrastable.

No era mala persona Juliana; dominante, eso sí, ávida de mostrar las grandes dotes de gobierno
que le había dado Dios, mujer que no soltaba a dos tirones la presa caída en sus manos. Pero
no carecía de amor al prójimo, se compadecía de Benina, y habiéndole dicho esta que el moro
la esperaba en la calle, quiso verle y juzgarle por sus propios ojos. Que la traza del pobre
africano le pareció lastimosa, se conoció en el gesto que hizo, en la cara que puso, y en el
acento con que dijo: «Ya le conocía yo a este, de verle pedir en la calle del Duque de Alba.
Es buen punto, y muy enamorado. ¿Verdad, Sr. Almudena, que le gustan a usted las chicas?

--Gustar mí B'nina, amri...

--Ajajá... Pobre Benina, ¡no se le ha sentado mala mosca! Si lo hace por caridad, de veras
digo que es usted una santa.

--El pobrecito está enfermo, y no puede valerse».

Y como el morito, acometido de violentísimas picazones en brazos y pecho, hiciera garras de
sus dedos para rascarse con gana, la ribeteadora se acercó para mirarle los brazos, que había
desnudado de la manga. «Lo que tiene este hombre--dijo con espanto--es lepra... ¡Jesús, qué
lepra, seña Benina! He visto otro caso: un pobre, del Moro también, mendigo él, de Orán él,
que pedía en Puerta Cerrada, junto al taller de mi padrastro. Y se puso tan perdido, que no
había cristiano que se le acercara, y ni en los santos Hospitales le querían recibir...

«Picar, picar mocha--era lo único que Almudena decía, pasando las uñas desde el hombro a la
mano, como se pasaría un peine por la madeja.

Disimulando su asco, por no lastimar a la infeliz pareja, Juliana dijo a Nina: «¡Pues no le
ha caído a usted mala incumbencia con este tipo! Mire que esa sarna se pega. Buena se va usted
a poner, sí señora; buena, bonita y barata... O es usted más boba que el que asó la manteca,
o no sé lo que es usted».

Con miradas no más expresó Nina su lástima del pobre ciego, su decisión de no abandonarle,
y su conformidad con todas las calamidades que quisiera enviarle Dios. Y en esto, Antonio Zapata,
que a su casa volvía, vio a su mujer en el grupo; llegose a ella presuroso, y enterado de lo
que hablaban, aconsejó a Benina que llevara al moro a la consulta de enfermedades dermatológicas
en San Juan de Dios.

«Más cuenta le tiene--afirmó Juliana--mandarle para su tierra.

--Luejos, luejos--dijo Almudena--. Dir nos Hierusalaim.

--No está mal. 'De Madrid a Jerusalén, o la familia del tío Maroma...'. Bueno, bueno. A otra
cosa, mujercita mía, no pegues y escucha. No he podido hacer tus encargos, porque... te digo
que no pegues.

--Porque te has ido al billar, granuja... Sube, sube, y ajustaremos cuentas.

--No subo porque tengo que volver a los carros de pateta.

--¿Qué dices, granuja?

--Que no va el carro grande por menos de cuarenta reales, y como me mandaste que no pasase
de treinta...

--Tendré yo que verlo. Estos hombres no sirven mas que de estorbo, ¿verdad, Nina?

--Verdad. ¿Y qué es? ¿Se muda la señora?

--Sí, mujer; pero ya no podrá ser hasta mañana, porque este marido tonto que me ha dado Dios,
salió antes de las ocho a tomar la casa y avisar el carro, y ya ve usted a qué hora se descuelga
por aquí, con todo ese cuajo, sin haber hecho nada.

--Bastante he corrido, chica: A las nueve entraba yo en casa de mamá con el contrato para que
lo firmara. Ya ves si ganábamos tiempo. ¿Pero tú sabes el que he perdido con Frasquito Ponte,
que nos ha dado una tabarra tremenda? Como que tuvimos que llevarle a su casa Polidura y yo
con grandísimo trabajo. ¡Dios, cómo está el hombre, y qué barullo tiene en la cabeza desde
el batacazo de ayer!».

Igualmente interesadas Benina y Juliana en la buena o mala suerte del hijo de Algeciras, oyeron
atentas lo que Antonio les refirió de las consecuencias funestísimas de la caída del jinete
en el camino del Pardo. Cuando le vieron en tierra, despedido por el jaco, pensaron todos que
en aquel crítico instante había terminado la existencia mortal del pobre caballero. Pero al
levantarle, recobró Frasquito, como quien resucita, el movimiento y la palabra, y asegurando
no haber recibido golpe en la cabeza, que era lo más delicado, y palpándose en distintas partes
del cráneo, les dijo: «Nada, nada, señores, tóquenme y no hallarán el más ligero chichón».
De brazos y piernas, si al principio pareció haber salido con suerte, pues hueso roto seguramente
no tenía, a poco de echar a andar cojeaba horrorosamente de la pierna izquierda, efecto, sin
duda, del violento choque contra el suelo. Pero lo más extraño fue que, al ser puesto en pie,
rompió en una charla incoherente, impetuosa, roja la cara como un tomate, vibrante y entrecortada
la lengua. Lleváronle a su casa en coche, creyendo que un reposo absoluto le restablecería;
frotáronle todo el cuerpo con árnica, le acostaron, se fueron... Pero el maldito, según les
dijo después la patrona, no bien se quedó solo, vistiose precipitadamente, y echándose a la
calle se fue a casa de Boto, y allí estuvo hasta muy tarde, metiéndose con todo el mundo, y
provocando con destempladas insolencias a los pacíficos parroquianos. Tan contrario era esto
al natural plácido de Frasquito, y a su timidez y buena educación, que seguramente había perturbación
cerebral grave, por causa del batacazo. No se sabe dónde pasó el resto de la noche: se cree
que estuvo alborotando en las calles de Mediodía Grande y Chica. Ello es que a poco de llegar
Antonio y Polidura a la casa de Doña Francisca, entró Frasquito muy alborotado, el rostro encendido,
brillantes los ojos, y con gran sorpresa y consternación de las señoras, empezó a soltar de
su boca, un poco torcida, atroces disparates. Combinando la maña con la fuerza, pudieron sacarle
de allí y volverle a su casa, donde le dejaron, encargando a la patrona que le sujetara si
podía, y que hiciera por darle de comer. Entre otras tenacidades monomaniacas, tenía la de
que su honor le demandaba pedir explicaciones al moro por el inaudito agravio de suponer, de
afirmar en público que él, Frasquito, hacía la corte a Benina. Más de veinte veces se arrancó
hacia la calle de Mediodía Grande, procurando ver al Sr. de Almudena, decidido a entregarle
su tarjeta; pero el africano escurría el bulto y no se dejaba ver por ninguna parte. Claro:
se había ido a su tierra, huyendo de la furia de Ponte... pero él estaba decidido a no parar
hasta descubrirle, y obligarle a cumplir como caballero, aunque se escondiese en el último
rincón del Atlas.

«Si venier mí galán bunito--dijo el moro riendo tan estrepitosamente, que los extremos de su
boca se le enganchaban en las orejas--, dar mí él patás mochas.

--¡Pobre D. Frasquito... cuitado, alma de Dios!--exclamó Nina cruzando las manos--. Yo me temía
que parara en esto...

--¡Valiente estantigua!--dijo la Juliana--. ¿Y a nosotros qué nos importa que ese viejo pintado
se chifle o no se chifle? ¿Sabéis lo que os digo? Pues que todo eso proviene de las drogas
que se pone en la cara, lo cual que son venenosas y atacan al sentido. Ea, no perdamos el tiempo.
Antonio, vuélvete a la calle Imperial, diles que preparen todo, y yo iré al carro a ver si
lo arreglo para esta tarde. Nina, vete con Dios, y cuidado no se te pegue... ¿sabes? ¡Ay, hija,
se te pegará, por mucho aseo que tengas! ¿Ves? ya empiezas a sufrir las consecuencias del mal
paso... por no hacer caso de mí. Doña Paca me dijo que te permitiera ir allá. Quiere verte:
¡pobre señora! Yo le di mi conformidad, y hoy pensaba llevarte conmigo... pero ya no me atrevo,
hija, ya no me atrevo. Habiendo de por medio esta pestilencia, no puedes rozarte... Yo había
determinado que fueras todos los días a recoger la comida sobrante en casa de la que fue tu ama.

--¿Y ya no...?

--Sí, sí: la comida es tuya... pero... verás lo que debes hacer... te llegas al portal a la
hora que yo te fije, y mi prima Hilaria te la bajará y te la dará... acercándose a ti lo menos
que pueda... Ya comprendes... cada una tiene su escrúpulo... No todos los estómagos son como
el tuyo, Nina, a prueba de bomba... con que...

--Comprendo... señora Juliana. Quédese con Dios».

XL

Las adversidades se estrellaban ya en el corazón de Benina, como las vagas olas en el robusto
cantil. Rompíanse con estruendo, se quebraban, se deshacían en blancas espumas, y nada más.
Rechazada por la familia que había sustentado en días tristísimos de miseria y dolores sin
cuento, no tardó en rehacerse de la profunda turbación que ingratitud tan notoria le produjo;
su conciencia le dio inefables consuelos: miró la vida desde la altura en que su desprecio
de la humana vanidad la ponía; vio en ridícula pequeñez a los seres que la rodeaban, y su espíritu
se hizo fuerte y grande. Había alcanzado glorioso triunfo; sentíase victoriosa, después de
haber perdido la batalla en el terreno material. Mas las satisfacciones íntimas de la victoria
no la privaron de su don de gobierno, y atenta a las cosas materiales, acudió, al poco rato
de apartarse de Juliana, a resolver lo más urgente en lo que a la vida corporal de ambos se
refería. Era indispensable buscar albergue; después trataría de curar a Mordejai de su sarna
o lo que fuese, pues abandonarle en tan lastimoso estado no lo haría por nada de este mundo,
aunque ella se viera contagiada del asqueroso mal. Dirigiose con él a Santa Casilda, y hallando
desocupado el cuartito que antes ocupó el moro con la Petra, lo tomó. Felizmente, la borracha
se había ido con Diega a vivir en la Cava de San Miguel, detrás de la Escalerilla. Instalados
en aquel escondrijo, que no carecía de comodidades, lo primero que hizo la anciana alcarreña
fue traer agua, toda el agua que pudo, y lavarse bien y jabonarse el cuerpo; costumbre antigua
en ella, que siempre que podía practicaba en casa de Doña Francisca. Luego se vistió de limpio.
El bienestar que el aseo y la frescura daban a su cuerpo, se confundía en cierto modo con el
descanso de su conciencia, en la cual también sentía algo como absoluta limpieza y frescor
confortante.

Dedicose luego al arreglo de la casa, y con el poquito dinero que tenía hizo su compra, y le
preparó a Mordejai una buena comida. Pensaba llevarlo a la consulta al día siguiente, y así
se lo dijo, mostrándose el ciego conforme en todo con lo que la voluntad de ella quisiese determinar.
Mientras comían, le entretuvo y alentó con esperanzas y palabras dulces, ofreciéndole ir, como
él deseaba, a Jerusalén o un poquito más allá, en cuanto recobrara la salud. Mientras no se
le quitara el sarpullo, no había que pensar en viajes. Se estarían quietos, él en casa, ella
saliendo a pedir sola todos los días para ver de sacar con qué vivir, que seguramente Dios
no les dejaría morir de hambre. Tan contento se puso el ciego con el plan concebido y propuesto
por su inteligente amiga, y con sus afectuosas expresiones, que rompió a cantar la melopea
arábiga que ya le oyó Benina en el vertedero; pero como al huir de la pedrea había perdido
el guitarrillo, no pudo acompañarse del son de aquel tosco instrumento. Después propuso a su
compañera que echase el sahumerio, y ella lo hizo de buena gana, pues el humazo saneaba y aromatizaba
la pobre habitación.

Salieron al día siguiente para la consulta; pero como les designaran para esta una hora de
la tarde, entretuvieron la primera mitad del día pordioseando en varias calles, siempre con
mucho cuidado de los guindillas, por no caer nuevamente en poder de los que echan el lazo a
los mendigos, cual si fueran perros, para llevarlos al depósito, donde como a perros les tratan.
Debe decirse que el ingrato proceder de Doña Paca no despertaba en Nina odio ni mala voluntad,
y que la conformidad de esta con la ingratitud no le quitaba las ganas de ver a la infeliz
señora, a quien entrañablemente quería, como compañera de amarguras en tantos años. Ansiaba
verla, aunque fuese de lejos, y llevada de esta querencia, se llegó a la calle de la Lechuga
para atisbar a distancia discreta si la familia estaba en vías de mudanza, o se había mudado
ya. ¡Qué a tiempo llegó! Hallábase en la puerta el carro, y los mozos metían trastos en él
con la bárbara presteza que emplean en esta operación. Desde su atalaya reconoció Benina los
muebles decrépitos, derrengados, y no pudo reprimir su emoción al verlos. Eran casi suyos,
parte de su existencia, y en ellos veía, como en un espejo, la imagen de sus penas y alegrías;
pensaba que si se acercase, los pobres trastos habían de decirle algo, o que llorarían con
ella. Pero lo que la impresionó vivamente fue ver salir por el portal a Doña Paca y a Obdulia,
con Polidura y Juliana, como si se fueran a la casa nueva, mientras las criadas elegantes se
quedaban en la antigua, disponiendo la recogida y transporte de las menudencias, y de toda
la morralla casera.

Turbada y confusa, Nina se escondió en un portal, para ver sin ser vista. ¡Qué desmejorada
encontró a Doña Francisca! Llevaba un vestido nuevo; pero de tan nefanda hechura, como cortado
y cosido de prisa, que parecía la pobre señora vestida de limosna. Cubría su cabeza con un
manto, y Obdulia ostentaba un sombrerote con disformes ringorrangos y plumas. Andaba Doña Paca
lentamente, la vista fija en el suelo, abrumada, melancólica, como si la llevaran entre guardias
civiles. La niña reía, charlando con Polidura. Detrás iba Juliana arreándolos a todos, y mandándoles
que fueran de prisa por el camino que les marcaba. No le faltaba más que el palo para parecerse
a los que en vísperas de Navidad conducen por las calles las manadas de pavos. ¡Cómo se clareaba
el despotismo hasta en sus menores movimientos! Doña Paca era la res humilde que va a donde
la llevan, aunque sea al matadero; Juliana el pastor que guía y conduce. Desaparecieron en
la Plaza Mayor, por la calle de Botoneras... Benina dio algunos pasos para ver el triste ganado,
y cuando lo perdió de vista, se limpió las lágrimas que inundaban su rostro.

«¡Pobre señora mía!--dijo al ciego en cuanto se reunió con él--. La quiero como hermana, porque
juntas hemos pasado muchas penas. Yo era todo para ella, y ella todo para mí. Me perdonaba
mis faltas, y yo le perdonaba las suyas... ¡Qué triste va, quizás pensando en lo mal que se
ha portado con la Nina! Parece que está peor del reúma, por lo que cojea, y su cara es de no
haber comido en cuatro días. Yo la traía en palmitas, yo la engañaba con buena sombra, ocultándole
nuestra miseria, y poniendo mi cara en vergüenza por darle de comer conforme a lo que era su
gusto y costumbre... En fin, lo pasado, como dijo el otro, pasó. Vámonos, Almudena, vámonos
de aquí, y quiera Dios que te pongas bueno pronto para tomar el caminito a Jerusalén, que no
me asusta ya por lejos. Andando, andando, hijo, se llega de una parte del mundo a otra, y si
por un lado sacamos el provecho de tomar el aire y de ver cosas nuevas, por otro sacamos la
certeza de que todo es lo mismo, y que las partes del mundo son, un suponer, como el mundo
en junto; quiere decirse, que en donde quiera que vivan los hombres, o verbigracia, mujeres,
habrá ingratitud, egoísmo, y unos que manden a los otros y les cojan la voluntad. Por lo que
debemos hacer lo que nos manda la conciencia, y dejar que se peleen aquellos por un hueso,
como los perros; los otros por un juguete, como los niños, o estos por mangonear, como los
mayores, y no reñir con nadie, y tomar lo que Dios nos ponga delante, como los pájaros... Vámonos
hacia el Hospital, y no te pongas triste.

--Mí no triste--dijo Almudena--; estar tigo contentado... tú saber como Dios cosas tudas, y
yo quirier ti como ángela bunita... Y si no quierer tú casar migo, ser tú madra mía, y yo niño
tuyo bunito.

--Bueno, hombre; me parece muy bien.

--Y tú com palmera D'sierto granda, bunita; tú com zucena branca... llirio tú... Mí dicier
ti amri: alma mía».
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08423</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>341132</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22382</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I've served, I've followed, I have held in
my adversity. You're good, very good, but not abuse, child, do not tell me you were coming home
with the Moor of dates, because believe you've gone mad.

- At home I had, yes, ma'am, as I brought Frasquito Ponte, for charity ... If there was mercy the
other, why should not having this? Or is that love is one for the gentleman frock coat, and
another for the poor naked?

I do not think so, I can not tell ... Therefore we brought, and if he does not admit, will be
the same as if I was not admitted.

- You always ... I say, not always ... I mean ... we have no gap in home ... We four women, you
see ... Will you come back tomorrow? The wretched places in a good inn ... not What nonsense!
Hospital ... Simply go to D. Romualdo ... Tell him from me I would recommend ... you look at
just my own ... Oh, I do not know what I mean! ... as something of yours, and so you ... In
short, daughter, you see ... May you shelter in the house of Mr. Kidron to be very big ... you told
me it's a huge coffer seems a convent ... I well know, as imperfect creature, I have no virtue
in a heroic degree that need to switch to pobretería dirty and smelly ... No, daughter, do not:
a question of stomach and nerve ... I would die of disgust, you know. As I say, with the misery
that will bring about you! ... I love you, Nina, but I know my stomach ... I see a speck in
the food, and I already stir it all, and I'm sick three days ... Take your clothes if you
want to move ... Juliana you give you what you need ... Do you hear
what I say?

Why are you silent? Ya, now I understand. You get the humble best to hide your pride ... I
forgive you everything, you know that I love you I'm good for you
... In short, you know me ... What?

- No, ma'am, I have not said
anything, I have nothing to say - Nina muttered between two sighs
deep -.

Stay with God.

- But do not go mad at me - said in a tremulous voice Doña Paca, following her distance in
its slow march down the aisle.

- No, ma'am ... you know that I do
not get mad at her old lady replied ...-- more compassionate than
angry -.

Bye bye. "

Obdulia led his mother to the dining room saying, "Poor Nina! ... Leaves. Well look, I would
have liked to see that moro Muza and talk to him ... This Juliana, who all want to get !...».

Stunned
by cruel doubts that baffled his spirit could not express Dona Francisca no idea, and continued
to review the silverware performed. Meanwhile, Juliana, leading the Nina to the door with soft
oppression of his hand on the back of the beggar, the dismissed with
these warm words: "Do not worry, Sena Benina that nothing must be
lacking ... I forgive you the drive that I paid last week, do not
you remember?

- Lady Juliana, I do remember.

Thanks.

- Well, well take this one hard to suit tonight ... Go tomorrow home,
you'll find there clothes ...

- Lady Juliana, God bless.

- Nowhere
else will you be better than Mercy, and if you want, I myself will
speak D. Romualdo, if you get embarrassed.

Doña Paca and I recommend ... For my wife mother-in put their trust
in me and gave me money to keep it ... and to rule the house, and
furnishes as you need.

Much has to thank God have fallen into these hands ...

- Good hands, Madam Juliana.

- Take home, and tell him what to do.

- Perhaps I know without you telling me.

- That you will ... If you do not want to go home ...

- I will go.

-
Well, Sena Benina, until tomorrow.

- Lady Juliana, servant to you.

"

Quickly dropped the worn steps, eager to be seen soon in the street.

When she reached the blind, which was waiting nearby place, the immense grief that oppressed
the heart of the poor mourn old burst into a fiery, anguished, and struck his forehead with his
fist, exclaimed: "Ungrateful, unthankful, ungrateful

- No yorar you, Amri - said the blind loving, tearful Talking -. Lady yours ill be your angel.

-
What ingratitude, Lord ... Oh world ... oh misery!

... Affront to God is to do well ...

- Dir us Lueje ... Dirna, Amri ... Mondo Dispreciar you wrong.

- God sees the hearts of all, mine is too ... See it, Lord of heaven
and earth, see it soon.

"

XXXIX

Having said that, he wiped his tears with a trembling hand, and thought
in making decisions practical than the circumstances demanded.

"Dirna, Dirna - Almudena said grabbing her arm.

- Where? - Nina said with astonishment -. Ah! the former home of D. Romualdo. "

As he said this name stood for a moment lela, completely idiotic.

-
"R'maldo lie - said the blind.

- Yes, yes, my invention was.

Which has been so much wealth to the lady will be another one D. Romualdo glue ... creature of
the devil ... No, no, the glue is mine ... I do not know, I know.

Come on, Almudena. Think you're bad, you need to spend well sheltered at night. Juliana Sena,
which is now cut the cheese in the house of my lady, and all supplies ... in good time is ...
has given me this hard. I'll take you to the palaces of Bernarda,
and tomorrow we'll see.

- Tomorrow, we Hierusalaim dir.

- Where
did you say?

To Jerusalem? And where is that? Well, we want to carry that point, as it were, a supposition, or
Carabanchel Jetafe Down!

- Lueje, Lueje ... you marry me and be a Migo tigo.

Marseille Dirna roads asking ... In Marseille steam ... pim, pam ... Jaffa ... Hierusalaim! ...
Arreligión married by your own, arreligión mine ... you want ...
Veder you Sepulchre, enter S'nagoga you pray Adonai ...

- Hold on,
son, have a little quiet, and I'm not dizzy with the inventions of
your head delusions.

The first thing you wear is good.

- Me to be good ... I do not c'lentura
and ... contented me.

You come Migo always, mondo large walk mochas, freeing, sea, terra, Legria mocha ...

- Very nice, but now I realize that you and I are hungry, and get to dinner in any tavern. If
you think, here in the Cava Baja ...

- Onde want you, I want ...».

Dined with relative content, and Almudena not stop to ponder the joys of going juntitos to Jerusalem,
begging by land and by sea, without hurry, without care. It would take months half a year maybe,
but finally give their bodies in Palestine, although undertake by land to Constantinople. As there were
few attractive countries to go! Nina that she had objected and bones would be hard for so
long, and Africa, not and knowing how to persuade, he said: "terra Ispani n'gratituda ... Running
Lueje, juyando of n'gratos them. "

As they dined are reflected in Bernarda's house, bedrooms down, two real bed. Almudena was quiet
all night, unable to fall asleep, stuck with the short trip to Jerusalem, and Benin, to see
to calm him, showed himself willing to undertake so long pilgrimage. Restless and sore, as if the bed
of brambles out punching, Mordechai did nothing turn from side to side, complaining of burning
in the skin and itching grievous, which were not motivated, that is the truth, about anything concerning
the misery fought with insecticide dusts. This came perhaps a strange turn took the fever,
and is told the next morning in a red rash on arms and legs. The unfortunate desperately scratched
and Benin took him to the street, hoping that the air free and the exercise will serve as a
relief. After wandering about asking, not as usual, went to San Carlos Street, and went to
see Juliana Benina, there he had his clothes, and gave it a mess, saying that while it managed to
be contained in the Mercy lodged in any house price, with or without
man, but he was better, for decency left so friendly and indecent
treatment.

He added that once it was cleaned of all the filth that had brought the Pardo, could go visit
Dona Paca, to joyful receive it, but I did not expect to return to his side, because the children
were opposed to it, mindful that his mother was well served, and provided regularly. Yet he
was as the good woman who saw in it a superior untestable.

Juliana was not a bad person, parent, yes, eager to show the great gifts of government God had
given him, a woman who would not let two jerks fall prey into their
hands.

But not without love of neighbor, he felt sorry for Benin, and having
said this that the Moor the waiting in the street, wanted to see him
and judge him by his own eyes.

That the trace of the poor African seemed pitiful, met in the gesture he made in the look
on his face, and accent said: "I already knew him to this, to see
him on the street asking the Duke of Alba.

He's a good point, and very much in love.

Right, Mr. Almudena, who likes you girls?

- Like my B'nina, Amri ...

- Ajaj ... Benina poor, he has not been granted poor fly! If you do this for charity, honest
I say you're a saint.

- The poor guy is sick and can not use. "

And as the Moor, seized with very violent itching in the arms and chest, claws do your fingers
to scrape win, edging closer to look at her arms, which had stripped from the sleeve. "What
has this man - said to fear - is leprosy ... Jesus, what Leprosy
Benina sign!

I have seen another case, a poor, del Moro well, begging him, Oran him calling at Puerta Cerrada,
next to the workshop of my stepfather. And it got so lost, not Christian had approached him, and
neither will the Saints Hospital wanted to receive ...

"Chop, chop mocha - Almudena was all he said, turning the nail from
the shoulder to hand, as would a comb through the tangle.

Concealing his disgust, not to hurt the unhappy pair, Juliana said Nina: "Well not you have fallen
ill concern with this guy! Look at that scab sticks. Good are you going put, yes ma'am, good,
nice and cheap ... Or are you more stupid than to cook the butter,
or do not know what it is you.

"

With Nina looks no more expressed their pity the poor blind man, his
decision not to leave him and compliance with all the calamities that
God would send. And in this, Antonio Zapata who returned home, saw
his wife in the group, came up to her hurriedly, and aware of what
speaking, Benina advised to carry the Moor to the query of skin diseases
San Juan de Dios.

"More consideration will have - said Juliana - send to their land.

- Lueje, Lueje - said Almudena -. Dir Hierusalaim us.

- Not bad. "From Madrid to Jerusalem, or the family of Uncle Maroma
...'.

Well, well. In other thing, my little lady, do not hit and listen. I could not do your assignments,
because ... I tell you they do not hit.

- Because you've gone to the pool, rogue ... Up, up, and adjust accounts.

- Do not climb because I have to go back to the cars of pathos.

- What do you say, you rascal?

- Not big go cart for less than forty real, and as you sent me from passing thirty ...

- Will I have to see. These men do not serve more than a hindrance, do you, Nina?

- Truth. What is it? Mrs. Will move?

- Yes, women, but may not be until tomorrow, because this silly husband God has given me, out before
the eight to take the house and alert the car, and you see what time you pick up here, with
all that rennet, without having done anything.

- Pretty've run, girl: At nine I went home mom with the contract for signature. You see if we
won time. But you know I've lost Frasquito Ponte, He has given us a tremendous s boring? As
we had to take him home and I Polidura with the greatest job. God, how is the man, and why mess on its
head from the thud of yesterday! ".

Benin and Juliana also interested in good or bad fortune of the son of Algeciras, heard attentive Antonio
told them what the consequences of the fall funestísimas Rider Pardo on the road. When I saw
on the ground, fired by jaco, everyone thought that at that critical moment he had finished the
poor knight's mortal existence. But lift, Frasquito recovered, as he revives the movement
and speech, and ensuring have not been hit in the head, which was the most sensitive, and
felt in different parts the skull, he said, 'No, no, gentlemen, touch Me and not find the slightest
bump. " Arms and legs, if at first seemed to have come out with fortune, for surely broken bone
I had to jump-start some horribly lame left leg, indeed, without doubt, the violent collision
with the ground. But the strangest thing was that, as he stood, broke into a gibberish, rash,
red face like a tomato, vibrant and breath language. They took him to his home by car, believing
that a complete rest will restore; frotáronle entire body with arnica, I went to bed, they
were ... But damn, as they after the patron said he had no sooner
left alone, dressed himself hastily, and fell to street was home to
Boto, and he stayed there until very late getting to everyone, and
leading to the peaceful insolence intemperate parishioners.

As this was contrary Frasquito the placid nature, and his shyness and good education, which
surely had disturbance severe brain because of the bump.

It is not known where he spent the rest of the night: it is believed that was stirring in the streets
of Midi Grande and Chica.

The fact is that shortly after arriving Polidura Antonio and home of Dona Francisca, took Frasquito
very excited, his face flushed, bright eyes, and with great surprise and dismay of the ladies,
began to drop in his mouth, a little crooked, outrageous nonsense. Combining skill with the force,
could get there and get back home, where they left him, ordering the employer to hold if could,
and to do for feeding. Among other monomaniacs toughness, was that of his honor demanded he seek
explanations for the unprecedented affront Moor presumably to say in public that he, Frasquito,
made the cut in Benin. More than twenty times tore Midi to Grand Street, trying to see Mr.
de Almudena, determined to give card, but the African slipped the package and would not let anyone
see it anywhere. Clear had gone to his country, fleeing from the fury of Ponte ... but he was
determined not to stop to discover, and force him to meet a gentleman,
but he hid in the last corner of the Atlas.

"If my lover venier Bunite - Moor said laughing so loudly, that the ends of His mouth caught on
the ears - to me he legs mochas.

- Poor D. Bottle ... wretched soul of God - Nina exclaimed clasping
her hands -.

I feared to stop this ...

- Valiente fright! - Said Juliana -.

What does it matter to us that this old wallpaper Whistle or not it nuts? Do you know what I
mean? Well, all that comes from drugs that is placed on the face, which are poisonous and attack
direction. Hey, do not waste your time. Antonio, go back to Imperial Street, tell them to
prepare everything, and I go to the car to see if fix it this afternoon. Nina, go with God, and
care not hit you ... You know? Oh, daughter, shall cling, even toilet you have! See? and start
to suffer the consequences of bad step ... by ignoring me. Doña Paca told me that I let you go there.
Wants to see: Poor lady! I gave my consent, and take you with me today I thought ... but I
do not dare, daughter, I do not dare. Having in between this plague, can not Rozart ... I had
you were given every day to collect the leftover food in the house that was your mistress.

-
And I do not ...?

- Yes, yes, the food is yours ... but ... see what to do ... you get to the portal to hours that
I set, and my cousin Hillary will bring it down and I will give ... coming at you at least I can
... You understand ... each has its qualms ... Not all stomachs are like yours, Nina, bombproof
... that ...

- I understand ... Lady Juliana. Stay with God. "

XL

Adversity and crashed in the heart of Benin, as the vague waves in
the robust cliff.

Rompíanse thundered, were broken, melted in white foam, and nothing else. Rejected by the family
that he had sustained in saddest days of misery and pain without story soon remake of the deep
trouble that caused him so notorious ingratitude; his conscience gave him unspeakable consolation: he
looked at life from the height at which his contempt of human vanity put it, saw the ridiculous
smallness beings around her, and spirit was big and strong. Had achieved glorious victory,
I felt victorious after have lost the battle on the ground material. More intimate satisfactions
of victory not deprived of his gift of government, and attentive to material things, came
in a little while depart from Juliana, to solve the most urgent as the life both body concerned.
It was crucial to seek shelter, then try to cure your scabies Mordechai or whatever, then
leave him in such a pitiable state would not do for anything in the world although she saw
the filthy infected wrong. And ran with him to Santa Casilda, and finding vacated the small
room occupied by the Moors with Petra, he took it. Fortunately, the drunk Diega had gone to live in the
Cava de San Miguel, behind the ladder.

Installed in that cache, which was not without comforts, the first thing that made the old
Alcarrian was to bring water, all the water he could, and wash and body soap, old habit in
it, that whenever he could practice at home of Dona Francisca. Then he wore clean. The welfare
cleanliness and freshness gave his body, somewhat confused with rest of his conscience, in which
he also felt something like absolute cleanliness and freshness comforting.

Then devoted himself to the arrangement of the house, and with the little money he had made
his purchase, and Mordechai prepared a good meal. They planned to bring the consultation the
following day, and so it said, showing the blind according to all with what she wanted the will
to determine. While they ate, entertained and encouraged him to hope and sweet words, offering
to go, as he wanted to Jerusalem or a little further, as regain health. Pending to take away
the rash, there was no need to think about travel. It would still, at home, she going to ask
for one every day to see get to live on, surely God not let them starve. So pleased the blind
conceived and proposed plan by his smart friends, and with his affectionate expressions, which
burst into singing the chant Arabic Benina already heard him in the landfill, but as to escape
the stoning had lost the small guitar, could not accompany the son of that rough instrument.
He then proposed to companion to cast incense, and she did it willingly, because the smog
and flavored saneaba poor room.

They left the next day for consultation, but as they nominate for this one-hour evening, entertained
the first half of the day pordioseando on several streets, always good care of the chili, not
to fall again in the hands of those who cast the tie to beggars, as if they were dogs and take them
to the warehouse, where they treated like dogs. It must be said that the ungrateful not come from Doña
Paca Nina woke up in hatred or malice, and that compliance with the ingratitude of this took away
the desire not to see the unhappy lady, who dearly wanted, as a partner of bitterness in many years.
Longed view, even if from afar, and brought this fondness, it was the street of Lettuce to
discern a discreet distance if the family was in the process of moving or had moved now. What
time has arrived! He was in the car door, and the boys got stuff in it with the barbarous quickly
that used in this operation.

From his vantage Benina recognized the decrepit furniture, bent, and could not contain his excitement
at seeing them. It was almost his, of its existence, and they saw, as in a mirror, the image
of their sorrows and joys; I thought that if approached, the poor tackle had to say something,
or cry with it. But what was strongly impressed to see out through the portal and Obdulia Dona
Paca, with Polidura and Juliana, as if it were a new home, while the maids are elegant remained in
the former, providing for collection and transportation of offal, and all the trash home.

Troubled and confused, Nina hid in a doorway, to see without being seen. What impaired Dona Francisca
found! He wore a new dress, but so heinous appearance, as cut and sewn in a hurry, it seemed
like the poor lady dressed in alms. Covered his head with a robe, and held a sombrerote Obdulia
with deformed flourish and feathers. Doña Paca walked slowly, staring at the floor, overwhelmed,
sad, as if carried by guards civilians. The girl laughed, chatted with Polidura. Juliana was
behind herding them all, and sending them they were in a hurry by the way that marked them.
No more than he needed to look like wood to that on Christmas Eve the streets leading flocks
of turkeys. How dawned despotism in the smallest movements! Doña Paca was the humble response
that goes where the lead, even at the slaughterhouse, Juliana and the shepherd who leads. Disappeared
the Plaza Mayor, the street of keypads ... Benina took steps to see
the sad cattle and when he lost it, wiped the tears flooding her face.

"Poor dear lady! - Said the blind man as he met him -.

I love her as a sister, because together we spent many penalties.

I was all for it, and it all for me. Forgive me my faults, I will forgive their own ... How
sad it is, perhaps thinking of how bad ported with Nina! It seems
that rheumatism is worse, so lame, and his face is not have eaten
in four days. I brought cherry-picked, I was cheating with good shade,
hiding our misery, and putting my face in shame for him to eat according
to what was his taste and custom ... In short, the past, and said
the other, it happened. Come on, Almudena, let's go here, and God
put you well soon to take the little road to Jerusalem, not and scares
me by far. Walking, walking, child, comes from a part of the world
to another, and if one hand we get the benefit of fresh air and see
new things, on the other we get the certainty that everything is the
same, and that parts of the world are a guess, as the world in together,
you say, that wherever people live, or verbigracia, women, be ingratitude,
selfishness, and ones that send to others and will catch them. As
we must do what conscience commands us, and let those who fight for
a bone, like dogs, the other over a toy, as children, or those by
bully, as older, and not to quarrel with anybody, and take what God
put us ahead, like the birds ... Come to the Hospital, and do not
be sad.

- Me not sad - said Almudena -; be satisfied tigo ... God
you know how things tudas and I quiries you and Angela Bunite ...
And if you do not want to marry me, this be your mother mine, and
I was a child Bunite yours.

- Well, man, that's fine.

- And you
com palm desert D'granda, Bunite thou zucena branca com ... Illyricum
you ... Telling me Amri you: my soul. </suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>