<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05189</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>75241</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22561</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> ¿Estás aquí? No he visto tu coche abajo.

--He salido a pie, papá.

--Es un milagro. Si quieres, puedes llevarte el mío.

--No; tengo deseos de caminar. Estoy estos días muy pesada.

El duque de Requena había prescindido de todos los presentes y hablaba a su hija con toda la
afabilidad de que era susceptible. La veía pocas veces. Clementina era su hija natural, habida
allá en Valencia, cuando joven, de una mujer de la ínfima clase social, como él lo era al parecer.
Luego se había casado en Madrid, ya en camino de ser rico, con una joven de la clase media,
de la cual no tuvo familia. Esta señora, extremadamente delicada de salud desde su matrimonio,
había cedido o, por mejor decir, había ella misma propuesto que la hija de su marido viniese
a habitar la misma casa. Clementina se educó, pues, aquí y fué amada de la esposa de su padre
como una verdadera hija. Ella la quiso y la respetó también como a una madre. Después que se
casó solía visitarla a menudo; pero como su padre estaba siempre muy ocupado, no entraba en
sus habitaciones, y desde las de su madre (así la llamaba) se iba a la calle. Sólo en los días
de banquete o recepción, o cuando casualmente le tropezaba en las casas o en la calle departía
un rato con él.

Después de preguntarle por su marido y por sus hijos, el duque se puso a hablar, sin sentarse,
con Calderón y Pepa Frías. Un hombre rudo y campechanote en la apariencia: sonreía pocas veces:
cuando lo hacía era de modo tan leve que aún podía dudarse de ello. Acostumbraba a llamar las
cosas por su nombre y a dirigirse a las personas sin fórmulas de cortesía, diciéndoles en la
cara cosas que pudieran pasar por groserías: no lo eran porque sabía darles un tinte entre
rudo y afectuoso que les quitaba el aguijón. No era muy locuaz. Generalmente se mantenía silencioso
mordiendo su cigarro y examinando al interlocutor con sus ojos oblicuos, impenetrables. Mostraba
al hablar una inocencia falsa y socarrona que no le hacía antipático. Detrás se veía siempre
al antiguo granuja del mercadal de Valencia, diestro, burlón, receloso y marrullero.

Pepa Frías le habló de negocios. La viuda era incansable en esta conversación. Quería enterarse
de todo, temiendo ser engañada ávida siempre de ganancias y temblando con terror cómico ante
la perspectiva de la baja de sus fondos. Se hacía repetir hasta la saciedad los pormenores.
"¿Soltaría las acciones del Banco y compraría Cubas? ¿Qué pensaba hacer el Gobierno con el
amortizable? Había oído rumores. ¿Se haría en alza la próxima liquidación? ¿No sería mejor
liquidar en el momento con treinta céntimos de ganancia que aguardar a fin de mes?"

Para ella las palabras de Salabert eran las del oráculo de Delfos. La fama inmensa del banquero
la tenía fascinada. Por desgracia, el duque, como todos los oráculos antiguos y modernos, se
expresaba siempre que se le consultaba, de un modo ambiguo. Respondía a menudo con gruñidos
que nadie sabía si eran de afirmación, de negación o de duda. Las frases que de vez en cuando
se escapaban de su boca entre el cigarro y los labios húmedos y sucios eran oscuras, cortadas,
ininteligibles en muchos casos. Además, todo el mundo sabía que no era posible fiarse de él,
que se gozaba en despistar a sus amigos y hacerles caer de bruces en un mal negocio. Sin embargo,
Pepa insistía aspirando a arrancar de aquel cerebro luminoso el secreto de la mina: bromeaba
tomándole de las solapas de la levita, llamándole viejo, cazurro, zorro, haciendo gala de una
desvergüenza que en ella había llegado a ser coquetería. El banquero no daba fuego. Le seguía
el humor respondiendo con gruñidos y con tal cual frase escabrosa que hacía reir a Calderón,
aunque no tenía muchas ganas de hacerlo viéndole echar sin miramiento alguno tremendos escupitajos
en la alfombra. Porque el duque con el picor del tabaco salivaba bastante y no acostumbraba
a reparar dónde lo hacía, a no ser en su casa donde cuidaba de ponerse al lado de la escupidera.
Calderón estaba inquieto, violento, lo mismo que si se los echase en la cara. A la tercera
vez, no pudiendo contenerse, fué él mismo a buscar la escupidera para ponérsela al lado. Salabert
le dirigió una mirada burlona y le hizo un guiño a Pepa. Ya tranquilo Calderón se mostró locuaz
y pretendió sustituirse al duque dando consejos a Pepa sobre los fondos. Pero aunque hombre
prudente y experto en los negocios, la viuda no se los apreciaba ni aun quería oirlos. Al fin
y al cabo, entre él y Salabert existía enorme distancia: el uno era un negociante vulgar, el
otro un genio de la banca. Sin embargo, éste asentía con sonidos inarticulados a las indicaciones
bursátiles del dueño de la casa. Pepa no se fiaba.

Salabert se apartó un poco del grupo y se dejó caer sobre el brazo de un sillón adoptando una
postura grosera, para lo cual sólo él tenía derecho. En vez de ser mal vistos aquellos modales
libres y rudos, contribuían no poco a su prestigio y al respeto idolátrico que en sociedad
se le tributaba. Lejos nuevamente de la escupidera volvió a salivar sobre la alfombra con cierto
goce malicioso, que a pesar de su máscara indiferente y bonachona se le traslucía en la cara.
Calderón tornó igualmente a nublarse y fruncirse hasta que, resolviéndose a saltar por encima
de ciertos miramientos sociales, le acercó otra vez la escupidera sin tanto valor como antes,
pues lo hizo con el pie. Pepa sentóse en el otro brazo y siguió haciendo carocas al duque.
Este comenzaba a fijar más la atención en ella. Sus miradas frecuentes la envolvían de la cabeza
a los pies, notándose que se detenían en el pecho, alto y provocador. Pepa era una mujer fresca,
apetitosa. Al cabo de algunos minutos el banquero se inclinó hacia ella con poca delicadeza,
y acercando el rostro a su cara, tanto que parecía que se la rozaba con los labios, le dijo
en voz baja:

--¿Tiene usted muchas Osunas?

--Algunas, sí, señor.

--Véndalas usted a escape.

Pepa le miró a los ojos fijamente, y dándose por advertida calló. Al cabo de unos momentos
fué ella quien acercando su rostro al del banquero le preguntó discretamente:

--¿Qué compro?

--Amortizable--respondió el famoso millonario con igual reserva.

Entraban a la sazón un caballero y una dama, ambos jovencitos, menudos, sonrientes, y vivos
en sus ademanes.

--Aquí están mis hijos--dijo Pepa.

Era un matrimonio grato de ver. Ambos bien parecidos, de fisonomía abierta y simpática, y tan
jóvenes, que realmente parecían dos niños. Fueron saludando uno por uno a los tertulios. En
todos los rostros se advertía el afecto protector que inspiraban.

--Aquí tienes a tu suegra, Emilio. ¡Qué encuentro tan desagradable! ¿verdad?...--dijo Pepa
al joven.

--Suegra, no; mamá ... mamá--respondió éste apretándole la mano cariñosamente.

--¡Dios te lo pague, hijo!--replicó la viuda dando un suspiro de cómico agradecimiento.

Volvió la tertulia a acomodarse. Los jóvenes casados sentáronse juntos al lado de Mariana.
Clementina había dejado aquel sitio y charlaba con Maldonado: el nombre de Pepe Castro sonaba
muchas veces en sus labios. Mientras tanto Cobo aprovechaba el tiempo, haciendo reir con sus
desvergüenzas a Pacita; pero aunque intentaba que Esperanza acogiese los chistes con igual
placer, no lo conseguía. La niña de Calderón, seria, distraída, parecía atender con disimulo
a lo que Ramoncito y Clementina hablaban. Pinedo se había levantado y hacía la corte al duque.
Y el general, viendo a su ídolo en conversación animada con los jóvenes casados, fatigado de
que sus laberínticos requiebros no fuesen comprendidos, ni tampoco sus restregones poéticos,
vino a hacer lo mismo. La marquesa y el sacerdote seguían cuchicheando vivamente allá en un
rincón, ella cada vez más humilde e insinuante, sentada sobre el borde de la butaca, inclinando
su cuerpo para meterle la voz por el oído; él más grave y más rígido por momentos, cerrando
a grandes intervalos los ojos como si se hallase en el confesionario.

--¡Qué par de bebés, eh!--exclamó Pepa en voz alta dirigiéndose a Mariana--. ¿No es vergüenza
que esos mocosos estén casados? ¡Cuánto mejor sería que estuviesen jugando al trompo!

Los chicos sonrieron mirándose con amor.

--Ya jugarán ... en los momentos de ocio--manifestó Cobo Ramírez con retintín.

--¡Hombre, ca!--exclamó Pepa, volviéndose furiosa hacia él--. ¿Le han dado a usted cuenta ellos
de sus juegos?

Aquél y Emilio cambiaron una mirada maliciosa. Irenita, la joven casada, se ruborizó.

--Te están haciendo vieja, Pepa. Acuérdate que eres abuela--respondió la señora de Calderón.

--¡Qué abuela tan rica!--exclamó por lo bajo Cobo, aunque con la intención de que lo oyese
la interesada.

Esta le echó una mirada entre risueña y enojada, demostrando que había oído y lo agradecía
en el fondo. Cobo se hizo afectadamente el distraído.

--¿Os ha pasado ya la berrenchina?--siguió la viuda dirigiéndose a sus hijos--. ¿Cuánto durarán
las paces?... ¡Jesús, qué criaturas tan picoteras!... Mirad, yo no voy a vuestra casa porque
cuando os encuentro con morro me apetece tomar la escoba y romperla en las costillas de los dos....

Los tertulios se volvieron hacia los jóvenes esposos sonriendo. Esta vez se pusieron ambos
fuertemente colorados. Después, por la seriedad que quedó bien señalada en el rostro de Emilio,
se pudo comprender que no le hacían maldita la gracia aquellas salidas harto desenfadadas de
su suegra.

El general Patiño, por orden de la bella señora de la casa, puso el dedo en el botón de un
timbre eléctrico. Apareció un criado: le hizo el ama una seña: no se pasaron cinco minutos
sin que se presentase nuevamente y en pos de él otros dos con sendas bandejas en las manos
colmadas de tazas de te, pastas y bizcochos. Momento de agradable expansión en la tertulia.
Todos se ponen en movimiento y brilla en los ojos el placer del animal que va a satisfacer
una necesidad orgánica. Esperancita deja apresuradamente a su amiga y a Ramírez y se pone a
ayudar con solicitud a su madre en la tarea de servir el te a los tertulios. Ramoncito aprovecha
el instante en que la niña le presenta una taza, para decirla en voz baja y alterada "que le
sorprende mucho que se complazca en escuchar las patochadas y frases atrevidas de Cobo Ramírez".
Esperanza le mira confusa, y al fin dice "que ella no ha oído semejantes patochadas, que Cobo
es un chico muy amable y gracioso". Ramoncito protesta con voz débil y lúgubre entonación contra
tal especie y persiste en desacreditar a su amigo, hasta que éste, oliendo el torrezno, se
acerca a ellos bromeando según costumbre. Con lo cual, a nuestro distinguido concejal se le
encapota aún más el rostro y se va retirando poco a poco: no sea que al insolente de Cobo se
le ocurra cualquier sandez para hacer reir a su costa.

Llegó el momento de hablar de literatura, como acontece siempre en todas las tertulias nocturnas
o vespertinas de la capital. El general Patiño habló de una obra teatral recién estrenada con
felicísimo éxito y le puso sus peros, basados principalmente en algunas escenas subidas de
color. Mariana manifestó que de ningún modo iría a verla entonces. Todos convinieron en anatematizar
la inmoralidad de que hoy hacen gala los autores. Se dijeron pestes del naturalismo. Cobo Ramírez,
que había tomado te y luego unos emparedados y se había comido una cantidad fabulosa de ensaimadas
y bizcochos, expuso a la tertulia que recientemente había leído una novela titulada Le journal
d'une dame (en francés y todo), preciosa, bonitísima, la más espiritual que él hubiera leído
nunca. Porque Cobo, en literatura--¡caso raro!--, estaba por lo espiritual, lo delicado. No
le vinieran a él con esas nove-lotas pesadas donde le cuentan a uno las veces que un albañil
se despereza al levantarse de la cama (o los bizcochos y ensaimadas que se come un chico de
buena sociedad), ni le hablaran de partos y otras porquerías semejantes. En las novelas deben
ponerse cosas agradables, puesto que se escriben para agradar. Esto decía con notable firmeza,
resollando al hablar como un caballo de carrera. Los demás asentían.

La entrada de un caballero ni alto ni bajo, ni delgado ni gordo, alzado de hombros y cogido
de cintura, la color baja, la barba negra y tan espesa y recortada que parecía postiza, cortó
rápidamente la plática literaria. Nada menos que era el señor ministro de Fomento. Por eso
llevaba la cabeza tan erguida que casi daba con el cerebelo en las espaldas, y sus ojos medio
cerrados despedían por entre las negras y largas pestañas relámpagos de suficiencia y protección
a los presentes. Hasta los veintidós años había tenido la cabeza en su postura natural; pero
desde esta época, en que le nombraron vicepresidente de la sección de derecho civil y canónico
en la Academia de Jurisprudencia, había comenzado a levantarla lenta y majestuosamente como
la luna sobre el mar en el escenario del teatro Real, esto es, a cortos e imperceptibles tironcitos
de cordel. Le hicieron diputado provincial; un tironcito. Luego diputado a Cortes; otro tironcito.
Después gobernador de provincia; otro tironcito. Más tarde director general de un departamento;
otro. Presidente de la Comisión de presupuestos; otro. Ministro; otro. La cuerda estaba agotada.
Aunque le hicieran príncipe heredero, Jiménez Arbós ya no podía levantar un milímetro más su
gran cabeza.

Su entrada produjo movimiento, pero no tanto como la del duque de Requena. Este, cuyo rostro
carnoso, sensual, no podía ocultar el desprecio que aquella asamblea le inspiraba, corrió a
él sin embargo, y le saludó con rendimiento y servilismo sorprendentes, teniendo en cuenta
la rusticidad y grosería con que generalmente se comportaba en el trato social. El ministro
comenzó a repartir apretones de manos de un modo tan distraído que ofendía. Únicamente cuando
saludó a Pepa Frías dió señales de animación. Esta le preguntó en voz baja tuteándole:

--¿Cómo vienes de frac?

--Voy a comer a la embajada francesa.

--¿Vas luego a casa?

--Sí.

Este diálogo rapidísimo en voz imperceptible fué observado por el duque, quien acercándose
a Pinedo le preguntó con reserva y haciendo una seña expresiva:

--Diga usted, ¿Arbós y Pepa Frías?...

--Hace ya lo menos dos meses.

La mirada que el banquero le echó entonces a la viuda no fué de la calidad de las anteriores.
Era ahora más atenta, más respetuosa y profunda, quedándose después un poco pensativo. Calderón
se había acercado al ministro y le hablaba con acatamiento. Salabert hizo lo mismo. Pero el
personaje no tenía ganas de hablar de negocios o por ventura le inspiraba miedo el célebre
negociante. La prensa hacía reticencias malévolas sobre los negocios de éste con el Gobierno.
Por eso, a los pocos momentos, se fué en pos de Pepa Frías y se pusieron a cuchichear en un
ángulo de la estancia.

Clementina estaba cada vez más impaciente, con unos deseos atroces de marcharse. Dejaba de
hacerlo por el temor de que su padre la acompañase. El ministro se fué a los pocos minutos,
repartiendo previamente otros cuantos apretones de manos con la misma distracción imponente,
mirando, no a la persona a quien saludaba, sino al techo de la estancia. Entonces el duque
se apoderó de Pepa Frías, mostrándose con ella tan galante y expresivo, como si fuese a hacerle
una declaración de amor. El general, observándolo, dijo a Pinedo:

--Mire usted al duque, qué animado se ha puesto. De fijo le está haciendo el amor a Pepa.

--No--respondió gravemente el empleado--. A lo que está haciendo el amor ahora es al negocio
de las minas de Riosa.

La viuda anunció al cabo en voz alta que se iba.

--¿Adonde va usted, Pepa, en este momento?--le preguntó el banquero.

--A casa de Lhardy a encargar unas mortadelas.

--La acompaño a usted.

--Vamos; le convidaré a tomar unos pastelitos.

Al duque le hizo mucha gracia el convite.

--¿Vienes, chiquita?--le dijo a su hija.

Clementina aún pensaba quedarse un rato. Pepa, al tiempo de salir del brazo del banquero, dijo
en alta voz volviéndose a los Presentes:

--Conste que no vamos en coche.

Lo cual les hizo reir.

--Conste--dijo el duque riendo--que esto lo dice por adularme.

--Que se explique eso: no hemos comprendido ...--gritó Cobo Ramírez.

Pero ya el duque y Pepa habían desaparecido detrás de la cortina. Clementina aguardó sólo cinco
minutos. Cuando presumió que ya no podía tropezar en la escalera a su padre, se levantó, y
pretextando un quehacer olvidado, se despidió también.

III

#La hija de Salabert.#

Bajó con ansia la escalera. Al poner el pie en la calle dejó escapar un suspiro de consuelo.
A paso vivo tomó la del Siete de Julio, entró en la plaza Mayor y luego en la de Atocha. Al
llegar aquí vino a su pensamiento la imagen del joven que la había seguido y volvió la cabeza
con inquietud. Nada; no había que temer. Ninguno la seguía. En la puerta de una de las primeras
casas y mejores de la calle, se detuvo, miró rápida y disimuladamente a entrambos lados y penetró
en el portal. Hizo una seña casi imperceptible de interrogación al portero. Este contestó con
otra de afirmación llevándose la mano a la gorra. Lanzóse por la escalera arriba. Subió tan
de prisa, sin duda para evitar encuentros importunos, que al llegar al piso segundo le ahogaba
la fatiga y se llevó una mano al corazón. Con la otra dió dos golpecitos en una de las puertas.
Al instante abrieron silenciosamente: se arrojó dentro con ímpetu, cual si la persiguiesen.

--Más vale tarde que nunca--dijo el joven que había abierto, tornando a cerrar con cuidado.

Era un hombre de veintiocho a treinta años, de estatura más que regular, delgado, rostro fino
y correcto, sonrosado en los pómulos, bigote retorcido, perilla apuntada y los cabellos negros
y partidos por el medio con una raya cuidadosamente trazada. Guardaba semejanza con esos soldaditos
de papel con que juegan los niños; esto es, era de un tipo militar afeminado. También parecía
su rostro al que suelen poner los sastres a sus figurines; y era tan antipático y repulsivo
como el de ellos. Vestía un batín de terciopelo color perla con muchos y primorosos adornos;
traía en los pies zapatillas del mismo género y color con las iniciales bordadas en oro. Advertíase
pronto que era uno de esos hombres que cuidan con esmero del aliño de su persona; que retocan
su figura con la misma atención y delicadeza con que el escultor cincela una estatua; que al
rizarse el bigote y darle cosmético creen estar cumpliendo un sagrado e ineludible deber de
conciencia; que agradecen, en fin, al Supremo Hacedor, el haberles otorgado una presencia gallarda
y procuran en cuanto les es dado mejorar su obra.

--¡Qué tarde!--volvió a exclamar el apuesto caballero dirigiéndola una mirada fija y triste
de reconvención.

La dama le pagó con una graciosa sonrisa, replicando al mismo tiempo con acento burlón:

--Nunca es tarde si la dicha es buena.

Y le tomó la mano y se la apretó suavemente, y le condujo luego sin soltarle al través de los
corredores, hasta un gabinete que debía ser el despacho del mismo joven. Era una pieza lujosa
y artísticamente decorada; las paredes forradas con cortinas de raso azul oscuro, prendidas
al techo por anillos que corrían por una barra de bronce; sillas y butacas de diversas formas
y gustos; una mesa-escritorio de nogal con adornos de hierro forjado; al lado una taquilla
con algunos libros, hasta dos docenas aproximadamente. Suspendidos del techo por cordones de
seda y adosados a la pared veíanse algunos arneses de caballo, sillas de varias clases, comunes,
bastardas y de jineta con sus estribos pendientes, frenos de diferentes épocas y también países,
látigos, sudaderos de estambre fino bordados, espuelas de oro y plata; todo riquísimo y nuevo.
Las aficiones hípicas del dueño de aquel despacho se delataban igualmente en los pasillos,
que desde la puerta de la casa conducían allí; por todas partes monturas colgadas y cuadros
representando caballos en libertad o aparejados. Hasta sobre la mesa de escribir, el tintero,
los pisapapeles y la plegadera estaban tallados en forma de herraduras, estribos o látigos.
Al través de un arco con columnas, mal cerrado por un portier hecho de rico tapiz en el que
figuraban un joven con casaca y peluca de rodillas delante de una joven con traje Pompadour,
veíase un magnífico lecho de caoba con dosel.

Así que llegaron a esta cámara, la dama se dejó caer con negligencia en una butaquita muy linda
y volvió a decirle con sonrisa burlona:

--¡Qué! ¿no te alegras de verme?

--Mucho; pero me alegraría de haberte visto primero. Hace hora y media que te estoy esperando.

--¿Y qué? ¿Es gran sacrificio esperar hora y media a la mujer que se adora? ¿Tú no has leído
que Leandro pasaba todas las noches el Helesponto a nado para ver a su amada?... No; tú no
has leído eso ni nada.... Mejor: yo creo que te sentaría mal la ciencia. Los libros disiparían
esos colorcitos tan lindos que tienes en las mejillas, te privarían de la agilidad y la fuerza
con que montas a caballo y guías los coches.... Además, yo creo que hay hombres que han nacido
para ser guapos, fuertes y divertidos, y uno de ellos eres tú.

--Vamos, por lo que estoy viendo me consideras como un bruto que no conoce ni la A--respondió
triste y amoscado el joven, en pie frente a ella.

--¡No, hombre, no!--exclamó la dama riendo; y apoderándose de una de sus manos la besó en un
repentino acceso de ternura--.Eso es insultarme. ¿Te figuras que yo podría querer a un bruto?...
Toma--añadió despojándose del sombrero--, pon ese sombrero con cuidado sobre la cama. Ahora
ven aquí, so canalla; ya que eres tan susceptible, ¿no consideras que has principiado diciéndome
una grosería?... ¡Hora y media!... ¿Y qué?... Acércate, ponte de rodillas; deja que te tire
un poco de los pelos.

El joven, en vez de hacerlo, agarró una silla-fumadora y se montó en ella frente a su querida.

--¿Sabes por qué he tardado tanto?... Pues por el dichoso niño, que me ha seguido hoy también.

Al decir esto, se puso repentinamente seria; una arruga bien pronunciada cruzó su linda frente.

--¡Es insufrible!--añadió--. Ya no sé qué hacer. A todas horas, salga por la mañana o por la
tarde, traigo aquel fantasma detrás de mí. He tenido que refugiarme en casa de Mariana. Luego,
una vez allí, no hubo más remedio que aguantar un rato. Vino papá, y porque no saliese conmigo
esperé otro poquito a que se fuese.... ¡Ahí ves!

--¡Tiene gracia ese chico!--dijo riendo el caballero.

--¡Mucha! ¡Si es muy divertido que le averigüen a una dónde va y lo sepa en seguida todo el
mundo, y llegue a oídos de mi marido! ¡Ríete, hombre, ríete!

--¿Por qué no? ¿A quién se le ocurre más que a ti tomarse un disgusto por tener un admirador
tan platónico? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01829</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>613786</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20236</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Are you here?

I have not seen your car down.

- I walk out, Dad.

- It's a miracle.

You may want to take mine.

- No, I have desire to walk. I am these days very heavy.

The Duke of Requena had dispensed with all present and spoke to his daughter with all affability that
was susceptible. The rarely seen. Clementina was his natural daughter, having back in Valencia,
when young, a woman from the lowest social class, as he apparently was. Then he had married in
Madrid, and on track to be rich, with a young middle class, which had no family. This woman,
extremely delicate health since her marriage, had given or, rather, had she proposed that her
husband's daughter came to inhabit the same house. Clementina was raised, then, here and was
beloved of his father's wife as a real daughter. She also wanted and respected as a mother.
After the married used to visit often, but as his father was always very busy, did not enter rooms,
and from his mother (so called) was to the street. Only on days banquet or reception, or when
by chance he encountered at home or on the street chatted around
with it.

After asking for her husband and their children, Duke began to talk, not sit, Calderon and Pepa
Frias. A rude man campechanote in appearance, smiled a few times: when he did so was so slight
that it could still be doubted. I used to call the things by their name and address people
not polite, telling the face things that could go through rudeness, because I knew they were not giving
a dye between rough and warm as they took away the sting. It was not very talkative. Generally remained
silent biting his cigar and looking to partner with slanted eyes, impenetrable. Showed speaking
false and sly innocence that he did not unfriendly.

Always looked after the old rogue mercadal of Valencia, right, mocking, suspicious and cunning.

Pepa
Frias told him about business. The widow was tireless in this conversation. I wanted to learn
all, for fear of being deceived profits always eager and trembling with terror comic before
Low perspective of their funds. It was repeated ad nauseam the details. "Would release the
Bank's shares and buy tanks? What did the government do with the redeemable? I had heard rumors.
Do you make the next payment rising? Would not it be better settle
upon thirty cents of profit to wait to make ends meet?

"

For her Salabert words were those of the oracle of Delphi. The banker's immense fame the was
fascinated. Unfortunately, the Duke, like all ancient and modern oracles are always expressed
that he consulted, in an ambiguous way. Often responded with grunts nobody knew whether they were
of affirmation, denial or doubt. The phrases occasionally escaped from his mouth between smoking
and moist lips were dark and dirty, cut, unintelligible in many cases. Moreover, everyone knew it
was not possible to trust him, to be enjoyed in confuse your friends and let them fall headlong
into a bad deal. However, Pepa insisted aspiring to boot from a brain light the secret of mine:
joke took him by the lapels of his coat, calling him old, taciturn, fox, displaying a shamelessness
that it had become flirtatious. The banker did not fire. He was responding with humor as he
grunts and lurid phrase that made laugh Calderon although I really wanted to do seeing tremendous
cast ruthlessly spat on the carpet. For the Duke, the hotness of snuff was not used enough
and salivated repair where to do it, unless in his house tended to get off the spittoon. Calderón
was restless, violent, just as if you cast them in the face. A third Once, unable to restrain
himself, he was looking for the spittoon to put it aside. Salabert sneer at him and winked at Pepa.
Calderón said he was quiet and talkative and sought to replace the Duke Pepa giving advice on the
funds. But though man prudent and skilled in business, the widow not appreciated or even wanted
to hear them. At last After all, between him and Salabert huge gap existed: one was an ordinary
businessman, the another genius from the bench. However, he nodded to the indications inarticulate
sounds stock of the owner of the house. Pepa did not trust.

Salabert pulled away a little of the group and fell on the arm of a chair by one gross position
for which he alone was right. Instead of being frowned upon those manners free and rude, contributed
not a little of its prestige and respect in society idolatrous is taxed. Far from the pan
again returned to salivate over the carpet with some Malicious enjoyment, which despite its good-natured
indifferent mask is reflected by the face. Calderon also turned to cloud and pucker up to, resolving
to jump over certain social ruthlessly, he again approached the spittoon without much value as
before as he did with his foot. Pepa sat on the other arm and continued to Caroca the Duke. This
began to set more attention on it. Their eyes frequent head wrapped at the foot, noticing
that they stopped in the chest high and provocative. Pepa was a woman fresh appetizing. After a
few minutes she leaned banker with little finesse, and bringing her face to face, as it seemed that
it touched his lips, he said quietly

- Do you have many Osuna?

- Some, yes, sir.

- You sell them to escape.

Pepa

looked into his eyes intently and noticed it being stopped.

After a few moments it was she who approached her face as the banker
asked quietly:

- What to buy?

- Redeemable - said the famous millionaire
with the same subject.

Entered at the time a gentleman and a lady, both young, petite, smiling,
and living in his manner.

- Here are my children - Pepa said.

Marriage was a pleasure to watch. Both handsome, open and friendly face, and so young people
who really like two children.

They were greeted one by one to the circles.

In every face guard warned that inspired affection.

- Here is your mother, Emily. What I find so disgusting!

Pepa said do you ?...-- the young.

- Mother in Law, no, mom ... mother - he replied, pressing her hand
affectionately.

- God bless you, son! - Said the widow with a sigh
of comic appreciation.

Again to accommodate the gathering. Married youth sat down together near Mariana. Clementina had
left the place and talked with Maldonado's name sounded Pepe Castro many times on his lips.
Cobo meanwhile used the time, making you laugh with their shameless to Pacita, but even trying
that we hope to jokes with equal pleasure, he could not. The girl Calderón, serious, distracted,
seemed to meet covertly to what Ramon and Clementina spoke. Pinedo was up and paid court to the
Duke. And the general, seeing his idol in animated conversation with the young married, fatigued
its labyrinthine compliments were not understood, nor their rubbings poetic came to do the same.
The Marquise and the priest were whispering sharply beyond a corner, she is increasingly humble
and insinuating, sitting on the edge of the seat, tilting your body to put him on the ear voice,
he more severe and rigid at times, closing at long intervals eyes as if he were in the confessional.

-
Which two babies, eh! - Pepa said aloud, addressing Mariana -.

Is not it shame that these brats are married? How much better would be if they were playing spin!

The
boys smiled looking with love.

- I play ... in moments of leisure - Cobo Ramírez said sarcastically.

- Man, ca! - Pepa said, becoming angry at him -.

Have they given you have them of their games?

He and Emilio exchanged a mischievous look. Irene, she married, she blushed.

- You are getting old, Pepa. Remember that you're a grandmother - Ms. Calderón said.

- What a rich grandma! - Cobo said under his breath, but with the intention that it should hear
the employee.

This gave him an angry glance between smiling and showing that he had heard and appreciated
in the background. Cobo was affecting the distracted.

- Do you have past and berrenchina? - Continued the widow ran to her
children -.

How long will peace? ... Jesus, what creatures so talkative! ... Look, I'm not going to your
house because nose when you meet me feel like taking the broom and breaking the ribs of the
two ....

The circles turned to the young couple smiling. This time he put both strongly red. Then, for
the seriousness that was well marked on the face of Emilio, Could you understand that there
were damn tired casual grace of those outputs her mother.

The general Patiño, by order of the beautiful lady of the house, put his finger on a button electric
bell. Came a servant, he did love a sign: not five minutes passed without providing any further
and after him two trays each with hands filled with cups of tea, pastries and cakes. Pleasant time
of expansion in the party. All are set in motion and shine in the eyes of animal pleasure
which will satisfy an organic necessity. Esperancita hurriedly left his friend and Ramírez
and starts request help with her mother in the task of serving tea to the circles. Ramon takes
the moment when the child presented with a mug to say it quietly
and upset "that very surprised to be pleased to hear the boobs and
phrases Cobo Ramirez daring.

" Hope you look confused, and finally says "she has not heard such blunders, that Cobo is a very
nice and funny guy. "Ramoncito protest weakly, lugubrious intonation against such species and
continues to discredit his friend, until it, smelling the bacon, it about them joking as usual.
Thus, our distinguished councilor is more overcast the face and is withdrawn gradually: that is not
insolent Cobo any nonsense you can think to laugh at his expense.

Came time to talk about literature, as always happens in all night gatherings or evening of the
capital. Patiño General spoke of a brand new play with most happy success and put their buts,
based mainly on increases scenes color. Mariana said no way would you see it then. All agreed
anathematize today's immorality displayed by the authors. They said pests of naturalism. Cobo
Ramirez I had taken and then some sandwiches and had eaten a fabulous amount of buns and biscuits,
spoke to the gathering that he had recently read a novel called Le journal d'une dame (in French
and all), beautiful, bonitísima, the most spiritual that he had read ever. For Cobo, in literature
- rare case! - He was so spiritual, delicate.

No will come to him with such heavy lotas nove-one where you have the time to a bricklayer
stretches to get out of bed (or the cakes and buns that eats a boy good society), nor did he
speak of birth and other similar crap. In the novels should wear nice things, because they
are written to please. This he said with considerable firmness, wheezing to speak like a racehorse.
The others nodded.

The entry of a knight neither tall nor short, neither thin nor fat, elevation of shoulders and
fucked the waist, low color, black beard so thick and cut that seemed fake, cut literary conversation
quickly. Nothing less than was the minister of Public Works. So his head was so upright that nearly
gave the cerebellum in the back, and his eyes half goodbye and closed between the long black lashes
sufficiency and protection lightning to the present. Up to twenty-two had had his head in his natural
position, but from this time, when he was named vice president for civil and canon law at the Academy
of Jurisprudence, had begun to rise slowly and majestically as moonlight on the sea in the Royal
Theatre stage, that is, short and imperceptible tugs of string.

They made a provincial deputy, a tug. Then Member of Parliament, another tug. After the provincial
governor, another tug. Later head of a department; another. Chairman of the Committee on Budgets;
another. Minister; another. The rope was exhausted. Although he made crown prince, Jiménez
Arbós could not lift his one millimeter big head.

His entry was movement, but not as much as the Duke of Requena.

East, whose face fleshy, sensual, could not hide the contempt he
felt for that assembly, ran it though, and you're greeted with amazing
performance and servility, taking into account rusticity and coarseness
with generally behaved in social intercourse.

Minister started handing out handshakes in a way that offended so
distracted.

Only when Pepa Frias greeted showed signs of animation.

This quietly asked tuteándole:

- How come in tails?

- I will eat
at the French embassy.

- Are you going home then?

- Yes.

This dialogue was imperceptible voice very fast observed by the Duke,
who approached Pinedo asked to reserve and making a sign of expression:

-
Say you, and Pepa Frias Arbós?

...

- You have at least two months.

The look she gave him then the banker's widow was not of the quality of the above. Was now
more careful, more respectful and thorough, leaving after a little thought. Calderón had approached
the minister and spoke with compliance. Salabert did the same. But character did not want to
talk business or perchance it was fearful the famous businessman.

The press was reluctant evil on this business with the government. Therefore, a few moments,
he went after Pepa Frias and began to whisper in a corner of the room.

Clementina was increasingly impatient with some atrocious wishes to leave. Kept do so for fear
of his father to accompany her. The minister was a few minutes, before handing another few handshakes
with the same distraction imposing looking, not the person greeted,
but the ceiling of the room.

Then the Duke Pepa Frias took over, showing her as gallant and expressive,
as if to make a declaration of love.

The general, watching, Pinedo said:

- Look at the Duke, which has been encouraged.

Of fixed he is making love to Pepa.

- No - seriously answered the employee -.

What we're making love now is the business of river mines.

The widow announced loudly after he was leaving.

- Where are you going, Pepa, at this time? - Asked the banker.

-
A house Lhardy to order some bologna.

- I accompany you.

- Come
on, you convidaré to take a few cupcakes.

At Duke he was funny treat.

- Are you coming, little girl? - She told her daughter.

Clementina still planned to stay a while.

Pepa, while leaving the arm of the banker said aloud, turning to
the Present:

- Be it known that we are not going away.

Which made them laugh.

- Const - Duke said, laughing - that says it for flatter.

- To explain that: we have not understood ...-- Cobo Ramirez shouted.

But the Duke and Pepa had disappeared behind the curtain. Clementina waited five minutes. When boasted
that he could not stumble on the stairs to his father, rose, and
claiming a chore forgotten, dismissed as well.

III

#'s Daughter Salabert. #

Fell forward to the ladder. To set foot on the street let out a sigh of relief. A brisk took
the Seventh of July, came into the Market Square and then at the Atocha. Al came here came to his mind
the image of the young man had followed her and turned her head uneasily. Nothing, there was
no fear. None followed. At the door of one of the first and better houses in the street, stopped,
looked at them both quickly and secretly sides and penetrated in the portal. He almost imperceptible
sign goalkeeper question. This answered another statement, touching his cap. He rushed up the stairs.
Rose as fast, no doubt to avoid encounters importunate, that on reaching
the second floor choking her fatigue and put a hand on his heart.

With the other he gave two taps on a door. Instantly opened quietly, threw himself in with
a vengeance, as if chased.

- Better late than never - said the young
man who had opened, becoming close with care.

He was a man of twenty to thirty years, more regular tall, thin, thin face and right, pink in
the cheeks, mustache twisted, pointed goatee and black hair and parties in the middle with a
line drawn carefully. Reminiscent of those soldiers paper that children play, that is, was
a military-style sissy. It also seemed his face that tailors usually put their costumes, and
was so nasty and disgusting like theirs. She wore a pearl-colored velvet robe with many exquisite
ornaments wore on her feet slippers of the same gender and color with the initials embroidered
in gold. Warned soon it was one of those men who care with dedication of dressing his person retouching
the figure with the same care and delicacy with which the sculptor carves a statue that curling
mustache and cosmetic believe him to be fulfilling a sacred and inescapable duty conscience, who
are grateful, finally, the Supreme Creator, the graceful presence will have granted them and
try as it is given to improve their work.

- What an afternoon! - She cried the handsome gentleman directing a sad stare counterclaim.

The
lady paid him with a gracious smile, replying at the same time mocking tone:

- Never too late if that is good.

And he took her hand and squeezed it gently, and then led him still
holding the through runners up a cabinet should be the release of
the young.

It was a luxurious room and artistically decorated, the walls lined
with dark blue satin curtains, pinned rings to the ceiling by running
for a bronze bar, chairs and armchairs in different ways and tastes,
a walnut writing table with wrought iron ornaments, next to a locker
with some books, two dozen or so.

Suspended from the ceiling by cords silk and attached to the wall
there hung some horse harness, chairs of various kinds are common,
bastard and outstanding rider in his stirrups, bridles from different
eras and countries, whips, sweatshirts fine worsted embroidery, gold
and silver spurs, all rich and new.

The hobby horse of the owner of that firm is also betrayed in the hallways, that from the front
door leading there, and everywhere hung frames and tables representing wild horses or incidental
thereto. Up to the bureau, the ink, paperweights and letter opener were carved in the form of
horseshoes, stirrups or whips. Through an arc to the columns, not closed by a rich tapestry portiere
fact which included a young man with coat and wig of a young woman kneeling before a suit Pompadour
stood a magnificent four-poster mahogany bed.

So I came to this chamber, the lady dropped carelessly in a very nice
armchair and returned to say with a mocking smile:

- What!

Are not you glad to see me?

- A lot, but I am glad to see you first. Hour and a half ago I'm waiting.

- So what? Do expect great sacrifice and a half to the woman he adores? Have not you read Leandro
spent every night by swimming the Hellespont to see his beloved?

... No, you do not you read that or anything .... Best: I think you
would set bad science.

Books dissipate these colorcito so cute you have in your cheeks,
you deprive them of agility and strength that ride on horseback, and
guides the car .... Besides, I think that there are men who are born
to be handsome, strong and funny, and one of them is you.

- Come
on, I watch what I regard as a brute who does not know the A - answered
sad and piqued the young man standing before her.

- No, man, no!
- Exclaimed the lady, laughing, and seizing one of his hands and kissed
in a sudden access of tenderness - .Eso is insulting.

Do you imagine that I could love a beast? ... Toma - said shedding
the hat - you put the hat on the bed carefully.

Now come here, so rogue, since you are so sensitive, do not you think you've begun telling rude?
... Hour and a half! ... So what? ... Come, kneel, let me pull a bit of hair.

The young, instead of doing so, grabbed a chair, smoking and mounted
it in front of his mistress.

- Do you know why I waited so long?

... As for the happy child, who has followed me today too.

In saying this, he became suddenly serious, a very pronounced wrinkles crossed her pretty face.

-
It's unbearable! - Added -. I do not know what to do. At all times,
leave by the morning or Later, I bring that ghost behind me. I had
to take refuge in the house of Mariana. Then once there, there was
no choice but to take a while. Dad came, and why not come out with
me I waited a little bit to that was .... There you see!

- It's funny
that guy! - The gentleman laughed.

- A lot! If you find out a lot
of fun to know where to go and then all world, and reaches the ears
of my husband's! Laugh, man, laugh!

- Why not? Who comes up with
more than you take a dislike to have a fan as platonic</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>