<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10900</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>89015</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19420</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Ha sido también causa de su disminución las contínuas correrías ó malocas (como llamamos acá)
de los Mamalucos del Brasil, que pasando el río Paraguay y haciendo grandes presas en estos
miserables, han reducido á poco menos que nada estos pueblos. Y ya que muchas veces habré de
escribir las maldades de esta gente, no será fuera del intento de dar de ellos aquí una breve
noticia.

Había la valerosísima nación portuguesa fundado muchas colonias en las partes Mediterráneas
del Brasil, una de ellas era Piratininnga, ó como otros dicen, San Pablo. Sus moradores, por
falta de mujeres europeas, mezclaron su noble sangre con la vilísima de los bárbaros, mejor
dijera que le mancharon, porque los hijos, saliendo más semejantes á las madres que á los padres,
degeneraron en breve de manera que avergonzadas y corridas las ciudades vecinas, renunciaron
su amistad; y porque la vileza de éstos no empañare ni aun levemente los candores de la generosidad
del nombre lusitano en el mundo, los llamaron Mamalucos. Mantuviéronse éstos mucho en la devoción
á Dios y á su príncipe por el celo del admirable P. Joseph Ancheta y sus compañeros, que fundaron
allí Colegio; hasta que cansados de vivir ajustados á los dictámenes de la conciencia, y perdiendo
el temor á las leyes, echaron á nuestros Padres y sacudieron el yugo de ambas majestades, divina
y humana de tal manera, que obedeciesen al Rey de Portugal cuando les estuviese bien, y á Dios,
cuando la necesidad fuese extrema.

A éstos se juntaron gran número de hombres perdidos, italianos, españoles, holandeses y la
hez de todas las naciones, que para librarse de las penas merecidas por sus delitos, ó para
vivir dando rienda á todo género de vicios y deshonestidades, y también corrompido de las feas
y malignas impresiones de los herejes modernos, acrecentar el número y el orgullo de los habitadores
y moradores de San Pablo.

Y á la verdad, el sitio de la ciudad, el clima de la tierra, todo era muy á propósito para
su genio depravado y vida brutal. Está fundada unas trece leguas del Oceano sobre unos peñascos
que por todas partes alrededor forman precipicios que hacen inaccesible la entrada, si no es
por una angosta senda, que pueden impedir bien pocos hombres; á la falda de la montaña hay
algunas aldeas para el servicio del Gobernador, de los forasteros y de los mercaderes, á quienes
no se permite pasar más adelante; el clima es templadísimo por estar en veinticuatro grados
entre las dos zonas tórrida y templada, y el aire tan puro y saludable que le hace uno de los
más amenos y deliciosos países de estas Indias Occidentales.

La tierra, ya por beneficio de la Naturaleza, ya por industria del arte, produce todo lo necesario
para pasar la vida con comodidad, abundantísima de trigo, ganado, azúcar y otros aromas de
que puede proveer á las tierras vecinas con abundancia, ni les faltan tampoco ricos minerales
de oro y otros metales. Libres, pues, de toda ley los naturales de esta ciudad, se dieron á
discurrir por el contorno, haciendo esclavos á los indios en gran multitud, robándoles su hacienda;
y viendo que no ha hecho algún castigo en ellos, sino publicado solamente algunas prohibiciones
y edictos que no han sido obedecidos, han proseguido por espacio de ciento treinta años en
sus infames latrocinios, que fuera de dos millones de almas que se sabe han destruído ó reducido
á miserable esclavitud, han hecho despoblar algunas ciudades de españoles y más de mil leguas
en tierra hacia el Marañón, experimentando esta nuestra provincia las primeras furias de su
arrojo en la destrucción de catorce Reducciones que se habían fundado con increíbles trabajos
y sudores en la nación de los Guaraníes, que en número de cerca de quinientos mil se había
reducido al gremio de nuestra santa fe.

Verdad es que en tantas presas no gozan de cien partes la una, porque la mayor parte, consumida
de los trabajos é incomodidades del camino hasta San Pablo, fallece antes de llegar, y los
otros empleados en la labor de las minas ó en el cultivo de los campos, con poco sustento y
muchos azotes y malos tratamientos, no estando por otra parte acostumbrados al trabajo, en
poco tiempo se consumen y aniquilan; y sé por cédula real que he visto, que de trescientos
mil indios cautivados en espacio de cinco años, no llegaron á salvamento al Brasil más que
veinte mil. Ni ha sido éste sólo el daño que nos han causado estos crueles hombres; lo peor
es el habernos hecho aborrecibles y abominables á todas las naciones, usando de las mismas
trazas é industrias de que usan y se valen nuestros Misioneros para reducir los gentiles al
conocimiento del verdadero Dios y á la observancia de su santa ley. Fingen, pues, los dichos
Mamalucos que son jesuitas, usando el nombre de Padre, nombre venerable y que estima mucho
á toda la gente, aun á los infieles; hácese uno súbdito, otro superior, y aun Provincial; y
en la rota que padecieron los españoles el año 1696 fué hecho prisionero uno, llamado Juan
Rodríguez, á que añadía el título de Payguazú, que en Guaraní es lo mismo que Padre Grande.

Después, enarbolando cruces y mostrándoles retratos de Cristo Nuestro Señor y su Santísima
Madre, entran en las tierras, acariciando la gente con regalos y brujerías, persuadiéndoles
dejen su nativo suelo y sus pobres Ranchos para fundar una numerosa Reducción, junto con otros
pueblos; y cuando ya los tienen asegurados, meten en prisiones á los caciques y principales
y se llevan por delante la chusma.

Esta infernal astucia nos ha hecho totalmente sospechosos á estas naciones, y muchas veces
corremos riesgos de la vida y se nos malogran las empresas, como nos ha sucedido en los viajes
por el río Paraguay, en que ningún infiel se quiere fiar de nosotros.

Pero no deja Nuestro Señor sin castigo, aun en esta vida, maldad tan enorme, porque los más
tienen malas muertes, y lo peor es que raro es el que de ellos se arrepiente y pide perdón
de sus culpas y maldades, porque se dejan arrastrar de la desesperación y se van al infierno;
y hay sujeto de los nuestros, testigo de vista, que dice que en la rota sobredicha el año de
1696, ninguno de los que murieron en el campo ó se ahogaron en el río, pidió confesión ni dió
señal alguna de arrepentimiento.

Pero no obstante que dichos Mamalucos, ya con engaños, ya con bocas de fuego, han hecho tan
horrendo estrago en estas naciones, incapaces de resistirles con sus débiles y flacas armas,
algunas veces, en no pocos reencuentros, han vuelto con las manos en la cabeza, y ha sido sujetado
su orgullo por los indios; porque éstos, arrestados de una vez á morir ó vencer, se han portado
con tal valor y esfuerzo, que ya en emboscadas, ya en campaña abierta, cara á cara han vencido
el orgullo enemigo, quedando prisioneros los que querían echar en prisiones á los indios.

CAPÍTULO IV

Da principio el P. Joseph de Arce á la nueva Iglesia de los Chiquitos, vencidas muchas dificultades.

Entrado, pues, ya el año de 1691 pasó el Padre Provincial de esta provincia, Gregorio de Orozco,
á visitar el Colegio de Tarija para entrar por allí á las tierras de los Chiriguanás y probar
á lo menos por algún poco de tiempo las incomodidades que sus súbditos habían de tolerar después
años enteros y hallarse en alguno de tantos peligros en que después ellos habían de vivir continuamente.
Aquí recibió las cartas del gobernador de Santa Cruz de la Sierra y las súplicas del P. Arce,
que desde Tariquea había venido para meter fuego más de cerca á negocio de tanto servicio de
Dios y bien de las almas, con esperanza de que algún día tendría la fortuna de regar con sus
sudores aquel nuevo campo y de derramar en él, por último, su sangre, predicando la fe.

Hallóse perplejo el Provincial en la resolución que tomaría, porque el celo de la salud de
las almas le persuadía abrazase á un mismo tiempo muchas empresas y diese principio, cuanto
le fuese posible, á nuevas obras para la dilatación de la fe; por otra parte, veía la grande
carestía de operarios que había y que apenas se podían mantener las Misiones antiguas, cuanto
más emprender otras nuevas.

Pesando, pues, atenta y maduramente estos motivos, le pareció que el primero no solo contrapesaba,
sino prevalecía al segundo, esperando en Dios que le proveería de Misioneros, como de hecho
sucedió, pues llegaron aquel mismo año á Buenos Aires cuarenta y cuatro sujetos de la Compañía,
que darán mucha materia á la historia de esta provincia, y los despachaba de España el P. Procurador
de esta provincia, Diego Francisco de Altamirano, á cargo del P. Antonio Parra, que venía por
superior de todos.

Con esto el P. Orozco ordenó al P. Arce que fuese en busca del origen del río Paraguay explorando
en el ínterin las voluntades de los Chiquitos y de las otras naciones que hallase dispuestas
á recibir el Santo Bautismo, y que á lo largo de la costa de aquel río esperase á los Padres
Constantino Díaz, natural de Ruinas, en Cerdeña; Juan María Pompeyo, de Benevento, en el reino
de Nápoles, Diego Claret, de Namur, en la Galo-Bélgica; Juan Bautista Neuman, de Viena, en
Austria; Enrique Cordule, de Praga, en Bohemia; Felipe Suárez, de Almagro, en la Mancha, y
Pedro Lascamburu, superior de todos, de Irún, en Guipúzcoa; todos los cuales, saliendo de las
Misiones de los Guaraníes, emprendían por agua el camino hacia el lago de los Xarayes para
ser sus compañeros en la conversión de aquellos pueblos.

Alegre el santo varón con la posesión de tanta dicha, como verse digno de una señalada Misión,
sin perder punto de tiempo, se partió de Tarija con el hermano Antonio Rivas, y llegando á
Santa Cruz de la Sierra, se aparejaba ya para pasar adelante en su derrota, cuando el infierno,
que interesaba tanto en que se embarazasen sus designios, levantó contra él un torbellino de
persecución tan fiero, que si no hubiera encontrado con un corazón y celo tan apostólico, hubiera
bastado á contrastarle totalmente: porque habiendo sucedido otro Gobernador, á D. Agustín de
Arce, mudaron las cosas de semblante y tomaron otro color, y sabiendo sus intentos, procuraron
apartarle de su propósito con cuantas más razones y autoridad pudieron, diciéndole era aquella
una empresa que no saldría felizmente por más fatigas que padeciese por conseguirla; que siendo
los Chiquitos, como decían, muy bárbaros y bestiales, ¿cómo había de poder sujetarlos de grado
al yugo de Cristo y refrenar sus depravadas costumbres con la estrechez de la ley Evangélica,
cuando ellos jamás habían querido aplicarse á ninguna de tantas idolatrías de los confinantes
con ser muy conformes con la disolución de sus procederes? ¿Cómo había de introducir el amor
de Dios y del prójimo en corazones faltos, aun de lo que la naturaleza dicta á las fieras más
crueles y salvajes? Que era mucha su animosidad, si ya no era temeridad revestida de celo,
en querer arrojarse á morir, cuando menos mal le fuese, á ser vendido bárbaramente; que no
se fiase de la voluntad que aquéllos salvajes habían mostrado de ser cristianos, pues todo
lo hacían á fin de dejar descuidar á los españoles, y cogiéndolos de improviso, robarles las
haciendas con insultos. Y que cuando aquéllas razones no les conveciesen para desistir de la
empresa, advirtiese y supiese que el clima era sobremanera nocivo á la complexión de los extraños,
y que padeciendo casi todos los años contagio aquellos pueblos, no le perdonarían á él. Que
por tanto enderezase sus designios á otra mies y escogiese otro campo que correspondiese el
cultivo con fruto más digno de sus fatigas.

Con estos y otros argumentos de este jaez procuraban muchos caballeros (mejor diré el mismo
infierno) apagar la encendida caridad que ardía en el pecho del P. Joseph, pero viendo que
nada aprovechaba, intentó otra máquina más formidable. Esta fué el interés, único contagio
de las cosas hechas, ó que se han de hacer por Dios.

Habíase formado tiempo antes una Compañía (llamémosla así) de mercaderes europeos que hacían
feria de los indios, y los compraban tan baratos, que una mujer con su hijo, valía tanto como
entre nosotros vale una oveja con su cordero.

Entraban éstos en las tierras de los indios circunvecinos y en breve tiempo hacían gran presa
de esclavos; y cuando no tenían bastantes, so color de vengar alguna injuria recibida, daban
de improviso sobre las Rancherías y pasada á cuchillo la gente que podía tomar armas, ó si
no abrasada viva dentro de sus casas, llevaban cautiva la chusma, y vendían en el Perú estas
mercancías muy caras, con que al año montaba la ganancia muchos millares de escudos.

Llevaba muy mal la piedad de los españoles que la codicia destruyese y acabase aquellos pueblos
é infamase el buen nombre de la nación, y no menos se sentía la fe de que tales maldades de
los suyos la desacreditasen ó hiciesen sumamente abominable con todas aquellas naciones; pero
por no romper á las claras con aquellos mercaderes y alborotar la provincia, no se atrevían
los Regidores á reclamar en Tribunal Supremo; hasta que los años pasados, estimulados de nuestros
misioneros, de los Moxos y de los Chiquitos, se quejaron gravemente en la Real Audiencia de
Chuquisaca, pero por haber ido á defender mercancías tan inícuas en la Audiencia cierta persona
de mucha autoridad y juntamente muy rica y poderosa, aquel sapientísimo Senado, temeroso de
alguna revolución en la provincia, tuvo por consejo más acertado remitir toda la causa al Príncipe
de Santo Bonol Virey y Capitán general de estos Reinos de Perú, quien con cristiana piedad
despachó rigurosas provisiones, so pena de perdimiento de bienes y destierro del país, á cualquiera
que osase comprar y vender á los indios: y al Gobernador que lo permitiese, condenó en privavación
de oficio y multó en doce mil pesos para el Fisco Real.

De esta manera, con incomparable gozo y júbilo de los españoles, se desterró y exterminó totalmente
de toda aquella provincia de Santa Cruz de la Sierra esta infame mercancía, que apoyada de
la codicia se había mantenido allí de pie firme, con gran dolor de los celosos.

He querido referir aquí todo lo dicho, atendiendo más al enlace de los infieles que á las circunstancias
de los tiempos en que sucedieron. Prosigamos ahora nuestra historia.

Habiendo, pues, llegado el P. Joseph á Santa Cruz, halló entablada tan de asiento esta mercancía,
y tan apoyada con la autoridad de gente de mucha suposición, que á pecho menos constante y
firme que el suyo, á quien nunca asustó el miedo, ni respeto humano, hubiera sido imposible
resistir á la fuerza de tantos contrastes; por lo cual es inexplicable lo que padeció y trabajó
para desarraigar trato tan inícuo; porque echando de ver los interesados que de poner los nuestros
el pie en aquellas naciones se les había de seguir menoscabo cierto de sus intereses y aun
acabárseles del todo, se le opusieron con todo el esfuerzo posible, previendo de antemano lo
que no mucho tiempo después sucedió, que nuestros católicos reyes, por instancias de los nuestros,
harían aquellos pueblos vasallos suyos, y libres é independientes y los encabezarían en su
Real Corona, de que les resultaría ruina irreparable de su grangería.

Pero fueron vanas todas las baterías que asestaron contra su designio, porque cuando este santo
varón conocía era voluntad de Dios lo que emprendía, no había respeto humano, miedo de peligro,
ni fuerza de embarazos poderosa á hacerle dar un paso atrás, ni desistir de lo comenzado.

Interpuso ruegos y súplicas muy eficaces y supo hablar con tanta energía de espíritu, que aquellos
mercaderes, teniendo la nota de impíos y crueles, se dieron por vencidos, mejor diré y con
más verdad, persuadidos á que, ó consumido de los muchos trabajos que era preciso padecer,
ó muerto á manos de los bárbaros, acabaría en breve la vida, le dieron paso franco para que
desahogase su santo celo.

Sólo faltaba ya quien le sirviese de guía en su viaje, porque sin ella era imposible entrar
y penetrar las tierras de los Chiquitos; y me persuado que el no hallar por entonces algún
práctico en los caminos, fué astucia y traza del demonio, que preveía la ruina que había de
causar á su partido el celoso Misionero. Pero era éste incansable y no dejaba piedra por mover
para conseguir su condución á aquellas provincias; con que á costa de bastantes trabajos halló,
finalmente, dos hombres de aguante, con quienes se concertó para que le guiasen y llevasen
hasta las primeras Rancherías de los Piñocas.

Triunfante, pues, de esta manera de todo el infierno, que contra él se había conjurado, se
puso en camino á los nueve de Diciembre; y sabiendo que el contagio hacía por aquel tiempo
gran riza en aquella gente, cada momento le parecía un siglo por llegar cuanto antes y poder
remediar, ya que no los cuerpos, á lo menos las almas de aquellos miserables.

Por eso le parecía poco arrojarse por los despeñaderos, subir sierras muy altas, vadear ríos
muy peligrosos, meterse por pantanos muy cenagosos y profundos y pasar otros grandes riesgos
de la vida; antes en todos éstos se hallaba una suavidad indecible, llevando siempre muy fijo
el corazón y la mente en el extremo abandono en que se hallaban aquellos pobres gentiles; no
tenía reposo ni quietud viendo la pérdida de tantos; y lo que más le llegaba al alma, que ellos
mismos, de grado, pedían ser lavados en las saludables aguas del santo bautismo.

Por fin, á los últimos de Diciembre, llegó más muerto que vivo por los muchos trabajos, fatigas
y molestias que sufrió, á las tierras tan deseadas de los Piñocas.

Inexplicable fué el consuelo que recibió el buen Padre de ver satisfechos plenamente sus ardientes
deseos; pero templaban su júbilo las graves miserias y aflicciones de sus amados Chiquitos;
sacábale muchas lágrimas á los ojos el ver aquellos desdichados tendidos y arrojados por los
suelos: unos en descampado, sin abrigo alguno, otros con sólo el reparo de una choza cubierta
sólo de algunas hojas de árboles, y otros luchando con la muerte, y muchos muertos en su infidelidad;
traspasábale el corazón oir á algunos lamentarse inconsolablemente por haber muerto sus parientes
sin haber tenido la dicha de ser (decían) hijos de Dios, como ellos con grande instancia lo
habían pedido. Pero en medio de tanta calamidad fué de grande consuelo y alegría á aquellos
bárbaros ver en sus países un ministro de nuestra santa fe.

Recibiéronle y tratáronle con tierno afecto, dándole de buena gana parte de su pobreza y regalándole
con algunas frutas silvestres, que eran las delicias de más precio que tenían en aquellas miserias.
Suplicáronle se quedase con ellos y no los abandonase en medio de tanta aflicción, prometiendo
levantarle iglesia y casa y proveerle de lo necesario para su sustento. Condujéronle desde
aquí á un paraje poco distante, diciéndole que escogiese allí sitio acomodado y que luego se
pasarían todos juntos á fundar una Reducción.

Viendo, pues, y considerando el P. Arce la buena disposición de la gente, y que si se ausentaba
de ellos los dejaba en un total desamparo, se resolvió á quedarse; y estando ya próximo el
tiempo de las lluvias que inundan las campañas y cierran los caminos para ir á encontrar en
las riberas del río Paraguay á sus conmisioneros, que venían de las Reducciones de los Guaraníes,
le pareció más conforme á las órdenes que llevaba de su Provincial hacer aquí alto y dar principio
á aquella nueva cristiandad que daba tan buenas esperanzas de que correspondería en adelante
con la multitud y fervor de los fieles al cultivo y celo de los obreros evangélicos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02451</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>328094</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17451</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Has been a cause of its decline the continuous raids or huts (as we call here) of Mamalucos of
Brazil, Paraguay and crossing the river by large dams in these miserable, reduced to nothing
to these people. And as many times shall I write the wickedness of these people, not outside
of them attempt to give here a brief news.

The valiant Portuguese nation had founded many colonies in the Mediterranean parts Brazil, one
of them was Piratininnga, or as others say, San Pablo. Its inhabitants, by lack of European
women, mixed their blood with the unholy noble barbarians, better said he spotted him, for
the children, leaving them more like mothers to the fathers, soon degenerated so embarrassed and
runs the neighboring cities, resigned their friendship, and because the vileness of these are
not even slightly empañare candor generosity Lusitanian name in the world, called Mamalucos. Mantuviéronse
much devotion they God and his prince by the admirable zeal of P. Joseph Ancheta and his companions,
who founded College there, until he tired of living adjusted to the dictates of conscience, and losing
fear to the laws, to cast our Fathers and threw off the yoke of both majesties divine and so human,
that obey the King of Portugal when they were good, and God, when the need was extreme.

To these were joined together large numbers of men lost, Italian,
Spanish, Dutch and dregs of all nations, to escape the deserved punishment
for their crimes, or to giving free living to all kinds of vices and
dishonesty, and the ugly corrupted and malignant impressions of modern
heretics, to increase the number and the pride of the inhabitants
and residents of San Pablo.

And indeed, the site of the city, the climate of the earth, all was well adapted to genius depraved
and brutal life. It is founded some thirteen miles from the ocean on a cliff that are everywhere around
cliffs that are inaccessible input, if not by a narrow path, which
may prevent very few men at the foot of the mountain there some villages
to serve the Governor, of strangers and merchants, to whom not allowed
to pass below, the weather is templadísimo to be in twenty-four degrees
between the two torrid and temperate zones, and air so pure and healthy
that makes him one of the more enjoyable and delicious these West
Indian countries.

Land, and for the benefit of nature and art by industry produces everything needed to spend your
life with comfort, abundant wheat, livestock, sugar and other flavorings it can provide to
the surrounding land with plenty, and they lack either rich minerals gold and other metals. Free
because of all the natural law of this city, occurred discourse by the outline, making slaves
of the Indians in large crowds, stealing their property; and seeing that there had been any punishment
on them, but published only a few prohibitions and edicts have been
obeyed, have continued for one hundred and thirty years his infamous
robberies, which were of two million people known to have destroyed
or reduced miserable slavery to have been depopulated some Spanish
cities and over a thousand miles ground to the Marañón, our province
is experiencing the fury of their first throw in the destruction of
fourteen reductions that had been founded with amazing works and sweating
in the nation of the Guarani, who number about five hundred thousand
had reduced to the bosom of our holy faith.

Truth is that many companies do not enjoy one hundred parts, for the most part, consumed of work
and inconvenience of the road to San Pablo, died before arriving, and other employees in the
work of the mines or in the cultivation of fields, with little support and many blows and bad treatment,
not being on the other hand used to working in quickly consumed and annihilated, and royal know
I've seen, that three hundred thousand Indians enthralled in the space of five years, Brazil
came to rescue more than twenty thousand. Nor was it only the damage we have caused these cruel
men, the worst is making us loathsome and abhorrent to all nations, using the same traces and
industries that use and rely our Missionaries to reduce Gentile knowledge of the true God and
to the observance of His holy law. Pretend, then, these Mamalucos who are Jesuits, using the
name of the Father, venerable name and considers much to all people, even the unbelievers
make one subject, other than, and even provincial, and in broken
Spanish suffered by the year 1696 was made a prisoner named John Rodriguez,
who added the title of Payguazú that Guaraní is the same as Father
Grande.

Then, waving crosses and showing pictures of Christ Our Lord and His Blessed Mother, come into
the land, touching people with gifts and witchcraft, persuading leave their native soil and
its poor Ranchos to found a large reduction, together with other people, and when and are
insured to get into prison chiefs and principal ahead and take the mob.

This infernal cunning suspect has made us fully to these nations, and often take risks in life
and spoil our business, as has happened in travel the river Paraguay, in which no infidel is
to trust us.

But our Lord does not leave unpunished, even in this life, evil so great, because most are bad
deaths, and the worst is that rare is that they will repent and ask forgiveness of his sins
and wickedness, because they are drawn from despair and go to hell
and no subject of ours, an eyewitness, who said that in the year aforesaid
broken 1696, none of those who died in the camp or drowned in the
river, called confession and gave sign of repentance.

But despite these Mamalucos, and by fraud, fire hydrants already have done so horrendous havoc
in these countries, unable to resist with their weak and skinny arms sometimes, in many reunions,
is back with his hands on his head, and has been subjected his pride
for the Indians, because they, once arrested for beating to death
or have been ported with such courage and effort, and in ambushes,
and open campaigning, face to face has expired pride enemy prisoners
leaving the prison who wanted to take the Indians.

CHAPTER IV

Da principle P. Joseph de Arce to the new Church of the Chiquitos, overcome many difficulties.

Entered,
then, since the year 1691 passed the Father Provincial of the province, Gregorio Orozco, to visit
the College of Tarija to go there to land and test the Chiriguanos , at least for some little
time the hardships that his subjects had to tolerate after for years and found in one of many
hazards that after they had to live continuously.

Here he received letters from the governor of Santa Cruz de la Sierra and pleas from P. Arce,
since Tarichea had come to send fire more closely to both business service God and the good
of souls, in hope that one day have the fortune of water with sweats this new field and shed on it,
finally, blood, preaching the faith.

Provincial puzzled found himself in the resolution that would, for
the zeal of health souls persuaded him to embrace the same time many
companies and give principle, the it were possible, to new works for
the expansion of faith, on the other hand, saw the largest shortages
of workers who had and that they could hardly keep the old missions,
the undertake more new ones.

Weighing therefore carefully and maturely these reasons, it seemed that the former not only counterbalanced,
but prevailed during the second waiting on God to provide for missionaries, and in fact happened
since that year came to Buenos Aires forty-four subject of the Company that will much matter to
the history of this province, and despatched from Spain P. Attorney of this province, Francisco Altamirano
Diego, in charge of P. Antonio Parra, who was coming top of all.

With this, the P. Ordered Orozco P. Arce was looking for the source of the Paraguay River exploring
in the meantime the will of the Chiquitos and other nations that
are disposed to receive Holy Baptism, and along the shore of that
river hopes for parents Constantino Diaz, a native of Ruins, Sardinia,
Juan María Pompey, of Benevento, in the kingdom Naples, Diego Claret,
Namur, in the Gallo-Belgium; Juan Bautista Neuman, of Vienna, Austria;
Enrique Cordula, Prague, in Bohemia, Felipe Suarez of Almagro in La
Mancha, Pedro Lascamburu, superior to all of Irun, in Guipuzcoa, all
of them, leaving the Guarani missions, begun on the water the way
to the lake for Xarayes be their partners in the conversion of those
peoples.

Alegre the holy man with possession of so much happiness, as being worthy of a designated Mission
without losing time point, we started from Tarija with the brother Antonio Rivas, and arrived
at Santa Cruz de la Sierra, was rigged and to move forward in their
defeat, when the hell that much interested in who conceived his plan,
he stood up against a whirlwind of persecution so fierce, if I had
not found a heart and as apostolic zeal, had enough to contrast fully:
because having happened another governor, Don Augustine Arce, moved
things took a different face and color, and knowing his intentions,
sought from his purpose with as many reasons and authority could,
saying was that a company that would not happily suffer more fatigue
than to get it, that being the Chiquitos, as they say, very barbaric
and brutal, how was able to hold grade the yoke of Christ and his
depraved ways to curb the narrowness of the Evangelical Law, if they
ever want to apply to any of the many idolatries of the confining
to be very satisfied with the dissolution of its procedures?

How could he make love of God and neighbor in hearts lacking, even from what nature gives to the beasts
more cruel and savage? That was a lot of their animosity, if it was not covered with heat rash,
throw in wanting to die, at least you were wrong, to be sold barbarously, that no was relying on
the willingness of those savages had shown to be Christians, for all did he neglect to leave the Spanish,
and catching them unawares, stealing the estates with insults. And when those are not reasons
to abandon the Maars company, notices and knew that the weather was
extremely harmful to the complexion of strangers and almost every
year suffering from infection those people, not to forgive him.

That therefore straighten their designs to another harvest and choose another field that accounts
for fruit crop with more worthy of their labors.

With these and other arguments of this ilk tried many gentlemen (I should say the same hell) off
the burning charity which burned in the bosom of the Father Joseph, but seeing no profit,
tried another machine more formidable. This was the interest, the only transmission of things
done, or that have to do for God.

He had formed long before a company (let's call it that) of European
merchants made Indian fair, and bought so cheap that a woman with
her son, was as good as between us is worth a sheep with her lamb.

They entered in the Indian lands surrounding and within a short time were large dam slave, and when
they were not enough, under the pretext of avenging any injury received, giving suddenly on
the past and sword Rancherías people who could bear arms, or if not burned alive inside their homes,
took captive the mob, and sold in Peru of expensive goods, with which a year riding the gain
many thousands of crowns.

Wearing poorly piety of the Spanish who had just greed destroyed and those people infamous and the
good name of the nation, and felt no less faith that such evils theirs the most abominable hiciesen
discredited or with all nations, but not the clear break with those merchants and disturbing
the province, did not dare the Rulers to claim in the Supreme Court, until the last years, stimulated
our missionaries, the Moxos and Chiquitos, complained seriously of the Royal Court Chuquisaca,
but goods have gone to so iniquitous defend in court a certain person of great authority and
together rich and powerful, that wise Senate, fearing a revolution in the province, had the
most successful board refer the whole case to Prince Santo Bonola Viceroy and Captain General
of these kingdoms of Peru, who with Christian piety dispatched stringent provisions, on pain
of wastage of goods and banishment from the country, to any who dared to buy and sell to the
Indians and the Governor to allow her, condemned privavación of office and fined twelve thousand
dollars for the Royal Treasury.

Thus, with incomparable joy and jubilation of the Spanish, was banished and completely exterminated
throughout the province of Santa Cruz de la Sierra is infamous commodity,
which supported the greed had remained there standing strong, with
great pain of jealousy.

I wanted to refer to everything said here, taking over the infidels that link to circumstances
of time they happened. Now continue our story.

Having thus arrived P. Joseph at Santa Cruz, found that the seat brought these goods and as supported
by the authority of people with a lot assumption, that at least constant
chest his firm, whom he never scared fear, or human respect would
have been impossible resist the force of many contrasts, so it is
inexplicable what he suffered and worked to eradicate unjust treatment
as, for casting to see stakeholders to put our foot in those nations
had to follow some impairment of their interests and even acabárseles
of all, he resisted with every effort, anticipating in advance what
Not long after that happened, that our Catholic kings, by request
of ours, vassals would those peoples, free and independent and would
head in Royal Crown, that they would ruin their grangerie irreparable.

But it was empty all the batteries that blow against his plan, because when this holy man knew
God was he undertook, had no human respect, fear of danger pregnancies and powerful force to
make him take a step back, not abandon it started.

Brought very effective prayers and supplications, and knew about spirit energy so that those
merchants, taking note of the wicked and cruel, they gave up, I should say and more truth, persuaded
that, consumption of the many jobs that needed to suffer, or dead at the hands of the barbarians,
life would end soon, gave free passage to vent their holy zeal.

All that was missing and who guides you on your journey, because without it was impossible to enter
and enter the land of the Chiquitos, and I am convinced that not then find some practical ways,
was cunning and trace the demon, which provided the ruin that was to cause their party to the zealous
missionary. But he was restless and kept no stone unturned to get your condución to those
provinces that at the expense of many jobs found, Finally, two men of endurance, with whom he arranged
to guide him and bear until the early settlements of the Piñocas.

Triumphant, because, this way all the hell that had conspired against him is set off on the ninth of
December, and knowing that the spread was at that time large ripples in these people, every
moment seemed a century to arrive early and remedy, since no bodies,
at least those wretched souls.

For this seemed slightly thrown by the cliffs, climbing very high mountains, ford rivers very dangerous,
very muddy crawl through swamps and deep and have greater risks of life before them all was
an indescribable softness, always being fixed the heart and mind in the extreme neglect of
these poor nations were, not had quiet rest or seeing the loss of so many, and what he came to
the soul, they same, grade, asked to be washed in the salutary waters of holy baptism.

Finally, the last of December, arrived more dead than alive for many jobs, fatigue and pains
he suffered, to the lands so sought-after Piñocas.

Unexplained was the comfort he received the good father to see his
fiery fully satisfied desires, but tempered his elation serious miseries
and sufferings of their beloved Chiquitos; sacábale many tears to
the eyes to see those unfortunate lines and thrown by soils: some
in the open, without shelter some, others with just the repair of
a covered hut only a few leaves, and others struggling with death,
and many killed in their infidelity; traspasábale the heart to hear
some lament inconsolably for dying relatives without having had the
good fortune to be (say) children of God, as you request them with
great had requested.

But in the midst of calamity was of great comfort and joy to those Barbarians in their countries
see a minister of our holy faith.

And tratáronle received him with tender affection, willingly giving of their poverty and giving him
some wild fruits, which were the delight of more money they had in those miseries. Suplicáronle
stay with them and not to abandon them in the midst of grief, promising build churches and
houses and provide what is necessary for their livelihood. Condujéronle from here to a place
not far, saying they chose there off site and then would be all together
to start a taper.

So, seeing and considering the P. Arce the willingness of the people, and if absent of them
left in total despair, he resolved to stay, and being now near the time of the rains that flooded
the campaigns and close the roads to go to find the banks of the Paraguay River to its conmisioneros,
coming from the Guarani Reductions, seemed more according to the orders that led to his provincial
air and get done here first to this new Christianity that was so
good hope that henceforth correspond with the crowd and fervor of
the faithful to the culture and evangelical zeal of the workers.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>