<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04261</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>200116</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18231</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Pasados los lloros y hechas las osequias, el nuevo Inca se encerró á hacer el ayuno; y porque
con su ausencia no recreciese alguna sedicion ó levantamiento de pueblo, mandó que uno de los
más principales de su linage estuviese en público representando su mesma persona; al cual dió
poder para que pudiese castigar al que hiciese por qué, y tener la ciudad en todo sosiego y
paz, hasta que él saliese con la insinia real de la borla. Y este Inca, dicen que tienen por
noticia que fué de gentil presencia, grave y de autoridad. El cual entró en lo más secreto
de su palacio, á donde hizo el ayuno, metiéndole á tiempos el maíz con lo que más comia, y
se estaba sin tener ayuntamiento carnal con muger. Acabado, se salió luego, mostrando con su
vista las gentes gran contento; y se hicieron sus fiestas y sacrificios grandes; y pasadas
las fiestas, mandó el Inca que se trajese de todas partes cantidad de oro y plata para el templo;
y se hizo en el Cuzco la piedra que llaman de la guerra, grande, y las engastonadas en oro
y piedras[116].

Estando Inca Yupanqui en el Cuzco procurando de lo ennoblecer, determinó de ir á Collasuyo,
que son las provincias que caen á la parte del Austro de la ciudad, porque tuvo aviso que los
descendientes de Zapana, que señoreaban la parte de Atuncollao, eran ya muy poderosos y estaban
tan soberbios, que hacian junta de gente para venir sobre el Cuzco; y así, mandó apercibir
sus gentes. Y como el Cuzco mucho tiempo no sufre paz, cuentan los indios, que como hobiese
allegado mucha gente Inca Yupanqui para la jornada que queria hacer, estando ya para se partir,
como hobiesen venido algunos capitanes de Condesuyo con gente de guerra, trataron entre sí
de matar al Inca, porque si de aquella jornada salia con victoria, quedaria tan estimado, que
á todos querria tener por vasallos y criados. Y así, dicen que estando el Inca en sus fiestas
algo alegre con el mucho vino que bebian, allegó uno de los de la liga y que habian tomado
el partido ya dicho, y alzando el brazo, descargó un golpe de baston en la cabeza real, y que
el Inca turbado y con ánimo, se levantó diciendo: "¿Qué hiciste, traidor?" Y ya los de Condesuyo
habian hecho muchas muertes; y el mismo Inca se pensó guarecer con irse al templo; mas fué
en vano pensarlo, porque alcanzado de sus enemigos, le mataron, haciendo lo mesmo á muchas
de sus mugeres.

Andaba gran ruido en la ciudad, tanto que no se entendian los unos á los otros: los sacerdotes
se habian recogido al templo y las mujeres de la ciudad, aullando, tiraban de sus cabellos,
espantadas de ver al Inca muerto de sangre, como si fuera algun hombre vil. E muchos de los
vecinos quisieron desamparar la ciudad, y los matadores la querian poner á saco, cuando, cuentan,
que haciendo gran ruido de truenos y relámpagos, cayó tanta agua del cielo, que los de Condesuyo
temieron, y sin proseguir adelante, se volvieron, contentándose con el daño que habian hecho.

Y [cuentan ó dicen] los indios, que en este tiempo eran señores de la provincia que llamaban
Andaguailas los Quíchuas[117], y que de junto á un lago que habia por nombre Choclococha[118],
salieron cantidad de gente con dos capitanes llamados Guaraca y Uasco, los cuales vinieron
conquistando por donde venian, hasta que llegaron á la provincia dicha; y como los moradores
della supieron su venida, se pusieron á punto de guerra, animándose los unos á los otros, diciendo
que seria justo dar la muerte á los que habian venido contra ellos; y así, saliendo por una
puerta que va á salir hacia los Aymaraes, los Chancas con sus capitanes venian acercándose
á ellos, de manera que se juntaron y tuvieron algunas pláticas los unos con los otros, y sin
quedar avenidos, se dió la batalla entre ellos; que, cierto, segun la fama pregona, fué reñida
y la victoria estuvo dudosa; mas, al fin, los Quíchuas fueron vencidos y tratados cruelmente,
matando á todos los que podian á las manos haber, sin perdonar á los niños tiernos, ni á los
inútiles viejos, tomando á sus mujeres por mancebas. Y hechos otros daños, se hicieron señores
de aquella provincia y la poseyeron como hoy dia la mandan sus descendientes. Y esto hélo contado,
porque adelante se ha de hacer mucha mencion de estos Chancas.

Y volviendo á la materia, como los de Condesuyo se fueron del Cuzco, fué limpiada la ciudad
de los muertos y hechos grandes sacrificios; y se dice por muy cierto, que á Inca Yupanqui
no se le hizo en su entierro la honra que á los pasados, ni le pusieron bulto como á ellos,
y no dejó hijo ninguno.

Pasado lo que se contó conforme á la relacion que los orejones del Cuzco dan de estas cosas,
dicen más, que como se hobiese hecho grandes lloros por la muerte del Inca, se trató entre
los principales de la ciudad quién seria llamado rey é merescia tener la tal dignidad. Sobre
esto habia diversas opiniones; y porque tales hobo que querian que no hobiese rey, sino que
gobernasen la ciudad los que señalasen, otros decian que se perdia sin tener cabeza.

Sobre estas cosas habia gran ruido; y temiendo su porfía, se cuenta que salió una mujer de
través de los Anancuzcos, la cual dijo: "¿En qué estais ahí? ¿Por qué no tomais á Viracocha
Inga, pues lo merece tan bien?" Oida esta palabra, como son tan determinables estas gentes,
dejando los vasos del vino, á gran priesa fueron por Viracocha Inga, hijo de Inca Yupanqui[119],
diciéndole, como le vieron, que ayunase lo acostumbrado y recebiese la borla que darle querian.
Viniendo Viracocha en ello, se entró á hacer el ayuno y encargó la ciudad á Inca Roca Inca,
su pariente, y salió al tiempo con la corona, muy adornado, y se hicieron fiestas solenes en
el Cuzco, y que muchos dias duraron, mostrando todos gran contento con la eleccion del nuevo Inca.

Del cual algunos quisieron decir que este Inca se llamó Viracocha por venir de otras partes
y que traia traje diferenciando, y que en las faiciones y aspecto mostró ser como un español,
porque traia barbas. Cuentan otras cosas que más cansáran, si las hobiese de escribir. Yo pregunté
en el Cuzco á Cayo Tupac Yupanqui y á los otros más principales que en el Cuzco me dieron la
relacion de los Incas que yo voy escribiendo, y me respondieron ser burla y que nada es verdad;
porque Viracocha Inga fué nascido en el Cuzco y criado, y que lo mesmo fueron sus padres y
abuelos; y que el nombre de Viracocha se lo pusieron por nombre particular, como lo tiene cada uno.

Y como le fué entregada la corona, se casó con él una señora principal, llamada Runtu Caya[120],
muy hermosa. Y como la fiesta del regocijo hobiese pasado, determinó de salir á conquistar
algunos pueblos de la redonda del Cuzco que no habian querido el amistad de los Incas pasados,
confiados en la fuerza de sus pucaraes; y con la gente que quiso juntar, salió del Cuzco con
sus ricas andas, con guarda de los más principales, y endrezó su camino á lo que llamaban Calca[121],
á donde habian sido rescebidos sus mensajeros con mucha soberbia; más, como supieron los del
Cuzco ya estaban cerca dellos, se juntaron, armándose de sus armas, y se ponian por los altos
de los collados en sus fuerzas y albarradas, de do desgalgaban[122] grandes piedras encaminadas
á los reales del Inca, para que matasen á los que alcanzasen. E los enemigos, poniéndolo por
obra, subieron por la sierra, y apesar de los contrarios, pudieron ganarles una de aquellas
fuerzas. Como los de Calca[123] vieron los del Cuzco en sus fuerzas, salieron á una gran plaza,
á donde pelearon con ellos reciamente, y duró la batalla desde por la mañana hasta el medio
dia, y murieron muchos de entrambas partes, y fueron más los presos. La victoria quedó por
los del Cuzco.

El Inca estaba junto á un rio, donde tenia asentados sus reales, y como supo la victoria, sintió
mucha alegría. Y en esto, sus capitanes abajaban con la presa y cativos. Y los indios que habian
escapado de la batalla con otros capitanes de Calca y de sus comarcas, mirando que pues tan
mal les habia cuadrado el pensamiento, que el final remedio que les quedaba era tentar la fe
del vencedor y pedirle paz con obligarse á servidumbre moderada, como otros muchos hacian;
y así acordado, salieron por una parte de la sierra, diciendo á voces grandes: "Viva, para
siempre viva el poderoso Inca Viracocha, nuestro Señor." Al roido que hacia el resonante de
las voces, se pusieron en armas los del Cuzco, más no pasó mucho tiempo, cuando ya los vencidos
estaban postrados por tierra delante de Viracocha Inga; á donde, sin levantar, uno que entre
ellos se tenia por más sabio, alzando la voz, comenzó á decir: "Ni te debes, Inca, ensoberbecer
con la vitoria que Dios te ha dado, ni tener en poco á nosotros por ser vencidos, pues á tí
y á los Incas es permitido señorear las gentes, y á nosotros es dado con todas nuestras fuerzas
defender la libertad que de nuestros padres heredamos, y cuando con ello salir no pudiéremos,
obedecer y recibir con buen ánimo la subjecion[124]. Por tanto, manda que ya no muera más gente
ni se haga daño, y dispon de nosotros á tu voluntad." Y como el indio principal hobo dicho
estas palabras, los demás que allí estaban dieron aullidos grandes, pidiendo misericordia.

El rey Inca respondió, que si daño venido les habia, que su ira habia sido la culpa, pues al
principio no quisieron creer sus palabras ni tener su amistad, de que á él habia pesado; y
liberalmente les otorgó que pudiesen estar en su tierra poseyendo, como primero, sus haciendas,
con tanto que, á tiempo y conforme á las leyes, tributasen de lo que hobiese en sus pueblos
al Cuzco; y que dellos mismos fuesen luego á la ciudad y le hiciesen dos palacios, uno dentro
della y otro en Caqui[125], para se salir á recrear. Respondió que lo harian, y el Inca mandó
soltar los cativos, sin que uno sólo faltase, y restituir sus haciendas á los que ya tenian
por sus confederados; y para que entendiesen lo que habian de hacer y entre ellos no hobiese
disensiones, mandó quedar un delegado suyo con poder grande, sin quitar el señorío al señor
natural.

Pasado lo que se ha scripto, Inca Viracocha envió un mensajero á llamar á los de Caitomarca[126],
questaban de la otra parte de un rio hechos fuertes, sin jamás haber querido tener amistad
con los Incas que habia habido en el Cuzco; y como llegó [el] mensajero de Viracocha Inga,
le maltrataron de palabra, llamando al Inca loco, pues así creia que ligeramente se habian
de someter á su señorío.

Luego que hobo enviado el mensajero Viracocha Inga, mandó á sus gentes que, alzado el real,
caminasen para se acercar á Caitomarca. Y andando por el camino, llegó junto á un rio, á donde
mandó que parasen para refrescar; y estando en aquel lugar, llegó el mensajero, el cual contó
cómo los de Caitomarca habian burlado dél, y cómo decian que ningun temor tenian á los Incas.
Y cómo fué entendido por Viracocha Inga, con gran saña subió en las andas, mandando á los suyos
que caminasen á toda priesa; y así lo hicieron hasta ser llegados á la ribera de un rio caudaloso
y de gran corriente, que creo yo debe ser el de Yucay[127]; y mandó poner sus tiendas el Inca,
y quisiera combatir el pueblo de los enemigos, que de la otra parte del rio estaban; más iba
el rio tan furioso, que no se pudo poner en efecto. Los de Caitomarca llegaron á la ribera,
desde donde con las hondas lanzaban muchas piedras al real del Inca, y comenzaron de una y
otra parte á dar voces y gritos grandes; porque en esto es estraña la costumbre conque las
gentes de acá pelean unos con otros, y cuán poco dejan á sus bocas reposar.

Dos dias cuentan questuvo en aquel rio el Inca sin pasarlo, que no habia puente ni tampoco
se usaban las que agora hay ántes que hobiese Incas; porque unos dicen que sí y otros afirman
que nó. Y como pasase el rio Viracocha Inga, dicen que mandó poner en un gran fuego una piedra
pequeña, y como estuviese bien caliente, puesto en ella cierta mestura ó confacion, para que
pudiese en donde tocase enprender la lumbre, la mandó poner en una honda de hilo de oro, conque,
cuando á él placia, tiraba piedras, y con gran fuerza la echó en el pueblo de Caitomarca; y
acertó á caer en el alar de una casa que estaba cubierta con paja bien seca, y luego con ruido
ardió de tal manera, que los indios acudieron por ser de noche al fuego que vian en la casa,
preguntándose unos á otros qué habia sido aquello y quién habia puesto el fuego á la casa.
Y salió de través una vieja, la cual dicen que dijo: "Mirá lo que os digo y lo que os conviniere,
sin pensar que de acá se haya puesto fuego á la casa, ántes creed que vino del cielo, porque
yo lo ví en una piedra ardiendo, que, cayendo de lo alto, dió en la casa y la paró tal como
la veis.

Pues como los principales é mandones con los más viejos del pueblo aquello oyeron, siendo,
como son, tan grandes agoreros y hechiceros, creyeron que la piedra habia sido enviada por
mano de Dios, para castigarlos porque no querian obedecer al Inca; é luego, sin aguardar respuesta
de oráculo ni hacer sacrificio ninguno, pasaron el rio en balsas, llevando presentes al Inca;
y como fueron delante su presencia, pidieron la paz, haciéndole grandes ofrecimientos con sus
personas y haciendas, así como lo hacian los confederados suyos.

Sabido por Viracocha Inga lo que habian dicho los de Caitomarca, les respondió con gran disimulacion,
que si aquel dia no hubieran sido cuerdos en venir, que el siguiente tenia determinado de dar
en ellos con grandes balsas que habia mandado hacer. Y pasado esto, se hizo el asiento entre
los de Caitamarca y el Inca; el cual dió al capitan ó señor de aquel pueblo una de sus mujeres,
natural del Cuzco, la cual fué estimada y tenida en mucho.

Por la comarca destos pueblos corria la fama de los hechos del Inca, y muchos, por el sonido
della, sin ver las armas de los del Cuzco, se le mandaban á ofrescer por amigos y aliados del
rey Inca, que no poco contento con ello mostraba tener, hablando á los unos y á los otros amorosamente
y mostrando para con todos gran benivolencia, proveyendo de lo que él podia á los que veia
tener necesidad. Y como vido que podia juntar grande ejército, determinó de hacer llamamiento
de gente para ir en persona á lo de Condesuyo.

De todas las cosas que á Viracocha sucedian iban al Cuzco las nuevas; y como en la ciudad se
contase la guerra que tenia con los de Caitamarca, dicen que se levantó un tirano hermano de
Inca Yupanqui el pasado, el cual, habiendo estado muy sentido, porque el señorío y mando de
la ciudad se habia dado á Viracocha Inga y no á él, y aguardaba tiempo oportuno para procurar
de haber el señorío. Y este pensamiento tenia éste, porque hallaba favor en alguno de los orejones
y principales del Cuzco del linaje de los Orencuzcos; y con la nueva desta guerra que el Inca
tenia, paresciéndoles que tenia harto que hacer en la fenecer, animaban á este que digo, para
que, sin mas aguardar, matase al que en la ciudad por gobernador habia quedado, para se apoderar
della.

Capac, que así habia por nombre, codicioso del señorío, juntados sus aliados, en un dia questaban
en el templo del sol todos los más de los orejones y entre ellos Inca Roca, el gobernador del
Inca Viracocha, tomando las armas, publicando libertad del pueblo y que Viracocha Inga no pudo
haber el señorío, arremetieron para el lugarteniente y lo mataron así á él como á otros muchos;
la sangre de los cuales regaba los altares donde estaban las aras y santuarios y las figuras
del sol. Las mamaconas con los sacerdotes salieron con grand ruido, maldiciendo á los matadores,
diciendo, que, tan grand pecado, grand castigo merecia. De la ciudad acudió grand golpe de
gente á ver lo que era; y entendido, unos, aprobando lo hecho, se juntaron con Capac; otros,
pesándoles, se pusieron en armas sin querer pasar por ello; y así, habiendo divison, caian
muchos muertos de una parte y de otra. La ciudad se alborotó en tanta manera, que reendiendo
por los aires el sonido de sus propias voces, no se oian ni entendian. En esto, prevaleciendo
el tirano, se apoderó de la ciudad, matando á todas las mugeres del Inca, aunque las más principales
habian ido con él. Huyéronse de la ciudad algunas, las cuales fueron á parar á donde Viracocha
Inga estaba; y como por él fué entendido, disimulando el pesar que sintió, mandó á su gente
que caminasen la via del Cuzco.

Pues volviendo á Capac el tirano, como hobo tomado la ciudad en sí, quiso salir en público
con la borla, para por todos ser tenido por rey; más como el primer ímpetu fuese pasado, y
aquel furor conque los hombres, saliendo de su entero juicio, acometen grandes maldades, los
mesmos que lo incitaron á que se levantase, riéndose de que quisiese la dignidad real, le injuriaron
de palabra y le desampararon, saliendo á encontrarse con el verdadero Señor, á quien pidieron
perdon por lo que habian cometido.

A Capac no le faltó ánimo para llevar el negocio adelante; mas, viendo la poca parte que era,
muy turbado, viendo la mudanza tan súpita, maldecia á los que le habian engañado y á sí propio,
por fiarse dellos; y por no ver con sus ojos al rey Inca, castigó el mesmo su yerro, tomando
ponzoña, [de que] cuentan que murió. Sus mujeres y hijos con otros parientes le imitaron en
la muerte.

La nueva de todo esto iba á los reales del Inca, el cual, como llegase á la ciudad y entrase
en ella, fué derecho al templo del sol á hacer sacrificios. Los cuerpos de Capac y de los otros
que se habian muerto, mandó que fuesen echados en los campos, para ser manjar de las aves,
y buscando los participantes en la traicion, fueron condenados á muerte.

Entendido por los confederados y amigos de Viracocha Inga lo sucedido, le enviaron muchas embajadas
con grandes presentes y ofrecimientos, congratulándose con él; y á estas embajadas respondió
alegremente.

En este tiempo, dicen los orejones que habia en el templo del sol muchas señoras vírgenes,
las cuales eran muy honradas y estimadas y no entendian en más de lo por mí dicho en muchas
partes desta Historia. Y cuentan que cuatro dellas usaban feamente de sus cuerpos con ciertos
porteros de los que las guardaban, y siendo sentidas, fueron presas y lo mesmo á los adulteradores,
y el sacerdote mayor mandó que fuesen justiciados ellas y ellos.

El Inca estaba con determinacion á lo de Condesuyo, mas, hallándose cansado y viejo, lo dejó.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10629</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>189616</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16728</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

After the tears and made the osequias, the new Inca make the fast shut up, and because heightening
their absence does not lift any sedition or people, and commanded one of the most of their seed
was leading in public accounting with her own person, which gave power to punish it could do
for what, and have the city in calmness and peace, until he come out with real insinia the
tassel. And the Inca, whose claim news that was of noble presence, serious and authoritative.
Which came in the most secret of his palace, to where did the fast, sticking to the corn times
what more he ate, and was without having carnal knowledge with a woman. Finishing, went off
course, showing your sight of people great joy, and made their big feasts and sacrifices, and
past parties, the Inca ordered that all parties bring much gold and silver for the temple
and became stone in Cuzco called the war, large, and the gold engastonadas and rocks [116].

While in Cuzco Inca Yupanqui trying to ennoble him, determined to
go to Collasuyo which are the provinces that fall to the party of
the south of the city, because he had notice that Zapana descent that
dominated the Atuncollao part, were already very powerful and were
so proud, she got together with people to come on Cuzco, and so, he
ordered its people.

And as long Cuzco suffers no peace, have the Indians, who as hobiese many people Inca Yupanqui
aide for the day I wanted to do, having now to be split, hobiesen come as some captains Condesuyo
with warriors, tried together killing the Inca, for if that day came out with victory, would be
so dear, that to all would be vassals and servants. And so, while the Inca say in their parties
something cheerful with lots of wine drinkers, a close one of the league and they had taken
and that the party, and lifting his arm, landed a blow on the head stick real, and the Inca troubled
and courage, stood up saying, "What did you, traitor?" And those of Condesuyo had been many
deaths, and the Inca himself garrison thought of going to the temple, but was in vain to think,
because of his enemies reached, was killed, making do the same to many of their wives.

He walked a great noise in the city, while not understood by one another: the priests it had collected
to the temple and women of the city, screaming, pulling her hair startled to see the dead Inca blood,
like some vile man. And many of neighbors wanted to abandon the city, and the killers wanted
to become a prey, when, count, that making a great noise of thunder and lightning, fell as
much water from heaven, that Condesuyo feared, and no further forward,
turned, satisfied with the damage they had done.

And [have or say] the Indians, who at this time were lords of the province called Quichua Andaguailas
[117], and from beside a lake that had his name Choclococha [118] left many people with two captains
called Guaraca and UASC, which came winning as you came, until they came to the province said, and
as the inhabitants della knew his coming, got ready for war, encouraging
one another, saying it would be fair to give death to those who had
come against them, and so, leaving a door is about to leave for the
Aymara, the chances with his captains came closer to them, so they
got together and had some talks with each other, and without become
avenues, was given the battle between them that way, according to
the fame announces, was at odds and the victory was doubtful, but
in the end, the Quichua were beaten and treated cruelly killing all
that were able to have hands, sparing children to tender, or to those
useless old, taking their wives and concubines.

And make other damage, became lords of that province and possessed as today they send their
children. And this he finds himself cash, because forward has to do much mention of these Chancas.

And
back to the subject, such as Condesuyo left Cuzco, the city was cleaned of the dead and made
great sacrifices, and is said by a certainty that he Inca Yupanqui not him at his funeral to
honor that past, or as they put the package to them, and no child left none.

After what was according to the relationship that the Cuzco apricots give these things say
again that as hobiese made great lamentations for the death of the Inca, it was between the
chief of the city who would be named king and merescia have such dignity. About this had different
opinions, and because such hobo who wanted hobiese not king, but which ruled the city noted,
others said it was lost without his head.

On this there was great noise, and fearing his contention is that a woman came Anancuzcos through,
which said: "What you are there and why you do not take to Viracocha
Inga, they deserve it so well?

"Having heard this word, as these people are so determined, leaving the vessels of wine were
in great haste by Viracocha Inca, son of Inca Yupanqui, [119] saying, as he saw that it used
to, and receive him in awe of the fringe that wanted him. Coming Viracocha in it, it came to
making the fast and ordered the city to Inca Roca Inca his relative,
and left while the crown, very ornate, and made a solemn holiday in
Cuzco, which lasted several days, all showing great satisfaction with
the election of the new Inca.

Which meant that some called Viracocha Inca to come from elsewhere and differentiating who brought
suit, and that in the faiciones and appearance proved to be as a Spanish because he had beards.
They have other things more tired, if hobiese writing.

I asked in Cayo Tupac Yupanqui Cuzco and to the others in the Cuzco major gave me relationship
of the Incas that I am writing, and I answered to be fun and that nothing is true; Viracocha
Inga was because NASCAR in Cuzco and raised, and do the same were his parents and grandparents,
and that the name of Viracocha the particular name was called, as does everyone.

And as I was handed the crown, he married a lady principal, called Runtu Caya [120] very beautiful.
And as the feast of joy hobiese past, determined to win out some villages in the round of Cuzco
who had not wanted the friendship of the Inca past confident in the
strength of their pucaraes, and people who wanted to put together,
out of Cuzco its rich litter, with the most major stores and endrezó
his way to what they called Calca [121] where he had been their messengers
receive him with great pride, more, as they learned of the Cuzco and
were close to Dell, together, arming themselves with weapons, and
set in the high the hills on their strengths and barricades, to do
desgalgaban [122] large stones towards to the actual Inca, to kill
the ones that had.

E enemies, putting it work, climbed the mountains, and in spite of the contrary, they could
beat one of those forces. Because of Calca [123] saw the forces of Cuzco, went out to a large
square to where they fought stoutly, and the battle lasted from morning until noon day, killing many
on both sides, and were more prisoners. The victory is those of Cuzco.

The Inca was next to a river, where they had settled their real, and as he knew the victory,
he felt joy. And in this, his masters down with the dam and cannot.

And the Indians who had escaped from the battle with other captains of Calca and its regions, looking
for since so square bad they had thought, that the final choice that remained was tempting
faith the winner and ask for peace with moderate bound to servitude, like many others were doing;
and so agreed, they went for a portion of the mountain, saying with great voices, "Viva, for
long live the mighty Inca Viracocha, our Lord. "At that gnawed at the resonant voices, took up arms those
of Cuzco, the more it was not long, when the defeated were prostrate on the ground in front
of Viracocha Inga, to which, without looking up, one between They had more wise, his voice began
to say: "Neither should you, Inca, make proud with the victory that God has given you, and take
little to us to be defeated, for thee and the Incas is allowed to rule over the nations, and
is given to us with all our strength defend the freedom we inherited from our parents, and
when doing so not out we can, obey and cheerfully receive the subjection [124]. Therefore, no longer
sends more people die or hurt, we have all thy will. "And as the leading Indian hobo these
words, others who were there were great cries, begging for mercy.

Inca King replied that if they had been hurt, that his anger had been at fault, since the first refused
to believe his words nor have his friendship, that he had heavy, and liberally granted them that
might be in owning land, as the first of their estates, with so much on time and according
to the laws, which are taxed in their villages hobiese Cuzco, and that treats them were then
to the city and might make him two palaces, one inside della and another in Khaki [125] to
be out to recreate. Responded that they would do, and the Inca ordered release the captives,
without missing a single one, and restore their properties to those who already had by his
confederates, and for them to understand what they had to do and these did not hobiese dissensions,
sent a delegate to be great power, without removing the estate to Mr. natural.

After what has been scripto, Inca Viracocha sent a messenger to summon the men of Caitomarca
[126] quest from the other side of a river made strong, without ever having wanted to be friends
the Incas, who had been in Cuzco, and how he got [the] runner Viracocha Inga verbally abused
him, calling the Inca crazy, because he believed that it had slightly to submit to his lordship.

Then they sent a messenger hobo Viracocha Inga, he commanded his people that raised the real
walked to be closer to Caitomarca. And walking along the road, came to a river, where ordered
them to stop for refreshment; and being in that place, the messenger came, which was how to Caitomarca
had scoffed at the, and how they said they had no fear to the Incas. And how it was understood
by Viracocha Inga, with great anger rose in the litter, ordering his men who walk all haste,
and did so until they arrived at the bank of a river flowing and high current, I think I should
be to Yucay [127], and ordered their stores to the Inca and people would fight enemies that
the other side of the river were, most would the river so angry, could not be put into effect.
Caitomarca those arrived at the riverside where with slings threw stones at many real del Inca,
and started one and In addition to giving great shouts and cries,
because this is the strange habit So people here fight with each other,
and how little their mouths to let stand.

Two days have questuvo in that river without passing the Inca, that there was neither bridge
agora which were used there before hobiese Incas, because some say yes and others say no.
And pass the river Viracocha Inga, commanded you to say a big fire
in a stone small, and as was very hot, put into it some mestura or
confacion, so that where enprender could touch the fire, had it put
in a sling of gold thread, and so, when a pleased, threw stones, and
with great force threw it in the village of Caitomarca, and happened
to fall from the eaves of a house that was covered with straw well
seasoned, and then noise burned so that the Indians came for the night
to fire Vian at home asking one another what had become what and who
had set the fire to the house.

And he went out through an old, which reported to have said: "Look what I say and what you
be convenient, here without thinking that has set fire to the house, before they believe that
came from heaven, because I saw a burning stone, which, falling from above, gave the house and
stopped as you see it.

For as the main and bossy with the oldest of the people that heard it, being, as they are, so great
soothsayers and sorcerers, believed that the stone had been sent by hand of God, to punish them
because they did not want to obey the Inca: and then, without waiting for an answer oracle or
make any sacrifice, crossed the river on rafts, leading to the Inca present; as they were before
his presence, asked for peace, making large offerings with persons and property as well as
they did the Confederates own.

Viracocha Inga known for what they had said those Caitomarca, responded with great dissimulation,
that if that day would not have been wise in coming, the next he was determined to them with
large ponds that had mandated. And after this, it became the seat between Caitamarca and those
of the Inca which gave the captain or master of that town one of his wives, native of Cuzco,
which was estimated and taken into a lot.

In the area of ??this village ran the fame of the facts of the Inca, and many, by the sound della
without seeing the arms of Cuzco, I offer you sent to friends and allies Inca king, who showed
little happy with it have, talking to each other lovingly and to and showing great benivolencia
for all, providing what he could to those who saw be necessary. And he saw that he could gather a
great army, he resolved to appeal of people to go in person to Condesuyo.

Of all the things that he went to Cuzco, Viracocha succeeded each
new, and as in the city would tell the war he had with those of Caitamarca
say that there arose a tyrant brother Last Inca Yupanqui, who, having
been deeply felt, because the mastery and control the city had given
to Viracocha Inga and not to him, and waited to ensure timely have
dominion.

This thought had it, because one was in favor of the dried and Cuzco's main Orencuzcos lineage,
and the new of this war that the Inca had, Paresce I had plenty to do in the defunct, encourage
this I say, for that, without further wait, killed in the city who had been governor, to be empowering
della.

Capac, who had his name and, greedy of dominion, coupled its allies,
in an orchestra day in the temple of the sun all over the apricots
and between Inca Roca, the governor of Viracocha Inca, taking up arms,
freedom of the people posting and Viracocha Inga could not have dominion,
to the deputy attacked and killed him and he and many others; blood
which watered the altars were the altars and shrines and figures the
sun.

The virgins and the priests came out with grand noise, cursing the murderers saying that, a great sin,
grand punishment deserved. The city went grand coup people to see what it was, and understood,
about adopting as fact, coupled with Capac, others pesándoles, took up arms not wanting to go
through it, and so, having DIVISION, fell many dead and another part. The city was moved in such
a way that reendiendo the air the sound of their own voices, they
were heard and understood.

In this, prevailing the tyrant, took over the city, killing all the women of the Inca, although
most major had gone with him. Huyéronse some city, which went to where Viracocha Inga was, and
as it was understood, concealing the grief he felt, he ordered his people who walked the Via del Cuzco.

Capac
return now to the tyrant, and hobo taken the city itself, wanted to go public with the fringe,
to be taken by all as king, more like the first impetus was gone, and So that men rage, leaving
his sole discretion, undertake great evils, the mesmos that prompted
him to get up, laughing that he wanted the kingship, they reviled
him speech and forsook him, coming to meet the true Lord, whom requested
sorry for what they had committed.

A Capac did not lack courage to take the business forward, but, seeing the little party was
very upset, seeing the move as Supit, cursed those who had deceived him and to himself, by trust
of them; and not see with their eyes Inca king, punished his mistake he himself, taking poison, [that]
have died. Their wives and children with other relatives joined him in death.

The news of this was going to the actual Inca, which, as will the city and enter in it, went straight
to the temple of the sun to make sacrifices.

Capac bodies and other who had died, he ordered them to be thrown into the fields to be food of birds
and looking for participants in the treason, were sentenced to death.

Understood by the Confederates and Viracocha Inga friends what happened, they sent many embassies
with great gifts and pledges, congratulating him, and responded to these embassies happily.

At
this time, say the apricots that were in the temple of the sun many ladies virgin which was very
honored and valued and did not understand more of what is to me that in many Part of this
history. They say that four of them used their bodies hideously certain porters who guarded,
and being felt, were arrested and do the same to adulterers, and the high priest commanded
them and they were righteous.

The Inca was with Condesuyo determination, but, being tired and old, left.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>