<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01241</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>2564</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>817</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Los caracteres meramente humanos del drama están trazados y aun acabados de mano maestra: parecen
más reales que la realidad. Marta y el fámulo Wagner son dos personajes cómicos que pueden
servir de modelos. Margarita y su hermano están llenos de alta poesía, y no por eso dejan de
pertenecer a una humilde posición social y a una época en que no estaba tan extendida como
ahora la cultura.

La sencillez y naturalidad de ambos hace más distinta, viva, honda y persistente la impresión
que dejan.

Fausto es ya criatura harto más complicada. Lo sobrenatural y lo trascendental influyen en
la formación de su carácter, y entran en él como elementos lo alegórico y lo simbólico, pero
despojándole imaginariamente de estas condiciones, queda un ser verdadero, noble, real y simpático,
a pesar de sus errores y delitos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00462</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>704</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>845</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

The human characters in this drama are masterfully plotted and developed; they seem even more real
than reality itself. Famulus Marta and Wagner are two comedic characters which can serve
as models. Margaret and her brother both wax poetic; however, their social status is too humble
for them to have been so culturally well-rounded, as culture would
not have been so widespread in the time period of the piece.

But the simplicity and purity of both is more distinct and persistent
despite this.

Fausto
is a far more complicated creature.

The supernatural and the transcendent influence the development of his character, and it
becomes the allegorical and symbolic element in the piece. However, even with depriving him of these
influential factors, his character is still true, noble, sympathetic,
and real, despite it's errors and crimes</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>