<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10623</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>6476</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24622</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Al punto salió rápidamente del dormitorio o cuchitril contiguo una mozuela de hasta trece años,
desgreñada, con el cierto andar de quien acaba de despertarse bruscamente, sin más atavíos
que una enagua de lienzo y un justillo de dril, que adhería a su busto, anguloso aún, la camisa
de estopa. Ni miró la muchacha al señor Rosendo, ni le dio los buenos días; atontada con el
sueño y herida por el fresco matinal que le mordía la epidermis, fue a dejarse caer en una
silleta, y mientras el barquillero encendía estrepitosamente fósforos y los aplicaba a las
virutas, la chiquilla se puso a frotar con una piel de gamuza el enorme cañuto de hojalata
donde se almacenaban los barquillos.

Instalose el señor Rosendo en su alto trípode de madera ante la llama chisporroteadora y crepitante
ya, y metiendo en el fuego las magnas tenazas, dio principio a la operación. Tenía a su derecha
el barreño del amohado, en el cual mojaba el cargador, especie de palillo grueso; y extendiendo
una leve capa de líquido sobre la cara interior de los candentes hierros, apresurábase a envolverla
en el molde con su dedo pulgar, que a fuerza de repetir este acto se había convertido en una
callosidad tostada, sin uña, sin yema y sin forma casi. Los barquillos, dorados y tibios, caían
en el regazo de la muchacha, que los iba introduciendo unos en otros a guisa de tubos de catalejo,
y colocándolos simétricamente en el fondo del cañuto; labor que se ejecutaba en silencio, sin
que se oyese más rumor que el crujir de la leña, el rítmico chirrido de las tenazas al abrir
y cerrar sus fauces de hierro, el seco choque de los crocantes barquillos al tropezarse, y
el silbo del amohado al evaporar su humedad sobre la ardiente placa. La luz del candil y los
reflejos de la lumbre arrancaban destellos a la hojalata limpia, al barro vidriado de las cazuelas
del vasar, y la temperatura se suavizaba, se elevaba, hasta el extremo de que el señor Rosendo
se quitase la gorra con visera de hule, descubriendo la calva sudorosa, y la niña echase atrás
con el dorso de la mano sus indómitas guedejas que la sofocaban.

Entre tanto, el sol, campante ya en los cielos, se empeñaba en cernir alguna claridad al través
de los vidrios verdosos y puercos del ventanillo que tenía obligación de alumbrar la cocina.
Sacudía el sueño la calle de los Castros, y mujeres en trenza y en cabello, cuando no en refajo
y chancletas, pasaban apresuradas, cuál en busca de agua, cuál a comprar provisiones a los
vecinos mercados; oíanse llantos de chiquillos, ladridos de perros; una gallina cloqueó; el
canario de la barbería de enfrente redobló trinando como un loco. De tiempo en tiempo la niña
del barquillero lanzaba codiciosas ojeadas a la calle. ¡Cuándo sería Dios servido de disponer
que ella abandonase la dura silla, y pudiese asomarse a la puerta, que no es mucho pedir! Pronto
darían las nueve, y de los seis mil barquillos que admitía la caja sólo estaban hechos cuatro
mil y pico. Y la muchacha se desperezó maquinalmente. Es que desde algunos meses acá bien poco
le lucía el trabajo a su padre. Antes despachaba más.

El que viese aquellos cañutos dorados, ligeros y deleznables como las ilusiones de la niñez,
no podía figurarse el trabajo ímprobo que representaba su elaboración. Mejor fuera manejar
la azada o el pico que abrir y cerrar sin tregua las tenazas abrasadoras, que además de quemar
los dedos, la mano y el brazo, cansaban dolorosamente los músculos del hombro y del cuello.
La mirada, siempre fija en la llama, se fatigaba; la vista disminuía; el espinazo, encorvado
de continuo, llevaba, a puros esguinces, la cuenta de los barquillos que salían del molde.
¡Y ningún día de descanso! No pueden los barquillos hacerse de víspera; si han de gustar a
la gente menuda y golosa, conviene que sean fresquitos. Un nada de humedad los reblandece.
Es preciso pasarse la mañana, y a veces la noche, en fabricarlos, la tarde en vocearlos y venderlos.
En verano, si la estación es buena y se despacha mucho y se saca pingüe jornal, también hay
que estarse las horas caniculares, las horas perezosas, derritiendo el alma sobre aquel fuego,
sudando el quilo, preparando provisión doble de barquillos para la venta pública y para los
cafés. Y no era que el señor Rosendo estuviese mal con su oficio; nada de eso; artistas habría
orgullosos de su destreza, pero tanto como él, ninguno. Por más que los años le iban venciendo,
aún se jactaba de llenar en menos tiempo que nadie el tubo de hojalata. No ignoraba primor
alguno de los concernientes a su profesión; barquillos anchos y finos como seda para rellenar
de huevos hilados, barquillos recios y estrechos para el agua de limón y el sorbete, hostias
para las confiterías--y no las hacía para las iglesias por falta de molde que tuviese una cruz--,
flores, hojuelas y orejas de fraile en Carnaval, buñuelos en todo tiempo.... Pero nunca lo
tenía de lucir estas habilidades accesorias, porque los barquillos de diario eran absorbentes.
¡Bah!, en consiguiendo vivir y mantener la familia....

A las nueve muy largas, cuando cerca de cinco mil barquillos reposaban en el tubo, todavía
el padre y la hija no habían cruzado palabra. Montones de brasa y ceniza rodeaban la hoguera,
renovada dos o tres veces. La niña suspiraba de calor, el viejo sacudía frecuentemente la mano
derecha, medio asada ya. Por fin, la muchacha profirió:

--Tengo hambre.

Volvió el padre la cabeza, y con expresivo arqueamiento de cejas indicó un anaquel del vasar.
Encaramose la chiquilla trepando sobre la artesa, y bajó un mediano trozo de pan de mixtura,
en el cual hincó el diente con buen ánimo. Aún rebuscaba en su falda las migajas sobrantes
para aprovecharlas, cuando se oyeron crujidos de catre, carraspeos, los ruidos característicos
del despertar de una persona, y una voz entre quejumbrosa y despótica llamó desde la alcoba
cercana al portal:

--¡Amparo!

Se levantó la niña y acudió al llamamiento, resonando de allí a poco rato su hablar.

--Afiáncese, señora... así... cárguese más... aguarde que le voy a batir este jergón... (Y
aquí se escuchó una gran sinfonía de hojas de maíz, un sirrisssch... prolongado y armonioso.)

La voz mandona dijo opacamente algo, y la infantil contestó:

--Ya la voy a poner a la lumbre, ahora mismito.... ¿Tendrá por ahí el azúcar?

Y respondiendo a una interpelación altamente ofensiva para su dignidad, gritó la chiquilla:

--Y piensa que.... ¡Aunque fuera oro puro! Lo escondería usted misma.... Ahí está, detrás de
la funda... ¿lo ve?

Salió con una escudilla desportillada en la mano, llena de morena melaza, y arrimando al fuego
un pucherito donde estaba ya la cascarilla, le añadió en debidas proporciones azúcar y leche,
y volviose al cuarto del portal con una taza humeante y colmada a reverter. En el fondo del
cacharro quedaba como cosa de otra taza. El barquillero se enderezó llevándose las manos a
la región lumbar, y sobriamente, sin concupiscencia, se desayunó bebiendo las sobras por el
puchero mismo. Enjugó después su frente regada de sudor con la manga de la camisa, entró a
su vez en el cuarto próximo; y al volver a presentarse, vestido con pantalón y chaqueta de
paño pardo, se terció a las espaldas la caja de hoja de lata y se echó a la calle. Amparo,
cubriendo la brasa con ceniza, juntaba en una cazuela berzas, patatas, una corteza de tocino,
un hueso rancio de cerdo, cumpliendo el deber de condimentar el caldo del humilde menaje. Así
que todo estuvo arreglado, metiose en el cuchitril, donde consagró a su aliño personal seis
minutos y medio, repartidos como sigue: un minuto para calzarse los zapatos de becerro, pues
todavía estaba descalza; dos para echarse un refajo de bayeta y un vestido de tartán; un minuto
para pasarse la punta de un paño húmedo por ojos y boca (más allá no alcanzó el aseo); dos
minutos para escardar con un peine desdentado la revuelta y rizosa crencha, y medio para tocarse
al cuello un pañolito de indiana. Hecho lo cual, se presentó más oronda que una princesa a
la persona encamada a quien había llevado el desayuno. Era esta una mujer de edad madura, agujereada
como una espumadera por las viruelas, chata de frente, de ojos chicos. Viendo a la chiquilla
vestida se escandalizó: ¿a dónde iría ahora semejante vagabunda?

--A misa, señora, que es domingo.... ¿Qué volver con noche ni con noche? Siempre vine con día,
siempre.... ¡Una vez de cada mil! Queda el caldo preparadito al fuego.... Vaya, abur.

Y se lanzó a la calle con la impetuosidad y brío de un cohete bien disparado.

-II-

Padre y madre

Tres años antes, la imposibilitada estaba sana y robusta y ganaba su vida en la Fábrica de
Tabacos. Una noche de invierno fue a jabonar ropa blanca al lavadero público, sudó, volvió
desabrigada y despertó tullida de las caderas.--Un aire, señor--decía ella al médico.

Quedose reducida la familia a lo que trabajase el señor Rosendo: el real diario que del fondo
de Hermandad de la Fábrica recibía la enferma no llegaba a medio diente. Y la chiquilla crecía,
y comía pan y rompía zapatos, y no había quien la sujetase a coser ni a otro género de tareas.
Mientras su padre no se marchaba, el miedo a un pasagonzalo sacudido con el cargador la tenía
quieta ensartando y colocando barquillos; pero apenas el viejo se terciaba la correa del tubo,
sentía Amparo en las piernas un hormigueo, un bullir de la sangre, una impaciencia como si
le naciesen alas a miles en los talones. La calle era su paraíso. El gentío la enamoraba, los
codazos y enviones la halagaban cual si fuesen caricias, la música militar penetraba en todo
su ser produciéndole escalofríos de entusiasmo. Pasábase horas y horas correteando sin objeto
al través de la ciudad, y volvía a casa con los pies descalzos y manchados de lodo, la saya
en jirones, hecha una sopa, mocosa, despeinada, perdida, y rebosando dicha y salud por los
poros de su cuerpo. A fuerza de filípicas maternales corría una escoba por el piso, sazonaba
el caldo, traía una herrada de agua; en seguida, con rapidez de ave, se evadía de la jaula
y tornaba a su libre vagancia por calles y callejones.

De tales instintos erráticos tendría no poca culpa la vida que forzosamente hizo la chiquilla
mientras su madre asistió a la Fábrica. Sola en casa con su padre, apenas este salía, ella
le imitaba por no quedarse metida entre cuatro paredes: vaya, y que no eran tan alegres para
que nadie se embelesase mirándolas. La cocina, oscura y angosta, parecía una espelunca, y encima
del fogón relucían siniestramente las últimas brasas de la moribunda hoguera. En el patín,
si es verdad que se veía claro, no consolaba mucho los ojos el aspecto de un montón de cal
y residuos de albañilería, mezclados con cascos de loza, tarteras rotas, un molinillo inservible,
dos o tres guiñapos viejos y un innoble zapato que se reía a carcajadas. Casi más lastimoso
era el espectáculo de la alcoba matrimonial: la cama en desorden, porque la salida precipitada
a la Fábrica no permitía hacerla; los cobertores color de hospital, que no bastaba a encubrir
una colcha rabicorta; la vela de sebo, goteando tristemente a lo largo de la palmatoria de
latón veteada de cardenillo; la palangana puesta en una silla y henchida de agua jabonosa y
grasienta; en resumen, la historia de la pobreza y de la incuria narrada en prosa por una multitud
de objetos feos, y que la chiquilla comprendía intuitivamente; pues hay quien sin haber nacido
entre sedas y holandas, presume y adivina todas aquellas comodidades y deleites que jamas gozó.
Así es que Amparo huía, huía de sus lares camino de la Fábrica, llevando a su madre, en una
fiambrera, el bazuqueante caldo; pero, soltando a lo mejor la carga, poníase a jugar al corro,
a San Severín, a la viudita, a cualquier cosa, con las damiselas de su edad y pelaje.

Cuando la madre se vio encamada quiso imponer a la hija el trabajo sedentario: era tarde. La
planta rústica no se sujetaba ya al espaller. Amparo había ido a la escuela en sus primeros
años, años de relativa prosperidad para la familia, sucediéndole lo que a la mayor parte de
las niñas pobres, que al poco tiempo se cansan sus padres de enviarlas y ellas de asistir,
y se quedan sin más habilidad que la lectura, cuando son listas, y unos rudimentos de escritura.
De aguja apenas sabía Amparo nada. La madre se resignó con la esperanza de colocarla en la
Fábrica. --«Que trabaje--decía--como yo trabajé». Y al murmurar esta sentencia suspiraba, recordando
treinta años de incesante afán. Ahora su carne y sus molidos huesos se tendían gustosamente
en la cama, donde reposaba tumbada panza arriba ínterin sudaban otros para mantenerla. ¡Que
sudasen! Dominada por el terrible egoísmo que suele atacar a los viejos cuya mocedad fue laboriosa,
la impedida hizo del potro de dolor quinta de recreo. Lo que es allí ya podían venir penas;
lo que es allí a buen seguro que la molestase el calor ni el frío. ¿Que era preciso lavar la
ropa? Bueno, ella no tenía que levantarse a jabonarla, le había costado bien caro una vez.
¿Que estaba sucio el piso? Ya lo barrerían, y si no, por ella, aunque en todo el año no se
barriese.... ¿De qué le había servido tanto romper el cuerpo cuando era joven? De verse ahora
tullida --«¡Ay, no se sabe lo que es la salud hasta después de que se pierde!» --exclamaba
sentenciosamente, sobre todo los días en que el dolor artrítico le atarazaba las junturas.
Otras veces, jactanciosa como todo inválido, decía a su hija:--«Sácateme de delante, que irrita
el verte; de tu edad era yo una loba que daba en un cuarto de hora vuelta a una casa».

Sólo echaba de menos la animación de su Fábrica, las compañeras. A bien que las vecinas de
la calle solían acercarse a ofrecerle un rato de palique: una sobre todo, Pepa la comadrona,
por mal nombre señora Porreta. Era esta mujer colosal, a lo ancho más aún que a lo alto; parecíase
a tosca estatua labrada para ser vista de lejos. Su cara enorme, circuida por colgante papada,
tenía palidez serosa. Calzaba zapatillas de hombre y usaba una sortija, de tamaño masculino
también, en el dedo meñique. Acercábase a la cama de la impedida, le sometía las ropas, le
abofeteaba la almohada apoyando fuertemente ambas manos en los muslos, a fin de sostener la
mole de su vientre, y con voz sorda y apagada empezaba a referir chismes del barrio, escabrosos
pormenores de su profesión, o las maravillosas curas que pueden obtenerse con un cocimiento
de ruda, huevo y aceite, con la hoja de la malva bien machacadita, con romero hervido en vino,
con unturas de enjundia de gallina. Susurraban los maldicientes que entre parleta y parleta
solía la matrona entreabrir el pañuelo que le cubría los hombros y sacar una botellica que
fácilmente se ocultaba en cualquier rincón de su corpiño gigantesco; y ya corroboraba con un
trago de anís el exhausto gaznate, ya ofrecía la botella a su interlocutora «para ir pasando
las penas de este mundo». A oídos del señor Rosendo llegó un día esta especie, y se alarmó;
porque mientras estuvo en la Fábrica no bebía nunca su mujer más que agua pura; pero por mucho
que entró impensadamente algunas tardes, no cogió infraganti a las delincuentes. Sólo vio que
estaban muy amigotas y compinches. Para la ex-cigarrera valía un Perú la comadrona; al menos
esa hablaba, porque lo que es su marido.... Cuando este regresaba de la diaria correría por
paseos y sitios públicos, y bajando el hombro soltaba con estrépito el tubo en la esquina de
la habitación, el diálogo del matrimonio era siempre el mismo:

--¿Qué tal?--preguntaba la tullida.

Y el señor Rosendo pronunciaba una de estas tres frases:

--Menos mal.--Un regular.--Condenadamente.

Aludía a la venta, y jamás se dio caso de que agregase género alguno de amplificación o escolio
a sus oraciones clásicas. Poseía el inquebrantable laconismo popular, que vence al dolor, al
hambre, a la muerte y hasta a la dicha. Soldado reenganchado, uncido en sus mejores años al
férreo yugo de la disciplina militar, se convenció de la ociosidad de la palabra y necesidad
del silencio. Calló primero por obediencia, luego por fatalismo, después por costumbre. En
silencio elaboraba los barquillos, en silencio los vendía, y casi puede decirse que los voceaba
en silencio, pues nada tenía de análogo a la afectuosa comunicación que establece el lenguaje
entre seres racionales y humanos, aquel grito gutural en que, tal vez para ahorrar un fragmento
de palabra, el viejo suprimía la última sílaba, reemplazádola por doliente prolongación de
la vocal penúltima:

--Barquilleeeeé....

-III-

Pueblo de su nacimiento

Al sentar el pie en la calle, Amparo respiró anchamente. El sol, llegado al zenit, lo alegraba
todo. En los umbrales de las puertas los gatos, acurrucados, presentaban el lomo al benéfico
calorcillo, guiñando sus pupilas de tigre y roncando de gusto. Las gallinas iban y venían escarbando.
La bacía del barbero, colgada sobre la muestra y rodeada de una sarta de muelas rancias ya,
brillaba como plata. Reinaba la soledad, los vecinos se habían ido a misa o de bureo, y media
docena de párvulos, confiados al Ángel de la Guarda, se solazaban entre el polvo y las inmundicias
del arroyo, con la chola descubierta y expuestos a un tabardillo. Amparo se arrimó a una de
las ventanas bajas, y tocó en los cristales con el puño cerrado. Abriéronse las vidrieras,
y se vio la cara de una muchacha pelinegra y descolorida, que tenía en la mano una almohadilla
de labrar donde había clavados infinidad de menudos alfileres.

--¡Hola!

--¿Hola, Carmela, andas con la labor a vueltas?--pues es día de misa.

--Por eso me da rabia... contestó la muchacha pálida, que hablaba con cierto ceceo, propio
de los puertecitos de mar en la provincia de Marineda.

--Sal un poco, mujer... vente conmigo.

--Hoy... ¡quién puede! Hay un encargo... diez y seis varas de puntilla para una señora del
barrio de Arriba.... El martes se han de entregar sin falta.

Carmela se sentó otra vez con su almohadilla en el regazo, mientras los hombros de Amparo se
alzaban entre compasivos e indiferentes, como si murmurasen--«Lo de costumbre»--. Apartose
de allí, y sus pies descendieron con suma agilidad la escalinata de la plaza de Abastos, llena
a la sazón de cocineras y vendedoras, y enhebrándose por entre cestas de gallinas, de huevos,
de quesos, salió a la calle de San Efrén, y luego al atrio de la iglesia, donde se detuvo deslumbrada.

Cuanto lujo ostenta un domingo en una capital de provincia se veía reunido ante el pórtico,
que las gentes cruzaban con el paso majestuoso de personas bien trajeadas y compuestas, gustosas
en ser vistas y mutuamente resueltas a respetarse y a no promover empujones. Hacían cola las
señoras aguardando su turno, empavesadas y solemnes, con mucha mantilla de blonda, mucho devocionario
de canto dorado, mucho rosario de oro y nácar, las madres vestidas de seda negra, las niñas
casaderas, de colorines vistosos. Al llegar a los postigos que más allá del pórtico daban entrada
a la nave, había crujidos de enaguas almidonadas, blandos empellones, codazos suaves, respiración
agitada de damas obesas, cruces de rosarios que se enganchaban en un encaje o en un fleco,
frases de miel con su poco de vinagre, como--ay, usted dispense.... A mí me empujan, señora,
por eso yo.... No tire usted así, que se romperá el adorno.... Perdone usted.

Deslizose Amparo entre el grupo de la buena sociedad marinedina, y se introdujo en el templo.
Hacia el presbiterio se colocaban las señoritas, arrodilladas con estudio, a fin de no arrugarse
los trapos de cristianar, y como tenían la cabeza baja, veíanse blanquear sus nucas, y alguna
estrecha suela de elegante botita remangaba los pliegues de las faldas de seda. El centro de
la nave lo ocupaba el piquete y la banda de música militar, en correcta formación. A ambos
lados, filas de hombres, que miraban al techo o a las capillas laterales, como si no supiesen
qué hacer de los ojos. De pronto lució en el altar mayor la vislumbre de oro y colores de una
casulla de tisú; quedó el concurso en mayor silencio; las damas abrieron sus libros con las
enguantadas manos, y a un tiempo murmuró el sacerdote Introito y rompió en sonoro acorde la
charanga, haciendo oír las profanas notas de Traviatta, cabalmente los compases ardientes y
febriles del dúo erótico del primer acto. El son vibrante de los metales añadía intensidad
al canto, que, elevándose amplio y nutrido hasta la bóveda, bajaba después a extenderse, contenido,
pero brioso, por la nave y el crucero, para cesar, de repente, al alzarse la hostia; cuando
esto sucedió, la marcha real, poderosa y magnífica, brotó de los marciales instrumentos, sin
que a intervalos dejase de escucharse en el altar el misterioso repiqueteo de la campanilla
del acólito.

A la salida, repetición del desfile: junto a la pila se situaron tres o cuatro de los que ya
no se llamaban dandys ni todavía gomosos, sino pollos y gallos, haciendo ademán de humedecer
los dedos en agua bendita, y tendiéndolos bien enjutos a las damiselas para conseguir un fugaz
contacto de guantes vigilado por el ojo avizor de las mamás. Una vez en el pórtico, era lícito
levantar la cabeza, mirar a todos lados, sonreír, componerse furtivamente la mantilla, buscar
un rostro conocido y devolver un saludo. Tras el deber, el placer; ahora la selecta multitud
se dirigía al paseo, convidada de la música y de la alegría de un benigno domingo de marzo,
en que el sol sembraba la regocijada atmósfera de átomos de oro y tibios efluvios primaverales.
Amparo se dejó llevar por la corriente y presto vino a encontrarse en el paseo.

No tenía entonces Marineda el parque inglés que, andando el tiempo, hermoseó su recinto: y
las Filas, donde se daban vueltas durante las mañanas de invierno y las tardes de verano, eran
una estrecha avenida, pavimentada de piedra, de una parte guarnecida por alta hilera de casas,
de otra por una serie de bancos que coronaban toscas estatuas alegóricas de las Estaciones,
de las Virtudes, mutiladas y privadas de manos y narices por la travesura de los muchachos.
Sombreaban los asientos acacias de tronco enteco, de clorótico follaje (cuando Dios se lo daba);
sepultadas entre piedras por todos lados, como prisionero en torre feudal. A la sazón carecían
de hojas, pero la caricia abrasadora del sol impelía a la savia a subir, a las yemas a hincharse.
Las desnudas ramas se recortaban sobre el limpio matiz del firmamento, y a lo lejos el mar,
de un azul metálico, como pavonado, reposaba, viéndose inmóviles las jarcias y arboladura de
los buques surtos en la bahía, y quietos hasta los impacientes gallardetes de los mástiles.
Ni un soplo de brisa, ni nada que desdijese de la apacibilidad profunda y soñolienta del ambiente.

Caído el pañuelo y recibiendo a plomo el sol en la mollera, miraba Amparo con gran interés
el espectáculo que el paseo presentaba. Señoras y caballeros giraban en el corto trecho de
las Filas, a paso lento y acompasado, guardando escrupulosamente la derecha. La implacable
claridad solar azuleaba el paño negro de las relucientes levitas, suavizaba los fuertes colores
de las sedas, descubría las menores imperfecciones de los cutis, el salseo de los guantes,
el sitio de las antiguas puntadas en la ropa reformada ya. No era difícil conocer al primer
golpe de vista a las notabilidades de la ciudad: una fila de altos sombreros de felpa, de bastones
de roten o concha con puño de oro, de gabanes de castor, todo puesto en caballeros provectos
y seriotes, revelaba claramente a las autoridades, regente, magistrados, segundo cabo, gobernador
civil; seis o siete pantalones gris perla, pares de guantes claros y flamantes corbatas denunciaban
a la dorada juventud; unas cuantas sombrillas de raso, un ramillete de vestidos que trascendían
de mil leguas a importación madrileña, indicaban a las dueñas del cetro de la moda. Las gentes
pasaban, y volvían a pasar, y estaban pasando continuamente, y a cada vuelta se renovaba la
misma profesión por el mismo orden.

Un grupo de oficiales de Infantería y Caballería ocupaba un banco entero, y el sol parecía
concentrarse allí, atraído por el resplandor de los galones y estrellas de oro, por los pantalones
rojo vivo, por el relampagueo de las vainas de sable y el hule reluciente del casco de los
roses. Los oficiales, gente de buen humor y jóvenes casi todos, reían, charlaban y hasta jugaban
con un enjambre de elegantes niñas, que ni la mayor sumaría doce años, ni la menor bajaba de
tres. Tenían a las más pequeñas sentadas en las rodillas, mientras las otras, de pie y con
unos atisbos de timidez y pudor femenil, no osaban acercarse mucho al banco, haciendo como
que platicaban entre sí, cuando realmente sólo atendían a la conversación de los militares.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01408</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>627623</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21705</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

To the point quickly left the bedroom or den adjacent to a girl of thirteen, disheveled, with a
walk of one who just woke up suddenly, without ornaments a linen skirt and a denim bodice
that clung to her bosom, yet sharp, shirt tow. Neither looked at the girl to Mr. Rosendo, and gave
him good morning, groggy with sleep and hurt by the cool morning that he was biting the epidermis,
was to be dropped in a saddle, and while the waffle spectacularly lit matches and applied
to chips, the girl began to rub with a chamois the huge tubes of tin where the wafers are
stored.

Mr. Rosendo seated himself on his high wooden tripod before the flame sputtered and crackling already,
and getting into the magna fire tongs, began the operation. He had his right Amoh borer, which
wet the magazine, kind of thick stick, and extending a thin coating of liquid on the inside of
the hot irons, hurried to wrap in the mold with your thumb, which by dint of repeating this act had
become a callus toast, no nail, no yolk and almost formless. The waffles, golden and warm, fell
in the lap of the girl, who was introducing each other by way of glass tubes, and symmetrically
placed in the bottom of the canes; work was executed in silence, that more be heard rumor that the
cracking of the wood, the rhythmic squeak of the tongs to open and close its jaws of iron, dry
shock of crisp wafers by stumbling and the hiss of Amoh to evaporate the moisture on the hot
plate. Candlelight and reflections of the light glinted on the tin clean the glazed clay pots
the shelves, and the softening temperature is raised to the point that Mr. Rosendo to take off
the rubber cap with visor, revealing his sweaty bald head, and she flinch with the back of his hand
that stifled unruly locks.

Meanwhile, the sun, and in the skies camper, was determined to sift
through some clarity of green glass and pigs of the windows that was
bound to illuminate the kitchen.

Street shook the sleep of the Castros, and women in braids and hair, when not in petticoats and
slippers, went in a hurry, what to look for water, what to buy supplies to neighboring markets,
could be heard crying kids, barking dogs, a hen cackled, the canary in the barber shop across the
street stepped chirping like crazy. From time to time the child throwing covetous glances
of waffle on the street. When God would have served she left the hard chair, and could look
out the door, which is not much to ask! Soon give nine, and six thousand wafers admitting the
box were made only four thousand plus. The girl stretched mechanically. Is that from here a few
months very little he wore his father's work. Before dispatched more.

Anyone who saw those golden canes, light and brittle as the illusions of childhood, I could not
imagine the enormous work that represented their preparation.

Better off driving hoe or beak to open and close the tongs relentlessly scorching, burning also
fingers, hand and arm, painfully tired shoulder muscles and neck. The gaze always fixed on
the flame, tired, decreased vision, his back, hunched continuously, led to pure strains, the number
of the wafers out of the mold. And no day off! Wafers can not be done yesterday, if they have
to please the little people and greedy, they should be cool. A no humidity to soften. It must
spend the morning, sometimes at night, in factories, and sell them later in vocearlos. In
summer, the season is good and shipped much fat is removed and wages, there that the hours
could you be scorching, lazy hours, melting the heart of that fire, chyle sweating, double
supply of wafers prepared for sale to the public and cafés. Not that Mr. Rosendo was down to his office,
none of this, artists have proud of their skill, but as much as him, none. For over the years
we were winning, even boasted to fill in less time than one tin tube. Do not know delicacy concerning
any of the profession; wafers wide and thin as silk filling yarn eggs, waffles tough and close
to the water and lemon sorbet, hosts for coffee shops - and was not for lack of mold churches
that had a cross - flowers, chips and Carnival friar ears, donuts all the time .... But never had
to wear these ancillary skills because they were absorbent wafers daily. Bah, in achieving
and maintaining family life ....

At nine very long, when about five thousand wafers resting on the tube, yet Father and daughter had
not exchanged a word. Coal and ash piles around the fire, two or three times renewed. The
girl sighed heat, shaking frequently old hand right, middle and grilled. Finally, the girl uttered:

-
I have hunger.

The father turned his head, and expressive eyebrows arching indicated a shelf of Vasari. He seated
the little girl climbing on the trough, and down a medium piece of bread mix, in which bit into
in good spirits.

Still rummaging in her lap remaining crumbs to exploit them, when
they heard creaking cot, coughs, such noises the awakening of a person,
and a plaintive voice from despotic called from the bedroom near the
portal:

- Amparo!

The girl got up and went to call, resonating in a little while your talking.

- Afiáncese, lady ... well ... ge more ... wait I'm going to beat this mattress ... (Y here
is a great symphony heard of corn leaves, one sirrisssch ... long
and harmonious.)

Bossy voice dimly said something, and the child
replied:

- I'm going to put the fire right now for very .... Will
sugar out there?

And responding to a question highly offensive to their dignity, the girl cried:

- And you think .... Although it was pure gold!

Hide it yourself .... There, behind cover ... See?

Came out with a chipped bowl in hand, full of dark molasses, and pulled the fire a pot which
was already the scale, he added in proper proportions and milk sugar,
and returned to the portal room with a steaming cup filled to revert.

At the bottom of pileup was a thing of another cup. The waffle straightened her hands to lumbar
region, and soberly, without concupiscence, had breakfast drinking the leftovers same pot. Then
wiped his forehead with sweat watered the sleeve, entered turn into the next room, and presented
again, dressed in trousers and jacket brown cloth, wore on his back the tin box and fell to
the street. Amparo covering the coal with ash together in a casserole cabbage, potatoes, bacon
rind, rancid pork bone, fulfilling the duty to flavor the broth of the humble household. So
everything was arranged, Then he put into the den, where he consecrated his six personal dressing
and a half minutes, divided as follows: one minute to put on his shoes calf, because I was
still barefoot, and two to throw a flannel petticoats and a dress tartan, one minute to spend
the end of a damp cloth for eyes and mouth (beyond not reach the toilet), two minutes to weed
through a toothless comb the revolt and curly tresses, and a half to touch pañolito neck a
calico. This done, presented a more plump princess the person who had been bedridden for breakfast.
This was a middle-aged woman, bored as a skimmer for smallpox, flat front, small eyes. Seeing the
little girl dressed was shocked: Where would now like wandering?

- A church, ma'am, that is Sunday .... What night or to go back to night? Whenever I came to
day, forever .... Once in a thousand! Preparadito broth is fire .... Well, Abur.

And he took to the streets with the impetuosity and vigor of a well-fired
rocket.

-II-

Father and mother

Three years earlier, was unable
healthy and robust and earned his living in the factory Tobacco.

One winter night was to soap to wash linens groups, sweat, again homeless and crippled hip woke
.-- An air, sir - she said the doctor.

Small abode the family that the Lord works Rosendo: the daily real
bottom Brotherhood of the factory received the patient was less than
half a tooth.

And the girl grew, and ate bread and shoes broke, and there was no
subject who sew or other kinds of tasks.

While his father left, the fear of shaken pasagonzalo charger had it still stringing and placing
wafers, but only the old man ply belt tube Amparo felt a tingling in the legs, a swarm of
blood, like impatience you were born thousands wings on his heels.
The street was his paradise.

The crowd of lovers, elbow and the flatter jerk as if they were touching, the military music
penetrated all his being shivers of excitement. We spent hours and hours running around aimlessly
to through the city, and returned home with bare feet stained with mud, her skirt in tatters,
made a soup, brat, disheveled, loss, and overflowing with happiness and health by pore of his
body. A maternal philippics force ran a broom across the floor, seasoned broth, brought a tool
of water then, with speed of bird escaped from the cage and returns to its free loitering
in the streets and alleys.

Of these instincts erratic little guilt would not necessarily life that made the girl while his
mother attended the factory. Home alone with his father, just this out, she imitate him not
to stay stuck in four walls: go, and they were not so happy to anyone looking at them enraptured.
The kitchen, dark and narrow, like a Espelunca, and over the fire glowed ominously the last
dying embers of the fire. In the skate, If it is true that it became clear, not consoled her
eyes look like a heap of lime and masonry waste, mixed with fragments
of plates, pans broken, a grinder useless, two or three old rags and
shoe ignoble laughed out loud.

Almost more pitiful was the spectacle of double room: the bed in disarray, because the abrupt
departure the factory did not allow it, the color covers hospital, it was not enough to cover
a quilt bobtail, the tallow candle, dripping sadly over the candlestick streaked with verdigris
brass, the pan placed on a chair and bursting with soapy water greasy, in short, the history of
poverty and neglect told in prose by a multitude ugly object, and that the girl understood
intuitively: for some people not born from silk and Dutch, and guess boasts all the comforts
and pleasures that never enjoyed. So Amparo fled, fled their dollars Factory road, taking his mother
in a lunchbox, the bazuqueante broth, but maybe dropping the charge, began to play the run,
St. Severin, the widow, anything with the ladies of her age and coat.

When the mother was bedridden daughter wanted to impose a sedentary work, was late. The rustic
plant is not held and the espaller. Amparo had gone to school in their early years, years of
relative prosperity for the family, going the way most poor girls, who soon tired and their parents
sending them to attend, and are no more skill than reading, when they are ready, and some rudiments
of writing. Amparo needle hardly knew anything. The mother was resigned to the hope of placing
in Factory. - "That work - he said - as I worked." And whisper this sentence sighed, remembering
thirty years of incessant toil. Now the ground meat and bones tended happy in bed, lying on her
back where it lay sweating meantime others to maintain it. That sudasen!

Dominated by the terrible selfishness that often strikes older whose youth was laborious, The
colt was barred fifth recess pain. What is there and could come penalties; what is there to
bother Surely you heat or cold. What was necessary to wash clothes? Well, she had to get up
to soaps, had cost him dearly at once. What floor was dirty? Since the sweep, and if not for
her, even throughout the year is not swept .... What had helped him break both the body when you
were young? Now be seen cripple - "Oh, do not know what health is until after you lose!" -
exclaimed sententiously, especially those days when you atarazaba arthritic pain joints. Other times,
boastful as any invalid, said to his daughter: - "Sácateme front, which irritates see you,
of your age I was a wolf that was a quarter of an hour back to a house. "

Only missed the animation of his factory, the companions. A well that neighboring the street
used to come to offer a bit of Smalltalk: an especially Pepa midwife by Mrs. Porretta bad name.
This woman was huge, across even more than the top, it seemed a rough hewn statue to be seen
from afar. His face enormous, encircled by hanging jowls, serosa was pale. She wore men's
shoes and he wore a ring, male size also, in the little finger. Approached the bed prevented,
was referred to the clothing, we strongly supporting the pillow slapped both hands on the
thighs, in order to sustain mole on his belly, and hollow voice and began to refer off the
neighborhood gossip, lurid details of his profession, or the wonderful cures that can be achieved
with an infusion rue, egg and oil, mallow leaf machacadita well with
rosemary boiled in wine, with ointments fat of chicken.

Revilers whispered that between Parlet and Parlet ajar midwife used the handkerchief that
covered her shoulders and get a bottle easily hidden in any corner of her bra huge, and as corroborated
with a anise drink the exhausted his throat, and offered the bottle to his interlocutor "to scroll
the sorrows of this world. " A hearing of Mr. Rosendo came one day this kind, and was alarmed;
because while the factory was never his wife did not drink more than pure water, but much unwittingly
entered some evenings, did not catch the criminals red-handed. Just saw were very cronies
and buddies. For ex-cigarette Peru worth a midwife, at least this talk, because what's her
husband .... When returning from daily runs by walkways and public places, and the men dropped
down the tube with a crash at the corner of the room, the dialogue of marriage was always the
same:

- What? - Asked the cripple.

And Mr. Rosendo uttered one of these three sentences:

- Thank God Damn .-- .-- A regular.

Referred to the sale, and never gave gender if you added any amplification or scoliosis their
classic prayers. He had the unwavering popular laconic, which is due to pain, Hunger, death
and even joy. Soldier re-enlisted, yoked in their best years iron yoke of military discipline,
he was convinced from the idleness of the word and need of silence.

First silent obedience, then as fate, then out of habit.

In elaborated the wafers silence, quietly sold them, and almost shouted
one can say that silent, for there was nothing analogous to the affectionate
communication setting out the language among rational human beings,
that guttural cry that, perhaps to save a fragment word, the old suppressed
the last syllable, replacing them by prolonged suffering penultimate
vowel:

- Barquilleeeeé ....

-III-

Town of birth

In setting foot
on the street, Amparo breath broadly.

The sun reached its zenith, so glad everything.

In the doorways cats, curled up, had their backs to charity warmth, his eyes winking tiger and
snoring of taste. The chickens came and went digging. The barber's basin, hanging on the sample
and surrounded by a bunch of teeth and rancid, shone like silver. There was loneliness, the
neighbors had gone to church or Bure ½ dozen toddlers, entrusted to the Guardian Angel, pleasured
themselves in the dust and filth the stream, with the chola uncovered and exposed to typhus.
Amparo joined himself to a the lower windows, and knocked on the glass with his fist. The windows
were opened, and was the face of a brunette girl and discolored, which was holding a pillow to
till where he had nailed plenty of tiny pins.

- Hello!

- Hello, Carmela, to hang out with the work around? - It is a day
of mass.

- So I get angry ... said the pale girl, who spoke with
a lisp, own sea ??of ??small harbors in the province of Marineda.

-
Sal a little woman ... come with me.

- Today ... Who can!

There is a custom ... sixteen yards of lace for lady Top neighborhood
.... Tuesday will have to deliver without fail.

Carmela sat down again with her pillow in her lap, while the shoulders of Amparo rose between compassion
and indifference, as if Murmur - "The usual '--. He removed from there, and his feet came down
with great agility the steps of the Plaza de Abastos, full at the time of cooks and saleswomen,
and threading in between baskets of chickens, eggs, cheese, hit the streets of St. Ephrem, and then
to the churchyard, where he stopped dazzled.

The estate boasts a Sunday in a provincial capital could be seen gathered at the gate, that people
crossed over majestic of well-dressed and composed, tasty to be seen
and resolved to respect each other and not to promote pushing.

Lined the ladies waiting their turn, buntings and solemn, with lots
of lace mantilla, long devotional singing gold, much gold and pearl
beads, mothers dressed in black silk, girls marriageable, colorful
showy.

Upon arrival in the shutters gave beyond the entrance gate the ship,
had cracks in starched petticoats, soft shoves, elbows soft, breathing
obese women stirred, crosses for rosaries that hooked into a lace
or fringe, phrase groups with some vinegar, and - oh, you dispense
.... A push me, madam, so I .... Do not pull you so, it will break
the ornament .... Excuse me.

Amparo glided between the high society group marinedina, and entered
the temple.

To the sanctuary were placed the girls, kneeling to study, so as not to wrinkle christening
cloths, as had his head down, could be seen to whiten their necks,
and some elegant narrow soled boots tucked in the folds of silk skirts.

Downtown the ship was occupied by the picket and the military band, in correct formation. Both
sides, rows of men, who looked to the ceiling or the side chapels, as if they knew Why do
the eyes. Suddenly looked at the altar glimpse of gold and colors of a chasuble of cloth, the
contest was more silence, the ladies opened their books to gloved hands, and murmured the priest
time Introit and burst into loud chord charanga, voicing notes Traviatta
profane, full of hot beats and febrile erotic duet in the first act.

The metals are added vibrant intensity the song, which, rising broad and nurtured to the roof,
then spread down, content, but spirited, down the nave and transept, to stop suddenly to lift the
host, when this happened, real progress, powerful and magnificent burst of martial instruments
without at intervals ceases to be heard on the altar the mysterious ringing of the bell the acolyte.

At
the start, repeat the parade next to the battery were placed three or four of those already
not yet called dandies and rubbery, but chickens and roosters, making a move to dampen fingers in
holy water, and tending to lean well to get a fleeting damsels Contact gloves monitored by the watchful
eye of their moms. Once on the porch, it was permissible heads up, look around, smile, secretly
composed the blanket, search a familiar face and return a greeting. After the duty, pleasure,
and now the select crowd was going to walk, by invitation of the
music and the joy of a mild Sunday in March, the sun planted the joyful
atmosphere of gold atoms and warm scents of spring.

Amparo was carried away by the current and soon came to be in the ride.

He had then Marineda English park, walking time, beautified the premises: and Rows, which circled
over the winter mornings and summer evenings were a narrow street, paved with stone, some manned
by high row of houses, another by a number of banks that crowned crude allegorical statues
of the Stations Virtues, maimed and deprived of his hands and nose for mischief of boys. Acacia
shaded seats emaciated body of chlorotic foliage (when God gave it); buried under rocks everywhere,
as a prisoner in feudal tower. At that time lacked of leaves but the caress of the sun scorching
impelled to sap up to the buds to swell. The bare branches are silhouetted against the clear
tint of the sky, and far away the sea a metallic blue and burnished, it lay still seeing the
rigging and spars of vessels in the bay, and quiet until the impatient pennants of the masts.
Not a breath of wind, or anything of harmony of deep and sleepy peacefulness of the environment.

Dropped the handkerchief and receiving to lead the sun in his head, looked with great interest
Amparo show that the walk had. Ladies and gentlemen, turning in the short stretch of Rows,
a slow and measured, carefully guarding the right.

The relentless solar light blue shiny black cloth of the Levites, the strong colors softening
silks, discovered the minor imperfections of the complexion, salseo the gloves the site of the
old stitches on clothing and reformed. It was difficult to know at first glance, the notables
of the city: a row of tall felt hats, canes of cane or shell-handled gold, beaver coats, all as
in horsemen proiects and Seriot, clearly revealed to the authorities, ruling, judges, second
place, Governor civil, six or seven pearl-gray trousers, a pair of light gloves, vibrant denounced
ties the gilded youth, a few parasols of satin, a bunch of clothes that transcended import
a thousand leagues from Madrid, indicated to the owners of the scepter of fashion. People passed,
and went back to pass, and were continually passing, and each turn
was being renovated same profession in the same order.

A group of infantry and cavalry officers occupied a whole bank, and the sun appeared concentrated
there, attracted by the glow of gold braid and stars, the pants red, the flash of sword sheaths
and shiny rubber hull of roses. The officers, people of good humor and almost all young, laughing,
chatting and even playing elegant with a swarm of girls, and most would add twelve years, down from
the lowest three. Smaller ones were sitting on the knees, while the other, standing and some glimpses
of women's shyness and modesty, did not dare get too close to the bank, pretending who talked among
themselves, when really only catering to the conversation of the military.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>