<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03526</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>90818</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23021</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> ¡la primera hembra del mundo!--,
acabando la buena mujer por desarrugar el ceño y reírse, mientras lo desnudaba y manejaba como
si fuese un niño enfermo.

Este era su único vicio. ¡Pobrecillo!... De mujeres y de juego, ni señal. Su egoísmo, que le
hacía ir bien vestido, mientras la familia andaba harapienta, y su desigualdad en el reparto
de los productos del trabajo, compensábalos con iniciativas generosas. La señora Angustias
recordaba con orgullo los días de gran fiesta, cuando Juan la hacía ponerse el pañolón de Manila,
la mantilla de casamiento, y llevando los niños por delante marchaba a su lado, con blanco
sombrero cordobés y bastón de puño de plata, dando un paseo por las Delicias, con el mismo
aire de una familia de comerciantes de la calle de las Sierpes. Los días de toros baratos la
obsequiaba rumbosamente antes de ir a la plaza, ofreciéndola unas cañas de manzanilla en La
Campana o un café en la plaza Nueva. Este tiempo feliz no era ya mas que un pálido y grato
recuerdo en la memoria de la pobre mujer.

El señor Juan enfermó de tisis, y durante dos años la esposa tuvo que atender a su cuidado,
extremando aún más sus industrias para compensar la falta de la peseta que le entregaba antes
el marido. Finalmente murió en el hospital, resignado con su suerte, convencido de que la existencia
nada vale sin manzanilla y sin toros, y su última mirada de amor y de agradecimiento fue para
su mujer, como si le gritase con los ojos: «¡Olé! ¡la primera hembra del mundo!...»

Al quedar sola la señora Angustias no empeoraba su situación; antes bien, considerábase con
mayor desembarazo en los movimientos, libre de aquel hombre que en los dos últimos años pesaba
más sobre ella que el resto de la familia. Mujer enérgica y de prontas resoluciones, marcó
inmediatamente un camino a sus hijos. Encarnación, que tenía ya diez y siete años, fue a la
Fábrica de Tabacos, donde pudo introducirla su madre gracias a sus relaciones con ciertas amigas
de la juventud llegadas a maestras. Juanillo, que de pequeño había pasado los días en el portal
del barrio de la Feria viendo trabajar a su padre, iba a ser zapatero por voluntad de la señora
Angustias. Le sacó de la escuela, donde había aprendido a mal leer, y a los doce años entró
como aprendiz de uno de los mejores zapateros de Sevilla.

Aquí comenzó el martirio de la pobre mujer.

¡Ay, aquel muchacho! ¡Hijo de unos padres tan honrados!... Casi todos los días, en vez de entrar
en la tienda del maestro, se iba al Matadero con ciertos pillos que tenían su punto de reunión
en un banco de la Alameda de Hércules, y para regocijo de pastores y matarifes, osaban echar
un capote a los bueyes, siendo volteados y pateados las más de las veces. La señora Angustias,
que velaba aguja en mano muchas noches para que el niño fuese decentito al taller, con las
ropas limpias, le encontraba en la puerta de su casa, temeroso de entrar y sin valor al mismo
tiempo para huir, por la servidumbre del hambre, con los pantalones rotos, la chaqueta sucia
y chichones y rasguños en la cara.

A los magullamientos del buey traidor uníanse las bofetadas y escobazos de la madre; pero el
héroe del Matadero pasaba por todo con tal que no le faltase la pitanza. «Pega, pero dame que
comer.» Y con el apetito excitado por el ejercicio violento, engullía el pan duro, las judías
averiadas, el bacalao putrefacto, todos los víveres de desecho que la hacendosa mujer buscaba
en las tiendas para mantener a la familia con poco dinero.

Atareada todo el día en fregar pisos de casas ajenas, sólo de tarde en tarde podía ocuparse
de su hijo, yendo a la tienda del maestro para enterarse de los progresos del aprendiz. Cuando
volvía de la zapatería bufaba de coraje, proponiéndose los más estupendos castigos que corrigiesen
al pillete.

La mayor parte de los días no se presentaba en la tienda. Pasaba la mañana en el Matadero,
y por las tardes formaba grupo a la entrada de la calle de las Sierpes con otros vagabundos,
admirando de cerca a los toreros sin contrata que se juntaban en La Campana, vestidos de nuevo,
con flamantes sombreros, pero sin más de una peseta en el bolsillo y hablando cada cual de
sus propias hazañas.

Juanillo los contemplaba como seres de asombrosa superioridad, envidiando su buen porte y la
frescura con que piropeaban a las mujeres. La idea de que todos ellos tenían en su casa un
traje de seda bordado de oro, y metidos en él marchaban ante la muchedumbre al son de la música,
producíale un escalofrío de respeto.

El hijo de la señora Angustias era conocido por el Zapaterín entre sus desarrapados amigos,
y mostrábase satisfecho de tener un apodo, como casi todos los grandes hombres que salen al
redondel. Por algo se empieza. Llevaba al cuello un pañuelo rojo que había sustraído a su hermana,
y por debajo de la gorra salíale el pelo amontonado sobre las orejas en gruesos mechones, que
se alisaba con saliva. Las blusas de dril queríalas hasta la cintura, con numerosos pliegues.
Los pantalones, viejos restos del vestuario de su padre acomodados por la señora Angustias,
exigíalos altos de talle, con las piernas anchas y las caderas bien recogidas, llorando de
humillación cuando la madre no quería ceñirse a estas exigencias.

¡Una capa! ¡Poseer una capa de brega, no teniendo que implorar a otros más felices el préstamo
del ansiado trapo por unos minutos!... En un cuartucho de la casa yacía olvidado un viejo colchón
con las tripas flácidas. La lana habíala vendido la señora Angustias en días de apuro. El Zapaterín
pasó una mañana encerrado en el cuarto, aprovechando la ausencia de su madre, que trabajaba
aquel día como asistenta en casa de un canónigo. Con la ingeniosidad del náufrago que, entregado
a sus iniciativas, tiene que fabricárselo todo en una isla desierta, cortó un capote de lidia
en la tela húmeda y deshilachada. Después hirvió en un puchero un puñado de anilina roja comprada
en una droguería, y sumió en este tinte el viejo lienzo. Juanillo admiró su obra. ¡Un capote
del más vivo escarlata, que iba a despertar muchas envidias en las capeas de los pueblos!...
Sólo faltaba que se secase, y lo puso al sol entre las ropas blancas de las vecinas. El viento,
al mecer el trapo chorreante, fue manchando las piezas inmediatas, y un concierto de maldiciones
y amenazas, de puños crispados y bocas que proferían las más feas palabras contra él y su madre,
obligó al Zapaterín a recoger su manto de gloria y salir por pies, cubiertas de rojo cara y
manos, como si acabase de cometer un homicidio.

La señora Angustias, hembra fuerte, obesa y bigotuda, que no temía a los hombres e inspiraba
respeto a las mujeres por sus resoluciones enérgicas, mostrábase descorazonada y floja ante
su hijo. ¡Qué hacer!... Sus manos habíanse ensayado en todas las partes del cuerpo del muchacho;
las escobas se rompían sin resultado positivo. Aquel maldito tenía, según ella, carne de perro.
Habituado fuera de casa a los tremendos cabezazos de los becerros, al cruel pateo de las vacas,
a los palos de pastores y matarifes, que trataban sin compasión a la pillería tauromáquica,
los golpes de la madre parecíanle un hecho natural, una continuación de la vida exterior, que
se prolongaba dentro de su casa, y los aceptaba sin propósito de enmienda, como un escote que
había de pagar a cambio del sustento, rumiando el pan duro con famélico regodeo, mientras las
maldiciones maternales y los puñetazos llovían en sus espaldas.

Apenas saciaba su hambre huía de la casa, valiéndose de la libertad en que le dejaba la señora
Angustias ausentándose para sus faenas.

En La Campana, ágora venerable del toreo, donde circulan las grandes noticias de la afición,
recibía avisos de sus compañeros que le producían escalofríos de entusiasmo.

--Zapaterín, mañana corrida.

Los pueblos de la provincia celebraban las fiestas del santo patrón con capeas de toros corridos,
y allá marchaban los pequeños toreros, con la esperanza de poder decir a la vuelta que habían
tendido el capote en las plazas gloriosas de Aznalcollar, Bullullos o Mairena. Emprendían la
marcha de noche, con la capa al hombro si era verano y envueltos en ella en el invierno, el
estómago vacío y hablando continuamente de toros.

Si la marcha era de varias jornadas, acampaban al raso o eran admitidos por caridad en el pajar
de una venta. ¡Ay de las uvas, de los melones y los higos que encontraban al paso en la buena
época!... Su única inquietud era que otro grupo, otra «cuadrilla», hubiese tenido igual pensamiento
y se presentase en el pueblo, entablando ruda competencia.

Cuando llegaban al término de su viaje, con las cejas y la boca llenas de polvo, flojos y despeados
por la marcha, se presentaban al alcalde, y el más desvergonzado, que llenaba las funciones
de director, hablaba de los méritos de su gente, dándose todos por felices si la generosidad
municipal los aposentaba en la cuadra del mesón, regalándolos encima con una olla, que quedaba
limpia a los pocos instantes. En la plaza del lugar, cerrada con carros y tablados, soltábanse
toros viejos, verdaderos castillos de carne, llenos de costras y cicatrices, con cuernos astillosos
y enormes; reses que llevaban muchos años de ser toreadas en todas las fiestas de la provincia;
animales venerables que «sabían latín», tanta era su malicia, y habituados a un continuo toreo,
estaban en el secreto de las habilidades de la lidia.

Los mozos del pueblo pinchaban a las fieras desde lugar seguro, y la gente buscaba motivo de
diversión, más aún que en el toro, en los «toreros» venidos de Sevilla. Tendían éstos sus capas
con las piernas temblorosas y el ánimo reconfortado por el peso del estómago. Revolcón, y grande
algazara en el público. Cuando alguno, con repentino terror, refugiábase en las empalizadas,
la barbarie campesina le acogía con insultos, golpeándole las manos agarradas a la madera,
dándole varazos en las piernas para que saltase a la plaza. «¡Arre, sinvergüenza! ¡A darle
la cara al toro, embustero!...»

Alguna vez sacaban de la plaza a uno de los «diestros» entre cuatro compañeros, pálido con
una blancura de papel, los ojos vidriosos, la cabeza caída, el pecho como un fuelle roto. Acudía
el albéitar, tranquilizando a todos al no ver sangre. Era una conmoción sufrida por el muchacho
al ser despedido a algunos metros de distancia, cayendo al suelo como un talego de ropa. Otras
veces era la angustia de haber sido pisado por una bestia de enorme pesadumbre. Le echaban
un cubo de agua por la cabeza, y luego, al recobrar los sentidos, obsequiábanle con un gran
trago de aguardiente de Cazalla de la Sierra. Ni un príncipe podría verse mejor cuidado.

A la plaza otra vez. Y cuando no le quedaban al pastor toros que soltar y se aproximaba la
noche, dos de la cuadrilla cogían el mejor capote de la sociedad, y sosteniéndole por las puntas,
iban de tablado en tablado solicitando una gratificación. Llovían sobre la tela roja las monedas
de cobre según el gusto que habían dado a los vecinos las proezas de los forasteros, y terminada
la corrida emprendían la vuelta a la ciudad, sabiendo que en la posada se había agotado su
crédito. Muchas veces reñían en el camino por la distribución de la calderilla guardada en
un pañuelo anudado.

Luego, en el resto de la semana, recordaban sus hazañas ante los ojos absortos de los compinches
que no habían sido de la expedición. Hablaban de sus verónicas en El Garrobo, de sus navarras
de Lora, o de una terrible cogida en El Pedroso, imitando los aires y actitudes de los verdaderos
profesionales que a pocos pasos de ellos consolaban su falta de contratas con toda clase de
petulancias y mentiras.

Cierta vez, la señora Angustias estuvo más de una semana sin saber de su hijo. Al fin tuvo
vagas noticias de que había sido herido en una capea en el pueblo de Tocina. ¡Dios mío! ¿Dónde
estaría aquel pueblo? ¿Cómo ir a él?... Dio por muerto a su hijo, le lloró, quiso, sin embargo,
ir allá, y cuando disponía el viaje vio llegar a Juanillo, pálido, débil, pero hablando con
alegría varonil de su accidente.

No era nada: un puntazo en una nalga; una herida de varios centímetros de profundidad. Y con
el impudor del triunfo, quería mostrarla a los vecinos, afirmando que metía en ella un dedo
sin llegar al fin. Sentíase orgulloso del hedor de yodoformo que iba esparciendo a su paso,
y hablaba de las atenciones con que le habían tratado en aquel pueblo, que era para él lo mejor
de España. Los vecinos más ricos, como quien dice la aristocracia, se interesaban por su suerte;
el alcalde había ido a verle, pagándole después el viaje de vuelta. Aún guardaba en su bolsillo
tres duros, que entregó a su madre con una generosidad de grande hombre. ¡Y tanta gloria a
los catorce años! Su satisfacción fue todavía mayor cuando en La Campana, algunos toreros--pero
toreros de verdad--fijaron su atención en el muchacho, preguntándole cómo marchaba de su herida.

Después de este accidente ya no volvió a la tienda de su maestro. Sabía lo que eran los toros;
su herida había servido para acrecentar su audacia. ¡Torero, nada más que torero! La señora
Angustias abandonó todo propósito de corrección, juzgándolo inútil. Se hizo la cuenta de que
no existía su hijo. Cuando se presentaba en casa por la noche, a la hora en que la madre y
la hermana comían juntas, hacíanle plato silenciosas, intentando abrumarle con su desprecio.
Pero esto en nada alteraba su masticación. Si llegaba tarde, no le guardaban ni un mendrugo,
y tenía que volverse a la calle lo mismo que había venido.

Era paseante nocturno en la Alameda de Hércules con otros muchachos de ojos viciosos, mezcla
confusa de aprendices de criminal y de torero. Las vecinas le encontraban algunas veces en
las calles hablando con señoritos cuya presencia hacía reír a las mujeres, o con graves caballeros
a los que la maledicencia daba motes femeniles. Unas temporadas vendía periódicos, y en las
grandes fiestas de Semana Santa ofrecía a las señoras sentadas en la plaza de San Francisco
bandejas de caramelos. En época de feria vagaba por las inmediaciones de los hoteles esperando
a un «inglés», pues para él todos los viajeros eran ingleses, con la esperanza de servirle de guía.

--¡Milord!... ¡Yo torero!--decía al ver una figura exótica, como si su calidad profesional
fuese una recomendación indiscutible para los extranjeros.

Y para certificar su identidad se quitaba la gorra, echando atrás la coleta: un mechón de a
cuarta que llevaba tendido en lo alto de la cabeza.

Su compañero de miseria era Chiripa, muchacho de su misma edad, pequeño de cuerpo y de ojos
maliciosos, sin padre ni madre, que vagaba por Sevilla desde que tenía uso de razón y ejercía
sobre Juanillo el dominio de la experiencia. Tenía un carrillo cortado por la cicatriz de una
cornada, y esta señal considerábala el Zapaterín como algo muy superior a su herida invisible.

Cuando, a la puerta de un hotel, alguna viajera ávida de «color local» hablaba con los pequeños
toreros, admirando sus coletas y el relato de sus heridas, para acabar dándoles dinero, Chiripa
decía con tono sentimental:

--No le dé usté a ese, que tié mare, y yo estoy solito en er mundo. ¡El que tié mare no sabe
lo que tiene!

Y el Zapaterín, con una tristeza de remordimiento, permitía que el otro se apoderase de todo
el dinero, murmurando:

--Es verdá... es verdá.

Este enternecimiento no impedía a Juanillo continuar su existencia anormal, apareciendo en
casa de la señora Angustias muy de tarde en tarde y emprendiendo viajes lejos de Sevilla.

Chiripa era un maestro de la vida errante. Los días de corrida afirmábase en su voluntad el
propósito de entrar en la Plaza de Toros con su camarada, apelando para esto a las estratagemas
de escalar los muros, deslizarse entre el gentío o enternecer a los empleados con humildes
súplicas. ¡Una fiesta taurina sin que la viesen ellos, que eran de la profesión!... Cuando
no había capea en los pueblos de la provincia, iban a echar su trapo a los novillos de la dehesa
de Tablada; pero todos estos alicientes de la vida de Sevilla no bastaban a satisfacer su ambición.

Chiripa había corrido mundo, y hablaba a su compañero de las grandes cosas vistas por él en
lejanas provincias. Era hábil en el arte de viajar gratuitamente, colándose con disimulo en
los trenes. El Zapaterín escuchaba con embeleso sus descripciones de Madrid, una ciudad de
ensueño con su Plaza de Toros que era a modo de una catedral del toreo.

Un señorito, por reírse de ellos, les dijo a la puerta de un café de la calle de las Sierpes
que en Bilbao ganarían mucho dinero, pues allí no abundaban los toreros como en Sevilla, y
los dos muchachos emprendieron el viaje, limpio el bolsillo y sin otro equipo que sus capas,
unas capas «de verdad», que habían sido de toreros de cartel, míseros desechos adquiridos por
unos cuantos reales en una ropavejería.

Introducíanse cautelosamente en los trenes y se ocultaban bajo los asientos; pero el hambre
y otras necesidades les obligaban a denunciar su presencia a los viajeros, que acababan por
compadecerse de estas andanzas, riendo de sus raras figuras, de sus coletas y capotes, socorriéndolos
con los restos de sus meriendas. Cuando algún empleado les daba caza en las estaciones, corrían
de vagón en vagón o intentaban escalar los techos para esperar agazapados a que el tren se
pusiera en marcha. Muchas veces les sorprendieron, y agarrándolos de las orejas, con acompañamiento
de bofetadas y puntapiés, quedaban en el andén de una estación solitaria, mientras el tren
se alejaba como una esperanza perdida.

Aguardaban el paso de otro, vivaqueando al aire libre, y si se veían vigilados de cerca, emprendían
la marcha hacia la inmediata estación por los desiertos campos, con la certeza de ser más afortunados.
Así llegaron a Madrid, después de varios días de accidentado viaje y largas paradas con acompañamiento
de golpes. En la calle de Sevilla y en la Puerta del Sol admiraron los grupos de toreros sin
contrata, entes superiores, a los que osaron pedir, sin éxito, una limosna para continuar el
viaje. Un mozo de la Plaza de Toros, que era de Sevilla, se apiadó de ellos y les dejó dormir
en las cuadras, proporcionándoles además el deleite de presenciar una corrida de novillos en
el famoso circo, que les pareció menos importante que el de su tierra.

Asustados de su audacia y viendo cada vez más lejano el término de la excursión, emprendieron
el regreso a Sevilla lo mismo que habían venido; pero desde entonces tomaron gusto a los viajes
a escondidas en el ferrocarril. Dirigíanse a pueblos de poca importancia en las diversas provincias
andaluzas cuando oían vagas noticias de fiestas con sus correspondientes capeas. Así llegaban
hasta la Mancha o Extremadura; y si los azares de la mala suerte les imponían el marchar a
pie, buscaban refugio en las viviendas de los campesinos, gente crédula y risueña, que se extrañaba
de sus pocos años, de su atrevimiento y su charla embustera, tomándolos por verdaderos lidiadores.

Esta existencia errante les hacía emplear astucias de hombre primitivo para satisfacer sus
necesidades. En las inmediaciones de las casas de campo arrastrábanse sobre el vientre, robando
las hortalizas sin ser vistos. Aguardaban horas enteras a que una gallina solitaria se aproximase
a ellos, y retorciéndola el cuello continuaban la marcha, para encender una hoguera de leña
seca en mitad de la jornada y engullirse el pobre animal chamuscado y medio crudo con una voracidad
de pequeños salvajes. Temían a los mastines del campo más que a los toros. Eran bestias difíciles
para la lidia, que corrían hacia ellos enseñando los colmillos, como si los enfureciese su
aspecto exótico y husmeasen en sus personas a enemigos de la propiedad.

Muchas veces, cuando dormían al aire libre cerca de una estación, esperando el paso de un tren,
llegábase a ellos una pareja de guardias civiles. Al ver los rojos envoltorios que servían
de almohadas a estos vagabundos, tranquilizábanse los soldados del orden. Suavemente les quitaban
las gorras, y al encontrarse con el peludo apéndice de la coleta, se alejaban riendo sin más
averiguaciones. No eran ladronzuelos: eran aficionados que iban a las capeas. Y en esta tolerancia
había una mezcla de simpatía por la fiesta nacional y de respeto ante la obscuridad de lo futuro.
¡Quién podía saber si alguno de estos mozos desarrapados, con costras de miseria, sería en
el porvenir una «estrella del arte», un gran hombre que brindase toros a los reyes, viviera
como un príncipe, y cuyas hazañas y dichos reprodujeran los periódicos!...

Una tarde, el Zapaterín quedó solo en un pueblo de Extremadura. Para mayor asombro del público
rústico que aplaudía a los famosos toreros «venidos adrede de Sevilla», los dos muchachos quisieron
clavar banderillas a un toro bravucón y viejo. Juanillo puso sus palos a la fiera y quedó junto
a un tablado, gozándose en recibir la ovación popular en forma de tremendos manotazos y ofrecimientos
de tragos de vino. Una exclamación de horror le sacó de esta embriaguez de gloria. Chiripa
no estaba ya en el suelo de la plaza. Sólo quedaban en él las banderillas rodando por el polvo,
una zapatilla y la gorra. Movíase el toro como irritado ante un obstáculo, llevando enganchado
de uno de sus cuernos un envoltorio de ropas semejante a un monigote. Con los violentos cabezazos
el informe paquete se soltó del cuerno, expeliendo un chorro rojo, pero antes de llegar al
suelo fue alcanzado por el asta opuesta, que a su vez lo zarandeó largo rato. Por fin el triste
bulto cayó en el polvo, y allí quedó, flácido e inerte, soltando líquido, como un pellejo agujereado
que expele el vino a chorros.

El pastor, con sus cabestros, se llevó el toro al corral, pues nadie osaba aproximarse a él,
y el pobre Chiripa fue conducido sobre un jergón a cierto cuartucho del Ayuntamiento que servía
de cárcel. Su compañero le vio con la cara blanca como si fuese de yeso, los ojos mates y el
cuerpo rojo de sangre, sin que pudieran contener ésta los paños de agua con vinagre que le
aplicaban, a falta de algo mejor.

--¡Adió, Zapaterín!--suspiró--. ¡Adió, Juaniyo!

Y no dijo más. El compañero del muerto emprendió aterrado la vuelta a Sevilla, viendo sus ojos
vidriosos, oyendo sus gimientes adioses. Tenía miedo. Una vaca mansa saliéndole al paso le
hubiese hecho correr. Pensaba en su madre y en la prudencia de sus consejos. ¿No era mejor
dedicarse a zapatero y vivir tranquilamente?... Pero estos propósitos sólo duraron mientras
se vio solo.

Al llegar a Sevilla sintió la influencia del ambiente. Los amigos corrieron hacia él para saber
con todos sus detalles la muerte del pobre Chiripa. Los toreros profesionales le preguntaban
en La Campana, recordando con lástima a aquel pilluelo de cara cortada que muchas veces les
hacía recados. Juan, enardecido por tales muestras de consideración, daba suelta a su potencia
imaginativa, describiendo cómo se había él arrojado sobre el toro al ver cogido a su pobre
compañero; cómo había agarrado al bicho de la cola, y demás hazañas portentosas, a pesar de
las cuales el otro había salido del mundo.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03714</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>97548</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20790</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The first female in the world! - good
woman running unwrinkle frowning and laughing, as he undressed and ran as if a sick child.

This was his only vice. Poor thing! ... Women and gambling, or signal. His egoism, which was
well dressed, as the family walked in rags, and the unequal allocation work products, compensábalos
with generic. Mrs Angus remember with pride the great feast days, when John was put on the
shawl of Manila, wedding blanket, and taking the children marched ahead to his side, with white Cordovan
hat and silver-headed cane, strolling by the Delicias, with the same air of a merchant family
Sierpes Street. The days of the flights bulls regaled course before going to the plaza, offering
her a beer of chamomile Bell or a coffee in the Plaza Nueva. This happy time was no longer anything
but a faint and pleasant remembrance in memory of the poor woman.

Mr. Juan ill with consumption, and for two years the wife had to attend
to their care, further exaggerating their industries to compensate
for the lack of the peseta which betrayed him before the husband.

He eventually died in the hospital, resigned to his fate, convinced that the existence no good
without chamomile and no fights, and his last look of love and gratitude was for his wife, as
if you scream with his eyes: "Olé! World's first female !...»

When left alone Mrs. Angustias not worsened her situation, but rather,
we considered with more disengage movements, free of the man who in
the past two years weighed more about it than the rest of the family.

Energetic woman and prompt decisions, marked once a path to their children. Encarnacion, who
was already seventeen years, went to Tobacco Factory, where his mother was able to enter through
their relationships with certain friends Youth arrivals teachers. Juanillo, that boy had spent
the day in the portal Fair district of watching his father work, going to be a shoemaker by
the will of Mrs. Troubles. Him out of school, where she learned the wrong read, and twelve years
came apprenticed to one of the best shoemakers in Seville.

Here began the martyrdom of the poor woman.

Oh, that boy! Son of parents so honored!

... Almost every day, instead of entering shop teacher, was going to the slaughter with some crooks
who have their meeting point on a bench in the Alameda de Hercules, and to the delight of shepherds
and butchers, dared to take a cloak to steers being flipped and kicked most of the time. Mrs
Angus, that needle in hand watched many nights the child was decentito the workshop, with clean
clothes, I was at the door of your home, afraid to enter and worthless at the same time to
flee the bondage of hunger, with ripped jeans, dirty jacket and bumps and scratches on his face.

For
the traitor ox bruises uníanse slaps and mother's broom, but the Slaughterhouse hero went through
everything so they do not need the pittance.

"Pega, but give me that eat. "And with the appetite aroused by the violent exercise, swallowed
hard bread, beans damaged, rotten cod, all food waste that the industrious woman sought in stores
to support the family with little money.

Busy all day scrubbing floors in the homes of others, only now and
then could deal his son, going to the shop teacher to learn about
the progress of the apprentice.

When snorted back of the shoe store of courage, proposing the most wonderful punishments corrected
the rascal.

Most of the days did not show up at the store.

Spent the morning in the slaughterhouse, and in the evening was the group at the entrance
to the street with other homeless Sierpes, admire about the bullfighters without contracts that
came together in La Campana, dressed again with brand new hats, but no more than a quarter in his
pocket and talking everyone from their own exploits.

Juanillo regarded them as beings of astonishing superiority, envying their good poise and freshness
that compliments to women. The idea that all they had at home a silk dress embroidered with
gold, and placed in him before the crowd marched to the sound of music producíale a shiver of respect.

The
son of Mrs. Angus was known for his ragged Zapaterin between friends
and showed himself satisfied to have a nickname, like almost all great
men that go to ring.

For a start. He wore a red scarf around his neck that was stolen from her sister, and below
the cap salíale hair piled on the ears in thick clumps, which smoothed with saliva. Queríalas
denim blouses to the waist, with numerous folds. Pants, old remains of his father's clothes off by
Ms. Anguish, exigíalos high waist with wide legs and hips well reflected, crying humiliation
when the mother did not want to adhere to these requirements.

A cape! Having a layer of hard work, not having to beg other loan happier the coveted cloth
for a few minutes! ... In a small room of the house lay forgotten
an old mattress with flabby gut.

Tell them the wool sold in days Mrs. Anguish of trouble. The Zapaterin spent a week locked in
the room, taking advantage of the absence of his mother, who worked that day as a maid in the house
of a canon. With the ingenuity of the shipwrecked sailor, delivered its initiatives, you have to make
all on a desert island, cut off a cloak of fighting in the wet and frayed fabric. Then boiled
in a pot a handful of red aniline purchased at a drugstore, and plunged into the dye the old canvas.
Juanillo admired his work. A cloak the most vivid scarlet, which was to arouse much envy in capeas
of the people! ... All that remained was to dry up, and put clothes in the sun from white neighbors.
Wind, to rock the rag dripping, staining the pieces was immediate, and a concert of curses and
threats, fists clenched and mouths that uttered the ugliest words against him and his mother,
Zapaterin forced to pick up his mantle of glory and leave by foot, covered with red face and hands,
as if he had to commit murder.

Mrs Angus, strong female, obese and whiskered, who feared and inspired men respect women for
their strong resolutions, showed himself to disheartened and loose
your child.

What to do! ... His hands habíanse tested in all parts of the body of a child; broom broke no
avail. He was cursed, she said, dog meat. Accustomed away the tremendous headers of the calves,
the cow kicked cruel, sticks to the shepherds and butchers, who were seeking the rascals mercilessly
bullfighting, the beating of the mother seemed to him a natural fact, a continuation of the outer
life, which dragged inside your home, and accept no purpose of amendment, as a cleavage had to
pay in exchange for sustenance, chewing stale bread with ravenous delight, while Maternal curses
and punches rained down on their backs.

Just sated their hunger fled from the house, using the freedom in which he left Mrs. Anxieties
leave for their work.

In The Hood, agora venerable of bullfighting, which circulate the
biggest news of the fans received notice of their colleagues who produce
shivers of excitement.

- Zapaterin, morning run.

The people of the province celebrating the patron saint fiestas with
bull capeas corridos, and there marched the young fighters, in the
hope of being able to say they had turned tended the cape in glorious
places Aznalcollar, Bullullos or Mairena.

Undertook the up at night, with the layer to shoulder if it was summer and wrapped it in the winter,
empty stomach continuously talking bull.

If the march was several days, camping in the open or were admitted for charity in the haystack
of a sale. Woe to the grapes, melons and figs that were to step in
the right time!

... His only concern was that another group, another "gang", had had the same thought and is present
in the village, establishing tough competition.

When they reached the end of his journey, eyebrows and mouth full
of dust, loose and dismissals by the way, were presented to the mayor,
and the most shameless, filling the roles director, spoke of the merits
of his people happy by giving everyone for generosity The chambers
in the municipal block from the inn, giving them over with a pot,
which was clean a few moments.

In the square of the area, closed to cars and tables, soltábanse old bulls, real castles of meat, full
of scabs and scars, horns splintered and large, animals that had many years of being bullfights
at all parties in the province; Revered animals who "knew Latin", such was their malice, and
accustomed to a steady bullfighting were in the secret of fighting skills.

The young men prodded the people to the beasts from a safe place, and people looking for reason fun,
more so than in the bull in the "bullfighters" came from Seville. They tended their coats shaky
legs and encouragement comforted by the weight of the stomach. Tumble, and large uproar in the
audience.

When one, with sudden terror, took refuge in the stockade, peasant barbarism welcomed him with
insults, blows to the hands gripping the wood, giving caned on the legs to jump to the square.
"Gee, you rascal! To give face the bull, a liar !...»

Have you ever taken out of the square to one of the "skilled" between four companions, pale
whiteness of paper, glazed eyes, his head down, his chest like a broken bellows. Came the
farrier, reassuring all seeing no blood.

It was a concussion suffered by the boy to be fired a few yards away, falling to the ground
like a sack of clothes. Other Sometimes it was the anguish of having been trampled by a beast of
enormous grief. He threw a bucket of water over his head, and then, regaining their senses, with
a large obsequiábanle Cazalla drink of brandy from the Sierra. Not a prince could be better care.

In
the square again. And when the pastor did not fit bulls and the approaching release evening,
two of the crew caught the best cape of society, and supported by the tips table in table ranged
from asking for a reward.

Rained down on the red cloth coins copper according to the taste which had given the residents
the exploits of outsiders, and finished undertook the run around the city, knowing that the inn had
exhausted their credit. Often quarreled on the way for the distribution of the coins stored in knotted
handkerchief.

Then in the rest of the week, recalled his exploits in the eyes of the cronies absorbed that
were not the issue.

They spoke of Veronica in the Garrobo, their Navarre Lora, or a terrible caught in El Pedroso, imitating
the air and the real attitudes professionals within walking distance of them comforted their
lack of contracts with every arrogance and lies.

Once, Ms. Angus was more than a week without knowing of his son.

Finally had vague word that he had been injured in an amateur bullfight in the town of bacon.
My God! Where would those people? How to get to him? ... Gave his son died, I cried, wished, however,
go there, and when the trip was available to reach Juanillo, pale, weak, but talking to manly joy
of his accident.

It was nothing: a puntazo in a buttock, a wound several inches deep. And the shamelessness of
the triumph, I wanted to show it to the neighbors, claiming that she got into a finger without
reaching the end. He felt proud of the stench of iodoform that was spreading in its wake, and
spoke of the care with which he had been treated in that town, it was for him the best Spain. Wealthier
neighbors, as it were the aristocracy, were interested in their fate; the mayor had come to him,
after paying the return trip. Still kept in his pocket three dollars, that he gave his mother with
a generosity of a great man. And as much glory to fourteen! Your satisfaction was even greater
when in La Campana, some bullfighters - but real bullfighters - turned their attention to the boy,
asking how its going to hurt.

After this accident did not return to the tent of his master. Knew what they were bulls; his
wound had served to increase his boldness. Torero, torero nothing but! Mrs. Anxieties abandoned
any intention of correcting, judging useless. It was realized that there was his son. When
present in home at night, when the mother and Sister ate together, they did so dish silent,
trying to overwhelm him with contempt. But this in no way altered his chewing. If you arrive
late, do not bore or a crust, and had to turn to the street as he
had come.

Night-walker was in the Alameda de Hercules with vicious eyes other boys, mix Learner confusing criminal
and bullfighter. The neighbors found him sometimes the streets talking to gentlemen whose presence
made women laugh, or with serious gentlemen slander those who gave feminine nicknames. Some
seasons he sold newspapers, and the great feasts of Easter offering to the ladies sitting in the
plaza of San Francisco trays of sweets.

At fair time wandering in the vicinity of the hotel waiting an 'English', since for him all
the passengers were British, hoping to serve as a guide.

- Milord!

... I torero! - Said to see an exotic figure, as if his professional a recommendation was indisputable
for foreigners.

And to certify their identity took off his hat, throwing back the
queue, a lock of a fourth that had stretched out on the top of the
head.

His misery was mate Chiripa, boy the same age, small body and eyes
malicious, without father or mother, who wandered through Seville
since I can remember and exercised on Juanillo the domain of experience.

He had a cut cheek and the scar of a goring, and this signal considerábala the Zapaterin as something
far beyond its invisible injury.

When the door of a hotel, some avid traveler of "local color" with
small talk bullfighters, admiring her pigtails and the story of his
wounds, to stop giving them money, Chiripa sentimental tone said:

-
Nah, you do not give to the practitioners which mare, and I'm alone
in the world er.

Tié mare who does not know what you have!

And Zapaterin, with a sad regret, allowing the other to seize all money, muttering:

- It's true ... is green.

This tenderness did not prevent their continued existence Juanillo abnormal, appearing in Madame
Angustias very from time to time and taking trips away from Sevilla.

Fluke was a master of the wandering life. The days of racing we stated in his will the purpose
of entering into the bullring with his comrade, appealing to it to the stratagems climbing
the walls, sliding or soften the crowd with humble employees pleas.

A bullfight without that they saw them, they were of the profession! ... When capea had not
in the villages of the province, would take his rag to the bulls in the meadow Tablada, but
all these attractions of life in Seville not enough to satisfy his ambition.

Chiripa had run the world, and spoke to his companion of the great
things seen by him in distant provinces.

He was skilled in the art of free travel, surreptitiously sneaking in trains. The Zapaterin
listened with rapt descriptions of Madrid, a city dream with its Plaza de Toros was by way
of a cathedral of bullfighting.

A gentleman, by laughing at them and said to the door of a cafe on the street Sierpes Bilbao
win that much money because there are not many bullfighters in Seville, and the two boys started to
go, clean pocket and no other team that its layers, layers 'real', which had been bullfighters
cartel, miserable wastes acquired real in a few ropavejería.

Introducíanse cautiously on trains and hid under the seats, but hunger and other needs required them to
report their presence to travelers, who eventually sympathize with these adventures, laughing
at their strange shapes, their pigtails and capes, aided with the remains of their lunches.
When an employee gave hunting seasons, running from car to car or attempting to climb the roof
to wait crouched on the train launched. Often surprised them, and grabbing the ears, accompanied
slapped and kicked, left in the lonely station platform as the train
moved away as a forlorn hope.

Awaiting the passage of another, bivouacking outdoors, and if they were closely monitored, undertook
immediate progress towards the station through the deserted fields, certain to be more fortunate.
Just arrived in Madrid after several days of long and eventful journey to the accompaniment
stops strokes. In the streets of Seville and the Puerta del Sol admired groups of fighters without
Contractual higher authorities, who dared to seek, without success,
a charity to continue trip.

A boy from the Plaza de Toros, who was in Seville, took pity on them and let them sleep in
the blocks, providing them the delight of witnessing a run of steers the famous circus, which seemed
less important than its land.

Afraid of their audacity and seeing more and more distant the end of the excursion, undertaken return
to Sevilla as they had come, but since then took a taste for travel sneaking onto the railway. Dirigíanse
minor villages in different provinces when they heard vague news Andalusian holiday with their
capeas.

Just arrived Mancha and Extremadura to, and if the chances of bad luck requiring them to march
foot, seeking refuge in the homes of peasants, gullible people and smiling, which is missed
of its few years of their boldness and deceitful talk, taking them for real tenderers.

This wandering life made them easy ways of primitive man used to meet their needs. In the vicinity
of the cottages on the belly arrastrábanse, stealing vegetables without being seen. They waited for
hours to come near a lone hen to them, and twisting the neck will go on, to light a wood fire
dry in the middle of the day and swallow the poor charred and medium rare animal with a voracious
of little savages. They feared the dogs of the field rather than
the bulls.

It was difficult beasts for the fight, running towards them showing their fangs, as if the anger
his exotic look and sniff in their persons enemies of the property.

Many times when sleeping outdoors near a station, waiting for the passage of a train we got them a couple
of Civil Guards. When you see the red wrappings which served Pillow these vagrants, soldiers
tranquilizábanse order. I gently removed caps, and to find the furry appendage of the queue, they
walked away giggling over inquiries. They were not thieves: they were fans who went to the amateur
bullfight. And in this tolerance was a mixture of sympathy for the national holiday and respect before
the darkness of the future. Who would know if any of these boys ragged, crusty misery, would
be the future an "art star" a great man who sires a toast to kings, live like a prince, whose exploits
and those reproducing the papers! ...

One afternoon, the Zapaterin left alone in a village in Extremadura. For more awe the public
rustic applauding the famous bullfighters' come on purpose of Seville ", the boys wanted flags
nailed to a bully and an old bull. Juanillo put their sticks to the fierce and stayed with a
boardwalk, enjoying receive popular acclaim in the form of slaps and offers tremendous sips
of wine.

An exclamation of horror him out of the intoxication of glory.

Fluke was no longer on the floor of the plaza. Only the flags were in it rolling in the dust a
shoe and cap. She moved the bull as irritated at an obstacle, being engaged one of its horns
a bundle of clothes like a puppet. With the violent headbutts The report was released horn
package, expelling a jet red, but before reaching the soil was achieved by the opposite pole,
which in turn shook him a long time.

At last the sad package fell headlong, and lay there, limp and lifeless, releasing liquid such
as a skin pierced expelling the jets came.

The pastor, with his oxen, took the bull pen, because no one dared approach him, and poor Chiripa
was conducted on a pallet to a small room that served as City Hall imprisonment. Her partner
was with a white face as if it were cast, eyes dull and blood-red body, but it could contain
the vinegar and water wipes it applied in the absence of anything
better.

- Adio, Zapaterin! - Sigh -. Adio, Juaniyo!

And he said
no more. The companion of the dead began returning to Sevilla terrified,
seeing his eyes glassy, ??hearing his whining goodbyes. I was scared.
A gentle cow coming out the way you had been run. He thought of his
mother and the wisdom of his advice. Was it not better engage shoemaker
and live peacefully? ... But these purposes only lasted while he was
alone.

Arriving in Sevilla felt the influence of environment. The
friends ran to him to know in full detail the death of poor Chiripa.
Professional bullfighters was asked La Campana, remembering with shame
to that urchin cut face that many times they ran errands. Juan, emboldened
by such tokens of regard, giving vent to its power imaginative, describing
how he had thrown on the bull to see his poor caught companion how
he had caught the bug in the queue, and other prodigious feats, despite
which the other had left the world</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>