<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10032</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>87687</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16231</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

El interpelado no contestaba nada, y parecía resuelto a emplear la más estudiada reserva con
su interlocutor, que se mostraba sumamente interesado en trabar relación con él.

--¿Es telescopio ese?--insistió el oficioso.

El dueño del anteojo no contestó nada. Semiavergonzado el preguntón, mironos a todos los que
rodeábamos al señor del anteojo, con cara de cretino como un individuo que se confiesa en una
posición falsa.

Pero nuestro hombre no era individuo de ceder a dos tirones y reincidió.

--¿Me quiere dejar mirar un momento?

El dueño del anteojo tampoco contestó esta vez.

--¡Eh, señor!--repitió tocándole tímidamente sobre el brazo--¿me quiere dejar mirar?

El del anteojo sacó los ojos del vidrio, dio vuelta para ver quién le hablaba y contestó secamente:

--¡No!

El desairado trató de forjar una sonrisa para disimular.

Entretanto, había ganado posiciones junto a la reja del murallón donde estábamos, una señora
gorda, con un peinado de bananas sobre el cual colgaba una mantilla española de chapa, metiendo
codo a todos los obstáculos que había encontrado a su paso; la cara, iluminada por una capa
de colorete recientemente aplicada, distribuía una sonrisa perenne por todas partes; y metida
dentro de un vestido de moirée verde, inflado por un miriñaque movedizo y oscilante, parecía
un montgolfier en el momento de elevarse.

Un lunar con pelo en la parte inferior de la cara daba a nuestra recién llegada un aire picaresco
de coqueta retirada.

Acompañábanla dos muchachas de aspecto poco distinguido, pero llenas de arrumacos y perendengues,
con unos cuerpos bien trazados, y unos bustos en los cuales la Naturaleza o el arte habían
abusado con cierta insolencia de una inclinación marcada a la exuberancia. Las dos muchachas,
oriundas del barrio de Monserrat seguramente, rayaban en los 20 o 22 años y penetraron en nuestro
grupo, que ya se iba estrechando, metiendo una algarabía inusitada de gritos y risotadas cuyas
causas no me podía explicar.

--Mira, mamá--dijo la mayor,--este caballero es tan amable, que te va a dejar mirar por el anteojo.

--¡Por Dios, Raquel! no molestes a ese señor... ¡qué va a decir de nosotras!--contestaba con
un tono de aparente reproche la señora.

--¡Señor, señor! ¿quiere dejarnos ver por ahí?--insinuó la otra joven.

--¡Ah, no, por Dios, no se incomode usted!... Judit, por Dios, cállate--repetía la madre con
un contoneo de cabeza continuo.

El del anteojo continuaba impasible como una estatua, como si nadie le hablase.

--Allá se ve un humo, allá vienen--gritó uno por allí cerca. La ola humana se agitó y se hizo
un remolino; la gente se agrupó en la baranda; todos querían ver. Yo, prendido de Alejandro,
trepado sobre sus hombros, dominaba la altura.

--¡Ay, que me arrugan!--- gritaba la madre de Raquel y de Judit, sin que el miriñaque la ayudara
a subir.--¡Ay, mi vestido, que me lo estropean todo! ¡No veo a Judit! ¡Judit, Judit, Judiiit!

Judit, que estaba allí cerca, y a quien la madre no podía encontrar, conversaba con un joven
de sombrero gacho, levita negra de lustrina y pantalón blanco almidonado, sin guardar distancias,
es decir, unida a él por una proximidad inusitada.

--¡Ay, mi hija, mi hija! ¿dónde está mi hija? ¡Se me ha perdido mi hija! ¡Judit, Judiiit!--exclamaba
la señora prolongando el grito.

--Aquí estoy, mamá, no alborote, aquí estoy--contestó por último Judit, haciendo lo posible
por soltar la mano de su galán, que retenía con fuerza para que no se marchara.

--No te muevas de acá, bribona; no te me separes. Ven tú también, Raquel. ¡Ay, Jesús! ¡bien
me decía tu padre! No té metas mucho entre la gente con las muchachas, Donata; mira que no
faltan atrevidos que las manoseen en los entreveros y que a ti también te han de manosear:
¡Qué gente, por Dios; qué gente! ¡qué falta de respeto con las señoras! ¡Cuánto mejor no hubiera
sido ir a los altos de Colón!...

Pero la muchedumbre en movimiento lo arrastraba todo. Cargado por Alejandro, que con el brazo
libre que le quedaba, se abría paso como un Hércules, avanzábamos a tomar otra posición.

Yo, desde los hombros elevados de mi conductor, veía a la pobre misia Donata y a sus dos bíblicas
criaturas, víctimas del pronóstico de su marido y manoseadas por aquella turba indisciplinada,
entre la cual había mocitos que le pirateaban las hijas y groseros que le deshacían las bananas
y le arrancaban su espléndido vestido color cotorra, admiración suprema del barrio de Monserrat
en la misa de una.

--¡Ya han fondeado, ya han fondeado los buques!--gritaban a nuestra alrededor.--Vea, señor,--le
decía un negro a un caballero petizón, que en vano se empinaba para poder ver;--vea, allí,
allí--y apuntaba con el dedo índice.

--¿Adonde? ¿adonde?--interrogaba el otro impaciente, parado sobre la punta de los pies.

--Allí están; ahí ha fondeado el Salto, allí el Pampero, más atrás el Hércules; aquel que viene
andando todavía es el Pintos, y los otros dos barcos de la izquierda son de vela, el San Juan
Bautista y el Río Bamba.

--¡Ché! y vos cómo sabés los buques--le dijo Alejandro.

--¡Oh! no ve que soy del Bajo, amigo--contestó el negro.--Mire--agregó,--allá van las falúas
a buscar la oficialidad, y las balleneras para desembarcar la tropa. ¡Bomba! ¡Pas! Ese es el
Córdoba que hace salvas.

Y, en efecto, una repentina nube blanca envolvió los costados del barco y el eco del cañonazo
se dilató retumbando sordamente por los espacios.

Eran las tres de la tarde de aquel día sofocante; las iglesias echaban a vuelo sus campanas,
los cohetes y las bombas estallaban en el aire sin interrupción. A medida que la tropa desembarcaba,
los batallones iban formando en el muelle la columna. Mientras esta operación tenía lugar,
Alejandro y yo contemplábamos desde lejos, recostados sobre la reja, porque no nos habían dejado
pasar de los quioscos, de la entrada para adelante.

En la playa, y al pie mismo del murallón donde nosotros estábamos, varios carreros del Bajo,
en traje de fiesta, se habían congregado para oír a dos de ellos que, armado el uno con una
guitarra profusamente encintada de blanco y celeste, y el otro con un acordeón, cantaban coplas
patrioteras en una de esas tonadas características del compadrito de Buenos Aires.

--¡Que cante el virola!--gritaba uno de los oyentes.

--¡Tu madrina!--contestole el guitarrero, que en efecto tenía los ojos más torcidos que una
encrucijada.

--Cantá ché lo que has arreglao pa la Guardia Nacional.

El de la guitarra con el del acordeón atacaron un aire vulgar, pero cadencioso, antepasado
en línea recta de la milonga del día, y detrás del aire, el virola dijo con voz nasal y chocante
la siguiente copla:

      Nuestra Guardia Nacional
    en Cepeda y en Pavón,
    con bravura sin igual,
    se lanzó sobre el cañón
    del cobarde federal.

--¡Lindo, don Polibio! Si a carrero y a verseador naide le gana. Hasta a los gringos de las
balleneras se les cae la baba cuando canta usted.

Los resuellos chillones del acordeón habrían seguido, junto con los gemidos de la guitarra,
si las músicas militares no hubiesen anunciado que la columna, formada ya, se ponía en marcha
a lo largo del muelle.

Fue entonces cuando la muchedumbre que obstruía la entrada, arrebatada por una fila de vigilantes
armados, encargados de abrir calle, remolineó y retrocedió de espaldas, compacta, hasta apretarse
contra las paredes de las casas inmediatas; un tropel de jinetes que venía de la ciudad, ocupó
el espacio abandonado. Me deslumbraron el oro de los galones, las plumas blancas y azules de
los elásticos agitadas por el viento, los colores llamativos de los uniformes. Alejandro me
alzó en alto para que pudiera ver bien, pero apenas tuve tiempo de columbrar un elástico cubriendo
una larga y abundante melena de guedejas indolentes que caían sobre una frente espaciosa y
unos ojos color plomo; todo esto sostenido sobre un cuerpo que Doré no habría desdeñado para
bosquejar un Lafayette en lontananza. Quise ver más, pero los jinetes hicieron caracolear sus
caballos; las primeras hileras de la columna aparecieron, y apenas llegó a mi oído el eco de
una proclama de acentos olímpicos pero simpáticos que se extinguía en el estruendo unísono
de un aplauso tributado por veinte mil manos. Yo aplaudía también y batía palmas.

--¿Por qué aplaude--me dijo Alejandro, de mal humor,--si no oye nada?

--¡Oh!--le contesté--¿acaso es necesario entender? ¿Cómo aplauden también todos los demás sin
entender?

VIII

Por la noche, mis tíos, como me lo habían prometido, me llevaron al teatro de la Victoria.
La compañía de García Delgado cantaba el himno nacional y representaba la Flor de un día, de
Camprodón. ¡Oh, Flor de un día! ¡Oh, Pavón del teatro dramático español! ¿Por qué mi fantasía
excéntrica te ve desaparecer en el pasado, en la misma tumba que tragó los miriñaques y el
peinado de bananas? ¿No era Lola la más encantadora y la más romántica de las mujeres? ¿No
tenía Diego el contorno poético del amante y el Marqués de Montero la estampa grave de un barítono
de zarzuela triste?

¿Por qué has de ser un disparate, oh hija legítima de don Francisco Camprodón, adoptada por
todos los teatros de la América Latina? ¡Tú que has hecho lagrimar un continente entero desde
Veracruz hasta Buenos Aires!

¡Tú has muerto con el batón blanco; porque, así como el guante de piel de Suecia, largo y arrugado,
sobre el brazo flaco y nervioso de Sarah Bernhardt ha dado su pincelada a Frou-Frou, así el
batón blanco, con cinturón celeste, te hizo a ti, hizo a Lola el prototipo de todas las mujeres
de tu tiempo! ¡Qué diablo! ¡tú has tenido también tu lugar en el siglo de Hernani!... ¡Presidentes
y ministros, generales y grandes abogados de la República Argentina, han creído en ti, como
la República ha creído en ellos! Tus octosílabos rumorosos agitaron más de una noche el pecho
de la virgen y no fue sólo el teatro tu dominio! Fue también la familia, el hogar; porque todo
lo invadiste, desde el salón de mi tía Medea hasta la academia de negros y mulatos en que era
halcón mi pardo Alejandro. Todavía recuerdo con escándalo el gesto irreverente y volteriano
con que el doctor Vélez se burlaba de ti una noche, dando la nota discordante en toda tu generación
literaria. Yo sostengo y sostendré siempre que tú has hecho a muchos de nuestros poetas: y
bastaría reflexionar un poco para notar que todas las manifestaciones sociales se parecían
a ti en aquellos días.

Tus versos llegaron a ser clásicos. Se citaban con gravedad en el editorial por los periodistas
contemporáneos y en la Cámara de Diputados por los oradores noveles, con el mismo respeto con
que en la restauración se citaban los dísticos de Boileau. ¡El día de la patria te pertenecía;
te pertenecía el día de toda fiesta nacional! ¡Hasta drama patriótico te había hecho el autor
de tus días sin sospecharlo!

Algunas de tus frases, como: «¿tiene vuestra espada punta?» se consagraron como el Di quella
pira y el la donna e mobile de Verdi. No había entonces realismo; mister Pickwick no había
atravesado el Atlántico; estaba en Bath presidiendo su club; Nana era un microbio; Artagnan
era catedrático de historia; los Girondinos enseñaban la política. Era la época de las cavatinas,
cuarteadas con acompañamientos rudimentarios; Lohengrin bebía mosela en los vidrios blasonados
de Baviera; el Trovador era la ópera con Mirati y Tamberlick; tú eras el drama con la Rodríguez
y la Bigones, con Enamorado y Vilardebó. ¡El teatro de la Victoria era tu campo de batalla!

¡Oh, mis buenos y bravos cómicos, aquella noche estaban todos! Mi imaginación los evoca; desfilan
como los fantasmas del sueño del pasado y penetran al obscuro y olvidado panteón de las glorias
del arte argentino; allí yo les levanto un monumento con los restos del guardarropa de Dagnino,
en que había de todo; forma la base el casco de Gonzalo de Córdoba, cubierto por el manto lanar
moteado, arminio de Isabel la Católica; Don Juan Tenorio vola sobre el Terremoto de la Martinica,
mientras que la Campana de la Almudaina toca a rebato en la horca de los Escalones del Cadalso.

Pero sobre esta pirámide funeraria, levantada a los Talma y a los Keen de la gran aldea, tres
figuras se levantan: Lola, Diego y el Marqués, cantando el himno nacional antes de contar su
candoroso poema de celos y de amor a una sala llena, en donde brillan las más lindas mujeres
de aquellos días. ¡Pasad, oh sombras!

       *       *       *       *       *

Habíamos ocupado un palco-balcón de la derecha, inmediato a aquella antigua viga blanqueada
que sostenía el techo y que por su espesor desafiaba las fuerzas de Sansón mismo.

Mi tía se había hecho acompañar por la señorita Fernanda, que yo estaba acostumbrado a ver
con frecuencia en casa. Fernanda tenía dieciocho años; pálida, de ojos claros y grandes, fríos
y como azorados entre las densas ojeras que los sombreaban; en sus labios gruesos que dibujaban
una boca que podía llamarse grande sin injusticia, trazábase no sé qué vaga sonrisa, en la
que un observador sagaz habría encontrado el amor y el desdén reunidos en un consorcio inexplicable;
la cabeza era noble y altiva, sin embargo. En aquella época, en que los peinados eran una epopeya
de rulos y rellenos, Fernanda llevaba el suyo de una simpleza tal, que rayaba en la suma elegancia:
sus cabellos, de un rubio mate, recogidos y sujetos por dos cintas de moirée celeste, iban
a rematar en la más linda nuca de mujer. Su seno escaso, tenía, sin embargo, no sé qué atrayente
seducción, dilatada por la morbidez de todo su busto: irradiaba su semblante esa gracia apática
e indolente que el pincel del Veronese imprimía en el rostro de sus patricias venecianas. Era,
en fin, aquella mujer un conjunto de frialdad y de elocuencia, de belleza y de defectos, que
atraía irresistiblemente, y en la que la originalidad del gesto y del mirar despertaban en
mí una profunda y codiciosa curiosidad.

Fernanda, recostada sobre la balaustrada, oyó de pie el himno, y, cuando éste terminó, se dejó
caer negligentemente sobre su silla y abrió su enorme abanico de plumas blancas, con un ademán
lleno de innata voluptuosidad. ¡Qué contraste formaba aquella delicada criatura con mi tía
Medea! Una era la distinción personificada; la envolvía, la perfumaba un vapor de elegancia
y de buen tono. La otra era un fauno obeso; su voz gruesa, su pescuezo corto, su pecho invasor,
un bozo recio, que ya era bigote casi, hacían de ella un ser híbrido, en el que los dos sexos
se confundían. Estaba esa noche verdaderamente constelada de diamantes, desde la cabeza hasta
los dedos, y como los tenía, y muy buenos, uno de sus orgullos era colgárselos para exhibirlos.

Inquieta y parlanchina, mantenía un verdadero telégrafo de saludos con todo el teatro; con
los palcos, con la cazuela, con la platea; a todos conocía, a todos saludaba francachonamente
con el abanico.

De repente, un murmullo de simpatía cundió por la sala entera, y todas las miradas convergieron
al palco central de la ochava: muchos personajes, vestidos con la más rigurosa etiqueta, tomaban
asiento.

Mi tía empezó a nombrarlos a todos.

--Saluda, Ramón, saluda--le decía a mi tío.

--Si no ven para acá, Medea...

--Sí que ven, saluda te digo--y mi tía, al propio tiempo que le ordenaba a mi tío que saludase,
hacía repetidos movimientos de cabeza en dirección al palco central, sin que fuesen notados
por sus ocupantes.

--¿Quiénes son, señora?--preguntaba Fernanda.

Pero mi tía no contestaba; empeñada en colocar su saludo en la cara de sus ídolos y en que
su marido también lo colocase, lo cazó materialmente del brazo y le mandó que esperara la ocasión
propicia para mover el pescuezo. De pronto pareciole que la miraban.

--¡Ahí mira don Buenaventura! ¡ahí te mira el doctor Trevexo...--dijo;--¡ahora!... saluda, Ramón.

Y ambos movieron la cabeza con urgencia; hicieron con ella un balance para cazar la visual
del adversario, pero ¡oh, contratiempo! Una mirada vaga e indecisa, de la cual tenía yo una
vaga idea, recorría la fila de los palcos sin detenerse en los brillantes de mi tía, y el saludo
fue un saludo en el vacío.

Mi tío tosió para disimular el contratiempo. Mi tía le echó la culpa, sosteniendo que se le
había puesto por delante; mi tío quiso rectificar, pero se le ordenó que guardase silencio,
y obedeció. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10957</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>359048</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14567</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

The apprehended no answer, and seemed determined to use the most studied reserve your correspondent,
who showed keen interest in locking relationship.

- Is telescope that? - Insisted the unofficial.

The owner of the telescope did not answer.

Semiavergonzado the questioner, voyeur everyone we surrounded the
lord of the telescope, looking like a geeky guy who confesses to a
false position.

But our man was not to assign individual strains and two relapsed.

- Do I want to leave to look for a moment?

The owner of the telescope did not answer this time.

- Hey, mister! - Timidly repeated touching on the arm - I want to stop looking?

The telescope took his eyes of glass, turned to see who spoke and
answered dryly:

- No!

The snubbed tried to forge a smile to hide.

Meanwhile, had won seats at the gate of the seawall where we were, a lady fat, with a style of bananas
on which hung a Spanish mantilla sheet, tucking side by all the obstacles that had found its
way, the face lit by a layer recently applied rouge, distributed a perennial smile everywhere,
and tucked in a green dress Moiree, inflated by a moving and oscillating crinoline appeared Balloon
in a time of rising.

A mole with hair on the lower face of our new arrival was a roguish air coquette withdrawal.

He was accompanied two undistinguished-looking girls, but plenty of
cuddles and perendengues, bodies with a well designed, and a bust
in which nature or art had abused with some insolence of a marked
inclination to the exuberance.

The two girls, coming from the neighborhood of Montserrat probably
verged on the 20 or 22 years and entered our group, which was narrowing,
putting an unusual cacophony of screams and laughter which I could
not explain causes.

- Look, Mom - said the eldest, - this gentleman
is so friendly, that will let you look through the telescope.

- By
God, Rachel! do not bother this man ... What to say about us! - Answered
with a tone of reproach Mrs. apparent.

- Sir, sir!

Will you let us see out there? - Hinted the other girl.

- Ah, no, by God, not bother you! ... Judith, by God, shut up - repeated
the mother a continuous head wiggle.

The telescope remained impassive as a statue, as if no one spoke.

-
There is smoke, there are - shouted one nearby.

The human wave was stirred and an eddy, the people were grouped in the rail, everyone wanted to
see. I, pinned Alexander, perched on their shoulders, dominated the height.

- Oh, I wrinkle! --- Cried the mother of Rachel and Judith, without the help crinoline up .-- Oh,
my dress, I spoil it all! I do not see Judit!

Judit, Judith, Judiiit!

Judith, who was nearby, and whom the mother could not find, talking to a young slouch hat, black
shiny material of alpaca coat and starched white trousers, without
saving distances that is, bound to him by a close unused.

- Oh, my
daughter, my daughter!

Where is my daughter? I have lost my daughter! Judith Judiiit! - Exclaimed Mrs. prolonging
the scream.

- Here I am, Mom, no fuss, here I am - finally answered Judith, making it possible to loosen the
hand of her beau, which held firmly to her not to go.

- Do not move
from here, hussy, do not separate me.

You come too, Raquel. Oh, Jesus! Well I said your father! Do not mess much among people with
the girls, Donata; sight not bold miss your hands in the brawl and
that you too have to handle: What people, by God, what people!

What lack of respect with the ladies! How much better would not been going to the heights of Columbus!
...

But the crowd pulled him moving around. Uploaded by Alexander, who with his arm it was free, he
made his way as a Hercules, we went to take another position.

Yo, from the shoulders elevated my driver, saw the poor Dona Donata
and her two biblical creatures, victims of the prognosis of her husband
and manhandled by the mob undisciplined between the lad who had pirated
it rude daughters and undid him bananas and tore his splendid parrot-colored
dress, supreme admiration Montserrat district in a mass.

- I have
anchored, moored vessels have already! - Screaming around us .-- You
see, sir, - I said a black gentleman petizón, tiptoe in vain to see,
- see, there there - and pointed his index finger.

- Where?

Where? - Questioned the other impatiently, standing on tiptoe.

- There are, there has anchored the waterfall, there the Pampero, behind the Hercules who comes
walking is still the Pintos, and the other two boats are sailing
left, the San Juan Bautista and the Rio Bamba.

- Che! and you how
you know the ship - said Alexander.

- Oh! I do not see the lower,
friend - said the black .-- Look - added, - the destination for gigs
to seek officers, and the whale to land the troops.

Bomb! Pas! That is the Cordoba ago saved.

And indeed, a sudden white cloud enveloped the ship's sides and the echo of cannon dilated echoing
dully through the spaces.

It was three in the afternoon of that sweltering day, the church bells cast in flight, rockets
and bombs bursting in air without interruption. As the troops landed, the battalions were formed in
the spring column. While this operation took place, Alejandro and I beheld from afar, leaning
over the fence, because we had left pass kiosks, entry forward.

On the beach, and at the foot of the seawall where we were, several rounds of Bass, in evening
gown, had gathered to hear two of them, one armed with a guitar heavily ribbed white and blue,
and one with an accordion, singing songs chauvinistic one of those tunes compadrito characteristics
of Buenos Aires.

- You sing the ring! - Shouted one of the listeners.

- Your godmother! - Then said the guitarist, who actually had his
eyes more twisted than a crossroads.

- Sing what you arreglao ché
pa National Guard.

The guitar with the accordion attacked a vulgar air, but rhythmic,
ancestor straight from the milonga of the day, and behind the air,
the nasal voice said ferrule and shocking the following couplet:

Our
National Guard in Cepeda and Pavón, bravely unparalleled was launched
on the barrel the federal coward.

- Lindo, Don Polybius!

      If you Naide verseador race
    and wins. Even the gringos
    of the whaling were drooling
    when you sing.
    

The shrill wheeze of the accordion would have followed, along with the wailing of the guitar
if military bands had not announced that the column, formed already
got underway along the waterfront.

That was when the crowd blocked the entrance, snatched by a row of
guards armed, in charge of opening streets, swirled and fell back,
compact, to tighten against the walls of the neighboring houses, a
troop of horsemen came from the town, occupied abandoned space.

Gold dazzled me gals, white feathers and blue elastics agitated by the wind, the bright colors of
the uniforms. Alexander I lifted up so that he could see well, but barely had time to descry an elastic
covering a long and rich mane of locks falling on an indolent and spacious front lead-colored
eyes, all this supported on a body that would not have disdained to Doré Lafayette in drafting
a distance. I wanted to see more, but the riders did prance their horses, the first row of
the column appeared, and just came to my ear the echo of Olympic accents a proclamation but nice to
be extinguished in unison roar of applause taxed for twenty thousand hands. I also cheered
and clapped his hands.

- Why applauds - Alejandro told me, in a bad mood - if you hear nothing?

- Oh - I said - do you need to understand? How also applaud all the
others without understand?

VIII

At night, my uncles, as I promised, I was taken to the Victoria Theatre. Delgado García company
sang the National Anthem and representing the flower of a day, Camprodón. Oh, flower of a day!
Oh, Pavón Spanish dramatic theater! Why is my fantasy Eccentric see you disappear in the past,
in the same grave that swallowed the crinolines and banana hair? Was not Lola the loveliest
and most romantic of women? Did not Diego had the outline poetic lover and the Marquis de
Montero grave picture of a baritone zarzuela sad?

Why have to be a nonsense, oh legitimate daughter of Don Francisco Camprodón adopted by every
theater in Latin America? You have done an entire continent from tears Vera Cruz to Buenos Aires!

You
have died with the white robe, for, as well as suede gloves, long
and wrinkled, on thin, nervous arm of Sarah Bernhardt has given his
brushwork to Frou-Frou, and the white robe with blue belt, made you,
Lola made the prototype of all women of your time!

What the devil! You have had your own place in the century of Hernani! ... Presidents and ministers,
generals and great lawyers of Argentina, have believed in you as the Republic had believed
in them! Your octosyllabic murmuring stirred over night chest of the Virgin and the theater was
not just your domain! It was also the family, home, for all assailed him from the room of my Aunt
Medea to the Academy of blacks and mulattoes was my brown hawk Alejandro. I still remember
the gesture scandalously irreverent Voltaire Dr. Velez that mocked you one night, giving discordant
note in all your generation literature. I argue and argue as long as you have done to many of
our poets: and enough to reflect a bit to notice that every social event seemed you in those
days.

Phone lines became classics. Gravely cited in the editorial by journalists contemporaries and
the Chamber of Deputies for novice speakers with the same respect that in citing the statistical
restoration of Boileau.

The day of the country belonged to you; you all owned the day a national holiday! Until you patriotic
drama made by the author of your life without knowing it!

Some of your phrases as: "Do you have your sword tip?" Were enshrined as the Di quella pyre and
the donna e mobile from Verdi.

There was so realistic, Mr. Pickwick had not crossed the Atlantic, was presiding over his club
Bath, Nana was a microbe; Artagnan was professor of history, the Girondins taught politics.
It was the time of the Cavatina, cracked rudimentary accompaniments; Lohengrin drinking glasses
emblazoned Moselle in Bavaria, the Troubadour was the opera and Tamberlick Mirati, you were the drama
with Rodriguez and Bigon, with Love and Vilardebó. Theatre de la Victoria was your field!

Oh, my good and brave comedians that night were all!

My imagination conjures up, parade Sleep like the ghosts of the past and enter the dark and forgotten
pantheon of glory Argentine art, there I will get up a monument with the remains of wardrobe Dagnino,
they had everything, forming the base hull Gonzalo de Cordoba, covered by the blanket wool mottled
ermine Isabel the Catholic, Don Juan Tenorio vola on Earthquake Martinique while Almudaina Bell
plays the alarm by hanging of the steps of a gallows.

But on this pyramidal tomb, built at the Talma and Keen of the large village, three figures rise:
Lola, Diego and the Marquis, singing the national anthem prior to having their naive poem of
jealousy and love to a room full, where the most beautiful women shine of those days. Come in,
oh shadows!

       

* * * * *

We occupied a stage-right balcony, that old beam immediately bleached supporting the roof and
its thickness defied the forces of Samson himself.

My aunt had been accompanied by Miss Fernanda, I was accustomed to seeing frequently at home.
Fernanda was eighteen years old, pale, clear eyes and big, cold and as bewildered among the dense shaded
circles that, in his thick lips that drew a mouth that could be called great without injustice, trazábase
not know what vague smile on a shrewd observer would have found love and contempt together in a consortium
inexplicable; the head was noble and proud, however. At that time, which was an epic hairstyles
of rollers and stuffed his Fernanda had such a simple, bordering on great elegance: her hair, a
blond mate, collected and held by two strips of blue Moiree, were to finish in the most beautiful
woman's neck. His little heart, had, however, I do not know how appealing seduction, dilated by
the softness around her bust, that grace her face radiated apathetic indolent the brush of Veronese
printed on the face of Venetian patrician. Was in short, that woman a set of coldness and
eloquence, beauty and flaws that irresistibly attracted, and the
originality of gesture and look aroused in me a deep and greedy curiosity.

Fernanda,

leaning over the railing, standing hear the anthem, and when he finished, he left carelessly dropped
on his chair and opened her huge white feather fan, with a flourish full of innate sensuality.
What a contrast was that delicate creature with my aunt Medea! A distinction was personified,
the wrapping, the steam perfumed elegance an and good tone. The other was a faun obese, his
voice thick, its short neck, his chest invasive a mighty mustache, mustache was already almost,
made it a chimera, in which both sexes blur. That night was truly studded with diamonds from
head to fingers, and as it had, and very good, one of their pride was hung for display.

Restless and talkative, kept a real telegram of greetings to the entire theater with the boxes,
with the bowl, with the audience, everyone knew everyone greeted francachonamente with the fan.

Suddenly,
a murmur of sympathy spread throughout the entire room and all eyes
converged the central stage of the facet: many characters, dressed
in the strictest etiquette, taking seat.

My aunt began to name them all.

- Saluda, Ramon, compliments - I
told my uncle.

- If you come here, Medea ...

- Yes you are, greet
you say - and my aunt, at the same time ordering him to my uncle who
salute, was repeated head movements towards the central stage, without
being noticed by their occupants.

- Who are they, madam? - Asked
Fernanda.

But my aunt did not answer, determined to put your greeting in the
faces of their idols and that her husband also places him physically
shot it the arm and told him to wait for the occasion propitious to
move the neck.

Suddenly it seemed that they looked.

- That looks don Buenaventura!

There you see the doctor told Trevexo ...--, - now!

... greets, Ramón.

They both nodded urgently, made her a visual balance to hunt the adversary,
but oh, mishap!

A look vague and indecisive, which I had a vague idea, crossed the
line of the boxes without stopping at my aunt's brilliant, and greeting
was a greeting in a vacuum.

My uncle coughed to hide the disappointment. My aunt put the blame, claiming that he had taken the
lead, my uncle wanted to rectify, but was ordered to be silent, and
obeyed.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>