<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10715</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>102141</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20525</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> A cada paso hallaba motivo
para empeñar la atención de su entusiasta amiga, ya indicándole los festones de aguinaldos
blancos o campanillas pendientes de todos los arbustos a orillas de los cañaverales, ya los
güines de las cañas, que comparaba con las garzotas de innumerables guerreros en marcial arreo,
mecidos blandamente por la gentil brisa de la mañana; ora los grupos de tomeguines que con
rumor sordo, cual de viento rastrero y en gran tropel, seguían por algún trecho la dirección
de los viajeros, rozando con las yerbas y luego desapareciendo por entre los troncos de las
cañas; o el vivaracho sabanero de tardo vuelo, que salía con estrépito del espeso matorral
y se posaba con mucha dificultad en la primer hoja de caña con que tropezaba en su desatentada
fuga; o la esquiva garza blanca que se abría paso por entre las ramas del roble ribereño, y
con el largo cuello replegado a la espalda y los pies colgando seguía en su huida el curso
del arroyo; o la bandada de alborotosas cotorras que cubrían los naranjos silvestres y sólo
se veían cuando se aferraban a la dorada fruta para extraerle la simiente; o el gavilán, en
fin, águila de Cuba, que daba gritos y gritos penetrantes mientras se cernía por encima de
las palmas más alterosas, entre la tierra y el cielo.

Finalmente, pasadas las diez de la mañana, atravesaron los viajeros los cañaverales del ingenio
Valvanera, a la vista de sus grandes fábricas. Dos millas adelante se acercaron al pueblo de
Quiebra Hacha. Aquí se dividía en dos el camino que traían, uno que torcía al oeste y era el
carretero de la Vuelta Abajo, y el otro, el de La Angosta, que servía de entrada a los ingenios
de azúcar, ya establecidos en esa región de la costa. Este tomaron nuestros viajeros. A su
paso por el pueblo varias personas reconocieron y saludaron con amistoso respeto a Leonardo Gamboa.

Presentábase adelante el país tan áspero, desigual y montuoso como el anterior recorrido, aunque
el arbolado era más frondoso y lozano, casi primitivo, y el suelo surcado de arroyos bulliciosos
y de limpias aguas que corrían a perderse al fondo de la bahía del Mariel, o en el mar abierto
al Norte. Tras media hora de camino debajo del bosque, donde no penetraban los rayos del sol,
se avistaron los cañaverales de un ingenio en el repecho de una colina, acotados por una cerca
rústica hecha de gajos, que mantenían en posición horizontal rajas de leña o estacas con horquilla
hincadas en tierra y atados juntos de trecho en trecho, para mayor seguridad, con un bejuco
que, cuando verde, es bastante flexible y elástico, conocido en la Vuelta Abajo con el nombre
vulgar de colorado, Bauchinis heterophyllas.

Luego que, siguiendo por breve espacio, paralelo a dicha ruda cerca, en cuyo tiempo ganaron
los viajeros la altura de la colina, se les ofrecieron en toda su extensión y grandeza los
campos de caña y allá, en el centro del cuadro, el variado grupo de sus fábricas, coronando
otra colina de mayor planicie y más ancha base. Aquél era el ingenio de La Tinaja, y Leonardo
Gamboa, que servía de guía, se las mostró a sus amigos con cierto sentimiento de orgullo. Para
ello había motivo sobrado, no ya sólo por el valor en dinero que representaba la finca, y por
las consideraciones sociales que se les guardaban a sus dueños, mas también por el cuadro bello
y pintoresco del conjunto, contemplado a buena distancia; encubridora eficaz de los lunares
y manchas inherentes a casi todas las obras, así humanas como divinas.

El camino por donde se habían internado los viajeros hasta allí era el denominado de la Playa,
porque servía para el acarreo de los azúcares al pueblo del Mariel, desde el cual se embarcaban
y conducían en goletas al mercado de La Habana. Cruzaba la colina por su cúspide y había establecida
en ella una talanquera no menos rústica que la cerca, pues se reducía a unas varas en bruto,
metidas por sus cabezas en los orificios de dos largueros paralelos. Arrimada a la cerca, y
en su encuentro con la talanquera, se alzaba una cabaña o bohío de los de vara en tierra o
de dos aguas, tan gacho que la techumbre se componía de hojas enteras de la palma tendidas
en los costados o vertientes, con las puntas descansando en el suelo.

Adelantose Leonardo para ver por qué no se hallaba en su puesto el negro guardiero y abría
la talanquera. Con tal objeto, plantó su caballo ante la única entrada del bohío, e inclinando
el cuerpo, trató de registrar el interior. Inútil trabajo: la puerta o boca era muy estrecha
y baja, y más allá de dos pies del umbral no podían penetrar ojos humanos, no tanto por la
viva claridad del día afuera, cuanto por la densa nube de humo de leña que ardía dentro y no
tenía otro medio de escape que ése.

--No veo nada y dudo que haya alma viviente en el bohío, dijo Gamboa hablando con las señoras
en el quitrín, parado en medio del camino. ¡Maldito negro!

--Tal vez duerme, dijo Isabel.

--Si no es el sueño de la muerte, repuso Gamboa, juro que no le salva nadie de un bocabajo.

--¿De qué se trata? preguntó Meneses. ¿De abrir la talanquera? Yo abriré y no perderé el casamiento
por eso.

--No harás tal, replicó Leonardo colérico. No lo consiento.

--Bien, sugirió Isabel con su voz argentina y dulce. Abrirá el calesero; los caballos están
harto cansados para echar a correr. Leocadio, apéate.

--No, no, Isabel, replicó Leonardo, cada vez más colérico. Tampoco puedo consentir en eso,
no debo consentirlo. Si el guardiero está vivo abrirá la talanquera, que para eso y para más
le han puesto ahí.

Sacó el reloj y añadió enseguida:

--Ya han dado las doce, hora en que sueltan la negrada para que coma. Si hubiéramos llegado
aquí un poco antes, habríamos oído la campana del ingenio. Apostaría a que el taita guardiero
se ha metido en el cañaveral para verse con alguna de sus carabelas. ¡Por Dios vivo que la
paga! Nada, no está en parte alguna. ¡Caimán! ¡Caimán!, gritó a todo torrente.

Los montes del rededor fueron los únicos que le devolvieron el eco de sus voces con temblor
continuado, hondo y siniestro; y luego empezó a ladrar un perrillo dogo dentro del bohío. Ahí
está el guardiero, pensó el joven, y se hace el dormido para no tomarse el trabajo de abrir
la talanquera. Lo haré salir a patadas, agregó alto, dando un puñetazo en el pomo de la silla.
Echó pie a tierra sin más demora y se metió en el bohío, teniendo siempre el caballo de la brida.

Muy mal sonaron estas palabras y aquellos juramentos en los oídos de la modesta Isabel, aun
cuando para no avergonzar a su amigo ni irritarle más contra el pobre esclavo, se guardó de
representarle lo absurdo y aun el riesgo de su final propósito, si a posta éste se escondía
por tener oculto algún compañero en el bohío o por otra causa cualquiera. Afortunadamente,
nada de eso ocurría. En aquel mismo instante las señoras del carruaje, Meneses y el calesero
a caballo oyeron un ruido de ramas en el bosque vecino, agitadas por una persona o animal que
se abría paso con alguna dificultad, y después apareció en la orilla un negro anciano mal vestido,
con un gorro de lana en la cabeza, un palo largo y nudoso en la mano, que le servía de apoyo,
tal vez para no besar la tierra con la frente, pues tenía el cuerpo hecho un arco por la edad,
por los trabajos o por la costumbre inveterada de vivir en casas de techo bajo. Echó de ver
a los viajeros apenas salió del bosque, porque se detuvo un momento indeciso del partido que
debía tomar, y en soltando entre las altas yerbas algo que brillaba a los rayos del sol y parecía
botella u otra vasija por el estilo, después continuó andando derecho al carruaje por la parte
opuesta al bohío.

Esta circunstancia casual le salvó del primer choque de la ira de su amo, el cual, no bien
salió del bohío, le reconoció desde lejos y se lanzó sobre él a carrera tendida. Pero mientras
montó a caballo y salvó la distancia que le separaba de su intentada víctima, dio tiempo para
que éste se pusiera inconscientemente al amparo de las señoras. Lo probable es que el infeliz
esclavo no tuviese noticias de que aquellas personas eran esperadas en el ingenio, ni que entre
ellas viniese guiándolas su joven amo. A derechas no le conocía tampoco. Pero al notar que
se le venía encima a todo correr, y que gritaba:--¡Ah, perro! ¡Ahora lo verás!, no pudo desconocerle
ni dejar de caer de rodillas a los pies del caballo, quien, conteniéndose y todo, le echó a
rodar con el solo bote del pecho.

El susto de las señoras fue grande. Rosa hizo una exclamación de horror; doña Juana repitió:--¡Jesús!
¡Jesús! e Isabel medio que se incorporó en el asiento, sacó el brazo fuera del carruaje y dijo
más indignada que asustada:--¡No le mate, Leonardo!

--Agradecer debe que están Vds. delante, dijo Leonardo; de otro modo me parece que le mataba.
Tan indignado me siento contra él.

--¡Ah, mi suamito!, exclamó el viejo incorporándose trabajosamente hasta ponerse otra vez de
rodillas, como humildísimo pecador en presencia de su airado juez.

--¿Dónde te habías metido, perro brujo? le preguntó el joven, y sin aguardar por la respuesta
continuó preguntando o diciendo: ¿Qué hacías en el monte? ¿Por qué no estabas en tu bohío?
¿A que habías ido a cambalachar por aguardiente con el tabernero del pueblo la raspadura que
robas en el ingenio? Sí, sí. Lo juraría.

--¡No, mi suamito, no siñó, sumercé! ¡Caimán no roba rapaúra! ¡Caimán no bebe aguaurdiente!

--¡Cállate, perro viejo! Anda, corre a abrir la talanquera. ¿No corres todavía? ¿No sabes correr?
Ya haré que el Mayoral te avive un poco con el cuero. ¡Anda! ¡Vuela!... y trató de pegarle
(sin alcanzarle por fortuna) un puntapié en la cabeza desde el caballo.

Parecía ser el guardiero hombre de más de sesenta años de edad. Tenía al menos encanecida la
cabeza, y aun la escasa barba, que le cubría el labio superior, señal segura de vejez en las
gentes de su raza. A unos brazos desproporcionadamente largos y huesosos, unía dedos crispados,
cual si padeciese lepra; ojos chicos de expresión hosca y triste, nunca más triste que, cuando
después de abierta la talanquera, echó una mirada a las señoras del quitrín y pareció rogarles
le protegieran de la cólera de su amo.

Pasado el primer momento de irritación y de ceguedad, comprendió éste que había mostrado demasiado
apasionamiento y bastante grosería delante de señoras que, además de hallarse bajo su protección,
iban a disfrutar de su hospitalidad en el ingenio. El caballo había sido más generoso que él
puesto que, pudiéndolo, no atropelló al esclavo cuando le halló postrado en su camino. Tuvo
vergüenza Gamboa de su conducta, pero muy soberbio para reconocer su falta y enmendarla con
la franqueza que demandaba el caso, se limitó a referir los rasgos principales de la vida del
guardiero, por supuesto, calumniándole de paso.

--No se figuren Vds., dijo, que el taita Caimán es lo que parece, un viejo inerme y manso o
esclavo leal y humilde. Han de saber Vds. que el sobrenombre que lleva no se lo han puesto
a humo de paja; es lo más astuto, maligno, con ribetes de taimado que existe; ni tan ignorante
que no practique ciertas artes, que le dan importante consideración entre los suyos. Pasa por
brujo y por hacerse invisible cuando le conviene o se halla en peligro. Construye ídolos y
encantos que tienen propiedades mágicas en ciertos casos. Nadie diría que ve, oye ni entiende,
y sin embargo, tanto de día como de noche nada ni nadie se le escapa; y sabe, como el caimán,
hacerse el dormido para asegurar mejor la presa. La juventud la ha pasado en el monte huido,
y en sus repetidas fugas ha visitado todos los palenques del Cuzco y hecho amistad con los
negros cimarrones más famosos de la Vuelta Abajo. Ahora está muy viejo para tales trotes, y,
en consideración a haber sido uno de los fundadores del ingenio de La Tinaja, el único que
sobrevive de los que tumbaron aquí los primeros palos, mamá hizo que lo pusieran de guardiero,
y le conserva en ese puesto contra la opinión de los empleados que conocen su historia y sus
malas mañas. Cuando quiere o le conviene no le gana a vigilante ni el perro más fino. Puede
decirse que es libre: cría gallinas, engorda todos los años uno o dos cochinos que vende, y
entierra el dinero en alguna parte, y posee una yegua, en la cual puede dar vueltas de noche
a los linderos de la finca. Pero como digo, es muy taimado y maligno y apostaría cualquier
cosa a que no se hallaba lejos del bohío y de su puesto sin algún objeto doloso y reprobado
a la mira. Por el cañaveral se ve con sus compañeros del ingenio; por el monte sólo con los
cimarrones o con los taberneros del pueblo para cambiar azúcar por tabaco, aguardiente u otra
cosa por el estilo.

--Así debe de ser, Leonardo, comenzó diciendo Rosa, pues me pareció que traía una...

La tía y la hermana, más avisadas que ella, no la dejaron terminar la frase; y nadie más habló
en el resto del camino.

Entre la una y las dos de la tarde, bajo un sol de fuego cuyos rayos los reflejaban las hojas
de la caña cual si fueran bruñidas espadas, se desmontaron los viajeros en la gran casa de
vivienda de La Tinaja.

CAPÍTULO IV

     Lo más negro de la esclavitud
      no es el negro.

         JOSÉ DE LA LUZ Y CABALLERO

Bajo más de un concepto era una finca soberbia el ingenio de La Tinaja, calificativo que tenía
bien merecido por sus dilatados y lozanos campos de caña-miel, por los trescientos o más brazos
para cultivarlos, por su gran boyada, su numeroso material móvil, su máquina de vapor con hasta
veinticinco caballos de fuerza, recién importada de la América del Norte, el costo de veinte
y tantos mil pesos, sin contar el trapiche horizontal, también nuevo y que armado allí había
costado la mitad de aquella suma.

La casa de calderas o de ingenio era tan fuerte como vasta: edificio exento casi enteramente,
cuya armadura se componía de pares rollizos, apoyados en soleras pesadas y éstas en pilares,
dichos horcones en el país, sin escuadría ninguna ni más pulimento que el que pudo darles con
la zuela el vizcaíno carpintero-arquitecto contratado en la finca para esos trabajos. Tenía
el aire imponente y rústico que parecía demandar su destino. Debajo de su cubierta de tejas
coloradas se abrigaban el trapiche, la máquina de vapor y el tren Jamaiquino de elaborar el
azúcar, montado sobre tres hornos o fornallas. No se hallaban en el mismo nivel todos estos
aparatos: el de las calderas era varios pies más bajo; y para pasar de un departamento a otro
había que descender dos anchas escalinatas de piedra, flanqueando el plano del trapiche y máquina
de vapor. Esto se hacía así para que tuviese una caída fácil el guarapo, que al salir de las
masas corría por una canal de madera a la artesa, llamada allí mansera, donde algo se limpiaba
y seguía al tacho o paila para recibir el primer hervor.

Paralelo con este edificio había otro tan grande y más gacho, cerrado por sus costados con
paredes de mampostería y una sola entrada, haciendo frente a la parte de las calderas mencionadas.
Este era la casa para la purga y el secado del azúcar. En otros separados se hallaban la carpintería,
la herrería, la enfermería, y la que puede llamarse casa de maternidad; las habitaciones del
mayoral, del boyero, carpintero, mayordomo y maestro de azúcar, quien temporalmente residía
también en el ingenio. Para el maquinista, cuyo oficio a la sazón desempeñaba un joven americano,
se había construido una habitación provisional con tablas de cedro, cerca de la máquina de
vapor; único sitio abrigado en aquel feo caserón. Seguían después, formando grupo, sobre doscientas
cabañas o bohíos de paja, con sus correspondientes corrales y gallineros adjuntos, para la
morada de los trescientos esclavos, o dotación del ingenio. Las otras casas exentas, a saber:
las del bagazo, la de batir el barro para la purificación del azúcar, y otras de menos importancia,
se hallaban erigidas en el espacio medianero entre la de calderas y la de purga.

La planta de aquélla, denominada por antonomasia «de vivienda», figuraba en paralelogramo trapezoidad,
sentada en el suave declive de una colina, cuya diferencia de nivel se había procurado remediar
alzando el piso por el frente. Era de un solo cuerpo de fábrica de manipostería gruesa con
cubierta de tejas huecas coloradas, amplio pórtico, la sala cuadrada al medio, flanqueada a
ambos lados por dos crujías de cuartos, pasadizos corridos por el interior, patio rectangular
en el centro, cerrado por una tapia alta con caballete de vidrios, y una portada en el lienzo
del fondo, que se cerraba con cerrojo y cerradura y servía para la comunicación interior de
la servidumbre de la casa. En el patio crecían muchas flores, algunos naranjos, higueras y
parras, que no contribuían poco con su verdor y su sombrío a la frescura de los cuartos; aunque
para quebrar la reflexión de los rayos solares en puntos de medio día, habían puesto cortinas
de cañamazo en todo el derredor de los pasadizos. Arreglo igual se advertía en el pórtico,
que por su elevación y amplitud, se hallaba más expuesto a los embates del viento y a los efectos
desagradables de la reflexión solar en el extenso y desolado batey.

Desde lo alto de la escalinata del pórtico se registraba de un extremo a otro la casa de calderas
al frente, la de purga algo más a la derecha, aunque sólo por el lado de las gavetas para secar
el azúcar; el barracón de los negros o la estacada que encerraba sus habitaciones rústicas;
en suma, la mayor parte de las que componían la vasta población del ingenio; los campos de
caña hacia el oeste, los techos pajizos de las casas del potrero, y más allá un palmar inmenso,
un codo del río y luego la selva alterosa y primitiva, que formaba como el fondo oscuro de
este variado cuadro campestre.

Cosa del medio día del 24 de diciembre de 1830, arrellanados en cómodas butacas de vaqueta,
se hallaban los amos del ingenio en cómodas butacas de vaqueta colorada, se hallaban los amos
del ingenio La Tinaja, junto con otras varias personas, al abrigo de la reflexión solar, tras
las cortinas de cañamazo. Casi todos los caballeros, don Cándido Valdés, cura de Quiebra Hacha,
el capitán del partido y el médico fumaban tabaco; doña Rosa, la esposa del capitán antes dicho,
la mujer y cuñada del mayoral del potrero y las señoritas Gamboa, comían unas dulces cañas
de la tierra, otras, naranjas de China y guayaba del Perú, etc., productos éstos de la estancia
del ingenio. Por allí andaban nuestros conocidos de La Habana: Tirso, Aponte, Dolores, junto
con otra de las negras que habían venido por mar, y dos o tres más de la dotación del ingenio,
que por criollas y de mejor apariencia las habían destinado al servicio doméstico, todos haciéndose
útiles.

De las señoritas Gamboa, Carmen y Adela no calentaban asiento, picaban un pedazo de guayaba
o de naranja y emprendían luego largos paseos, enlazadas de las manos, de un extremo a otro
del pórtico, con manifiestas señales de impaciencia por la tardanza, a su juicio, de las amigas
de Alquízar. Adela en particular, cada vez que tocaba en el ángulo del sur, levantaba un canto
de cortina de cañamazo y echaba una ansiosa mirada por toda la guardarraya maestra adelante
hasta su intercepción en el camino de la Playa. Al fin, poco después de la una de la tarde,
se oyó a lo lejos ruido de ruedas de un carruaje y la marcha precipitada de varias caballerías;
y Adela, sin ver nada aún, exclamó alegre:--¡Ahí están!

No se engañó esta vez. A poco más llegaron al pie de la escalinata del pórtico las señoritas
Ilincheta en su carruaje, el cual, junto con sus ocupantes, los caballos y los jinetes, venían
cubiertos con el polvo de la tierra colorada. Inútil sería detenernos a describir punto por
punto las variadas escenas del encuentro de ambas familias en medio de las soledades de la
Vuelta Abajo. Más de un motivo había para que, al menos algunos de los presentes, mirasen aquel
instante como un evento verdadero, digno de nota. Sucede, además, que los jóvenes, y también
a veces las personas mayores, cuando se reúnen en un sitio de campo con ánimo de pasar sólo
unos días en franca y cordial sociedad, lejos de los lugares donde se han acostumbrado a vivir
y divertirse, se sienten fuertemente atraídos; si son amigos lo son y lo expresan más; si parientes,
se persuaden que los unen más estrechos lazos; si amantes, ¡ah!, su amor les parece eterno,
la dicha de amarse, celestial.

Las mujeres se estrecharon fuertemente entre los brazos. Adela lloró de alegría al apretar
entre los suyos a Isabel, por la cual sentía afición extraordinaria. Para ella era la más modesta
y amorosa de las mujeres. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02019</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>119481</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18339</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Each step was reason to engage
the attention of his enthusiastic friend, and telling the festoons of bonuses pending or white
bells of all the bushes on the banks of reeds, and Guines of reeds, which compared with the
egrets of countless martial warriors herding, gently rocked by the gentle breeze of the morning
prayer groups that Tomeguin low rumble, like a trailing wind and large crowds, followed by
some distance the direction of travelers, brushing with the herbs and then disappeared between
the logs of reeds or savanna lively late flight, which came with a crash in the thicket and
lighting with great difficulty on the first leaf of cane it faced in its heedless leakage,
or the elusive white heron made his way through the branches of coastal oak and with the long
neck retreated to the back and feet still dangling in his flight course the stream, or the
flock of parrots riots covering the wild orange and only they looked when they clung to the
golden fruit to extract the seed, or the hawk, in Finally, Cuba eagle, which gave sharp cries
and screams as she hovered above more affected palms, between earth and sky.

Finally, after ten o'clock in the morning, travelers crossed the reeds
of wit Valvanera, in view of their large factories.

Two miles later came to town Join bankruptcy. Here are divided into two the way they had, one that
twisted the west and was the Back Down the road, and the other, the narrow, which served as
input to refineries sugar, already established in this region of the coast. This took our travelers.
In passes through the town several people recognized and greeted with friendly respect for Leonardo
Gamboa.

Below the country presented itself as rough, uneven and hilly as the previous route, but The tree
was more lush and lusty, almost primitive, and noisy streams lined ground and clean running water
to be lost at the bottom of the bay of Mariel, or in the open sea North. After half an hour's
walk below the forest, where no sunlight penetrated, were seen in a sugar cane fields on the
steep slope of a hill, bounded by a fence Paperback made of segments, which kept horizontal strips
of wood or stakes fork kneeling on the ground and tied together at intervals, for safety, with a vine
that, when green, is quite flexible and elastic, known in the Tour Down with the name colorado
vulgar, Bauchinis heterophylla.

After that, continuing short, rough parallel to this close, at which time they won travelers
the height of the hill, were offered the full extent and greatness of cane fields and there
in the middle of the table, the group changed its factories, crowning other more plain and
hill wider base. That was the genius of a barrel, and Leonardo Gamboa, who served as guide, he
showed his friends with a sense of pride. To It had every reason, not only by the dollar value
representing the estate, and social considerations are kept to their owners, but also for the
beautiful picture and picturesque of the whole, provided a good distance, effectively concealing
spots and spots inherent in almost all the works, human and divine.

The road where passengers were boarding up there was called to the Beach because it served the
transportation of sugars to the town of Mariel, from which were shipped and led in schooners to
market in La Habana. Crossed the hill by its height and had established talanquera it no less a rustic
fence, it was reduced to a few yards in the rough, tucked their heads into the holes of two
parallel rails. Leaning against the fence, and in his meeting with the talanquera, stood a
cabin or hut of the ground rod or gabled, so droopy that the roof was composed of whole leaves
of the palm outstretched side or sides, with the tips resting on the ground.

Leonardo came forward to see why he was not in his job and opened the black watchman the talanquera.
To this end, he planted his horse before the only entrance to the hut, and tilting the body, tried
to register the interior. Useless work: the door was too narrow or mouth and low, and two feet
beyond the threshold could not penetrate human eyes, not by the living daylight out, but because
of the dense cloud of smoke from burning wood inside and not had other means of escape than
that.

- I do not see anything and I doubt there is a living soul in the
hut, Gamboa said talking with the ladies the chitin, standing in the
road.

Damn black!

- Maybe you sleep, "said Isabel.

- If not the sleep of death, "said Gamboa, I swear I did not save
someone from a face down.

- What is it?

Meneses said. How talanquera open? I will open and not lose the marriage so.

- You will not do so, Leonardo replied angrily. I do not agree.

- Well, his voice suggested Isabel Argentina and sweet.

Open the coachman, the horses are tired tired to run away.

Leocadio, Get down.

- No, no, Isabella, Leonardo said, more and more angry. I can not agree on that, I should not
spoil. If the watchman opens talanquera alive, that for that and
for more I have been there.

His watch and added immediately:

- They have already struck twelve, at which time the black loose to
eat.

If we had arrived here a little earlier, we would have heard the bell of the mill. Bet that
the Taita watchman has gotten into the reeds to meet with some of his ships. For the living
God pay! Nothing, not anywhere. Cayman! Cayman!, Cried the whole stream.

The mountains around were the only ones who gave back the echo of their voices shaking continued,
deep, sinister, and then started to bark a bulldog puppy in the hut. There is the watchman, he
thought the young man, and does not sleep for the trouble of opening the talanquera. I will go out
kicking, added high, taking a punch in the pommel. Dismounted without delay and went into the
hut, keeping the horse by the bridle.

Too bad these words rang in my ears those oaths of Elizabeth modest, even when not to embarrass
your friend or irritate more against the poor slave, was saved from represent the absurdity and even
the risk of their final purpose, if it was hidden on purpose to have hidden a fellow in the hut
or any other cause.

Fortunately, none of that happened. At that moment the ladies from the carriage, and coachman
Meneses horse heard the sound of branches in the nearby forest, agitated by a person or animal
made his way with some difficulty, and then appeared on the shore a shabby old black, a woolen
cap on his head, a long stick in his hand knotted, which served as support perhaps not kiss the
ground with his forehead, as his body made an arch by age, for the work or the inveterate habit
of living in houses with low ceilings. He perceived travelers out of the woods just because
time stopped for a party to indecisive should take, and in the tall grass releasing something that glittered
in the sun's rays, and seemed bottle or other container of the sort, then continued walking
right into the carriage by the opposite the hut.

This fortuitous circumstance saved the first match of the wrath of
his master, who, as soon left the hut, he recognized from a distance
and fell on him gallop.

But while mounted his horse and saved the distance that separated him from his attempted victim
had time to unconsciously it is put under the ladies.

It is likely that the unfortunate slave had no news that people were expected at the mill, or
come them came by guiding his young master. Right hand does not know
either.

But note that was coming at full speed, and cried: - Ah, you dog! Now I see!, Could not unknown
or stop his knees at the foot of the horse, who, contents and all, he threw boat ride to the
breast only.

The scare of the ladies was great. Rosa made an exclamation of horror,
Dona Juana repeated: - Jesus!

Jesus! and Isabel medium was incorporated into the seat, pulled out of the carriage arm and said
more angry than frightened - not kill him, Leonardo!

- Thank Vds. it that are ahead, "said Leonardo, otherwise I think he killed. I feel so angry
at him.

- Ah, my suamito!, Said the old man to be incorporating work again knees, as humble sinner in the
presence of his angry judge.

- Where were you, dog witch? asked the young man, and without waiting for the answer continued asking
or saying, "What were you doing in the bush? Why were not you at your hut? What you had gone to swap
for tavern liquor with the scraping of the people that steal in the mill? Yes, yes. I swear.

-
No, my suamito, but no, sumercé! Cayman Rapaura not steal! Cayman aguaurdiente not drink!

- Shut up, you old dog! Walk, run to open the talanquera. Do not run yet? Do not you run? The
Mayoral and you'll stir up a little leather. Go!

Fly! ... and tried to hit (Fortunately without hitting) a kick in the head from the horse.

Seemed
to be the watchman man over sixty years of age. He's graying at least head, and even the little
beard that covered his upper lip, a sure sign of aging in people of his race. A disproportionately
long arms and bony, twitching fingers linked, as if with leprosy, eyes sullen boys and sad, sadder
than ever, when talanquera after open, glanced at the ladies of chitin and appeared to beg
protect him from the wrath of his master.

After the first moment of irritation and blindness, realized he had been too passionate and quite
rude in front of women who, besides being under its protection, would enjoy their hospitality
at the mill. The horse had been more generous than he since, being able to not hit the slave
when he found him lying in his path. Had Gamboa ashamed of his behavior, but very proud to
recognize his fault and amend it with openness demanded by the case, merely to refer the main
features of life watchman, of course, slandering of way.

- Not included DVDs, said that the Taita Cayman is as it seems, an old helpless and meek or
loyal and humble slave. Vds. must know that the nickname has not it have been smoke with straw
is the most cunning, evil, cunning trimmed there, nor so ignorant does not practice certain
arts, which give important consideration among his people. Passes witch and become invisible
when it suits or is in danger. Build idols charms have magical properties in certain cases.
Nobody would see, hear or understand, and yet, day and night no one and nothing escapes him,
and know, like the alligator, play possum to better secure the dam.

The youth has been spent on the mountain fled and his repeated escapes
runaway has visited all of Cuzco and made friends with Maroons most
famous Vuelta Abajo.

It is now too old for such jogging, and considered to have been one of the founders of La Tinaja,
the only that survives of the first poles knocked down here, Mom
had him put the watchman, and keeps him in that position against the
wishes of employees who know their history and bad habits.

When you want or should not beaten the dog guard or finer. Can said to be free: raising chickens,
fat every year one or two pigs to sell, and money buried somewhere, and has a mare, which
may turn at night to the boundaries of the property.

But as I say, is very cunning and evil and I'd bet any thing that
was not far from the hut and its position without any intentional
object and failed to look.

     For the cane is seen with his
      fellow wits, for the mount only with Maroons or the bartenders of
the people to change snuff sugar, brandy or other anything like that.

-
That must be, Leonardo, Rosa began by saying, as I thought it brought
a ...

The aunt and sister, plus she advised, would not let her finish
the sentence, and no one else spoke in the rest of the road.

         

Between one and two in the afternoon, under a blazing sun's reflected rays whose leaves cane if
they were polished swords, passengers were cleared in the big house The Tinaja housing.

CHAPTER IV

Most black of slavery is not black.

JOSE DE LA LUZ Y CABALLERO

Under more than one farm concept was a superb wit The Tinaja, qualifier was well deserved for
his long and lush fields of sugar cane-honey, for the three hundred or more arms to cultivate,
for his great drove of oxen, and his vast rolling, his steam up twenty-five horses of force,
newly imported from North America, the cost of twenty and many thousand dollars, excluding the
horizontal mill, also new and there were armed cost half of that sum.

The boiler house or wit was as strong as vast, almost entirely exempt building, whose armor was
made up of pairs logs, supported by heavy sills and these pillars,
those pitchforks in the country, without squaring no more polish and
that he could give to zuela Biscayan the carpenter-architect hired
by the farm for such work.

Had stunning and rustic air that seemed to claim his destiny. Under her roof tiles red were
entertained the mill, the steam train and develop the Jamaican sugar, mounted on three ovens or fornallas.
Were not at the same level all these equipment: the boiler was several feet lower, and to move from one
department to another had to descend two broad stone steps, flanking the level of mill and machine
steam. This was done so for it to have an easy drop the juice, which on leaving the running
masses by a wooden trough to trough, here called Mansehra, where something was cleaned and followed
the pan or pot to receive the first boil.

Parallel with this building was another big and more down, shut down by its sides with masonry
walls and a single entrance, facing the boiler mentioned. This was the house for draining and
drying of sugar. In other woodwork were separated, blacksmithing, nursing and the house can be called
maternity rooms overseer, the stockman, carpenter, foreman and master
of sugar, who is temporarily residing also wit.

To the engineer, whose office at that time played a young American, had built a temporary room with cedar
boards, near the machine steam only warm place in that ugly old house. Followed later formed a
group, over two hundred thatched cottages or huts, with their pens and chicken coops attached
to the abode of the three hundred slaves, or endowment of wit. The other houses exempt, namely:
those of bagasse, beat the mud to the purification of sugar and other less important were erected
in the space mediator between the boiler and drain.

The former plant, known as the quintessential "housing" contained in trapezoid parallelogram,
sitting on the gentle slope of a hill, the difference of level was sought to remedy raising the
floor by the front. Was a single body with thick masonry factory hollow red tile roof, wide porch,
square room in the middle, flanked on both sides by two bays of rooms, corridors run by the
interior, rectangular patio in the center, enclosed by a high wall with casement windows, and a cover
on the canvas the fund, which closed with a lock and lock and was
used for internal communication the servants of the house.

In the courtyard grew many flowers, orange trees, fig and vines that did not contribute little to
its greenery and the freshness of dark rooms, although to break the reflection of sunlight in midday
points, had made curtains All burlap around those passages. As cautioned under the porch, to
its elevations and breadth, was more exposed to the ravages of wind and the effects nasty
solar reflection in the vast and desolate batey.

From the top of the steps of the portico was recorded from one extreme
to another the boiler house front, the more drain on the right, but
only on the side of the drawers to dry sugar, the barracks of blacks
or the stockade that enclosed its rustic rooms; In short, most of
which comprised the vast population of wit, the fields of cane to
the west, the straw roofs of the houses of pasture, and beyond that
a huge palm, a bend of the river and then altered and primitive jungle,
which was like the dark background this varied table setting.

Cosa noon on December 24, 1830, sprawled in comfortable chairs of cowhide they were the masters
of ingenuity in red cowhide easy chairs, were the masters The Tinaja wit, along with several others,
sheltered from solar reflection, after canvas curtains. Almost all the men, Don Candido Valdez,
pastor of Bankruptcy Axe Captain of the party and the doctor smoking snuff, Dona Rosa, the
wife of the captain before, women's and sister's mayoral ladies paddock and Gamboa, ate some candy
canes land, others, orange guava China and Peru, etc., the products they stay wit. Roamed around
our famous of Havana: Tirso, Aponte, Dolores, along with another black who had come by sea, and
two or three more of the endowment of wit, Creole and that they had better look for domestic service,
making all useful.

In the ladies Gamboa, Carmen and Adela not heated seat, biting a piece of guava or orange and then
undertook long walks, linked hands, from one extreme to another the porch, with obvious signs
of impatience at the delay, in his view, the friendly Alquízar. Adela in particular, every
time he touched the corner of the south, stood a song canvas curtain and cast an anxious glance
across the front master guardarraya until interception on the road from the beach. Finally, shortly
after one o'clock in the afternoon, was heard in the distance sound
of carriage wheels and the sudden departure of several horses; and
Adela, seeing nothing yet, said cheerfully: - There they are!

Do not be fooled this time. A little more than reached the foot of the steps of the portico
ladies Ilincheta in his carriage, which, along with their passengers, horses and riders came
covered with red dust of the earth. Useless would stop and describe point about the various scenes
of the meeting of both families in the midst of the solitude of the Vuelta Abajo. More than
one reason was so that at least some of those present, that mirasen moment as a real event
worthy of note. It happens also that young people, and also Sometimes older people, when they
meet at a field site with the intention to pass only few days in open and friendly society, far from
the places where they have been accustomed to living and have fun, feel strongly attracted,
if friends are and express it more, if relatives are persuaded that
closer ties together, if lovers, ah, love seems eternal the joy of
loving, heavenly.

Women narrowed sharply between the arms. Adela cried with joy when
tightening among his Elizabeth, for whom he had an extraordinary passion.
For it was the most modest and loving women</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>