<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03420</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>8597</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24506</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Puse la gumía sobre la mesa de noche. La puse allí con
mucho tiento y temblando de que mi mujer se despertase. Volví a mirar a Beatriz. La miré como
quien mira el tesoro que ha perdido. Todo su valer, toda su belleza, todo su hechizo fulguró
ante mis ojos con más brillo que nunca. ¿Qué bastarda dulzura, qué amor sin honra y sin vergüenza,
qué afecto villano me emponzoñó en aquel instante el corazón y corrió por mis venas con mi
perversa sangre? Ello es que enjugué mis lágrimas, bajé la cabeza con lentitud y suavidad,
y sin rozar apenas con los labios, besé sus mejillas sonrosadas.

»Por fortuna se realizó en mí la reacción. El ultraje recibido se ofreció a mi espíritu. Me
llené de rubor. Tuve vergüenza; tuve asco de mi flaqueza.

»La idea de matar a Beatriz me solicitó de nuevo la voluntad indecisa. Empuñé el hierro nuevamente.
Nuevamente retrocedí espantado.

»Huí del cuarto; huí de la casa como un ladrón. Abrí ambas puertas con las llaves que había
guardado, cerrando luego cuidadosamente. Me encontré en la calle.

»¿Qué hacer? Yo me veía ridículo. No podía sufrirme. En mitad de la calle me dió un ataque
de risa nerviosa. Si alguien me oyó debió tomarme por loco.

»Multitud de pensamientos encontrados, y todos tristísimos, cruzaban por mi mente; pasaban
y volvían con persistencia cruel.

»Por un breve momento insistí en imaginar aún que podría ser calumnia la delación anónima,
pero pronto huyó de mí esta idea consoladora. Es la única que no ha vuelto.

»¿Qué solución tenía la crisis en que me hallaba? ¿Acaso había yo de asesinar a mi mujer? ¿Acaso
había yo de asesinar a su amante?

»No; no era debilidad mía: yo me sentía con ánimos para matar a alguien que hubiera venido
en aquel punto a robarme el reloj o los pocos reales que en el bolsillo llevaba; pero quizá
por una perversión moral, no podía yo considerar de ladrón al que me robaba la dicha, el amor
de mi mujer y la limpia honra de mi casa. El reloj y el dinero son mi propiedad, no tienen
libre albedrío; no se van con el ladrón y me dejan porque le prefieren, mientras Beatriz se
iba con otro y me dejaba porque le prefería. El hacía bien en llevársela. ¿Por qué había yo
de asesinarle por esto? ¿Qué me debe él a mí para respetar mi felicidad y desatender la suya?

»Deseché, pues, de mi alma el pensamiento de asesinar a mi rival. Juzgándole en el tribunal
de mi conciencia, yo no le absolvía, pero reconocía la incompetencia del tribunal. Yo no le
absolvía por ser yo el agraviado. Si el agraviado hubiera sido un indiferente, le hubiera absuelto.
Podía, pues, matarle, no como justicia, sino como venganza.

»Entonces pensé en el duelo; pero ¿cómo pelear ni con espadas ni con pistolas que en la vida
he tomado en las manos? Me repugnaba además la idea de darme antes por ofendido; de reclamar
igualdad de condiciones y de probabilidades para vengar mi agravio; de confesar mi torpeza
en las armas y mi incapacidad; de apelar a no sé qué medios para forzar a un rival dichoso
a que se pusiera de suerte enfrente de mí, que yo, flaco, viejo y enfermizo pudiera matarle,
siendo él joven, ágil y robusto.

»Ni el asesinato ni el duelo eran posibles. Otro hombre que no fuese yo se separaría para siempre
de su mujer. No había partido más conforme a la razón. Yo, sin embargo, no podía seguirle.
Yo no viviré lejos de ella. Es horrible, es estúpido, es monstruoso, pero yo la amo; seguiré
amándola siempre. Sin su amor, el mundo será un desierto para mí; la vida, soledad medrosa;
mi corazón, un vacío que con nada se llenará.

»El alma humana necesita amar, adorar, creer. El cielo ha castigado la soberbia de mi alma.
De ella han sido arrojados ídolos, altares, todo ser digno de adoración y de amor. En cambio,
puse mi adoración, mi amor, mi fe y mi esperanza en Beatriz. Ella era... es mi idolatría.

»El amor del descreído es inmenso. El descreído consagra a un objeto despreciable toda la fuerza
de amor con que procura el creyente elevarse a su ideal divino.

»En fin, ¿para qué cansarte? He vagado como una fiera mansa que lleva clavado en el pecho un
dardo envenenado. De noche he vagado; de día he estado oculto. Tengo vergüenza de que la gente
me vea. Se me antoja que todos conocen la burla de que soy víctima, mi paciencia, mi amor mal
pagado, y que van a reír al verme o van a escupirme a la cara.

»Anoche llegó mi ridiculez a último extremo.

»Ya no cabe la menor duda. Yo andaba en torno de mi casa, y cerca de las cuatro de la mañana
vi que salía un hombre... misteriosamente... de allí. Tengo ojos de lince... le vi... era él.
Llevaba yo un revólver en el bolsillo. ¿Para qué? Si hubiera disparado los seis tiros que tiene,
ninguno hubiera dado a mi enemigo. No sé tirar, y además me temblaba la mano. Todo yo estaba
convulso.

»Además, ¿por qué no confesarlo? Creo que yo no sería capaz de matarle, aunque le hallase dormido
y pudiese poner a mansalva el cañón del revólver en una de sus sienes.

»No comprendo ya más que una cosa. No puedo sufrir mi amor inextinguible. No puedo sufrir la
ridiculez que en mí noto. Hasta la poesía de un gran dolor no es dable en mí, porque me río
yo mismo de mi dolor y le hallo cómico.

»No me queda más recurso, si no muero buenamente, que buscar modo de morir cuanto antes.

»Perdona este largo desahogo. Perdona esta prolija carta. Será la última. Adiós.»

Paco Ramírez era un hombre de cierta ilustración y de claro entendimiento; pero le tenía aún
más sano que claro; le tenía tan sano como su cuerpo, que era el de un atleta. Paco amaba a
don Braulio, aunque era quien más le había siempre echado en cara que se pasase de listo, que
tuviese maneras de pensar que él calificaba de tortuosas y que se hiciese víctima de los más
alambicados y singulares sentimientos.

Apenas leyó la carta, creyó que Braulio estaba loco. No podía creer la falta de doña Beatriz:
tan buena opinión tenía de ella. Imaginó al punto que la persona de quien andaba celoso Braulio
era el Conde, de quien Beatriz le hablaba en su carta. Fuese como fuese, Paco temió una catástrofe.
Pensó en que Braulio, o se iba a morir, o se iba a matar, o se iba a Leganés. A fin de evitarlo,
si era tiempo, se puso inmediatamente en camino para Madrid. Braulio no le había dado señas,
pero él le hallaría. Si no llegaba a salvarle, llegaría a vengarle. Paco no se andaba con metafísicas
ni discreteos. No pensaba ni en asesinatos a traición ni en duelos de toda ceremonia. Sólo
pensaba en sacar el amor y hasta el alma del Condesito de su gallardo cuerpo a mojicones y patadas.

Con tan buenos propósitos, ansioso además de ver a su Inesita, y con esperanzas de enamorarla
y de traérsela al lugar, a las treinta y dos horas no cabales de haber recibido y leído la
lamentable carta de su desesperado amigo, llegó Paco a esta heroica y coronada villa, y sin
sacudir siquiera el polvo del camino, después de dejar la maletilla en una casa de huéspedes,
y de instalarse, tomando cuarto en ella, se dirigió a la vivienda de las dos lindas hermanas.

XX

Conforme iba Paco Ramírez hacia dicha vivienda, aunque muy apresuradamente, se ofrecían a su
imaginación con mayor viveza todas las dificultades de la entrevista que debía tener.

En la carta de don Braulio recordaba los párrafos más siniestros y ominosos, y preveía alguna
desgracia. Hasta una contradicción que había notado en la carta le daba entonces mucho que
sospechar. Don Braulio confesaba al principio, como era cierto, que jamás usaba ni llevaba
armas, y hacia el fin de la carta hablaba de un revólver que tenía en el bolsillo. Paco Ramírez
veía claro que don Braulio le había comprado o le había adquirido en aquellos días, después
de la noche que estuvo de oculto en su casa. ¿Para qué esta adquisición? ¿Qué pensaba hacer
su desventurado amigo?

Paco estaba cierto de que don Braulio no mataría ni a su mujer ni a su rival, pero tenía miedo
de que atentase a su propia vida, y ya pensaba en vengarle matando al Condesito.

Era Paco tan fuerte, tan sereno, y estaba tan seguro de sí, que nada le parecía más fácil.

En cuanto a doña Beatriz, Paco la amaba como a una hermana y la respetaba como a un ser superior,
por donde, aunque le afligiese mucho el creerla culpada, como ya la creía, estaba dispuesto
a perdonarle la culpa. En este punto comprendía y aplaudía y hasta bendecía la debilidad o
la ternura de don Braulio. Lo que no se explicaba es que don Braulio no tratase de vengarse
del Condesito de cualquier modo que fuese.

Entre tanto, ¿qué iba él a hacer, qué iba a decir en casa de doña Beatriz? Después de reflexionarlo,
formar varios planes y componer mentalmente varios discursos, determinó dejarse guiar de la
inspiración del momento e improvisarlo todo.

Así llegó a casa de don Braulio. Subió los escalones de dos en dos y tiró del cordón de la
campanilla. Eran las nueve de la mañana.

En seguida le abrieron, con aquella franqueza y prontitud con que suelen abrir los pobres.

Apenas tuvo tiempo de ver quién le abría. Se encontró ceñido por unos brazos que le estrechaban
y abrumado por una boca que cubría sus mejillas de un diluvio de sonoros besos.

--¡Válgame Dios, hombre!--dijo al cabo el ama Teresa, que era quien le besaba--. ¡Cómo has
embarnecido en estos tres años! Da gloria verte: estás hecho un real mozo. Pero díme, ¿y don
Braulio? ¿Viene contigo? ¿Qué ha hecho en el lugar? ¿Por qué no escribe? Beatriz está con el
alma en un hilo.

--Quiero verla. ¿Puedo verla?--dijo Paco.

--Ahora mismo. Entra. ¿Traes noticias de don Braulio?

--Sí.

--Pues entra.

--¿Está Inés con su hermana?

--Inés no se ha levantado aún.

--Mejor--dijo Paco--. Necesito ver a Beatriz a solas--añadió entre dientes.

Antes de que acabara de murmurar esta frase, antes de que entrara en el saloncito de doña Beatriz,
apareció ésta en la antesala, y asiendo cordial y apretadamente las manos de Paco entre las
suyas, exclamó:

--¿Qué es esto? ¿Y Braulio? ¿Dónde está? ¿Cómo no viene contigo? Estoy llena de zozobra. ¿Qué
sucede, Dios mío? ¿Qué sucede?

Hablando así, entraron ambos en el salón. El ama Teresa fué tras ellos.

--Déjanos, Teresa. Luego vendrás. Tengo que hablar con Beatriz--dijo Paco.

Este misterio pareció aumentar el sobresalto de la linda muchacha.

El ama Teresa salió de la sala regañando.

Ya solos Paco y Beatriz, dijo ésta:

--¿Qué misterios son los tuyos? ¿Qué me vas a decir? Habla. Todo es mejor que la ansiedad,
que la duda en que me tienes. Mi mal no será más horrible, mi desventura no será más honda
en realidad que lo que me finge ya la fantasía. Habla. ¿Dónde está mi marido? ¿Qué hiciste
de él? ¿Por qué no viene en tu compañía?

--Tu marido no ha ido al lugar. Mal puede venir conmigo. Tu marido no ha salido de Madrid.
Aquí está. Aquí vengo a buscarle.

--Es imposible. Braulio no miente nunca. Braulio me dijo que iba a verte. Le habrá ocurrido
alguna desgracia en el camino. Estará enfermo, muerto quizá en algún pueblo del trayecto. Braulio
fué a verte. Braulio no me ha engañado.

Paco Ramírez, que no era hombre muy dado a perífrasis y rodeos, y que además creía que era
urgente e indispensable una pronta explicación, dijo entonces:

--Braulio te ha engañado porque creía que tú le engañabas.

--No puede ser--respondió Beatriz, subiendo la roja sangre a sus mejillas--. ¿Quién ha inventado
esa infamia? ¿Quién ha dicho esa locura?

--El mismo Braulio.

--¿Cómo? ¿Cuándo? ¿Dónde le has visto?

--No le he visto. He recibido carta suya.

--Dámela. Quiero leerla.

--¿Tendrás valor para leerla?

--Dios me dará valor para todo. Dame tú la carta.

Paco vacilaba aún.

--Dame la carta--volvió a decir doña Beatriz.

--Te la daré--contestó Paco--; pero antes exijo de ti una cosa.

--Dí, pide pronto.

--Vas a responder con sinceridad a lo que te pregunte: vas a declararme la verdad desnuda:
no como si respondieses a tu hermano, sino como si respondieses a tu propia conciencia; como
si estuvieses ante el tribunal del Eterno y fuese El quien te interrogase.

--Pregunta. No receles. No manchará mis labios la mentira.

--¿Amas a Braulio?

--Con todo mi corazón.

--Braulio es feo y tú hermosa. Braulio es viejo... ¿Le amas de amor?

--El alma de Braulio es hermosa; el alma de Braulio es inmortalmente joven. Sí; le amo de amor.

--¿No has amado nunca a otro hombre?

--Nunca.

--Mira bien en el fondo de tu alma. Beatriz, ¿no has amado nunca a otro hombre?

--Apenas comprendo lo que me quieres decir; pero no ha de quedarme el menor escrúpulo. Voy
a escudriñar en el abismo más hondo de mi mente; voy a buscar allí y a hacerte patentes mis
más ocultos pensamientos; las ideas vagas y confusas de que yo misma no me he dado cuenta hasta
ahora.

--Dí, Beatriz.

--Digo que nunca amé de amor sino a mi marido; que no creo haberle faltado una sola vez, ni
con el más fugaz pensamiento, ni con el más efímero deseo mal nacido.

--¿Es cierto lo que dices? ¿No te acusa la conciencia de la menor falta?

--¿Cómo he de declararme impecable? Paco, sí; la conciencia me acusa, pero no me atormenta;
dame la carta: acabemos. ¡Qué interrogatorio! ¡Qué dilaciones crueles! ¿Has venido a matarme?

--No, Beatriz. Díme, sin embargo, ¿de qué te acusa la conciencia?

--Soy vanidosa, lo confieso. Ahora que presiento una desventura, veo que es pecado lo que yo
no creía que lo fuese. Yo misma me examino, me juzgo y me condeno. Mira, Paco: yo he creído
que un hombre me amaba, y, aunque no pagaba su amor, me complacía y me enorgullecía de que
me amase. Su amor estaba de tal suerte refrenado por el respeto, que jamás se mostró en palabras.
Yo le adivinaba; no le veía. Y yo le adivinaba, no como pasión que tuviese en sí la menor impureza,
sino como sentimiento etéreo, inmaculado, que no es amor, ni es amistad; que no ha de tener
nombre; que es inefable en todo lenguaje de la tierra; que si tiene nombre ha de ser en el
cielo. ¿Qué quieres? Vanidad de mujer. Novelas ridículas que nosotras nos forjamos en la imaginación
y que, sin duda, no tienen realidad alguna. El hombre que así me acata, el hombre que así me
considera y admira, es el más discreto, el más elegante de la aristocracia de Madrid; es celebrado
por su gentil presencia, por su gracia, por su valentía y hasta por sus conquistas amorosas.
Al verle tan rendido conmigo, al notar lo que se deleitaba en oírme hablar, lo que celebraba
mi talento, lo que se afanaba por agradarme y porque yo tuviese de él el mejor concepto, no
lo niego, mi orgullo de mujer estaba muy lisonjeado. Juzgaba yo valer más, cuando había inspirado
tan noble afecto a aquel hombre. Mi propia vanidad me movía a formar a mi vez un concepto,
quizá exagerado, de todas sus prendas personales. Aquel hombre, que también, en mi sentir,
me comprendía, valía mucho más a mis ojos. La gratitud hacia aquel hombre en mis momentos de
modestia, cuando yo creía que yo no se lo debía todo a mi propio mérito, llenaba mi corazón.
Jamás, sin embargo, le he amado. Todas las noches, desde hace meses, hablo con él más de una
hora en voz baja. Me elogia, me dice mil corteses rendimientos; pero de amor no me habla. Entre
él y yo existen tácitamente estas extraordinarias relaciones. ¿Es esto pecado? ¡Ah! Yo creo
que sí. Ahora creo que sí. Me lo dice el corazón. Braulio está celoso. Pero, Dios mío, ¿por
qué no me lo ha dicho? ¿Por qué no se ha quejado? Yo le hubiera pedido perdón. Yo le hubiera
repetido mil veces que le amaba. Yo le hubiera renovado mis juramentos. Yo hubiera puesto término
a la insana poesía, a la soñada historia que sólo a mi vanidad satisfacía. Pero no: Braulio
tiene razón, Braulio es delicado. Un marido no debe tener celos. No debe decir a su mujer que
sospecha de ella. Sería una indignidad, una vergüenza de que él no es capaz. Y yo, necia, ciega,
que no he comprendido hasta hoy lo peligroso y absurdo de mi conducta. ¿Quién sabe? Tal vez
los maldicientes lo han entendido todo de la peor manera. Tal vez han mancillado mi honra y
la de mi marido. Tal vez han tenido al cabo la crueldad de acusarme. Vamos, Paco; ya lo sabes
todo. No me mates. Dame la carta. ¡Pronto! Dame la carta.

Paco, sin responder palabra, sin saber qué pensar de todo aquello, no atreviéndose a creer
que Beatriz mentía, no atinando a explicarse cómo se mintiese tan bien, y recordando, no obstante,
que en la carta de Braulio había pruebas casi evidentes de que Beatriz era culpada, le entregó
por último la carta.

Beatriz la desdobló con ansia, y no la leyó, la devoró.

No interrumpió la lectura, ni con un suspiro, ni con una exclamación, ni con una queja. Se
puso alternativamente colorada y pálida. Mortal palidez prevaleció al cabo. Gruesas lágrimas
brotaron de los hermosos y negros ojos de Beatriz y se deslizaron por sus mejillas.

El silencio era completo. Se podían contar los latidos violentos del corazón de Beatriz y del
corazón de Paco.

Otra mujer, culpada o no culpada, hubiera fingido un desmayo, se hubiera desmayado de veras
o hubiera hecho extremos con sollozos, con gemidos y aun con gritos tal vez.

Beatriz, leída la carta, conocido ya todo el infortunio de su marido y el suyo, si es que a
su marido estimaba, contuvo toda explosión vehemente de dolor, y dijo a Paco de esta manera:

--Reconozco mi delito. Reniego de mi estúpido engreimiento, de mi afán de lucir, de mi deseo
liviano de ser admirada; pero no basta todo ello para explicar esta desventura. Soy víctima
de una trama infernal; de una serie de coincidencias fatales. ¿Quién sabe, Dios mío? ¿Quién
sabe? Pero es muy duro, es tremendo, es cruel el castigo que cae sobre mi cabeza. ¿Por qué
no me mató? ¿Por qué tuvo compasión de mí? Yo hubiera despertado al sentirme herida. Yo le
hubiera perdonado. ¿Qué digo... le hubiera perdonado? Yo le hubiera pedido perdón y hubiera
sido dichosa muriendo en sus brazos. ¡Cuánto me ama! Este amor sí que vale. En este amor sí
que debiera yo haber cifrado siempre mi orgullo. ¿Por qué le he descuidado, hasta perderle
tal vez, desvanecida yo, loca, atolondrada por una vanidad mezquina? Y él me besó mientras
yo dormía, en vez de matarme, como yo merecía de veras. Vino a darme de puñaladas y me dió
besos de amor, y lloró de ternura, y me halló hermosa y me contempló extasiado. Paco, hermano
mío; corre, ve al Ministerio, ve a todas partes, búscale; díle que le amo; tráele vivo a mis
brazos; devuélvemele para que me perdone. ¿Qué haré, Jesús mío? ¿Qué haré? Estoy por salir
a buscarle yo misma, como loca. Sólo me detiene el temor de que sean mayores el escándalo y
la vergüenza. Hermano mío, por piedad, corre; busca a Braulio. Temo, tiemblo por su vida. ¡Qué
horror! El no me ha dado muerte: él me ha besado, creyéndose mortalmente ofendido. Y, en pago
de tanto amor, yo le mato.

Paco estaba mudo, extático, lleno de asombro, con la boca abierta, y sin saber qué pensar ni
qué decir.

Beatriz, con más agitación, contrariada, impaciente por la inmovilidad de Paco, prosiguió de
esta suerte:

--No te detengas: vuela, busca a Braulio. Se va a matar si te tardas. Díle pronto que le amo,
que le idolatro; que su beso vale más que todas las satisfacciones y vanaglorias; que su amor
me enamora; que la belleza divina de su alma excede para mí a toda la belleza de las demás
criaturas de Dios. ¡Que yo le vuelva a ver, cielos santos! ¡Que yo me arroje a sus plantas
y le pida mil veces perdón! ¡Que yo le pague el beso que me dió dormida, exhalando mi alma,
infundiéndola en la suya con un beso eterno... infinito!

Mientras Beatriz hablaba, iba empujando a Paco fuera del saloncito; le iba echando a empellones
de la casa.

Ya en la antesala, Beatriz añadió:

--Ve al Ministerio; acude a la policía; busca a Braulio por todos los medios, no te detengas.

Paco salió al fin de su mutismo, y contestó:

--Sosiégate, Beatriz, yo le encontraré. Pronto estaré aquí de vuelta. No lo dudes: le traeré
conmigo. Ten confianza en la bondad de Dios.

Dicho esto, abrió la puerta, salió de la habitación y bajó precipitadamente la escalera.

Doña Beatriz volvió vacilando y tropezando hasta la sala. No podía ya sostenerse. Cayó desplomada
en el sofá.

Después de un instante de calma y de silencio, rompió en gemidos y sollozos y vertió un mar
de lágrimas.

Acudió entonces el ama Teresa.

--¿Qué te pasa, hija? ¿Por qué lloras?

--Déjame, ama, déjame--contestó doña Beatriz--. Soy la más desventurada de las mujeres.

El ama Teresa insistió en vano en idénticas o semejantes preguntas.

Beatriz no le contestaba sino rogándole que la dejase.

Cansada, pues, y hasta algo picada de aquel sigilo con que de ella se recataba Beatriz, el
ama Teresa se salió de la sala y se fué al cuarto de Inesita.

--Niña--dijo--, ¿no te levantas hoy?

Inesita, medio dormida aún, si bien tenía abiertas ya las maderas de la ventana, y el sol inundaba
su cuarto, se incorporó un poco y contestó:

--Pues ¿qué hora es?

--Las nueve y media; cerca de las diez. De sobra es hora de que te levantes. Además es menester
que te levantes. Hay grandes novedades. Paco Ramírez ha venido.

--¿Con mi cuñado?--preguntó Inés.

--Sin tu cuñado--dijo el ama.

--¿Y dónde está? ¿Se quedó en el lugar? ¿Por qué no viene?

--Lo ignoro. Sólo sé que tu hermana está llorando como jamás la he visto llorar. Sin duda ha
ocurrido alguna gran desgracia. Beatriz nada ha querido decirme; pero algo ocurre de muy grave
y lastimoso. Levántate, hija. Ve a consolar a tu hermana y a saber la causa de su dolor.

Inesita saltó de la cama llena de sobresalto. Se puso una bata, sin atender a más cuidado,
por la precipitación, y corrió al saloncito, donde Beatriz se hallaba.

XXI

--¿Qué tienes, hermana? ¿Por qué lloras?--preguntó Inesita con mucho cariño apenas entró en
el saloncito y vió a Beatriz tan afligida.

Como Beatriz no le contestase y siguiese llorando, Inesita se inclinó sobre el sofá en que
estaba echada Beatriz, y volvió a hacerle las mismas preguntas, acompañadas de besos y caricias.

Beatriz no pudo ya resistirse; sentía además necesidad de desahogar su corazón, e incorporándose
y teniendo a Inés a su lado, dijo con un suspiro:

--¡Qué desgraciada soy, Inés!

--¿Qué sucede?--interrumpió ésta.

--Que por mi culpa Braulio está celoso y se ha ido de casa y puede que no vuelva más.

--¿Y de quién tiene celos?

--Tiene celos del Conde de Alhedín.

--¡Vaya un desatino!--dijo Inesita--. Pues qué, ¿no ve claro que el Conde no tiene por ti mas
que mera amistad?

--Eso no--dijo candorosamente Beatriz, la cual, en medio de todo, amando a don Braulio, llena
de sobresalto por él, y arrepentida de su intimidad con el Conde, no podía conformarse con
que el Conde no estuviese enamorado de ella.

--Eso no; yo creo que el Conde me ama; pero yo no le he amado nunca.

--Singular idea tienes del Conde, hermana. Créeme, hombres como él no aman sin ser amados.
El Conde te distingue, te aprecia, te halla linda y agradable y discreta, y por eso habla contigo.
Como es muy galante, te hace doscientos mil elogios; pero de ahí al amor hay una distancia
infinita.

--¿Y quién te asegura que no ha salvado él esa distancia?--preguntó Beatriz.

--Nadie me lo asegura--contestó Inés--; pero yo lo supongo. En todo caso, lo mejor es que no
te ame. ¿Habías tú de amarle?

--No.

--Pues entonces, ¿para qué querías esa víctima?

--Yo no quería... ni dejaba de querer... no se trataba aquí de lo que yo quería, sino de lo
que era. El Conde estaba asiduo conmigo, y yo, lo confieso, me complacía en sus asiduidades.
No le amaba; pero sentía una satisfacción de amor propio en creerme amada por él. Esto me ha
perdido.

--Vamos, hermana, tranquilízate. Nadie se pierde por tan poco. Si tu marido tiene celos, con
explicarle que no hay motivo para que los tenga, estará todo terminado.

--¿Y cómo se lo explico? ¿Dónde podré verle? ¿No te he dicho que se fué y no volverá más? Quizá
se mate.

--Tales cosas me dices que empiezas a ponerme en cuidado, aunque no soy de las que se ahogan
en poca agua. Braulio es suspicaz y caviloso; Braulio te adora; Braulio tiene de sí mismo,
allá en el fondo del alma, la noble estimación que debe tener; pero de sus prendas exteriores
no tiene buena idea. Su modestia en este punto traspasa los límites de la humildad y raya en
desconfianza. Aunque te adora, aunque ha creído siempre en tu amor, opina en general poco favorablemente
de las mujeres; cree que el lujo, la brillantez, la elegancia y la alta posición nos deslumbran.

--Y no cree mal. A mí me han deslumbrado, no para dejar de amar a Braulio y amar a otro, sino
para complacerme en otro amor sin pagarle.

--Mira, hermana, no es tiempo de recriminaciones. Si hiciste mal en complacerte en ese supuesto
amor, ya el arrepentimiento es tardío y estéril. Busquemos remedio a tu ligereza. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00996</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>150303</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22732</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Gumi I put on the table at night. I put it there with very
cautiously and shaking that woke my wife. I looked at Beatrice. I looked like who looks at the
treasure that has been lost. All your worth, all its beauty, all spell flashed his before my
eyes brighter than ever. What sweet bastard, what love without honor and without shame, what affection
villain poisoned me at that moment the heart and ran through my veins to my perverse blood?
This is wiped my tears, got his head slowly and gently and without barely touching his lips,
kissed her rosy cheeks.

"Fortunately I was in the reaction. Received the outrage offered to
my spirit.

I filled with shame. I was ashamed, I was disgusted by my weakness.

"The idea of ??killing Beatriz again asked me undecided will. I grabbed the iron again. Again
stepped back frightened.

"I fled the room, fled from the house like a thief.

I opened both doors with the keys had saved, then carefully closed. I found myself in the
street.

»What to do? I looked ridiculous. He could not suffer.

In the middle of the street gave me a seizure of nervous laughter. If someone had heard me take
me for crazy.

"Lots of thoughts found, and all very sad, crossed my mind went and returned with cruel persistence.

"For
a brief moment imagine still insisted that it could be slander anonymous accusations, but soon
ran away from me this idea comforting. It alone has not returned.

"What was the crisis solution that was me? Did I had to kill my wife? Does I had to kill her
lover?

"No, it was not weakness of mine: I was in the mood to kill someone who had been at that point
to steal my watch or the few actual carrying in his pocket, but perhaps a moral perversion, I could
not consider me a thief who stole the joy, love my wife and the honor
of my house clean.

The watch and money are my property, no free will, not the thief go and leave me because I prefer,
while Beatrice was with another and left me because she preferred. He did well to take it. Why
had I to kill him for this? What should I respect him to me for neglecting my happiness and
yours?

"Therefore, putting aside my soul the thought of killing my opponent.

Tried in the court my conscience, I do not absolve, but recognized the incompetence of the court.
I do not acquitted because I am the victim. If the victim had been an indifferent, would have
acquitted. Could therefore kill, not justice but revenge.

"Then I thought of the duel, but how to fight with swords or guns
or in life I have taken into their hands?

I also hated the idea of ??me before and offended to claim and equal chance to avenge my wrong,
to confess my stupidity in arms and my inability, to appeal to not know what means to force a
happy rival to be put in front of me luck, I, skinny, old and infirm
could kill him he being young, agile and robust.

"Neither murder nor the match were possible. Another man who was not I would be separated forever
of his wife. There was no party more in accord with reason. I, however, could not follow. I will
not live away from home. It's horrible, stupid, it is monstrous, but I love, I will continue
always loving.

Without your love, the world will be a desert for me, life, loneliness
fearful; my heart, an emptiness that is filled with nothing.

"The human soul needs love, worship, believe. Heaven has punished the pride of my soul. Have been
thrown her idols, altars, all worthy of adoration and love. In contrast, I put my worship, my
love, my faith and hope in Beatrice.

She was ... my idolatry.

"The love of the unbeliever is immense. The unbeliever devoted to a negligible object full force
of love that seeks to elevate the believer to the divine ideal.

"Well, why tired? I wandered like a meek beast that has stuck in his
chest a poisoned dart.

At night I wandered, the day I've been blind. I have shame that people
I see.

It seems to me that everyone knows the teasing that I am a victim, my patience, my love bad
paid, and will laugh at me or going to spit in the face.

"Last night was my last resort to ridicule.

"I do not doubt. I walked around my house, and close to four o'clock I saw a man coming out ...
mysteriously ... there. I have eagle-eyed ... I saw him ... he was. I carried a revolver in his
pocket. Why? If he had fired six shots you have, none would have given my enemy. I do not shoot, and
I also shook his hand. All I was convulsive.

"Also, why not confess? I think I would not be able to kill him, but finding him asleep and could put
at close range the gun barrel in his temples.

"I do not understand now but one thing. I can not bear my inexhaustible love. I can not bear the
ridiculous that I noticed. To the poetry of great pain can not draw on me because I laugh
myself from my pain and I find him funny.

"I have no other recourse, if I die no good, they look way to die soon.

"Forgive this long relief. Sorry this neat card. Be the last. Goodbye. "

Paco Ramírez was a man of some clear illustration and understanding, but he still had healthier
than clear, he was as healthy as his body was that of an athlete. Loved Paco Don Braulio,
though who else had ever thrown up ready for a shift of that had ways of thinking that he
described as tortuous and that it should be subjected to the most convoluted and unique feelings.

Just
read the letter, believed that Braulio was crazy. I could not believe the lack of Dona Beatriz:
very good opinion of her. Imagined the extent that the person who walked jealous Braulio was
the Count, who Beatriz spoke in his letter.

Would be like, Paco feared a catastrophe. Braulio thought that, or he would die, or was about
to kill, or would be Leganés. To avoid this, if it was time, he immediately
en route to Madrid.

Braulio had given no sign, but he would find. If you did not come
to save him, would avenge him.

Paco was with no metaphysical or discreteos. No thought or treason or murder in duels of every ceremony.
Only thought to get the love and the soul of Condesito of her lively body punches and kicks.

With
such good intentions, also anxious to see his Inesita, and hoping to woo and fetch the scene,
thirty-two hours is not sane to have received and read lamentable letter from her desperate
friend, Paco came to this heroic and crowned villa, and without shake
even the dust of the road, after leaving the valise in a guest house
and installed, taking fourth in her, she went to the home of two beautiful
sisters.

XX

As she Paco Ramírez to that household but hurriedly, offered to imagination
more vividly the difficulties of the interview should have.

In the letter from Don Braulio paragraphs remembered more sinister
and ominous, and provided some Unfortunately.

So he had noticed a contradiction in the letter that gave him so much suspect. Don Braulio
confessed at first, as was true that never used or had weapons, and towards the end of the letter
spoke of a revolver in his pocket. Paco Ramírez Don Braulio was clear that he had bought or
acquired in those days, after the night he was in hiding at home.

Why the acquisition? What did make his hapless friend?

Paco was sure that Don Braulio not kill nor his wife nor his rival,
but was afraid of attempting his own life, and thought to avenge killing
Condesito.

Paco was so strong, so calm, and was so confident that nothing seemed
easier.

As Dona Beatriz, Paco loved her like a sister and respected as a superior
being, where, but believe you are afflicted much blamed, as we believed
it was ready to forgive the guilt.

At this point understood and applauded and even blessed the weakness or Don Braulio tenderness.
What is not explained is that Don Braulio not try to revenge Condesito
of any way to be.

In the meantime, what would he do, what to say at Dona Beatriz?

After reflection, form various plans and mentally composing several
speeches, he determined to be guided by the inspiration of the moment
and improvise everything.

So it came to Don Braulio. He climbed the stairs two by two and pulled the cord of bell. It
was nine o'clock.

Then they opened, with that frankness and readiness with which the poor are usually open.

Barely had time to see who would open. It was found wrapped around her arms clasped him and
overwhelmed by a mouth covered her face with a flood of sound kisses.

- Good God, man! "- Said after the housekeeper Teresa, who was kissed -. How has embarnecido
in these three years! Give glory to see you: you made a real boy.

But tell me, and Don Braulio? Does it come with you?

What have you done on site? Why not write? Beatriz is the heart in her mouth.

- I want to see.

"I can see it? - Paco said.

- Right now. Sign.

Do you bring news of Don Braulio?

- Yes.

- Well, come.

- Is Agnes
with her sister?

- Inés not up yet.

- Best - Paco said -.

I need to see Beatriz alone - added between his teeth.

Before the end of muttering the phrase, before I entered the sitting
room of Dona Beatriz, it appeared in the lobby, and friendly and tightly
grasping the hands of Paco between over and said:

- What is this?

What Braulio? Where?

How can you not come? I am feeling very uneasy. What happens, God? What happens?

So saying, both came into the room. He loves Teresa went after them.

- Let us, Teresa.

Then will come.

I have to talk to Beatrice - Paco said.

This mystery seemed to increase the shock of the pretty girl.

He loves Teresa left the room grumbling.

Paco and Betty alone and said this:

- What mysteries are yours?

What do you say? Speech. Anything is better than the anxiety, that doubt that I have. My bad
not horrible, my misfortune will not be deeper actually what I pretend
and fantasy.

Speech. Where is my husband? What did it?

Why not come in your company?

- Your husband has gone to the scene. Evil can come with me.

Your husband has left Madrid. Here it is. Here I come to fetch him.

- It is impossible. Braulio never lies. Braulio said he was going to see. We will have occurred
some misfortune on the road. Be sick, dead, perhaps in some people's way. Braulio was to see. Braulio
not deceived me.

Paco Ramirez, who was not a man much given to circumlocution and rodeos, and also thought it
was urgent and essential to a prompt explanation, then said:

- Braulio has deceived you because you thought you fooled.

- No way - said Beatriz, red blood rising to her cheeks -. Who has invented this infamy? Who
said this madness?

- The same Braulio.

- How? When? Where you've seen?

- I have not seen. I received a letter from him.

- Give it to me. I read it.

- Will you have courage to read it?

- God give me courage for all. You give me the letter.

Paco still hesitated.

- Give me the letter - again said Beatriz.

- You shall - Paco said - but before I demand of you one thing.

-
Say, calls soon.

- You will respond honestly to what you ask, you
will declare the naked truth: not as if in answer to your brother,
but as if in answer to your own conscience as if you were in the court
of the Lord and He who will be questioned.

- Question.

Not aside. Do not stain my lips lies.

- Do you love Braulio?

- With all my heart.

- Braulio you ugly and beautiful. Braulio is old ... Do you love love?

- Braulio's soul is beautiful, the soul is immortal Braulio young. Yes, I love him love.

- Have you ever loved another man?

- Never.

- Look carefully at the bottom of your soul. Beatrice, have you ever loved another man?

- Just understand what I want to say, but not to stay a qualm. I to peer into the deepest abyss
of my mind, I will look there and make my patent most hidden thoughts, ideas vague and confusing
that I did not realize until I now.

- Say, Beatrice.

- I say I never loved but to love my husband I do not think having failed once, or with the
most fleeting thought, or the more ephemeral desire bastard.

- Is it true what you say? Do not you accuse the consciousness of the child missing?

- How do I declare impeccable? Paco, yes, conscience accuses me, but it haunts me; give me the
letter, we end. What interrogation! What a cruel delay! Have you come to kill me?

- No, Beatriz.

Tell me, however, what you are accused of consciousness?

- I'm vain, I admit. Now that I sense a misfortune, I see it is sin that I I did not think it
was.

I examine myself, I judge and condemn me. Look, Paco: I have believed a man I loved, and though
not paid for his love, I was pleased and proud that I love me. His love was in such a way restrained
by the respect that was never in words. I guess, did not see him. And I guess, not passion
itself had the lowest impurity but as ethereal feeling, immaculate, that is not love, nor
friendship, which should not be name, which is unspeakable in every language on earth, that
if you name must be in sky. What? Vanity of women.

Novels ridiculous that we forged in the imagination and certainly have no reality whatsoever. The
man who obeys me well, the man and me seen and admired, is the wisest,
the most elegant of the aristocracy of Madrid, is held for their gracious
presence, her grace, courage and even their sexual conquests.

Seeing him so exhausted me, seeing what he delighted in hearing me
talk, which celebrated my talent, which is struggling to please me
and because I had it the best concept, not deny it, my wife was very
proud of flattered.

I judged worth more, when he had inspired affection noble man.

My own vanity I moved my turn to be a concept, perhaps exaggerated,
of all his personal belongings.

The man, who also, in my opinion, I understand, was worth much more to my eyes. Gratitude to
this man in my moments of modesty, when I thought I owed it all to
my own merit, filled my heart.

Never, however, I have loved. Every night for months, talked to him
more than hours in a low voice.

Praises me, I said a thousand polite returns, but I love talking. Among he and I are tacitly these
extraordinary relationships.

Is this sin? Ah! I think yes. Now I think so. Heart tells me. Braulio is jealous. But, my God,
why did not I tell you?

Why has not complained?

I would have apologized.

I would have thousand times that she loved him. I have renewed my
vows.

I would have been terminated the insane poetry, dream story that
only satisfy my vanity.

But no: Braulio right, Braulio is delicate.

A husband should not be jealous. Should not tell his wife that suspected. It would be an indignity,
a shame he can not.

And I, stupid, blind, I have not until now understood the danger
and absurdity of my behavior.

Who knows? Maybe slanderers have understood everything in the worst way. Maybe you have besmirched
my honor and my husband's. Maybe you have had within the accuse cruelty.

Come on, Paco, you know everything.

Do not kill me. Give me the letter. Pronto! Give me the letter.

Paco, without a word, not knowing what to think of everything, not
daring to believe Beatriz lied, failed to explain how they lied so
well, and remembering, however, that the letter was evidence Braulio
almost obvious that Beatrice was guilty, he gave Finally the letter.

Beatriz unfolded it eagerly, and did not read it, devoured it.

Do not interrupted the reading, not with a sigh, nor a cry nor a complaint.

It put alternately red and pale. Prevailed after deathly pallor. Big tears sprang from the
beautiful black eyes of Beatrice and slid down her cheeks.

The silence was complete. You could count the violent beating of the heart of Beatrice and Paco
heart.

Another woman, guilty or not guilty, had pretended to faint, had fainted
in earnest or done ends with tears, with groans and cries even with
maybe.

Beatriz, read the letter, known and all the misfortune of her husband
and his, if that her husband felt, contained all vehement explosion
of pain, and Paco told this way:

- I acknowledge my offense.

I deny my foolish conceit, my desire to look, my desire light to
be admired, but not enough to explain all this misery.

I am a victim an infernal plot, a series of fatal coincidences. Who
knows, God?

Who knows?

But it is very hard, it's awful, is cruel punishment that falls on
my head.

Why did not kill me? Why did he have mercy on me? I had awakened to feel hurt. I have forgiven.
What do I say ... I have forgiven?

I would have apologized and have been happy to die in his arms. How I love! This love itself
is worth. In this love itself I have encryption you should always my pride. Why do I have
neglected to lose perhaps I fainted, mad, giddy for a paltry vanity?

And he kissed me while I slept instead of killing me, like I really
deserved.

He came to stab me and gave me kisses of love, and wept with tenderness, and found me I looked
beautiful and ecstatic. Paco, brother mine, run, go to the Ministry, is everywhere, seek him, tell
him I love him, bring him to my live arms, give it back to forgive me. What will I do, my
Jesus?

What shall I do? I'm about to leave to pick myself crazy.

I only fear that stops are over the scandal and shame. Brother, for pity's sake, run, looking
for Braulio. I fear, I tremble for his life.

What horror!

The death has not given me: he kissed me, believing himself mortally
offended.

And in return so much love, I'll kill him.

Paco was dumb, ecstatic, full of wonder, his mouth open, not knowing what to think or what to
say.

Beatrice, with more agitation, upset, impatient with the immobility
of Paco, continued to thus:

- Do not stop: flies, looking for Braulio.

It'll kill you if you take too. Tell him I love him soon, idolize you, that your kiss is worth more
than all the satisfaction and pride, that his love I love, that divine
beauty of his soul for me to go beyond the beauty of the other God's
creatures.

That I will see her again, heavens! That I throw at her feet and ask forgiveness a thousand
times! That I will pay the kiss he gave me sleeping, blowing my soul infusing into his with
an everlasting kiss ... infinite!

Beatriz While he spoke, Paco was pushing out of the parlor, he was throwing to shove of the house.

Already in the anteroom, Beatriz said:

- Go to the Ministry, go to the police, Braulio seeks by all means, do not stop.
Paco came at the end of his tongue, and replied:

- Be still, Beatriz,
I find. Soon I'll be back here. Never doubt that I will bring me.
Have faith in the goodness of God.

That said, opened the door, left
the room and rushed down the stairs.

Doña Beatriz hesitating and
stumbling back to the room. He could no longer stand. Sank down on
the couch.

After a moment of quiet and silence, broke into sobs and
moans and poured a sea tears.

Then came the love Teresa.

- What
ails you, child? Why are you crying?

- Let me, love, let me - replied
Dona Beatriz -. I am the most unfortunate of women.

He loves Teresa
insisted in vain on the same or similar questions.

Beatrice did not
answer but asking him to leave her.

Tired, then, and even a little
bite of that secrecy with which it is demure Beatrix, Teresa loves
left the room and went to bed and Ines.

- Girls - said - do not you
wake up today?

Ines, still half asleep, but was open and the wood
of the window, and sun flooded his room, sat up a little and answered:

-
Well, what time is it?

- The nine and a half, about ten o'clock.
Is plenty of time to get up. It is also necessary to get up. Big news.
Paco Ramírez has come.

- With my brother? - Asked Agnes.

- Without
your brother - said the housekeeper.

- Where is? Have you stayed
in place? Why not come?

- I do not know. Just know that your sister
is crying as I have never seen mourn. It has certainly some great
misfortune. Beatrice wanted to tell me anything, but something very
serious happens and pitiful. Get up, daughter. Go to console your
sister and know the cause of your pain.

Inesita jumped out of bed
full of fright. He put on a gown, without considering more carefully,
by precipitation, and ran into the parlor, where Beatrice was.

XXI

-
What are you, sister? Why are you crying? - Asked Inesita fondly just
entered the parlor and saw so distraught Beatrice.

As Beatrice and
he told her not continue crying, Inesita bent over the couch where
Beatriz was sealed and returned to ask the same questions, along with
kisses and caresses.

Beatriz could no longer resist, was also a need
to unburden his heart, and joining Agnes taking her hand, said with
a sigh:

- What I'm miserable, Ines!

- What? - Broke it.

- That's
my fault Braulio is jealous and has left home and may not return.

-
And who is jealous?

- Is jealous of the Count of Alhedín.

- What
a blunder! - Said Ines -. Why, do not see clearly that the Count is
not for you but than mere friendship?

- That's not - candidly said
Beatrice, which, amid all Don Braulio loving, full startle him, and
repented of his intimacy with the Count could not settle the Count
was not in love with her.

- That does not, I think the Count loves
me, but I have never ever loved.

- Unique idea of ??Conde you, sister.
Believe me, men like him do not love without being loved. The Count
makes you different, you can see, you is cute and nice and quiet,
so speak to you. Since it is very gallantly, you two hundred thousand
compliments, but there is a distance love infinite.

- Who says you
have not saved it that far? - Asked Beatrice.

- Nobody says it to
me - said Agnes - but I guess. In any case, it is best not love you.
Have you ever you love him?

- No.

- Well then, what the victim wanted?

-
I did not want ... or did not love ... here was not what I wanted,
but what was. The Count was a regular with me, and I confess, I delighted
in their attentions. Did not love him, but felt a satisfaction of
self-esteem to believe me loved by him. This me lost.

- Come on,
sister, relax. No one is lost for so little. If your husband is jealous,
with explain that there is no reason to have them, you're all finished.

-
And how do I explain? Where can I see him? Have I not said that it
was and never come back? Perhaps be killed.

- Such things tell me
that you begin to put in care, although I am not of those who drown
in a little water. Braulio is suspicious and captious; Braulio adores
you; Braulio's self, in the depths of the soul, the estimate should
be noble, but their outer garments no good idea. His modesty at this
point beyond the limits of humility and ray distrust. Although I love,
but has always believed in your love, generally unfavorable opinion
for women, believes that luxury, brilliance, elegance and high position
dazzle us.

- And do not think evil. I have been amazed, not to stop
loving Braulio and love another, but to indulge in another love without
paying.

- Look, sister, is not time for recriminations. If you've
done wrong please you in this course love, and repentance is late
and sterile. Seek cure for your light</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>