<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09574</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>403838</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18539</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Pero no por eso dejó de experimentar súbito calofrío que le bajó hasta las plantas.

Hizo llamar a Medrano y refiriole su extraña situación, el menosprecio de Beatriz, la frialdad
de don Alonso y lo que acababa de decirle su paje.

El escudero palideció de pronto y, mesándose la barba, repuso:

--Amor de niña, agua en cestilla--luego alzando la frente:--¿No será alguna treta de Franco,
el campanero?

Ramiro, pensando que podía referirse al asunto de los moriscos, meneó la cabeza negativamente.
Acto continuo, como hombre resuelto a desatar el nudo de modo harto breve, vistiose el coleto
de ante y ciñose la espada que le diera don Rodrigo del Aguila. Luego, desnudando la hoja,
oprimió con ambas manos la guarnición sobre su pecho, para rezar de aquella guisa una larga
plegaria. En acabando persignose con la empuñadura, y haciendo correr a lo largo del acero
indefinible mirada, envainolo otra vez en silencio.

Todo quedó convenido. Ordenó a Medrano que fuese a rondar la casa de Beatriz. Quería saber
lo que pasaba, instante por instante, por si era verdad lo del billete. El por su parte iría
a esperar junto a la Puerta de San Vicente, y Pablillos haría de correo.

Eran pasadas las once de la mañana cuando Ramiro y su criado dejaron la ciudad, tomando, hacia
la izquierda, el camino exterior que corre, por la parte de Mediodía, al pie de los muros.
El muchacho caminaba por delante con el gesto despejado y feliz, y aunque llevaba el estómago
más hueco que un atambor, su instinto atisbaba cierto olorcillo de aventura que hacía para
él las veces de sustento. Su amo no era hombre de muchos memoriales, y si el otro se presentaba
con la música bajo las ventanas de la señora, habría de seguro una gresca digna de las calles
de Salamanca. El, por su parte, creía poseer las mejores piernas del reino; y, a no ser que
le cegaran de improviso haciéndole entrar la cabeza en el vientre de alguna guitarra, como
le había acontecido cierta vez, riberas del Tormes, estaba seguro de su persona.

La mañana era fresca y radiosa. Pablillos sentía en su sangre hervor de vida, escozor de danza,
cerril impulso de zapatear la tierra y lanzar a los vientos largos cantares agudos que rebotasen
en los collados. La primavera prestaba a los trigales undoso brillo de sedas; ¡verde y plateada
casulla sobre el buriel de los terruños! El sol chispeaba en la mica de las peñas, en la reja
de los arados, en el agua del río, fingiendo como un chubasco de luz, a lo lejos, sobre las
sierras de Villatoro. Todo parecía impregnado de claridad y de matutino frescor, hasta el tañer
de las campanas, el sonido de los yunques, y el cantar de los tejedores y caldereros en el
morisco arrabal de Santiago. Algunas mujeres quemaban al pie de la cuesta montones de hojarasca,
y un perfume rústico, mejor que el incienso, sahumaba deliciosamente el contorno. Ramiro recordó
sin quererlo sus amores con la sarracena.

Cuando hubo llegado a la Puerta de San Vicente, díjole al paje que esperara en aquel sitio,
mientras él iba a situarse frente a la muralla del Norte.

Pasó el mediodía sin que Ramiro recibiese aviso alguno. A eso de las cinco de la tarde, Pablillos
vino a comunicarle que don Alonso acababa de salir de su casa en una silla cubierta, y que,
según les había dicho un viejo lacayo, aquel señor, después de algún tiempo, pasaba la noche
en el convento de Santo Tomás.

La tarde moría. Ramiro se sentó sobre una peña, con el rostro casi oculto por el ala del fieltro.
El suelo violáceo parecía ondular a sus pies bajo la vibración alucinadora de la penumbra.

De tiempo en tiempo, el joven hidalgo levantaba la cabeza y perdía la mirada en el contorno,
indiferente a la magia del cielo y a las seducciones del paisaje; pero recogiendo en el alma,
de un modo instintivo, la reciedumbre de aquel sitio de pasión y de sublime violencia.

El sol, antes de ocultarse, exaltó con su gloria muriente el oro del cielo. Las pupilas de
Ramiro se dilataron.

Desolada melancolía bañó de pronto la imponente rudeza de la muralla. Ramiro imaginó que las
torres se sucedían a espacios iguales, como los paternoster del rosario; que las almenas figuraban
las avemarías, y la Catedral, con su saliente cimborio, el hueco crucifijo lleno de reliquias
de santos y caballeros.

Cuando Pablillos volvió a presentarse sin ninguna noticia, su amo le manifestó que se iba a
rezar a las cuevas de San Vicente, y encaminose, en efecto, a echarse a los pies de la Virgen
de la Soterraña.

Al acercarse a la basílica hundió la mano en la faltriquera y extrajo el rosario de quince
misterios que le había ofrecido su primer preceptor Fray Antonio de Jesús. Era un viejo rosario
de Tierra Santa, cuyas cuentas, hechas de hueso de camello, habían sido ensartadas en fuerte
y apretado cordón de seda blanca.

«Lleva siempre contigo esta soga de estrangular demonios», habíale dicho el franciscano al
ofrecérselo.

La iglesia estaba sola y obscura. Una lámpara de plata ardía en la capilla mayor. Misterioso
como nunca pareciole ahora el extraño monumento dorado y azul de los Mártires. Bajó a la cripta.
La milagrosa imagen estaba rodeada de cirios ardientes. Dos mujeres, echadas de pechos en el
suelo, gemían hacia un rincón, cubiertas completamente por sus mantos, haciendo pensar en dos
enormes murciélagos moribundos.

Rezó con fervor los quince misterios, y cuando creyó que la sombra le permitiría caminar por
las calles sin ser reconocido, se dirigió a la ciudad, entrando a ella por la puerta vecina
y yendo a situarse a pocos pasos de la casa de Beatriz.

Esperó mucho tiempo.

De pronto, un bulto humano rozole y pasó. Algo después vio llegar una ronda. Un corchete venía
por delante meneando hacia uno y otro lado la humosa y enrejada linterna. Aquella luz alumbraba
con crudeza los semblantes de los ministros. Ramiro reconoció al alguacil Pedro Ronco por la
facha imponente. Las cejas y el mostacho parecían trazados con un tizón sobre su tez color
sebo. El ruido autoritario de los pies y las espadas fuese alejando.

Escuchose luego una voz:

--¡Señor! ¡Mi señor!

Era Pablillos.

Refirió que, un momento antes, un hombre enmascarado se había detenido frente a la casa de
don Alonso, y que a tiempo que Medrano le mandaba con aquella noticia, apareció un nuevo enmascarado,
el cual, acercándose al primero, le interpeló con dureza. Ya parecían irse a las manos, cuando
acertó a pasar la ronda. Haciendo abatir las máscaras y arrimada la lumbre a los rostros, el
alguacil Pedro Ronco reconoció a los dos hermanos San Vicente, ordenando con fieras amenazas
al segundón que se alejara al punto, si no quería acabar en la cárcel. El mayorazgo retirose
también; pero, según el escudero, no tardaría en volver al mismo sitio.

Ramiro fue a colocarse en la esquina más próxima. Encontrándose allí con Medrano, dijo a éste
y al paje que le dejasen solo.

La luna debía asomar hacia el naciente, pues la muralla comenzaba a contornear por ese lado
sus triangulares almenas.

Más de una hora pasó Ramiro sin apartar los ojos de la casa de Beatriz. Parecíale por momentos
que el postigo de la puerta se entreabría y se cerraba. De pronto, un cuerpo de mujer asomó
por la abertura. Las blancas tocas y la singular corpulencia denunciaban a doña Alvarez. Cada
vez sacaba fuera mayor parte del busto, cobrando confianza. Por fin, chistó quedo, muy quedo,
varias veces. Nadie respondía. El postigo cerrose.

Cuando Ramiro comenzaba a pensar que Gonzalo no volvería tal vez a presentarse aquella noche,
vio llegar a lo largo de la calle, la figura de un hombre que fue a detenerse ante la casa
de Beatriz, al pie de las ventanas.

Ramiro desenvainó la espada, y tomándola de la hoja por encima de la capa, adelantose, prestamente,
rozando la pared más obscura. ¡Era Gonzalo! Aunque su rostro estaba cubierto por el negro tafetán,
reconociole, al pronto, por la pluma blanca, sujeta a la gorra con hermoso joyel de diamantes,
y la capa cenicienta que llevaba, también, noches pasadas, en la casa de juego.

Al tiempo que el joven regidor iba a golpear la puerta con los nudillos, Ramiro, corriendo
hacia él, asiole el brazo en el aire. Luego, estrujándole con fuerza la máscara sobre el rostro,
acabó por arrancársela con rabioso tirón. San Vicente desenvainó a su vez, y exclamando: «¡Muera!»,
se arrojó sobre su rival. Pero éste le esperaba ya con el acero tendido.

Gonzalo se detuvo, y blandiendo furiosamente la espada, gritó de nuevo:

--Pida perdón el alevoso.

--Vos a mí, villano, por vuestras calumnias menguadas.

--¡Muera entonces el perro morisco!--volvió a gritar San Vicente.

--Hablad más quedo, señor regidor; no sea que os preste ayuda la ronda.

--No la he menester.

--Pues busquemos, si os place, algún sitio más apartado, donde el rumor de las espadas no haga
asomar a alguna dueña pensando que es el oro de vuestra bolsa.

--Vamos donde gustéis.

Los dos envainaron, y Ramiro tomó por la angosta calleja, en la dirección del Nordeste, hacia
un paraje solitario dentro de los muros, que él había observado en uno de sus paseos.

Gonzalo marchaba a la izquierda, y su capa gris semejaba una tela de plata entre la incierta
claridad de la noche.

Llegados que fueron ante un viejo portalón, Ramiro se detuvo y trató de violentar el cerrojo.
Gonzalo ayudó con el hombro. Por fin, después de un vano forcejeo, convinieron en escalar juntos
la tapia. Gonzalo apoyó su pie en el muslo de Ramiro y, cuando se hubo encaramado, tendió desde
arriba la mano a su rival, ayudándose uno a otro como en los desafíos de los libros caballerescos
y como lo hicieran Amadís, Rugero o Esplandián, con su valiente cortesanía.

Era una cantera abandonada. La roca, formando una sola mole en forma de colina, no había permitido
levantar vivienda alguna sobre su pétreo caparacho, antiguo como el mundo. La muralla se levantaba
hacia la derecha, almenada, fosca, solemne y revestida de sombras formidables.

Deteniéndose en el paraje más llano, los dos mancebos derribaron al suelo sus capas. Gonzalo
arrojó también lejos de sí la rodela que llevaba colgada del cinto. El cielo, todo entoldado,
de nubes transparentes, esparcía sobre la callada ciudad una lumbre misteriosa de amanecer.
Hacia el naciente, nacarada aureola rodeaba la escondida perla del plenilunio.

Los aceros se cruzaron.

Gonzalo paraba los golpes con maestría, acechando el instante. Ramiro, a su vez, desplegaba
una esgrima aparatosa y soldadesca, con molinetes fantásticos, y su boca, entreabierta por
el ansia homicida, dejaba rebrillar la dentadura.

San Vicente, a pesar de su destreza sentíase vacilar ante aquella máscara cruel, toda confianza,
toda vigor, toda coraje; y, por fin, temiendo que el corazón le flaqueara, hizo una falsa y
enviole a Ramiro una punta derecha y veloz como un dardo. El arma atravesó de parte a parte
el coleto por el costado, rozando la carne. Ramiro, entonces, iluminado por una centella de
instinto, dio dos grandes pasos hacia adelante, para dejar aprisionada en el cuero la hoja
del adversario; y tomando su propia espada, como quien alza un puñal, clavósela de golpe en
medio del pecho. Luego se la hundió ferozmente, a través del justillo, toda entera, toda, toda,
hasta los gavilanes.

Gonzalo exclamó:

--¡Esto es hecho!

Y, lanzando por la boca una onda negrusca, desplomose.

Sus brazos y sus piernas se sacudieron un instante; y su cabeza, sin vida, se dobló, se acostó
de lado, sobre la piedra.

Al mirar extendido a sus plantas el cuerpo exánime de su rival, Ramiro elevó una oración jaculatoria
a la Virgen de la Soterraña. ¡Estaba vengado! La fuente del orgullo derramaba ahora por todo
su cuerpo un goce inmenso y bravío. Sintió erguirse en la brisa, como una cresta de gallo,
la pluma de su sombrero, y experimentó en los talones una extraña sensación de fuerza invencible.
Hubiera querido lanzar, con toda su voz, hacia la luna, el grito de guerra de sus mayores.

Asaltado por súbito pensamiento, se agachó hacia el cadáver, y desciñendo las agujetas, sacó
de entre el jubón y la ensangrentada camisa un billete sin sobrescrito. Lo desplegó. La claridad
era débil; pero, al mirar hacia el cielo, observó que la luna iba a pasar muy pronto tras una
grieta de las nubes. Poco después sus ojos leyeron las siguientes palabras:

«Sírvase vuesa merced venir esta noche pasadas las once. Golpee primero tres veces y luego
otras dos, muy quedo, en el postigo. Yo le abriré. Cruce el patio y el huerto y suba a la torre
de la muralla. Mi señora irá luego a hablar con vuesa merced.

»Vuestra fiel servidora, Alvarez.»

Tomose la frente con ambas manos, ¡Era posible! ¿Sería verdad que Beatriz?... ¿No habría en
todo aquello algún ardid infame de la dueña? Fácil era saberlo. Contuvo su meditación, e, instantáneamente,
con nerviosa premura, cambió su negro sombrero por la gorra de Gonzalo. Arrastrando en seguida
el cadáver hasta el borde de una cavidad que negreaba al pie de los muros, empujolo con el
pie reciamente para que rodara hasta el fondo. Luego, recogiendo la clara capa del muerto,
embozose con ella, haciendo de lo suyo un lío que apretó bajo el brazo.

Cuando se disponía a saltar de nuevo la tapia, vio asomar por detrás dos rostros obscuros.
Tuvo un estremecimiento. Eran Medrano y Pablillos, que habían presenciado desde allí toda la
escena. Al caer a la calle, el escudero recibiole sobre su pecho, exclamando:

--Famosa estocada, ¡voto a Cristo! Huyamos, huyamos presto, no sea que vuelva la ronda.

Ramiro ordenoles esta vez con imperio que fueran a esperarle al solar, y, dándoles la capa
y el sombrero, enderezó resueltamente a la casa de Beatriz.

Llegado ante la puerta, advirtió en el suelo la mascarilla negra de Gonzalo; cogiéndola con
presteza se la puso en el rostro.

Golpeó tres veces y luego otras dos con los nudillos. El paño de la capa desprendía afeminado
perfume. Su espíritu comenzó a divagar. Vio y dejó de ver varias veces una almohada de Aixa
engalanada con hilo de oro y piedras preciosas. Observó que los clavos de la puerta figuraban
cabezas de leones. Llamó de nuevo. El exceso de emoción le embriagaba. Por fin, el cerrojo
crujió levemente y el postigo entreabriose; doña Alvarez asomó la cabeza, y después de haberle
observado un instante, le dijo en voz baja:

--¡Albricias, señor don Gonzalo!

Luego, abriendo del todo el postigo y sacudiendo la mano con impaciencia:

--Presto, presto--agregó;--cruce vuesa merced el patio y el huerto, y suba a la torre.

Cuando Ramiro se halló en lo alto del cubo, desde cuya plataforma había visto atardecer siendo
niño, en compañía del enano, apoyó su espalda contra las almenas y se puso a esperar. Incomprensible
apatía le inundaba: una inconsciencia, una vaguedad de emoción, comparables al comienzo de
la embriaguez. Su razón meditaba sin comprender. La frescura de la noche hacíale sonreír.

Abajo, profundamente, los altozanos ondulaban con color fosco de acero. El convento de la Encarnación,
con sus tristes paredes pálidas, adormía en la noche su sosiego santo. Tenue claridad flotaba
sobre la morada de pureza y de pasión, como si sus tapias encerrasen algún milagroso huerto
de lirios. Nubes bajas, resquebrajadas como témpanos, cubrían el cielo, dejando transparentar
esa temerosa luz cenicienta favorable a todos los ensalmos. Los gallos cantaban por momentos,
como si comenzase la aurora. Un perro latió de modo lúgubre al pie de la muralla.

De pronto, oyose en la escalera sedoso crujir de vestidos.

Ramiro se irguió.

Cubierta de un velo obscuro, una mujer acababa de aparecer sobre la torre; su mano, enguantada,
abatió con gracia el embozo. La pálida tez de Beatriz resplandeció entonces con blancura de
mármol, y sus lustrosos cabellos, ceñidos por un aro de oro, tomaron en la noche azulenco pavón
de armadura sombría. Dos mechones se desprendieron de los demás, vibrando en el aire cual doble
serpiente.

Anchos galones de plata recamaban la falda color zafiro, mientras la tela del jubón desaparecía
bajo cuentas y canutillos, cota de abalorio cabrilleando sin cesar como el agua intranquila.
La doncella levantó el rostro con los ojos entrecerrados, quedándose inmóvil un instante. Sus
labios parecían sorber la fluida claridad que bajaba del cielo.

Ramiro se sintió como enloquecido ante aquella aparición. Todo su ser no fue sino un brusco
frenesí, una llama que se estira para devorar el velo cercano. Era Beatriz la que estaba ante
él, su Beatriz, su señora, divinizada por la magia de la noche y del silencio. Olvidó su sospecha;
olvidó el papel de doña Alvarez y el drama reciente; olvidó como un ebrio, como un insano,
que llevaba las ropas de otro hombre; olvidó la máscara que ocultaba su rostro; y pareciole
que, después de un sueño desesperante, se encontraba por fin con su amada, esposo y señor,
sobre la torre de encantado castillo. Caminó hacia ella y asiola con dulzura. Beatriz se resistió
débilmente; ¡en su labio, humedecido, temblaba una lucecilla azul, una gota de luna!

Fue al principio un beso ideal, casi incorpóreo, tomado con el aliento, en la quietud, en la
altura, sobre el sueño de la ciudad y las tierras; pero, al pronto, el indeciso contacto acabó
por despertar los sentidos, y las bocas se ligaron, se apretaron fuertemente, bajo el masculino
furor. Beatriz gimió sin poder esquivarse, mientras Ramiro sentía correr por su cuerpo sobrehumano
deleite. ¡Al fin lograba la ansiada, la soñada caricia! ¡Era el beso de ella, el beso de Beatriz,
tantas veces imaginado! Pero, de pronto, en medio de aquel loco transporte, un relámpago de
razón brilló en su cerebro. La realidad acababa de herirle de súbito. Fue algo espantoso. Con
la boca estremecida aún sobre el rostro de la doncella, pensó de repente que estaba con la
capa y la toca del muerto; que llevaba sobre el rostro una máscara; que Beatriz creía hallarse
en brazos de Gonzalo, y, en fin, ¡que aquel beso era el beso de otro, el triunfo de otro, la
caricia suprema destinada a otro labio, a otro hombre!

En ese instante la niña, levantando su rostro, exclamó con pasión:

--¡Ah, Gonzalo, cuán dichosa me hacéis!

Y tendió de nuevo su boca insaciada.

Ramiro recibió de lleno el aletazo de la demencia. Todo su ser rechinó cual la hoja ígnea que
el espadero sumerge de golpe en el agua. Sentía que su mente giraba en una vorágine de negrura,
y escuchaba dentro de su cerebro el ladrido de las potencias tenebrosas de la venganza; no
viendo sino una sola idea, una sola necesidad, una sola justicia: ¡el exterminio, la muerte!

Tomó, sin embargo, sin poder resistirlo, el nuevo beso de Beatriz, devolviendo aquella caricia
con una mordedura salvaje. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>267783</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16863</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

But no longer experience sudden chill that went down to the plants.

Medrano did call and he rehearsed his strange situation, Beatriz contempt,
coldness Don Alonso and what he had to tell her page.

The squire paled suddenly and, stroking his beard, said:

- Love child,
water basket - after raising the front: - Could it be some mischief
Franco Ringer?

Ramiro, thinking it could refer the matter of the Moors, shook his head. Continuous act like
a man determined to undo the knot so soon tired, he clothed himself with the doublet suede
and girded his sword to give him Eagle Don Rodrigo. Then, stripping the leaf pressed with
both hands on his chest lining, to pray in that guise long prayer.

Persignose finish with the handle, and by running along the steel indefinable look, envainolo
again in silence.

Everything was agreed. Medrano was ordered to haunt the house of Beatrice. I wanted to know what
was happening, moment by moment, as if it was true what the ticket. The in turn would to wait
by the Puerta de San Vicente, and would Pablillo email.

It was past eleven o'clock when Ramiro and his valet left the city, taking, to the left, the road
that runs outside, at the Lunch at the foot of the walls. The boy was walking ahead with the
air clear and happy, and although he had the stomach more hollow than a drummer, his instinct
peeped some whiff of adventure that was to he often livelihood. His master was not a man of
many memorials, and if the other was presented with music under the
windows of the lady, would secure a fight worthy of the streets of
Salamanca.

He, in turn, believed to have the best legs of the kingdom, and, unless will blind you suddenly
making him enter his head in the belly of a guitar, had happened some time, banks of the Tormes,
was secure in his person.

The morning was fresh and radiant. Pablillo felt his blood boil of life, burning of dance, wild
urge to stomp the ground and throw to the winds long sharp songs that bounce in the hills. Spring
wheat provided to the undulating sheen of silk, green and silver chasuble over the puce of
terroir! The sun sparkled on the mica from the rocks, at the gate of the plows in the river, pretending
like a light shower in the distance, on the Villatoro saws. Everything seemed imbued with clarity
and freshness of morning, to the tolling of bells, the sound of the
anvils, and the song of the weavers and tinkers in the Moorish suburb
of Santiago.

Some women burned at the foot of the hill piles of litter and a rustic scent, better than the
incense, the outline deliciously perfumed.

Ramiro recalled without wanting his love to the Saracen.

When he had come to the Puerta de San Vicente, the page who said to wait at that site, while
he would stand against the North wall.

He spent the afternoon without Ramiro would receive notice. At about five in the afternoon, Pablillo
came to inform you that Don Alonso had just left his house in a deck chair, and that as he had
told an old servant, that gentleman, after some time, spent the night
in the convent of Santo Tomas.

The later died. Ramiro sat on a rock, his face almost hidden by the brim of his felt. The purplish
soil at his feet seemed to ripple under the vibration of the dark hallucinatory.

From time to time, the young nobleman raised his head and looked lost
on the boundary, indifferent to the magic of the sky and the seductions
of the landscape, but picking up in the soul, an instinctive way,
the vigor of the place of sublime passion and violence.

The sun, before hiding, dying with his glory exalted gold of the sky.

The pupils Ramiro widened.

Desolate melancholy suddenly bathed the roughness of the wall awesome. Ramiro imagined that towers
are succeeding to the same space as the paternoster of the rosary,
which included the battlements Hail Marys, and the Cathedral, with
its projection dome, the hole filled with relics crucifix saints and
knights.

When Pablillo resubmitted without any notice, his master told him that he would pray to the caves
of San Vicente, and proceeded, in effect, to lie at the feet of the Virgin the Soterraña.

Approaching the Basilica dipped his hand in his pocket and pulled out the rosary of fifteen mysteries
that he had offered his first preceptor Fray Antonio de Jesus.

It was an old Rosary Holy Land, whose accounts, made of camel bone, were strung on strong and
tight white silk cord.

"Always carry the rope to strangle the hell" said Franciscan Tell
them to offer it.

The church was lonely and dark. A silver lamp burning in the chapel. Mysterious ever it seemed
strange monument now the gold and blue of the Martyrs. He descended into the crypt. The miraculous
image was surrounded by burning candles.

Two women, breasts pitches in ground, wailing into a corner, completely
covered by their cloaks, suggesting two huge bats dying.

Fervently prayed the fifteen mysteries, and when he thought that the shadow he would walk the
streets without being recognized, addressed to the city, entering it through the next door and going
to stand a few steps from the house of Beatrice.

She waited a long time.

Suddenly a man Rozol package and passed. Something was reached after
a round.

A bracket came by shaking it back and forward across the smoky lantern barred. That light shone
crudely the faces of the ministers.

Pedro Ramiro recognized the sheriff Ronco by imposing facade. The eyebrows and mustache seemed
drawn to a brand on his skin color tallow.

Authoritarian noise of feet and the swords were away.

Escuchose then a voice:

- Lord! My lord!

Was Pablillo.

He said that, a moment before, a masked man was standing in front of the house Don Alonso, and that
Medrano was sending time with this news, there was a new masked which, approaching the first questioned
him harshly. And seemed to go hands when happened to pass the round. Using masks and leaning abate
the fire at the faces, the Sheriff Peter Ronco two brothers recognized
the San Vicente, ordering with fierce threats the second son to go
away to the point, if you do not want to end up in jail.

The mayorazgo withdrew also, but, as the squire, would soon return to the same place.

Ramiro was to be placed on the nearest corner. Medrano he encountered, he said and the page to leave
him alone.

The moon was leaning over the rising, then began to outline the wall
on that side their triangular turrets.

Over an hour passed, his eyes Ramiro's house Beatriz.

It seemed at times the flap of the door half opened and closed.

Suddenly a woman's body appeared through the opening. White singular touch and bulk denounced
Mrs. Alvarez. Each Once pulled out most of the bust, gaining confidence.

Finally, hissed quietly, very quietly, several times.

Nobody answered. The shutter remained closed.

When Ramiro Gonzalo began to think that perhaps would not occur that night, saw him coming along
the street, the figure of a man who went to stop at the house Beatrice,
at the foot of the windows.

Ramiro drew his sword, and grasping of the blade above the water, stepped forward, speedily, touching
the wall darker. It was Gonzalo! Although his face was covered by black taffeta reconociole, at first,
by the white feather, subject to the cap with a beautiful ornament
of diamonds, Cinderella and the layer carrying also nights spent at
the gambling house.

While the young ruler was going to hit the door with his knuckles,
Ramiro, running to him, asiole arm in the air.

Then, squeezing hard on the face mask, eventually tear it with furious tug. San Vicente drew
in turn, and saying, "Kill him!" fell on his opponent. But it was waiting already stretched steel.

Gonzalo
stopped, and angrily waving his sword, shouted back:

- Ask for forgiveness of the treacherous.

- You to me, villain, for
your slanders diminished.

- Then the dog Moorish Die! - San Vicente
screamed again.

- Speak more softly, Mr. Alderman, lest you help
pay the round.

- Have not necessary.

- Well, look, if you please,
somewhere further away, the buzz of the swords do not poke someone
thinking it owns the gold of your bag.

- We go where you please.

The two sheathed, and Ramiro took the narrow lane, in the direction
of east, towards a lonely place within the walls, he had observed
in one of his walks.

Gonzalo going to the left, and his gray coat looked like a silver fabric between the uncertain
clear night.

Arrivals who were at an old gate, Ramiro stopped and tried to violate the lock. Gonzalo helped
with my shoulder. Finally, after a vain struggle, agreed to climb together the wall. Gonzalo put
his foot on the thigh of Ramiro and when he had climbed, stretched
from hand up to his rival, helping each other as on the challenges
of chivalrous books and as they did Amadis Rugero or Esplandián, with
its brave courtesy.

It was an abandoned quarry.

The rock, forming a single mass in the form of choline, did not allow any house up on its stone
caparacho, as old as the world.

The wall stood right, embattled, sullen, solemn and formidable shadow covered.

Stopping at the flattest place, the two young men knocked down their coats. Gonzalo also threw
the shield away from him that had hung from his belt. The sky, all Tented, transparent clouds, spread
over the quiet city with a mysterious light of dawn. Towards the
rising, pearly halo surrounding the hidden pearl of the moon.

Steels crossed.

Gonzalo masterfully blows stopped, awaiting the moment. Ramiro, in turn, displayed a flamboyant
fencing and soldiers, with turnstiles fantastic, and his mouth slightly open for the lust murderer,
leaving teeth glittered.

San Vicente, despite his skill he felt cruel hesitation to that mask, confidence, any force,
any courage, and finally, fearing that her heart faltered, made a false and Ramiro sent it to a right end and
swift as a dart. The weapon pierced through and through the doublet from the side, scraping the
flesh. Ramiro then lit by a spark of instinct, took two big steps forward, to allow trapped
in the leather leaf the opponent, and took his own sword, as one who stands a dagger blow
clavósela of the chest. Then he plunged it fiercely through the bodice,
all whole, all, all, to the hawks.

Gonzalo said:

- It is done!

And, casting a wave by mouth blackish desplomose.

His arms and legs shook for a moment, and his head and lifeless, bent, lay side on the stone.

When
looking at the plants spread to her lifeless body of his rival, Ramiro submitted a short prayer
Our Lady of the Soterraña. He avenged! The source of pride now shed all enjoy your body a huge
and brave. Stand in the breeze felt like a cockscomb, feather in his hat, and experienced
on the heels a strange sense of invincible power. Had wanted to launch, with all their voice,
to the moon, the battle cry of their elders.

Assaulted by a sudden thought, he ducked into the body, and undoing
the laces, took between the jacket and the bloody shirt a ticket without
overwritten.

Unfolded. Clarity was weak, but looking to the sky, observed that the moon was going to happen
very soon after crack in the clouds. Shortly after his eyes read the following words:

"Please your worship come tonight after eleven. First hit three times
and then two, very quietly, in the wicket.

I'll open. Cross the yard and garden and climb the tower of the wall. My lady will then talk to your worship.

"Your
faithful servant, Alvarez."

Tomos forehead with both hands, was possible! Is it true that Beatrice? ... Is there not some
trick everything infamous mistress? It was easy to know. He held his meditation, and, instantly,
with nervous haste, changed his black hat cap Gonzalo.

Then dragging the body to the edge of a cavity than black at the
bottom of the walls, with empujolo standing stoutly for rolled to
the bottom.

Then, collecting the clear layer of dead embozose with it, making
it a mess that pushed him under the arm.

As he prepared to jump back over the wall, he saw two faces looming behind dark. Was a thrill. Medrano
and Pablillo were, they had witnessed from there all scene. Falling into the street, the squire
received him on his chest, exclaiming:

- Famous thrust, vote for
Christ!

Flee, flee quickly, lest the round again.

Ramiro ordenoles this time to rule that they would wait for the sun, and layer them and hat, stood
up resolutely to the home of Beatrice.

Arrived at the door, said on the floor the black mask Gonzalo holding it with promptly put it
in his face.

Hit three times and then another two with his knuckles. The cloth layer gave off sissy perfume.
His spirit began to wander. Saw and stopped several times to see a pillow Aixa adorned with
gold thread and precious stones. Noted that the door contained nails heads of lions. Called again.
Too much emotion you drunk.

Finally, the bolt wicket creaked slightly and entreabriose; Dona Alvarez looked out, and after
having observed a moment, he whispered:

- Good news, Don Gonzalo!

Then, opening the shutter completely and shaking his hand impatiently:

- Presto, presto - added; - cross your grace the yard and garden, and climb the tower.

When Ramiro was found at the top of the cube, from whose platform was being seen sunset child,
accompanied by the dwarf, leaned his back against the battlements
and began to wait.

Incomprehensible apathy flooded him: unconsciousness, a vague emotion,
comparable to early intoxication.

His meditating without understanding why.

The freshness of the night doeth smile.

Down deep, undulating hillocks with gloomy color of steel. The convent of the Incarnation with
her sad pale walls, poppy at night its holy calm.

Dim light floated on the abode of purity and passion, as if its walls enclose some miraculous
garden lilies. Low clouds, cracked like icebergs, covered the sky,
leaving transparent that fearful ashy light favorable to all spells.
The roosters crowed at times as if you started the aurora. Beat a
dog so grim at the foot of the wall.

Suddenly, on the stairs was
heard rustling silk dresses.

Ramiro stood.

Covered with a dark veil,
a woman had appeared on the tower, his hand, gloved gracefully struck
her veil. The pale complexion Beatriz then shone with whiteness marble,
and lustrous hair, girded by a ring of gold, taken at night peacock
bluish dark armor. Two locks were detached from others, which vibrate
in the air twice snake.

Wide silver braid bedrooms sapphire skirt,
while the fabric of my jacket disappeared under accounts and beads,
height of wavelet trinket like water constantly restless. The girl
lifted her face with narrowed eyes, remaining motionless for a moment.
Its smooth lips seemed to suck the light coming down from heaven.

Ramiro
felt like mad before this apparition. His whole being was not an abrupt
frenzy, a flame that reaches out to devour the veil soon. Beatrice
was standing before him, his Beatrice, his wife, deified by the magic
of the night and silence. Forgot your suspicion; forget the role of
Mrs. Alvarez and the recent drama; forgot like a drunkard, as an insane,
wearing the clothes of another man, forgot the mask that hid his face,
and it seemed that, after a hopeless dream, was last with her beloved
husband and lord, on the enchanted castle tower. Asiola walked toward
her and gently. Beatriz resisted weakly on his lip, wet, shivering
a little light blue, a drop of moon!

It was at first a perfect kiss,
almost disembodied, taken with the breath, in the stillness, in the
high on the dream of the city and land, but at first, the contact
undecided over to awaken the senses, and their mouths were bound,
tightly clenched under the male furor. Beatriz moaned unable to dodge,
while Ramiro was running for his superhuman body delight. In order
to achieve the longed, the dream touch! It was the kiss, the kiss
of Beatrice so many times imagined! But suddenly, in the midst of
this crazy transportation, a lightning reason shone in his brain.
Reality just hit you suddenly. It was awful. With still quivering
mouth on the face of the girl, suddenly thought he was with the layer
and the touch of the dead man wearing a mask over his face, that Beatriz
believed found in the arms of Gonzalo, and, finally, that the kiss
was the kiss of another, the triumph of another, supreme caress intended
for another lip, another man!

At that moment the girl, lifting her
face, exclaimed with passion:

- Ah, Gonzalo, how happy you make me!

She
placed her mouth again insatiable.

Ramiro gives flight was full of
dementia. His whole being gritted which igneous sheet the swordsmith
suddenly immersed in water. She felt that her mind spinning into a
vortex of darkness, and heard in his brain the barking of the dark
powers of revenge, not seeing but one idea, one need only one justice:
the destruction, death!

It took, however, unable to resist the new
kiss of Beatriz, returning that caress with a savage bite</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>