<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03472</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>48488</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>767</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> La libertad tendrá que hacer muchos
milagros en España.

Pero si allí la civilizacion está muy atrasada respecto de otras sociedades europeas, no hay
que pensar por eso que España no progresa. Cuatro siglos de tiranía, intolerancia y errores
inauditos, han dejado atras á un pueblo que, si hubiera sido gobernado como Inglaterra desde
1688, sería hoy el primer pueblo del mundo. Apesar de eso, la España de hoy está muy distante,
muchísimo, de la de 1825; progresa visiblemente, y en solo cinco años, despues de la pasajera
cuasi-revolucion de 1854, ha dado grandes pasos.

Se dirá talvez: «Si la mayoría del pueblo español tiene tan buenas cualidades características,
¿por qué se deja gobernar mal y no cambia su situacion?» La explicacion del fenómeno es sencilla.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05355</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1363</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>707</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Freedom will have many miracles in Spain.

But
if there's civilization is far behind on other European societies,
there to think about why Spain does not progress.

Four centuries of tyranny, intolerance and errors unheard, have left behind them a people who,
if he had been ruled as England from 1688, today would be the first people in the world. Despite
that, the Spain of today is very distant greatly from that of 1825, visible progress, and in
just five years after the passing quasi-revolution of 1854, has made great strides.

Perhaps will say: "If the majority of Spanish people have such good
character traits, Why is let evil rule and does not change your situation?

"The explanation is simple.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>