<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04261</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>292175</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23987</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Cuentan questos fueron muertos en pago del bien que iban á hacer, y que Tupac Inca invió ciertos
capitanes con gente á castigarlos; mas, como lo supiesen, se juntaron tantos de los bárbaros,
que mataron y vencieron á los que fueron, de que mostró sentimiento el Inca; mas, por tener
negocios grandes entre las manos, y convenir en persona volver al Cuzco, no fué él propio á
dalles castigo por lo que habian hecho.

En Quito tuvo nueva cuán bien se hacia lo que por él habia sido mandado y cuánto cuidado tenian
los delegados suyos de imponer aquellas gentes en su servicio, y cuán bien los trataban, y
ellos cómo estaban alegres y hacian lo que les era mandado; y de muchos señores de la tierra
le venian cada dia embajadores y le traian grandes presentes, y su córte estaba llena de principales,
y sus palacios de vasijas y vasos de oro y plata y otras grandes riquezas.--Por la mañana comia,
y desde medio dia hasta ser algo tarde, oia en público, acompañado de su guarda, á quien le
queria hablar. Luego gastaba el tiempo en beber hasta ser noche, que tornaba á cenar con lumbre
de leña, porque ellos no usaron sebo ni cera, aunque tenian harto de lo uno y de lo otro.

En Quito dejó por su capitan general y mayordomo mayor á un orejon anciano, quien todos cuentan
que era muy entendido y esforzado y de gentil presencia, á quien llamaban Chalco Mayta, y le
dió licencia para que pudiese andar en andas y servirse con oro, y otras libertades que él
tuvo en mucho. Mandóle, sobre todas cosas, que cada luna le hiciese mensajero que le llevase
aviso particularmente de todas las cosas que pasasen, y del estado de la tierra, y de la fertilidad
della, y del crecimiento de los ganados, con más lo que ordinariamente todos avisaban, que
era, los pobres que habia, los que eran muertos en un año y los que nacian, y lo que se ha
escripto en lo de atrás que sin esto sabian los reyes en el mesmo Cuzco; y con haber tan grande
camino desde Quito al Cuzco, que es más que ir de Sevilla á Roma, con mucho, era tan usado
el camino como lo es de Sevilla á Triana, que no lo puedo más encarecer.

Dias habia que el grand Tupac Inca tenia aviso de la fertilidad de Los Llanos y de los hermosos
valles que en ellos habia, y cuánto se estimaban los señores dellos, y determinó de les enviar
mensajeros con dones y presentes para los principales, rogándoles que le tuviesen por amigo
y compañero, por quél queria ser igual suyo en el traje cuando pasase por los valles, y no
dales guerra si ellos quisiesen paz, y que daria á ellos de sus mujeres y ropas, y él tomarla
de las suyas, y otras cosas destas. Y por toda la costa habia volado ya la nueva de lo mucho
que habia señoreado Tupac Inca Yupanqui, y cómo no era cruel ni sanguinario ni hacia daño sino
á los cavilosos y que querian oponerse contra él; é loaban la costumbre y religion de los del
Cuzco, tenian los orejones por hombres sanctos, creyendo que los Incas eran hijos del sol,
ó que en ellos habia alguna deidad. Y considerando estas cosas y otras, determinaron muchos,
sin haber visto sus banderas, de tomar con él amistad, y asi se lo enviaron á decir con sus
propios embajadores, con los cuales enviaron muchos presentes al mesmo rey, y le rogaban quisiese
venir por sus valles á ser dellos servido y á holgarse de ver sus frescuras; y alabando el
Inca tal voluntad, hablando de nuevo al gobernador de Quito lo que habia de hacer, salió de
aquella ciudad para señorear los Yuncas.

Como el rey Tupac Inca determinase de ir á los valles de Los Llanos, para atraer á su servicio
y obediencia los moradores dellos, abajó á lo de Túmbez y fué honradamente rescibido por los
naturales, á quienes Tupac Inca mostró mucho amor, y luego se puso del traje quellos usaban
para más contentarles, y alabó á los principales el querer sin guerra tomarle por Señor, y
prometió de los tener y estimar como á hijos propios suyos. Ellos, contentos con oir sus buenas
palabras y manera con que les trataba, dieron la obediencia con honestas condiciones, y permitieron
quedar entre ellos gobernadores y hacer edificios; puesto que, sin esto que algunos indios
afirman, tenian otros que Tupac Inca pasó de largo sin dejar hecho asiento en aquella tierra,
hasta que Guayna Capac reinó; mas, si hemos de mirar estos dichos de los indios, nunca concluiremos
nada.

Saliendo de aquel valle, caminó el rey Inca por lo más de la costa, yendo haciendo el camino
real tan grande y hermoso como hoy parece lo que dél ha quedado; y por todas partes era servido
y salian con presentes á le servir; aunque, en algunos lugares, afirman que le dieron guerra;
pero, no fué parte para quedar sin ser vasallos suyos. En estos valles se estaba algunos dias
bebiendo y dándose á placeres, holgándose de ver sus frescuras. Hicieron por su mandado grandes
edificios de casas y templos. En el valle de Chimo dicen que tuvo recia guerra con el Señor
de aquel valle, y que teniendo su batalla, estuvo en poco quedar el Inca desbaratado de todo
punto; mas, prevaleciendo los suyos, ganaron el campo y vencieron á los enemigos, á los cuales
Tupac Inca, con su clemencia, perdonó, mandándoles, á los que vivos quedaron, en sembrar sus
tierras entendiesen, y no tomasen otra vez las armas para él ni para otros. Quedó en Chimo
su delegado; y lo más destos valles iban con los tributos á Caxamalca; y porque son hábiles
para labrar metales, muchos dellos fueron llevados al Cuzco y á las cabeceras de las provincias,
donde labraban plata y oro en joyas, vasijas y vasos, y lo que más mandado les era. De Chimo
pasó adelante el Inca, y en Parmunquilla[187] mandó hacer una fortaleza, que hoy vemos, aunque
muy gastada y desbaratada.

Estos Yuncas son muy regalados, y los señores, viciosos y amigos de regocijos; andaban á hombros
de sus vasallos; tenian muchas mujeres, eran ricos de oro y plata y piedras y ropa y ganados.
En aquellos tiempos, servíanse con pompa; delante dellos iban truhanes y decidores; en sus
casas tenian porteros; usaban de muchas religiones. Dellos, de voluntad se ofrecieron al Inca,
y otros, se pusieron en armas contra él; mas, al fin, él quedó por soberano Señor dellos todos
y monarca. No les quitó sus libertades ni costumbres viejas, conque usasen de las suyas, que
de fuerza ó de grado se habian de guardar. Quedaron indios diestros que les impusieran en lo
que el rey queria que supiesen, y en aprender la lengua general tuvieran cuidado grande. Pusiéronse
mitimaes, y por los caminos, postas; cada valle tributaba moderadamente lo que dar de tributo
podia que en su tierra, sin lo ir á buscar á la agena, hobiese; á ellos guardábase la justicia,
mas cumplian lo que prometian; cuando nó, el daño era suyo y el Inca cobraba enteramente sus
rentas. Señorío no se tiró á señor natural ninguno, pero sacáronse de los hombres de los valles
muchos, poniéndose de los unos en los otros, y para llevar á otras partes para los oficios
que dicho se han.

Dióse el Inca á andar por los demás valles con el mejor órden que podia, sin consentir que
daño ninguno fuese hecho en los pueblos ni en los campos de las tierras por do pasaban; y los
naturales tenian mucho bastimento en los depósitos y aposentos que por los caminos estaban
hechos. Y con esta órden, el Inca anduvo hasta que llegó al valle de Pachacama, donde estaba
el templo tan antiguo y devoto de los Yuncas, muy deseado de ver por él; y como llegó á aquel
valle, afirman que solamente quisiera que hubiera el templo del sol, más como aquel era tan
honrado y tenido por los naturales, no se atrevió, y contentóse con que se hiciese casa del
sol grande y con mamaconas y sacerdotes, para que hiciesen sacrificios conforme á su religion.
Muchos indios dicen que el mesmo Inca habló con el demonio que estaba en el ídolo de Pachacama,
y que le oyó como era el hacedor del mundo, y otros desatinos que no pongo por no convenir;
y que el Inca le suplicó le avisase con qué servicio seria más honrado y alegre, y que respondió
que le sacrificasen mucha sangre humana y de ovejas.

Pasado lo sobredicho, cuentan que fueron hechos grandes sacrificios en Pachacama por Tupac
Inca Yupanqui, y grandes fiestas; las cuales pasadas, dió la vuelta al Cuzco por un camino
que se le hizo, que va á salir al valle de Xauxa, que atraviesa por la nevada sierra de Pariacaca,
que no es poco de ver y notar su grandeza, y cuán grandes escaleras tiene, y hoy dia se ven
por entre aquellas nieves, para la poder pasar. Y visitando las provincias de la serranía,
y proveyendo y ordenando lo que más convenia para la buena gobernacion, allegó al Cuzco, á
donde fué recebido con grandes fiestas y bailes, y se hicieron en el templo grandes sacrificios
por sus victorias.

La provincia de Chincha fué en lo pasado gran cosa en este reino del Perú, y muy poblada de
gente, tanto, que ántes deste tiempo habian con sus capitanes salido y allegado al Collao,
donde, con grandes despojos que hobieron, dieron la vuelta á su provincia, donde estuvieron
y fueron siempre estimados de los comarcanos, y temidos. El Inca padre de Tupac Inca, se dice
que envió desde los Soras un capitan con gente de guerra, llamado Capac Inca, á que procurase
atraer á los de Chincha al señorío suyo; mas, aunque fué y lo procuró, fué poca parte, porque
se pusieron en arma, y de tal manera se querian defender, quel orejon, lo mejor que pudo, se
volvió; y estuvieron sin ver capitan del Inca ninguno hasta que Tupac Inca los sojuzgó, á lo
quellos mesmos cuentan; porque yo no sé en esto más de lo que ellos mismos cuentan.

Volviendo al propósito, como Tupac Inca hobiese llegado al Cuzco, como se ha escripto, despues
de se haber holgado y dádose á sus pasatiempos los dias que le pareció, mandó de nuevo hacer
llamamiento de gente, con intencion de acabar de señorear los indios de Los Llanos. Su mandado
se cumplió, y prestamente parecieron en el Cuzco los capitanes de las provincias con la gente
de guerra que habian de traer, y despues de puesto en órden lo de la ciudad y lo que más el
rey habia de proveer, salió del Cuzco y abajó á Los Llanos por el camino de Guaytaray. Sabiendo
de su ida, muchos le aguardaban con intencion de le tomar por Señor, y muchos con voluntad
de le dar guerra y procurar de conservar [se] en la libertad que tenian. En los valles de los
Nazcas habia copia de gente y apercibidos de guerra.

Llegado Tupac Inca, hobo embajadas y pláticas entre unos y otros, y aunque hubo algunas porfías
y guerrilla, se contentaron con lo que el Inca dellos quiso por cimiento (así): que se hiciesen
casas fuertes y que hobiese mitimaes, y pagar lo que de tributo les pusieron. Y de aquí fué
el Inca al valle de Ica, á donde halló resistencia más que en lo de la Nazca; mas, su prudencia
bastó [á] hacer, sin guerra, de los enemigos amigos, y se allanaron como los pasados. En Chincha
estaban aguardando si el Inca iba á su valle, puestos más de treinta mill hombres á punto de
guerra, y esperaban favores de los vecinos. Tupac Inca, como lo supo, les envió mensajeros,
con grandes presentes para los señores y para los capitanes y principales, diciendo á los embajadores
que de su parte les hiciesen grandes ofrecimientos, y quél no queria guerra con ellos, sino
paz y hermandad, y otras cosas desta suerte. Los de Chincha oyeron lo que el Inca decia, y
recibiéronle sus presentes, y fueron para él algunos principales con lo que habia en el valle,
y hablaron con él y trataron el amistad, de tal manera, que se asentó la paz, y los de Chincha
dejaron las armas y recibieron á Tupac Inca, que luego movió para Chincha. Esto cuentan los
mesmos indios de Chincha y los orejones del Cuzco; otros indios de otras provincias he oido
que lo cuentan de otra manera, porque dicen que hobo grande guerra; más yo creo que sin ella
quedó por Señor de Chincha.

Llegado el Inca á aquel valle, como tan grande y hermoso lo vió, se alegró mucho. Loaba las
costumbres de los naturales, y con palabras amorosas les rogaba que tomasen de las del Cuzco
las que viesen que les cuadraban, y ellos le contentaron y obedecieron en todo; y dado asiento
en lo que se habia de hacer, partió para Ica, de donde fue á lo que llaman del Guarco, porque
supo questaban aguardándole de guerra; y así era la verdad, porque los naturales de aquellos
valles, teniendo en poco á sus vecinos porque así se habian amilanado y, sin ver porqué, dado
la posesion de sus tierras á rey estraño, y con mucho ánimo se juntaron, habiendo hecho casas
fuertes y pucaraes en la parte perteneciente para ello, cerca de la mar, en donde pusieron
sus mujeres, y hijos. Y andando[188] el Inca con su gente en órden, allegó á donde estaban
sus enemigos, y les envió sus embajadas con grandes partidos, y algunas veces con amenazas
y fieros; mas, no quisieron pasar por la ley de sus comarcanos, que era reconoscer á extranjeros,
y entre unos y otros, al uso destas partes, se trabó la guerra y pasaron grandes cosas entre
ellos. Y como viniese el verano y hiciesen grandes calores, adolesció la gente del Inca, que
fué causa que le convino retirar; y así, con la más cordura que pudo, lo hizo; y los del Guarco
salieron por su valle, y cogieron sus mantenimientos y comidas, y tornaron á sembrar los campos,
y hacian armas, y aparejábanse para, si del Cuzco viniesen contra ellos, que los hallasen apercebidos.

Tupac Inca revolvió sobre el Cuzco; y como los hombres sean de tan poca constancia, como vieron
que los del Guarco se quedaron con lo que intentaron, comenzó á haber novedades entre algunos
dellos, y se rebelaron algunos y apartaron del servicio del Inca.--Estos eran naturales de
los valles de la mesma costa.--Todo fué á oido del rey, y lo que quedaba de aquel verano, entendió
en hacer llamamiento de gente y en mandar salir orejones para que fuesen por todas partes del
reino á visitar las provincias, y determinó de ganar el señorio del Guarco, aunque sobre ello
se le recreciese notorio daño. Y como viniese el otoño y fuese pasado el calor del estío, con
la más gente que pudo juntar, abajó á Los Llanos y envió sus embajadores á los valles dellos,
afeándolos su poca firmeza en presumir de se levantar contra él, y amonestóles que estuviesen
firmes en su amistad, donde nó, certificóles que la guerra les haria cruel. Y como llegase
al principio del valle del Guarco, en las haldas de una sierra, mandó á sus gentes fundar una
ciudad á la cual puso por nombre Cuzco, como á su principal asiento, y las calles y collados
y plazas tuvieron el nombre que las verdaderas. Dijo, que hasta quel Guarco fuese ganado y
los naturales sujetos suyos, habia de permanecer la nueva poblacion, y que en ella siempre
habia de haber gente de guarnicion; y luego que se hobo hecho lo que en aquello se ordenó,
movió con su gente á donde estaban los enemigos, y los cercó, y tan firmes estuvieron en su
propósito, que jamás querian venir á partido ninguno, y tuvieron su guerra, que fué tan larga,
que dicen que duró tres años, los veranos de los cuales el Inca se iba al Cuzco, dejando gente
de guarnicion en el nuevo Cuzco que habia hecho, para que siempre estuviese contra los enemigos.

Y así, los unos por ser señores, y los otros por no ser siervos, procuraban de salir con su
intencion; pero al fin, al cabo de los tres años, los del Guarco fueron enflaqueciendo, y el
Inca, que lo conoció, les envió de nuevo embajadores que les dijiesen que fuesen todos amigos
y compañeros, quel no queria sino casar sus hijos con sus hijas, y por el consiguiente, sustener
en todo confederacion con gran igualdad; y otras cosas dichas con engaño, paresciéndole á Tupac
Inca que merescian grand pena por haberle dado tanto trabajo; y los del Guarco, paresciéndoles
que ya no podrian sustentarse muchos dias, y que con las condiciones hechas por el Inca sería
mejor gozar de tranquilidad y sosiego, concedieron en lo que el rey Inca queria; que no debieran,
porque dejando el fuerte, fueron los más principales á le hacer reverencia, y sin más pensar,
mandó á sus gentes que los matasen á todos, y ellos con gran crueldad lo pusieron por obra,
y mataron á todos los principales y hombres más honrados dellos que allí estaban, y en los
que no lo eran, tambien se ejecutó la sentencia; y mataron tantos como hoy dia lo cuentan los
descendientes dellos y los grandes montones de huesos que hay son testigos; y creemos, que
lo que sobre esto se cuenta es lo que veis escripto.

Hecho esto, mando hacer el rey Inca una agraciada fortaleza tal y de tal manera que yo conté
en la Primera parte[189]. Asentado el valle y puestos mitimaes y gobernador, habiendo oido
las embajadas que le vinieron de los Yuncas y de muchos serranos, mandó ruinar el nuevo Cuzco
que se habia hecho, y con toda su gente dió la vuelta para la ciudad del Cuzco, donde fué recebido
con gran alegria, y se hicieron grandes sacrificios con alabanza suya en el templo y oráculos,
y por el consiguiente se alegró el pueblo con fiestas y borracheras y táquis solenes.

Como Tupac Inca hobiese llegado al Cuzco con tan grandes victorias como se ha escripto, estuvo
algunos dias holgándose en sus banquetes y borracheras con sus mujeres y mancebas, que eran
muchas, y con sus hijos, entre los cuales se criaba Guayna Capac, el que habia de ser rey,
y salia muy esforzado y brioso. Pasadas las fiestas, el gran Tupac Inca pensó de dar vista
al Collao y señorear la tierra que más pudiese de adelante; y para hacerlo, mandó que se apercebiesen
en todas partes gentes, y se hiciesen muchos toldos para dormir en los lugares desiertos. Y
comenzaron á venir con sus capitanes, y alojábanse á la redonda del Cuzco, sin entrar en la
ciudad otros que los que la ley no proibia, y á los unos y á los otros proveian cumplidamente
de todo lo necesario, teniendo en ello cuenta grande los gobernadores y proveedores de la mesma
ciudad. Y como se hobiesen juntado todos los que habian de ir á la guerra, se hicieron sacrificios
á sus dioses, conforme á su ceguedad, poniendo á los adivinos que supiesen de los oráculos
el fin de la guerra; y hecho un convite general y muy espléndido, salió del Cuzco Tupac Inca,
dejando en la ciudad su lugarteniente y su hijo mayor Guayna Capac, y con grand repuesto[190]
y majestad, caminó por lo de Collasuyo, visitando sus guarniciones y tambos reales, y holgóse
por los pueblos de los Canas y Canches.

Entrando en lo de Collao, anduvo hasta Chucuito, donde los señores de la tierra se juntaron
á le hacer fiesta; y habia con su buena órden todo recaudo y abasto de mantenimientos, sin
que faltase á más de trescientas mill personas que iban en sus reales. Algunos señores del
Collao se ofrecieron de ir por sus personas con el mesmo Inca, y con los que señaló, entró
en el palude de Titicaca, y loó á los que entendian en las obras de los edificios que su padre
mandó hacer, cuán bien lo habian hecho. En el templo hizo grandes sacrificios, y dió al ídolo
y sacerdotes dones ricos, conforme á tan gran señor como él era. Volvió á su gente y caminó
por toda la provincia del Collao hasta salir della; envió sus mensajeros á todas las naciones
de los Charcas, Carangas y más gentes que hay en aquellas tierras. Déllas, unos le acudian
á servir y otros á le dar guerra, mas, aunque se la dieron, su potencia era tanta, que bastó
á los sojuzgar, usando con los vencidos de gran clemencia, y con los que se venian, de mucho
amor. En Paria mandó hacer edificios grandes, y lo mesmo en otras partes. Y cierto debieron
pasar á Tupac Inca cosas grandes, muchas de las cuales priva el olvido, por la falta que tienen
de letras, y yo pongo sumariamente algo de lo mucho que sabemos, por lo que oimos y vemos,
los que acá estamos, que pasó.

Yendo victorioso adelante de los Charcas, atravesó muchas tierras é provincias y grandes despoblados
de nieve, hasta que llegó á lo que llamamos Chile, y señoreó y conquistó todas aquellas tierras,
en las cuales dicen que llegaron al rio de Maule. En lo de Chile hizo algunos edificios, y
tributáronle de aquellas comarcas mucho oro en tejuelos. Dejó gobernadores y mitimaes, y puesto
en órden lo que habia ganado, volvió al Cuzco.

Hácia la parte de Levante envió orejones avisados, en hábito de mercaderes, para que mirasen
las tierras que hobiese y qué gentes las mandaban; y ordenadas estas otras cosas, volvió al
Cuzco; de donde afirman que tornó á salir á cabo de algunos dias, y con la gente que convino
llevar, entró en los Andes, y pasó grand trabajo por la espesura de la montaña, y conquistó
algunos pueblos de aquella region, y mandó sembrar muchas sementeras de coca, y que la llevasen
al Cuzco, donde él dió la vuelta.

Y dicen que pasados pocos dias, le dió cierto mal que le causó la muerte, y que encomendando
á su hijo la gobernacion del reino y á sus mujeres é hijos, y diciendo otras cosas, murió.
Y se hicieron grandes lloros y tan notable sentimiento desde Quito hasta Chile, ques extraña
cosa de oir á los indios lo que sobre ello cuentan.

Adonde, ni en qué lugar está enterrado no lo dicen. Cuentan que se mataron grand número de
mujeres y servidores y pajes para meter con él, con tanto tesoro y pedrería, que debió montar
más de un millon; y seria poco, pues los señores particulares se enterraban algunos con más
de cient mill castellanos. Sin la gente tanta que metieron en su sepultura, se ahorcaron y
enterraron muchas mujeres y hombres en partes diversas del reino, y en todas partes se hicieron
lloros por un año entero y se tresquilaron las más de las mujeres, poniéndose todas sogas de
esparto; y acabado el año, se vinieron á hacer sus honras. Y lo que dicen que usaban hacer
no lo quiero poner, porque son gentilidades; y los chripstianos questaban en el Cuzco el año
de mill y quinientos y cincuenta, acuérdense de lo que vieron que se hizo por las honras y
cabo de año de Paulo Inca, con se haber vuelto chripstiano, y sacarán lo que seria en tiempo
del reinado de los reyes pasados, ántes que perdiesen su señorío.

CAP. LXI.--De cómo reinó en el Cuzco Guayna Capac que fué el dozeno rey Inca.

Muerto que fué el gran rey Tupac Inca Yupanqui, se entendió en hacer sus obsequias y entierro
al uso de sus mayores, con gran pompa. Y cuentan los orejones, que de secreto tramaban entre
algunos de cobrar la libertad pasada y eximir de sí el mando de los Incas, y que de hecho salieran
con lo que intentaban, si no fuera por la buena maña que se dieron los gobernadores del Inca
con la gente de los mitimaes y capitanes, que pudieron sustentar en tiempo tan revuelto y que
no tenia rey, lo quel pasado les habia encargado. Guayna Capac no descuidó ni dejó de conocer
que le convenia mostrar valor para no perder lo que su padre con tanto trabajo ganó. Luego
se entró á hacer el ayuno, y el que gobernaba la ciudad le fué fiel y leal. No dejó de haber
alguna turbacion entre los mesmos incas, porque algunos hijos de Tupac Inca, habidos en otras
mujeres que la Coya, quisieron ponerse á pretender[191] la dignidad real, mas el pueblo, que
vian estaba con Guayna Capac, no lo consintió, mas estorbó el castigo que se hizo. Acabado
el ayuno, Guayna Capac salió con la borla muy galano y aderezado, y hizo las cirimonias usadas
por sus pasados, con el fin de las cuales el nombre de rey le pusieron, y así, á grandes voces
decian[192]: Guayna Capac Inca Zapalla tucuillacta uya; que quiere decir; "Guayna Capac solo
es rey; á él oyan todos los pueblos."

Era Guayna Capac, segun dicen muchos indios que le vieron y conocieron, de no muy grand cuerpo,
pero doblado y bien hecho; de buen rostro y muy grave; de pocas palabras, de muchos hechos;
era justiciero y castigaba sin templanza. Queria ser tan temido, que de noche le soñaran los
indios. Comia como ellos usan, y así vivia vicioso de mujeres, si así se le puede decir; oía
á los que le hablaban bien, y creíase muy de ligero: privaron con él mucho los aduladores y
lisonjeros, que entre ellos no faltaban, ni hoy deja de haber; y daba oidos á mentiras, que
fué causa que muchos murieron sin culpa. A los mancebos que tentados de la carne dormian con
sus mujeres ó mancebas, ó con las que estaban en el templo del sol, luego los mandaba matar
á ellos, y á ellas castigo igual. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09586</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>32894</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22296</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Orchestras
have been killed in payment for the good they were going to do, and he sent some Inca Tupac captains
to punish people, but, as I knew, gathered many of the barbarians who killed and those who were
defeated, that the Inca was feeling, but, having large business in his hands, and agree in
person back to Cuzco, he was not to own dalles punishment for what they had done.

In Quito how well it was new to what he had been sent and how much care had his delegates to impose
such people into his service, and how well they were treated and them how they were happy
and did what was commanded them, and many landlords I came every day and brought him great ambassadors
present, and his court was full of major and palaces of pots and vessels of gold and silver and other
great riches .-- In the morning he ate, and from noon to be a bit late, heard in public, accompanied
by his guardian, whom he wanted to talk. After spending the time to be drinking at night, that
turned out to dinner with fire wood, because they did not use tallow or wax, but had tired of the
one or the other.

In Quito left by the captain general and chief steward to a orejon elderly, who all have I was
very knowledgeable and hard and gentle presence, whom they called Chalco Mayta, and he gave
license so he could walk on a platform and served with gold and other freedoms he had a lot.
Ordered him on all things that each moon do him messenger to bring him particular notice of all things
to pass over, and the state of the earth, and fertility della, and the growth of the livestock,
over all what we ordinarily notice, which was the poor who had, who were killed in one year
and he was born, and what has been eScript in the back knew that without it he himself kings in
Cuzco, and having so great way from Quito to Cuzco, which is more than going from Seville
to Rome, by far, was so used as is the way to Seville Triana, that
I can not more expensive.

Dias had the grand Inca Tupac had notice of the fertility of Los Llanos and the beautiful valleys
than they had, and how much they felt the lords of them, and determined to send them messengers
with gifts and presents for the principal, asking that they had for a friend and companion, Quél
wanted to be like him in the suit when passing over the valleys, not war if they wanted to give
them peace, and that up to them from their wives and clothes and take him their own, and other
things in this. And all along the coast had flown and how much new you ladies were Tupac Inca
Yupanqui, and how it was not cruel or vicious or to harm but to the brooding and wanted to
stand against him: and they praised the custom and religion of the Cuzco, the apricots had male
saints, believing that the Incas were the children of the sun, or that they had a deity. And
considering these things and others, identified many without seeing their flags, taking with him
friendship, and so sent him to say with own ambassadors, to which sent many presents to the
king himself, and begged wanted come the valleys to be Dell Server and Holger to see their
freshness, and praising the Inca such a will, again speaking to the
governor of Quito what he had done, left that city to rule the Yuncas.

As Tupac Inca king resolved to go in the valleys of Los Llanos, to attract to its service and
obedience the inhabitants of them, down to what Tumbez and was honorably receive me by natural
whom showed much love Tupac Inca, and then put the suit wore T hose for more content, and praises
the war leading to will not take him as Lord and and have promised to the estimate as to his own children.
They hear happy with their good words and manner with which he treated them, gave honest obedience
to conditions, and allowed be including governors and make buildings because, without it that
some Indians say, others had passed by Tupac Inca made seat while in the land, reigned until Huayna
Capac, but if we look at these sayings of the Indians, never conclude
nothing.

Leaving the valley, walked the Inca king by most of the coast, going by the way real big and beautiful
as what of today seems to have been, and was served everywhere and going to present to serve
him, though in some places, they say they gave war but was not party to be without his subjects.
In this valley was a few days drinking and giving them pleasure, rejoiced to see their freshness.
Made by his command large building houses and temples. Chimo in the valley say they had a fierce
war with the Lord of that valley, and taking their battle, was in little being disrupted all the
Inca point, but, whichever their own, won the field and defeated the enemy, whom Tupac Inca,
with his mercy, spared, commanding, to those who were living in planting their land would
understand, and should not take up arms again to himself or others. He was Chimo to represent
him, and most of these valleys were the tributes to Cajamarca, and they are working for metal working,
many of them were taken to Cuzco and to the heads of provinces, tilled where silver and gold
jewelry, vases and vessels, but it was more ordered them. Chimo passed on the Inca, and Parmunquilla
[187] ordered a fortress we see today, although very worn and broken
up.

These Yuncas are given, and the lords, vicious and friends rejoicing, went to shoulders of
his subjects, had many women, were rich in gold and silver and precious clothing and livestock.
In those days, servíanse with pomp in front of them were crooks and decision-makers, in their
houses had gatekeepers, used in many religions. Dell, will be offered to the Inca and others
took up arms against him, but at last he was by the sovereign lord of it all and monarch. No
freedoms and seized their old habits, use of theirs So that degree of force or they were to save. Indians
were skilled as they impose that the king wanted them to know, and learn the common language
had great care. They stood mitimaes, and roads, clinics, each moderately taxed valley that tribute
to that their land could, without going to look to the Agency, hobiese, watched over them to
justice, more fulfilled what they promised, if not, the damage was his and the Inca earned their
entire income. Lordship is not shot no natural lord but sacáronse of men of the valleys many,
getting to the each other, and to bring other parties to the trades
that this has been.

Inca God to walk in the other valleys in the best order he could, without allowing no harm
was done in the towns or in the fields of land do they passed, and the had many provisions in
natural deposits and quarters that the roads were facts. And with this order, the Inca walked
until he reached the valley of Pachacamac, which was the temple as old and devout Yuncas very
desired to see him as he arrived at that valley, say only wish there was the temple of the
sun, more like that was so honored and taken by the natives, did not dare, and that it should
be contented with house and large sun virgins and priests, for that would make sacrifices according
to his religion. Many Indians say that he himself spoke with the devil Inca was the idol of
Pachacamac, and he heard it was the maker of the world and other nonsense that I do not do not agree;
and the Inca begged to let him know what service would be more honest
and happy, and responded he sacrificed a lot of human and sheep blood.

After the aforesaid, have great sacrifices that were made in Pachacama by Tupac Inca Yupanqui, and
large celebrations, which last, he turned back to Cuzco on a path that was done, what you will
get the Xauxa Valley, which runs through the snowy mountains of Pariacaca, which is something
to see and feel his greatness, and how large steps are, and today are and among those snows,
to get through. And visiting the provinces of the highland and providing and rearranging the most
convenient for good governance, who is close to Cuzco, to where he
was received with great feasts and dances, and made great sacrifices
in the temple for their victories.

Chincha province in the past was much in this kingdom of Peru, and most populated People, therefore,
that before this one time with their masters had left and joined himself to the Collao, where,
with great spoil that hobieron, turned back to his province, where they were and were always
estimated their neighbors, and feared. The father of Tupac Inca Inca, is said Soras sent from
a captain with warriors, called Capac Inca, to obtain Chincha attract the lordship of his own:
but, although he was and what he tried, was low partly because got a weapon, and so it wanted
to defend, quel orejon, the best he could, returned, and were not
seeing any captain until Tupac Inca Inca subjugated, to what T hose
same tale, for I do not know about this more than they themselves.

Returning to the purpose, as Tupac Inca reached the Cuzco hobiese, as eScript, after to be loose
and have given to their hobbies seemed like days, sent it back to People call, with the intention
of ending the Lady Indians of Los Llanos. His command was met, and appeared in Cuzco speedily
masters of the provinces with people of war who were to bring, and put in order after the city
and what more King had to provide, out of Cuzco and down to the plains by way of Guaytaray.
Knowing its way, many were waiting for him with the intention of taking him as Lord, and many
willing to give him war and try to keep [it] in the freedom they had.

In the valleys of the Nazca people had back and ready against war.

Tupac Inca arrived, hobo embassies and talks between them, and although there were some stubbornness
and guerrillas, were content with what the Inca Dellos wanted by the foundation (and) that hiciesen
fortified houses and hobiese mitimaes, and pay tribute to what they put. And here was the Inca to
the valley of Ica, where he found more resistance in the Nazca, but, wisdom enough [to] do,
without war, enemies friends, and were broken as the last. In Chincha waiting if the Inca were
going to the valley, made more than thirty thousand men on the point of war, and hoped to curry favor
with the neighbors. Tupac Inca, as he knew, he sent messengers, with great presents for the
lords and masters and principals, said the ambassadors that of his party's hiciesen great
offers, and chelate did not want war with them, but peace and brotherhood, and other things to
this pass. The Chincha heard what the Inca he said, and received him his present, and were for
him some principal with what was in the valley and talked to him and sought the friendship
so that peace was settled, and Chincha weapons and were left to Tupac Inca, then moved to Chincha.
This counted mesmos Chincha Indians of Cuzco and the dried, other Indians from other provinces
have heard have it otherwise, because they say large hobo war more
I believe that without it was for Lord of Chincha.

Inca come to this valley, so great and beautiful saw it, was delighted. He praised the customs
of the natives, and with loving words I begged them to take those of Cuzco which would see them
add up, and they obeyed him and contented throughout, and given seat when it had to do, went
to Ica, where he was to what they call the Guarco, because questa knew war and turned around,
and it was true, because the natives of those valleys, taking little by their neighbors because
they had so unnerved and do not see why, given possession of their lands to stranger king,
and gathered a lot of courage, having made houses pucaraes strong in the part belonging to
it, near the sea, where they put their wives and children. And walking [188] the Inca with
their people in order, who is close to where they were their enemies, and sent their embassies to
big games, and sometimes threats and fierce, but did not want to go through the law of their
neighbors, who was foreign to Acknowledge, and with each other, the use of these parts, locked
the war and spent great things from them. And come the summer and hiciesen great heat, the people
of the Inca adolesció that was because he agreed to withdraw, and so, with more sanity as he could,
did, and those of Guarco out of its valley, and took their maintenance
and meals, and turned to sow the fields, and they made weapons and
aparejábanse for, if the Cuzco should come against them, found them
apercebidos.

Tupac Inca Cuzco stirred about, and as men are of so little evidence, they saw than the Guarco
were left with what they tried, he began to have news from some of them, and rebelled and departed
from the service some of the Inca .-- These were natural valleys up the same coast .-- All the
king went to hearing, and what remained of that summer, he understood to make calls and send
people out to apricots were all over the kingdom to visit the provinces, and determined to win
the dominion of Guarco, though about it ingrowth was evident harm. As autumn came and went past
the heat of summer, with The more people who might join, down to the Plains and sent their ambassadors
to the valleys of them, afeándolos his unsteadiness in presuming he is up against, and they
were amonestóles firm in their friendship, where not, certificóles that the war would make cruel.
And how to get at first Guarco Valley, in Halden saw, he commanded his people to found a city
??to which his name Cuzco, as his chief seat, and the streets and hills and squares were the
real name. He said that even cattle would quel Guarco the native subjects of his, had to remain
the new settlement, and that it always People had to be quartered, and then hobo who did what
on what was ordered, moved with his people to where they were the enemy, and besieged it, and
so firm were in purpose, never wanted to come to any party, and had his war, which was so long,
saying that lasted three years, the summers of which the Inca went to Cuzco, leaving people quartered
in the new Cuzco he had done, that was always against the enemy.

And so, one to be gentlemen, and the other for not being slaves, tried to leave with his intention,
but finally, after three years, the Guarco were emaciated, and Inca, who met him, I again sent
ambassadors to them that they were all friends dijiesen and colleagues, quel did not want to marry
their sons but his daughters, and the resulting, sustener confederation all very equal, and other
things such deception, Paresce to Tupac Merescian grand Inca punishment for having given so much
work, and the Guarco, Paresce could no longer sustain many days, and that conditions would be
made by the Inca better to enjoy peace and quiet, gave what the Inca king wanted, who should not,
since leaving the fort, were the key to reverence him, and without thinking, commanded his people
that kill them all, and they put him with great cruelty at the hands, and slew all the major
and most honest men them who were there, and in they were not, also be carried out the sentence,
and killed as many as today, we have the descendants Dell and large piles of bones that there
are witnesses, and we believe that what about this account is what you see eScript.

This done, he ordered the Inca king and a graceful strength that so I told in Part [189]. Settled
the valley and put mitimaes and governor, having heard embassies which came from the Yuncas
and many mountain, commanded want to ruin the new Cuzco had been done, and all the people turned
around for the city of Cuzco, where he was received with great joy, and made great sacrifices to praise
him in the temple and oracles and therefore he was glad the town with parties and drinking and
táquis Solenoid.

As Tupac Inca reached the Cuzco hobiese with such great victories as has eScript, was some days
rejoiced at their feasts and drinking with their wives and concubines, who were many, and
their children, including growing up Huayna Capac, who was to be king and came out very courageous
and spirited. After the holidays, the great Tupac Inca thought of giving sight Collao and rule the earth
that could front more, and to do so, he issued apercebiesen people everywhere, and many tents
hiciesen sleeping in desert places. Y began to come with their masters, and to the round alojábanse
Cuzco, without entering the city ??other than the law does not proibia, and to each other and
to dutifully provided everything you need, taking into account this great governors and providers
MESMA city. And as hobiesen together all those who had to go to war, is made sacrifices their gods,
according to his blindness, making wizards, who knew of the oracles the end of the war, and
made a general and very splendid treat, Tupac left Cuzco Inca in the city leaving his lieutenant
and his eldest son Huayna Capac, and spare grand [190] and majesty, so Collasuyo walked, visiting
the seals and real drums, and rejoice by the peoples of the Canas and Canches.

Entering in the Collao, walked up Chucuito, where the lords of the earth together him to make
merry, and had its good order all collection and supply of maintenance without who miss more
than three hundred mill people who were on their real. Some lords Collao offered to go for
their people with the same saddle Inca, and with that said, came In malaria Titicaca, and
Loo to those who understood the works of the buildings that his father commanded to do, how well
they had done. In the temple made great sacrifices, and gave the idol priests and rich gifts,
according to so great a lord as he was. He returned to his people and walked throughout the
province to leave della Collao, sent his messengers to all nations of Charcas, Carangas and more
people who are in those lands. Dellas, flocked around him to serve and others to you make
war, but though it was given, his power was so great that enough to the subjugation, using the
conquered of great mercy, and with which it came, much love. In Paria sent to large buildings,
and do the same elsewhere. And some had Inca Tupac go to great things, many of which deprives
the forgetfulness, the need to have letters, and I summarily put something of how much we know
from what we hear and see, that here we are, what happened.

Going ahead of the Charcas victorious, went through many lands and depopulated provinces and large snow,
until he came to what we call Chile, and lorded over and conquered all the lands, in which they
say they came to the river Maule. As of Chile made some buildings and tributáronle of regions
much gold in ingots. Governors and mitimaes left, and since in order you had won, he returned to
Cuzco.

Towards the Levante sent apricots warned, in the dress of merchants, who would look for hobiese
lands and what the people sent, and ordered these other things, returned to Cuzco, in which
contend that turned to go out after a few days, and with people who agreed lead, went into
the Andes, and spent the grand work of the mountain wilderness, and conquered some villages in
that region, and sent many crops of coca plant, and which led Cuzco,
where he turned around.

And they say past few days, gave him some evil that caused his death, and commending his son
the government of the kingdom and their wives and children, and saying
other things, he died.

And there were great tears and feeling so remarkable from Quito to Chile, strange forests
thing to hear what the Indians on that count.

Where or in what place he is buried not say. That have killed large number of women and servers
and pages to get to him with so much treasure and jewels, which had mounted more than one million,
and would be little, because individual lords were buried some of them over a hundred miles
from Castile. Without so much that people got into his grave and hanged buried many women
and men in different parts of the kingdom, and everywhere were crying for an entire year and
is shorn of most of the women, putting all ropes esparto, and finish the year, came to make
their reputations. And what they say they used to I do not want to because they are nations,
and the Christians Quest in Cuzco year of fifteen hundred and fifty,
remember what they saw was made by the honors and After years of Inca
Paulo, with it having become Christians, and bring forth what would
in time the reign of former kings, rather than lose their sovereignty.

CAP. LXI .-- Of how he reigned at Cuzco Huayna Capac who was the Inca king dozen.

Dead king was the great Inca Tupac Yupanqui, is understood to make their funeral rites and burial
the use of their elders, with great pomp. And have the apricots, which secretly plotted between
freedom to collect some past and hold it the command of the Incas, and in fact leave with what
they intended, if not for the very quick, which gave the governors of the Inca with people
of mitimaes and captains, they could sustain such a troubled time and had no king, they had
charged last nickel. Huayna Capac not neglected or failed to meet that he must show courage to
keep it that his father worked so hard won. Then it came to making the fast, and the city will
ruling was faithful and loyal. Have not stopped some confusion among the Incas mesmos, because
some children of Tupac Inca, have occurred in other Coya women, wanted to pretend to be [191]
the kingship, but the people who Vian was with Huayna Capac, not consent, but interfered with
the punishment that was done. Finish fasting, Huayna Capac went with tassel very gallant and
dressed, and made the cirimonias used by their past, to which the
name of king wore, and so loud voices they said [192]: Inca Huayna
Capac Zapalla tucuillacta Uya, which means, "Huayna Capac only is
king Øyan unto him all peoples.

"

Huayna Capac was, as they say many Indians saw him and knew of no very great body but bent and
well done, good and very serious face, a few words, many facts was righteous and punished without
restraint. I wanted to be as feared, that night I dreamed of Indians. Ate as they use, and
so lived cycle of women, if you can tell, hear to those who spoke well, and believed very light:
long deprived him of flatterers and flattering, that among them there were plenty, and today
there is no longer, and gave ear to lies, was the reason that many died without guilt. For
the young men who slept meat tempted to their wives or concubines,
or with which they were in the temple of the sun, then sent them to
kill to them, and to punish them equally</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>