<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02128</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>225419</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18525</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Vió que alzaban el retrato, que la turba se arremolinaba en circuitos sin fin, y vió agitarse
en el aire multitud de pañuelos blancos que salían de aquel torbellino como una espuma.

La comitiva desordenada siguió por la calle de Atocha y penetró en la Plaza Mayor. Allí se
difundió un poco. Pero después trató de atravesar el arco de la calle de la Amargura para entrar
en Platerías. El gran monstruo midió de una mirada el volumen de sus miembros multiplicados
y la anchura del arco por donde había de pasar. El camello iba á pasar por el ojo de la aguja.
Hubo un movimiento convulsivo de codos, y los abdómenes se deprimieron, giraban los cuerpos,
y algunos sombreros saltaron á impulsos de las repercusiones y choques de tantas cabezas. Algunas
voces trataron de pronunciar una orden para vencer aquella dificultad, problema de obstetricia
sin duda.

--Delante el retrato. Dejen pasar el retrato--decían. Era imposible; la gente se agolpaba de
tal modo, que el retrato no podía pasar. Al fin, tras largos esfuerzos, el retrato pasó por
el arco. Detrás seguía con la mayor confusión la gran masa de gente. La multitud que llenaba
la plaza se había parado y esperaba. El retrato y sus corifeos desembocaron en la calle Mayor;
pero al llegar allí, una sorpresa sin igual detuvo la procesión. Dos filas de soldados formaban
en las Platerías, llegando más allá de la plazuela de la Villa. Las picas de un escuadrón de
lanceros brillaban á lo lejos, y delante de esta tropa estaba, el Capitán General de Madrid,
á caballo, esperando con grande aplomo y entereza. Este hombre avanzó seguido de dos ó tres,
y señalando con el sable, intimó la orden de retirada á los del retrato. Hubo una rápida consulta
de miradas entre éstos. Una autoridad civil se acercó también, y con los mejores ademanes dijo
que se fuera cada cual á su casa y renunciaran á aquella manifestación, porque el Gobierno
estaba resuelto á que no dieran un paso más. El aspecto de la tropa impresionó vivamente á
los del retrato; además, éstos contaban con la ayuda del regimiento de Sagunto, y el regimiento
de Sagunto estaba encerrado y perfectamente custodiado en su cuartel.

Trataron, sin embargo, de pasar adelante, y dijeron que aquella manifestación era puramente
moral; que no trataban de producir ningún trastorno, ni era agresiva su actitud, ni tenían
más objeto que tributar un homenaje de admiración al héroe que había dado la libertad á su patria.

"¡Cada uno á su casa! Atrás el retrato", dijo resueltamente Morillo.

La defensa era imposible. La procesión no tenía armas.

La supuesta debilidad del Gobierno se había trocado en inquebrantable firmeza. Algunos empezaron
á desertar, desfilando por la calle de Milaneses y la plazuela de San Miguel. El retrato descansaba
en tierra y se movía adelante y atrás, poco seguro en manos de sus portadores. Estos hablaron:
pero todo fué inútil: la gente empezó á retroceder, algunos á gritar, y hubo también quien
quiso oponer resistencia á la tropa.

Entre tanto el gentío que ocupaba la plaza permanecía inmóvil. ¿Quién era aquél que entre tanta
gente se elevaba, y agitando las manos, profería voces que la muchedumbre aplaudía? El orador
hablaba bien, sin duda: grandes aclamaciones acogían sus palabras; pero los continuos empellones,
los gritos de los pisoteados y estrujados no permitían á aquél expresarse con desahogo.

Algunos pedían silencio; pero el silencio en toda la plaza era imposible. A lo mejor, los que
en el arco discutían con la autoridad, retrocedieron al ver que la tropa resistía. La confusión
entonces llegó á su término. El orador continuó su filípica; pero la continuó excitando al
pueblo á que no cediera en su empeño de verificar la manifestación. Estaba lívido, anhelante,
y cada palabra suya era como un latigazo que estimulaba á la muchedumbre á seguir adelante.

En tanto las tropas avanzaban despejando la plaza, y algunos eran tan osados, que delante de
los caballos oponían resistencia y vociferaban apostrofando á Morillo y á su gente.

--¡A esos que gritan!--dijo el que mandaba el piquete. Arremolinóse el gentío. Muchos corrieron
á escape. Otros dieron vueltas, arrastrados por la oleada, ó permanecieron turbados sin saber
qué partido tomar. Lázaro calló.

--¿Quién gritaba?--dijo el capitán,--A los que gritan. Prender á los que gritan.

Lázaro quiso huir; pero el brazo vigoroso de un soldado le detuvo fuertemente.

--Prender á los que gritan. Este es el predicador. ¡A ese!

Lázaro pasó de una mano fuerte á otra fortísima. Apenas se daba cuenta de que le habían prendido.
Creyó que le soltarían en seguida, é intentó desasirse, aunque inútilmente.

-¡Atrás, atrás! ¡Fuera de la plaza!--continuaba el capitán.

Y era bien obedecido, porque el gentío se desbandaba á toda prisa. La procesión fracasó. El
retrato quedó hecho trizas en medio de la plaza; la tropa tomó todas las entradas.

¿Qué fué de Lázaro? Un cuarto de hora después entraba, honrosamente custodiado, por las puertas
de la cárcel de Villa, y era introducido también honrosamente en un tristísimo, obscuro y sucio
calabozo.

CAPÍTULO XIII

#No llega el esperado.--Llegada de un importuno.#

De todos los procedimientos que el espíritu emplea para atormentarse á sí mismo, el más terrible
es esperar. Contra esto no hay remedio. Parece que ha de ser fácil resolverse á no esperar,
apartar la imaginación de la cosa esperada, y vivir sólo en un punto de la vida, en un momento
del tiempo, sin esa dolorosa aspiración á lo venidero que desquicia el ser, sacándole de su centro.

Cuando se espera lo que ha de llegar las horas son siglos; cuando se espera lo que debió llegar,
las horas vuelan como segundos. Clara estaba á la hora de las diez con el alma suspensa, trémula
y atenta, llena de inquietud y zozobra. Pasa de las diez, y el viajero no viene; el reloj vuela
de las once á las doce, y de las doce á la una. Pascuala tenía mucho miedo, porque el ruido
de gentes que en la calle se sentía aumentaba á cada hora. Las dos estaban sentadas en el cuarto
interior, y no decían cosa ninguna, ni la criada contaba aquellos cuentos de las ninfas y el
dragoncillo, que había aprendido en su pueblo, ni la huérfana se reía con la franca expansión
y natural sencillez de su carácter. Ambas estaban muy silenciosas: se miraban con ansiedad
cuando algún ruido se sentía en la escalera; y al cerciorarse de que no era lo que aguardaban,
caían la una en su abatimiento indiferente, la otra en su calmosa, melancólica y disimulada
agitación.

Clara, á la madrugada, entró en el período de las conjeturas; forma con que el espíritu se
da todos los tormentos imaginables. ¿Qué le había pasado? ¿Volcaría el coche? ¿le habrían salido
ladrones con aquellos tremendos trabucos que pintan en las estampas? ¿Habría desistido del
viaje? ¿Tendría tal vez amores con alguna muchacha del pueblo? ¿Le detendría alguna partida
de realistas? Todo le ocurría menos lo cierto. En estos momentos fácil es tranquilizarse teniendo
un poco de serenidad; pero nadie la tiene, y una ceguera profunda sustituye á la normal lucidez
del entendimiento. Basta razonar en calma y decir: "¿No ha venido? Se habrá detenido casualmente.
Mañana vendrá." Pero en vez de hacer este lógico razonamiento, lo que generalmente se piensa
es esto: "¿No ha venido? Pues se ha muerto: le mataron."

Luego la noche contribuye á este tormento; la noche, que á todo da formas horribles, lo mismo
á las cosas materiales que á las visiones internas. Clara, que no había podido ni podía dormir,
no cesaba de percibir informes, bultos, sangre, obscuridad, repentinamente opuesta á una gran
luz que alumbra horrores. Da calentura esa situación. Impaciencia febril se apodera de la sangre
que se agita y circula, como si la rapidez de su marcha acelerase la llegada de lo que se espera.
Esta contrariedad de nuestro deseo es más terrible, porque es lenta, sin límites. Delante no
se ve sino la eternidad. No vienen á la mente las modificaciones que puede traer el próximo
día. Aquella noche y aquella soledad parece que no han de tener fin.

Las primeras luces del día no hicieron, sin embargo, otra cosa que aumentar su tristeza. ¡Ayer!
¡Desde ayer le había estado esperando! Deseaba salir fuera y correr, preguntando á todos por
el desventurado joven. Abrió el balcón, miró á la calle, creyendo que iba á verle pasar, y
examinó á todos los transeúntes. Entonces le llamó la atención una persona que, fija en la
esquina, la miraba con tenacidad. Segura de que no era él volvió la cara, y no se cuidó más
de aquella persona.

Cerró el balcón, porque sentía fatiga y mucha necesidad irresistible de dormir. Fué á su cuarto,
y sentada en una silla, recostó la cabeza sobre la cama. Pero en vez de dormir empezó á cavilar
con tanto desvarío y agitación como durante la noche. Elías tampoco había vuelto. ¿Qué sería
de él? ¡Oh, qué luz! Tal vez le había encontrado y estarían juntos en alguna parte.

En esto entró Pascuala que venía de la calle. La alcarreña se acercó á Clara, adornando la
redonda y vasta fachada de su cara con impertinente sonrisa.

--¿Sabe usted lo que ha pasao?

--¿Qué? ¿qué hay?--dijo Clara con interés.

--Que aquel caballerito del otro día ... pues ... el señor militar ... me paró en la esquina.

--¿Y á mí qué me importa eso?

--Que dice que viene acá.

--¡Jesús, acá! ¿Y á qué viene acá? Estamos solas.

--Pues es un caballero muy cumplido.

--¿Si? Pues no me he fijado.

--¿No le vió usted el otro día aquí ... cuando el señor vino malo?

--Sí: parecía una buena persona. ¿Pero á qué quiere volver aquí?

--Usted bien se lo malicia. ¡Ah, qué picarona es usted! En aquel momento sonaron en el bolsillo
de Pascuala las pesetas que el militar le había dado. Después se sintieron pasos en la escalera
y sonó muy débilmente la campanilla.

--Es él--dijo la alcarreña.

Y antes que Clara pudiera impedírselo, la moza corrió, abrió la puerta, y el militar, que ya
conocemos, entró en el pasillo, se descubrió con respeto y se acercó á Clara.

--¿A quién buscaba usted?--dijo Clara.--No está: ha salido.

--Sí está, no ha salido,--contestó el militar con aplomo.

--¿Quién? ¿Pero á quién buscaba usted?

--Fácil es comprender que no busco á ese viejo, cuyo trato aleja en vez de atraer á las personas.

--¿Pero qué quiere decir? ¿á qué viene usted?--le preguntó Clara con ligera expresión de alarma.--Estoy
sola, váyase usted.

--Por lo mismo no me voy.

--Si usted no se va, llamaré, gritaré,--dijo Clara, resuelta sin duda á hacer lo que decía.

--Entonces reñiremos,--afirmó el militar con sonrisa de amistosa franqueza, que desarmó en
parte el enojo de Clara.

--¡Por Dios, que va á llegar! ¿Pero quién es usted? ¿A qué viene usted aquí? ¿Quién le ha dado
licencia para entrar? Usted es el que vino el otro día con él. Ya le reconozco; pero no entiendo
á qué viene hoy. ¡Pascuala, Pascuala!

--No me mire usted como enemigo. Mi entrada ha sido singular; pero no soy un ladrón ni un asesino.
Vengo como amigo: traigo paz y amistad. No tenga usted miedo, Clara. Vengo como amigo. Ya nos
conocemos de un solo día, cuando vine aquí sosteniendo á ese pobre señor.

--¡Oh! y ahora puede venir--dijo Clara alarmada. Márchese usted, por Dios. Yo no le conozco,
ni me importa todo eso que me ha dicho. Si él llega....

--Lo que menos me importa es ese viejo--contestó el militar.--Antes me interesaba un poco.
Creí que era de usted pariente, su esposo tal vez. Pero después he sabido que es un tiranuelo
que vive para martiriza á una pobre huérfana, que se muere da melancolía encerrada aquí. No
puedo ver con indiferencia que una persona tan guapa, tan amable, tan digna de ser feliz, pase
la vida en poder de esa fiera.

--¡Oh! Pues yo estoy bien así. Le agradezco á usted su bondad--contestó Clara;--pero no es
necesaria. Váyase usted, por Dios.

--No me iré, no--dijo el militar, exaltándose un poco. Hace algunos días que me preocupa la
idea de los martirios que usted debe sufrir. Siento un deseo muy grande de libertarla á usted
de ese maniático, y creo que realizaré este propósito. He pasado por ahí cien veces al día
y me ha dado horror el aspecto sombrío de esta casa, sepulcro en vida de tan bella criatura.
Usted se reirá de mí, lo comprendo. Le parecerá extraño este interés que tomo por una persona
á quien sólo he visto una vez; pero de este misterio no hay que hablar ahora. Lo que importa
es que usted se decida á hacer lo que yo le aconseje. Sepa usted que he jurado no permitir
que muera aquí de hastío y soledad. Estoy seguro de que usted, que con tanta sencillez me comunicó
la única vez que nos vimos parte de sus desventuras, tendrá hoy la confianza que necesito,
sabrá apreciar la nobleza de mis propósitos y no se opondrá á que se realicen.

Clara no sabía qué contestar. Estaba confundida al ver el generoso y fraternal interés que
tenía por ella una persona á quien había visto tan poco. Esto hubiera llenado de orgullo á
otra mujer; pero Clara era muy modesta, y ante aquella manifestación afectuosa no tuvo más
que gratitud y vergüenza. Nunca creyó merecer aquello.

--Yo lo agradezco mucho, señor--dijo;--pero....

La verdad es que no podía decirle que era feliz y que deseaba continuar aquel género de vida.
Era cierto lo que el militar decía. Era imposible vivir en compañía de aquella fiera. ¿Pero
acaso no esperaba su salvación de otra persona? Esta idea la indujo á rechazar con más energía
las ofertas que aquél le hacía.

--Usted no conoce á la persona con quien vive--continuó el militar.--Usted no le conoce, yo
sí: ya me he informado de su carácter y de sus ideas. No sólo es un hombre extravagante é intratable,
sino un fanático sin corazón, un hombre feroz, de perversos instintos y cálculos terribles.
No: usted no puede seguir más tiempo en manos de ese hombre, que no es su pariente, ni su amigo:
que se llama su protector, para hacer de usted una víctima de su orgullo brutal.

Clara comprendió, por la vehemencia con que el joven hablaba, que era cierto su interés, y
conoció también que la pintura que del viejo hacía no era exagerada. El desconocido obraba
con la mayor nobleza, sinceridad y buena fe. Era uno de esos caracteres inclinados á las aventuras
difíciles y que implicaban la salvación peligrosa de los que sufrían. Su espíritu caballeresco,
su corazón inclinado al bien, hallaron en aquel suceso un motivo de ocupación, y dedicó toda
su actividad á la realización del más generoso propósito. Además, un sentimiento bastante enérgico
de simpatía hacia aquella pobre huérfana, le impulsaba á proceder con tanta diligencia. Más
adelante conoceremos el nombre y los hechos de este noble, caballero.

--Pero no esté usted más tiempo aquí--dijo Clara.--¿Cómo quiere usted convencerme de que se
interesa por mí, si precisamente estando aquí me prueba lo contrario? Si él viene y le encuentra
en la casa....

--No dirá nada. Ese hombre es tan miserable, que no le importa ni la felicidad ni el honor
de usted: todo lo mirará con indiferencia. A usted no le queda más amparo que yo.

La huérfana, al oír estas palabras sintió un frío en el alma. El momento en que eran dichas
hacía que parecieran una gran verdad. Su único, legítimo y verdadero amigo no vendría. Ya no
le quedaba más amparo que el de un advenedizo.

--Nada más que yo; pero es bastante--continuó el joven con afectada voz.--Siga usted el plan
que yo le marque: no haga usted caso de ese viejo. Yo seré para usted todo lo que puede ser
un hombre de corazón y honradez. Tenga usted en mí la confianza que se tiene en lo que nos
ha de salvar.... Y ahora, Clara, me voy. Pero no tardaré en volver á dar mis órdenes á la pobre
prisionera, cuya felicidad pende de mí. ¡Qué orgullo siento en esto! Yo estaré siempre alerta.
Si le ocurre á usted una nueva desventura, no necesita avisarme. Yo me hallaré aquí para socorrerla
y animarla. No le queda á usted más amparo que yo. Piénselo usted bien. Adiós.

La decisión de aquel hombre desconocido, insinuado tan novelescamente en los secretos de la
casa, era muy firme. Se había propuesto emprender una aventura generosa, á que le inclinaban
al mismo tiempo un sentimiento de simpatía, y el deseo inveterado en él, de hacer bien.

Si había un poco de egoísmo en él, después lo veremos. Ya se marchaba, cuando Pascuala salió
de la cocina asustada, y dijo:

--¡El amo!

--No abras--dijo Clara temerosa.--Espera: escóndase usted.

Pero Elías, que tenía llave, no necesitaba que le abrieran para entrar.

--No importa--dijo el militar, que trataba de serenar á Clara.

Coletilla abrió y entró. Venía cabizbajo y abstraído. Dió algunos pasos por el corredor sin
ver al intruso; mas al llegar al extremo, notó aquel bulto, alzó la cabeza, y vió al joven,
que se inclinaba ante él con mucho respeto.

CAPÍTULO XIV

#La determinación.#

--¿Qué busca usted? ¿quién es usted? ¿qué hace usted aquí?

--¿No me conoce usted? Soy el que hace unos días le trajo á usted muy mal parado á su casa,
y venía á ver si estaba usted ya completamente restablecido.

--Si, señor; estoy bueno--contestó bruscamente, y entrando en la sala, á donde le siguió el
joven:--¿no se ofrece nada más?

--Nada más, y me retiro: acabo de llegar--dijo con afectada naturalidad el militar.--Me retiro
repitiéndole que me intereso mucho por su salud.

--Bien: ya me lo dijo usted el otro día,--respondió Coletilla dirigiendo miradas recelosas
á Clara y á Pascuala.

--¿Y no me manda usted nada?

--Nada más sino que me deje usted en paz. ¿No va usted á la procesión? Está muy lucida.

--No estoy para procesiones.

--¿Le gusta á usted saber lo que pasa en las casas de los realistas?--añadió el anciano con
el acento amargo y receloso propio de su carácter.--Aquí no se conspira. Y si yo conspirara,
lo haría de modo que no vinieran á sorprenderme los lechuguinos de la Milicia Nacional.

Clara estaba temblando. La parecía que el militar, ofendido por aquel insulto, iba á desenvainar
el tremendo sable que llevaba en la cintura y á descargarlo sobre la cabeza del realista. Pero
aquel sonrió desdeñosamente y dijo:

--Amigo, veo que me juzga usted mal. Puede estar seguro de que no me ocuparé en delatarle.
¿Qué daño puede hacer usted?

--¿Yo?... Daño....--respondió el fanático con una mueca feroz, que en él equivalía á la sonrisa.

--Poco será el que usted haga y por poco tiempo. Eso se lo juro á usted. Con que voy á hacerle
el favor de marcharme. Adiós.

Dirigióse á la salida, no sin tratar de expresar á Clara con una mirada lo que antes le había
dicho con muchas palabras, es decir, que confiara en él y esperara. Hubiera querido verse acompañado
de la joven hasta la puerta; pero la infeliz no se atrevió. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02362</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1319</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17322</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

He saw that lifted the portrait, which the crowd swirled in endless circuits and saw agitated
in the air crowd of white handkerchiefs coming out of the turmoil as a foam.

The disorderly procession went down the street from Atocha and entered the Plaza Mayor. There spread
a little. But then tried to cross the street arc to enter the Bitterness in silver. The great
monster was measured at a glance the number of its members multiplied arch width and the way he
had to pass. The camel was going to go through the eye of the needle. There was a convulsive
movement of elbows, and the abdomens became depressed, turned the bodies and some hats jumped impelled
by the impact and shock of many heads. Some voices tried to pronounce an order to overcome this
difficulty, a problem of obstetrics no doubt.

- In front of the
portrait.

Pass up the portrait - said. It was impossible, people flocked to Thus, the portrait could not
happen. Finally, after long efforts, the picture passed the arc. Behind the more confusion
was the great mass of people. The crowd that filled the square was standing and waiting. The
portrait and its lackeys resulted in the High Street; but once there, unparalleled surprise stopped
the procession. Two rows of soldiers were in Platerías, reaching beyond the square of the town.
The stakes of a squad lances gleaming in the distance, and before the troops were, Captain General
of Madrid, horseback, waiting with great poise and courage. This man came, followed by two or
three, and pointing with his sword, summoned the removal order to the portrait. There was a
quick consultation of glances between them. A civil authority also approached and said the best manners
to leave everyone to his house and to give up the demonstration, because the government was determined
to not go one step further. The appearance of a vivid impression to the troops the portrait,
besides, they had the help of Sagunto regiment and the regiment Sagunto was locked and well
guarded in their barracks.

They tried, however, move on, and said that this demonstration was purely moral, not trying
to cause any disturbance, nor was aggressive attitude, or were more object of admiration paid
tribute to the hero who gave freedom to his country.

"Every man to his house! Behind the portrait," Morillo said resolutely.

The

defense was impossible. The procession had no weapons.

The alleged weakness of the government had turned to unwavering firmness. Some began to desert,
parading through the streets of Milan and the square of San Miguel. The portrait rested ground
and moved back and forth, unsure in the hands of its bearers.

They spoke: but all was useless: people began to recede, some screaming, and there were also those
who wanted to resist the troops.

Meanwhile, the crowd stood still occupied the square.

Who was it that so many people rose, and shaking hands, voices uttering the crowd cheering? He
spoke well, no doubt: big cheers welcomed his words, but the constant jostling, the cries of the
downtrodden and crushed not allow one to express relief.

Some called for silence, but silence the whole place was impossible.

At best, those who in the arc discussed with the authorities, fell to see that the troops resisted.
Confusion then came to a close.

He continued his invective, but the continued exiting the not to give to people in their efforts
to verify the event. He was pale, panting, and every word was like a whip that encouraged the
crowd to move forward.

As the troops advanced clearing the square, and some were so bold,
that before horses resisted and shouted apostrophizing Morillo and
his people.

- To those who cry! - Said the commander of the picket.

Arremolinóse the crowd. Many ran to escape.

Others took turns, carried by the wave, or remained troubled, not knowing what to do. Lazarus was
silent.

- Who cried? - Captain said, - To those who cry. Seize the screaming.

Lazarus tried to flee, but the strong arm of a soldier stopped him strongly.

- Seize the screaming.

This is the preacher.

In this!

Lazarus went from a strong hand to another very strong. Just realized that he had on. He thought
he would release him immediately and tried to free herself, but to no avail.

- Back, back! Outside the plaza! - Continued the captain.

And it was well obeyed, because the crowd was quickly disbanded. The procession failed. The picture
was shattered in the middle of the square, the troops took all the entries.

What happened to Lazarus? Fifteen minutes after entering, honorably guarded the gates Villa of
the jail, and was honorably also introduced a sad, dark and dirty cell.

CHAPTER XIII

# Do not get the expected arrival of an unwelcome .--.

#

Of all the procedures that the spirit used to torment himself, the most terrible is expected.
Against this there is no remedy. Seems to be easily resolved not to wait, divert the imagination
of the thing hoped for, and live by only one life at a time time, without that painful aspiration
for the future that unsettles the self, leading him out of the center.

When you expect what is to come times are centuries, when what should have been expected to arrive,
flying hours and seconds.

Clara was at the time of the ten with the soul in suspense, trembling and attentive, full of
restlessness and anxiety. Spend ten, and the traveler is not, the clock flies eleven to twelve,
and twelve to one. Pascuala was very afraid, because the noise of people in the street was increased
every hour. The two were sitting in the room interior, and did not say any thing, nor the maid had
those tales of nymphs and little dragon, who had learned in his village, and the orphan was laughing
with the booming and natural simplicity of his character. Both were very quiet, looked anxiously
when some noise is felt on the stairs and make sure that was not what I waited, fell in his
despondency one indifferent, the other on her calmly, melancholy
and hidden agitation.

Clara, at dawn, entered the period of speculation, forming the spirit gives all the torments
imaginable. What had happened? "Would overturn the car? Do you have left Thieves with those
tremendous trabucos painting in prints? Had he abandoned the trip? Perhaps Would love with
some girl in the village?

Would you stop a game of realistic? All he could think less right. Right now it is easy to reassure
taking a bit of serenity, but nobody does, and a blindness to the normal deep insight replaced
understanding. Calm enough reason to say: "Did not come? You have stopped casually. Tomorrow
will come. "But instead of doing this logical reasoning, it is generally
thought is this: "Do not you come?

For it is dead: killed him."

Then the night contributes to this torment the night, which gives
to every horrible ways, as to material things than to the visions.

Clara, who had failed or could not sleep, never ceased to receive
reports, bumps, blood, darkness, suddenly opposed to a large light
that shines horrors.

Da fever that situation.

Feverish impatience creeps into the blood that stirs and circulates
as if the speed of its march accelerate the arrival of what is expected.

The disappointment of our desire is more terrible, because it is slow,
with no limits.

No front but eternity is.

Do not come to mind the changes that can bring next day.

That night and the loneliness seems to have no end in sight.

The first light of day did, however, only increase their sadness. Yesterday! Since yesterday he
had been waiting for! I wanted to get out and run, asking you all for the unfortunate young man.
He opened the balcony, looked into the street, thinking that I would
see him pass, and considered to all passersby.

Then he noticed a person who sets the corner, looking at her tenacity.

Confident that he was not turned away, and did not care more of that person.

Closed the balcony, because he felt fatigue and many irresistible
urge to sleep.

He went to his room and sitting in a chair, rested his head on the
bed.

But instead of sleep began to ponder with such as delirium and agitation
overnight.

Elijah had not returned. What would it? Oh, what light! Maybe he'd
found and would be together somewhere.

Then there came Pascuala coming from the street.

The Alcarrian came to Clara, decorating round and broad front of
his face with cheeky smile.

- Do you know what is going on?

- What?

What's up? - Clara said with interest.

- That this gentleman the other day ... well ... Mr. military ... I stood in the corner.

- And what do I care?

- That says it comes here.

- Jesus, here! And why come here? We are alone.

- As it is a very accomplished gentleman.

- Yes? Well I have not noticed.

- Did not you saw the other day here ... when the Lord came bad?

-
Yes, like a good person.

But back to what you want here?

- You either it maliciously. Oh, you naughty! At that moment in his pocket rang Pascuala the
pesetas that the military had given him. Then he felt footsteps on the stairs and the bell sounded
faintly.

- Is he - said Alcarria.

And before Clara could stop him, the damsel ran, opened the door, and the military, which know,
entered the hall, was found with respect and went up to Clara.

- Who were you looking for? - Clara said .-- It is not: it has gone.

- If you are, not out, - said the military with aplomb.

- Who? But who were you looking for?

- It is easy to understand that do not look that old, whose deal away rather than attract people.

-
But what do you mean? What's you? - Clara asked with a slight look of alarm .-- I alone, leave
you.

- For the same reason I will not.

- If you do not leave, call, yell, - said Clara, certainly determined to do what he said.

- Then reñiremos - military said with a smile of friendly frankness
that disarmed in Clara's anger part.

- For God, who is about to arrive!

But who are you? What you come here? Who has given permission to enter? You are the one who
came the other day with him. Because I recognize, but do not understand to what is today.
Pascuala, Pascuala!

- Do not look at me as an enemy. My entry was unique, but I'm not a thief or a murderer. I come
as a friend, bring peace and friendship. Do not be afraid, Clara. I come as a friend. And we know
of a single day when I came here to this poor guy holding.

- Oh! and can now come - said Clara alarmed. Go away you, God. I do not know him I do not care
all that I said. If he comes ....

- The last thing I care about is that old - he answered .-- Before the military was interested
a little. You thought it was relative, perhaps her husband.

But then I know that is a petty tyrant who lives to torment a poor orphan, who dies giving
melancholy enclosed here. No I can see with indifference that someone so beautiful, so kind,
so worthy of being happy, go life in the hands of this beast.

-
Oh! Well, I'm fine.

We appreciate your kindness - Clara answered, - but not necessary. Go away, by God.

- I will not go, no - the military said, getting excited a little. A few days ago that I am
concerned idea of ??martyrdom that you must suffer. I feel a strong desire to liberate you of this
maniac, and I think I will realize this purpose. I've been there a hundred times a day and horror
has given me the dark side of this house, grave in life so beautiful creature. You will laugh at me,
I understand. It might seem strange that I have taken this interest
a person whom I've only seen once, but this mystery not talk now.

What matters is that you decide to do what I advise. You know, I've sworn not to allow here
die of boredom and loneliness. I'm sure you, so simply told me the only time we saw some of
his misadventures, have the confidence I need today, will appreciate
the nobility of my purposes and will not object to that conduct.

Clara did not know what to say.

I was confused to see the generous and fraternal interest was to
a person whom she had seen so little.

This would be proud to another woman, but Clara was very modest,
and before that had no affectionate demonstration that gratitude and
shame.

Never thought to deserve that.

- I really appreciate it, sir - said, - but ....

The truth is that I could tell he was happy and wanted to continue
that kind of life.

It was true what the military said.

It was impossible to live in the company of that beast.

But perhaps did not expect their salvation from another person? This idea led to more vigorously
reject the offers that you did.

- You do not know the person with whom you live - continued military
.-- You do not know him, I yes: I have already informed of his character
and his ideas.

Not only is a flamboyant man and intractable, but a fanatic without a heart, a fierce man of perverse
instincts and horrible calculations.

No: you can not go longer in the hands of this man, who is not your relative or friend: is
called its guard, to make you a victim of brutal pride.

Clearly understood by the vehemence with which the boy spoke, it was
certainly his interest, and also known that the old paint was not
exaggerated.

The stranger was acting with the highest nobility, sincerity and good faith. He was one of
those characters inclined to adventures difficult and dangerous involving the salvation of the
suffering.

His spirit of chivalry, his heart for good, in that event found a reason for occupation, and devoted
its activity to the completion of the most generous purpose. In addition, a very strong feeling
of sympathy for this poor orphan, he was moved to proceed with such
diligence.

More later we will know the name and deeds of this noble gentleman.

- But you is not here any longer - Clara said .-- How do you convince
me that interested in me, if just being here proves to me otherwise?

If he comes and finds him at home ....

- Do not say anything. That man is so miserable, that does not care neither happiness nor honor
you: everything look with indifference. You has no more protection than me.
The orphan, when he heard these words he felt a chill in the soul.
The timing was such made them look like a great truth. Its sole, legitimate
and true friend would not come. No he had more protection than an
upstart.

- Nothing more than me, but it is enough - the young man
with affected voice you follow the plan .-- I will check: If you do
not that old. I will for you all that can be a man of heart and honesty.
You have in me the confidence that what we have has to be saved ....
And now, Clara, I go. But I shall soon return to give my orders to
the poor prisoner, whose happiness depends on me. What pride I feel
at this! I am always alert. If you think of a new misfortune, no need
to tell me. I find myself here to help her and cheer. He has no more
protection to you than me. Think you well. Goodbye.

The unknown man's
decision, suggested as novel in the secrets of home, was very firm.
It was proposed to undertake an adventure generous, he bowed to at
the same time a feeling of sympathy, and confirmed in him the desire,
to do well.

If there was a bit of selfishness in it, then we will
see. Since he left, when left Pascuala scared of the kitchen and said:

-
The Master!

- Do not open - Clara said .-- Wait fearful, hiding you.

But
Elias, who had a key, you need not open for entry.

- No matter -
said the officer, who was trying to calm Clara.

Opened and tagline.
Came downcast and withdrawn. Took a few steps down the corridor without
see the intruder, but to get to the end, he noted that bulk, looked
up and saw the young man who bowed before him with respect.

CHAPTER
XIV

# The determination. #

- What do you look? Who are you? What
are you doing here?

- Would not you know me? I few days ago brought
to you very badly to his house, and went to see if you were already
fully recovered.

- Yes, sir, I'm good - snapped, and went into the
room, where he followed the young man - not offered anything else?

-
Nothing more, and I retire, I have just arrived - said the military
naturally affected .-- I retire repeating that I care very much for
your health.

- Well, since you told me the other day - said glancing
suspicious Coletilla to Clara and to Pascuala.

- Did not send me
anything?

- Nothing more but I leave you in peace. Are not you going
to the procession? It is very lucid.

- I'm not for processions.

-
Do you like them you know what happens in the houses of the royalists?
- Said the old man bitter and suspicious accent typical of his character
.-- Here there is a conspiracy. And if I conspired, so you would not
come to amaze the dandies of the National Militia.

Clara was shaking.
The military seemed that, offended by this insult, was about to draw
his the tremendous saber at his waist and to download it over the
head of the realist. But he smiled disdainfully and said:

- Dude,
I see that I judged you wrong. You can be sure to give him away I
will not. What harm can you do?

- Me? ... ....-- Damage the fan responded
with a fierce grin, that it was equivalent to the smile.

- Soon will
you do and for a short time. That I swear to you. With that I shall
make the favor of leaving. Goodbye.

He went to the exit, not without
trying to express to Clara with a look which he had previously that
in so many words, that is, to trust him and wait. Would have liked
to be accompanied the girl to the door, but dared not unhappy</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>