<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04603</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>166099</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18238</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Era de pieles de zorro azul, y a pesar de la estatura de Rafael, sus bordes rozaban el suelo.
El joven comprendió que le habían echado sobre los hombros unos cuantos miles de francos, y
tímido, con temblorosa mano, recogía el borde, temeroso de pisarlo.

Leonora reía de su timidez.

--No se encoja usted; no importa que lo estropee. ¡Parece que lleva usted un velo sagrado por
el respeto con que lo trata! No vale la pena. Yo sólo uso esta capa en los viajes. Me la regaló
un gran duque en San Petersburgo.

Y para asegurar más su desprecio por el rico manto, embozó al joven en él, golpeando sus hombros
para que amoldara más a su cuerpo.

Lentamente volvían a la sala donde estaba el balcón, mientras en el comedor sonaban carcajadas
saludando la aparición del barbero, envuelto en su lujosa bata. Cupido sacaba partido de la
situación para provocar la risa, y recogiéndose la cola y atusándose las patillas, braceaba
cual una tiple en una romanza dramática cantando de falsete. Los hortelanos reían como locos,
olvidando el agua que llenaba su casa; Beppa abría desmesuradamente sus ojos, admirada por
la figura, las contorsiones de aquel señor y la gracia con que estropeaba los versos italianos,
y hasta la pobre doña Pepa se retorcía en su silla, admirando al barbero, que según ella, era
el más gracioso de todos los demonios.

Rafael estaba en el balcón, junto a Leonora, con la mirada perdida en la obscuridad, arrullado
por la música de aquella voz, que con marcado interés le hacía preguntas sobre el desesperado
viaje por el río.

La finura de aquella capa que le envolvía, dábale la sensación de una epidermis satinada y
tibia. Parecíale que aún quedaba en aquella suavidad algo del calor de los hombros desnudos;
creía estar envuelto en la piel de Leonora, y el perfume de su cuerpo, que sentía junto a él,
aumentaba esta ilusión.

Rafael, con voz entrecortada, contestaba a sus preguntas.

--Lo que usted ha hecho--decía la artista--merece honda gratitud. Es un arranque caballeresco
digno de otros tiempos. Lohengrín, llegando en su barquilla para salvar a Elsa. Sólo falta
el cisne... a no ser que el barbero se contente con este papel... Hablando en serio, no creía
que aquí hubiese un hombre capaz de portarse así.

--¡Y si usted hubiese muerto!...--exclamó el joven para justificar su aventura.

--¡Morir!... Le confieso a usted que al principio tuve algún miedo; no de morir, que yo le
temo poco a la muerte. Estoy algo cansada de la vida; ya se convencerá usted de ello cuando
me conozca más. Pero morir ahogada en el barro, sofocada por esa agua que huele tan mal, no
me hacía gracia. ¡Si al menos fuese el agua verde y transparente de los lagos suizos!... Yo
busco la belleza hasta en la muerte; me preocupo de la última postura como los romanos y temía
perecer aquí como una rata sitiada en la alcantarilla... Y, sin embargo, ¡si supiera usted
lo que he reído viendo el terror de mi tía y de esas pobres gentes que nos sirven!... Ahora
el agua no sube ya, la casa es fuerte, no hay más molestia que la de verse sitiados y espero
el día para ver. Debe ser muy hermoso el espectáculo de toda esa hermosa campiña convertida
en un lago. ¿Verdad, Rafael?

--Usted habrá visto cosas más interesantes--dijo el joven.

--No digo que no; pero a mí, lo que más me impresiona es la sensación del momento.

Y calló, mostrando en su repentina seriedad la molestia que le causaba la ligera alusión al pasado.

Quedaron los dos en silencio un buen rato, hasta que Leonora reanudó la conversación.

--La verdad es que si el agua sigue subiendo, a usted le hubiéramos agradecido la vida... Vamos
a ver, con franqueza; ¿por qué ha venido usted? ¿Qué buen espíritu le ha hecho acordarse de
mí a quien apenas conoce?

Rafael enrojeció de rubor, tembló de cabeza a pies, como si le exigiera una confesión mortal.
Iba a soltar la verdad, a volcar de un golpe su pensamiento, con todos los ensueños y las angustias
de aquellos días, pero se contuvo y se asió a un pretexto.

--Mi entusiasmo por la artista--dijo con timidez.--Yo admiro mucho el talento de usted.

Leonora prorrumpió en una ruidosa carcajada.

--¡Pero si usted no me conoce! ¡Si usted no me ha oído nunca!... ¿Qué sabe usted de eso que
llaman mi talento? A no ser por ese parlanchín de Cupido, hasta ignorarían en Alcira que yo
canto y soy conocida fuera de aquí.

Rafael quedó aplastado por la réplica; no se atrevía a protestar.

--Vamos, Rafael--continuó cariñosamente la artista--no sea usted niño ni pretenda turbarme
con esas mentirillas semejantes a las que se usan para engañar a la mamá. Yo sé por qué ha
venido aquí. ¿Cree usted que no le han visto desde este mismo balcón rondando la casa todas
las tardes, apostándose en el camino como un espía? Está usted descubierto, señor mío.

El tímido Rafael creía que el balcón iba a hundirse bajo sus pies. Temblaba de miedo, arrebujábase
en el manto de pieles, sin saber lo que hacía y protestaba con enérgicas cabezadas, negando
las afirmaciones de Leonora.

--¿Conque no es verdad, embusterillo?--dijo ésta con cómica indignación.--¿Conque niega usted
que desde que nos vimos en la ermita, su paseo de todas las tardes son estos alrededores? ¡Dios
mío! ¡qué monstruo de falsedad es este chico! ¡con qué aplomo miente!

Y Rafael, vencido por aquella alegría franca, acabó riéndose, confesando con una carcajada
su delito.

--Usted se extrañará de mis actos y palabras--continuó Leonora aproximándose más a él, apoyando
un hombro en el suyo, con un abandono fraternal, como si estuviera junto a una amiga.--Yo no
soy como la mayoría de las mujeres. ¡Bueno fuera que con la vida que llevo me mostrara hipócrita!...
Mi pobre tía me cree una loca, porque digo las cosas como las siento: en mi vida me han querido
mucho o me han aborrecido, por esta manía de no ocultar la verdad... ¿Quiere usted que se la
diga?... Pues bien, usted ha venido aquí porque me ama, o al menos cree amarme; el defecto
de todos los muchachos de su edad apenas encuentran una mujer que no es igual a las otras que
conocen.

Rafael estaba silencioso y cabizbajo; no osaba levantar la vista; sentía en su nuca la mirada
de aquellos ojos verdes que parecían registrarle el alma.

--A ver; levante usted esa cabeza; proteste un poquito como antes. ¿Es verdad o no lo que digo?

--¿Y si fuera?...--se atrevió a suspirar Rafael, viéndose descubierto bruscamente.

--Como sé que es cierto he querido provocar esta explicación para que usted no viva en el engaño.
Después de lo de esta noche deseo que seamos amigos; amigos nada más; dos camaradas unidos
por el agradecimiento. Pero para evitar la confusión, había que marcar nuestras respectivas
situaciones. Seremos amigos, ¿eh?... Esta es su casa, yo le consideraré como un camarada simpático;
con lo de esta noche ha ganado usted en mi ánimo más que con un continuo trato; pero va usted
a prometerme que no reincidirá en esas tonterías de admiración amorosa que han sido siempre
el tormento de mi vida.

--¿Y si no puedo?...--murmuró Rafael.

--La cantinela de siempre--dijo riendo Leonora, remedando la voz y la expresión del joven.--¿Y
si no puedo? ¿Por qué no ha de poder usted? ¿Por qué ha de ser verdad ese amor tan inmenso
por una mujer que ve usted ahora por segunda vez? Esas pasiones repentinas se las inventan
ustedes; no son verdad; las han aprendido en las novelas o las han oído cantadas por nosotras
en las óperas. Invenciones de poeta que los muchachos se tragan como unos bobos y quieren trasplantar
a la vida, no comprendiendo que los que estamos en el secreto nos reímos de su necedad. Con
que ya lo sabe usted; a ser formal, a no ponerse pesado con miradas tiernas y frases entrecortadas.
Así seremos amigos y esta será su casa.

Se detuvo Leonora, y amenazándole graciosamente con el índice, añadió:

--De lo contrario, seré todo lo ingrata y cruel que usted quiera; pero a pesar de la hermosa
acción de esta noche, usted no entrará más aquí. No quiero adoradores: he venido buscando reposo,
amigos, tranquilidad... ¡El amor! ¡hermosa y cruel patraña!...

Dijo estas últimas palabras con acento grave, y quedó inmóvil mucho rato, con la vista perdida
en la inmensa sábana de agua.

Ahora la miraba Rafael. Había levantado la cabeza y contemplaba a Leonora pensativa. Su hermoso
rostro se teñía de una luz azulada que parecía envolverla en un nimbo de idealidad. Comenzaba
a amanecer y los plomizos velos del cielo se rasgaban por la parte del mar, transparentando
una claridad lívida.

Leonora se estremeció, como si sintiera frío, apretándose instintivamente contra Rafael. Pareció
sacudir con un movimiento de cabeza un tropel de penosos pensamientos, y dijo tendiéndole la mano:

--¿Qué resolvemos? ¿Amigos o indiferentes? ¿Promete usted no incurrir en niñerías y ser un
camarada formal?

Rafael estrechó con avidez aquella mano suave y fuerte, sintiendo en sus dedos como cariñosa
mordedura, el contacto de las sortijas.

--¡Amigo!... me resignaré ya que no hay otro remedio.

--Se resignará usted y encontrará dulce y tolerable eso que cree un sacrificio; usted no me
conoce, pero créame a mí que me conozco bien. Aunque llegase a amarle (y esto no será nunca),
saldría usted perdiendo. Yo valgo más como amiga que como amante. Hay en el mundo más de uno
y de dos que lo saben bien.

--Seré un amigo dispuesto a hacer por usted mucho más que esta noche. También espero yo que
usted llegará a conocerme.

--Déjese usted de promesas. ¿Qué más ha de hacer usted por mí? El río no se desborda todos
los días, ni son posibles a cada momento estas hazañas novelescas. Me basta con lo de esta
noche. No sabe usted cuánto se lo agradezco. Ha sido un paso decisivo en mi corazón de amiga...
¿Quiere usted que siga siendo franca? Pues cuando le encontré allá en la ermita, me pareció
usted uno de esos señoritos lugareños que, acostumbrados a triunfar en el pueblo, miran como
de su dominio cuantas mujeres encuentran. Después, al verle rondando esta casa, se aumentó
mi desprecio y mi rabia. «¿Pero ese señoritín qué se habrá figurado?» ¡Lo que hemos reído a
costa de usted Beppa y yo! Ni siquiera me había fijado en su cara y su figura: no me había
dado cuenta de que es usted guapo...

Leonora reía recordando sus cóleras contra Rafael, y éste, anonadado por su franqueza, sonreía
también para ocultar su turbación.

--Pero después de lo de esta noche, le quiero a usted... como un buen amigo. Estoy sola: la
amistad de un muchacho bueno y noble como usted, capaz del sacrificio por una mujer a la que
apenas conoce, resulta grata. Además, esto no compromete. Yo soy ave de paso: he venido porque
estoy cansada, enferma no sé de qué, pero profundamente quebrantada en mi espíritu. Necesito
reposo, vida animal, sumirme en una dulce imbecilidad, olvidarlo todo, y acepto con reconocimiento
su mano amiga. Después, el día que menos lo piense usted, levantaré el vuelo; la primera mañana
que despierte alegre y me cante dentro de la cabeza el pájaro travieso que tantas locuras me
ha aconsejado, hago las maletas y ¡a mover las alas! Le escribiré; le enviaré periódicos que
hablen de mí y usted verá como tiene una amiga que no le olvida y le saluda desde Londres,
San Petersburgo, o Nueva York, cualquiera de los rincones de este mundo que muchos creen grande
y en el cual no puedo revolverme sin tropezar con el fastidio.

--¡Que tarde ese momento!--dijo Rafael.--¡Que no llegue nunca!

--¡Loco!--exclamó Leonora.--Usted no sabe cómo soy. Si estuviera aquí mucho tiempo, acabaríamos
por reñir y pegarnos. En el fondo odio a los hombres; he sido siempre su más terrible enemiga.

Oyeron a sus espaldas el roce de la bata que arrastraba Cupido con grotescos contoneos: se
aproximaba al balcón con doña Pepita para contemplar el amanecer.

Comenzaba a desplomarse del cielo una luz gris, cernida por el denso celaje: la inmensa sábana
de agua tomaba un color blancuzco de ajenjo. Flotaban en la corriente, como escobazos de miseria,
los despojos de la inundación; árboles arrancados de cuajo, haces de cañas, techumbres de paja
de las chozas; todo sucio, pringoso, nauseabundo. Estas almadías del desastre, se enredaban
entre los naranjos y formaban barreras que, poco a poco iban engrosándose con nuevos despojos
de la corriente.

Allá lejos, en el límite de la laguna, movíanse con regularidad algunos puntos negros, agitando
sus patas como moscas acuáticas, en torno de las casas, que apenas asomaban sus techumbres
sobre la inmensa lámina de agua. Eran los socorros que llegaban de Valencia; los botes de la
Armada, traídos en ferrocarril hasta el límite de la inundación.

Iban a llegar a Alcira las autoridades; la presencia de Rafael era indispensable. El mismo
Cupido, con repentina gravedad, le aconsejaba salir al encuentro de aquellas barcas.

Mientras el barbero recobraba su traje, Rafael se despojó con gran disgusto de su capa de pieles.

Le parecía que abandonándola, iba a perder el calor de aquella noche de dulce intimidad, el
contacto del hombro suave y carnoso que había estado horas enteras apoyado en él.

Mientras se ajustaba al cuerpo las prendas de su traje ya secas, Leonora le miraba fijamente.

--Quedamos entendidos, ¿eh?--preguntó con lentitud.--Amigos, sin esperanza de más. Si rompe
usted el pacto, no entrará aquí, ni aun por el balcón como esta noche.

--Sí; amigos y nada más--murmuró Rafael con sincero acento de tristeza que pareció conmover
a Leonora.

Sus ojos verdes se iluminaron; brilló el polvo de oro que moteaba sus pupilas y avanzó hacia
Rafael, tendiéndole la mano.

--Buen muchacho; así me gusta: resignado y obediente. Por esta vez y en premio a su cordura,
habrá extraordinario. No nos despidamos así... Como en la escena. Bese usted.

Y puso su mano al nivel de la boca del joven. Rafael la agarró ávidamente y besó, besó, hasta
que Leonora, desasiéndose con un brusco movimiento que demostraba su extraordinario vigor,
le amenazó con su mano.

--¡Ah, tunante!... ¡Bebé travieso! ¡Qué manera de abusar! ¡Adiós! ¡adiós! Cupido llama... Hasta
la vista.

--Y le empujó al balcón, a cuyos hierros estaba agarrado el barbero sosteniendo la barca.

--Salta, Rafael--dijo Cupido.--Apóyate en mí; el agua desciende y la barca está muy baja.

Rafael se deslizó en su bote blanco, manchado por el agua rojiza. El barbero movió los remos;
comenzaron a alejarse.

--¡Adiós! ¡adiós! ¡muchas gracias!--gritaban desde el balcón la tía, la doncella y toda la
familia del hortelano.

Rafael, abandonando el timón, con el rostro vuelto a la casa, sólo veía aquella arrogante figura,
que agitaba un pañuelo saludándoles. La vio mucho tiempo, y cuando las copas de los árboles
sumergidos le ocultaron el balcón, inclinó la cabeza, entregándose al silencioso placer de
saborear la dulzura que aún sentía en sus labios.

VI

Las elecciones pusieron en movimiento a todo el distrito. Había llegado el momento solemne
para la casa de Brull y todos sus fieles, no seguros aún de la omnipotencia del partido, como
si temieran a ocultos enemigos que podían presentarse inesperadamente, se agitaban en la ciudad
y los pueblos lanzando cual grito de victoria el nombre de Rafael.

Pocos se acordaban de la inundación. El sol bienhechor había secado los campos; los huertos
se mostraban más hermosos que nunca, como si el río, al invadirlos, les hubiese fecundado con
nueva vida; se anunciaba una cosecha magnífica, y sólo como recuerdo de la catástrofe quedaba
algún seto aplastado, alguna cerca desmoronada, algún camino hondo con los ribazos destruidos.

Todo se reparaba con relativa rapidez y la gente mostrábase contenta hablando del pasado peligro
con desprecio. ¡Hasta la otra!

Además, se había repartido mucho dinero. Llegaron socorros de la capital de la provincia, de
Madrid, de toda España, gracias al trompeteo lastimoso de la prensa, y los hortelanos, con
la credulidad del devoto que atribuye todos sus bienes a la protección del santo patrono, agradecían
la limosna a Rafael y su madre, proponiéndose ser cada vez más fieles a la poderosa familia.
¡Viva el padre de los pobres!

Doña Bernarda, viendo próximos a realizarse sus ensueños de ambición, no se daba un momento
de reposo. Indignábase ante la indiferencia y frialdad de su hijo. El distrito era suyo, pero
no había que dormirse. ¿Quién sabe lo que a última hora podían hacer los enemigos del orden,
que eran bastantes en la ciudad? Había que ir a tal pueblo para decir cuatro palabras a los
electores ricos; visitar al alcalde del otro para que viera que se le hacía caso; moverse mucho,
que toda la gente se preocupara de su persona.

Y Rafael obedecía, pero evitando que le acompañase don Andrés, pues a la ida o a la vuelta
pasaba unas cuantas horas en la casa azul o suprimía por completo el viaje para quedarse allí
temblando al volver a casa por si su madre se enteraba de tales distracciones.

Doña Bernarda conocía aquella nueva amistad. Sin otra preocupación que la salud y los actos
de Rafael, y ayudada por el chismorreo de una ciudad curiosa, nada hacía su hijo que no lo
supiera a las pocas horas. Hasta tenía noticias, por una indiscreción de Cupido, de aquel arriesgado
viaje de noche y a través de los peligros de la inundación, para ir a presentarse a la cómica,
como ella decía con rabioso acento de desprecio.

Entonces ocurrieron las tormentosas escenas que habían de dejar en Rafael una profunda impresión
de amargura y miedo.

La dureza del carácter de doña Bernarda quebrantó al joven, haciéndole comprender con cuánta
razón había temido siempre a su madre. La áspera devota, con su coraza de virtud y sanos principios,
le aplastó desde las primeras palabras. ¿Se había propuesto deshonrar la casa? Ahora que tras
muchos años de trabajos iba a alcanzar el fruto de tantos sacrificios ¿quería, por su afición
a una cómica, ponerse en ridículo dando motivos de burla a los enemigos? E indignada, no vaciló
en rasgar brutalmente el velo de prudencia tras el cual se habían desarrollado misteriosamente
sus desventuras y sus rabias conyugales; no dudó en volcar sobre la cabeza del hijo todas las
miserias ocultas de su matrimonio.

--Lo mismo que tu padre--exclamó iracunda doña Bernarda.--No puedes negar su sangre: mujeriego,
amigo de las perdidas, capaz por una cualquiera de comprometer la suerte de la casa... ¡Y yo,
grandísima tonta, trabajando por ellos! </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08065</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>195374</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16505</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> It
was blue fox fur, despite the stature of Rafael, its edges touched the floor. The young man saw
that he was thrown over her shoulders a few thousand francs, and shy, with a trembling hand,
picked up the edge, afraid to step on it.

Leonora laughed at his shyness.

- Not to shrink you, no matter what damage.

It appears that you wear a sacred veil the respect with which it is! Not worth it. I only use this
layer on the road.

Gave me a Grand Duke in St. Petersburg.

And to further ensure their contempt for the rich robe, wrapped the boy in him, hitting his
shoulder to adjust more to your body.

Slowly returned to the room where was the balcony, while in the room sounded loud greeted the appearance
of the barber, wrapped in a luxurious robe. Cupid took advantage of situation to provoke laughter,
and recording the tail and stroking his whiskers, stroking which
a dramatic soprano singing in a falsetto ballad.

The gardeners were laughing like crazy ignoring the water that filled his house, his eyes widened
Beppa admired by the figure, the contortions of that man and the grace with which marred the
Italian verses, and even poor Dona Pepa squirmed in his chair, admiring
the barber, who she says was the funniest of all demons.

Rafael was on the balcony, near Leonora, staring into the darkness, lulled the music of that voice,
that strong interest questioned him on the desperate river trip.

The thinness of that layer that enveloped him, gave him the feeling of a satiny skin tibia.
It seemed that there was still something in that heat soft bare shoulders; believed to be involved
in the skin of Leonora, and the scent of her body, which was next
to him increased this illusion.

Rafael, in a faltering voice, answered their questions.

- What you've done - said the artist - deserves deep appreciation. It is a chivalrous boot worthy
of the past. Lohengrin, arriving in his little boat to save Elsa. It remains the swan ... unless
the barber is content with this role ... Seriously, did not believe here there was a man capable
of behaving well.

- And if you had died young !...-- said to justify his adventure.

- Die! ... I confess to you that at first I had some fear, not death,
that I little fear of death.

I'm a little tired of life, and you will be convinced of this when
I know more.

But drowning in the mud, choked by the water that smells so bad,
no I was amused.

If it were green and clear water of Swiss lakes!

... I I look for beauty even in death, I worry about the latter position as the Romans and feared
perishing here like a rat in the sewer under siege ... And yet, if you only knew I've laughed
watching the terror of my aunt and those poor people who serve us!

... Now the water rises and the house is strong, no more hassle than a siege and wait the day
to see. It must be very beautiful sight of all that beautiful countryside converted in a lake. Right,
Rafael?

- You've seen more interesting things - said the young man.

- Do
not say no, but to me, what impresses me most is the feeling of the
moment.

And silent, showing her sudden seriousness the trouble that caused
him the slightest allusion to the past.

They were both silent for a while, until Leonora resumed the conversation.

- The truth is that if the water keeps rising, you would have appreciated
the life ... Let to see, frankly, why have you come?

What good spirit made him remember he barely knows me?

Rafael blushed with shame, she trembled from head to foot, as if he
demanded a mortal confession.

I was going to release the truth, to overturn a blow your mind with all the dreams and anxieties
of those days, then stopped and grabbed a pretext.

- My enthusiasm for the artist - timidly said .-- I admire your talent.

Leonora burst into a loud laugh.

- But if you do not know me! If you have not ever heard me! ... What do you know why call my talent?
Were it not for that chatterbox of Cupid, to ignore me in Alcira singing and I'm known out here.

Rafael
was crushed by the reply, did not dare to protest.

- Vamos, Rafael - continued affectionately artist - do not be a child or intend to disturb me
with these little lies like those used to fool mom.

I know why he come here. Do you think you have not seen from this same balcony around the house
all afternoon, betting on the road like a spy? You found, sir.

The shy Rafael thought the balcony would collapse under their feet. Trembling with fear, arrebujábase
in the mantle of fur, without knowing what he did and complained to vigorous nodding, shaking
Leonora claims.

- "So not true, embusterillo? - Says it with comic indignation .-- So you deny that since we were
in the chapel, his walk each evening are around here? God mine! What a monster of falsehood
is this guy!

Lies with what aplomb!

And Rafael, vanquished by the joy frank, finished laughing, admitting with a laugh his crime.

-
You will be surprised by my actions and words - Leonora went closer to him, supporting on
his shoulder, with fraternal abandon, as if with a friend .-- I do not I'm like most women. Well
out with the life I live show me hypocrite! ... My poor aunt thinks me mad, because I say things the
way I feel, in my life I have wanted much or hate me for this hobby not hide the truth ...
Do you want it say? ... Well, you've come here because they love me, love me or at least believed,
the defect of all boys his age just find a woman who is not equal
to the others known.

Rafael was silent and downcast, not daring to look up, he felt in his neck look of those green eyes
that seemed to register you for the soul.

- Let's see, you lift the head a little protest as before.

Is it true or not what I mean?

- What if he dared to sigh ?...-- Rafael, looking suddenly discovered.

- As I know it's true I wanted to lead this discussion so that you do not live in deception. After
what happened tonight I want to be friends, friends only, two comrades
united by the appreciation.

But to avoid confusion, we had to make our respective situations. We'll be friends, eh? ...
This is your house, I consider it a nice fellow; so tonight you won
in my mind rather than a continuous treatment, but you will to promise
not to repeat such an offense in that nonsense about loving admiration
has always been the torment of my life.

- What if I can not ?...--
murmured Rafael.

- The usual mantra - Leonora laughed, imitating
the voice and the expression of the young .-- What if I can not?

Why should not you be? Why it must be true that love so great by a woman who sees you now for
the second time?

Such is the sudden passions invent you, they are not true, they have
learned in the novels and we have heard sung by in the operas.

Inventions poet who swallowed boys like suckers and want to transplant to life, not realizing
that we are in the secret laugh at his folly. With which as you know, to be formal, not to get
heavy with tender eyes and broken sentences. So we will be friends and this will be your home.

Leonora paused and threat thanks to the index, added:

- Otherwise,
I will be ungrateful and cruel what you want, but despite the beautiful
action tonight, you will not come here anymore.

Not worship, I have come seeking rest, friends, relax ... Love! Beautiful and cruel hoax!
...

He said these last words with an accent grave, and lay still for a long time, looking lost in
the vast sheet of water.

Rafael looked now. Had raised his head thoughtfully and looked at Leonora. Its beautiful face
was tinged with a bluish light that seemed to envelop her in a halo of idealism. Began to
dawn and the sky leaden veils torn apart by the sea, by transparently
clarity livid.

Leonora shivered as if he felt cold, clutching instinctively against Rafael. Seemed shaking
with a nod a rush of painful thoughts, and said holding out his hand:

- What do we solve it? Friends or indifferent? Do you promise not to engage in childish things
and be a formal comrade?

Rafael eagerly shook the hand soft, hard and feeling in his fingers as loving bite, the contact
of the rings.

- Dude! ... I resign as there is no other choice.

- You resign and you will find is sweet and tolerable that he believes
a sacrifice you are not me known, but believe me I know well.

Although come to love (and this will never) you would lose. I am worth more as friends than as
lovers. In the world more than one and two who know it well.

- I'll be a friend willing to do for you more than tonight.

I also hope that you get to know.

- Let your promises. What else must you do for me? The river does not overflow every day, nor are
possible at any moment these fictional exploits. I just what this night. You do not know how
much I appreciate it. It was a milestone in my heart for friend ... Do you want to remain free?
Then when I met him there in the chapel, it seemed you one of those
gentlemen villagers, accustomed to triumph in the village, they look
like its domain are few women.

Then, seeing him hanging around the house, was increased My contempt and my anger. "But that will
be featured señoritín what?" What we have laughed at Beppa coast you and me! I had not even
set in his face and figure: I had not realize that you are cool ...

Leonora laughed recalling his anger against Rafael, and he, stunned by his candor, smiling
also to hide his embarrassment.

- But after tonight, I want you ... as a good friend. I am alone: friendship of a good and noble
boy like you, capable of sacrifice for a woman who hardly knows,
is welcome.

Moreover, this does not compromise. I am a bird of passage: I came
because I'm tired, sick, dunno, but deeply broken in my spirit.

Need resting, wildlife, sink into a sweet stupidity, forget everything, and accept with appreciation
a helping hand.

Then the day know it, you, get up the flight, the first morning you wake up happy and I sing
in the bird's head so many crazy naughty me has recommended, I pack
up and move the wings!

I write, I will send periodic talk about me and you look like you have a friend who does not
forget and greets from London St. Petersburg, or New York, any of
the corners of this world that many think big and in which I can not
turn round without bumping into annoyance.

- So late this time! -
.-- Rafael said that never comes!

- Crazy! - Said Leonora .-- You
do not know how I am.

If he were here a long time, we would end to scold and beat us. In the background I hate men,
I have always been his most terrible enemy.

Behind heard the rustle of the gown which trailed Cupid strutting grotesque: it approached
Dona Pepita balcony to watch the sunrise.

Began to plummet from the sky a light gray, sifted through the dense
cloudscape: the immense sheet water took a whitish color of absinthe.

Floating in the stream like broom of misery the remains of the flood
uprooted trees, bundles of reeds, thatched roofs the huts, all dirty,
greasy, nauseating.

These rafts of the disaster became entangled between the orange and barriers were gradually thicken
with new offal were current.

Far on the edge of the lagoon regularly moved about some black spots, stirring their legs like aquatic
flies, around houses, scarcely protruding roofs, on the vast sheet of water. Relief supplies
were arriving from Valencia, the boats of Navy, brought by rail to the edge of the flood.

Alcira
Iban reach the authorities, the presence of Rafael was indispensable.

The same Cupid, with sudden seriousness, advised him to go and meet
the boats.

While the barber regained his suit, Rafael took off to the disgust of his fur coat.

He felt that leaving her, he would lose the heat of the night of sweet intimacy, Contact fleshy
soft shoulder that had been leaning against him for hours.

While the clothes fit the body of his suit and dry, Leonora was staring.

- It is understood, huh? - Asked slowly .-- Friends, more hopeless.

Breaking you the pact, will not come here, even from the balcony as tonight.

- Yes, friends and nothing more - Rafael murmured with a sincere tone of sadness that seemed to move
Leonora.

Her green eyes lit up, flashed gold dust dappled his eyes and walked toward Rafael, extending
his hand.

- Good boy, so I like: resigned and obedient. By this time, and as a reward for his sanity,
there will be extraordinary. No way ... we say goodbye As in the scene. Kiss you.

And he put his hand to the level of the mouth of the young. Rafael eagerly grabbed her and
kissed and kissed until Leonora, detachment with an abrupt move that demonstrated his extraordinary
strength, threatened him with his hand.

- Ah, rogue! ... Naughty Baby! What a way to abuse! Goodbye! Bye Cupid called ... Up view.

-
And he pushed the balcony, to which iron was the barber caught holding the boat.

- Salta, Rafael - Cupido said .-- Lean on me, the water drops and
the boat is very low.

Rafael slipped into his white boat, the water stained red. The barber pulled the oars; began
to walk away.

- Goodbye! Bye Thank you very much! - Shouted from the balcony of her aunt, the girl and all family
gardener.

Rafael, leaving the helm, with his face turned to the house, just saw that arrogant figure, greeting
them waving a handkerchief.

He saw a long time, and when the tops of the trees submerged hid the balcony, head bowed, giving
the silent pleasure taste the sweetness was still on his lips.
VI

The elections set in motion the entire district. It was time
solemn for the house of Brull and all the faithful, not sure yet of
the omnipotence of the party, as if they feared a hidden enemy that
might arise unexpectedly stirring in the city and throwing people
shout of victory which the name of Rafael.

Few remembered the flood.
The beneficent sun had dried the fields, orchards were more beautiful
than ever, as if the river to invade, they had fertilized new life,
announcing a magnificent harvest, and only as a reminder of the catastrophe
was hedge some crushed, some close to crumbling, a hollow way to the
slopes destroyed. 

Everything was repaired relatively quickly and
people talking about the past showed himself happy danger with contempt.
Until the next!

Also, a lot of money had been distributed. Relief
arrived in the capital of the province, Madrid, in Spain, thanks to
the pitiful trumpeting the press, and the gardeners, with the credulity
of the devotee who gives all his property to protect the patron, thanking
alms to Rafael and his mother, intending to be ever more faithful
to the powerful family. Viva the father of the poor!

Dona Bernarda,
looking ahead to realize their dreams of ambition, not given a time
rest. Indignant at the indifference and coldness of his son. The district
was his, but did not have to sleep. Who knows what could be done late
enemies of order that was enough in the city? Had to go to such people
to say four words to rich voters, visit the mayor's another to see
who paid attention to move much, that all people cared for him.

And
Rafael obeyed, but should not accompany him Don Andres, as on the
outward or return spent a few hours in the blue house or completely
abolished the trip to stay there trembling to return home if his mother
found out such distractions.

Doña Bernarda know this new friendship.
No other health concerns and actions Raphael, and helped by the curious
gossip of a city, nothing was his son who did not I knew a few hours.
Even had news, an indiscretion of Cupid, in that risky overnight trip
and through the dangers of flooding, to go to report to the comic
as she said with angry tone of contempt.

Then occurred the stormy
scenes that had to leave a deep impression Rafael of bitterness and
fear.

The hardness of the character of Dona Bernarda broke the young
man, making him understand how reason he had always feared her mother.
The harsh devotee, with his shield of virtue and sound principles,
crushed her first words. Had he proposed to dishonor the house? Now
that after many years of work was to achieve the fruit of many sacrifices
did you want for your hobby a comic, make a fool of a cause of mockery
of the enemy? E indignant, did not hesitate in brutally rip the veil
of caution after which mysteriously had developed their misfortunes
and their anger conjugal did not hesitate to dump on the head of every
child hidden misery of her marriage.

- The same as your father -
angry Dona Bernarda exclaimed .-- You can not deny his blood: womanizer
Friend of the losses, which can compromise by any of the luck of the
house ... And I very great fool, working for them</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>