<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10900</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>508566</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18585</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Mientras sucedía lo referido con los Carerás, se estaba disponiendo el infatigable Misionero
para llevar al cabo y conseguir el fin glorioso de tan trabajosa empresa; para la cual, escogiendo
segunda vez algunos cristianos de más valor y fuerzas, partió á fines de Mayo de 717, y llegando
al lugar de sus sudores, se puso luego con mayor brío á cortar árboles y á allanar la tierra,
facilitando este trabajo y fatiga la esperanza de feliz suceso.

Parecía casi imposible quitar aquel embarazo; pero nada le es inaccesible, nada duro de vencer,
á quien ha ofrecido su espíritu á Dios, y á los prójimos su vida en obsequio de la caridad.

Al cabo de veinte días se llegó á abrir del todo aquel impenetrable bosque, y á los 12 de Julio
llegó á la primera Ranchería de los Zamucos.

Estos, á quienes había llegado antes la fama de su venida, le festejaron con demostraciones
de extraordinaria alegría; cercáronle todos en rueda, y los varones todos, uno por uno, le
fueron besando la mano; querían hacer lo mismo las mujeres; mas el santo varón que se deshacía
todo en lágrimas de consuelo, les dió á besar la imagen de la Virgen santísima, que traía en
la mano.

Cumplimentaron después á los neófitos, abrazándoles en señal de paz y de amor, y les alojaron
en sus casas, dándoles parte de la pobreza y escasez del país.

El día siguiente juntó el pueblo en la plaza, les dió razón y juntamente una breve noticia
de Dios, de su santa ley, y los preguntó si querían que los Misioneros viniesen á predicarles
allí la fe de Jesucristo, y enseñarles el camino del cielo.

Respondieron ellos que había mucho tiempo que lo deseaban, y el no ser ya cristianos era porque
no tenían quién les explicase los misterios de la fe que habían de creer, ni los mandamientos
que debían observar.

--Pues si es así--añadió el Padre, bañado en alegría--es necesario levantar primero iglesia
á vuestro criador y señor, y que os juntéis todos en un pueblo.

A esta propuesta se levantaron dos caciques principales, diciendo que lo harían de buena voluntad,
mas no allí, sino en mejor sitio, y que juntarían luego al punto toda la gente del contorno
para fundar una reducción numerosa.

Entre tanto hizo el P. Zea enarbolar una cruz en un alto, y puestos todos de rodillas delante
de ella, la adoraron; y entonadas las letanías de la Virgen, puso aquel pueblo debajo del patrocinio
y tutela de nuestro Padre San Ignacio, cuya advocación le dió.

Hubiérase quedado allí de buena gana para dar calor á la buena voluntad de los Zamucos si hubiera
llevado consigo los ornamentos sagrados y el altar portátil, aunque le fuese forzoso sufrir
muchas incomodidades, y no tener otra cosa para comer que agua y algunas raíces de yerbas silvestres;
por esta causa se hubo de despedir de ellos y volverse por entonces con igual sentimiento y
dolor del que se partía y de los que se quedaban.

A la vuelta tuvo ocasión oportuna de ganar para Cristo á cien indios de varias naciones Zinotecas,
Japorotecas y Cucarates que se trajo consigo á la Reducción de San Juan Bautista, en donde
mientras se estaba disponiendo de nuevo para volver á sus Zamucos, recibió orden de nuestro
Padre General Miguel Ángel Tamburini, de que tomase á su cargo el gobierno de provincia; á
que obedeció prontamente, no sin incomparable dolor de su corazón.

Y porque con esta ocasión murió al bien público de estas misiones, dejando después de dos años
poco menos, la vida en el empleo de Provincial, haremos aquí una breve relación de los méritos
que partiéndose de aquí llevó consigo al Paraguay, para ejemplo de los súbditos, y después
al cielo, para recibir la corona debida á los operarios apostólicos.

Fué el P. Juan Bautista de Zea, natural de Goaze, lugar de Castilla la Vieja, en donde nació
á 18 de Marzo de 1654.

Aquí aprendió los primeros rudimentos de la gramática, aunque por la calidad del lugar y de
los maestros, aprovechó más en la devoción que en las letras, creciendo no menos en la virtud
que en los años.

Para estudiar las ciencias mayores pasó á la Universidad de Valladolid, donde dió buenas muestras
de ingenio en las ciencias especulativas, pero mucho más en la de los santos.

Sobresalía en él una modestia virginal, una inocencia de costumbres tan cristianas como amables,
un desprecio grande de las cosas del mundo, y un no gustar de otra cosa que de Dios y de su alma.

Poco era menester para que quien estaba tan despegado de los afectos de la carne y sangre se
rindiese á la voluntad divina que le llamaba á la Compañía, en que á 13 de Agosto de 1671 le
recibió el doctísimo P. Diego de la Fuente Hurtado, el cual descubriendo con luz soberana,
y anteviendo los fines á que Dios tenía destinado al nuevo Jesuita, pronosticó de él cosas
grandes en el servicio de Dios y aumento de la santa Iglesia, y de allí adelante le amó siempre
y le veneró como á santo.

Apenas el hermano Zea se vistió la sotana de la Compañía, cuando haciéndose cargo de las nuevas
obligaciones que con ella había contraído, procuró dar á ellas entero cumplimiento; y como
si empezara de nuevo el camino de la virtud, se miraba en las virtudes de sus connovicios,
observando cuanto en ellos era digno de ser imitado para copiar en sí mismo la perfección de todos.

Dándosele para leer y considerar nuestras reglas, se las puso delante como modelo, á que se
arregló perfectamente en lo interior y exterior.

Tuvo muy poco en qué vencerse para entregar del todo su corazón á Dios, no queriendo ni amando,
ni pensando en otro bien que en Su Majestad; y testifica sujeto que le conoció estudiando la
filosofía, que habiéndole dado los Superiores el cuidado del reloj de casa, se estaba sólo
en un aposento bien incómodo sin salir de él sino obligado de las funciones escolásticas ó
domésticas.

Aquí todo el tiempo que le sobraba de las tareas del estudio lo daba á Dios, y rarísima vez
á los hombres, porque usaba muy poco de su conversación, y esto solamente cuando lo pedía la
obligación.

Pasó después á estudiar la teología á Salamanca, y á este tiempo corrió la noticia por las
provincias de España de haber llegado á Cádiz los PP. Cristóbal de Grijalva y Tomás Dombidas,
procuradores del Paraguay, y poniéndose á considerar sobre la conversión de los idólatras y
el extremo desamparo en que están innumerables pueblos del Occidente, dilatado campo en que
ofrece copiosísima mies á muchos operarios Evangélicos, si hubiese muchos que despreciando
las comodidades propias atendiesen á la eterna salvación de las almas; se le encendió el corazón
en deseos de ser uno de los escogidos á quien tocase la suerte de ser señalado para la Misión
de la dilatadísima provincia del Paraguay; por tanto puso luego todo empeño en alcanzar licencia
de sus Superiores, los cuales sintieron mucho su petición, porque por una parte no querían
privarse de él, y por otra no querían oponerse á la voluntad de Dios, conocida claramente en
su vocación, prevaleció finalmente la América, y la abandonada gentilidad del Paraguay: por
lo cual, nuestro Zea, contento y alegrísimo se partió de su provincia de Castilla, á quien
como hijo profesó siempre tiernísimo afecto; y sus condiscípulos le siguieron con el corazón,
conservando su dulcísima memoria; singularmente se esmeró en esto su maestro en la filosofía
el P. Baltasar Rubio, confesor que fué de la serenísima reina de España doña María Luisa de
Saboya; éste le siguió con el afecto; con sus oraciones y con sus cartas pues cuando se ofrecía
ocasión siempre le escribía, por tener del P. Zea subido concepto, como en ellas lo manifestaba.

Ordenóse de sacerdote antes de embarcarse para esta provincia, á que pasó el año de 1681 y
apenas se dieron á la vela en Cádiz, cuando se le ofreció ocasión en qué dar muestras del espíritu
y virtudes, de las cuales iba abundantemente prevenido para aquel viaje.

Cayeron enfermos casi todos sus compañeros, que llegaban á sesenta, porque se marearon con
extraordinaria inapetencia y fastidio de la comida; á que se siguieron otras enfermedades,
de que murieron ocho de los Jesuitas, como dije en la vida del P. Caballero, que pasó también
á Indias en esta ocasión.

El P. Zea era entonces todo para todos, sirviéndoles no solamente de enfermero, sino de cocinero,
aunque sin experiencia en tales oficios; mas la caridad, que es maestra muy ingeniosa, le enseñó
estos y otros oficios para servir á sus hermanos.

Convalecidos éstos, empleó todos sus pensamientos y celo en la chusma de los grumetes del navío,
tomando á su cargo el cuidado espiritual de ellos con las pláticas, exhortaciones, confesiones
y todos los otros ejercicios conducentes al aprovechamiento de las almas, no dejando, entre
tanto, obra ninguna, por vil y repugnante que fuese, que no la ejecutase en servicio de ellos,
por ganarlos para Dios, y de mejor gana y más alegremente hacía aquellas que eran de mayor
trabajo y desprecio.

Con este porte tan santo procedió toda la navegación, que duró tres meses, con aprovechamiento
maravilloso de muchos, á quien redujo á bien vivir, ya valiéndose de las verdades eternas,
ya poniéndoles á la vista tantos peligros y tempestades del mar, que aun á los más perdidos
suelen obligar á cuidar de la conciencia y del alma, que antes tenían en tal olvido ó parecía
no tenerla.

Lo que obró después que llegó á las Indias y en qué oficios se empleó en el largo curso de
su vida, no lo he podido averiguar, por la distancia de los lugares donde vivió y trabajó,
y por haber muerto muchos de la Compañía que le trataron familiarmente. Pero sé que por el
aprecio que desde el principio hicieron de él los Superiores, poco después que llegó de España
le hicieron ministro del Colegio Máximo de Córdoba, donde se cría la religiosa juventud de
toda esta provincia.

Después fué Superior de las Misiones del Uruguay, Visitador de la de los Chiquitos, Vice-Rector
del Colegio de Córdoba, y estuvo también señalado Rector del Colegio de las Corrientes, á que
por motivos que tuvo propuso; y últimamente fué Provincial de esta provincia, oficio en que
le cogió la muerte al año y medio de su gobierno.

Ahora sólo diré brevemente alguna cosa de sus virtudes, reservando para mejor ocasión el dar
por extenso relación completa de sus muchas empresas y acciones heroicas. Y en primer lugar
diré de su pobreza religiosa.

Fué siempre pobrísimo en su vestido, tanto, que por los muchos remiendos que tenía, decía con
gracia un Misionero, que había en él más accidentes que substancia; él mismo lo remendaba por
sus manos; jamás mudó otro, hasta que el primero, por no poder ya subsistir, se le caía á pedazos.

Al entrar en Buenos Aires, siendo Provincial, le rogó su secretario el P. Juan de Alzola, que,
á lo menos en aquella ciudad, se dejase ver con sotana un poco decente, pues la que llevaba
estaba de muy desteñida, casi blanca, porque si no le obligaría á él á que se vistiese otra
semejante.

--Yo le mando á V. R.--respondió el P. Zea--que no haga mudanza ninguna en su vestido y deje
que yo me goce en esta pobreza, de que hago más aprecio que de cuantas púrpuras visten los
monarcas y emperadores.

Todos los muebles de su aposento eran una red, ó como aquí llamamos, hamaca, para dormir, sin
colchón ni almohada, unos cuantos libros devotos y un Santo Cristo.

Su breviario era tan viejo y hecho pedazos, que sólo ayudado de la memoria podía satisfacer
á la obligación de rezar el oficio divino; su mayor tesoro eran los instrumentos de penitencia,
con que maceraba su carne, cilicio, cadenas de hierro, cruces armadas de agudas puntas y otros
de este jaez, con que redujo su cuerpo á perpetua esclavitud, con aquel santo temor con que
se armó también contra sí mismo el Apóstol San Pablo.

En sus viajes sólo comía un poco de pan y alguna otra vianda, de que usan los pobres indios;
bien que cuanto al pan ú otro de los manjares que usan los europeos, en muchos años no probó
bocado; contento sólo con un puñado de maíz mal cocido y en muchas ocasiones con raíces ó frutas
silvestres, pues muchas veces no tenía ni hallaba otra cosa en los bosques; y cuando comía
con más esplendidez era, ó algún pececillo ó unas hierbas cocidas sin algún aderezo; y vivía
tan gozoso y alegre en esta pobreza y miseria, que en su última enfermedad le eran molestas
y pesadas las comodidades que usa con sus enfermos la Compañía.

No fué inferior á la pobreza su obediencia, de que dió pruebas maravillosas, las cuales, por
ventura, alguno que no mira la verdadera santidad sino con los ojos del cuerpo, tendrá en poco,
pero no quien mirando las cosas con los ojos limpios y claros del espíritu, mide la perfección
de las virtudes, no con lo que muestran en la apariencia, sino con lo que en la realidad son
en sí mismo.

Era, como después veremos, varón de celo ardientísimo y de natural sobre manera ardiente; con
todo eso, á una leve insinuación de sus superiores, desde las Misiones de los Guaranís, donde
trabajaba en grandes obras del servicio de Dios y provecho de las almas, se redujo, sin la
menor propuesta, á las angustias de un aposento en un colegio, con el empleo de enseñar á los
niños los primeros rudimentos de la gramática. A otra insinuación de su Provincial, mientras
estaba reduciendo al gremio de la iglesia gran número de infieles, dejando al punto aquella
grande obra, pasó á las Reducciones del Uruguay, como si dijéramos, de un cabo del mundo al
otro, pues distaban éstas más de mil y doscientas leguas de las otras donde estaba; y un viaje
de veinticuatro horas, volvió á desandarle, por obediencia, en veinticuatro días.

Finalmente, donde esta virtud campeó con admiración de todos, fué cuando estando en el fervor
de sus conversiones y á lo mejor de la obra de reducir á la fe á los Zamucos y fundar aquella
nueva cristiandad, levantó al punto las manos de la labor, sin esperanza de volver jamás á
proseguirla, á un orden de nuestro Padre general de que tomase á su cargo el gobierno de esta
provincia; él mismo confesó con toda ingenuidad que le costó la ejecución de este orden increíble
dolor y sentimiento, y que jamás había sentido tanta repugnancia su natural como en este caso
de ser Superior; y aunque fácilmente se hubiera podido excusar de aquella carga, para él tan
pesada, con todo eso, por no dejar de obedecer, la aceptó prontamente, y sin dilación se vino
á largas jornadas al Tucumán, sufriendo por el camino increíbles trabajos é incomodidades.

Mas en lo que sobre todo se hizo admirable entre los nuestros fué en el celo de las almas y
en la conversión de los infieles. El dilatar la fe, el predicar á los cristianos, el reducir
á los gentiles, no parecía en él obra de virtud, sino inclinación y apetito natural; por lo
cual no sabía vivir de otra suerte ni en otra ocupación recibía gusto, sino en esta de conducir
almas al conocimiento y amor de Dios, y en este ejercicio estaba toda su quietud y descanso
y para aliviarle en todas enfermedades, no había mejor medio que hablarle de nuevas empresas
en bien de las almas, de la santa vida de los nuevos cristianos y de nueva conversión de infieles
á la santa iglesia.

Ojalá pudiera yo trasladar aquí algunas cartas suyas, que tengo en mi poder, para que vieran
todos que no pudieran los enamorados del mundo y de la carne explicar con más vivas expresiones
sus contentos y deseos, cuanto este obrero Evangélico manifiesta los sentimientos de su corazón
en los negocios del servicio de Dios; los lamentos y quejas que hace de su mayor enemigo el
demonio cuando se le atravesaba, ó hacía se le desvaneciesen sus designios. Por eso no me causa
admiración que con ánimo invicto sufriese muchas persecuciones y reparase, aun con la pérdida
de su reputación, los daños, bien que ligeros, de su cristiandad; antes dando cuenta de estas
sus borrascas al P. Francisco Burgés, Procurador general de esta provincia, en carta de 29
de Septiembre de 1705, escrita á Madrid, le dice así:

«Para mí no puede haber mayor gloria que el que me persigan por llevar adelante aquella nueva
cristiandad de los Chiquitos que tantos trabajos y sudores me ha costado desde los principios.»

Y decía la verdad; porque si se habla de solos trabajos que se padecen en desvastar é instruir
á estos gentiles, que en las facciones son hombres, pero en las obras se distinguen poco de
los brutos, sufría y hacía por ellos cuanto puede hacer un verdadero padre, para provecho espiritual
y corporal de sus hijos, porque á él la virtud le había dado tan tiernas entrañas y amor de
verdadero padre, como los padres naturales suelen tenerlas por naturaleza con los hijos; de
día y de noche trabajaba, no sólo para bien de las almas, sino también de los cuerpos de sus
neófitos, ya proveyendo de víveres en abundancia á los hambrientos, ya componiendo recetas
y aplicando remedios á los enfermos, y aunque se revistiese la naturaleza, tratando y limpiando
sus llagas con tal desembarazo, como si no sintiese la menor repugnancia y asco en sí mismo;
el mismo amor le enseñó á ser juez y árbitro en sus litigios, gastando mucho tiempo en oirles
contar, con paciencia y dulzura inexplicable, las diferencias que tenían entre sí, para lograr
así el mantener y conservar entre ellos la paz porque antes de ser cristianos, cada uno por
su propia autoridad se hacía justicia y vengaba sus agravios con las armas.

Esto y mucho más hacía y sufría por los pobres indios: y aunque otros no pudieran tolerar el
contínuo peso de vida tan trabajosa y con tan poco alivio, con todo eso él duró en ella por
muchos años, y cada día se hallaba con tanto vigor como si en aquel comenzase; de lo cual,
como dije en otra parte, no acababa yo de maravillarme; pues cuando oídos sus trabajos en la
Misión de los Zamucos le consideraba consumido de fuerzas y que apenas se podía tener en pie,
le ví poco después en Córdoba, con alientos y vigor de joven, siendo así que ya contaba sesenta
y cuatro años de edad.

A tantas fatigas por el bien de aquellos nuevos cristianos, se añadió otra trabajosísima, de
aprender tantos y tan dificultosos idiomas bárbaros, para que al tiempo que ellos en las obras
le experimentaban padre, no le tuviesen en la lengua por extranjero.

Cosa era esta que á un hombre de su edad le pudiera ser muy enfadosa y de mucho empacho; mas
el celo de las almas le obligó á volver á la condición y simplicidad de niño para aprender
uno por uno los vocablos y significados de aquellas lenguas, y para expresar las voces con
los acentos propios de los bárbaros, y no rehusando hacerse discípulo de los mismos infieles,
los tomaba por intérpretes para traducir en su idioma los misterios y preceptos de la ley de
Dios, procurando después enseñárselos á ellos con trabajo contínuo de meses y años enteros.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04505</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>187485</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16936</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

As was true Carer referred to, was having the indefatigable missionary to carry out and achieve
the glorious end of such laborious undertaking, for which, by choosing second time some Christians
more courage and strength, started in late May of 717, and reaching the place of his sweats, then
put more verve to cut trees and to pave the earth, facilitating this work and fatigue in the
hope of good success.

It seemed almost impossible to remove this pregnancy, but nothing
is inaccessible, nothing hard to beat, whom he has offered his spirit
to God and his neighbor his life for the sake of charity.

Twenty days after it was open to anyone in the impenetrable forest, and to the July 12 arrived
at the first Rancheria of Zamucos.

These, whom fame had preceded his coming, we celebrated with demonstrations of extraordinary
joy cercáronle all in a circle, and men all, one by one, we were
kissing his hand, wanted to do the same for women, but the holy man
crumbled all in tears of relief and gave them to kiss the image of
the Blessed Virgin, who brought in hand.

Completed after the neophytes, embracing in peace and love, and I stayed in their homes, giving
them part of the poverty and the country.

The next day the people gathered in the square, right, and together they gave a brief report of
God, his holy law, and asked if they wanted should come and preach the Missionary Hence the faith
of Jesus Christ and teach the way to heaven.

They answered that he had long wished, and not being Christian and it was because I had no one explain
the mysteries of the faith they had to believe, or the commandments to be observed.

- Well if so - said the Father, bathed in joy - you need to first raise church to your Creator
and Lord, and that you keep company all in one village.

That proposal was raised two principal chiefs, saying they would of goodwill but not there, but in
a better place, and that would gather at once to all the people of the neighborhood to found
a large reduction.

Meanwhile made P. Zea fly a cross on a high, and put all kneel before
it, worship it, and chanted the Litany of the Virgin, placed under
the patronage that people and protection of our Father St. Ignatius,
which gave invocation.

One would have gladly stayed there for warmth to the good will of the Zamucos if there brought
with them the sacred vestments and altar laptop, but he was forced to suffer many inconveniences,
and having nothing else to eat but water and some wild grass roots;
from this cause was to dismiss them and turn then to the same feeling
and pain that started and those who stayed.

On the return was timely opportunity to win for Christ to one hundred Indians of various nations
Zinotecas, Japorotecas and Cucarates that brought to the Reduction
of San Juan Bautista, where as he was preparing again to return to
their Zamucos, received orders to our General Michelangelo Tamburini
father, that he take charge of the provincial government, to they
promptly obeyed, not without pain in his heart incomparable.

And this time he died because the public good of these missions, leaving after two years slightly
less, life in the provincial employment, we here a brief account of the merits starting from
here took with him to Paraguay, for example of the subjects, and
then the sky to receive the crown due to the apostolic workers.

Father was Juan Bautista de Zea, a native of Goaz, instead of Old Castile, where he was born to March
18, 1654.

Here he learned the rudiments of grammar, but by the quality of place and teachers, took over
in devotion in the letters, not least in growing under that year.

To study more science went to the University of Valladolid, where he gave good examples ingenuity
in the speculative sciences, but much more on the saints.

He excelled in maiden modesty, innocence of manners as Christian and kind, great contempt of
worldly things, and not like anything other than God and his soul.

There was little need for one who was so detached from the affections
of flesh and blood surrender to the will of God calling him to the
Company, in which to August 13, 1671 will P. was the most learned
Diego Hurtado de la Fuente, who discovered light sovereign and foreseeing
the end to which God had designed the new Jesuit, it predicted things
great in the service of God and increase the holy Church, and from
then on he always loved and was venerated as a saint.

Zea brother just donned the robes of the Company, when taking over new obligations that she
had contracted, he tried to give them full compliance, and as if I started again the path
of virtue, he looked in the virtues of their connovicios, As observed
in them worthy of emulation to copy itself to the perfection of all.

Bragging to read and consider our rules, they are put forward as a
model, to which perfectly arranged in the interior and exterior.

Had very little to overcome to deliver the all his heart to God, not wanting or loving, or thinking
of other good that Her Majesty and subject testifies he met while studying the philosophy,
having given the Supreme clock care home, was only rather uncomfortable in a room without
leaving it but forced or scholastic functions domestic.

Here all the time that he had plenty of work study God gave it, and very rarely to men, because they
used very little of their conversation, and then only when requested by the obligation.

Then he went to study theology at Salamanca, and at this time the news spread by provinces of
Spain have arrived at Cadiz PP. Cristóbal de Grijalva and Thomas Dombaas, Prosecutors in Paraguay,
and to consider putting on the conversion of idolaters and the extreme distress in which are
innumerable peoples of the West, where extensive field offers copious harvest operators to many
Evangelicals, if there are many who disregard the amenities to attend to the eternal salvation
of souls is kindled the heart the desire to be one of the elect whom he touched the good fortune
to be appointed for the Mission the very extensive province of Paraguay,
and therefore made every effort to reach then leave of his superiors,
who felt much his request, because one part would not deprived of
it, and otherwise would not oppose the will of God, clearly known
their vocation, the American finally prevailed, and the abandoned
paganism of Paraguay by thus, our Zea, happy and alegrísimo broke
his province of Castile, to whom as a child always professed most
tender affection, and his classmates followed him to the heart, retaining
its sweet memory; singularly took pains to master this, your philosophy
Fr Baltasar Rubio, who was confessor of the Most Serene Queen of Spain,
Dona Maria Luisa Savoy, he followed him with affection, with their
prayers and their letters because when offered always hand wrote,
having the P. Zea uploaded concept, as I stated them.

Ordenóse a priest before embarking for the province, he spent the
year 1681 and were just sailed in Cadiz, when occasion offered which
demonstrate the spirit and virtues, of which plenty was prevented
for that trip.

Fell ill almost all his companions, who came to sixty, it is dizzy with extraordinary loss of
appetite and food boredom, to be followed by other diseases, that
killed eight of the Jesuits, as I said in the life of P. Caballero,
who also spent Indians on this occasion.

Fr Zea was time for everyone, serving not only as a nurse, but a cook,
but no experience in such trades, but the charity which is very clever
teacher, taught him these and other offices to serve his brethren.

Convalesced them, used all his thoughts and zeal in the mob of apprentices of the ship, taking
responsibility for the spiritual care of them with the talks, calls, confessions and all other
exercises leading to the advantage of souls, leaving between therefore no work, were vile
and disgusting it was, who did not run on their service, to win them
for God, and better and more happily did win those who were most work
and contempt.

With this size so holy proceeded all the navigation, which lasted three months, taking advantage
many wonderful, whom reduced to living well, and drawing on the eternal truths and putting them
in sight so many dangers and storms at sea, which even the most lost
often obliged to care for the conscience and soul, who had previously
appeared in such neglect or not having it.

What worked after he came to the Indies and in what trades are employed in the long course
his life, I have not been able to ascertain, by the distance of the places where he lived and
worked and having killed many of the Company who treated him familiarly. But I know that by
the I appreciate that from the beginning made him superiors soon
after he arrived from Spain made him minister of the Colegio Máximo
de Cordoba, where they breed the religious youth throughout the province.

After

he was Superior of the Missions of Uruguay, Visitor of the Chiquitos, Vice-Rector College of Córdoba,
and was also designated the Rector of Corrientes, to which for reasons that had proposed, and
recently was Provincial of the province, letter by Death took him a year and a half of his
government.

Now I'll just say briefly something of their virtues, reserving for another day to give in full
respect of all his many enterprises and heroic deeds.

And first tell your religious poverty.

He was always very poor in their dress, so much that by the many patches
that had, say with grace a missionary, he was in more accidents than
substance, he himself mended by their hands never moved another, until
the first, and can not survive, was falling to pieces.

Upon entering Buenos Aires, with Provincial, begged his secretary Fr Juan de Alzola, which at
least in that city, it ceases to do with some decent cassock, as
carrying was very faded, almost white, because if you do not force
him to dress another similar.

- I send to VR - said Fr Zea - that
does not make any move on her dress and let I rejoice in this poverty,
that I most appreciate that many are wearing purple monarchs and emperors.

All

the furniture in his room were a network, or as we call, hammock, sleeping without mattress or
pillow, a few books devoted and Santo Cristo.

Her old breviary was so shattered, that only helped the memory could meet the obligation to pray
the Divine Office, its greatest treasure were the instruments of
penance, that macerated his flesh, and sackcloth, iron chains, crosses,
armed with sharp ends and other of this sort, with which reduced his
body to perpetual slavery, with that holy awe with which also armed
himself against himself the Apostle Paul.

In his travels just ate some bread and some other snack, they use the poor Indians; well as to
bread or other of the dishes used by Europeans for many years did not prove snack; happy with
just a handful of corn undercooked and often with roots or fruit
wild, since many had no else was in the woods, and when he ate more
largesse was a little fish or some herbs or cooked without any seasoning,
and lived so joyful and happy in this poverty and misery in his last
illness he was annoying facilities and heavy with their patients using
the Company.

It was not inferior to his obedience poverty, gave proof that wonderful, which, by chance, one that
is not true holiness look with the eyes of the body, will take little but who look at things
with clear eyes and clear the mind, perfectly measured of virtues, not what they show in appearance,
but which in reality are itself.

It was, as we shall see, a man of zeal and natural ardientísimo on how hot, with all that, to
a hint from his superiors, from the Missions of the Guarani, where worked great works of the service
of God and the good of souls, was reduced without retail proposal, to the anguish of a room in
a school, with the use of teaching children the rudiments of grammar. In another hint of his
Provincial, while was reducing the bosom of the church a large number
of infidels, leaving the point that great work, went to the Reductions
of Uruguay, as it were, from one end of the world another, as they
were far more than a thousand and two hundred leagues from the other
where he was, and a trip twenty-four hours, turned to retrace, in
obedience, in twenty days.

Finally, where this virtue champion with admiration of all, it was that being in the fervor
of their conversion and to the best of the work to reduce faith to the Zamucos and found that
new Christendom, hands raised to the point of work, no hope of ever returning to continued at
a general order that our Father to take charge of the government of this province, he naively
confessed that cost him his incredible performance of this order grief and sorrow, and had
never felt so much his natural repugnance in this case to be High, and though it easily could
have been excused from that burden for him as heavy, with all that,
no longer obey, promptly accepted, and promptly fell to long hours
at Tucumán, suffering incredible by the way work and discomfort.

But in what was particularly remarkable among us was in the zeal for souls and in the conversion
of infidels. The delay of faith, to preach to the Christians, reducing to the Gentiles, it did
not seem to work under, but natural inclination and appetite, for what which could not live in any
other way or in another occupation got taste, but this driver souls to the knowledge and love
of God, and this year was all quiet and rest your and ease in all conditions, there was no better
way to talk of new businesses for the good of souls, the holy life of new Christians and new
conversion of infidels to the holy church.

I wish I could bring here some of his letters, I have in my possession, to see all that they
could not lovers of the world and the flesh liveliest explain their content and desires, the
Protestant states this worker's feelings of his heart businesses in the service of God, the laments
and complaints that makes the most enemy demon when he crossed it, or did he allayed your designs.
So I do not cause admiration that undefeated spirit suffer much persecution and repaired, even
with the loss its reputation, damage, rather than light, its Christianity, before realizing these
his squalls Fr Francisco Burgos, Attorney General of this province,
in a letter dated 29 September 1705, written at Madrid, he says:

"For
me there can be no greater glory than that pursued me to take forward
this new Christianity of the Chiquitos so many work and sweat has
cost me from the beginning.

"

And telling the truth, because if it comes to their own jobs that have to devastate and to instruct
to these nations, that the factions are men, but in the works differ little brutes, they had
suffered and how much you can make a real father to spiritual profit and body of their children,
because he had given under belly so tender and love true father as the natural parents usually
have them by nature with children, of worked day and night, not only for the good of souls, but
also the bodies of their neophytes, providing plenty of food to the hungry, and writing recipes
and applying remedies to the sick, and although journal Nature, treating
and cleaning his wounds with such disengage, as if I did not feel
the slightest repugnance and disgust in himself; the same love he
showed to be the arbiter in their disputes, spending much time listening
to him have, with patience and gentleness inexplicable, differences
had each other to achieve and to maintain and preserve peace among
them because before being a Christian, each one their own authority
and justice was done to avenge their grievances with the weapons.

This and much more doing and suffering for the poor Indians, and though others could not tolerate
continuous weight of life so laborious and so little relief for all that he lasted in it for
many years, and every day was as vigorously as if just begun, and of that, as I said elsewhere, not
just to amaze me, because when hearing his work in Mission Zamucos forces was considered consumed
and could barely keep his feet, I saw him shortly afterwards in Cordoba, with encouragement
and vigor of youth, being so I was sixty and four years old.

In many hardships for the sake of those new Christians, they added another trabajosísima of difficult
to learn so many barbarous languages, so that while they in the works her father experienced,
do not take into the foreign tongue.

Thing was this that a man of his age could be very annoying and much embarrassment, but zeal
for souls forced him to return to the status and simplicity of a
child to learn one by one the words and meanings of those languages,
and to express the voices the accents of the barbarians, and not refusing
to become a disciple of these infidels, I took them by interpreters
to translate into your language the mysteries and precepts of the
law God, after trying to teach them to work continuously for months
and years on end.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>