<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04637</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>37304</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23522</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Solo es facultativo de la potestad real conceder licencia temporal ó absoluta para el aprovechamiento
de estas pesquerias, como mares que pertenecen á sus dominios. Abiertos los ojos con conocimiento
práctico de la mucha utilidad de este comercio, ha de atraer interesados á su aprovechamiento.
Este es el estado en que puede sacar fruto la Corona, no por medio de los intereses que gira
Portugal, sino por los reconocimientos y poblaciones en aquellos parages mas avanzados al sur,
que tanto nos importa ó interesa. Al que se aventaje en los mas útiles, y nos demuestre puerto
seguro para el abrigo de las embarcaciones, ofreciendo poblar, compénsesele estos gastos con
la concesion de algun privilegio, ó licencia para hacer su pesqueria en el tiempo que parezca
regular, con formal obligacion y contrata de hipotecas. Unansele aquellas gracias que permite
la real proteccion y soberania, y de este modo, sin dispendio del real erario, conseguirá el
Rey hacer útiles estos despoblados dominios, preparando los medios de atraer á verdadero conocimiento
tantas almas idólatras que los ocupan, en la propagacion de la Fé y utilidad del Estado, y
proporcionará diferentes ventajas á la navegacion y comercio.

Aunque del estrecho de Magallanes é islas del Fuego nos es importantísimo un verdadero y exacto
reconocimiento, por si permite puertos que nos faciliten aquel pasage á la mar del sur, no
debe despreciarse el golfo de San Jorge, que está situado á los 45 grados y minutos, para mirarlo
con la indiferencia que hasta aquí.

El reconocimiento que en Marzo de 1780 hicieron los pilotos de la expedicion que salió al mando
de D. Antonio Viedma, para establecer en San Julian, solo reconocieron con la lancha del paquebot
San Sebastian, unas 40 leguas por la banda del norte, tirando al oeste de dicho golfo. Por
informes y noticias que se han tomado de los indios prácticos de sus inmediaciones, aseguran
que á este rumbo llega muy cerca de las cordilleras, donde desaguan algunos arroyos de agua
dulce, y que en el terreno que media á ellas, está el camino de los indios de San Julian para
el rio Tucamelel, ó de la Encarnacion. Esto se comprueba con el diario de Villarino del reconocimiento
del Rio Negro, en que refiere el viage que acababan de hacer á las inmediaciones de aquel rio
los expresados indios. Si el ingles reconociera y se apoderára de este golfo, tendria entrada
por él para Valdivia y otros pueblos del reyno del Perú, y le seria fácil establecerse sin
noticia nuestra. Abunda de gran numero de ballenas, cuyo parage proporciona esta pesca con
mayores ventajas que otras. Estos fundamentos, que á ser ciertos manifiestan su importancia,
alentarán á los interesados en la pesqueria á su reconocimiento, el que nos ha de desengañar,
y dar una verdadera luz de la importancia de aquel golfo, y comunicacion que se teme. Lo cierto
es que los indios de aquellos parages transitan el Rio Negro por el camino que se dice, y desde
este rio pasan á las fronteras de Buenos Aires.

Todas estas utilidades nos las ha de atraer la subsistencia y fomento de la poblacion del Rio
Negro. Ella le ha de dar la mano al puerto de San José con sus frutos y ganados, y como por
escala, han de salir estos auxilios para las demas poblaciones, descubriendo los caminos que
transitan los indios, sus aguadas, campañas y montes hasta el Estrecho: pues de todos hay noticia,
y solo ha faltado en el anterior ministerio el calor que se necesita en semejantes casos, para
que en el tiempo que ambos Super-intendentes han estado en sus respectivas comisiones, hubieran
reconocido la parte mas principal de este continente.

La internacion del comercio para Valdivia, Chile, Mendoza y otros parages por el Rio Negro,
seria utilísima por la menor distancia que media comparada á la de Buenos Aires, por el auxilio
de la navegacion, y porque se presentan otras comodidades que pueden hacer mas suaves las asperezas
del camino.

Los mas opuestos enemigos del establecimiento del Rio Negro confiesan la utilidad de esta internacion,
pero lo dan por imposible, hablando con tanta valentia y seguridad, como si hubieran medido
palmo á palmo aquellos caminos, y se hubieran enterado con un conocimiento práctico de la navegacion
del rio.

No falta sugeto á quien se le debe hacer la justicia de confesarle instruccion y talento superior,
que apoye y sostenga la misma imposibilidad, y me aseguran lo ha hecho manifiesto en un papel
que entregó al superior Gobierno; el que por mas diligencias no he podido obtener. Seria utilisimo
que estas impugnaciones fueran recíprocas, y con conocimiento mútuo de ellas: porque de la
contenciosa y racional oposicion resulta el esclarecimiento de la verdad, que es la que apetecen
y buscan los que procuran el acierto. Si tantos dictámenes que se tomaron para dar en tierra
con los establecimientos, esto es, para disuadir al Rey y sus Ministros de la importancia de
ellos, se les hubieran primero pasado á los Super-intendentes, para que en su vista informasen
y respondiesen, entonces se hubieran tenido otras noticias y conocimientos que esclareciesen
la verdad de todo. Por estos motivos se solicita y apetece el citado papel, pues son asuntos
que no deben reservarse con tanto misterio de unos sugetos que han merecido la confianza del
Rey para el desempeño de tan importante comision; mayormente cuando parece ha corrido entre
personas que no tienen conexion con estas materias, por las cuales se me noticia aquellos puntos
mas esenciales de dicho papel, aunque en confuso, las que expondré para satisfacer y demostrar
cuanto llevo propuesto.

Dos son las mas poderosas objeciones que parece demuestra este sugeto, en las cuales apoya
y sostiene los fundamentos de su oposicion. La primera, la dificultosa navegacion que hizo
Villarino en el reconocimiento del Rio Negro hasta el Catapuliché, donde llegó, que ella misma
demuestra su inutilidad para el comercio. La segunda, graduar de intransitables las cordilleras,
desde aquel parage hasta Valdivia.

Por las mismas operaciones, expresadas en el diario de Villarino, demuestra este sugeto lo
inaccesible del Rio Negro en su navegacion. Si hubieramos de estar á aquel punto, á aquella
estacion, á aquel estado en que encontró y navegó el rio Villarino, es menester confesar su
inutilidad: pero si todo ello varía con la diferencia de tiempos, y con mas repetidas pruebas
que dén una verdadera luz de los canales, arrecifes, saltos y corrientes del rio, demostrando
el modo de vencerlas con otros auxilios, parece en algun modo extraño que con tanta viveza,
sin esperar á distinto conocimiento práctico, se condene y falle por inútil un asunto que tanto
interesa á nuestra felicidad.

La navegacion que hizo Villarino fué en la estacion mas contraria. Los cuarenta y cinco dias
que se detuvo en el Choelechel, esperando víveres para continuarla, le atrasó el tiempo, de
modo que cuando llegó á la confluencia que hace el Diamante con el Rio Negro, habian bajado
las aguas, en términos que causaron lo penoso de su navegacion. Esta falta descubrió saltos
y arrecifes, y su vencimiento fué la mayor dificultad. Si se hubiese salido á este reconocimiento
por el mes de Julio, que es el tiempo en que principian las crecientes, y duran hasta Marzo,
seria menos dificultosa y mas suave; no se descubrieran tantos saltos y arrecifes; y las canales
no causarian tan vehementes corrientes, originadas de lo angosto de ellas, pues con la mayor
agua se extiende el rio y evita el impetu de sus efectos. Con el auxilio de los caballos ó
mulas (de que no pudo valerse Villarino, por los riesgos que se preveian de los indios, que
son el atractivo de sus invasiones) se suavizaba y facilitaba la navegacion, tirada de ellas
á la sirga, recayendo el mucho trabajo de los marineros en las fuerzas y vigor de este ganado,
desmontando y abriendo camino por las orillas del rio á hacer útil estas operaciones.

Para tomar un verdadero conocimiento de todo esto, es menester distintas experiencias que la
gravedad del caso lo pide: pues no debemos deferir á la relacion de una precipitada y obscura
tentative, que por muchas razones puede engañarnos.

Es caractéristico de todo descubridor ponderar las dificultades y trabajos que ha vencido para
hacer valer su mérito, y aun sin faltar á la sinceridad y buena fé, aquellas primeras impresiones
suelen causar en el hombre distintas apariencias á proporcion de los afectos en que lo cogen.
No seria estraño que á Villarino y los suyos, las soledades de aquellos parages, falta de comunicacion,
y otros acasos, les produgesen un afecto ó pasion odiosa, que en su imaginacion elevase á encumbradas
montañas de dificultades las colinas ó barrancas accesibles.

Cuando descubrieron el Rio Negro, el primer piloto de la real armada, D. Manuel Bruñel, y el
teniente de infanteria D. Pedro García, en la zumaca San Antonio la Oliveyra, fué tal la impresion
que les causó la barra, que retrocedieron al puerto de San José, y dieron por imposible su
entrada. Fué Villarino, y demostró lo contrario; y en el dia se hace tan fácil, que con viento
por la proa á bordos han entrado los bergantines. Si hubieramos estado á la decision é informes
de aquellos sugetos no hubieramos visto un desengaño tan claro.

La navegacion del Rio Negro no se nos presenta imposible, sino dificultosa: esto es accesorio
á todos principios, pues las mayores facilidades que despreciamos en el dia, en su orígen costaria
mucho trabajo y vencimiento.

El tiempo, y la demostracion práctica de lo importante de esta entrada y camino, subsistiendo
el establecimiento del Rio Negro, han de dar luz á ir preparando y allanando tanto horror,
tanta dificultad como se aparenta, extendiendo sus poblaciones rio arriba, que servirán de
escala á su comodidad; prepararán mayores intereses al comercio; contendrán el atrevimiento
de los indios en los insultos y robos que experimentan las fronteras de Buenos Aires, serán
los cimientos mas sólidos en que se han de fundar las esperanzas de reducir estos infieles
habitadores de los vastos y fértiles terrenos que componen el Huechuhuehuem y faldas de las
cordilleras, hasta la Concepcion de Chile, cuyas industriosas operaciones en el beneficio de
las lanas, de que fabrican ponchos y mantas, el cultivo de la agricultura en que nos imitan,
la poblacion fija, aunque muy dispersa de sus domicilios, nos ofrecen las mas vastas y felices
ideas para la exaltacion de nuestra santa Fé, y prosperidad del Estado; y puede llegue el dia
que á imitacion nuestra se rian de estas aparentes dificultades.

Para satisfacer á la segunda objecion, necesitaria enteramente de las pruebas y fundamentos
que le dá su autor, pues en la primera adquirí algunas noticias que las saqué del diario que
llevó Villarino en su navegacion. Pero en esta, si es cierto que dá por inaccesibles las cordilleras
por aquellos parages, no puedo atinar con ellos, porque no los ha de sacar de su vasta comprension,
ciencias y literatura, si no es en el de un desengaño físico, del que puede dar razon, y estar
instruido el rústico mas zafio.

Es cierto que las cordilleras son inaccesibles por muchos parages. Los indios de San Julian
contestan, que desde el Estrecho, tirando por la parte del norte, lo son aun para los brutos:
lo mismo notó el Super-intendente D. Antonio de Viedma cuando reconoció el rio de Santa Cruz
hasta su naciente[A], pero no debe entenderse con el rigor que piensa el autor, pues solo las
encuentra accesibles por el camino que usamos por Mendoza á Chile. Son igualmente transitables
desde Huechuhuehuem, ó Catapuliché, por el Portillo, á los indios y ganados que conducen. La
prueba que doy á esta afirmativa es la uniforme contestacion de los indios habitadores de aquellos
parages, á quienes he preguntado con proligidad repetidas veces, cuyas noticias se fueron comprobando
con los descubrimientos de Villarino; ya con haber encontrado cerca del rio Diamante, el ganado
vacuno y caballar que llevaban los indios hurtado de las fronteras de Buenos Aires, para vender
á Valdivia, donde habian ofrecido esta remesa un año antes; y ya por haberle informado estos
infieles, cuando llegó al Catapuliché, que habia bajado un cristiano de Valdivia, como un dia
de camino, donde se hallaba, para tratar y ajustar la compra de él, dándole individuales señas
de su persona[B].

Todas estas pruebas son de hecho propio: las del autor han de ser de reflexiones y referencias,
cuya desigualdad es notoria en la fé de una justificacion que está apoyada tan legalmente.
Pero enhorabuena, he de conceder la igualdad, que no tienen: en este caso, ¿no debiamos haber
ocurrido á Valdivia á examinar y comprobar aquellas citas que eran un verdadero testimonio
de la verdad? Pero ¿qué se hizo? Diferir en un todo á la autoridad del autor, como si las inaccesibles
montañas, que formaba su imaginacion y discurso, fuesen verdaderas.

Supuesto que hay pruebas expuestas á favor y en contra de lo inaccesible ó transitable de las
cordilleras por el Catapuliché, Huechuhuehuem á Valdivia, debemos estar en favor de estas últimas,
á menos que un desengaño fisico de personas sínceras y verdaderas hagan ver lo contrario. No
podemos dejar de conocer, que nos presenta la naturaleza los dos caminos que llevo propuesto
por agua y por tierra á dicha plaza y reyno de Chile: pues en los tiempos oportunos no solo
se puede navegar como llevo demostrado al parage donde llegó Villarino, sino de la laguna Huechum-lauquen,
ó del límite de donde nace el rio, que está un dia de camino mas distante. Desde este sitio
á Valdivia echan los indios en mula tres dias, por la aspereza de las montañas: tránsito muy
corto, comparado con el que media por Mendoza á Chile, que nos franquea menos gastos y otras
comodidades.

Desde el establecimiento del Rio Negro á la laguna Huechum-lauquen por tierra, su distancia
aun no llega á 160 leguas: hasta la punta del Diamante se puede abrir camino muy cómodo para
carretas, por la orilla del mismo rio, cuyas aguadas es el mayor socorro y alivio del ganado.
A este sitio puede conceptuarse 120 leguas: desde él á dicha laguna 40, y desde esta á Valdivia
20; de modo, que siendo toda la distancia 180 leguas, las 120 es camino carretero muy suave
y cómodo; las 40 con el tiempo talvez se pondrán en igual disposicion, aplicándose á suavizar
algunos malos pasos; y las 20 restantes es el único malo que hay que transitar. Pero este,
segun lo explican los indios, no tiene aquellos voladeros y precipicios que el de Mendoza á
Chile. Compárese, pues, lo dilatado de este desde Buenos Aires, que pasa de 500 leguas, lo
penoso y arriesgado de la travesia de sus pampas, por la escasez de agua é indios, con lo corto
y suave del que puede abrirse por el Rio Negro, y de la seguridad de estos infieles, tomadas
sus principales avenidas y puestos, que es otro de los asuntos que mas importa á la prosperidad
de Buenos Aires, como demostraré en su lugar, por medio de las expresadas poblaciones.

He hablado con concepto á lo que promote lo descubierto en el Rio Negro para la plaza de Valdivia;
prescindiendo del reconocimiento del rio Diamante, ó Sanquel, que por la observacion hecha
por el piloto Villarino, en la confluencia de este rio con el Negro, de 38 grados 44 minutos
y otras combinaciones y noticias, hay fundadas esperanzas, la tiene con el Tunuyan, que pasa
por la ciudad de Mendoza, y á ser ciertas descubren iguales proporciones.

Llegamos ya al punto mas importante, y en que estriba toda la felicidad de la Provincia; esto
es, en reparar el destrozo de ganado que causan los indios en las dilatadas campañas y fronteras
de Buenos Aires; en librar á aquellos infieles de tantas muertes, robos y cautiverios; en aprovechar
los inmensos campos que de esta capital median al Rio Negro, donde puede dilatarse y fomentarse
la cria de ganado, que debe ser otro de los ramos que ha de sostener este establecimiento,
y el apoyo de los demas. Los asuntos son gravísimos, pero la felicidad de ellos pende en una
misma causa, cual es refrenar á los indios.

Por las noticias adquiridas del reconocimiento del rio que hizo Villarino, hemos comprobado
los informes que habian dado muchos indios, de no tener otro paso los de la nacion Tehuelche,
Villiches, Puelches, y otras naciones habitadoras del Huechuhuehuem, é inmediaciones de Valdivia
en las cordilleras, que el sitio llamado el Choelechel, para transitar al Colorado, sierras
de la Ventana, Tandil, Volcan, Cashuatí, y fronteras de Buenos Aires; por carecer de aguadas
los otros parages, y ser terrenos intransitables. La seguridad de estas particulares noticias
me hizo creer se extendia á todas la naciones de indios, que nos causan tanto daño, y que tomando
aquel paso estaban sugetos. Este concepto me estimulaba á repetir las instancias al Sr. Virey
para ocuparle y asegurarle.

Posteriormente traté un indio muy ladino, y práctico de aquellos vastísimos terrenos, llamado
José Yati, el que me desengañó, informándome, que el Choelechel era paso respectivamente de
las naciones de indios que llevo citadas, pero no de todas, pues habia otros dos caminos por
donde venian, y se internaban: el uno caia á las Salinas, de donde se ha proveido de sal Buenos
Aires con las carretas; y es transitado de los indios Peguenches, y Aucases, cuyo cacique nombran
Guchulap, y el otro, mas al norte y no muy distante de la ciudad de Córdoba, que frecuentan
los de nacion Ranqueles.

El motivo de usar de diferentes caminos estas naciones, es por la enemistad que tienen unas
con otras, y estar mas inmediatos á sus tierras; pues de hacerse comunes en el tránsito, habian
de atravesar por las de su convecinos.

Los otros dos caminos es asunto que merece mayor atencion en el dia, porque no tenemos conocimiento
fisico de ellos, lo que no acaece con el de Choelechel: solo hablamos por informes y noticias
de los indios, y se necesita un descubrimiento formal de estos parages para tirar las líneas
de su seguridad.

Aun sin la noticia de tan importantes motivos, en oficio de 31 de Julio de 1781, propuse al
Señor Virey cuan útil era ir adquiriendo conocimiento de las naciones de indios que habitaban
los campos de Buenos Aires; sus albergues y retiros, donde se ponian á seguro, cuando se veian
perseguidos, ó atacados de nosotros; á cuyo intento habia destinado á los peones, Antonio Godoy
y Juan José Gonzales, que con el pretesto de pasar á sus toldos á comprarles ganado, les llevasen
aguardiente, avalorios, y yerba, con cuyas dádivas se iban familiarizando con unos, y tomando
noticias de otros; único medio que podia vencer estas dificultades. Iguales diligencias manifesté
á dicho Exmo. Señor serian útiles practicar desde la fronteras de Buenos Aires y sus guardias,
destinando sugetos adaptados para el caso; con cuyos conocimientos era fácil con dos expediciones
que salieran de esta capital y Rio Negro contenerlos y refrenarlos.

Esta propuesta no mereció aprobacion, y Godoy y Gonzales habiéndolos mandado con cartas para
S. E., y este haber sido el primero que se aventuró á transitar el camino por entre tantos
indios, y dado conocimiento para el viage que hizo el piloto D. Pablo Sisur por tierra á dicho
establecimiento, tuvieron ambos el desgraciado fin de parar en una cárcel, de cuya prision
los libró su propia inocencia.

No obstante el desprecio con que se trató mi propuesta, los continuados insultos y robos de
los indios, obligaron al Señor Virey á determinar las expediciones que han salido de Córdoba,
Mendoza y esta capital; pero no del Rio Negro, que es el parage mas inmediato á ellos. La causa
no soy capaz de comprender aunque me dé mucha márgen la oposicion de los establecimientos.
Dios quiera no se malogran estos gastos, por haber dejado libre aquel portillo.

Estas expediciones eran los mejores principios para descubrir y reconocer los dos citados pasos
y caminos; porque las de Mendoza y Córdoba deben cruzarlos, y comunicándo á sus respectivos
comandantes las instrucciones y noticias, con un mismo gasto se levantaban planos de aquellos
sitios, acompañándoles sugetos facultativos de sinceridad y verdad, y no llenos de la preocupacion
que reina de los establecimientos: si acaso se han internado, puede ser que sirvan de mucho
sus noticias.

Tomado un verdadero conocimiento de estos pasos y caminos, podian fortificarse, y repararse,
extendiendo á ellos las guardias de las fronteras, porque cortadas estas avenidas, y la del
Choelechel, quedaban libres las demas campañas, y á Buenos Aires, y poblaciones del Rio Negro
se daban la mano por tierra para su comunicacion, para la cria y fomento de ganado, y para
la extension de sus poblaciones. Véase pues, que ventajas tan grandes resultaban á la provincia,
y aun á todo el reyno el reconocimiento y seguridad de estos pasos.

Las inmensas indiadas que por ellos bajan á proveerse de caballos y ganados, es una langosta,
ó plaga de su destruccion: que á no ser unos campos tan dilatados y fértiles, no dejarian casta.
El no acabar de apurarles, dan una segura idea de su abundancia y propagacion; cesando esta
causa será un aumento ventajosísimo para el comercio de la corambre, que, como fruto de la
tierra, merece la primera atencion por ser permanente y no precario. Las poblaciones de los
campos de Buenos Aires irian tomando otro incremento y extension, particularmente si se reuniesen
á ellas los vecinos, que en despoblados dispersos habitan en chácras, como está mandado por
repetidas reales cédulas: pues este disimulo es perjudicialísimo al bien espiritual de aquellas
almas, y legislacion real, porque carecen de instruccion cristiana en nuestros sagrados dogmas;
rara vez frecuentan los santos sacramentos de la penitencia, y eucaristía, y casi no tienen,
ó reconocen á quien obedecer y temer: de modo que poco se diferencian de los indios salvages.

Este método de gobierno es la destruccion de si mismos, porque la mucha extension, que media
de una chácra á otra, dá márgen á los indios para robar los ganados, cautivar y matar á sus
habitadores, á cuyas desgracias coadyuvan en mayor parte los que frecuentemente se pasan á
estos infieles, comunicándoles las noticias y caminos seguros á sus invasiones, de tal modo
que ninguna malogran.

Enterado yo en el Rio Negro por los mismos indios, y viages que hicieron los dos expresados
peones Godoy y Gonzales, de esta maldad en los nuestros, han sido repetidas las instancias
que he hecho al Señor Virey, para que se les castigue con egemplar rigor al que se aprenda
haber incurrido en tan horroroso delito, y juntamente dí cuenta á S. E. de uno de estos impios
que los dirigia: el que llegó á tal extremo su crueldad, que no estuvieron exentos de ella
sus propios padres, á quien él mismo mató en una de las entradas que hizo con los indios.

Reducidos á poblaciones los vecinos de estas chacras, tendrán diferente instruccion y gobierno,
y por medio de padrones donde se anoten, habrá conocimiento de los sugetos que falten en el
pueblo, y podrá saberse con otra facilidad su paradero.

No puedo omitir, por el mucho conocimiento adquirido en los cinco años que he estado tratando
estos salvages en el Rio Negro, cuan útil nos es el método que observan los franceses en sus
Indias con semejantes bárbaros, y con cuanta razon nos lo recomienda el Señor Ward en su proyecto
económico. Sin tener yo las mas leves noticias de estas reglas, las he seguido; y notoria es
la buena armonia que he conservado con ellos, y lo útil que han sido al fomento del establecimiento:
y no puede decirse que son de mejor índole aquellos que los de estos campos, porque allí han
concurrido los que aquí nos dañan. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03136</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>38919</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21615</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Optional only the real power to grant temporary or permanent license to use of these fisheries, as seas
belonging to his dominions. Eyes open knowledge the great practical value of this trade, will attract
interest to their use. This is the fruit that can take the crown, not by the interests that rotates
Portugal, but by the survey and those populations most advanced Parages south she cares about
or interested. At that excels in the most useful, and we show port insurance for the shelter of
the boats, offering people, these costs compénsesele the granting of any privilege or license
to the fishery in the time it seems regular, formal contractual obligation and mortgages. Unansele
those graces which allows the real protection and sovereignty, and thus, without squandering
the royal purse, get the These wastes to useful Rey domains, preparing a means to attract true
knowledge many heathen souls occupy in the propagation of the faith and usefulness of State
and provide different benefits to navigation and trade.

While the Magellan Strait and islands of Fire is important to us a
true and accurate recognition by if you allow ports that provide us
passage to the South Sea, no be neglected the Gulf of San Jorge, which
is located at 45 degrees and minutes to look with the indifference
that so far.

The recognition that in March 1780 did the pilots of the expedition which came to control D. Antonio
Viedma, to set in San Julian, only recognized with the launch of
the packet boat San Sebastian, about 40 miles from the northern side,
pulling the west of the gulf.

For and news reports are from practical Indians their surroundings, ensuring that to this course
comes very close to the mountains, where some streams draining water sweet, and half the land to
them, is the way of the Indians of San Julian to Tucamelel river, or of the Incarnation. This
is evidenced by the daily recognition Villarino Black River, which relates the journey they
had just done to that river near those expressed Indians. If the English recognize and take
hold of the Gulf, would have input for him to Valdivia and other towns of the kingdom of Peru,
and he could easily be established without Our news. Abundant large number of whales, which place provides
the fishing greater advantages than others. These grounds, that to be true express their importance,
encourage stakeholders in the fishery to its recognition, we must disabuse, and give a true view
of the importance of the gulf, and communication that is feared. The fact is that the Indians
of those Parages transiting the Black River by the way you say, and from this river go to
the borders of Buenos Aires.

All of these utilities will attract to us the survival and development of the population of Rio
Black. She has to shake hands at the port of San José with its fruits and cattle, and as scale,
such aid must go to other towns, discovering the ways that pass the
Indians, their watery, campaigns and mountains to the Straits, because
of all there is news and has only missed the previous ministry, the
heat required in such cases, that in time the two Super-mayors have
been on their committees, have but recognized the principal of this
continent.

The internment of trade for Valdivia, Chile, Mendoza and other Parages by the Black River, would
be very useful for smaller gap compared to that of Buenos Aires, for the help of navigation, and because
they have other amenities that can make softer asperities the road.

The more enemies opposed the establishment of the Black Rio admit
the usefulness of this hospitalization, but are impossible, speaking
with such courage and security, as if they had measured inch by inch
on those roads, and had learned with a practical knowledge of navigation
River.

No need sugeto whom he should confess the justice of instruction and superior talent, that supports
and sustains the same impossibility, and they assure me it has become
clear in a paper that gave the government greater, the more steps
that I could not get.

Would be most useful These challenges were reciprocal and mutual knowledge of them: for the contentious
and rational opposition is the discovery of the truth which is that crave and seek those who
seek the wisdom. If so many opinions to be taken to give ground with the establishments, that is, to
deter the King and his Ministers of the importance of them, they
had first gone to the Super-intendant, to inform its view and respond,
then it would have had more news and knowledge that shed light the
whole truth.

For these reasons, the aforementioned request and feel like paper, they are matters should not be
booked as much mystery about sugetos they have earned the trust of King for the performance of
this important commission, mostly when it seems has run between people who have no connection with
these materials, which I notice those points most essential for this role, though confusing,
of which I will to meet and demonstrate As I proposed.

Two are the most powerful objections to this individual seems to show, in which supports and
maintains the grounds of their opposition. The first, which made navigation difficult Villarino
in recognition of Black River to the Catapuliché, where she arrived, she herself demonstrates
its irrelevance to trade. The second grade of impassable mountain ranges, from that place to
Valdivia.

For the same operations, expressed in log Villarino, this individual demonstrates the Black River
inaccessible in its navigation. If we would have to be to that point, at that station, to that
state in which they found and navigated the river Villarino, it is
necessary to confess futility, but this varies with the time difference,
and repeated tests over give a true view of the channels, reefs, waterfalls
and river flows, showing how to overcome them with other aid, seems
somehow strange that so vividly, without waiting for other than practical
knowledge, is useless to condemn and fail for a case that both interest
to our happiness.

Villarino navigation was made at the station opposite. The forty-five days we stopped at the Choelechel,
food waiting to be continued, we delayed the time, So when he arrived at the confluence with Diamond
makes the Black River, had fallen water, in terms that caused the
hardship of his voyage.

This lack discovered jumps and reefs, and their maturity was the greatest difficulty. If he
had come to this recognition for the month of July, which is the time that begin growing, and
last until March, would be less difficult and softer, not so many breaks were discovered and
reefs, and carcasses would not cause so vehement currents caused constriction of them, as with
most water extends the river and avoids the momentum of its effects. With the help of horses
or mules (that could not fend Villarino, the risks that were expected of the Indians, who are
the attractiveness of their invasions) was smoothed and facilitated navigation and throwing them
to the towpath, falling all the work of the sailors on the strength
and vigor of these animals, removing and opening the way for the banks
of the river to do useful these operations.

To take a true knowledge of all this, it is necessary that the different experiences seriousness
of the case he asks: We must not defer to the relationship of a hasty and obscure tentative,
which may be misleading for many reasons.

Discoverer is characteristic of all ponder the difficulties and work that has prevailed to to assert
their merit, and even without fail the sincerity and good faith, those first impressions in
humans often cause different looks in proportion to the affection in which he is caught. Would
not it strange that he and his Villarino, the loneliness of those spot, lack of communication,
and others perhaps, I produgesen an affection or passion hateful in his imagination soar to
lofty mountains of difficulty accessible hills or ravines.

When they discovered the Black River, the first pilot of the royal fleet, D. Manuel Brunel, and
infantry lieutenant D. Pedro Garcia, the San Antonio Zumaca Oliveyra, such was the impression
they caused the bar, which retreated to the port of San José, and
gave for impossible input.

Villarino was, and proved otherwise, and on the day it is so easy, windy the bow on board have
entered the launches. If we had been to the decision and inform sugetos those we would not have been
a disappointment so clear.

Black river navigation presents is not impossible, but difficult: it is fitting to all principles, since
the best facilities that we despise in the day, at its source would
cost hard work and maturity.

The time and the practical demonstration of the importance of this post and walk, subsisting
the establishment of the Black River, are to give light to start preparing and paving the horror,
much difficulty as it appears, extending its upstream populations, which will serve to your comfort
level, prepare more interest to trade; contain the audacity Indians
in insults and robberies that experience the frontiers of Buenos Aires,
will be more solid foundation on which to found their hopes of reducing
these infidels inhabitants of the vast and fertile lands that make
up the skirts of Huechuhuehuem and ranges, to Concepcion, Chile, whose
industries benefit operations wool, ponchos and blankets that make
the cultivation of agriculture in which we imitate, fixed population,
but widely dispersed from their homes, we offer the most extensive
and happy ideas for the exaltation of our holy faith, and prosperity
of the State and the day may come that imitation we laugh at these
apparent difficulties.

To meet the second objection, would need all of the evidence and rationale
it gives the author because the first acquired some news that I got
the diary Villarino was in navigation.

But this, if it is true that given by inaccessible mountains by those spot, I can not hit upon
them, because they do not have to draw from their vast comprehension, science and literature,
if not a disappointment in the physical, that can reason and be dealt with the most uncouth
rustic.

It is true that the ranges are inaccessible for many Parages. The Indians of San Julian answer,
that from the Straits, pulling the northern part, they are even for the brutes: noticed the
same Super-intendant D. Antonio de Viedma when he recognized the Santa Cruz River to its source
[A] but should not be understood with the rigor that the author thinks, because only the is
accessible by road we use for Mendoza to Chile. They are also passable from Huechuhuehuem, or
Catapuliché, on the Portillo, the Indians and cattle driving. The give evidence to this claim
is the standard reply of the Indian inhabitants of those spot, with
whom I have asked repeatedly prolixity, news of which went checking
with the findings of Villarino, and to be found near the river Diamond,
livestock cattle and horses that the Indians had stolen them from
the borders of Buenos Aires, to sell to Valdivia, where the consignment
had been offered a year earlier, and as for having reported these
infidels, when he came to Catapuliché, who had fallen Christian Valdivia,
as a day Road, where he was, to try and adjust the purchase of it,
giving individual signs of person [B].

All these tests are indeed his own: those of the author must be of ideas and references, which inequality
is evident in the faith of a justification which is supported so legally. But congratulations, I have
to grant equality, which do not: in this case, we should not have happened to Valdivia to examine
and verify those quotes that were a true testament of truth?

But what was it made? Differ by a whole to the authority of the author, as if the inaccessible
mountains, which was his imagination and discourse, were true.

Of course there is evidence advanced for and against the inaccessible and transit of ranges by
Catapuliché, Huechuhuehuem to Valdivia, we should be in favor of the latter, Unless a physical
disappointment sincere and true people do see the opposite. No we must know that nature gives
us two ways that I have proposed by water and by land to the plaza and the kingdom of Chile, at the
proper time for not only I can navigate as shown at the place where he Villarino, but the gap Huechum-lauquen,
or limit the source of the river, which is a more distant day's journey. From this site Valdivia
to throw the Indians three days by mule, by the harshness of the mountains, traffic very short,
compared to half that by Mendoza to Chile, crossing us less expenses and other amenities.

Since the establishment of Black River to the lagoon-lauquen Huechum land, its distance not even
reach 160 leagues to the top of Diamond to open way too comfortable
carts along the same river, which washes the largest livestock rescue
and relief.

A site can be conceptualized 120 leagues: from him at this gap 40, and from this to Valdivia 20,
so that the whole distance being 180 miles, the 120 is very smooth turnpike road and comfortable,
the 40 with time maybe you will in the same provisions, applicable to soften some missteps, and
the remaining 20 is the only bad thing is that travel. But this, as explained by Indians,
not those aviaries and cliffs to the Mendoza Chile. Compare, then, the increase of this from Buenos Aires,
which went from 500 leagues, painful and risky for the crossing of
the pampas, of water scarcity and Indians, with short soft and can
be opened by the Black River, and the safety of these infidels, taken
its main avenues and places, that is another issue that matters most
to the prosperity Buenos Aires, as I will show in place, expressed
through the populations.

I've talked to Promote the concept to what I discovered in the Black River to the Plaza de Valdivia;
regardless of the recognition of Diamond Rio, or Sanquel, which made observation Villarino the
pilot, at the confluence of this river with the Black, 38 degrees 44 minutes and other combinations
and news, there is reason to hope, has with the Tunuyan, which passes by the city of Mendoza, and to be certain
they discover equal proportions.

We arrived as the most important point, and that happiness lies across the province, this is
to repair the destruction caused by livestock in the vast Indian
campaigns and borders Buenos Aires, in book to those who disbelieve
so many deaths, robberies and captivity, to take advantage the vast
fields that mediate this capital Black River, where you can expand
and encouraged raising cattle, which must be one of the branches has
to sustain this facility and support of others.

The issues are very serious, but their happiness depends on a same cause, which is to restrain
the Indians.

News acquired by the recognition of the river that made Villarino, we found reports had been many
Indians, having no other way those of the nation Tehuelche Villiches, Puelches, and other inhabitants
of the Huechuhuehuem nations, near Valdivia é in the mountains, the site called the Choelechel,
to travel to Colorado mountains Window, Tandil, Volcano, Cashuatí, and frontiers of Buenos
Aires, for lack of watering the other spot, and be impassable terrain. The safety of these
particular news made me believe it spread to all nations of Indians, that cause us much harm,
and taking that step were sugetos. This concept encouraged me to repeat the request to Mr. Viceroy
to occupy and to ensure.

Later an Indian tried very cunning, and practices of those sites Vastis
called José Yati, who disabused me, informing me that the step was
respectively Choelechel Indian nations that I mentioned, but not all,
as I had two paths where they came, and penetrated: one fell to the
Salinas, where salt has provided Buenos Aires with the carts, and
is gone from the Indians Peguenches and Aucases, whose leader named
Guchulap, and the other farther north and not far from the city of
Córdoba, who attend those Ranqueles nation.

The reason for using different ways these nations, is the enmity that have a with others, and
be more immediate to their lands to become as common in traffic, had to go through those of
its neighbors.

The other two roads is a matter that deserves more attention in the day, because we have no knowledge
physicist of them, which does not occur with that of Choelechel: just talked on the news reports and
Indians, and you need a formal discovery to pull these lines Parages for their safety.

Even without the news of these important reasons, in office from July 31, 1781, I proposed to
Viceroy Lord how useful it was to be gaining knowledge of the Indian
nations inhabiting fields of Buenos Aires, its shelters and retreats,
where he began to secure, when they saw persecuted, or attacked us,
to which he had intended to try to the peons, Antonio Godoy and Juan
Jose Gonzales, with the pretext to go to their tents to buy cattle,
lead them brandy, beads, and grass, with whose gifts were being familiar
with some, and taking other news, the only way he could overcome these
difficulties.

Record showed equal he said His Excellency. Lord would be useful to practice from the borders
of Buenos Aires and his guards sugetos allocating adapted to the case, with whose knowledge was
easy with two expeditions come out of this capital and Black River contain and restrain.

This proposal was welcomed, and Godoy and Gonzales sent with letters to habiéndolos SE, and this
being the first who ventured to walk the way through so many Indians, and given knowledge to
the journey made by the pilot D. Paul Sisur by land to the establishment, both had the unfortunate
end to stop at a prison, which prison he delivered his own innocence.

Notwithstanding the contempt with which it was my proposal, the continued abuse and theft Indians
forced the Viceroy Lord to identify shipments that have come from Cordoba, Mendoza and the
capital, but not the Black River, which is the most immediate camp site to them. The cause I
can not understand me much room but the opposition of the establishment. God will not spoil those
costs, have left open that gate.

These expeditions were the best principles to discover and recognize
the two aforementioned steps and roads, for those of Mendoza and Córdoba
be crossed, and share them with their instructions and news commanders,
with the same spending levels rose to those sites, accompanying optional
sugetos sincerity and truth, and not full of prejudice Queen of the
establishments that: whether you have admitted, they may serve as
much news.

Taken from a true understanding of these steps and pathways, could
fortify and repair, extending to them the border guards, because they
cut these avenues, and the Choelechel, the other campaigns were free,
and to Buenos Aires, Rio and Black populations they shook hands on
the ground for communication, for the breeding and promotion of livestock,
and the extension of their populations.

See then that were so big advantages to the province, and even to the entire kingdom and safety recognition
of these steps.

The huge Indian they fall to provide themselves with horses and cattle,
is a lobster, pest or its destruction, that had it not been a very
long and very fertile fields, I would not breed.

The end does not hurry, give an idea of ??his wealth safe and propagation; ceasing this cause
will be most advantageous for increased trade corambre that, as a result of earth, deserves attention
for being the first permanent and non-poor. The populations of Buenos Aires fields would go take
another increase and extension, particularly if they were met them to neighbors, who live on farms
scattered uninhabited, as is mandated by repeated royal decrees: for this concealment is perjudicialísimo
the spiritual good of those souls, and real legislation, for lack of instruction in our holy
Christian dogmas; rarely frequent the sacraments of Penance and Eucharist, and have almost no, recognize
or obey and whom to fear: so that differ little from the savage Indians.

This method of government is the destruction of themselves, because
the lot extension, which mediates one farm to another, leaves room
for the Indians to steal cattle, engage and kill their inhabitants,
whose misfortunes contribute to a greater part of which often go to
these infidels, communicating news and safe routes to their invasions,
so any spoil.

I heard on the Black River by the Indians, and that made voyages both expressed Godoy and Gonzales
pawns in this evil in our time have been repeated instances I made the Viceroy Lord to punish
them with rigor egemplar is learned have committed such horrific
crime, and realized together to know one of these ungodly who led
them: that was so extreme cruelty, which were not exempt from it their
own parents, whom he killed in one of the entries made with the Indians.

Populations

reduced to the neighbors of these farms will have different instructions and government and
through standards which are scored, there sugetos knowledge of the missing at people, and may
be known for another facility of his whereabouts.

I can not ignore, for a lot of knowledge acquired in the five years
I've been trying these savages in the Black River, how useful is the
method we observe the French in their Indies with such barbarians,
and with what reason we are recommended by Lord Ward in its draft
economic.

Without me the news milder these rules, I followed, and is notorious good harmony that I have kept
with them, and how useful it has been the promotion of the establishment: and can not be said
to be the best to are those that these fields, because there have busy on here hurt us.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>