<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04501</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>186553</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17475</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Pepet sacó a Marieta de
aquel antro, satisfecho de tener como suya la mujer más hermosa del distrito.

¡Qué manera de vivir! Las buenas mujeres lo recordaban con escándalo. Bien se veía que el tal
casamiento era por arte del Malo. Apenas si Pepet salía de su casa: olvidaba los campos, dejaba
en libertad a los jornaleros, no quería apartarse ni un momento de su mujer; y las gentes,
a través de la puerta entornada o por las ventanas siempre abiertas, sorprendían los abrazos;
los veían persiguiéndose entre risotadas y caricias, en plena borrachera de felicidad, insultando
con su hartura a todo el mundo. Aquello no era vivir como cristianos. Eran perros furiosos
persiguiéndose, con la sed de la pasión nunca extinguida. ¡Ah, la grandísima perdida! Ella
y la madre le abrasaban las entrañas con sus bebidas.

Bien se veía en Pepet, cada vez más flaco, más amarillo, más pequeño, como un cirio que se
derretía.

El médico del pueblo, único que se burlaba de brujas, bebedizos y de la credulidad de la gente,
hablaba de separarles como único remedio. Pero los dos siguieron unidos; él cada vez más decaído
y miserable; ella engordando, rozagante y soberbia, insultando a la murmuración con sus aires
de soberana. Tuvieron un hijo, y dos meses después murió Pepet lentamente, como luz que se
extingue, llamando a su mujer hasta el último momento, extendiendo hacia ella sus manos ansiosas.

¡La que se armó en el pueblo! Ya estaba allí el efecto de las malas bebidas. La vieja se encerró
en su casucha temiendo a la gente; la hija no salió a la calle en algunas semanas y los vecinos
oían sus lamentos. Por fin, algunas tardes, desafiando las miradas hostiles, fue con su niño
al cementerio.

Al principio le tenía cierto miedo a Teulaí, el terrible cuñado, para el cual matar era ocupación
de hombres, y que, indignado por la muerte del hermano, hablaba en la taberna de hacer pedazos
a la mujer y a la bruja de la suegra. Pero hacía un mes que había desaparecido. Estaría con
los roders en la montaña, o los negocios le habrían llevado al otro extremo de la provincia.
Marieta se atrevió, por fin, a salir del pueblo; a ir a Valencia para sus compras... ¡Ah, la
señora! ¡Qué importancia se daba con el dinero de su pobre marido! Tal vez buscaba que los
señoritos le dijesen algo, viéndola tan guapetona...

Y zumbaba en todo el vagón el cuchicheo hostil; las miradas afluían a ella, pero Marieta abría
sus ojazos imperiosos, sorbía aire ruidosamente con gesto de desprecio, y volvía a mirar los
campos de algarrobos, los empolvados olivares, las blancas casas, que huían trazando un círculo
en torno del tren en marcha, mientras el horizonte inflamábase al contacto del sol, que se
hundía entre espesos vellones de oro.

Detúvose el tren en una pequeña estación, y las mujeres que más habían hablado de Marieta se
apresuraron a bajar, echando por delante sus cestas y capazos.

Unas se quedaban en aquel pueblo y se despedían de las otras, de las vecinas de Marieta, que
aún tenían que andar una hora para llegar a sus casas.

La hermosa viuda, con el niño en brazos y apoyando en la fuerte cadera la cesta de las compras,
salió de la estación con paso lento. Quería que la adelantasen en el camino aquellas comadres
hostiles; que la dejasen marchar sola, sin tener que sufrir el tormento de sus murmuraciones.

En las calles del pueblo, estrechas, tortuosas y de avanzados aleros, había poca luz. Las últimas
casas extendíanse en dos filas a lo largo de la carretera. Más allá veíanse los campos, que
azuleaban con la llegada del crepúsculo, y a lo lejos, sobre la ancha y polvorienta faja del
camino, marcábanse como un rosario de hormigas las mujeres que, con los fardos en la cabeza,
marchaban hacia el inmediato pueblo, cuya torre asomaba tras una loma su montera de tejas barnizadas,
brillantes con el último reflejo de sol.

Marieta, brava moza, sintió repentinamente cierta inquietud al verse sola en el camino. Éste
era muy largo, y cerraría la noche antes que llegase a su casa.

Sobre una puerta balanceábase el ramo de olivo, empolvado y seco, indicador de una taberna.
Bajo de él, y de espaldas al pueblo, estaba un hombre pequeño, apoyado en el quicio y con las
manos en la faja.

Marieta se fijó en él... Si al volver la cabeza resultase que era su cuñado, ¡Dios mío, qué
susto! Pero segura de que estaba muy lejos, siguió adelante, saboreando la cruel idea del encuentro,
por lo mismo que lo creía imposible, temblando al pensar que fuese Teulaí el que estaba a la
puerta de la taberna.

Pasó junto a él sin levantar los ojos.

--Buenas tardes, Marieta.

Era él... Y la viuda, ante la realidad, no experimentó la emoción de momentos antes. No podía
dudar. Era Teulaí, el bárbaro de sonrisa traidora, que la miraba con aquellos ojos más molestos
y crueles que sus palabras.

Contestó con un ¡hola! desmayado, y ella, tan grande, tan fuerte, sintió que las piernas le
flaqueaban y hasta hizo un esfuerzo para que el niño no cayera de sus brazos.

Teulaí sonreía socarronamente. No había por qué asustarse. ¿No eran parientes? Se alegraba
del encuentro; la acompañaría al pueblo, y por el camino hablarían de algunos asuntos.

--Avant, avant--decía el hombrecillo.

Y la mocetona siguió tras él, sumisa como una oveja, formando rudo contraste aquella mujer
grande, poderosa, de fuertes músculos, que parecía arrastrada por Teulaí, enteco, miserable
y ruin, en el cual únicamente delataban el carácter los alfilerazos de extraña luz que despedían
sus ojos. Marieta sabía de lo que era capaz. Hombres fuertes y valerosos habían caído vencidos
por aquel mal bicho.

En la última casa del pueblo una vieja barría canturreando su portal.

--¡Bòna dòna, bòna dòna!--gritó Teulaí.

La buena mujer acudió, tirando la escoba. Era demasiado célebre el cuñado de Marieta en muchas
leguas a la redonda para no ser obedecido inmediatamente.

Cogió al niño de brazos de su cuñada, y sin mirarlo, como si quisiera evitar un enternecimiento
indigno de él, lo pasó a los brazos de la vieja, encargándole su cuidado... Era asunto de media
hora: volverían pronto por él, en cuanto terminasen cierto encargo.

Marieta rompió en sollozos y se abalanzó al niño para besarle. Pero su cuñado tiró de ella.

--Avant, avant.

Se hacía tarde.

Subyugada por el terror que inspiraba aquel hombrecillo venenoso a cuantos le rodeaban, siguió
adelante, sin el niño y sin la cesta, mientras la vieja, santiguándose, se apresuraba a meterse
en casa.

Apenas si se distinguían como puntos indecisos en el blanco camino las mujeres que marchaban
al pueblo. Los pardos vapores del anochecer extendíanse a ras de los campos, la arboleda tomaba
un tono de oscuro azul, y arriba, en el cielo, de color violeta, palpitaban las primeras estrellas.

Continuaron en silencio algunos minutos, hasta que Marieta se detuvo con una decisión inspirada
por el miedo... Lo que tuviera que decirle, lo mismo podía ser allí que en otra parte. Y la
temblaban las piernas, balbuceaba y no se atrevía a alzar los ojos por no ver a su cuñado.

A lo lejos sonaban chirridos de ruedas; voces prolongadas se llamaban a través de los campos,
rasgando el silencioso ambiente del crepúsculo.

Marieta miraba con ansiedad el camino. Nadie. Estaban solos ella y su cuñado.

Éste, siempre con su sonrisa infernal, hablaba con lentitud... Lo que tenía que decirle era
que rezase; y si sentía miedo, podía echarse el delantal por la cara. A un hombre como él no
le mataban un hermano impunemente.

Marieta se hizo atrás, con la expresión aterrada del que despierta en pleno peligro. Su imaginación,
ofuscada por el miedo, había concebido antes de llegar allí las mayores brutalidades; palizas
horrorosas, el cuerpo magullado, la cabellera arrancada, pero... ¡rezar y taparse la cara!
¡Morir! ¡Y tal enormidad dicha tan fríamente!...

Con palabra atropellada, temblando y suplicante, intentó enternecer a Teulaí. Todo eran mentiras
de la gente. Había querido con el alma a su pobre hermano, le quería aún; si había muerto fue
por no creerla a ella, a ella que no había tenido valor para ser esquiva y fría con un hombre
tan enamorado.

Pero el valentón la escuchaba acentuando cada vez más su sonrisa, que era ya una mueca.

--¡Calla, filla de la Bruixa!

Ella y su madre habían muerto al pobre Pepet. Todo el mundo lo sabía; le habían consumido con
malas bebidas... Y si él la escuchaba ahora sería capaz de embrujarlo también. Pero no; él
no caería como el tonto de su hermano.

Y para probar su firmeza de hiena, sin otro amor que el de la sangre, cogió con sus manos huesosas
la cara de Marieta, la levantó para verla más de cerca, contemplando sin emoción las pálidas
mejillas, los ojos negros y ardientes que brillaban tras las lágrimas.

--¡Bruixa... envenenaora!

Pequeñín y miserable en apariencia, abatió de un empujón a la buena moza; hizo caer de rodillas
aquella soberbia máquina de dura carne, y retrocediendo buscó algo en su faja.

Marieta estaba anonadada. Nadie en el camino. A lo lejos los mismos gritos, el mismo chirriar
de ruedas: cantaban las ranas en una charca inmediata; en los ribazos alborotaban los grillos,
y un perro aullaba lúgubremente allá en las últimas casas del pueblo. Los campos hundíanse
en los vapores de la noche.

Al verse sola, al convencerse de que iba a morir, desapareció toda su arrogancia de buena moza;
se sintió débil como cuando era niña y le pegaba su madre, y rompió en sollozos.

--¡Mátam, mátam!--gimió echándose a la cara el negro delantal, enrollándolo en torno de su cabeza.

Teulaí se acercó a ella impasible, con una pistola en la mano. Aún oyó la voz de su cuñada
gimiendo a través de la negra tela con lamentos de niña, rogándole que la rematase pronto,
que no la hiciera sufrir intercalando sus súplicas entre fragmentos de oraciones que recitaba
atropelladamente. Y como hombre experimentado, buscó con la boca de la pistola en aquel envoltorio
negro, disparando los dos cañones a la vez.

Entre el humo y los fogonazos viose a Marieta erguirse como impulsada por un resorte y desplomarse
con un pataleo de agonía que desordenó sus ropas.

En la masa negra e inerte quedaron al descubierto las blancas medias de seductora redondez,
estremeciéndose con el último estertor.

Teulaí, tranquilo como hombre que a nadie teme y cuenta en último término con un refugio en
la montaña, volvió al inmediato pueblo en busca de su sobrino, satisfecho de su hazaña.

Al tomar al pequeñuelo de manos de la aterrada vieja, casi lloró.

--¡Pobret! ¡pobret meu!--dijo besándole.

Y su conciencia de tío inundábase de satisfacción, seguro de haber hecho por el pequeño una
gran cosa.

La pared

Siempre que los nietos del tío Rabosa se encontraban con los hijos de la viuda de Casporra
en las sendas de la huerta o en las calles de Campanar, todo el vecindario comentaba el suceso.
¡Se habían mirado!... ¡Se insultaban con el gesto!... Aquello acabaría mal, y el día menos
pensado el pueblo sufriría un nuevo disgusto.

El alcalde con los vecinos más notables predicaban paz a los mocetones de las dos familias
enemigas, y allá iba el cura, un vejete de Dios, de una casa a otra recomendando el olvido
de las ofensas.

Treinta años que los odios de los Rabosas y Casporras traían alborotado a Campanar. Casi en
las puertas de Valencia, en el risueño pueblecito que desde la orilla del río miraba a la ciudad
con los redondos ventanales de su agudo campanario, repetían aquellos bárbaros, con un rencor
africano, la historia de luchas y violencias de las grandes familias italianas en la Edad Media.
Habían sido grandes amigos en otro tiempo; sus casas, aunque situadas en distinta calle, lindaban
por los corrales, separados únicamente por una tapia baja. Una noche, por cuestiones de riego,
un Casporra tendió en la huerta de un escopetazo a un hijo del tío Rabosa, y el hijo menor
de éste, porque no se dijera que en la familia no quedaban hombres, consiguió, después de un
mes de acecho, colocarle una bala entre las cejas al matador. Desde entonces las dos familias
vivieron para exterminarse, pensando más en aprovechar los descuidos del vecino que en el cultivo
de las tierras. Escopetazos en medio de la calle; tiros que al anochecer relampagueaban desde
el fondo de una acequia o tras los cañares o ribazos cuando el odiado enemigo regresaba del
campo; alguna vez un Rabosa o un Casporra camino del cementerio con una onza de plomo dentro
del pellejo, y la sed de venganza sin extinguirse, antes bien, extremándose con las nuevas
generaciones, pues parecía que en las dos casas los chiquitines salían ya del vientre de sus
madres tendiendo las manos a la escopeta para matar a los vecinos.

Después de treinta años de lucha, en casa de los Casporras sólo quedaba una viuda con tres
hijos mocetones que parecían torres de músculos. En la otra estaba el tío Rabosa, con sus ochenta
años, inmóvil en un sillón de esparto, con las piernas muertas por la parálisis, como un arrugado
ídolo de la venganza, ante el cual juraban sus dos nietos defender el prestigio de la familia.

Pero los tiempos eran otros. Ya no era posible ir a tiros como sus padres en plena plaza a
la salida de misa mayor. La Guardia civil no les perdía de vista; los vecinos les vigilaban,
y bastaba que uno de ellos se detuviera algunos minutos en una senda o en una esquina para
verse al momento rodeado de gente que le aconsejaba la paz. Cansados de esta vigilancia que
degeneraba en persecución y se interponía entre ellos como infranqueable obstáculo, Casporras
y Rabosas acabaron por no buscarse, y hasta se huían cuando la casualidad les ponía frente
a frente.

Tal fue su deseo de aislarse y no verse, que les pareció baja la pared que separaba sus corrales.
Las gallinas de unos y otros, escalando los montones de leña, fraternizaban en lo alto de las
bardas; las mujeres de las dos casas cambiaban desde las ventanas gestos de desprecio. Aquello
no podía resistirse; era como vivir en familia, y la viuda de Casporra hizo que sus hijos levantaran
la pared una vara. Los vecinos se apresuraron a manifestar su desprecio con piedra y argamasa,
y añadieron algunos palmos más a la pared. Y así, en esta muda y repetida manifestación de
odio, la pared fue subiendo y subiendo. Ya no se veían las ventanas; poco después no se veían
los tejados; las pobres aves del corral estremecíanse en la lúgubre sombra de aquel paredón
que las ocultaba parte del cielo, y sus cacareos sonaban tristes y apagados a través de aquel
muro, monumento del odio, que parecía amasado con los huesos y la sangre de las víctimas.

Así transcurrió el tiempo para las dos familias, sin agredirse como en otra época, pero sin
aproximarse: inmóviles y cristalizadas en su odio.

Una tarde sonaron a rebato las campanas del pueblo. Ardía la casa del tío Rabosa. Los nietos
estaban en la huerta; la mujer de uno de éstos en el lavadero, y por las rendijas de puertas
y ventanas salía un humo denso de paja quemada. Dentro, en aquel infierno que rugía buscando
expansión, estaba el abuelo, el pobre tío Rabosa, inmóvil en su sillón. La nieta se mesaba
los cabellos, acusándose como autora de todo por su descuido; la gente arremolinábase en la
calle, asustada por la fuerza del incendio. Algunos, más valientes, abrieron la puerta, pero
fue para retroceder ante la bocanada de denso humo cargada de chispas que se esparció por la calle.

--¡El agüelo! ¡El pobre agüelo!--gritaba la de los Rabosas volviendo en vano la mirada en busca
de un salvador.

Los asustados vecinos experimentaron el mismo asombro que si hubieran visto el campanario marchando
hacia ellos. Tres mocetones entraban corriendo en la casa incendiada. Eran los Casporras. Se
habían mirado cambiando un guiño de inteligencia, y sin más palabras se arrojaron como salamandras
en el enorme brasero. La multitud les aplaudió al verles reaparecer llevando en alto como a
un santo en sus andas al tío Rabosa en su sillón de esparto. Abandonaron al viejo sin mirarle
siquiera, y otra vez adentro.

--¡No, no!--gritaba la gente.

Pero ellos sonreían siguiendo adelante. Iban a salvar algo de los intereses de sus enemigos.
Si los nietos del tío Rabosa estuvieran allí, ni se habrían movido ellos de casa. Pero sólo
se trataba de un pobre viejo, al que debían proteger como hombres de corazón. Y la gente les
veía tan pronto en la calle como dentro de la casa, buceando en el humo, sacudiéndose las chispas
como inquietos demonios, arrojando muebles y sacos para volver a meterse entre las llamas.

Lanzó un grito la multitud al ver a los dos hermanos mayores sacando al menor en brazos. Un
madero, al caer, le había roto una pierna.

--¡Pronto una silla!

La gente, en su precipitación, arrancó al viejo Rabosa de su sillón de esparto para sentar
al herido.

El muchacho, con el pelo chamuscado y la cara ahumada, sonreía ocultando los agudos dolores
que le hacían fruncir los labios. Sintió que unas manos trémulas, ásperas, con las escamas
de la vejez, oprimían las suyas.

--¡Fill meu! ¡Fill meu!--gemía la voz del tío Rabosa, quien se arrastraba hacia él.

Y antes que el pobre muchacho pudiera evitarlo, el paralítico buscó con su boca desdentada
y profunda las manos que tenía agarradas, y las besó, las besó un sinnúmero de veces, bañándolas
con lágrimas.

       *       *       *       *       *

Ardió toda la casa. Y cuando los albañiles fueron llamados para construir otra, los nietos
del tío Rabosa no les dejaron comenzar por la limpia del terreno, cubierto de negros escombros.
Antes tenían que hacer un trabajo más urgente: derribar la pared maldita. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10957</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>225444</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15702</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Marieta's brought Pepet that
den, pleased to have as his most beautiful woman in the district.

What a way to live! Good women remembered him with scandal. Everyone could see that this marriage
was for Bad Art. Pepet barely left his house, forgot the fields, leaving release the laborers
did not want a moment away from his wife, and the people, through the open door or windows always
open, caught the hugs; saw them chasing each laughter and caresses, in full intoxication of happiness,
insulting fill with everyone. That was not live as Christians. They were angry dogs chasing,
with the thirst of passion never extinguished. Ah, the great loss! She and the mother blazed
guts with their drinks.

Everyone could see in Pepet increasingly thinner, more yellow, smaller,
like a candle that melting.

The village doctor, only to be mocked witches, potions and credulity, talked to separate them
as the only remedy. But the two went together, he increasingly fallen and miserable, she getting
fat, ruddy, arrogant, insulting gossip with their air of sovereignty.

They had a son, and two months after Pepet died slowly, like a light extinguished, calling his wife
until the last minute, extending his hand to her anxious.

The one that was assembled in the village!

Was there the effect of bad drinks. The old woman locked in his hut fearing people, the daughter
went out in a few weeks and neighbors heard their cries. Finally, some evenings, defying the hostile
stares, was with her child the cemetery.

At first he was somewhat afraid to Teulaí, the terrible brother, for whom killing was occupation
men, and, outraged by the death of his brother, spoke at the tavern to pieces the woman and
the witch mother. But a month ago it was gone.

Be with the roders in the mountains, or the business would have led to the other end of the province.
Marieta dared at last to leave the village, to go to Valencia for shopping ... Ah, lady! How
important is giving the money to her poor husband! Perhaps it wanted the snobs will say something,
seeing it as nice weekend ...

And buzzing around the car whispering hostile poured into her eyes, but opened Marieta their
large eyes compelling, loud air sucked in a gesture of contempt,
and turned to look at carob trees, the dusty olive, white houses,
fleeing in a circle around the train, while the horizon inflammable
on contact with the sun, which sinking through thick fleece of gold.

He stopped the train at a small station, and women who had discussed more Marieta hurried down,
throwing forward their baskets and baskets.

Some stayed in the village and fired from the other, the neighbors of Marietta, which still had to
walk an hour to get home.

The beautiful widow with a child in her arms and supporting the strong hip shopping cart, left
the station at a slow pace. I wanted the down the road those gossips hostile to be allowed to go alone,
without having to suffer the torment of his grumbling.

In the town's streets, narrow, tortuous and advanced eaves, there was little light. Latest extendíanse
houses in two rows along the road. Could be seen beyond the fields, blue with the arrival of
dusk, and far above the broad, dusty strip of way, like a rosary
marcábanse ant women with head bundles, immediately marched towards
the village, whose tower looming behind a hill its cap of glazed tiles,
bright with the latest reflection of the sun.

Marieta, brave girl, suddenly felt some anxiety at being alone on the road. This was very long,
and closed the night before he got home.

On a door balanceábase the olive branch, dusty and dry, an indicator of a tavern. Under him, and
back to town was a small man, leaning against the doorjamb and the hands on the belt.

Marieta noticed him ... If it turns out that looking back was his brother, my God, what shock!
But sure it was far away, moved on, savoring the cruel idea of ??meeting
through what I thought impossible, trembling at the thought that was
Teulaí which was to tavern door.

Walked past him without looking up.

- Good afternoon, Marieta.

Was it ... And the widow, to reality, did not experience the thrill of times before. Could not
doubt.

Teulaí was the Barbarian treacherous smile, as he looked more upset
with those eyes and cruel than his words.

Answered with a hello! fainted, and she, so great, so strong, she
felt her legs wavered and even made an effort to make the child fall
from her arms.

Teulaí smiled slyly. There was no need to panic. Were they not related?

He was glad the meeting, would accompany the people and by the way talk of some issues.

- Avant, avant - said the man.

And Bouncers followed after him, meek as a lamb, forming contrast
rude woman big, powerful, strong muscles, which seemed drawn by Teulaí,
sickly, miserable and ruin, in which only betrayed the character the
pinpricks of light that gave off strange his eyes.

Marieta knew what he was capable. Strong and brave men had fallen due by the evil bug.

In the last house in the village an old neighborhood chanting his website.

- Donates Bona, bona Donate! - Teulaí shouted.

The good woman went, pulling the broom. It was too famous Marieta's brother-in many miles around
not to be obeyed immediately.

He took the child from the arms of her sister, and without looking, as if to avoid a tenderness
unworthy of him, he passed into the arms of the old, entrusting their care ... Was a matter
of half Time: back soon for him, as after a certain order.

Marieta broke into tears and rushed the child to kiss him. But his brother pulled.

- Avant, avant.

It was getting late.

Subdued by the terror inspired by this man poisonous to those around
him, continued Later, without the child and without the basket, while
the old woman crossing herself, she hurried to get at home.

Hardly be distinguished as white spots in the road undecided women marching the people. The
dark brown fumes extendíanse separate fields, the trees took a shade
of dark blue, and up in the sky, purple, pulsing the first stars.

Continued silent several minutes, until Marieta stopped with an inspired
choice fear ... What I had to say, the same could be there than elsewhere.

And legs trembled, stammered and did not dare raise his eyes from
seeing your brother.

In the distance sounded squeaky wheels of extended voice called through the fields, tearing the
quiet atmosphere of twilight.

Marietta looked forward to the road.

Nobody. They were alone she and her brother.

This, always with his infernal smile, spoke slowly ... What I had
to say was to pray, and if he was afraid he could throw her apron
over her face.

To a man as he a brother kill him with impunity.

Marietta drew back, with the terrified expression when one awakes in the middle of danger. His
imagination, clouded by fear, had conceived before I got there the greatest brutality, beatings horrible,
the body bruised, her hair pulled, but ... Pray and cover your face!

Die! And such enormity that so coldly! ...

With word hit, trembling, pleading, tried to soften Teulaí. All were lies people. He had wanted
the soul to his poor brother, he still wanted, if he was dead not
believe her, she had not had the courage to be aloof and cold with
a man so in love.

But the bully listened increasingly emphasizing his smile, which was
already a grin.

- Shut up, fill the Bruixa!

She and her mother had died the poor Pepet.

Everyone knew it had consumed bad drinks ... And if he listened now
also be able to bewitch.

But no, he not fall as the fool of his brother.

And to prove his strength of hyena, no other love than that of blood, grabbed his bony hands
Marieta's face, lifted for a closer look, looking pale emotionless
cheeks, black eyes burning behind the tears shining.

- Bruixa ...
envenenaora!

Tiny and miserable in appearance, struck a boost to the good-looking,
his knees this superb machine hard flesh, and reached into his back
belt.

Marietta was shocked. Nobody on the road. In the distance the same cries, the same chirp Wheel:
singing frogs in a pond immediate rattled on the slopes the crickets and a dog howled mournfully
beyond the last houses in the village. Hundíanse fields in the vapors of the night.

Finding himself alone, to convince himself that he would die, all his arrogance disappeared
pretty girl; felt weak as a child and his mother beat him and broke into sobs.

- Kill me, kill me! - Moaned face breaking into the black apron wrapped around his head.

Teulaí impassive approached her with a gun in his hand. Even heard the voice of his sister moaning
through the black cloth as a child cries, begging him to the top area soon that did not suffer
inserting their pleas between fragments of prayers recited hastily. And as a man of experience,
looked to the mouth of the gun in one package black, firing both barrels at once.

Amid the smoke and the flashes Marieta saw himself standing like a spring-driven collapse with
a kick of his clothes messed agony.

In the black mass were exposed inert white stockings seductive roundness
quivering with the last gasp.

Teulaí, quiet as a man who has no fear and ultimately to a shelter in the mountain, immediately
returned to the village in search of his nephew, satisfied with his achievement.

By taking the little one's hands of the terrified old, almost cried.

- Poblete! Meu poor fellow! - Said kissing him.

And his uncle inundábase awareness of satisfaction have made sure the little one big deal.

Wall

Whenever Uncle Rabosa grandchildren were the children of the widow of Casporra in the paths of
the garden or on the streets of Campanar, the whole neighborhood commented the event. It had
looked! ... Was insulted by the gesture! ... That would end badly, and when you least thought
the people would suffer a new disappointment.

The mayor's most notable residents preached peace to the young man
of the two families enemy, and he was the priest, an old man of God,
from one house to another recommending oblivion offenses.

Thirty years of hatred and Casporras Rabosas brought uproar to Campana. Almost the gates of Valencia,
the sunny little town from the river looking at the city with the round windows of his sharp
bell, echoed those barbarians, with a grudge Africa, the history of struggles and violence
of the great Italian families in the Middle Ages. They had been friends in another time, their
homes, although located in different streets, bordered by the pen,
separated only by a low wall.

One night, for reasons of irrigation a Casporra tended in the garden of a shotgun to a child's
uncle Rabosa, and the youngest of this, because it was stated that
the family were not men, succeeded, after a months of stalking, placing
a bullet between the eyes to the killer.

Since then the two families live to kill themselves, thinking more about harness the neighbor's carelessness
in the cultivation land. Gunshots in the middle of the street at dusk shots flashed from the
bottom of a ditch or embankment after cañares or when returning from the hated enemy field, once a
Rabosa or Casporra way to the cemetery with an ounce of lead in the skin, and thirst for revenge
without extinction, rather, ends with the new generations, it seemed that in both houses and
the little ones out of his belly mothers tending their hands the
shotgun to kill the neighbors.

After thirty years of struggle, only Casporras house was a widow with three children seemed
towers guys went muscles. The other was the guy Rabosa, with eighty years, still on a couch
of straw, his legs dead from paralysis as a wrinkled idol of vengeance, to which his two grandsons
vowed to defend the prestige of the family.

But times were different.

It was no longer possible to go dead and their parents in the middle
square output mass. The Civil Guard were not lost sight of, the neighbors
watched, and one of them was enough to stop a few minutes in a trail
or in a corner be when surrounded by people who advised him peace.

Tired of this surveillance degenerated into persecution and stood between them as insurmountable
obstacles, Casporras and eventually Rabosas not found, and even fled
when they stand before the accident to face.

Such was his desire not to be isolated and that seemed low wall that
separated their yards.

The hens of each other, climbing the piles of firewood, fraternizing
at the top of the fences, the women of both houses changed from windows
gestures of contempt.

What I could not resist, it was like living with the family and the widow had her children
Casporra lifted a rod wall. The neighbors were quick to express their disdain with stone and mortar,
and added some more to the wall spans.

       And so, in this move and repeated demonstration hatred, the Wall
was going up and up.

No longer see the windows and shortly thereafter were not the roofs of poor poultry birds
trembled in the dark shadow of that wall that hid the sky, and their crowing sounded sad and subdued
through that Wall, monument of hatred, which looked kneaded with
bones and blood of the victims.

Thus passed the time for the two
families, not attack each other and in time, but approach: stationary
and crystallized in their hatred.

One afternoon sounded the alarm
bells of the village. Uncle's house burned Rabosa. Grandchildren were
in the garden, the wife of one of these in the laundry room, and through
the cracks of doors out windows and thick smoke from burning straw.
Inside, looking raging inferno expansion, was the grandfather, the
poor guy Rabosa motionless in his chair. The granddaughter was tearing
hair, arrested and charged for his neglect, people in arremolinábase
Street, frightened by the force of fire. Some, braver, opened the
door, but was to go back to the dense cloud of smoke filled with sparks
that spread down the street.

- The grandfather! Poor grandfather!
- Screamed that of Rabosas look back in vain in search on a savior.

The
frightened neighbors experienced the same awe as if they had seen
the bell march to them. Three guys went running into the burning house.
Were Casporras. It had looked at changing a nod of intelligence, and
without further words were thrown as salamanders in the huge hearth.
The crowd cheered at seeing them reappear as holding high a saint
in his litter Rabosa the guy on his couch of straw. Without looking
at the old abandoned even, and again inside.

- No, no - people screaming.

But
they smiled moving forward. Iban to save some of the interests of
their enemies. If Uncle Rabosa grandchildren were there, or would
have moved them from home. But only it was an old man, who must protect
as men of heart. And people are soon saw on the street and inside
the house, going into the smoke, sparks shaking as restless demons,
throwing furniture and bags for getting back into the flames.

The
crowd screamed when they saw the two older brothers taking the child
in her arms. A tree, fell, broke her leg.

- Soon a chair!

People,
in their haste, tore the old Rabosa of his chair to sit esparto the
wounded.

The boy, his hair singed and smoky face, smile hiding the
pangs that made him puckering. He felt shaky hands, rough, with scales
of old age, oppressing their own.

- Fill meu! Fill meu! - Wailed
the voice of Rabosa uncle, who was crawling toward him.

And before
the poor boy could stop the paralytic sought with his toothless mouth
deep and had clasped hands and kissed them, kissed them countless
times, bathing them with tears.

* * * * *

It burned the whole house.
And when the builders were called in to build another, grandchildren
Rabosa uncle would not let them start with clean ground, covered with
black debris. Previously they had to do a more urgent: the wall down
damn</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>