<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04501</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>122900</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17992</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Hasta el alcalde estaba aquí, para servir en lo que fuera bueno. Y los carabineros, excelentes
muchachos que viven entre nosotros y son casi de la familia, hacíanse a un lado, comprendiendo
la situación y no queriendo perder a unos pobres.

--¡A tierra, muchachos!--gritaba nuestro patrón--. Vamos a embarrancar. Lo que importa es poner
en salvo fardos y personas. El Socarrao ya sabrá salir de este mal paso.

Y sin plegar casi el trapo, embestimos la playa, clavando la proa en la arena. ¡Señor, qué
modo de trabajar! Aún me parece un sueño cuando lo recuerdo. Todo el pueblo se tiró sobre la
barca, la tomó por asalto: los chicuelos se deslizaban como ratas en la cala.

--¡Aprisa! ¡Aprisa! ¡Que vienen los del gobierno!

Los fardos saltaban de la cubierta: caían en el agua, donde los recogían los hombres descalzos
y las mujeres con la falda entre las piernas; unos desaparecían por aquí; otros se iban por
allá; fue aquello visto y no visto, y en poco rato desapareció el cargamento, como si lo hubiera
tragado la arena. Una oleada de tabaco inundaba a Torresalinas, filtrándose en todas las casas.

El alcalde intervino paternalmente.

--Hombre, es demasiado--dijo al patrón--. Todo se lo llevan, y los carabineros se quejarán.
Dejad al menos algunos bultos para justificar la aprehensión.

Nuestro amo estaba conforme.

--Bueno; haced unos cuantos bultos con dos fardos de la peor picadura. Que se contenten con eso.

Y se alejó hacia el pueblo, llevándose en el pecho toda la documentación de la barca. Pero
aún se detuvo un momento, porque aquel diablo de hombre estaba en todo.

--¡Los folios! ¡Borrad los folios!

Parecía que a la barca le habían salido patas. Estaba ya fuera del agua y se arrastraba por
la arena en medio de aquella multitud que bullía y trabajaba, animándose con alegres gritos.

--¡Qué chasco! ¡Qué chasco se llevarán los del gobierno!

El compañero de la pierna rota era llevado en alto por su mujer y su madre. El pobrecillo gemía
de dolor a cada movimiento brusco, pero se tragaba las lágrimas y reía también como los otros,
viendo que el cargamento se salvaba y pensando en aquel chasco que hacía reír a todos.

Cuando los últimos fardos se perdieron en las calles de Torresalinas, comenzó la rapiña de
la barca. El gentío se llevó las velas, las anclas, los remos: hasta desmontamos el mástil,
que se cargó en hombros una turba de muchachos, llevándolo en procesión al otro extremo del
pueblo. La barca quedó hecha un pontón, tan pelada como usted la ve.

Y mientras tanto, los calafates, brocha en mano, pinta que pinta. El Socarrao se desfiguraba
como un burro de gitano. Con cuatro brochazos fue borrado el nombre de popa; y de los folios
de los costados, de esos malditos letreros, que son la cédula de toda embarcación, no quedó
ni rastro.

El cañonero echó anclas al mismo tiempo que desaparecían en la entrada del pueblo los últimos
despojos de la barca. Yo me quedé en este sitio, queriendo verlo todo, y para mayor disimulo
ayudaba a unos amigos que echaban al mar una lancha de pesca.

El cañonero envió un bote armado, y saltaron a tierra no sé cuántos hombres con fusil y bayoneta.
El contramaestre, que iba al frente, juraba furioso mirando a El Socarrao y a los carabineros,
que se habían apoderado de él.

Todo el vecindario de Torresalinas se reía a aquellas horas, celebrando el chasco, y aún hubiera
reído más, viendo, como yo, la cara que ponía aquella gente al encontrar por todo cargamento
unos cuantos bultos de tabaco malo.

--¿Y qué pasó después?--pregunté al viejo--. ¿No castigaron a nadie?

--¿A quién? Únicamente podían castigar al pobre Socarrao, que quedó prisionero. Se ensució
mucho papel y medio pueblo fue a declarar; pero nadie sabía nada. ¿De qué matrícula era el
barco? Silencio; nadie le había visto los folios. ¿Quiénes lo tripulaban? Unos hombres que
al varar habían echado a correr tierra adentro. Y nadie sabía más.

--¿Y el cargamento?--dije yo.

--Lo vendimos completo. Usted no sabe lo que es la pobreza. Cuando embarrancamos, cada uno
agarró el fardo que tenía más a mano y echó a correr para esconderlo en su casa. Pero al día
siguiente estaban todos a disposición del patrón: no se perdió ni una libra de tabaco. Los
que exponen la vida por el pan y todos los días le ven la cara a la muerte, están más libres
de tentaciones que los otros...

--Desde entonces--continuó el viejo--que está aquí preso el pobre Socarrao. Pero no tardará
en hacerse a la mar con su antiguo amo. Parece que ha terminado el papeleo; lo sacarán a subasta,
y se lo quedará el patrón por lo que quiera dar.

--¿Y si otro da más?

--¿Y quién ha de ser ese? ¿Somos acaso bandidos? Todo el pueblo sabe quién es el verdadero
amo de la barca abandonada, y nadie tiene tan mal corazón que intente perjudicarle. Aquí hay
mucha honradez. A cada uno lo que sea suyo: el mar, que es de Dios, para nosotros los pobres,
que hemos de sacar el pan de él, aunque no quiera el gobierno.

El maniquí

Nueve años habían transcurrido desde que Luis Santurce se separó de su mujer. Después la había
visto envuelta en sedas y tules en el fondo de elegante carruaje, pasando ante él como un relámpago
de belleza, o la había adivinado desde el paraíso del Real, allá abajo, en un palco, rodeada
de señores que se disputaban el murmurar algo a su oído para hacer gala de una intimidad sonriente.

Estos encuentros removían en él todo el sedimento de la pasada ira: había huido siempre de
su mujer como enfermo que teme el recrudecimiento de sus dolencias, y sin embargo, ahora iba
a su encuentro, a verla y hablarla en aquel hotel de la Castellana, cuyo lujo insolente era
el testimonio de su deshonra.

Los rudos movimientos del coche de alquiler parecían hacer saltar los recuerdos del pasado
de todos los rincones de su memoria. Aquella vida que no quería recordar, iba desarrollándose
ante sus ojos cerrados: su luna de miel de empleado modesto casado con una mujer bonita y educada,
hija de una familia venida a menos; la felicidad de aquel primer año de pobreza endulzado por
el cariño; después, las protestas de Enriqueta revolviéndose contra la estrechez; el sordo
disgusto al oírse llamar hermosa por todos y verse humildemente vestida; los disgustos surgiendo
por el más leve motivo; las reyertas a media noche en la alcoba conyugal; las sospechas royendo
poco a poco la confianza del marido, y de repente el ascenso inesperado, el bienestar material
colándose por las puertas, primero tímidamente, como evitando el escándalo; después con insolente
ostentación, como creyendo entrar en un mundo de ciegos, hasta que ya por fin Luis tuvo la
prueba indudable de su desgracia. Se avergonzaba al recordar su debilidad. No era un cobarde,
estaba seguro de ello, pero le faltaba voluntad o la amaba demasiado, y por esto, cuando tras
un vergonzoso espionaje se convenció de su deshonra, sólo supo levantar la crispada mano sobre
aquella hermosa cara de muñeca pálida, y acabó por no descargar el golpe. Sólo tuvo fuerzas
para arrojarla de la casa y llorar como un niño abandonado apenas cerró la puerta.

Después, la soledad completa, la monotonía del aislamiento, interrumpida por noticias que le
hacían daño. Su mujer viajaba por el centro de Europa como una princesa; un millonario la había
lanzado; aquella era su verdadera existencia, para aquello había nacido. Todo un invierno llamó
la atención en París; los periódicos hablaban de la hermosa española; sus triunfos en las playas
de moda eran ruidosos, se buscaba como un honor arruinarse por ella, y varios duelos y ciertos
rumores de suicidio formaban en torno de su nombre un ambiente de leyenda. Después de tres
años de correría triunfal, volvió a Madrid, acrecentada su hermosura por el extraño encanto
del cosmopolitismo. Ahora la protegía el más rico negociante de España, y en su espléndido
hotel reinaba sobre una corte sólo de hombres: ministros, banqueros, políticos influyentes,
personajes de todas clases que buscaban su sonrisa como la mejor de sus condecoraciones.

Tan grande era su poder, que hasta Luis creía sentirlo en torno de su persona, viendo que se
sucedían las situaciones políticas sin que le tocasen su empleo. El miedo a combatir por el
sostenimiento de la vida le hacía aceptar aquella situación, en la que adivinaba la mano oculta
de Enriqueta. Solo y condenado a trabajar para vivir, sentía, sin embargo, la vergüenza del
miserable que tiene como único mérito ser esposo de una mujer hermosa. Todo su valor consistía
en huir cuando la encontraba a su paso, insolente y triunfadora en su deshonra; huir perseguido
por aquellos ojos que se fijaban en él con sorpresa, perdiendo su altivez de mujer codiciada.

Un día recibió la visita de un cura viejo y de aspecto tímido; el mismo que ahora iba sentado
junto a él en el coche. Era el confesor de su mujer. ¡Bien había sabido escogerlo! Un señor
bondadoso, de cortos alcances. Cuando dijo quién le enviaba, Luis no pudo contenerse: «¡Valiente
tal!», y soltó redondo el insulto. Pero imperturbable el buen viejo, como quien trae aprendido
el discurso y lo teme olvidar si tarda en soltarlo, le habló de Magdalena pecadora; del Señor,
que siendo quien era, la había perdonado; y pasando al estilo llano y natural, contó la transformación
sufrida por Enriqueta. Estaba enferma; apenas si salía de su hotel; una enfermedad que roía
sus entrañas, un cáncer al que había que domar con continuas inyecciones de morfina para que
no la hiciera desfallecer y rugir de dolor con sus crueles arañazos. La desgracia la había
hecho volver sus ojos a Dios; se arrepentía del pasado, quería verle...

Y él, el hombre cobarde, saltaba de gozo al oír esto, con la satisfacción del débil que se
ve vengado. ¡Un cáncer!... ¡El maldito lujo que se pudría dentro de ella, haciéndola morir
en vida! Y siempre tan hermosa, ¿verdad? ¡Qué dulce venganza!... No; no iría a verla. Era inútil
que el cura buscase argumentos. Podía visitarle cuando quisiera y darle noticias de su mujer:
aquello le alegraba mucho; ahora comprendía por qué los hombres son malos.

Desde entonces el cura le visitaba casi todas las tardes, para fumar unos cuantos cigarros,
hablando de Enriqueta, y alguna vez salían juntos, paseando por las afueras de Madrid como
antiguos amigos.

La enfermedad avanzaba rápidamente; Enriqueta estaba convencida de que iba a morir. Quería
verle para implorar su perdón; así lo pedía, con tono de niña caprichosa y enferma que exige
un juguete. Hasta el otro, el protector poderoso, dócil a pesar de su omnipotencia, le suplicaba
al cura que llevase al hotel al marido de Enriqueta. El buen viejo hablaba con fervor de la
conmovedora conversión de la señora, aunque confesando que el maldito lujo, perdición de tantas
almas, todavía la dominaba. La enfermedad la tenía prisionera en su casa; pero en los momentos
de calma, cuando el pícaro dolor no la hacía ir de un lado a otro como una loca, hojeaba catálogos
y figurines de París, escribía a sus proveedores de allá, y rara era la semana en que no llegaban
cajones con las últimas novedades: trajes, sombreros y joyas que, después de contemplados y
manoseados un día en el cerrado dormitorio, caían en los rincones o se ocultaban para siempre
en los armarios, como juguetes inútiles. Por todos estos caprichos pasaba el otro, con tal
de ver a Enriqueta sonriente.

Estas continuas confidencias hacían penetrar lentamente a Luis en la vida de su mujer; seguía
de lejos el curso de su enfermedad y no pasaba día sin que mentalmente se rozase con aquel
ser, del que se había apartado para siempre.

Una tarde se presentó el cura con desusada energía. Aquella señora estaba en las últimas, le
llamaba a gritos; era un crimen negar el último consuelo a una moribunda, y él no lo consentía.
Sentíase capaz de llevárselo a viva fuerza. Luis, vencido por la voluntad del viejo, se dejó
arrastrar y subió a un coche, insultándose mentalmente, pero sin fuerzas para retroceder...
¡Cobarde! ¡Cobarde para siempre!

En pos de la negra sotana atravesó el jardín del hotel que tantas veces, al pasar por el inmediato
paseo, había espiado con miradas de odio... Y ahora, nada; ni odio ni dolor: un vivo sentimiento
de curiosidad, como el que entra en país desconocido, paladeando anticipadamente las maravillas
que espera ver.

Dentro del hotel la misma impresión de curiosidad y asombro. ¡Ah, miserable! ¡Cuántas veces,
en los ensueños de su voluntad impotente, se había visto entrando en aquella casa como un marido
de drama, el arma en la mano para matar a la esposa infiel, y destrozando después, como una
fiera loca, los muebles costosos, los ricos cortinajes, las mullidas alfombras! Y ahora la
blandura que sentía bajo sus pies, los bellos colores por los que resbalaba su mirada, las
flores que le saludaban con su perfume desde los rincones, causábanle una embriaguez de eunuco,
y sentía impulsos de tenderse en aquellos muebles, de tomar posesión, como si le pertenecieran,
por ser de su mujer. Ahora comprendía lo que era la riqueza y con qué fuerza pesaba sobre sus
esclavos. Estaba ya en el primer piso, y ni siquiera había percibido, en la calma solemne del
hotel, ninguno de esos detalles con que se revela la muerte al entrar en una casa.

Vio criados tras cuya máscara impasible creyó percibir un gesto de curiosidad insolente: una
doncella le saludó con enigmática sonrisa, que no se sabía si era de simpatía o de burla para
«el marido de la señora»; creyó distinguir en una habitación inmediata un señor que se ocultaba
(tal vez era el otro); y aturdido por aquel mundo nuevo, atravesó una puerta, empujado suavemente
por su guía.

Estaba en el dormitorio de la señora: una habitación sumida en suave penumbra, que rasgaba
una faja de sol filtrándose por un balcón entreabierto.

En medio de este rayo de luz estaba una mujer erguida, esbelta, sonrosada, vestida con un hermoso
traje de soirée, las nacaradas espaldas surgiendo de entre nubes de blondas, y el pecho y la
cabeza deslumbrantes con el centelleo de las joyas. Luis retrocedió asombrado, protestando
de la farsa. ¿Aquella era la enferma? ¿Le habían llamado para insultarle?

--¡Luis... Luis!...--gimió tras él una voz débil, con entonación infantil y suave, que le recordaba
el pasado, los mejores instantes de su vida.

Sus ojos, acostumbrados ya a la oscuridad, vieron en el fondo de la habitación algo monumental
e imponente como un altar: una cama con gradas, y en la cual, bajo los ondulantes cortinajes,
se incorporaba trabajosamente una figura blanca.

Entonces se fijó en la mujer inmóvil, que parecía esperarle con su esbelta rigidez y sus ojos
de vaga mirada, como empañados por lágrimas. Era un artístico maniquí que guardaba cierta semejanza
con Enriqueta. La servía para poder contemplar mejor aquellas novedades que continuamente recibía
de París. Era el único actor de las representaciones de elegancia y riqueza que se daba a solas
para remedio de su enfermedad.

--¡Luis... Luis!...--volvió a gemir la vocecita desde el fondo de la cama.

Tristemente fue Luis hacia ella para verse agarrado por unos brazos que le apretaron convulsivamente
y sentir una boca ardorosa que buscaba la suya, implorando perdón, al mismo tiempo que en una
mejilla recibía la tibia caricia de las lágrimas.

--Di que me perdonas; dilo, Luis, y tal vez no me muera.

Y el marido, que instintivamente intentaba repelerla, acabó por abandonarse entre aquellos
brazos, repitiendo sin darse cuenta las mismas palabras cariñosas de los tiempos felices. Ante
sus ojos, habituados a la oscuridad, iba marcándose con todos sus detalles el rostro de su mujer.

--¡Luis, Luis mío!--decía ella sonriendo en medio de las lágrimas--. ¿Cómo me encuentras? Ya
no soy tan hermosa como en nuestros tiempos de felicidad... cuando yo aún no era loca. Dime,
¡por Dios! dime qué te parezco.

Su marido la miraba con asombro. Hermosa, siempre hermosa, aquella belleza infantil e ingenua
que tan temible la hacía. La muerte aún no estaba allí: únicamente por entre el suave perfume
de aquella carne soberana, de aquel lecho majestuoso, parecía deslizarse un vaho sutil y lejano
de materia muerta, algo que delataba la interior descomposición que se mezclaba en sus besos.

Luis adivinó la presencia de alguien detrás de él. Un hombre estaba a pocos pasos, contemplándolos
con expresión confusa, como atraído allí por un impulso superior a la voluntad que le avergonzaba.
El marido de Enriqueta conocía, como media nación, la austera cara de aquel señor ya entrado
en años, hombre de sanos principios, gran defensor de la moral pública.

--¡Dile que se vaya, Luis!--gritó la enferma--. ¿Qué hace ahí ese hombre? Yo sólo te quiero
a ti... sólo quiero a mi marido. Perdóname... fue el lujo, el maldito lujo: necesitaba dinero,
mucho dinero; pero amar... sólo a ti.

Enriqueta lloraba mostrando su arrepentimiento, y aquel hombre lloraba también, débil y humilde
ante el desprecio.

Luis, que tantas veces había pensado en él con arrebatos de cólera, y que al verle había sentido
impulsos de arrojarse a su cuello, acabó por mirarle con simpatía y respeto. ¡También la amaba!
Y la comunidad en el afecto, en vez de repelerlos, ligaba al marido y al otro con una simpatía
extraña.

--Que se vaya, que se vaya--repetía la enferma con una terquedad infantil.

Y su marido miraba al hombre poderoso con expresión suplicante, como si pidiera perdón para
su mujer, que no sabía lo que decía.

--Vamos, doña Enriqueta--dijo desde el fondo de la habitación la voz del cura--. Piense usted
en sí misma y en Dios: no incurra en el pecado de soberbia.

Los dos hombres, el marido y el protector, acabaron por sentarse junto al lecho de la enferma.
El dolor la hacía rugir, había que darla frecuentes inyecciones, y los dos acudían solícitos
a su cuidado. Varias veces se tropezaron sus manos al incorporar a Enriqueta, y no los separó
una repulsión instintiva; antes bien, se ayudaban con efusión fraternal.

Luis encontraba cada vez más simpático a aquel buen señor, de trato tan llano a pesar de sus
millones, y que lloraba a su mujer más aún que él. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07318</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>638813</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16324</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Even the mayor was here, to serve on what was good. And the police, excellent boys who live among
us and are almost family, hacíanse aside, understanding the situation and not wanting to miss
a few poor.

- To earth, boys - screaming our pattern -. Let's run aground.

What matters is to in bundles and save people. The Socarrao already know this evil out of
step.

And cloth unfolded almost rammed the beach, digging the bow into the
sand.

Lord, what way of working! Still seems like a dream when I remember. The whole town was thrown
on boat, took by assault: the youngsters like mice slipped into the cove.

- Quick! Quick! What are the government!

Packages jumped from the roof: they fell into the water, where men gathered barefoot and women
with the skirt between the legs, some disappearing around here, others
were on there, was something seen and unseen, and soon disappeared
while loading, as if he had swallowed sand.

A wave of flooding to snuff Torresalinas, seeping into every home.

The mayor intervened paternally.

- Men, too - said the pattern -. Have it all, and the police complain. Leave at least some packages
in order to justify apprehension.

Our master was satisfied.

- Well: do a few packages with two bundles of the worst sting. To
be content with that.

And he went into town, taking in the chest all the documents of the boat. But even stopped for
a moment, because that devil of a man was in everything.

- The sheets! Delete pages!

It seemed that the boat had left legs.

Was out of the water and dragged by sand in the middle of that crowd seethed and work, animated
with happy cries.

- What a disappointment! What a disappointment will be the government!

The companion of the broken leg was carried aloft by his wife and
mother.

The poor man groaned of sharp pain with every movement, but swallowed the tears and laughed too
as the others, seeing that the cargo was saved and thinking of that disappointment which made
everyone laugh.

When the last bales were lost in the streets of Torresalinas began the plunder of the boat.
The crowd took the sails, anchors, oars, to dismantle the mast, was loaded on the shoulders
of a crowd of boys, leading him in procession to the other end of people. The boat was made
a pontoon, as bare as you see it.

Meanwhile, the shipwrights, brush in hand, he paints he paints. The Socarrao is disfigured
Roma as a donkey. With four strokes was erased the name of stern and folios the sides of those
damn signs, which are the charter of any vessel, was not trace.

The striker dropped anchor at the same time disappearing into the
edge of town the past remains of the boat.

I stood on this site, wanting to see everything, and more openly helped some friends who were
putting to sea a fishing boat.

The striker sent an armed boat, and jumped to the ground do not know
how many men with a rifle and bayonet.

The boatswain, who was leading, swore furiously looking at the Socarrao and carabinieri, who
had seized him.

Torresalinas entire neighborhood laughed at that hour, celebrating
the disappointment, and even had laughed more, seeing as I, the face
that put those people to find all cargo a few packages of snuff bad.

-
What happened next? - Asked the old man -.

Do not punish anybody?

- Who?

Could only punish the poor Socarrao, which was taken. Is dirty lot of paper and half the town
was to testify, but nobody knew anything. What was the enrollment boat? Silence, no one had seen the
folios. About the manned? Some men the beach had run inland. And nobody knew more.

- And the cargo? "- I said.

- I completely sold. You do not know what poverty is. When stranded, each grabbed the bundle
that was at hand and ran to hide at home.

But the day were all available following the pattern: not lost even a pound of snuff. The
exposing the bread of life and every day you see the face of death, are freer temptations than
others ...

- Since then - continued the old man - who is here imprisoned Socarrao poor. But do not take
in going to sea with his old master. Seems to have completed paperwork, bring him out to auction
and it will be the pattern for what you want to.

- What if another more?

- Who has to be that? Are we outlaws? All the people know who the real master of the ship abandoned,
and nobody has so badly hurt heart to try. Here much honesty. To each what is his: the sea, which
is of God, to us poor, we have to remove the bread from him, but does not want the government.

The
dummy

Nine years had passed since Louis Santurce was separated from his wife. After he had been involved
in silk and tulle at the bottom of elegant carriage, passing before him in a flash beauty, or had
guessed from the paradise of Real, down there in a box, surrounded of men who were fighting the
murmuring something in her ear to show off an intimacy smiling.

These events removed in all the sediment of the last wrath had fled forever his wife as a patient
who fears the resurgence of their ailments, and yet, now would to meet, to see it and speak
it at the hotel de la Castellana, which was insolent luxury the witness of his disgrace.

The rough movements rental car seemed to blow past memories from all
corners of his memory.

That life did not want to remember, was developing with your eyes closed: their honeymoon modest
employee married to a beautiful woman, educated, daughter of a family fallen on hard times,
the joy of that first year of poverty sweetened by affection, then tossing Enriqueta protests against
the narrowness, the deaf displeasure at being called beautiful by all and be humbly dressed,
the troubles emerging for the slightest reason, the brawls at midnight in the marital bedroom,
the gnawing suspicion Gradually confidence husband, and suddenly the unexpected rise, material
wealth slipping through the door, timidly at first, and avoiding
the scandal, then insolent display, as believing enter a world of
blind people, until they finally Louis had the unquestionable proof
of his misfortune.

He was ashamed to remember his weakness. It was not a coward was sure of it, but lacked the will
or loved him too, and therefore, when after an embarrassing intelligence was convinced of his
disgrace, he knew only raise the clenched hand that beautiful doll face pale, and ended up not strike
a blow. Only had the strength to throw the house and mourn as an abandoned child just closed the
door.

Then complete solitude, the monotony of isolation, interrupted by news that they hurt. His wife
was traveling through central Europe as a princess, a millionaire had released, this was their
very existence, for what he was born. A winter call attention in Paris, the newspapers talked
about the beautiful Spanish, and his triumphs on the beaches were
noisy fashion, tried to ruin an honor for her, and several duels and
certain rumors of suicide were around his name a legend environment.

After three year would be triumphant, returned to Madrid, its beauty enhanced by the strange
charm of cosmopolitanism. Now protect the richest businessman in Spain, and in his splendid
court ruled on a hotel only for men: ministers, bankers, political influence, characters of all
classes who sought his smile as the best of his decorations.

So great was his power, until Luis believed to feel around him, seeing that political situations
were happening without being touched their jobs. The fear to fight for the sustaining life
made him accept this situation, in which sensed the hidden hand Harriet.

Solo and sentenced to work for a living, I felt, however, the shame of wretch whose only claim
to be the husband of a beautiful woman. Was worthless running away when its path, insolent and
triumphant in his disgrace, to escape persecution those eyes that were fixed on him with surprise,
pride of women losing their coveted.

One day he received a visit from an old priest and timid-looking, the same who now sat with him
in the car. He was the confessor of his wife. Well had learned to choose! A man kind, short-sighted.
When you say who sent him, Luis could not contain himself: "Valiente such, 'and let the insult round.
But the good old imperturbable as he brings learned discourse and are afraid to forget if it
is slow release, he spoke of Magdalena sinful, the Lord that being who he was, had forgiven him
and passing to the plain style and natural, had transformation suffered by Harriet. I was
sick, barely out of his hotel, a disease that gnawed her womb, a
cancer that had to be tamed with continuous injections of morphine
for did not faint and roar of pain with his cruel scratches.

Misfortune had have turned their eyes to God repented of the past, wanted to see ...

And he, the cowardly man, jumped with joy on hearing this, weak with
satisfaction that is avenged.

A cancer! ... The luxury damn rotting inside her, making her die in life! And always so beautiful,
right? What sweet revenge! ... No, not go to see it. It was useless arguments that seek healing.
Could visit whenever he wanted and give news of his wife: that he was very happy and now understand
why men are bad.

Since then the priest visited him almost every evening, smoking a few cigars, speaking of Harriet,
and sometimes went out together, walking on the outskirts of Madrid old friends.

The disease progressed rapidly convinced that Harriet was going to
die.

Wanted him to beg his forgiveness, calling it a tone of whimsical and ill child requiring a
toy. To the other, the powerful protector, gentle disposition despite his omnipotence, he begged
the priest to take them to the hotel to the husband of Harriet. The good old man spoke with
fervor of the conversion touching the lady, although admitting that the cursed estate, loss
of so many souls, still dominated. Her illness was a prisoner in her home, but at times of
calm, when the rogue pain did not go back and forth like crazy, flipping through catalogs and figurines
in Paris, wrote to its suppliers there, and rare was the week that did not reach drawers with the
latest news: costumes, hats and jewelry, after targeted and hands a day in the closed room, fell
into the corners or hiding forever in closets, and useless toys. For all these fads going the
other, provided to see Harriet smiling.

These confidences were continuing to slowly penetrate Luis in the life of his wife was by far
the course of their disease and not a day passed without rozase with that mentally being, we had
departed forever.

A priest was later presented with unusual energy. This lady was in the past, we called aloud,
was a crime to deny the last consolation to a dying, and he does
not consented.

He felt able to take it by force. Luis, defeated by the will of the old, left Drag and got into a
car, mentally insulting, but no strength to back ... Coward! Coward forever!

In pursuit of the black cassock crossed the garden of the hotel many
times, going by the immediate walk, had spied with looks of hate ...
And now, nothing, no hate or pain: a strong sense curiosity, like
entering unknown country, savoring the wonders ahead he expects to
see.

Inside the hotel the same feeling of curiosity and wonder. Ah, wretch! How often in dreams of his
will impotent, was seen entering the house as a husband drama, gun in hand to kill his unfaithful
wife, and destroying afterwards, as a wild beast, expensive furniture,
rich draperies, fluffy carpet!

And now tenderness he felt under his feet, the beautiful colors by sliding his eyes, the flowers
that greeted him with her perfume from the corners, an intoxication causábanle eunuch and felt impulses
to lie in that furniture, to take possession, as if he belonged, being of his wife. Now he understood
what was wealth, and how hard hung over their slaves. Was already on the first floor, and had not
even seen, in the solemn quiet hotel, none of these details is revealed
in death as they enter a home.

Saw as impassive mask reared after thought he saw a gesture of insolent curiosity: a girl greeted
him with enigmatic smile, it was not known whether it was sympathy
or mockery "The husband of the lady", he believed distinguished in
an adjoining room a man who was hiding (Maybe it was the other), and
stunned by this new world, went through a door, gently pushed for
his guidance.

Was in the bedroom of the lady: a room engulfed in soft shadows, ripping a strip of sun filtering
through a balcony ajar.

In the midst of this beam of light was a straight woman, slender, pink, dressed in a beautiful
soirée dress, the pearly emerging from behind clouds of lace, and
chest and head with the dazzling sparkle of the jewels.

Luis back amazed, protesting the farce. "That was the sick? Had he been called to insult?

- Luis ... Luis !...-- groaned behind him a weak voice, with intonation and gentle child, reminding
him the past, the best moments of his life.

His eyes, already accustomed to the darkness, saw in the back of the room something monumental and
terrible as an altar, a bed stands, and which, under the undulating curtains, incorporating
work was a white figure.

Then he noticed the motionless woman, who seemed to wait with her slender stiff and his eyes of
vague look like blurred by tears.

It was a mannequin art bore some resemblance with Harriet. The best served to consider developments
that continuously received Paris.

It was the only actor in the representations of elegance and wealth that was given alone a remedy
for his illness.

- Luis ... Luis !...-- groaned again the little voice from the bottom
of the bed.

Sadly it was Luis to her to be grasped by arms that tightened convulsively
and feel a burning mouth seeking hers, imploring forgiveness, while
a cheek received the warm touch of tears.

- Say you forgive me, say
it, Luis, and I may not die.

And the husband, who instinctively tried to repel it, ended up throwing themselves into those arms,
unwittingly repeating the same loving words of the happy times. To his eyes, accustomed to the
darkness, was dialed with every detail of his wife's face.

- Luis, Luis mine! - She said smiling through tears -. How do I find? And I'm not as beautiful
as in our times of happiness ... when I still was not crazy. Tell
me God! tell me what you look like.

Her husband looked at her in
amazement. Beautiful, always beautiful, her beauty and innocent child
that made it so scary. The death was not yet there: only between the
soft perfume Sovereign of the meat of this majestic bed, seemed to
slip a subtle and distant mist of dead, which gave away the rotting
interior mixing in her kisses.

Luis divined the presence of someone
behind him. A man was walking distance, contemplating with a confused
expression, as if drawn there by a superior boost to the will that
he was ashamed. Harriet's husband knew, on average nationwide, the
stern face of that man and entered years, a man of sound principles,
great defender of public morals.

- Tell him to go, Luis! - Cried
the sick -. What does that man there? I just want you you ... I just
want my husband. Forgive me ... was luxury, luxury damned: I needed
money, a lot of money, but love ... just you.

Cried Henrietta showing
his repentance, and the man wept, weak and humble with contempt.

Luis,
who had so often thought of him with fits of anger, and had been seeing
him impulses to throw around his neck, finally looking at him with
sympathy and respect. We also loved her! And the community on affection
rather than repel, linking the husband and the other with sympathy
strange.

- Let him go, let her go - repeating the sick with a stubborn
child.

And her husband watched the powerful man with pleading, as
if asking forgiveness for his wife, not knowing what he said.

- Come
on, Mrs. Henrietta - said from the back of the room the voice of the
priest -. Think in herself and in God does not commit the sin of pride.

The
two men, the husband and the guard, ended up sitting by the bedside
of the sick. The pain was roaring, we had to give frequent injections,
and the two went solicitous their care. Several times he stumbled
his hands to incorporate Harriet, not separated instinctive revulsion,
but rather, helped with effusion fraternal.

Luis was increasingly
sympathetic to that good man, so smooth treatment despite their million,
and that his wife was crying even more than him</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>