<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01241</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>18475</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>722</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Cuenta con Mefistófeles, esto es, con el espíritu de astucia y de conducta para la vida, que
ya le devolvió la juventud y que podrá aún darle riqueza, poder, fama y deleites materiales.
Y cuenta, por cima de Mefistófeles, porque la magia natural toca puntos más altos que la magia
negra o hechicería, con la ciencia, que le revelará los arcanos del universo, y con la poesía
y el arte, que realizarán para él la ideal hermosura.

No bien Fausto se recobra de sus violentas emociones, merced a un sueño mágico, arrullado por
cantos de genios y de ninfas, en un fertilísimo y ameno vergel, las mencionadas aspiraciones
empiezan sucesivamente a realizarse, hasta donde la condición finita de Fausto y del mundo
lo consiente.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00462</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>2347</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>647</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Mephistopheles
has, in the spirit of cunning and conduct for life, returned the youth and may even give you
wealth, power and fame. It counts on the summit of Mephistopheles, because the natural magig
touch is more powerful than any other kind of black magic or witchcraft. Using science he has revealed
the secrets of the universe, poetry and art which made him the ideal image for beauty. Fausto soon
recovered from his violent emotions.

All thanks to a magic sleep, induced by lullabies of genius and nymphs in a fertile and pleasant
garden. As Faust consents and falls more comfortably into the sleep, the set aspirations begin
to take place</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>