<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03144</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>19574</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17491</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> La corteza del árbol es blanquecina,
semejante á las de los nogales. El fruto son unas cañas de palmo y medio, y algunas de dos
palmos de largo. Tienen dentro granos grandes como las habas, y entre los granos cierta pulpa
negra, que sirve para purga suave, y se vende en las boticas. El color de la caña, estando
madura, es negro como el de la pulpa.

El árbol Taruma es cierta especie de olivo silvestre. Su tamaño el mismo que el de los olivos
con poca diferencia, y aun la hoja no es muy diferente. La frutilla es como las aceitunas pequeñas,
y tiene su hueso como aceituna. Los paraguayos comen esta fruta, aunque me pareció bien desabrida.
Seria bueno que probasen si de ella se podia sacar aceite: y tambien si prendian en los tarumas
los injertos de olivo.

* * *

§. IV.

Establecimientos de Cuyabá y Mattogroso.

La ciudad de Cuyabá, segun algunos mapas de portugueses, está en 14 grados y 20 minutos de
latitud austral, y segun se infiere de la longitud en que se halló la boca del Xaurú, y la
distancia en que está de Cuyabá, podemos poner á esta ciudad en 322 grados de longitud, contada
del Fierro, con corta diferencia. Su situacion es en la banda oriental del rio llamado de Cuyabá,
el cual hasta desembocar en el de los Porrudos, corre de norte á sur, y se navega hasta el
puerto de Cuyabá, que dista de dos á tres leguas de la ciudad.

Por la parte del norte se estiende por muchas leguas la gran serranía, donde tienen su orígen
los dos caudalosos rios Paraná y Paraguay. Y de la misma, por la parte del norte, bajan al
Marañon los rios Topayós, Xingu, el rio de Dos Bocas, el Tocantins y otros.

Por la parte del sur de Cuyabá se estienden por muchas leguas los anegadizos de Xarayes: de
suerte que por esta parte no se puede entrar á la ciudad sino por el rio. Ni es posible que
pueda pasar de otro modo gente de á pié, ni de á caballo. En tiempo de aguaceros se inunda
casi todo el espacio de sesenta leguas de norte á sur, y casi lo mismo de oriente á poniente,
que hay entre el rio de los Porrudos y las serranias de Cuyabá; y pueden en este tiempo atravesar
embarcaciones desde Cuyabá al rio Paraguay, sin bajar á los Porrudos: pero en tiempo de seca
quedan reducidos los rios Cuyabá y Paraguay á sus canales estrechas y profundas. Y aunque en
el espacio intermedio quedan muchas lagunas, ó no queda comunicacion, ó no se ha descubierto
hasta ahora, por donde se pueda atravesar en derechura de un rio al otro. Por lo cual, para
navegar en tiempo de seca desde Cuyabá al Xaurú, y pasar á Mattogroso, se hallan los portugueses
necesitados á dar una grande vuelta, bajando al rio de los Porrudos, y por este al rio Paraguay,
por el cual vuelven á subir mas de sesenta leguas hasta la boca del Xaurú.

Por la parte del oriente tiene Cuyabá muchas tierras habitadas solamente de indios infieles:
y aunque hay camino para ir por esta parte al Brasil, es camino larguísimo, muy trabajoso y
espuesto á los asaltos de los bárbaros y de los negros alzados. Por estas causas pocos son
los portugueses que emprenden el viage por tierra. La grande distancia del Brasil, y lo trabajoso
del camino hacen que los caballos y mulas en Cuyabá se vendan á precio muy subido: pues se
vende un caballo ordinario en cien pesos, y una mula en docientos.

Por el occidente, desde Cuyabá á Mattogroso, se estienden algunas montañas, que son ramos de
la gran cordillera ó serranía de que hablamos antes. Los portugueses abrieron camino por estas
montañas, para tener comunicacion con los de Mattogroso: pero es camino trabajoso, y solamente
para gente de á pié acostumbrada al temperamento poco saludable de aquel clima.

La ciudad de Cuyabá no tiene muralla, ni artillería, ni fortificacion alguna; porque con los
anegadizos de los Xarayes, y con la suma negligencia de los españoles, se juzgan bastante defendidos.
Solamente para la guardia del Capitan General, y para defensa de los indios infieles, mantienen
una compañía de soldados pagados á quince pesos por mes. De estos se hacen varias reparticiones.
Doce en dos presidios á la frontera de los infieles: otros doce en una canoa de guerra que
sirve para escoltar las canoas que navegan á San Pablo: y los restantes, hasta veinte, quedan
en Cuyabá, y son toda la defensa de la ciudad.

El número de habitantes de todas castas llegarán á cinco mil personas, de las cuales solo un
corto número son libres: los demas, ó son esclavos, ó tenidos y tratados como tales; porque
á excepcion de poco mas de doscientas personas que se hallarán de gente blanca, las demas,
muchas son negros y mulatos, y muchos indios mestizos, que son tratados de los portugueses
como si fueran esclavos: pues, aunque por ordenanza real solamente á los Payaguás y á los de
otra nacion pueden hacer esclavos, pero en aquellas partes se sirven los portugueses de cualesquiera
indios que puedan coger, y los tienen en esclavitud. Los indios mas inmediatos á Cuyabá por
el norte son los Paresis y los Barbudos: estos nunca se rinden á los portugueses, porque ó
han de vencer, ó han de quedar muertos en la refriega. Por el nord-este estan los Indios Bororos:
estos tienen la simpleza de que, aprisionada por los portugueses alguna india de su nacion,
luego se vienen los parientes inmediatos á entregar y servir al portugues que la tiene en su
casa. Por el sur, pasados los anegadizos, estan los Mbayás de arriba, que al paso de los Paulistas
por el Tacuarí los suelen acometer.

* * *

§. V.

Minas de Cuyabá.

En todo el Brasil dan los portugueses nombre de minas á los lavaderos de oro. Y así ni en Cuyabá,
ni en otra parte alguna del Brasil, que haya llegado á mi noticia, se trabajan minas propiamente
tales. Pero hay en Cuyabá lavaderos de oro de 23 quilates, y en uno de los lavaderos de oro
se hallan diamantes. Mas en estos años antecedentes, porque los diamantes no perdiesen su estimacion,
se prohibió por el Rey de Portugal sacarlos de Cuyabá. Los lavaderos se hallan en varias partes
á las caidas ó vertientes de la gran Cordillera. Trabajan en estos lavaderos los negros esclavos,
y dá cada negro á su amo en cada semana tres pesos de oro en grano, que es la única moneda
que allí corre. Y se hacen las cuentas en las compras y ventas por octavas de oro, y cada octava
son dos pesos. En algunas partes se halla oro en abundancia, pero no se pueden aprovechar de
él, por faltar allí el agua para los lavaderos.

La grande distancia de Cuyabá á la costa del Brasil es causa de que los géneros de Europa se
vendan allí á precio muy subido. Una camisa muy ordinaria vale seis pesos, ó tres octavas de
oro: un par de zapatos, lo mismo: una frasquera de vino y aguardiente, que en el Janeiro se
diera por diez pesos, vale en Cuyabá sesenta. Y á esta proporcion se venden los otros géneros.
Lo que allí sube á precio exorbitante, y se tiene por el mayor contrabando, si va sin el despacho
de la aduana, es la sal, la cual se lleva de Lisboa, y no se permite de otra parte.

* * *

§. VI.

Temperamento de Cuyabá y frutos que produce la tierra.

En Cuyabá y sus cercanias es el temperamento muy ardiente y húmedo; y consiguientemente se
goza en toda aquella tierra de poca salud. La enfermedad mas frecuente es la que llaman los
portugueses del bicho: y de la cual mueren muchos, porque no saben curarla. La enfermedad consiste
en una extremada laxitud del orificio con disenteria, y algo de calentura. Los portugueses,
persuadidos de que se cria dentro de la carne algun bicho ó guzano, que causa aquellos efectos,
pretenden á fuerza de jugo de limon y otros agrios, matar el bicho, y acontece no pocas veces,
que acaban con el enfermo. El cirujano D. Pedro Gracian, que navegó conmigo en un barco por
medio de los Xarajes, hombre bien inteligente en su facultad, oyendo al alferez de Cuyabá quejarse
de que tenia entre su gente algunos enfermos del bicho; quizo informarse que cosa era el bicho,
y en efecto fué á ver los enfermos, y halló que no habia tal bicho ni guzano, y se ofreció
á curarlos luego. Los portugueses porfiaban con mucha eficacia que no habia otra cura para
aquella enfermedad que el agrio de limon, con el cual talvez mezclaban agí, ajos y sal: pero
el cirujano les mostró el error en que estaban, pues tomando á su cuenta el enfermo que tenian
de mas peligro, á dos dias se le dió sano, sin haber aplicado cosa alguna de las sobredichas
para matar al bicho, teniendo por cierto que no habia tal animal.

Las aguas de lluvias, que allí corren por montes de cañafistula, por parages cubiertos de las
cañas que caen de los árboles, y por grandes matorrales de otras plantas purgantes, con los
excesivos calores y el desvelo que ocasiona la multitud de mosquitos, son á mi parecer la causa
de aquella destemplanza y de aquella enfermedad. Los españoles, que subimos al Xaurú, esperimentamos
en aquel temperamento semejante disenteria, con grande relajacion en el estómago, que no tenia
el calor necesario para la digestion. A este accidente se ocurrió con felicidad, tomando antes
de comer un poco de mistela: remedio necesario en aquel pais para no perder la salud.

Los aguaceros son frecuentes en aquellas alturas; pero los mas fuertes, que hacen crecer extraordinariamente
los rios, comienzan por el mes de Diciembre. Y crecen tanto los rios, que no hallando bastante
abertura para salir las muchas aguas que bajan á la llanura de los Xarayes, rebalsan inundando
los campos, y formando por este tiempo un grande lago; aunque despues, en cesando los aguaceros,
se desagua por el cauce del rio Paraguay, y quedan solamente las canales de los rios, y algunas
lagunas, descubriéndose todo lo demas de aquella llanura, lleno de pajonales impenetrables.
Sin embargo de inundarse todo aquel espacio, hay en él algunas arboledas de árboles muy altos,
cuyos troncos se inundan hasta tres y cuatro varas en alto. Y lo mas admirable que observamos
en los Xarayes, es que con estar todo el terreno anegado parte del año, hallaron las hormigas
(de las cuales hay innumerable multitud) modo de conservar sus hormigueros. Estos los fabrican
de barro muy fuerte en lo alto de grandes árboles, con tal arte que queda como un horno al
rededor de una de las ramas superiores, y tan bien construído, que no le pueden ofender las
lluvias ni los vientos. Y para que estos no puedan llevarse las hormigas, que suben ó bajan
en tiempo de seca, tienen hecho del mismo barro fuerte un canal ó camino cubierto, que baja
hasta el pié del árbol, por el cual canal suben y bajan las hormigas con toda seguridad.

Los frutos que produce la tierra de Cuyabá y su comarca, son maiz, arroz, mandioca (en otras
partes de América llaman cazave), piñas, pacobas ó plátanos, con otras muchas especies de frutas
propias de los climas ardientes de América, azucar, miel de cañas y de abejas, de las cuales
hay varias especies en los montes. El arroz se halla silvestre en las márgenes del rio de Cuyabá
y de los Porrudos. No se coje trigo, ni vino, ni otros frutos de Europa. La falta de pan suplen
los portugueses con farinha do pao, ó cazave. Hay en Cuyabá algun ganado vacuno, aunque poco.
En el Xaurú les compró D. Manuel Flores algunas vacas para la gente de los barcos, y pagó veinte
pesos por cada una. De lechones y caza hay mas abundancia.

* * *

§. VII.

Navegacion que hacen los portugueses del Brasil á Cuyabá.

Cada año van los portugueses comerciantes del Brasil á Cuyabá con una gran flota de canoas
cargadas de géneros, y vuelven con el producto en oro y diamantes. La navegacion es larga y
trabajosa: salen con sesenta ó setenta canoas de un puerto, que dista cuatro ó cinco leguas
de San Pablo, ciudad bien conocida en el Brasil. Bajan por el rio Añembí, hasta caer al Paraná.
Por este navegan aguas abajo hasta la boca del rio Pardo, que viene del occidente, y tiene
su orígen de algunos riachuelos que bajan de la gran cordillera que se extiende del norte al
sur, desde cerca de Cuyabá hasta el monte de Itapuá en las Misiones de Guaranís. Suben con
sus canoas los portugueses, hasta que no pueden navegar mas por el rio Pardo: allí descargan
los géneros, y para pasar dos leguas de cordillera, que hay desde el Pardo hasta el rio Camapoan,
transportan embarcaciones y carga en las carretas de un portuguez que para esto se pobló en
aquella cordillera, y tiene su interes en el transporte de dichas canoas. Antes que hubiese
allí poblacion, pasaban las canoas en hombros de negros esclavos que llevan para remar. Transportadas
las canoas al Camapoan, las vuelven á cargar, y navegan rio abajo hasta entrar en el Tacuarí.
Por este navegan con algun cuidado, porque llegan hasta sus márgenes los indios Mbayás corriendo
la campaña, los cuales son enemigos de los portugueses, y no pierden la ocasion de matar ó
llevar cautivo al que cogen apartado de la flota. Antes que lleguen á la desembocadura del
Tacuarí en el Paraguay, ya se hallan con la canoa de guerra de Cuyabá, que al tiempo que acostumbran
llegar los Paulistas con las suyas, los estan esperando para defenderlos de los Payaguás, porque
las canoas que llevan de San Pablo no bastan para su defensa, pues en cada una va solo un portuguez
blanco, ó á lo mas dos, y los negros remeros: pero estos no llevan armas. Los Payaguás los
suelen esperar con multitud de canoas muy ligeras, en cada una de las cuales van seis ó siete
hombres, y para no ser descubiertos, se meten con las canoas debajo de las ramas de los árboles,
que llegan hasta tocar en el agua: y cuando van pasando los portugueses, los asaltan de improviso,
y les dan una descarga de flechazos, tirando siempre al portuguez blanco, y se echan sobre
las canoas que pueden tomar; y recogiendo los géneros y los negros, se bajan á la Asumpcion,
donde los españoles por compasion rescatan á los cautivos. Por evitar los portugueses estos
asaltos y daños que hacen los Payaguás en sus flotas, han armado la canoa que llaman de guerra,
para que las escolte desde el Tacuarí á Cuyabá.

El armamento de la canoa de guerra consiste en un cañoncillo de bronce de una vara ó algo mas
de largo, con el cual disparan con presteza muchos tiros. Y para esto llevan en sus cajones
bien acondicionados los cartuchos, hechos de camellote en lugar de lienzo, porque de esta suerte
evitan que quede algun fuego en el cañon, y dicen que no se calienta tanto, aunque se disparen
muchos tiros seguidamente con dicho cañoncillo. La presteza con que disparan, procede en parte
de tener todas las cosas á punto, y poderse con facilidad manejar el cañon por ser tan corto,
y en parte por ser cuatro bien ejercitados los que concurren á cargarlo: uno con el cartucho,
otro con el taco y atacador, otro con una espoleta que clava en el fogon lleno de pólvora para
no detenerse en cebar, y el otro finalmente con el bota-fuego. El cañoncillo, aunque es bien
reforzado, no tiene alguna diferencia de otros cañones en su fábrica. Solamente la cureña es
algo diversa, porque carece de ruedas, y está con su espigo dispuesta de tal suerte sobre un
banco de la canoa, que puede con facilidad volverse á todas partes: y así en disparando á un
lado, lo pueden volver y disparar al otro.

La tripulacion de la canoa de guerra se compone de doce soldados con su alferez, y ocho ó nueve
negros remeros de pala con sus uniformes. El alferez tiene en la canoa para defensa del sol
y de la lluvia su carroza muy buena con cortinas y asientos. Los soldados llevan tambien en
medio de la canoa su toldo acomodado para su resguardo. Los remeros van á la proa y á la popa,
y uno con la pala sirve de timonero.

Para dormir, así los de las canoas de guerra como los de las de carga, se previenen buscando
antes de anochecer algun parage en la márgen del rio, donde el monte sea muy cerrado, y tenga
mucha maleza de abrojos y espinas, de lo cual hay en aquella tierra abundancia entre los árboles.
Allí arriman las canoas, y con machetes abren un semi-círculo, ó media luna, donde arman la
tienda del alferez. Esta tienda es de bayeta aforrada en lienzo, por haber mostrado la experiencia,
que esta especie de tiendas resiste mejor al agua. Tenia ocho pasos comunes de largo, y mas
de tres varas de alto: y por cumbrera servia una muy gruesa tacuara, ó caña. Los soldados y
los remeros cuelgan las hamacas de los árboles, y las cubren con una grande sábana, que por
ambos lados llega hasta el suelo, la cual sirve para defender de la lluvia, y mas principalmente
les sirve para defenderse de los mosquitos, de los cuales hay en aquellos rios increible multitud.
Para meterse en la hamaca sin que al mismo tiempo entren estos enemigos, es menester levantar
la sábana del suelo, solamente lo preciso para meter arrastrando el cuerpo, sin dejar algun
hueco por donde puedan entrar, porque si entran no dejan de inquietar toda la noche.

Para no ser sorprendidos de los infieles del rio, que son los Payaguás, y otra nacion que solamente
se deja ver en el rio de los Porrudos, dejan siempre un soldado de centinela defendido de alguna
estacada ó maleza, el cual tiene á mano muchos fusiles cargados, para poder hacer fuego si
se ofreciere, mientras acuden los otros soldados. Por la parte de tierra no es fácil que puedan
ser acometidos, por la impenetrable maleza del monte, y por la vigilancia de algunos perros
que llevan siempre consigo los portugueses.

Luego que llega la flota al rio Paraguay, para acortar el viage entran por un brazo estrecho
del mismo rio: al cual brazo llaman Paraguay-miní, y hace con el Paraguay grande una isla de
diez leguas de largo: y es á mi juicio, la que llamaron los antiguos Isla de los Orejones,
pues la pone la Argentina mas abajo de los Xarayes. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06175</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>66006</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15691</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The bark is white, similar to those of
the walnut. The result is a beer and a half span, and some two feet long. Have in large grains
such as beans, grains and between some pulp black, used to purge soft, and is sold in pharmacies.
The color of the cane, while ripe, is black as the pulp.

Taruma tree is a species of wild olive. The same size as that of the olive trees with little difference,
and even the leaf is not very different. The icing is like small olives, and has his blood like olives.
The Paraguayans eat this fruit, but I found it bland. It would be good to test whether it can be very
useful oil, and even if ignited in the Tarumas olive grafts.

* * *

§.

IV.

Cuyabá facilities and Mattogroso.

The city of Cuiaba, according to some Portuguese maps, is at 14 degrees and 20 minutes south latitude,
and as inferred from the length that was found the mouth of Xaurú, and distance is of Cuiaba, we
can put this city in 322 degrees of longitude, counting del Fierro, with a short difference.
Its situation is on the east of the river called Cuiaba, which to
lead in the Porrudos, runs north to south, and navigate to the Cuyabá
port, a distance of two to three miles from the city.

In the northern part extends for many miles the great mountains, where
they have their origin the two mighty rivers Paraná and Paraguay.

And just for the north, down to the Topayos Marañon rivers, Xingu, rio de Dos Bocas, Tocantins
and others.

In the southern part of Cuyabá be stretched for many leagues the wetlands of Xarayes: from so
that this part can not enter into the city but by the stream. Nor is it possible that otherwise you
can pass people on foot or on horseback. In times of heavy rains flooded almost all the space
of sixty miles from north to south, and about the same from east to west, that between the river
and the mountains of Porrudos Cuyabá, and may at this time through Cuyabá boats from the river
Paraguay, without getting to the Porrudos, but dry weather Cuyabá are reduced and Paraguay
rivers to their narrow and deep channels. And although the intermediate space are many gaps, or
there is no communication, or not been discovered so far, where you can go through in straight from
a river to the other.

Therefore, for sailing time from Cuiaba to Xaurú dry, and go to Mattogroso, are the Portuguese
need to give a great back, down the river of Porrudos, and for this the river Paraguay, by
which to climb back over sixty miles to the mouth of Xaurú.

On the east side has Cuyabá many Indian lands inhabited only infidels: and although there is
no way to go through this part of Brazil, is the way very long, very
laborious and esponse to the assaults of the barbarians and the black
rebels.

For these reasons there are few The Portuguese who undertake the journey by land. The great
distance from Brazil, and laborious the road make the horses and mules in Cuyabá be sold at prices
very deep: it is sell an ordinary horse in a hundred pesos, and a mule in two hundred.

To the west, from Cuiaba to Mattogroso, be stretched some mountains, which are branches of the
great mountain or mountain range that we discussed earlier. The Portuguese led the way for these mountains,
to have communication with those of Mattogroso: but laborious way, and only for ordinary people
used to temper the climate unhealthy.

The city of Cuiaba no wall, or artillery, or a fortification, for the wetlands of the Xarayes,
and the neglect of the Spanish total, judge fairly defended.

Only the guard of Captain General, and to defend the infidel Indians, maintain a company of
soldiers paid to fifteen dollars per month. From these various departments are. Twelve in two
prisons to the frontier of the infidels: twelve others in a war canoe serves to escort the
boats that sail to St. Paul, and the remaining twenty, are in Cuiaba, and they are all defending
the city.

The number of people of all castes come to five thousand people, of which only a small number
are free, others, or slaves, or taken and treated as such, because Except for little more
than two hundred people who will find white people, the others, many are black and mulattoes, and
mestizos many Indians, who are treated by the Portuguese like slaves: for, though only to the
actual ordinance and to those of Payaguá other nation can make slaves, but those parts are served
any Portuguese Indians who can catch, and keep them in slavery. The Indians Cuyabá by more immediate
the north are the Paresis and Barbudos: they never give to the Portuguese,
for either have to overcome, or are to be killed in the fray.

On the north-east are the Bororo Indians: these have the simplicity
of it, caught India by the Portuguese some of his nation, then come
the immediate relatives to deliver and serve the Portuguese who has
her home.

To the south, after the flooding, are above the Mbayas that the passage
of the Paulist Tacuarí by the usually undertake.

* * *

§. V.

Cuyabá mines.

Throughout Brazil are the Portuguese name of mines to the gold mines. And so neither in Cuiaba, or
any other part of Brazil, which has come to my knowledge, mine is working properly such. But
there are gold mines Cuyabá of 23 carats, and one of the gold mines
are diamonds.

But in these years history, because diamonds are not losing their estimation, was banned by
the King of Portugal them out of Cuiaba. The sinks are located in various parts to falls or
slopes of the great Cordillera. Work in these laundries black slaves, black and gives each
his master in every week three pieces of gold grains, which is the only currency runs there. And
you do the math on buying and selling gold in octaves and each octave are two weights. In some parts
is gold in abundance, but you can not take advantage of him there
for missing water for washing.

The great distance from Cuiaba to the coast of Brazil is due to the
gender of Europe thence selling price up.

A very ordinary shirt worth six dollars, or three octaves gold: a pair of shoes, the same:
a flask of wine and brandy, which in the Janeiro given for ten pesos worth in Cuyabá sixties.
And this proportion is sold to other genres. What goes up there at exorbitant prices, and is the largest
smuggling, if you're not at the office custom, is salt, which is carried in Lisbon, and not
permitted elsewhere.

* * *

§. VI.

Cuyabá temperament and fruits of the earth.

In Cuiaba and its vicinity is very hot and humid temperament, and consequentially enjoys all the
land of poor health. The most common disease which is called the Portuguese of the beast: and
they die a lot, because they can not cure.

The disease is extreme laxity in the hole with dysentery, and some fever. The Portuguese, convinced
that is bred in the flesh some bug or Guzan, causing those effects, intended to force lemon
juice and other citrus fruits, to kill the bug, and happens not infrequently ending with the patient.
The surgeon D. Pedro Gracian, who sailed with me on a boat through the Xarajes, very smart man in his
right, hearing the ensign of complaining Cuyabá that was between the people some patients the
bug, maybe something was informed that the bug, and actually went to see the sick, and found that
there was no such creature or Guzan, and offered to cure them later.

The Portuguese insisted upon very effectively that there was no cure for this disease the lemon tart, which
maybe mixed with AGI, garlic and salt, but The surgeon showed them the error where they were,
then taking his account of the patient who had of more danger, he was given two days healthy,
without applying any of the sobredichas thing to kill the bug, have certainly had no such animal.

The
storm water that run through forests there cañafístula, Parages covered by the rods that fall from
the trees, bushes and other plants large purges, with excessive heat and the sleepless nights
caused by the multitude of mosquitoes are in my opinion the cause of that distemper and that disease.
The Spanish, who got into Xaurú, experiments at that temper like dysentery, with great relaxation
in the stomach, which had no the heat needed for digestion. In this accident happened to happiness,
taking before eating a bit of sweet wine: remedy needed in that country to avoid losing health.

The
downpours are common in the uplands, but the strongest, which are grown dramatically rivers,
beginning with the month of December. And grow both rivers, not finding enough opening out
the many waters that flow down into the plain of Xarayes, overflow flooding fields, and forming
by this time a big lake, but later, in the rain ceasing, is drained by the Paraguay river channel,
and are only the channels of the rivers, and some gaps, uncovering
all the rest of the plain, full of impenetrable marshes.

But all that space for flooding, there are some groves of trees he very high whose trunks are
flooded up to three and four yards high. And most fans watched in Xarayes, is that all land to be
flooded part of the year, they found ants (Of which there are innumerable crowd) way to keep
their nests. These are manufactured by strong clay on top of large trees, with such art is like
a furnace around one of the upper branches, and so well constructed that they can not offend rain
or wind. And so that these can not be ants going up or down in dry weather, have made of it a
strong mud-covered road or canal, descending to the foot of the tree, which channel the ants up
and down safely.

The fruits of the land of Cuiaba and its region are maize, rice, cassava
(in other parts of America called cazave), pineapples, bananas or
pacobas with many other fruit species typical of hot climates of America,
sugar, cane syrup and bees, which There are several species in the
mountains.

The wild rice is on the banks of the Rio Cuiaba and Porrudos.

No fucks wheat, no wine, no nuts in Europe. The lack of bread supplement Portuguese with farinha
do pao, or cazave. There are Cuyabá some cattle, but little. In D. Xaurú bought them Manuel
Flores some cows for people on boats, and paid twenty pesos each. Piglets and game are more
abundant.

* * *

§. VII.

Navigation made by Portuguese in Brazil to Cuiaba.

Each year the Portuguese traders go to Cuiaba Brazil with a large fleet of canoes gender-laden, and return
the product in gold and diamonds. The voyage is long and work: out of sixty or seventy canoes
of a harbor, which is four or five leagues San Pablo, a city well known in Brazil. Añembí down by
the river, to fall to the Paraná. On this sail downstream to the mouth of the Rio Pardo, which
comes from the west, and has the origin of some streams that flow down from the great chain
that extends from north to south, from near to Mount Cuyabá Itapuá in the Guarani missions. Up to Portuguese
canoes, until they can sail above the river Pardo: download here gender, and to spend two miles
of mountains, which are from the Rio Pardo to Carnap, vessels and cargo transported on the truck of
a Portuguez that it was filled in that range, and is interested in the transport of these
canoes. Before there was population there, spent their canoes on the shoulders of slaves who
have to paddle. Carried canoes to Carnap, the reloaded, and sail down the river to enter the Tacuarí.
For this sailing with some care, because their margins go up the Indians running Mbayas campaign,
which are enemies of the Portuguese, and not lose the opportunity to kill or captive lead
away from catching the fleet. Before arriving at the mouth of Tacuarí in Paraguay, as are the
Cuyabá war canoe, which, while usually Paulist arrive with their own, are waiting to defend
the Payaguá because canoes carrying of San Pablo is not enough for his defense, since each is only
a Portuguez white, or at most two, and the black rowers but they
do not carry weapons.

The Payaguá the usually expect a multitude of very light canoes, each of which are six or seven
men, and to avoid detection, they come with their canoes under the branches of trees, coming
to play in the water: and when they pass the Portuguese, the assault of a sudden and give them a
volley of arrows, throwing Portuguez always white, and lie on canoes can take, and collecting
gender and blacks, are lowered to the Assumption, where the Spanish out of compassion to rescue
the captives. To avoid the Portuguese these assaults and damage Payaguá do in their fleets, have
reinforced the call of war canoe, for the escort from the Tacuarí to Cuiaba.

The weapons of war canoe is a bronze Cañoncillo a rod or something else long, which promptly
fired several shots. And for this they bear in their drawers well conditioned cartridges, made
of canvas instead camellote because in this way prevent is some fire in the canyon, and say
they are not so hot, although shoot then with that many shots Cañoncillo. The alacrity with
which soar, due partly to have everything ready, and be able to easily
handle the gun for being so short, and partly because those who exercised
four well concur in charge: one with the cartridge, other with the
heel and attacked, one with a fuse that sticks in the stove filled
with gunpowder not stopping at prime, and the other end with boot-fire.

The Cañoncillo, although it is well strengthened, not unlike some other guns in his factory. Only
the carriage is somewhat different, because it has no wheels and is arranged with its spigot
such luck on a bank of the canoe, which can easily get to all parts, and so shooting a hand,
they can come back and shoot the other.

The crew of the war canoe consists of twelve soldiers and their ensign, and eight or nine black
spade oars in their uniforms. The ensign is in the canoe for sun protection and rain His chariot
very good with curtains and seats. The soldiers are also in canoe through the canopy off for safekeeping.
The rowers are to the fore and aft, and one with the blade serves as a helmsman.

To sleep, and those of war canoes as the load, looking preventable any camp site before nightfall
on the river bank, where the mountain is very close, and have overgrown with weeds and thorns,
of which the land is in abundance among the trees. They cuddle their canoes, and with machetes
open a semi-circle or crescent, where the arm Ensign shop. This store is aforrada canvas cloth,
for showing experience Store this species is more resistant to water. Had eight common steps long,
and more three yards high, and served a very thick ridge tacuara, or cane. Soldiers and rowers
hammocks hung from the trees, and covered with a large sheet, which both sides down to the
ground, which serves to protect from rain, and more especially serves
to fend off mosquitoes, which are in those rivers incredible crowd.

To get into the hammock without falling while these enemies, it is necessary to raise the sheet from
the floor, only to get the precise dragging the body, while some hole through which to enter, because
if they come not stop fidgeting all night.

Not to be surprised by the infidels of the river, which are the Payaguá, and a nation that only
be seen in the river of Porrudos, always leave a soldier on guard
defended in fence or bush, which has many loaded guns at hand, in
order to fire if he offer, while the other soldiers come.

On the ground can not easily be undertaken, by the impenetrable undergrowth of the mountain,
and the monitoring of some dogs who always carry with them the Portuguese.

After the fleet arrives at the river Paraguay, to shorten the journey
go by a narrow arm the same river, which they call Paraguay-mini arm,
and makes the big island of Paraguay ten miles long, and in my opinion,
they called the old Island Orejones Argentina puts because the Xarayes
below</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>