<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09574</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>496911</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16988</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Fue como un relámpago. Sin embargo,
Ramiro reconoció al instante los ojos de Casilda, y en vez de detenerse, terciose la capa y
enderezó a toda prisa hacia la otra ribera.

Después de errar más de media hora, en la dirección del sudeste, sin alejarse del río, vio
asomar una cruz entre los cantos. Era la cruz de una ermita construida al borde del abismo.
Acercose; y a pesar de su profunda tribulación, la sorpresa del cuadro dejole absorto un momento,
haciéndole presentir un sentido provechoso para su alma.

Frente a él, en la margen opuesta, Toledo se extendía de naciente a poniente, escalonando sobre
el alto peñón sus tejados grises, sus pálidas paredes, sus torres numerosas. Liso y vertiginoso
escarpamiento caía desde la ciudad hasta el fondo de la angostura, cubierto al parecer de vieja
ceniza deleznable, como si el fuego de Dios hubiese pasado por allí, arrasando toda raíz y
toda simiente. Ramiro pensó con religioso espanto en las cuestas del eterno castigo que los
réprobos tienen que trepar con los pies y con las manos, para caer de nuevo en las ondas inflamadas,
y volver a trepar y a caer sin perdón y sin tregua, indefinidamente.

Sentose sobre un peñasco.

El río se deslizaba a una hondura terrible entre rocas herrumbradas y fieras. Pareciole un
río de culpas y expiaciones, como los que forja la imaginación al pensar en los infiernos.
Hubiérase dicho que dolorosos espectros pasaban en procesión, allí abajo, rozando las ondas
con sus colgantes velos obscuros.

Entretanto el caserío tomaba, con la hora, desolada blancura de huesos en el yermo, y toda
la ciudad, mirada a distancia, a través de la vibradora penumbra, parecía una ciudad de otro
mundo, una ciudad fuera de la vida y del tiempo, mística y anhelosa como los salmos.

En la parte más elevada, sobresalía el Alcázar bañado en melancólico reflejo crepuscular. Ramiro
recordó con misteriosa inspiración que aquellos muros habían alojado a uno de los reyes más
gloriosos de la historia, a un monarca de monarcas que acabó por arrojar el cetro y la corona
para refugiarse en escondido monasterio; y, al pronto, el fantasma del Emperador Carlos Quinto
apareció ante sus ojos con el rostro medio oculto por la capilla de un hábito.

¡Ah! ¡aquel sayal sobre el dueño del mundo...!

El sol se ocultó detrás de los cerros, y la ciudad tomó una coloración mustia y violácea, cual
si fuera contemplada al través de transparente amatista. Algunas vidrieras que habían flameado
un instante se apagaron. Ramiro dejose penetrar por el sagrado recogimiento, presintiendo un
signo, una voz de lo alto. En ese instante las campanas de la ciudad rompieron a tocar las
oraciones. Los tañidos concertaban a distancia un canto prolongado y conmovedor que hacía pensar
en las letanías de la muerte, y hubiérase dicho que la peña que sustentaba los numerosos campanarios
vibraba a su vez como la caja de un órgano. Ramiro acordose de las campanas de Avila, de las
tardes de su niñez en la torre solariega y de su madre, siempre llorosa, siempre enlutada,
siempre taciturna.

Rezó las avemarías. Estaba redimido, estaba purificado, pero sentía su pecho ávido y triste,
como un arroyo sin agua. Quiso entrar en la ermita para verter al pie del altar su congoja
profunda. Levantose. El suelo y las rocas oscilaban a su alrededor; su cuerpo, aligerado, iba
a desprenderse, sin duda, de la tierra. De pronto, un fuego, una inflamada saeta, venida de
lo alto, se le entró por el pecho, sumergiéndole durante algunos segundos en un estado delicioso,
gozado sólo con el alma.

Luego, todo pasó. Creyó entonces que había sido trasverberado como la Madre Teresa de Jesús,
y que Dios acababa de abajarse hasta él en todo su poder y misericordia, para hacerle probar
un sorbo, apenas, de los goces que le esperaban cuando su alma, vencedora del mundo, se entregase
por fin, con soberana pasión, a la soledad y a la penitencia.

Un instante después regresaba a la ciudad en busca de un convento donde le cambiaran las ropas
de caballero por un sayal de ermitaño.

V

Vestido de áspero buriel y sosteniendo con el bordón, por encima del hombro, la humilde barjuleta
que le aparejaron para el viaje las religiosas franciscanas de San Juan de la Penitencia, marchose
Ramiro de Toledo, a la mañana siguiente, tomando a través de los montes la dirección del mediodía.

Llevaba todo el cabello hacia atrás, la frente sin ceño, los ojos humedecidos.

Caminó muchos días, de sol a sol, bebiendo de bruces en los arroyos y comiendo los mendrugos
que le daban los labradores. Más de un compasivo caminante le ofreció llevarle en el anca de
su cabalgadura; pero él sonreía santamente y marcaba en el polvo con más fuerza la huella de
sus sandalias. Dormía en el corral de las ventas o al borde de los caminos, donde le tomaba
la noche.

Por fin, una madrugada, después de larguísimo viaje, llegó a divisar desde lo alto de un cerro
la blanca ciudad de Córdoba, bañada en el rubor húmedo y radioso del amanecer. Se hizo señalar
desde allí, por una frutera que pasaba, el convento de las monjas del Carmen, y al pensar que
bajo aquella cercana techumbre se hallaba su madre, sintió que los sollozos le entrecortaban
el aliento.

Sin querer acercarse a la ciudad, y apartándose de los senderos, descubrió por fin, en el flanco
de la montaña, una gruta escondida entre malezas y arbustos. Había en su interior una mesa
hecha de ramas de alcornoque sin descorchar, un tintero de raíz de naranjo, un taburete, un
azadón y varios cacharros hundidos en el lodo. De la parte más alta, colgaba un antiguo traje
de caballero, y además, semejante a dos perniles ahumados, un par de botas de camino con sus
espuelas.

Esa misma noche, al encender el candil que llevaba consigo, y al ir a acostarse sobre un montón
de hojarasca, hacia el fondo de la gruta, hallose con el cuerpo momificado de un viejo anacoreta,
que apretaba todavía entre sus manos resecas las cuentas del rosario. Ramiro dejose caer de
rodillas y alzó los brazos al cielo, dando gracias a Dios por haberle puesto, a la vez, en
su camino, el anhelado refugio y el ejemplo de aquella muerte.

Al otro día, por la mañana, dio sepultura al ermitaño y ordenó lo mejor que pudo el interior
del obscuro escondrijo, donde había resuelto pasar todo el resto de su existencia.

Muy pronto una sublime voluptuosidad inundó su corazón. La continua plegaria, el total desprecio
del mundo y, sobre todo, las arduas e ingeniosas penitencias que se impuso, le hicieron conocer
el inefable orgullo de la santidad; orgullo grandioso que le dilataba el alma infinitamente,
y le alzaba con sublime vuelo sobre las miserias del hombre. Se comparó a los admirables anacoretas
de la Tebaida, y tuvo por seguro que en los tiempos venideros su historia sería leída en hogares
y refectorios para edificación de las almas.

Las religiosas de Toledo habíanle puesto en el zurrón algunos libros de mística. Conducido
por aquellas lecturas, Ramiro se propuso recorrer las tres vías espirituales descritas en los
tratados, y lograr al fin la posesión de esa gloria máxima que había buscado hasta ahora por
engañosos caminos.

Pero la llama de los primeros días no pudo mantenerse; ya no volvió a sentir aquellos arrobos
que encendían en la cripta de su alma las lámparas de fuego de que hablaba Fray Juan de la
Cruz. La noche de frío y de tinieblas cayó sobre su corazón; la lobreguez y la humedad de su
guarida comenzaron a hastiarle; la lectura se le hizo insufrible.

Algunas tardes, deseando respirar libremente, salía a pasearse por la montaña hasta la noche.
La brisa era siempre deliciosa y traía de los cortijos un perfume de azahares que reblandecía
la voluntad y alejaba toda idea de penitencia. Sonrisas de mujeres, carmines de labios entreabiertos,
maliciosos pestañeos, aparecían ante él en la penumbra rosada o bajo la sombra azul de los árboles.

Una apatía, una pereza invencible comenzó a postrar como un ensalmo sus miembros y su espíritu,
hasta hacerle pasar la mayor parte del día tendido en la cama del anacoreta, ocupado en contar
los hoyuelos de la roca o las gotas de agua que caían de las vertientes. Las lagartijas, las
cucarachas, los ratones y muchos insectos que le eran desconocidos, acabaron por trepar sobre
su cuerpo, y él, en vez de espantarlos, mantenía completa inmovilidad, a fin de observar de
cerca todos sus movimientos.

Pasó semanas enteras sin rezar el rosario y sin bajar a la ciudad para oír la misa del domingo
y pedir provisiones, como era su costumbre.

Cierta mañana escuchó una voz de mujer a pocos pasos de la gruta:

      Cantan de Oliveros e cantan de Roldán
    e non de Zurraquín, cá fue gran barragán.

      Cantan de Roldán o canta de Olivero
    e non de Zurraquín, cá fue gran caballero.

Era un doble estribillo que Medrano, el escudero, no se cansaba de repetir. Pareciole la voz
de Casilda. ¿No sería algún engaño de los sentidos? Levantose y miró un momento hacia afuera.
Una mujer, cubierta de un velo verdoso, bajaba de prisa por la cuesta; y la canción caía y
se alejaba con ella graciosamente.

Otra mañana, recogiendo leña por el contorno, descubrió al pie de un árbol una espada cubierta
de herrumbre. Llevola a su escondrijo y frotola fuertemente con la arena humedecida. Era un
arma señoril: varios anillos de plata ceñían la negra vaina de cuero; la hoja tenía la marca
de Hortuño; la guarnición era calada y fina, como una randa.

Aquel trivial incidente vino a arrancarle de su pereza. Desde entonces pasaba horas y horas
acicalando la espada en sus menores intersticios; y se complacía en sacarla a la luz para hacer
correr una llama de sol a lo largo de la hoja, en empuñarla y blandirla con fuerza, en hacerla
resoplar en el viento.

Ya no salía nunca hacia el bosque que no la llevase consigo; y a veces, mirando hacia una y
otra parte, como si alguien pudiera sorprenderle, hincaba la punta de cierto modo en el tronco
de los árboles para recordar la terrible estocada con que había dado muerte a Gonzalo.

Su sangre se enardeció de nuevo, y su espíritu, inflado otra vez con el viento de la honra,
volvió a soñar en los triunfos y loores de la vida y en todas las hazañas que él hubiera podido
realizar por el mundo.

Hallábase una tarde del mes de Septiembre sentado sobre un alto peñasco, y meditando la idea
de visitar en breve a su madre, cuando vio subir por la cuesta, sobre una mula parda, a un
anciano enjuto y esbelto que agachaba la cabeza y miraba con singular atención hacia la gruta.

El hombre volvió a pasar a la mañana siguiente, mirando siempre con la misma curiosidad.

Por fin, un día en que Ramiro llegó a sentir de modo insufrible el tormento del hambre, el
anciano misterioso acertó a pasar a la hora del anochecer, llevando por delante, sobre la silla,
un cesto pequeño lleno de hogaza y una ristra de cebollas colgada del hombro.

Ramiro caminó hacia él, exclamando:

--¡Dadme, por Dios, una cebolla y un poco de pan!

El hombre prosiguió su camino.

Ramiro, entonces, con voz amenazadora y más fuerte, repitió:

--¡Por el amor de Dios, dadme un poco de pan!

Pero el desconocido, sujetando apenas la mula, contestó secamente:

--Mejor sería ir a ganalle con vuestros brazos. ¿Pensáis acaso que esa roñosa pereza borra
crímenes y perjurios?

El se le cruzó en el camino, y asiendo con una mano el freno de la cabalgadura, levantó con
la otra su crucifijo de bronce, repitiendo:

--¡Dadme, os digo, unas migajas, en nombre de Nuestro Señor Jesucristo!

Entonces, el anciano, inclinó su cuerpo hacia adelante y, por toda respuesta, escupió dos veces
con bárbara osadía la santa imagen del Redentor. Ramiro exhaló un grito de espanto. Su cuerpo
vacilaba combatido por dos impulsos adversos. Por fin, corriendo con ímpetu a la cueva, cogió
la espada y se vino derecho hacia el hombre, con la intención de darle muerte allí mismo. Pero
al levantar la punta para hundirla en aquel pecho sacrílego, una voz recia y dominante, una
voz que penetró en sus entrañas, le contuvo de golpe:

--¡Ah! ¡Ramiro, Ramiro, sólo falta agora que acuchilles al hombre que te engendró!

Al pronunciar estas palabras, el caminante quitose el ancho sombrero que llevaba, a fin de
descubrir su cabeza y mostrar mejor todo el rostro. Ramiro experimentó profunda conmoción.
Acababa de reconocer al misterioso personaje del arrabal de Santiago, al abnegado morisco que
le había salvado la vida, dejándole después, como recuerdo, la valiosa daga sarracena.

--Sí, yo te engendré en la altiva doña Guiomar--prosiguió el anciano--y tu agüelo prefirió
casalla en seguida con el viejo don Lope, en odio a mi raza y a mi creencia. Luego, allá en
Avila, te di la vida por segunda vez, sacándote de entre las dagas de los creyentes; y fui
expulsado de Castilla como traidor. Pero tú, Ramiro, me pagaste en buena moneda cristiana,
faltando a tu juramento y entregando a la Inquisición a la infelice Gulinar y a Aixa, a Aixa
la jarifa, a Aixa la santa, para que fuesen arrojadas a la hoguera, después de haberte curado
y regalado con tanto amor como ellas te tenían!

Las lágrimas brotaron de sus ojos, y con voz temblorosa, exclamó por fin:

--¡Ah! No quiero maldecirte, porque la maldición de un padre es siempre escuchada por Alá...;
no, no me atrevo a maldecirte...!

Con estas palabras agitó su mano izquierda hacia atrás, y taloneando fuertemente la mula, dejó
caer al suelo toda la hogaza, desapareciendo en seguida entre los peñascos.

Ramiro le miró partir sin llamarle, y caminando hacia la cueva, fue a sentarse en el rincón
más obscuro, oprimiendo el crucifijo contra su pecho.

¿Qué había escuchado? ¿Su padre? ¡Un morisco!

Todos los enigmas de su vida acudían a su memoria: la soledad de su infancia, la dureza del
abuelo para con él, la continua y llorosa melancolía de doña Guiomar, las especies tan extrañas
que había suscitado su lance con los conversos, el súbito desvío de Beatriz, el denuesto de
Gonzalo en la callejuela... ¡el abnegado amor de aquel hombre de otra fe, de otra raza!; y
vio que todo resultaba harto comprensible a la luz de la espantosa revelación.

¿Sería verdad? ¿Sería, en efecto, hijo de moro? ¡Ah! Más valiera entonces romperse las venas
y dejar que toda su sangre se derramase sobre el lodo de la ignorada caverna. Su razón cayó
en espantosa vorágine. Las ideas parecían ulular y remolinear como los vientos en una noche
de vendaval. No quería, no quería pensar, y se hincaba las uñas en la frente para aturdirse,
agitaba los brazos en las tinieblas, resoplaba con furia como un hombre enajenado por el terror;
pero la cavilación era cada vez más inexorable, más elocuente, más honda. Unas veces reía de
su propia credulidad, desechando como el más grande de los absurdos las palabras del moro;
otras llegaba a sentir total convencimiento, y se sorprendía de no haber concebido hasta ahora
ninguna sospecha en medio de tantos indicios.

De pronto, el mismo horror de aquella incertidumbre, le yergue sobre los talones. Enciende
la candileja. Un pensamiento instantáneo acaba de cruzar por su mente. Sube al escabel, descuelga
los viejos vestidos y las botas que penden de lo alto de la gruta. Un bolsillo de monedas suena
en los gregüescos.

Cuando hubo cambiado el sayal por aquellas ropas de otro tiempo y ceñido la espada, salió de
la cueva y se puso a errar en la noche. No le quedaba ahora otra idea que huir sin descanso
hacia el mar, otra esperanza que los galeones.

Soñaba en alguna región de las Indias, donde las plantas, las frutas, las aves, las estrellas,
todo fuera nuevo para él y nada le recordase la tierra vieja y maligna en que había nacido,
aquella tierra en que todo era adversidad, maleficio, embrujamiento. Sólo así podría escapar
a la maldición que le perseguía quizá desde el vientre de la madre.

Caminó incansablemente, empujado como Ashavero, por un viento misterioso que no movía las hojas
de los árboles, y que él, con todas sus fuerzas, no hubiera podido resistir.

De noche, en las ventas, al verle aparecer con el anticuado traje y la luenga barba en desorden,
más de un gañán empinaba de golpe la taza de vino y se escapaba al corral haciéndose cruces.

En cambio, de día, al cruzar por los pueblos, los chiquillos se mofaban de su estampa y le
arrojaban por detrás cáscaras de nueces y puñados de polvo.

Con el dinero que había encontrado en los gregüescos compró una mula para abreviar el camino
y un capote para cubrirse, y de este modo, después de innumerables peripecias, llegó, por fin,
a la ciudad de Cádiz, a mediados de diciembre.

El mismo día, recorriendo las calles, vio una bandera de compañía colgada de una ventana; preguntó
por el capitán y le dijeron que se había marchado la víspera para Jerez. Iba a retirarse, cuando
un soldado, que estaba sentado en un poyo, junto a la puerta, exclamó:

--Si vuesa mercé, seor caballero, quiere hablar con Pablo Martínez, el alférez, ahí le tiene
a su derecha.

Ramiro volvió el rostro y su asombro fue inmenso al ver cruzar la calle a su antiguo paje vestido
con galas de soldado.

Pablillos llegaba apenas de Flandes. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>160818</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15182</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> It was like lightning. However, Ramiro
instantly recognized the eyes of Casilda, and instead of stopping, the layer terciose straightened
up hastily to the other side.

After missing more than half an hour in the direction of the southeast, without departing from
the river, he saw poke a cross between the ridges. It was the cross in a chapel built on the edge
of the abyss.

He approached, and despite deep trouble, let them fall by the surprise box absorbed a moment informing
it useful sense of his soul.

Opposite him, on the opposite side, extending from Toledo to the west rising, staggering on
the high gray rock roofs, their pale walls, numerous towers. Smooth and rapid escarpment from
the city fell to the bottom of the narrow, old apparently covered crumbly ash, as if the fire of God
had been there, destroying all roots and all the seed.

Ramiro religious thought with horror on the slopes of the eternal
punishment that reprobates have to climb with your feet and hands,
to fall back on the air inflamed and re-climb and fall without forgiveness,
without truce indefinitely.

He sat on a rock.

The river flowed at a terrible depth between rusty rocks and wild beasts. It seemed a River
of guilt and atonement, as it forges the imagination to think about hell. It seemed as though
painful spectra passed in procession down there, skimming the waves
Hanging with dark veils.

Meanwhile, the village took, with the time, desolate whiteness of bones in the wilderness, and
all the city, looking from a distance, through the vibrating shadows, like a city in another world,
a city outside of life and time, as anxious as the mysticism and psalms.

In the highest part, outstanding pieces drenched in melancholy reflection Alcázar twilight. Ramiro
recalled with mysterious inspiration that those walls had hosted one of the greatest kings glorious
history, a monarch of monarchs who ended up throwing the scepter and crown hidden refuge in
the monastery, and, suddenly, the ghost of Emperor Charles V. appeared before him with his
face half hidden by the hood of a habit.

Ah! Sackcloth that the owner of the world ...!

The sun sank behind the hills, and the city took a limp and purple
coloring, which if referred to by transparent amethyst.

Some windows that had flamed a flash went off. Ramiro overtones penetrate the sacred gathering,
sensing a sign, a voice from above. At that moment the bells of the city burst into touch
prayers. The chimes were entering long distance and moving a song which suggested in the litany
of death, and seemed as if the rock that supported the many steeples vibrated at the same time
as the box of an organ. He remembered Ramiro Avila bells, the afternoons of his childhood in the
stately tower and his mother, always weeping, always in mourning
always moody.

He prayed the Hail Mary. Was redeemed, was purified, but his chest felt hungry and sad, like a stream
without water. He wanted to enter the shrine at the foot of the altar
pour their grief deep.

Arose. The soil and rocks ranged around, his body, relieved, went to come off, no doubt, of the
earth.

Suddenly, a fire, a bolt inflamed, coming above, he entered his chest,
immersing for a few seconds in a rich state, enjoyed only with the
soul.

Then everything happened.

He thought then that he had been trasverberado as Mother Teresa of
Jesus and God just down to him in all his power and mercy, to make
testing a sip, just, of the joys that awaited him when his soul, conquering
the world, was delivered Finally, with sovereign passion, solitude
and penance.

A moment later he returned to the city in search of a convent where he changed clothes Knight
by a sackcloth of a hermit.

V

Puce dress and holding roughly with the refrain, over his shoulder, the humble backpacks saddled
him for the trip the Franciscan Sisters of Penance San Juan, funky Ramiro de Toledo, the next
morning, taking over the management of forests noon.

He wore all the hair back, the forehead without frowning, eyes moist.

He walked many days, from sunrise to sunset, sipping on his face in streams and eating the crumbs
which gave the farmers.

More than a compassionate Walker offered to take her on the rump of his horse, but he smiled and
marked in holy dust stronger footprint sandals. He slept in the yard sales or the roadside, where
he took night.

Finally, one morning, after very long trip, came to see from the top
of a hill the white city of Cordoba, bathed in the moist and radiant
blush of dawn.

It was noted from there, passing by a fruit, the convent of the Sisters of Mount Caramel, and
thought that under that roof was near his mother, felt the sobs choked breath.

Without wishing to approach the city and away from the trails, found at last, on the edge of the
mountain, a cave hidden by weeds and shrubs. Was inside a table made of branches of oak without
uncorking, an ink orange root, a stool, a hoe and several pots sunk in the mud. From the top, hung
an old suit gentleman, and besides, like two smoked hams, a pair of boots on the way with spurs.

That
same night, lighting the lamp she had, and going to bed on a pile
of litter to the bottom of the cave, he found himself with the mummified
body of an old hermit, that his hands still clutching rosary beads
dried.

Ramiro dropping hints knees and raised his arms to heaven, thanking God for having placed,
while in his way, the desired shelter and example of that death.

The next day morning, was buried the hermit, and ordered his best
inside the dark hiding place, where he had resolved to spend the rest
of his life.

Soon a sublime pleasure flooded her heart. The prayer continues, the total disregard the world
and, above all, the arduous and ingenious imposed penance, he did
know the ineffable pride of holiness great pride that swelled the
soul infinitely and he rose to sublime flight over the miseries of
man.

Compared to the admirable anchorites of the Thebaid, and was assured that in times to come would
read her story homes and dining halls for the edification of souls.

The nuns of Toledo habíanle put in the bag some books on mysticism.

Driven by those readings, Ramiro was proposed through the three spiritual paths described in treated,
and finally achieve possession of the greatest glory he had sought so far by misleading ways.

But
the flame of the early days could not be maintained, no longer feel those raptures again that
lit up in the crypt of her soul heat lamps that spoke Fray Juan de la Cruz. The night of cold
and darkness fell upon his heart, the gloom and damp of den began to stale, the reading made
him insufferable.

Some afternoons, hoping to breathe free, leaving you to walk through
the mountains until the evening.

The breeze was always delicious and brought from the farms to the
perfume of blossoms softened the will and away any idea of ??penance.

      Smiles of women, carmine of her lips
    parted, Blinks malicious, appeared before him in the dark pink or
blue in the shade of trees.

      
    

Apathy, laziness invincibility began to overwhelm its members as a magic and spirit until he
spent most of the day lying in bed hermit, busy counting dimples in the rock or water droplets
that fell from the slopes. Lizards, cockroaches, mice and many insects that were previously
unknown, ended up climbing over his body, and he, rather than frighten,
maintained complete immobility, to observe about their every move.

He spent weeks without praying the rosary and without going into the city to hear the Sunday
Mass and call provisions, as was his custom.

One morning he heard a woman's voice a few steps from the cave:

They sing and sing of Roland Oliveros and non of Zurraquín, CA was
great barragán.

Song of Roland or Olivero sings and non of Zurraquín, CA was a great gentleman.

It was a double chorus Medrano, Esquire, never tired of repeating. It seemed the voice Casilda.
Would not it be a deception of the senses?

He got up and looked out a moment. A woman, covered with a green veil, hurry down the hill,
and the song fell and walked away with it gracefully.

Another morning, gathering firewood by the outline, found at the foot
of a tree a sword cover rust.

Took her to his hideout and frotola strongly with wet sand. Was a lordly weapon, several silver
rings girdled the black leather scabbard, the blade had the mark of Hortunas, the garrison was shed
and thin, like a Miranda.

One trivial incident came to tear your laziness.

Since then spend hours sprucing up the sword in the smallest cracks,
and was pleased to bring it to light for sun run a flame over the
sheet, and wield wield it with force, it blow in the wind.

Since she never went out into the woods that carry it, and sometimes,
looking over and Moreover, as if someone might surprise you, bend
the tip of the trunk somewhat trees to remember the terrible lunge
that had killed Gonzalo.

His blood was roused again, and spirit, inflated again with the wind of honor dream again and
praise the triumphs of life and all the deeds that he could have
performed by the world.

Hallab an afternoon of September sitting on a high cliff, and pondering the idea shortly to visit
her mother when she saw walk up the hill, on a gray mule, a old lean and slender than his head
down and looked with singular attention to the grotto.

The man happened again the next morning, looking always with the same
curiosity.

Finally, one day when Ramirez came to feel so unbearable torment of hunger, mysterious old
man happened to be passing at the time of dusk, carrying forward on the chair a small basket
full of loaves and a string of onions around his shoulder.

Ramiro walked toward him, exclaiming:

- Give me, by God, an onion and some bread!

The man went on.

Ramiro, then, in a menacing voice and stronger, he repeated:

- For the love of God, give me some bread!

But the stranger, holding just the mule, said sharply:

- Better to go to ganalle with your arms.

Do you think perhaps that this filthy lazy delete crimes and perjury?

He crosses his path, and grasping with a hand brake of the horse, lifted with the other of its
bronze crucifix, repeating:

- Give me, I say, a few crumbs in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ!

Then the old man bent his body forward and, in reply, spat twice with holy boldness barbaric
image of the Redeemer. Ramiro gave a cry of horror. His body hesitated fought side by two impulses.
Finally, running with a vengeance to the cave, took the bar and came straight to the man, intending
to kill him right there. But to raise the tip to sink in that breast sacrilegious, a voice strong
and dominant, a voice penetrated his heart, checked him at once:

- Ah! Ramiro, Ramiro, just want now to stab the man who gave you life!

In pronouncing these words, Walker took off his broad hat he wore, to discover your head and better
show the whole face.

Ramiro experienced great shock. He had just recognized the mysterious character of the suburb
of Santiago, the dedicated Moorish had saved his life, leaving later, as I recall, the Saracen
dagger valuable.

- Yes, I have begotten you in the haughty Dona Guiomar - continued the old man - and your grandfather
preferred Casalla at once with the old Don Lope, in hatred of my race and my belief. Then, back
in Avila, I gave you life a second time, sacándote from the daggers
of the believers, and I Castilla expelled as a traitor.

But you, Ramiro, I paid in good coin Christian break your oath and giving to the Inquisition and
the wretched Gulina Aixa Aixa the Jarifa, Aixa the holy, that they
were thrown into the fire after they have cured and given with much
love as you have them!

Tears fell from his eyes and trembling voice, exclaimed at last:

- Ah! I do not want to curse, because a father's curse of Allah is always heard ..; no, I dare
not curse ...!

With these words he waved his left hand back, and heavily beaded mules, left fall down all the loaf,
then disappeared among the rocks.

Ramiro looked after him without calling him and walking toward the cave, went to sit in the corner
darker by pressing the crucifix to her chest.

What was heard? Her father? A Moorish!

All the mysteries of his life
came to his memory: the loneliness of his childhood, harsh grandfather
before him, the continuous and tearful melancholy Dona Guiomar, so
foreign species he had raised his lance to the converted, the sudden
diversion of Beatrice, the insult of Gonzalo on the street ... The
selfless love of one man of another faith, another race!, And saw
that it was highly understandable in light of the terrible revelation.

Could
it be true? Is it, indeed, the son of a Moor? Ah! More worth then
broken veins and let all his blood was spilled on the mud of the cave
ignored. His reason fell in terrible turmoil. The ideas seemed to
howl and swirl like the wind in one night gale. I did not want, do
not want to think, and knelt in front of nails to stun, waved his
arms in the darkness, puffing furiously as a man alienated by terror;
but was increasingly brooding inexorable, more eloquent, more profound.
Sometimes laughing their own credulity, dismissing as absurd greatest
words of the Moor; others came to feel fully convinced, and was surprised
not to have conceived so far no suspicion among many clues.

Suddenly,
the same horror of that uncertainty, he stands on his heels. Turns
the limelight. Instant thought just crossed his mind. Get in the stool,
picks old clothes and boots hanging from the top of the cave. A sound
currency pocket in breeches.

When he had changed the sackcloth of
those clothes from another time and girded sword, left the cave and
began to wander at night. He had no idea that yet another break away
without to the sea, another hope that the galleons.

He dreamed of
a region of India, where plants, fruits, birds, stars, everything
was new to him and nothing will remind old and evil land of his birth,
the land where everything was adversity, hex, hexing. Only then could
escape the curse that haunted him perhaps from the womb. 

Walked
tirelessly pushed as Ashavero, by a mysterious wind that moved the
leaves trees, and that he, with all his might, I could not resist.

At
night, in sales, seeing him appear with the old suit and beard disheveled,
tiptoe over a farmhand hit the cup of wine and crossing himself escaped
the corral.

In contrast, day, crossing the villages, the kids made
fun of his appearance and he threw behind nutshells and handfuls of
dust.

With the money he had found in the breeches bought a mule to
shorten the path and a cloak to cover, and thus, after many adventures,
was finally the city of Cadiz, in mid-December.

The same day, walking
the streets, saw a banner hung from a window company, asked by the
captain and told him that he had left the day before to Jerez. Was
going to retire when a soldier who was sitting on a bench, next to
the door, said:

- If your worship, sir knight, wants to talk to Pablo
Martinez, the lieutenant, there will have on your right.

Ramiro turned
her face and her astonishment was immense when he saw crossing the
street to her house dress page soldier's finery.

Pablillo was barely
in Flanders</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>