<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02451</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>96559</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17783</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Y ansí, se partieron[32], y Inca Yupanqui se quedó en la ciudad, y los tales señores caciques
se fueron de allí derechos do Viracocha Inca estaba; y despues de le haber hecho su debido
acatamiento, como Inca Yupanqui se lo habia mandado, le dijeron cómo Inca Yupanqui los inviaba
allí a que viesen en qué era servido que ellos le sirviesen; y como Viracocha Inca los viese
delante de sí y tan gran multitud de señores y de tanto poder, holgóse mucho de ello, porque
dellos tenia gran necesidad al presente, para que le favoresciesen con algun tanto de sus rentas,
para edificar aquel pueblo que allí queria hacer; é díjoles que fuesen muy bien venidos, é
levantóse de su asiento y abrazólos á todos y tornóse á sentar en su silla, y mandólos á todos
que ansí se sentasen; y mandó que sacasen muchos vasos de chicha, y que les diesen á beber;
y luego les hizo sacar mucha cantidad de coca, una yerba preciada que ellos siempre traen en
la boca, la cual yerba la historia adelante dirá. Y ansí repartida entre aquellos señores,
levantóse en pié Viracocha Inca, [y] considerando, que pues su hijo le inviaba aquellos señores
y ellos tanto le amaban y le querian por Señor, que era justo que él ansimismo en ello les
animase, les hizo cierta oracion, por la cual él de su parte les agradescia lo que por él y
por su hijo habian hecho, y que ya sabian y habian oido decir que él hasta allí habia sido
Señor del Cuzco, é que él se habia salido dél por causas que para ello le movieron; y que de
allí adelante Inca Yupanqui, su hijo, habia de ser Señor en la ciudad del Cuzco, y que á él
obedeciesen y respetasen, como su tal Señor, y que él desde allí se desestia de la insignia
y borla real y la ponia en la cabeza de su hijo Inca Yupanqui. Todo lo cual oido por los señores,
se levantaron en pié, y uno á uno fueron á él y le dieron grandes gracias, y mostraron que
rescibian en gran merced ellos el hecho del tal desistirse de la tal dignidad y darla á su
hijo Inca Yupanqui, que ellos tanto amaban é querian por Señor; y esto hecho, se tornaron á sentar.

Y Viracocha Inca les rogó, que por cuanto él queria allí en el peñol do estaba edificar un
pueblo, y que para ello tenia necesidad de su ayuda y gente, que les rogaba que tuviesen por
bien de darle aquella ayuda; á lo cual le respondieron aquellos señores, que ellos habian venido
allí para que él viese lo que ellos le pudiesen hacer algun servicio, como su Señor Inca Yupanqui
se lo habia mandado; é que aquello y otra cualquier cosa que él mandarles quisiese estaban
prestos de lo hacer; que les dijese el tiempo y mes en que queria comenzar [á] hacer su obra,
para que ellos inviasen allí sus principales é indios para que entendiesen en la hacer y hiciesen
los tales edificios; y que él, entretanto, diese la traza del tal pueblo, y hiciese hacer de
barro la figura de los tales edificios, que ellos le inviarian allí maestros que los supiesen
bien hacer, ansí de cantería, como de la manera quél los quisiese. Y Viracocha Inca su hijo
(así) se lo agradeció á todos ellos, y luego mandó sacar muchas cosas, como fueron hondas y
petacas de coca, y ciertas piezas de ropa fina y otras muchas cosas entre ellos muy preciadas;
todas las cuales fueron traidas delante dél, y siendo, él allí mesmo por sus manos las dió
y repartió á aquellos señores; y esto hecho, mandóles dar á beber, y que asímesmo les fuese
repartida cierta cantidad de coca. Y esto hecho, Viracocha Inca se levantó en pié y les agradeció
la voluntad y amor que á él y á su hijo le mostraban y tenian; y díjoles el mes y tiempo en
que habian de enviarle sus indios y gentes para que edificasen su pueblo; é ansí, los señores
se levantaron en pié, é quedando con él de se los inviar, como dicho tenian, le hicieron su
acatamiento, é ansí se despidieron dél; donde le dejaremos, y hablaremos de Inca Yupanqui.

Salidos que fueron aquellos señores caciques de donde Inca Yupanqui estaba, y fueron á do Viracocha
Inca estaba, como ya la historia os ha contado, é Inca Yupanqui quedase solo en su ciudad con
los suyos, despues de haber reposado dos dias, parescióle que tenian ya ociosidad, é habia
tomado por recreacion el ejercer de su persona; é ansí, salió un dia de mañana de la ciudad
del Cuzco, é llevando consigo los señores que allí consigo tenia, anduvo aquel dia todas las
tierras que en torno de la ciudad eran, y lo mismo hizo otro dia siguiente; [y] despues de
las haber bien visto y mirado, vió la mala reparticion é arte que el tiempo que allí su padre
estuvo ellas tenian. El tercero dia, tambien ansímismo anduvo mirando, juntamente con los señores,
el sitio donde la ciudad del Cuzco estaba fundada, todo lo cual, ó lo más dello, eran ciénagas
y maniantales, como ya la historia os lo ha contado, y las casas de los moradores della eran
pequeñas y pajizas é mal edificadas y sin proporcion de arte de pueblo que calles tuviese;
y bien ansí como es el dia de hoy junto á esta ciudad un pueblo que llaman Cayaucachi, era
en aquel tiempo las casas y pueblo que agora es la gran ciudad del Cuzco.

Y como Inca Yupanqui viese tan mal parado este pueblo del Cuzco, é ansímismo las tierras de
labranzas que en torno dél eran, parescióle, viendo que tenia tiempo y gran aparejo para de
nuevo reedificarla, y que primero que en el pueblo hiciese casa, ni el reparto de las tierras,
que seria bien hacer y edificar una casa al sol, en la cual casa pusiesen y fuese puesto un
bulto en el lugar do el sol reverenciasen y hiciesen sacrificios; porque, aunque ellos tienen
que haya uno que es el Hacedor, á quien ellos llaman Viracocha Pachayachachic, que dice Hacedor
del mundo, y ellos tienen que éste hizo el sol y todo lo que es criado en el cielo y tierra,
como ya habeis oido; caresciendo de letras, y siendo ciegos del entendimiento en el saber,
casí muchos varian en esto en todo y por todo, que unas veces tienen al sol por hacedor, y
otras veces dicen que el Viracocha; y por la mayor parte, en toda la tierra y en cada provincia
della, como el Demonio les traiga ofuscados, y en cada parte que se les demostraba les decia
mil mentiras y engaños, y ansí los traia engañados y ciegos, y en los tales lugares do ansí
le vian ponian piedras en su lugar, á quien ellos reverenciaban y adoraban. Y como les dijese
unas veces que era el sol, y á otros en otras partes decia que era la luna, y á otros que era
su Dios y Hacedor, é á otros que era su lumbre que los calentaba y alumbraba, é que ansí lo
verian en los volcanes de Arequipa[33]; en otras partes decia que era el Señor que habia dado
el ser al mundo, y que se llamaba Pachacama, que dice, Dador de ser al mundo; y ansí los traya,
como tengo dicho, engañados y ciegos.

Y volviendo á nuestra historia, este Señor Inca Yupanqui, como quisiese hacer casa y adoratorio
á quien él reverenciase y los demás de su pueblo, quiriendo lo hacer á reverencia y semejanza
del que habia visto ántes de su batalla, y considerando él quel que ansí viera, á quien él
llamaba Viracocha, que le vió con gran resplandor, segun ellos dicen, y en tanta manera que
le paresció que todo el dia era allí delante dél y su lumbre, lo cual viendo delante de sí,
dicen que hubo gran pavor, y que nunca le dijo quién fuese; considerando él en sí, cuando esta
casa queria edificar, que aquel que viera, segun la lumbre que en él habia visto, que debia
de ser el sol, y que como llegase á él y la primera palabra que le dijese "Hijo, no tengas
temor," y ansí los suyos, como la historia os ha contado, le llamaron despues Hijo del Sol;
y tiniendo él ansí lo que ya habeis oido, propuso de hacer esta Casa del Sol.

Y como la propusiese, llamó los suyos y los señores de la ciudad del Cuzco que allí consigo
tenia, y díjoles lo que ansí tenia pensado y que queria edificar esta casa; y ellos le dijeron
que diese la órden y traza del edificio della, porque tal casa como aquella, ellos, los naturales
y propios de la ciudad del Cuzco la debian edificar é hacer; é Inca Yupanqui les dijo que la
casa debia ser edificada luego, porque él ansí lo tenia pensado. Y visto por él el sitio do
á él mejor le paresció que la casa debia de ser edificada, mandó que allí fuese traido un cordel,
y siéndole traido, levantáronse del lugar do estaban él y los suyos, y siendo ya en el sitio
do habia de ser la casa edificada, él mismo por sus manos con el cordel midió y trazó la Casa
del Sol; y habiéndola trazado, partió de allí con los suyos y fué á un pueblo que dicen Salu[34],
que es casi cinco leguas de esta ciudad, ques do se sacan las canteras, y midió las piedras
para el edificio desta casa, y ansí medidas, de los pueblos comarcanos pusieron las piedras
que les fué señaladas y las que fueron bastantes para el edificio desta casa; y juntamente
con esto, trujeron todo lo demás que para el edificio desta era necesario; y siendo ya allí,
pusieron por obra el edificio della, bien ansí como Inca Yupanqui la habia trazado y imaginado.
Andó él siempre y los demás señores encima de la obra, mirando cómo la edificaban, y ansí él
como los demás, trabajaban en el tal edificio; la cual obra, como allí tuviese juntos los materiales
y menesteres della, que en breve tiempo fué acabada.

Y como ya fuese acabada esta otra Casa del Sol que habeis oido, mandó Inca Yupanqui que luego
fuesen juntas quinientas mujeres doncellas, y como allí fuesen traidas, ofreciólas al sol,
para que allí siempre estas tales doncellas sirviesen al sol y estuviesen allí dentro, bien
ansí como las monjas son encerradas; y luego, allí, llamando á un señor anciano y natural de
la ciudad del Cuzco que á él le pareció que era hombre honesto y de buen exemplo y fama, que
estuviese y regiese allí en la Casa del Sol, y que fuese mayordomo del sol y de la tal casa.
Y luego mandó que allí fuesen entregados doscientos mozos de servicio del sol; y ansímismo
en aquella hora señaló ciertas tierras para el sol, en que sembrasen estos doscientos yanaconas.

Y esto hecho, mandó Inca Yupanqui á los señores del Cuzco que, para de allí á diez dias, tuviesen
aparejado mucho proveimiento de maíz, ovejas y corderos, y ansímismo mucha ropa fina, y cierta
suma de niños y niñas, que ellos llaman Capacocha, todo lo cual era para hacer sacrificio al
sol. Y siendo los diez dias cumplidos y ésto ya todo junto, Inca Yupanqui mandó hacer un gran
fuego, en el cual fuego mandó, despues de haber hecho degollar las ovejas y corderos, que fuesen
echados en él, y las demás ropas y maíz, ofreciéndolo todo al sol; y los niños y niñas que
ansí habian juntado, estando bien vestidos y aderezados, mandólos enterrar vivos en aquella
casa, que en especial era hecha para donde estuviese el bulto del sol; y con la sangre que
de los corderos y ovejas habian sacado, mandó que fuesen hechas ciertas rayas en las paredes
desta casa; todo lo cual hacia y los sus tres amigos é otros; todo lo cual sinificaba una manera
de biendecir y consagrar esta casa; en el cual sacrificio andaba Inca Yupanqui y sus compañeros
descalzos y mostrando gran reverencia á esta casa y al sol. É ansímismo con la misma gente
[sangre?] el Inca Yupanqui hizo ciertas rayas en la cara [á] aquel señor que era señalado por
mayordomo desta casa, y lo mismo hizo á aquellos señores, sus tres amigos, y á las mamaconas
monjas que para el servicio del sol eran allí. Y luego mandó que todos los de la ciudad, ansí
hombres como mujeres, viniesen á hacer sus sacrificios allí á la casa del sol; los cuales sacrificios
que ansí la gente comun hizo, fué quemar cierto maíz y coca en aquel fuego que ansí era hecho,
entrando cada uno destos uno á uno y descalzos, los ojos bajos; y al salir que ansí salian,
despues de haber hecho su sacrificio, á cada uno destos por sí mandó Inca Yupanqui que aquel
mayordomo del sol hiciese la raya misma que habeis oido, con la sangre de las ovejas, en los
rostros destos que ansí salian, á los cuales les era mandado, que desde aquella hora hasta
que el bulto del sol fuese hecho de oro, todos estuviesen en ayuno, y que no comiesen carne
ni pescado ni áun guisallo, ni llegasen á mujer, ni comiesen verdura ninguna, y que solamente
comiesen maíz crudo y bebiesen chicha, sopena que el que el ayuno quebrantase, fuese sacrificado
al sol y quemado en el mismo fuego. El cual fuego mandó Inca Yupanqui que siempre estuviese
ardiendo de noche y de dia; la leña del cual fuego mandó Inca Yupanqui que fuese labrada y
quemada mientras al ídolo se hiciesen en el fuego sacrificios, los cuales mandó que durante
este tiempo hiciesen las mamaconas del sol; las cuales ansímismo estaban en grande ayuno y
lo mismo el Inca Yupanqui y los demás señores.

Y esto hecho y proveido, mandó Inca Yupanqui que viniesen allí los plateros que en la ciudad
habia, y los mejores oficiales, y dándoles todo aparejo allí en las Casas del Sol, les mandó
que hiciese un niño de oro macizo y vaciadizo, que fuese el tamaño del niño del altor y proporcion
de un niño de un año y desnudo; porque dicen que aquel que le hablara cuando él se puso en
oracion estando en el sueño, que viniera á él en aquella figura de un niño muy resplandeciente,
y que él vino á él despues, estando despierto, la noche ántes que diese la batalla á Uscovilca,
como ya os he contado, que fué tanto el resplandor que vió que dél resultaba, que no le dejó
ver qué figura tenia; y ansí mandó hacer este ídolo del tamaño y figura de un niño de edad
de un año; el cual bulto se tardó de hacer un mes, en el cual mes tuvieron grandes sacrificios
y ayunos.

Y este bulto acabado, mandó Inca Yupanqui que aquel señor que habia señalado por mayordomo
del sol, que tomase el ídolo, el cual le tomó con muchas reverencias, y vistióle una camiseta
muy ricamente tejida de oro y lana é de diversas labores, y púsole en la cabeza cierta atadura
á uso y costumbre de ellos, y luego le puso una borla segun la del estado de los Señores, y
encima della le puso una patena de oro, y en los piés le calzó unos zapatos, uxutas[35] que
ellos llaman, ansímismo de oro. Y estando ansí el bulto, llegó Inca Yupanqui á do el bulto
estaba, el cual iba descalzo, y como llegase á él, hízole sus mochas[36] y gran reverencia,
mostrándole gran respeto; é ansí, tomó el bulto del ídolo en sus manos y llevólo á do era la
casa y lugar do él habia de estar; en la cual casa estaba hecho un escaño, hecho de madera
y muy bien cubierto de unas plumas de pájaros tornasoles de diversas maneras y colores, de
las cuales y con las cuales era muy vistosamente labrado; en el cual escaño puso Inca Yupanqui
el bulto del ídolo. Y siendo allí puesto, hizo traer un brasero de oro, y siendo encendido
en él fuego, mandóle poner delante del ídolo, en el cual fuego y brasero hizo echar ciertos
pajaricos y ciertos granos de maíz, y derramar en el tal fuego cierta chicha; todo lo cual
dijo que comia el sol, é que haciendo aquello, le daba de comer; y de allí adelante se tuvo
aquella costumbre ordinariamente; lo cual hacia aquel mayordomo dél, ansí como si fuera persona
que comiera y bebiera; ansí se tenia especial cuidado de le guisar de comer diversas comidas
y maneras de manjares, y ansí las quemaban delante, á la tarde y á la mañana en braseros de
oro y plata, en la manera que ya habeis oido. Y dende allí adelante adoraban en aquel ídolo;
y no entraban dentro del ídolo donde estaba, sino eran los señores principales, entrando con
mucha reverencia y veneracion, los zapatos quitados, y las cabezas bajas; y el Inca Yupanqui
entraba sólo, y él mismo por su mano sacrificaba las ovejas y corderos, haciendo él el fuego
y quemando el sacrificio. Y cuando él ansí estaba haciendo el sacrificio, ningun señor osaba
entrar dentro, y todos se quedaban en el patio, y allí hacian ellos fuera sus sacrificios y
sus mochas y adoramientos. Y para en que la gente comun adorasen allá fuera, porque no habian
de entrar allá dentro si no fuesen señores, y éstos en el patio, hizo poner en medio de la
plaza del Cuzco, donde agora es el rollo, una piedra de la hechura de un pan de azúcar, puntiaguda
para arriba y enforrada de una hoja de oro; la cual piedra hizo ansímismo labrar el dia que
mandó hacer el bulto del sol, y esta piedra, para en quel comun adorase, y el bulto, en la
Casa del Sol, los señores; la cual casa era reverenciada y tenido en gran reverencia, no solamente
el bulto, mas las piedras della y los sirvientes y yanaconas della eran tenidos por cosa bendita
y consagrada.

Y al tiempo que la edificaban, estando asentando cierta piedra, quebróse de la juntura de la
tal piedra un pedazo como tres dedos en ancho y largo, y mandó Inca Yupanqui que luego fuese
allí derretida cierta plata y vaciada de tal manera en la piedra y quebrado della, que viniese
al justo de lo que la piedra se quebró; todo lo cual era de cantería, y la juntura de la tal
cantería de piedra con piedra era tan sotilmente asentado, que parescia raya hecha con un clavo
en una piedra. En la cual se enterraban los señores principales en los patios y aposentos,
excepto donde el ídolo estaba; y el dia quel ídolo se puso en la casa, entraron en la ciudad,
que no lo saben ni pueden inumerarlo, mas que dicen que la vez que ménos ovejas y corderos
allí sacrificaron, que pasaba de más de quinientos.

Acabado de dar órden Inca Yupanqui é de haber hecho los ídolos y casas del sol, que habeis
oido, mandó en la ciudad del Cuzco que en un cierto dia señalado fuesen juntos en ella todos
los señores, caciques y principales que en las provincias y comarcas de en torno de la ciudad
del Cuzco vivian y á él habian dado obidiencia, para [por] que tenia ciertas cosas que comunicar
con ellos; é oido el mando por los principales del Cuzco, luego inviaron sus orejones por las
provincias y comarcas que ya habeis oido, con los cuales inviaban á mandar á los tales señores
de ellas el mando que el Inca Yupanqui tenia hecho, y que para aquel dia señalado fuesen todos
á la ciudad. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05425</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>321281</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16418</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

And thus, the left [32], and Inca Yupanqui stayed in the city, and such gentlemen caciques went
from there do Viracocha Inca was right, and after you have done your due compliance, as Inca
Yupanqui had commanded him, told him how the winters Inca Yupanqui there for them to see what
was served that they serve him, and saw them as Inca Viracocha front of him and such a multitude
of lords and so much power, much of it rejoiced because Dell had this great need for favoresciesen
him with some much of his income to build that people there wanted to do: and told them that they
were very welcome, é arose from his seat and embraced them all and it became to sit in his
chair, and commanded them to all that longs to sit down, and commanded them to put many glasses
of chicha, and gave them to drink; and then they brought out a large amount of coca, an herb
prized that they always bring in mouth, which tell the story along grass. And thus divided between
those gentlemen, Viracocha rose standing, [and] considering that as your child masters those
invia and they both loved him and wanted him as Lord, it was just that he ansimismo it will encouraged,
we did some prayer, by which he in turn agradescia them what he and his son had done, and
already knew and had heard that he had been up there Lord of Cuzco, é he had gotten off to
do so for reasons that moved him, and that Inca Yupanqui then on, his son, was to be Lord
in the city of Cuzco, and that to him obey and respect, such as their Lord, and from there he
Desesti logo and real fringe and put it on the head of his son Inca Yupanqui. All of which
is heard by the lords, stood up, and one by one went to him and gave him great thanks, and
showed that rescibian large grant them the fact of such waiver of such dignity and give your son
Inca Yupanqui, which they both loved é wanted by the Lord, and this fact, it turned to sit.

Viracocha
Inca and begged them, that because he wanted there in the Peñol do was build a people, and
that this had need of your help and people, he begged them who had
them well to give that assistance, to which the gentlemen replied
that they had come there so that he could see what they could do him
some service, as Lord Inca Yupanqui had commanded him: and that this
and any other thing he wanted was to send ready for what to do, to
tell them the time and wanted to start the month in which [to] do
its work for them to invest their principal and Indians there that
they might understand the how and hiciesen of such buildings, and
he, meanwhile, give the trace of such people, and make hiciese clay
figure of such buildings, they will inviarian teachers who knew there
doing good ANSI stonework as chelate the way I wanted.

And his son Viracocha (So) was grateful to them all, and then sent out many things, as they
were deep and suitcases of cocaine, and certain pieces of fine clothes and other things between
them very valuable; all of which were brought in front of him, and being, he mesmo there got their
hands and distributed to those men and this fact, he commanded them to drink, and that they be provided
himself distributed a certain amount of coca. And this fact, Viracocha Inca stood up and thanked
them the will and love to him and his son and had showed him, and said the month and time they
had to send his Indians and people to build their people, and so he, Mr. rose on foot, and was staying
with him in winter, and that they had, they made their compliance, and so he will leave of him,
where we will leave, and talk of Inca Yupanqui.

These gentlemen were coming out of where Inca Yupanqui chiefs was, and went to do Viracocha
Inca was, as history has told you, and Inca Yupanqui left alone in the city their own, after having
rested two days, they had already parescióle idleness, E had recreation taken by the exercise
of his person, and so he came out one day in the city tomorrow Cuzco, é carrying the gentlemen
who had him there, he walked all that day land around the city were, and so did another the next
day, [and] after the well have seen and watched, saw the poor distribution é art that while
there his father was they had. The third day, also went looking ansímismo, together with the
gentlemen, the site where the city of Cuzco was founded, all of which, or as dello were swamps
and maniantales, as history has told you, and the houses of the inhabitants
were della é thatched small and poorly built and no proportion of
street art that people had; ANSI well as in the present day near this
city a village called Cayaucachi was At that time the houses and people
that now is the great city of Cuzco.

And Inca Yupanqui saw too badly this town of Cuzco, land ansímismo é Around the crops that
were parescióle, seeing that he had time and a great rig for the new rebuilt, and that first
house in the village hiciese nor the distribution of land, it would be okay and to build a house
in the sun, in whose house verifications and was wearing a package in place and revere the
sun do hiciesen sacrifices because, although they have there is one who is the Maker, whom they
called Viracocha Pachayachachic, says maker the world, and they have it made the sun and all that
is raised in heaven and earth, as we have heard; caresciendo of letters of understanding and being
blind in the know, almost many variants on this at all and everything, which sometimes have
the sun by maker, and sometimes say that the Viracocha, and for the most part, the whole earth
and every province della, as the Devil brings you befuddled, and each party told them they
showed thousand lies and deceptions, and so they brought them deceived
and blind, and in such places do ANSI Vian will they placed stones
in place, whom they revered and worshiped.

And as I say sometimes it was the sun, and to others elsewhere said it was the moon, and to
others that it was their God and Maker, E to others it was their fire that the heat and light,
that they crave é would see the volcanoes of Arequipa [33] in other parts said it was the Lord
who had given Being the world, and was called Pachacamac, he says, Giver of being the world,
and so he's brought, as I have said, deceived and blind.

And back to our history, the Lord Inca Yupanqui, and wanted to make home and shrine whom he revered
and others of his people, Quiros what to do reverence and likeness which had been before his
battle, and considering he craves quel see, whom he called Viracocha, who saw him brightly,
they say, and in such a way that paresció that he was there all day and before the fire, which
saw before him say there was great fear, and never told him who it was, considering it as such,
when this House wanted to build, than that which saw, according to the fire that he had seen,
which was to to be the sun, and how to get there and the first word he said "Son, do not be fear,
"and so they own, as history has told you, he was called after Son of the Sun tiniendo he craves
and what we have heard, proposed to the House of the Sun

And as proposed, called his men and the lords of the city of Cuzco to get there had, and said they
look forward had thought and wanted to build this house, and they
said to give the order and trace the building of it, because such
a house like that, they, the natives and own the city of Cuzco to
the debian build é, é Inca Yupanqui said that house was to be built
then, because he had thought they crave.

And seen him do site paresció it to him better than the house was to be built, he ordered that
there be brought a string, and being so brought, rose up the place do were he and his men, and
now the site do was to be the house built, he himself by his hands with the line measured
and drew the House the Sun, and having drawn, left there with his family and went to a people
who say Salu [34] which is nearly five miles from this city parks do is take the quarries,
and measured the stones for the building of this house, and so he measures in the neighboring
villages began stones them was identified and those were enough for the building of this house,
and together with this, they brought everything else to the building Desta was necessary,
and being already there, put to work building della either ANSI as the Inca Yupanqui had traced
and imagined.

Ando he provided the other lords over the work, watching the builders, and longing as others
working in this building, which work together as there had material and necessities of it, which
was finished in short time.

And as I was finished the other house of the sun that you have heard, then sent Inca Yupanqui
together five hundred women were virgins, and as there were brought, offered him the sun, so that
there are always such to worship the sun and maidens were in there, well ANSI as the nuns are
enclosed, and then, there he called an old man and natural Cuzco that he thought he was honest
and of good examples and fame, which and regiese was there at the Casa del Sol, and to be steward
of the sun and that house. And then there were sent two hundred waiters delivered the sun,
and ansímismo at that time said some land for the sun, who planted these two hundred yanaconas.

And
this fact, Inca Yupanqui sent to the lords of Cuzco, and from there to ten days, they had
much proveimiento rigged corn, sheep and lambs, and ansímismo much fine clothes, and some amount
of children, they call Capacocha, all of which was to make sacrifice sun. And since the ten days
of age and this and all together, Inca Yupanqui ordered a large fire, which sent fire, after
having made slaughter sheep and lambs, which were thrown into it, and other clothing and corn, offering
all the sun, and the children who ANSI had assembled, being well
dressed and seasoned, mandolin buried alive in that house, which was
especially made for where was the bulk of the sun, and with blood
lambs and sheep had taken, he ordered them to be made certain lines
on the walls this house, all of which made it and his three friends
and others, all of which sinificaba way of biendecir and consecrate
this house, in which sacrifice was walking Inca Yupanqui and his companions
Barefoot and showing great reverence to this house and the sun.

É ansímismo with the same people [Blood?] The Inca Yupanqui had some scratches on the face [to]
this man who was identified by steward of this house, and so did those gentlemen, his three
friends, and to the virgins nuns to serve the sun were there. And then ordered that all city,
ANSI men and women, should come and make their sacrifices there to the house of the sun, which
sacrifices craves the common people did was burn some corn and coca craves that fire was made,
entering every one of these one by one and barefoot, looking down, and leaving it craves Salian,
after making his sacrifice, to every one of these on their Inca Yupanqui ordered that Butler
hiciese sun stripe same as you have heard, with the blood of sheep,
in faces of these who craves Salian, whom I was commanded, that from
that time until the bulk of the sun were made of gold, they were all
fasting, and not to eat meat or fish or even his cooking, and reaching
women, nor eat any vegetables, and only eat raw corn and drink chicha,
Sopena that would break the fast, were sacrificed the sun and burned
in the fire itself.

The Inca Yupanqui ordered that fire was always burning night and day, the wood fire which sent Inca
Yupanqui was wrought and while the idol was burned in the fire hiciesen sacrifices, which he commanded
during this time would go all the virgins of the sun, which ansímismo were big and fast the
same as the Inca Yupanqui and other masters.

And this fact and provided, Inca Yupanqui ordered them to come there silversmiths in the city
had, and the best officers, and tackle them all there in the Casas del Sol, I sent that would
make a child-cast solid gold, it was the child's size and proportion of altor a one year old
and naked, for they say that he who would speak when he stood in prayer while in the dream,
to come to him at that figure of a very bright child, and he came to him later, while awake, the
night before the battle to give Uscovilca, as I told you that was so much glare that you saw the
result, which left him no see what shape he was, and so they sent to the idol of the size
and shape of a child aged a year which it took to package a month, which month had the great
sacrifices and fasting.

And this package finished, Inca Yupanqui ordered that the gentleman who had reported by Butler the sun,
take the idol, which he took with many bows, and clothed a T-shirt richly woven with gold and
wool and various tasks, and put him in the head some bond to use and practice of them, then
put a tassel according to the state of the Lords, and della above put a whistle of gold, buckled
on his feet in shoes, uxutas [35] they call ansímismo gold. ANSI standard and the bulk, Inca
Yupanqui arrived to do the bulk was, who was barefoot, and how to get there, made him their
mochas [36] and great reverence, showing great respect, and so he took the bulk of the idol
in his hands and carried him to do was home and instead do it was to be, in whose house was made
a seat, made of wood and well covered with iridescent feathers of birds in different ways and colors,
which and with whom was ornately carved, in which seat put Inca Yupanqui the bulk of the idol.
And being there since, he brought a brazier of gold, and being fired fire him, ordered him
to put before the idol, which did take fire and hearth certain birds and some corn kernels
and pour into the fire that some chicha, all of which said they ate the sun, and that by doing
that, fed him, and from then on it was custom that ordinarily, which
made it that Butler, like ANSI person to eat and drink, craving is
especially careful you had to eat different foods cooking and ways
of delicacies, and so they burned them before, afternoon and in the
morning in braziers gold and silver, as you have already heard.

And from then onwards there worshiped the idol; and do not fall within the idol where it was,
but were the lords, entering with great reverence and veneration, shoes removed and their heads
low, and the Inca Yupanqui entered alone, and he sacrificed his own hand sheep and lambs, making it
the fire and burning the sacrifice. And when he craves he was making the sacrifice, no sir
dared enter, and everyone was in the yard, and there they were doing was their sacrifices and their
mochas and worship. And that the common people worship out there, because they had not to go in
there unless they were gentlemen, and these in the yard, he put through square of Cuzco, where
now is the roll, a stone of the making of a sugar cone, pointed enforrada up and a sheet of
gold which made stone till the day ansímismo he ordered the bulk of the sun, and this stone, so
that the community in worship, and bulk in Casa del Sol, the rulers
whose house was revered and held in great reverence, not only the
package, but the stones and the servants and della della yanaconas
were counted blessed thing and consecrated.

And while the builders, while settling some stone quebróse the juncture of the stone such a piece
as three fingers in width and length, and sent Inca Yupanqui was then there some silver melted
and poured in such a manner and broken stone of it, to come to just what the stone was broken,
all of which was of stone, and the juncture of such stone quarry stone was so crafty settled,
which made parescia streak with a nail on a stone. In which the lords were buried in the courtyards
and rooms, except where the idol was, and the day quel idol was in the house, entered the city,
who do not know and can not innumerable, but they say that while fewer sheep and lambs killed
there, who spent more than five hundred.

Order to finish é Inca Yupanqui had made idols and houses of the sun, that you have hearing,
ordered the city of Cuzco in a certain appointed day they were together in it all lords, chieftains
and principal in the provinces and counties around the city Cuzco lived and had given to him
obidient, for [for] I had some things to communicate with them: and heard by the main control
of Cuzco, then their apricots in the winter provinces and counties that already have heard, with
which command the winters such gentlemen of them command the Inca Yupanqui had done, and that
for that day said they were all to the city.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>