<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10623</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>156243</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21245</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Es que la muchacha se lo merecía todo: la luz del blandón descubría
su rostro animado, encendía sus ojos rechispeantes, y mostraba la crespa melena, desanudada
por la agitación de la caminata, y flotando en caprichosas roscas por su frente, hombros y
cuello. Baltasar y Borrén, de americana y hongo, se colocaron entre la apiñada muchedumbre
y quizá le murmuraron al oído cien mil dislates; pero no estaba el alcacer para gaitas, es
decir, no estaba Amparo de humor de requiebros, hallándose exclusivamente poseída del fervor
político.

Sentíase sobreexcitada, febril, en días tan memorables. Por todas partes fingía su calenturienta
imaginación peligros, luchas, negras tramas urdidas para ahogar la libertad. De fijo de fijo
el Gobierno de Madrid sabía ya a tal hora que una heroica pitillera marinedina realizaba inauditos
esfuerzos para apresurar el triunfo de la federal: y con tales pensamientos latíale a Amparo
su corazoncillo y se le hinchaba el seno agitado. En medio de la vulgaridad e insulsez de su
vida diaria y de la monotonía del trabajo siempre idéntico a sí mismo, tales azares revolucionarios
eran poesía, novela, aventura, espacio azul por donde volar con alas de oro. Su fantasía inculta
y briosa se apacentaba en ellos. Las enfáticas frases de los artículos de fondo, los redundantes
períodos de los discursos resonaban en sus oídos como el ritornelo del vals en los de la niña
bailadora. Aquella llegada de los individuos de la Asamblea de la Unión fue para Amparo lo
que sería la de los Apóstoles para un pueblo que oyese hablar del Evangelio y de pronto viese
arribar a sus costas a los encargados de anunciarlo.

Tenía Amparo por cosa cierta que se acercaba la hora de señalarse con algún hecho digno de
memoria: ansiaba, sin declarárselo a sí misma, emplear las fuerzas de abnegación y sacrificio
que existen latentes en el alma de la mujer del pueblo. ¡Sacrificarse por cualquiera de aquellos
hombres, venidos de Cantabria a vaticinar la redención; inmolarse por el más viejo, por el
más feo, prestándole algún extraordinario y capital servicio! Llamar a su puerta a las altas
horas de la noche; decirle con voz entrecortada que «ahí viene la policía» y que se oculte;
acompañarle por recónditas callejuelas a un escondrijo seguro; meterle en la mano unos cuantos
pesos ahorrados a fuerza de liar pitillos; recibir, en cambio, un haz de proclamas para repartir
al día siguiente, con la advertencia de que «si se las cogen, puede contarse ánima del Purgatorio»;
distribuirlas con sigilo y celo; y por recompensa de tantas fatigas, de riesgos semejantes,
ganar un expresivo apretón de manos, una mirada de gratitud del proscrito.... Si el heroísmo
es cuestión de temperatura moral, Amparo, que se hallaba a cien grados, tal vez se dejara fusilar
por la causa sin decir esta boca es mía; y quién sabe si andando los tiempos no figuraría su
retrato al lado del de Mariana Pineda en los cuadros que representan a los mártires de la libertad....
Feliz o desgraciadamente, lo que ustedes quieran, que por eso no reñiremos, los tiempos eran
más cómicos que trágicos, y los loables esfuerzos de Amparo no le obtuvieron otra corona de
martirio sino el que en la Fábrica se prohibiese la lectura de diarios, manifiestos, proclamas
y hojas sueltas, y que a ella y a otras cuantas que pronunciaron vivas subversivos y cantaron
canciones alusivas a la Unión del Norte las suspendieran, como suele decirse, de empleo y sueldo.

-XVIII-

Tribuna del pueblo

El Círculo Rojo echa el resto; no se habla en Marineda sino del banquete que ofrece a los delegados
de Cantrabria y Cantabrialta. No tiene el Círculo Rojo socios tan opulentos como el Casino
de Industriales y la Sociedad de Amigos; pero sóbrale alma y desprendimiento, cuando la ocasión
lo requiere, para sangrarse los bolsillos, empeñarse, si es preciso, hasta los ojos y salir
con color y presentar una mesa que no le avergüence.

Llamada a conferenciar con el presidente del Círculo la «persona de buen gusto», que nunca
falta en los pueblos para dirigir las solemnidades, entró al punto en el desempeño de sus funciones,
y se dio tal maña, que en breve pudo negociar un empréstito de candeleros de plata, centros
de mesa, vajilla fina, mantelería adamascada y nueva, palilleros caprichosos y pureras sorprendentes.
Obtenido lo cual, el correveidile se frotó las manos asegurando al presidente que la mesa estaría
regiamente exornada.

--Regiamente, no señor--contestó el presidente algo fosco--. Republicanamente, dirá usted.

No quiso el organizador de la fiesta discutir el adverbio, y satisfecho de haber encontrado
los accesorios, se dio a buscar lo principal, o sea la comida. Bregando con fondistas y cafeteros,
consiguió combinar platos, vinos y helados del modo que le parecía más ortodoxo y elegante;
pero quiso su desdicha que a última hora el entusiasmo político lo echase todo a perder, instigando
a este bodegonero federal a enviar «la prueba» de sus vinos y a aquel hornero a remitir media
docena de robustas empanadas, que cayeron en el banquete como barbarismos en selecto trozo
de latinidad clásica. Menudencias que la Historia no registrará seguramente.

De propósito se empezó tarde la comida, y circulaban aún las dos sopas de hierbas y de puré,
cuando los camareros cerraron las maderas de las ventanas y encendieron las bujías de los candelabros
y los aparatos de gas. Viose entonces salir de las vaguedades del crepúsculo la mesa, la larga
mesa de sesenta cubiertos, con sus brillantes objetos de plata, sus ramos de flores simétricamente
colocados, sus altos ramilletes de dulce, sus temblorosas gelatinas, donde la luz rielaba como
en un lago. El presidente del Círculo tendió en derredor una mirada de orgullo. En verdad que
el aspecto del banquete era majestuoso. Imperaba en él todavía la reserva de los primeros momentos:
la gente comía con moderación y delicadeza, los camareros y mozos de servicio andaban discretamente
sin taconear, las cucharas producían leve música al tropezar con los platos, la virginidad
del mantel alegraba los ojos, y el vaho aperitivo de la sopa no desterraba del todo las fragantes
emanaciones de las rosas y claveles de los floreros. No obstante, al servirse la primer entrada
comenzaron a dialogar los vecinos de mesa, y el rumor creciente de las conversaciones envalentonó
a los mozos, que pisaron ya más recio.

Presidía la mesa el viejo de blanca barba, y la teatral nobleza de su figura completaba la
decoración. A su derecha tenía al presidente del Círculo y a su izquierda al orador de tenebrosa
faz, el que, según Amparo, «echaba términos» difíciles de entender. Seguían los demás delegados
por orden de respetabilidad, alternando con individuos de la Junta, de la Prensa, del partido.

Fue poco a poco acrecentándose el ruido de la charla y desatándose las lenguas, por donde rebosaba
ya la abundancia del corazón. El que, merced a su ancianidad venerable, podía ser llamado patriarca,
sonreía, aprobaba, estaba de acuerdo con todo el mundo, mientras el delegado tétrico y ceñudo
se las componía lo mejor posible para disputar. Al tercer plato disparó con bala rasa contra
la propiedad, el capital y la clase media, y el presidente del Círculo, patrón y dueño del
establecimiento, hubo de amoscarse; poco después fue el patriarca mismo el enojado, a causa
de no sé qué frases sobre el derecho de insurrección y el empleo de medios violentos y coercitivos.
Ninguno le parecía al patriarca lícito; en su concepto, el amor, la paz, la fraternidad, eran
las mejores bases para fundar la unión federativa, no sólo de Cantabria y de España, sino del
mundo. Cada cual alegaba sus razones, tratando de quimera el ajeno parecer; la discusión se
hacía general; intervenían en ella periodistas y delegados desde los más remotos extremos de
la mesa; alguien brindaba sin ser oído; personas de voz escasa exclamaban en tono suplicante:
«Pero oigan ustedes, señores... si ustedes oyesen una palabra...». Era en balde. El grupo central
se lo hablaba todo; de su confuso vocerío sólo se destacaban frases sueltas, airadas, empeñadas
en descollar. «Eso son utopías, utopías fatales.... No, es que le convenzo a usted con la historia
en la mano.... Sí, sí, hagámonos de miel.... La Revolución Francesa.... Era otro régimen, señores....
No confundamos los tiempos.... Está usted en un error.... Un hecho no es ley general.... Eso
lo ha dicho Pi.... Cantú es un reaccionario.... El bautismo de la sangre.... Horrores infecundos...».
Mientras duraba la polémica, los mozos no se entendían para pasar las fuentes del asado y para
escanciar el Champaña.... Uno de ellos se inclinó hacia el presidente y le dijo al oído no
sé qué... El presidente se levantó al punto y salió de la sala, volviendo a entrar presto seguido
de un grupo de mujeres.

Amparo lo capitaneaba. Penetró airosa, vestida con bata de percal claro y pañolón de Manila
de un rojo vivo que atraía la luz del gas, el rojo del trapo de los toreros. Su pañuelito de
seda era del mismo color, y en la diestra sostenía un enorme ramo de flores artificiales, rosas
de Bengala de sangriento matiz, sujetas con largas cintas lacre, donde se leía en letras de
oro la dedicatoria. Diríase que era el genio protector de aquel lugar, el duende del Círculo
Rojo; las notas del mantón, del pañuelo, de las flores y cintas se reunían en un vibrante acorde
escarlata, a manera de sinfonía de fuego.

Adelantose intrépida la muchacha levantando en alto el ramo y recogiendo, con el brazo libre,
el pañolón, cuyos flecos le llovían sobre las caderas. Y como el conspicuo disputador, dejando
su asiento, mostrase querer tomar el ex-voto que la muchacha ofrecía en aras de la diosa Libertad,
Amparo se desvió y fuese derecha al patriarca. El corro se abrió para dejarla paso.

La muchacha, sin soltar el ramo, miraba al viejo. Este, de pie, con su barba plateada y levemente
ondulosa como la de los ermitaños de tragedia, con su calva central guarnecida de abundantes
mechones canos, con su alta estatura, un tanto encorvada ya, se le figuraba la ancianidad clásica,
adornada de sus atributos, coronando la cima de los tiempos. Y el patriarca, a su vez, creía
ver en aquella buena moza el viviente símbolo del pueblo joven. Ambos formularon en sus adentros
el pensamiento de simpatía que les asaltaba.

--Este señor mete respeto lo mismo que un obispo--se dijo Amparo.

--Esta chica parece la Libertad--murmuró el patriarca.

Entre tanto la muchacha comenzaba su peroración. Temblábale la voz al principio; dos o tres
veces tuvo que pasarse la mano, yerta, por la frente húmeda, y sin saber lo que hacía accionó
con el ramo, cuyas cintas culebrearon como serpientes de llama, y carraspeó para deshacer un
nudo que le apretaba el galillo. Poco a poco, el rumor de la mesa, el cuchicheo de los convidados
más distantes, la luz de los mecheros de gas que le calentaba los sesos, el aroma de los vinos
y la espuma del Champaña, que aún parecía bullir en la iluminada atmósfera, la embriagaron,
y sintió fluir de sus labios las palabras y habló con afluencia, con desparpajo, sin cortarse
ni tropezar. Los convidados se daban al codo sonriendo, pronunciando entre dientes algún «¡bravo!,
¡muy bien!», al oír que las operarias republicanas de la Fábrica ofrecían aquel ramo a la Asamblea
de la Unión del Norte y al Círculo Rojo en prueba de que... y para manifestar cuanto... y como
testimonio de que los corazones que latían..., etc. El patriarca se colocaba la mano sobre
el pecho, se la llevaba a la boca con sincerísima complacencia, mientras el disputador, tieso
y serio, inclinaba de vez en cuando lentamente la cabeza en señal de aprobación. Por fin, la
oradora acabó su discurso entregando el ramo al patriarca y gritando: «¡Ciudadanos delegados,
salud y fraternidad!».

Tomó el viejo la ofrenda y la pasó al presidente, que se quedó con ella muy empuñada y sin
saber qué hacer. Confusas las compañeras de Amparo por el silencio repentino, miraban de reojo
hacia todas partes, maravillándose del esplendor de la mesa y algo sorprendidas de que el banquete
republicano fuese cosa de tanto orden y de que los delegados comiesen en vez de salvar la patria.
El patriarca se acercó a Amparo; sus mejillas arrugadas y marchitas tenían a la sazón sonrosados
los pómulos.

--Gracias, hijas...--tartamudeó cabeceando senilmente--. Gracias, ciudadanas.... Acércate,
tribuna del pueblo... que nos una un santo abrazo de fraternidad.... ¡Viva la tribuna del pueblo!
¡Viva la Unión del Norte!

--¡Viva!--balbució Amparo toda enternecida, ahogándose--. ¡Viva usted... muchos años!--Y el
viejo y la niña estaban a dos dedos de romper a llorar, y algunos de los convidados se reían
a socapa viendo aquel brazo paternal que rodeaba aquel cuello juvenil.

-XIX-

La Unión del Norte

¡Cuidado si hace calor!

Sobre el duro azul de un celaje no empañado por la más leve bruma, ondean las flámulas, colocadas
en mástiles a la veneciana alrededor del baluarte de la Puerta del Castillo, y sus gayos colores
no desdicen del júbilo radiante del cielo y de la estrepitosa y alegre multitud. Arcos y ondas
de follaje verde corren de mástil a mástil, disonando y contrastando con el tono cerúleo del
firmamento. En mitad del anfiteatro se alzaba el palco destinado a la Asamblea de la Unión,
con su tribuna al centro, y flanqueado de otros dos más bajos, pero mayores, destinados a las
comisiones del partido. Bien podía la Asamblea constitutiva de la Unión del Norte de la costa
ibérica--que así se nombraba en sus documentos oficiales--ocupar oronda y satisfecha el palco
presidencial: pocas sesiones y breves horas le habían bastado para sentar las bases del gran
contrato unionista federativo; actividad gloriosa, sobre todo comparándola con la flema y machaconería
de aquellas holgazanas de Cortes Constituyentes, que tardaban meses en redactar un código fundamental
y definitivo para la nación.

Caminaba impetuosa hacia el anfiteatro la comitiva, compuesta del partido y juventud republicana,
de mucha chiquillería, de los comités rurales, de los delegados y de todo fiel cristiano que
movido de curiosidad quiso injerirse en la procesión. Apresuradamente, como si fuese un ser
único animado por un solo soplo vital, y tuviese por voz la banda de música que aturdía el
ambiente con himnos y más himnos, adelantábase la palpitante masa humana; y empujadas por la
compacta muchedumbre, las banderas, coronadas de flores, vacilaban cual si estuviesen ebrias,
y tan pronto daban traspiés y se inclinaban acá o acullá, como tornaban a erguirse rectas y
altivas. Y las casas del tránsito parecían contemplar el cuadro y entender su asunto, y de
unas llovían flores, ramos, coronas, y otras, en menor número, cerradas a piedra y lodo, dijérase
que fruncían el ceño y se ponían hurañas y serias al sentir el roce de las olas revolucionarias.

Cuando estas llegaron a estrellarse en el baluarte, se esparcieron y derramaron por doquiera.
El gentío trepó a las escaleras, cabalgó en el caballete de los bastiones, invadió los palcos
de los comisionados, y se extendió coronando las alturas vecinas; por los troncos de los mástiles
se encaramó más de un granuja, resuelto a dominar la situación. Penetró majestuosamente en
su palco la Asamblea, y así que los delegados ocuparon sus asientos, el tumulto se apaciguó
como por magia, y cerca de veinte mil personas guardaron silencio religioso. Sólo se oyó salir
de algún rincón del anchuroso escenario, el melancólico grito que pregonaba: «¡Agua de limón
fría, barquillos, agua, azucarillos, agua!». Dos fotógrafos, situados en el lugar oportuno
para tomar la vista, enfocaban cubriéndose la cabeza con el paño de bayeta verde, y sus máquinas
parecían los ojos de la Historia contemplando la escena. Casi se oiría el volar de una mosca,
sobre todo en las cercanías del palco presidencial.

Procediose a la firma y lectura del contrato de Unión. Desde lejos se veía en el palco una
agrupación de cabezas, entre las cuales se destacaba la negra cabellera melodramática del disputador
y sus quevedos de oro, y la barba nívea del Patriarca, resplandeciente al sol como la de Jehová
en los cuadros bíblicos. Estaban Baltasar y Borrén apoyados en un lienzo de parapeto, de pie
sobre un sillar de piedra, lo cual les permitía ver cuanto ocurriese. Ambos prestaban atención
suma, comprendiendo que presenciaban un episodio interesante del drama político español.

--Aquí se incuba algo, hombre--exclamó Borrén inclinándose hacia su amigo.

--¡Claro que se incuba! ¡El desbarajuste universal... y el picadillo que van a hacer de España
esos señores!

--Hombre, dice que no.... Dice que lo que desean es confederarnos, para que estemos más uniditos
que antes... ¿no ve usted que esto se llama la Unión?

--¡Sí, sí, corte usted un dedo y péguelo después con saliva!

--A bien que una nación no es ninguna naranja para hacerse cuarterones tan fácilmente.... ¿Sabe
usted lo que me contaron de ese viejecito... del Patriarca? Mire usted, yo me explico que sea
republicano... ¡había cosas en aquellos tiempos antiguos! ¡Era el segundo de una casa rica...
poderosa, hombre! El mayorazgo arrampló con todo, ¿eh?, mimos y hacienda, y a él le quedó un
palomar viejo y la memoria de las azotainas.... Otro se hubiera hecho misántropo... Él se hizo
filántropo y luego progresista, y luego federal... y es un bienaventurado que abraza a todo
el mundo, y oye misa, y es incapaz de hacer daño a nadie... acá inter nos le tengo por algo
chocho....

--¿Y aquel moreno... el de los quevedos?

--¡Ah! ese... ese dicen que es de los que quieren perder las colonias y salvar los principios:
hombre de línea recta, de geometría.... Según Palacios, que lo conoce, la ecuación entre la
lógica y el absurdo: no en balde es ingeniero. Si para lograr sus ideales tuviese que desollarnos...
¡pobre pellejo!

--¿Y si tuviese que desollarse a sí mismo?

--¡Cáspita!, de la epidermis ajena a la propia.... Con todo, no seamos escépticos, hombre.
Allí tiene usted a aquel otro... al del bigote negro... el que está a la izquierda del Patriarca.
Pues mire usted, hombre, que le ha costado ya dinero y disgustos esta mojiganga política...
emigrado, encausado, maltratado... y se libró de ir a las Marianas... no sé cómo.... Hay humor
para todo en este mundo sublunar.... ¡Y decir que cuando Dios produce chicas como esa se ocupen
en politiquear los muchachos!

Al pronunciar estas palabras señalaba Borrén a Amparo, cuyos rojos atavíos la distinguían del
círculo femenino que la rodeaba.

--Pues esa chica aún politiquea más que los barbudos... ¿no sabe usted...?

Y el incidente del banquete fue comentado, desmenuzado, acribillado por las dos bocas masculinas,
que lo adornaron con festones satíricos. Entre tanto se leía el contrato de la Unión, y a pesar
de que el sol no estaba en el zenit ni mucho menos, la gente arracimada y prensada producía
una temperatura insufrible, y se oían exclamaciones de este jaez: «Nos morimos.--Nos asfixiamos.--¡Cuándo
vendrá un poco de fresco!--Pero, hombre, no nos estruje usté.--Ave María, qué bárbaro.--Estese
usté quieto.--Pues si no ve, fastidiarse: ¿sa figurao que vemos los demás? --¡Tan siquiera
puede uno meter la mano en el bolsillo para sacar un triste pañuelo!--Cuidado con el reloj,
palpa si lo tienes». Y la voz del lector del Contrato volaba por cima del mar de cabezas, y
las palabras «garantías sacrosantas... dogmas de libertad... derechos invulnerables... ideales
benditos... pueblo honrado y libre...» se dilataban en el cálido y sereno ambiente. Una lluvia
de flores vino, de improviso, a oscurecerlo, y multitud de blancas palomas fueron lanzadas
a él, abatiendo al punto el vuelo con aletear trabajoso, y cayendo sobre la muchedumbre, entorpecidas
de tener tanto tiempo ligadas las patas. Un estruendoso cubo de cohetes de lucería salió bufando
en todas direcciones; retumbó la música; hubo un minuto de gritos, vivas, estruendo y confusión,
y nadie reparó en que un pobre viejo, un barquillero, salía del recinto mitad arrastrado y
mitad en brazos de dos hombres. «Le dio un accidente», decían al verlo pasar, sin añadir otro
comentario.

-XX-

Zagal y zagala

Y del accidente se murió aquella noche misma, sin confesión, sin recobrar los sentidos. ¿Fue
el sol abrasador? Mil veces le cayó verticalmente sobre el cráneo al señor Rosendo en sus épocas
de vida militar, y vamos, que el de la isla de Cuba pica en regla.... ¿Fue el haber vuelto
a manejar las tenazas y a elaborar barquillos para el extraordinario consumo de aquellos días
solemnes? ¿Fue, como dijeron algunas comadres, el orgullo de ver a su hija tan elocuente y
bizarra, y tan agasajada por los señores de la Asamblea? Quédese para la posteridad el arduo
fallo, si bien parece infundada la última suposición, por cuanto el señor Rosendo, lejos de
manifestar complacencia cuando la chica se metía en semejantes trifulcas, rompiera pocos días
antes su mutismo para decirle cosas muy al alma sobre eso de buscar tres pies al gato y perder
su colocación por locuras. El servicio militar había formado de tal suerte el carácter del
viejo, que la insubordinación era para él el más feo delito, y su divisa, obediencia pasiva,
automática; así es que amenazó a Amparo, poniendo los ojos fieros y la voz tartajosa, con romperle
una costilla si volvía a leer periódicos en la Fábrica. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01408</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>127878</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19434</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Is that the girl deserved it all: the light of the brazier discovered
his face animated, his eyes lit rechispeantes, and showed the curly hair, undone by agitation
of the walk, and floating in fancy threads on his forehead, shoulders and neck. Baltasar and
erased in American and fungi, were placed between the jostling crowd and perhaps he whispered
to one hundred thousand blunders, but it was not for bagpipes CAFTA is that was not in the
mood for compliments Amparo, being solely owned by the fervor political.

He felt overwrought, feverish, in days so memorable. Everywhere he pretended his fevered imagination
dangers, struggles, hatched plots to stifle black freedom. Of fixed-fixed the Madrid government
already knew such time that cigarette marinedina performed a heroic unprecedented efforts to hasten
the triumph of federal, and with such thoughts latíale Amparo his little heart and swelled the
bosom agitated. Amid the vulgarity and dullness of daily life and the monotony of work always
identical to itself, such hazards revolutionary were poetry, novel, adventure, blue sky through which
to fly with wings of gold. His fantasy uneducated and spirited was tending them. The emphatic phrases
of the articles, the redundant periods of speeches rang in his ears like the refrain of the waltz
in the child dancer. That arrival of individuals of the Assembly of the Union was to safeguard
what would the Apostles for a people who hear about the Gospel and soon saw arrive on its
shores to announce makers.

Amparo by certain thing was approaching when observed with a fact worthy of Memory: craved,
without declaring itself, using the forces of self-denial and sacrifice that there are latent
in the soul of the woman of the people. Sacrifice for any of those men who came from Cantabria to
predict the redemption immolate himself for the oldest, by uglier, paying capital and some
extraordinary service! Knocking on your door to high at night, say breathlessly that "here comes
the police 'and that is hidden; hidden alleys accompany him to a safe hiding place, put him
in a few hands dollars saved by dint of rolling cigarettes, receiving instead a bundle of proclamations
to divide the next day, with the caveat that "if they are caught, can be counted soul in Purgatory";
distributed by stealth and zeal, and as a reward for so many hardships, risks similar win an expressive
handshake, a look of gratitude for the outlawed .... If heroism temperature is a matter of
moral, Amparo, who was a hundred degrees, perhaps stop shooting for the cause without saying
a peep, and who knows if time would not be included walking her side portrait of Mariana Pineda in
the tables represent the martyrs of freedom .... Happy or unfortunately, what you want, that's
why no reñiremos, times were more comic than tragic, and the laudable efforts of Amparo not won another
crown but martyrdom in the factory were prevented from reading newspapers, manifestos, proclamations
and leaflets, and that she and a few others who spoke and sang live subversive songs related
to the suspended Northern Union, as they say, employment and salary.

-XVIII-

Village Tribune

The Red Circle check the rest, it is not spoken, but the banquet Marineda offers delegates
of Cantrabria and Cantabrialta. You do not have the Red Circle partners as opulent as the Casino
Manufacturers and the Society of Friends, but sobral soul and detachment, as occasion required,
bleed the pockets, pledged, if necessary, to the eyes and leave with
color and present a table that does not embarrass you.

Call to confer with President of the Circle "person of good taste," never needed in the villages
to conduct the formalities, came to the point where the performance of their duties, and gave such skill
that may soon negotiate a loan of silver candlesticks, shopping table, fine china, damask tablecloths
and fresh, whimsical toothpick and amazing cigar.

Which received the go-between rubbed his hands ensuring that the
board chairman would royally ornamented.

- Regia, no sir - said the
president somewhat gloomy -.

Republican, you say.

He declined the organizer of the festival to discuss the adverb, and pleased to have found accessories,
was to seek the main, or food. Coping with joggers and coffee, managed to combine food, wine and ice
cream as it seemed more orthodox and elegant; but he wanted his unhappiness at the last minute
political enthusiasm throw it all away, prompting this federal bodegonero to send 'proof'
of its wines and one baker to send half robust dozen pies, which
fell at the banquet as barbarians in selected piece of classical Latin.

Trifles that history will surely record.

Purpose began food late, and still circulated two herbal soup and puree, when the waiters closed
timber windows and lit the candles on the chandeliers and gas appliances. Then saw himself out of
the vagaries of twilight the table, the long sixty-covered table, with its bright silver, their
bouquets of flowers symmetrically placed, tall bunches of sweet, his trembling jellies, where
the light shimmered as in a lake. The president handed Circle around a look of pride. In truth the
appearance of the banquet was magnificent. Still prevailed in the book the first time: people ate in
moderation and delicacy, bartenders and waiters walked quietly no heels, spoons produced slight
music-over dishes, virginity Tablecloth happy eyes, and taste of the soup fog not totally banished
the fragrant fumes of roses and carnations in the vases. However, to serve the first entry neighbors
began to talk table, and the growing buzz of conversation emboldened the waiters, who walked and
more stout.

Head of the table the old white-bearded, and his noble theatrical figure completed the decoration.
To his right was the president of the Circle and left the speaker's dark face, which, according
to Amparo, "threw terms" hard to understand.

Still other delegates order of respectability, alternating with members of the Board, the press, the
party.

Was gradually heightening the noise and sparking talk of languages, where overflowing and abundance
of the heart. Which, thanks to venerable old age, could be called patriarch, smiling, approving,
agreeing with everyone, while the grim and frowning delegate they are composed his best to
play. The third dish rasa bullet fired against property, capital and the middle class, and the president
of the Circle, skipper and owner facility had to be piqued and shortly afterwards the patriarch
himself was the angry, because I know not what phrases on the right of insurrection and the use
of violent and coercive means. None seemed to the lawful patriarch, in his opinion, love, peace,
fraternity, were the best basis to establish the federal union, not only of Cantabria and Spain,
but the world. Each claimed their reasons, trying to look like the alien Chimera, the discussion
was general involved in her journalists and delegates from the farthest ends the table, someone offered
without being heard, people in low voice exclaimed in a pleading tone: "But hey, gentlemen ...
if you hear a word ...». It was in vain. The core group it was spoken all, of his confused clamor
only highlighted phrases, angry, determined in excel. "That's utopia, utopias fatal .... No, I will convince
you with the story in hand .... Yes, yes, let us honey .... The French Revolution .... It was
another scheme, gentlemen .... Do not confuse the times .... Are you an error .... A fact is no general
law .... That Pi has said .... Cantu is a reactionary .... The baptism of blood .... Infertile
horrors ...». While the controversy lasted, the waiters did not understand to pass the sources
of the roast and pour the champagne .... One of them leaned over the chair and whispered to him not
I know what ... The president stood up to the point and left the
room, followed quickly reentering a group of women.

Under the captains. Penetrated gracefully, wearing a cotton gown and shawl clear Manila bright red
light that attracted the gas, the red rag of the bullfighters. His handkerchief Silk was the
same color, and the right hand holding a huge bouquet of artificial flowers, roses Bengal bloody
hue, covered with long sealing tape, which read in letters the dedication gold. One might say that
was the protecting genius of the place, Elf Circle Red, the white
shawl, scarf, flowers and ribbons gathered in a vibrant chord Scarlet,
like a symphony of fire.

Intrepid girl came forward holding up the field and picking up, with the free arm the shawl, whose
fringes he rained down on the hips.

And as the conspicuous debater, leaving his seat, shew want to take the ex-voto offered the girl
for the sake of the goddess Liberty Amparo swerved and went right to the patriarch. The circle
opened to let pass.

The girl, still holding the field, watching the old man. This, standing with his silver beard and
slightly undulating like the hermits of tragedy, with his bald head
adorned with abundant central tufts es, with his tall, slightly stooped
and, he imagined the old classical adorned with his attributes, crowning
the top of the times.

And the patriarch, in turn, thought see that good-looking the living
symbol of young people.

Both made in his mind thinking of sympathy assaulted them.

- This
guy gets respect as well as a bishop - is said Amparo.

- This girl
seems to Freedom - murmured the patriarch.

Meanwhile, the girl began his peroration. Temblábale voice at the beginning, two or three sometimes
had to move his hand, motionless, his forehead damp, and not knowing what had triggered to the branch,
whose films wriggle like snakes of flame, and coughed to break a knot that tightened the uvula.
Gradually, the rumor of the table, the whisper of the guests more distant, the light from gas
burners that heated the brains, the aroma of wine and Champagne foam, which still seemed to budge
on the bright atmosphere, the drunk, and felt flowing from his lips the words and spoke with affluence,
with aplomb, without cutting or trip. The guests were given the elbow, smiling, speaking through his
teeth a "bravo!, Very good! "To hear that Republican operatives Factory branch offered to the
Assembly that North Union and the Red Circle to test ... and to show respect ... as testimony
that the hearts that beat ... etc. The patriarch's hand was placed on chest, carried it to his
mouth most sincere pleasure, while the debater, stiff and serious, occasionally bowed his head
slowly in approval. Finally, the She ended her speech giving the bouquet to the patriarch and
shouting: "Citizens delegates health and fraternity!

".

Offering the old man took and passed the president, who stayed with her very fist and without what
to do. Amparo companions confused by the sudden silence, looked askance all directions, wondering
the splendor of the table and somewhat surprised that the banquet Republican order was a matter
of both delegates and eat them instead of saving the country.

The patriarch approached Amparo, his cheeks were wrinkled and withered at the time rosy cheekbones.

-
Thanks, nodding stammered daughters senile ...-- -. Thank you, citizens .... Closer, tribune of the
people ... us a fraternal embrace a saint .... Viva la tribune of
the people!

North Union Viva!

- Viva! - All tenderly Amparo stammered, choking -.

Whether you live ... many years! - And old and the girl were two
fingers to break to mourn, and some of the guests laughed Socapa to
see that paternal arm around her neck that youth.

-XIX-

North Union

Beware
if it's hot!

On the hard blue clouds of the horizon is not tainted by the slightest mist, waving streamers, placed
in the Venetian masts around the stronghold of the Puerta del Castillo, and their colors Gayoso
do not detract from the joy radiating from the sky and the loud and cheerful crowd. Bows and waves
green foliage are mast to mast, Dishon and contrasted with the tone of cerulean sky. Amphitheater
in the middle of the stage stood for the Assembly of the Union with its platform to the center
and flanked by two lower, but higher, for the party committees. Well might the Constituent Assembly
of the Union's North Coast Iberian - so named in their official documents - take the stage plump
and satisfied Presidential session and few brief hours had sufficed to lay the foundations of
the great federal union contract; glorious activity, especially compared with phlegm and machaconería
those lazy Constituent Cortes, which took months to write a basic code and final for the nation.

Impetuously walked into the amphitheater the delegation, composed
of the Republican party and youth, a lot of small fry, rural committees,
delegates and all Christian faithful moved out of curiosity wanted
to interfere in the procession.

Hastily, as if it were a being only animated by a single breath of life, and voice had the band that
stunned the environment with more hymns and anthems, overtook the pulsating mass of humanity,
and driven by the compact crowd, flags, wreaths, hesitated as if he were drunk, and as soon
gave stumbled and swayed hither and thither, like tornadoes to stand up straight haughty.
And the houses seem to be talking traffic picture and understand your case, and some rained
flowers, bouquets, wreaths, and others in smaller numbers, closed and bolted, we said they frowned
and put on sullen and serious as he felt the touch of revolutionary waves.

When these came crashing into the bulwark, spread and spilled everywhere. The crowd climbed ladders,
rode on the bridge of the bastions, invaded the boxes commissioners,
and spread topping the neighboring heights, for the trunks of the
masts climbed more than a rogue, bent on dominating the situation.

Majestically entered Assembly his box, and so the delegates took their seats, the tumult subsided
as if by magic, and about twenty thousand people were silent religious. Only be heard out in
some corner of the wide scenario, the melancholy cry proclaiming: "Lemon Water cold, wafers, water,
sugar, water! ". Two photographers, located in the right place to take the view, focused covering
his head with green baize cloth, and their machines seemed the eyes of history, watching the
scene. Almost hear the flight of a fly especially near the presidential box.

They proceeded to the signing and reading of the Union contract. From a distance it looked
in the box a grouping of heads, including the black hair stood out from the debater melodramatic
and gold pince-nez and the Patriarch's snowy beard, shining in the sun like the Jehovah's in
biblical paintings.

Baltasar and Borren were supported on a canvas of parapet, standing on a stone chair, which
allowed them to see what is happening. Both paid attention short, realizing that witnessed an interesting
incident of the Spanish political drama.

- Here is incubated something, man - said Borren leaning toward his friend.

- Obviously, you incubated!

The universal mess ... and hash that will make Spain these gentlemen!

- Man, says no .... Said that they wish to confederate, to make us more uniditos than before ...
Do not you see that this is called the Union?

- Yes, yes, you cut a finger with saliva and then paste!

- A well that a nation is no orange paneled so easily done .... You know what you told me of this
old man ... Patriarch? Look, I explained that it Republican ... There were things in those ancient
times! It was the second in a rich house ... powerful, man! The arrampló mayorazgo all, huh?,
Mimes and finance, and he was a old pigeon of the flogging memory .... Another had been made
misanthropic ... He became then progressive philanthropist, and then federal ... and is a blessed
that embraces all the world, and hear Mass, and is incapable of harming
anyone ... I have him here between ourselves for something pussy ....

-
And that dark ... that of eyeglasses?

- Ah! that ... say is that
those who want to lose the colonies and save the principles: straight
man, geometry .... According to Palacios, who knows, the equation
between logic and absurdity: not for nothing is an engineer.

If to achieve their ideals had to skin them ... Poor skin!

- And
if I had skinned himself?

- Caspita!, The epidermis outside the own
.... However, we are not skeptics, man.

There you to that other ... the black mustache ... which is to the left of the Patriarch. Well
look, man, that has cost him money and aggravation this political masquerade ... emigre, accused,
abused ... and escaped to go to the Mariana ... I do not know how .... There is humor for everything
in this sublunary world .... And to say that when God brings about
girls like that deal politicking in the boys!

In pronouncing these words pointed Borren Amparo, whose red dresses will distinguish the female circle
around her.

- Well, that girl still politicking rather than the bearded ... Do not you know ...?

And the incident of the banquet was discussed, shredded, pierced by the two men's mouths, it adorned
with festoons satirical.

Meanwhile, there was the Union contract, and despite the sun was
not far from the zenith, people clustered and pressed produced unbearable
temperatures, and you could hear cries of this ilk: "We die .-- .--
When we stifle come a little cool! - But, man, Nah, you squeeze us
.-- Hail Mary, how awful .-- Estes Nah, you still .-- For if you do
not see, annoyed: sa figurae we see others? - So even can reach into
a pocket for a handkerchief sad! - Watch the clock if you have felt.

" And the voice of the reader of the Contract was flying atop the sea of ??heads and the words "sacrosanct
guarantees ... tenets of freedom ... invulnerable rights ... ideal blessed ... honest and free
people ... "dilate in warm and serene environment. A rain flowers came, unexpectedly, to obscure,
and many white doves were released to it, lowering the point the laborious flapping flight, and fell over
the crowd, hampered bound to have long legs. A roaring rocket bucket came snorting Luceria in
all directions, echoing the music, there was a minute of screaming, live, noise and confusion,
and no one noticed that an old man, a waffle, half dragged out of the enclosure and half in
the arms of two men. "He gave an accident," they said as he passed, without adding another
comment.

-XX-

Lad and lass

And the accident, died that same evening, without confession, without regaining the senses.
Was the scorching sun? A thousand times he fell vertically on the skull to Mr. Rosendo in their
times of military life, and we, the island of Cuba pica in order
.... Was to have become to handle wafer chuck prepare for the extraordinary
rate of consumption of those days solemn?

Was it, as some gossips said, the pride of seeing his daughter so
eloquently and bizarre, and so feted by the lords of the Assembly?

Stay for posterity the hard failure, although the latter assumption
seems unfounded, because Mr. Rosendo, far from express satisfaction
when the girl got into such quarrels, broke a few days before his
silence to tell things to the soul searching about it three feet and
lose the cat placement by madness.

Military service had been formed in such a way the character of old, that insubordination was
for him the ugliest crime and its currency, passive obedience, automatic, and so he threatened Amparo,
rolling her eyes and voice fierce stammer, to break a rib if you would read newspapers in
the factory.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>