<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09395</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>50122</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24680</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
(pág. 13). Como no se hallan aquí incluidos los católicos de Estados Unidos, el Buró de Sanidad
debe recordar que tales ciudadanos con los no católicos que habitan Filipinas, no gozan de
la protección antipestífera de San Roque.

La superstición y el crimen

En su notable estudio sobre la Antropología Criminal en Filipinas, dice el Doctor Sixto de
los Ángeles (pág. 119): "La fácil credulidad, fomentada por el sobrecultivo del fanatismo religioso,
ha constituído desde un principio y hasta el presente uno de los defectos, por desgracia bastante
extendidos aún, entre los naturales del país * * *. Amante de sus tradiciones y hábitos heredados,
y falta de suficientes oportunidades para adquirir conocimientos, la masa popular filipina
tiene que aferrarse, como es lógico y natural, a sus creencias, las que, por no requerir ningún
esfuerzo para su comprehensión, se agravan y se arraigan de una manera espontánea en su mente.
Como lo demuestran nuestros anales judiciales, la superstición ocupa una categoría notable
entre los factores de la criminalidad en el país." Las supersticiones a que alude el Dr. Ángeles
no son tan sólo las de la antigua gentilidad de los filipinos que los misioneros, después de
más de tres siglos, no han logrado destruir completamente. Las supersticiones a que se refiere
en esta conferencia son las traídas por esos mismos misioneros y que han logrado fácilmente
hacer penetrar en la conciencia filipina, dispuesta naturalmente a la credulidad, por medio
de la propaganda eficaz y generosamente esparcida en las novenas y otros libritos llamados
de devoción.

Como hasta la llegada de los americanos la enseñanza en Filipinas fué siempre y exclusivamente
religiosa, y dirigida por los sacerdotes romanos, la persistencia de antiguas supersticiones
son una demostración del fracaso de la educación religiosa. Tendrían por excusa los misioneros
culpar a la rudeza invencible del filipino, que podríamos admitir por cortesía y para evitar
discusiones. Pero lo grave no es que ellos no pudieron quitar algo de la supuesta cabeza dura
del indio, sino el tremendo caudal de supersticiones que durante más de tres siglos, esos misioneros
han hecho penetrar en esa misma cabeza con tan grave perjuicio para su mentalidad y su moralidad.

Falta de voluntad

El pecador falto de voluntad para refrenar sus malas obras le dice a Jesús, lavándose las manos
en la intervención divina y dando testimonio de la falta de sentido de responsabilidad: "¿Es
posible, dulcísimo Salvador de las almas, que convirtiendo tantos cada día, solo á la pérdida
de la mía te has de demostrar insensible?" (Pág. 13.) Esta es una parte de una oración compuesta
nada menos que por el Sumo Pontífice Gregorio VII, en su Ejercicio Devoto de la Pasión de Cristo
(Manila, 1905).

También se dice a la Virgen: "Limpiad, Vírgen Inmaculada, mi corazón de todo pecado, y echad
de mí todo aquello que desagrade a vuestros ojos purísimos. Purgad mi alma de los amores y
afectos terrenos." (Págs. 10-11; Corona Franciscana--de la Virgen María. Manila, 1902.)

Por la intercesión de San Francisco el devoto pide a Dios que: "Yo sujete en un todo mis desordenadas
pasiones, potencias y sentidos," para que "yo pueda reducir mis pensamientos, medir mis palabras
y dirigir mis obras a la mayor perfección," y "que te dignes ablandar la dureza de mi corazón."
(Págs. 18, 20 y 21 de la novena a San Francisco de Asís. Manila, 1899.)

Asustado de las maquinaciones de Satanás, el devoto a Santa Filomena le pide (pág. 23, Nov.),
"que alcances del Señor el que quiebre más y más las fuerzas de mis contrarios, los demonios,
y que me salve a pesar mío."

Se invoca el auxilio de Santa Filomena diciendo (pág. 25, Nov.): "Haz que yo también sea casto,
según mi estado, y que mi boca no profiera ninguna de aquellas palabras que según San Pablo,
no deben nombrarse entre los fieles."

A Santa Ana, Madre de María, le dice su devoto: "Interesaos, pues, Santa mía, para que se me
conceda paciencia en mis adversidades, tolerancia en las injurias, y en todo un ánimo tranquilo
* * * (Novena, pág. 1; Manila, 1893). También se le dirige el siguiente ruego; "Empeñaos, pues,
Santa mía, con vuestro sagrado nieto Jesús para que se quite de nuestro corazón todo desafecto
y mala voluntad que perdonemos por amor de Dios todas las injurias * * *."

No es posible cultivar el sentido de la dignidad, ni del respeto de sí mismo cuando se diseminan
doctrinas como las que resultan de los siguientes ejemplos, en la novena de Santa Rosa de Lima:

"Llevada de su humildad, hacía que una criada le pisara los labios," (pág. 10). "Amaba más
los desprecios que las mundanas honras * * *." (pág. 102), y "deseaba con tanta eficacia que
los otros la tuvieran por la cosa más vil del mundo, que aseguraba merecía estar en el infierno
y que ese era su propio lugar por sus pecados. Si alguno mostraba no creerla y que la tenía
por inocente, Nadie me conoce a mí, añadía, yo sola sé lo que soy" (pág. 11). "Oyendo una vez
que la alababan de virtuosa, lo sintió tanto que quedó desmayada" (pág. 11).

En una oración a Santa Filomena (Novena, pág. 16) se dice a la Santa, pidiéndole su protección:
"Mis pecados me han vuelto de poco menor que los ángeles, muy inferior a las bestias, pues
que éstas no olvidan el pesebre de su amo, y a su modo agradecen la comida y yo me he olvidado
de la casa de Dios * * *." No es tan sólo desprecio de sí mismo lo que resulta de tales consideraciones,
sino la falta de lógica en atribuir a la gratitud de las bestias su vuelta al pesebre del amo,
cuando es claro que el móvil que les conduce es sencillamente el hambre.

La ira de Dios

Los fenómenos naturales se miran por la ignorancia como manifestaciones de la ira divina, que
no llegarían a producirse si alguien, en la humanidad, no la provocara por medio de su conducta.
Santo Tomás de Aquino, que con razón es considerado como el hombre más científico de su época,
creía firmemente que los truenos, los rayos y las tempestades fueron tan sólo manifestaciones
punitivas de Dios irritado contra los hombres. "De su temor a Dios, nacía en el Santo Doctor
un género de miedo a los truenos y tempestades, con que como reverente hijo, temía ver airado
el rostro del Padre, recelando no fueran aquellas tempestades provocadas por sus culpas." (Milicia
Angélica, Manila, 1907, pág. 21.)

El miedo ciego de Santo Tomás le hacía concebir una justicia ciega de la Divinidad porque por
su culpa Dios desencadenaba una tempestad y prodigaba el rayo que naturalmente dañaba y molestaba
a un gran número de personas que sufrían por causa de las culpas del Santo. Para el sencillo
creyente, cuando el Santo sabio pensaba y creía de tal manera, no habrá motivo para rechazar
su explicación, mucho menos sospechar siquiera que lo de castigar justos con pecadores no es
obra de justicia ni siquiera de sentido común.

Ausencia de lógica

La mentalidad lógica no se puede desenvolver cuando se fomenta y cultiva el absurdo, principalmente
cuando se le presenta cubierto con el falso barniz de religión, cuando se funda en la superstición
de un carácter totalmente pueril y simple.

En la vida de San Vicente Ferrer, impresa en su novena, se refieren los siguientes milagros,
y no hay duda alguna que quien cree en ellos, no puede de ninguna manera cultivar las funciones
de su inteligencia.

"En Valencia, un criado del conde de Faura, que nació sordo y sin lengua, estuvo así muchos
años; y adorando un día la reliquia de San Vicente, curó de la sordera, le nació la lengua
y habló en adelante" (pág. 17).

"Una mujer dió a luz un pedazo de carne sin figura humana. Ofrecióle a San Vicente haciendo
decir una misa, y a la Epístola ya tenía cabeza, al Evangelio brazos, al Consagrar piernas,
y al fin se hallaron con un bello niño. Lo mismo ocurrió a otra señora de Toledo" (pág. 34).

"En Lisboa vivía corrida una dama por ser tan fea, que era la risa de los que la veían. Acudió
a San Vicente y amaneció una mañana muy hermosa y agraciada, de que resultó ser tan devotas
a San Vicente las damas de Lisboa que no las exceden las de Valencia" (pág. 37).

"Un mercader partió a una feria y entretanto su mujer cometió una fragilidad por lo que quedó
* * *. Se encomendó arrepentida a San Vicente y el Santo salió al camino por donde volvía el
marido con unos caballos, poniéndose allí a espantarlos por medio de una capa y los dispersó.
Entonces el marido perdió su tiempo en reunir sus caballos, de modo que, cuando llegó a su
casa, ya había tenido tiempo su esposa de salir de su cuidado, librándose de las consecuencias
de su falta." Así se refiere con la mayor naturalidad un acto inmoral y grotesco, en que sale
sin razón ni causa castigado el marido inocente, y el Santo ejecuta con su capa una picardía
digna tan sólo de un granuja del arroyo.

Se dice que San Ramón toma tal interés en las desdichas y penas de sus devotos y es tan extremadamente
compasivo "que han sudado sus imágenes por la aflicción de los devotos" (pág. 12). "Una imagen
del Santo sudó tan manifiestamente al tiempo que su devota padecía, que se manchó el velo con
que se cubría; y algunos pañolitos mojados en el sudor aliviaban maravillosamente los dolores
de cabeza" (pág. 21).

San Roque tiene el poder de evitar la propagación de las epidemias. "Su protección es la que
nos preserva de la peste y de otras muchas dolencias, que teniendo su origen en la corrupción
del aire que nos había de conservar la vida, nos causa la muerte" (pág. 3).

El colmo de lo absurdo

¿Es acaso posible inventar ni suponer mayores absurdos que los hasta aquí mencionados? Sin
embargo, para no alargar esta conferencia sólo presento un pequeño número de casos citados
a montones en estos pequeños opúsculos repartidos con profusión en nuestro pueblo. ¿Qué lógica,
qué razonamiento podemos esperar de cerebros nutridos con tales absurdos, alimentados con patrañas
de carácter tan pueril que no se comprende que hayan sido narrados por hombres de simple sentido
común?

"El colchón en que murió San Vicente quedó con virtud de hacer milagros; pues acostándose en
él en diversas ocasiones más de 400 enfermos de diferentes accidentes, todos lograron la salud"
(pág. 32).

Una vez que San Antonio de Padua predicaba en la playa, ocurrió que "salieron del agua los
peces a quienes predicó y que le oyeron atentos." Ningún devoto pone en duda la salida de los
peces ni tampoco se interesa en resolver los problemas de física, fisiología, lingüística y
principalmente de lógica de semejante acontecimiento, pero así lo afirma la novena al Santo
(pág. 20).

Prolongaría innecesariamente esta conferencia si mencionara todos los absurdos consignados
en las Novenas de los cuales tengo un amplio caudal que constituye una documentación positiva
utilísima para la historia de la superstición que apenas desfloro aquí. Con lo dicho hay bastante
para explicar el origen de la inmoralidad, la verdadera causa de la predisposición al vicio,
la ausencia del sentido de responsabilidad, la explicación natural de ese carácter incomprensible
formado de una mezcla de sentimientos encontrados que los misioneros han atribuido al filipino,
indio, español y chino, influidos todos por el espíritu nocivo que informa toda esa literatura
completamente perturbadora de la razón. Ella y no la educación laica es la responsable del
fenómeno.

No vengo formulando teorías ni emito hipótesis caprichosas. Ante un auditorio como el que tengo
el honor de hablar, necesito pesar el valor de mis palabras y de mis juicios. Por tal motivo
he traído hechos, he citado textos repitiendo las propias palabras, no de la literatura profana
constituida por los Corridos anónimos cuya perjudicial influencia es perfectamente conocida,
sino de los textos auténticos de novenas autorizadas por la censura eclesiástica por no contener
cosa contraria a la sana moral, como se dice en las licencias para imprimir.

Ni por un momento he tratado de mezclar la religión en mi crítica ni tampoco está en mis manos
variar las consecuencias que se deducen de los hechos mencionados en las novenas, que es la
literatura responsable de un estado de mentalidad pueril, absolutamente inadecuada para la
inteligencia de la moral, compuesta de elementos paralizadores y no de progreso.

La moral no es más que el triunfo sobre sí mismo mediante el cual el hombre hace lo que debe
y no lo que quiere. En el hombre inmoral no hay lucha entre dos tendencias, una hacia el mal,
otra hacia el bien. Solamente hay una tendencia instintiva: ningún freno racional que se oponga.
¿Qué dominio de sí mismo tiene quien para refrenar su costumbre y pronunciar palabras sucias
y obscenas recurre a la intervención de un santo? Falto de voluntad, desprovisto de la idea
misma de lucha consigo mismo, ¿cómo puede triunfar sobre sí mismo? Juguete de sus pasiones,
parecía que lo único que podría retenerle era el castigo en la vida futura; pero ese temor
no le preocupa, puesto que al mismo tiempo que se le amenaza con el fuego eterno, se le dice
de qué manera lo puede evitar, sin dejar de practicar el mal.

La inmoralidad de las novenas

Esas novenas contienen una enseñanza funesta para la sociedad cuyo fundamento moral consiste
en el desarrollo de las condiciones individuales tales como el trabajo, el cumplimiento del
deber, el respeto a la ley, la lucha contra los propios instintos y pasiones que requiere antes
que nada el dominio de sí mismo. No solamente no se enseñan ni siquiera se mencionan estas
obligaciones sociales, sino que se estimula a todo lo malo asegurando al criminal, al pecador,
que será perdonado, que podrá librarse del castigo, que por mal que obre y por culpable que
sea, sin el menor esfuerzo, con la mayor naturalidad y facilidad, conseguirá lo que se le antoje
y triunfará en la tierra, lo mismo que en la otra vida.

Por un lado se atemoriza al individuo con el genio del mal, siempre empujándole por el camino
del vicio y la ignominia: por otro se le inspira confianza ciega poniéndole al lado un Ángel
de la Guardia que no le abandona noche y día, que le sostiene, le conduce, "siendo su intervención
tan útil, que modifica aquello que pedíamos a Dios cuando conoce que nuestras peticiones pueden
acarrearnos algún mal espiritual o corporal."

¿Qué idea de justicia puede concebir quien recuerda el espectáculo que presenció aquel caballero
en el cementerio de Cuzco? No sólo se le presenta a María y a José intercediendo con toda energía
por la salvación del malvado por la sola razón que invocaba sus nombres, sino que ni se conmueven
ni ensayan siquiera dulcificar la crueldad de Jesucristo cuando condena a muerte repentina
y condenación eterna a las dos desdichadas mujeres de mala vida. Ellas no invocaban a María
y José, quienes sólo se apiadan de sus clientes y obran con la misma parcialidad de un cacique
nacionalista o demócrata.

¿Y qué significa la ley que no admite y persigue la poligamia cuando son esposas de Jesús tantas
vírgenes que esperan otra vida para entregarse a su esposo? ¿Y qué decir de María, esposa del
Padre, de su propio hijo, de José y Santo Domingo?

El Sr. Ignacio Villamor refiere en un informe al Comité de Mortalidad Infantil, escrito cuando
era Fiscal General, varios casos de asesinatos de personas consideradas como embrujadas y como
tales sacrificadas por los fanáticos.

El mozo de Traiguerra que acometió a una vieja fea por suponerla el mismo demonio, después
de oir un sermón de San Vicente, es absolutamente del mismo carácter que los posesionados del
asuang referidos por el Sr. Villamor.

¿Y qué decir del patrocinio de San Isidro, invocado por los agricultores? El dió ejemplo de
abandono de su deber como agricultor, puesto que en lugar de arar la tierra haciendo el trabajo
por el que su amo le pagaba, se pasaba el día rezando. Por un milagro, un ángel tomaba el arado
y conducía los bueyes mientras el Santo oraba y no trabajaba. ¡Y a la sombra de nuestras mangas,
confiando en San Isidro, la gente del campo duerme esperando que los ángeles hagan su trabajo!
¿Cómo predicar lo de "Comerás el pan con el sudor de tu rostro," cuando el trabajo que ese
sudor significa no es necesario?

Sin conexión alguna con el Buró de Educación del Gobierno de Filipinas he discurrido en la
forma en que acabo de hacerlo, no para defender las escuelas laicas de una acusación injusta
e injustificable, no para atacar a personas ni a ideales religiosos ni políticos, sino para
contribuir a extirpar una de las bases, una de las causas más fuertes de la criminalidad, de
la corrupción, de la formación de individuos inútiles y nocivos a la sociedad: ¡la superstición!
Y, señores, no es una superstición digna solamente de risa: de ninguna manera. Es una superstición
ridícula, sí, absurda, pero trágica, peligrosa, porque ofrece a los malvados, a los criminales,
a los ignorantes, los medios de triunfar en la vida, de salirse con la suya, de conseguir lo
que quieren dándoles los medios de evitar el castigo, burlando en la tierra la justicia de
los hombres, y consiguiendo de Dios el perdón de la condenación eterna, por el sencillo medio
de la invocación de un nombre de santo, o de una palabra latina que, como un sésamo ábrete,
franquea al devoto las puertas del cielo.

Error lamentable del obispo de Cebú

El prelado que acusó en la forma antes mencionada a las escuelas públicas, ha cometido un error
lamentable. Por mi parte puedo asegurar que sus acusaciones despertaron en mí la curiosidad
de investigar las causas de la inmoralidad y de la perversión de costumbres que dicho prelado,
y nosotros con él, todos lamentamos. De acuerdo con los que han estudiado la mentalidad de
la mayoría de nuestro pueblo, resulta evidente que la superstición es el enemigo que tenemos
que combatir, que ella es la causa de los errores morales que observamos. Tanto los sacerdotes
regulares como los del clero secular confiesan que la masa del pueblo se halla aún sometida
a la superstición heredada de los antepasados, la superstición que podría llamarse genuinamente
filipina, la que proviene de las antiguas creencias en el nunu, el asuang y el anito y todos
los espíritus de la antigua idolatría, anterior a la implantación del catolicismo por los misioneros
españoles.

El fracaso de los misioneros

Según propia confesión, estos misioneros, después de tres siglos de predicaciones, no han logrado
extirpar esas supersticiones incrustadas en la conciencia del pueblo. Debemos aceptar su declaración
como honrado testimonio del fracaso de su misión religiosa. No me interesa ni discuto el punto
de vista religioso, sino la importancia de la superstición en la vida social, su influencia
perniciosa contra la evolución de la moralidad. Lo que resulta, sin duda alguna, consecuencia
de los relatos contenidos en esa literatura que constituye la única lectura del pueblo, es
el fomento de la ignorancia, propagando de una manera tan efectiva todas las supersticiones
antes mencionadas y aumentando con ellas el caudal de errores que por desdicha gobierna la
mentalidad de la masa del pueblo.

No se trata solamente de los llamados indios; también están acusados de supersticiones los
hijos de españoles de pura sangre o mezclados con indios, así como los mestizos chinos. Todos
estos, todos nosotros, filipinos, estamos incluidos entre los individuos contagiados con la
lepra de la superstición, fomentada por la absurda milagrería de las novenas, y no se puede
decir que sea un mal de una raza de Filipinas, sino de los habitantes de Filipinas en general.

Para que la educación sea útil, tiene que formar en el individuo el sentido de responsabilidad
mediante el libre automático ejercicio de la razón. El cumplimiento del deber será su objetivo;
para conseguir tal fin es indispensable desarrollar en el hombre la voluntad por medio de la
cual luchará contra los instintos bestiales, contra los impulsos sentimentales, contra todo
lo que se halla en oposición a los dictados de la razón.

Mentalidad lógica para saber lo que debemos hacer, para poder trazarnos un camino justo que
seguir: Voluntad, para lograr sobreponer los dictados de nuestra razón a los impulsos de nuestros
deseos. Este es el objeto de la educación laica, de la educación de las escuelas sin Dios,
aquí con las escuelas del gobierno como en aquel Colegio de la Beata Imelda, dirigido por los
PP. Dominicos, bajo la norma de las ideas japonesas traducidas en leyes imperativas, situado
en Taihoku, capital de Formosa.

La lectura de los llamados milagros de la índole de los que antes he citado, hace que el imposible
parezca posible, gracias a influencias misteriosas fáciles de conseguir, no por el trabajo,
sino sencillamente por medios indignos, rebajantes y reprobados por la moral, como son la humillación,
los halagos, la propiciación. No se pide ni espera un beneficio por medio de un bien positivo
que hacemos, por el cumplimiento de un deber del que resulta un bien que es como un derecho;
se recurre a procedimientos de favor, a ganar la benevolencia de un santo haciéndole creer
que se le quiere, se le adora, se le admira, tratando de exaltar su vanidad y por su mediación
ganar la voluntad de Dios, no como un beneficio otorgado directamente al que pide, sino por
consideración a los méritos del mediador. No se puede imaginar nada más inmoral, más primitivo,
más despreciable. La corte celestial resulta una corte más corrompida que las de aquellos autócratas
que la historia ha condenado; la corte de los Khanes, los Sultanes, los Emperadores bizantinos,
mongoles, persas, tártaros, todos los bárbaros que han abusado de la humanidad y que han personificado
la injusticia y justificado la revolución y las matanzas.

Una sociedad cuyos miembros esperan todo del favoritismo, desconoce la emulación; cuando el
individuo encuentra un medio tan sencillo como el ofrecido en las novenas para conseguir lo
que desea, siguiendo la ley del menor esfuerzo, no recurre a ejercitar ninguna actividad noble
y no puede, por lo tanto, perfeccionar sus facultades ni siquiera usarlas; un individuo que
espera lograr lo absurdo, lo inverosímil, no puede conocer la existencia de las leyes inmutables
que rigen el universo; un individuo que espera conseguir lo que quiere por medio del valimiento
de un patrón celestial, ni puede concebir un Dios de justicia, ni puede de ninguna manera ser
un miembro útil a la sociedad.

Favor, propiciación, excepción, protección, gracia, preferencia, predilección, pugnan contra
lo que debe ser Dios, contra el Ideal de la civilización, contra la suprema aspiración de la
humanidad: la Justicia.

Funestos resultados

Los que creen en esa milagrería absurda, protectora de los tontos, cómplice de los perezosos,
de los jugadores, de los asesinos, de los ladrones, de todos los que por su medio logran lo
que quieren, esos son los criminales que llenan nuestras cárceles y que mueren en el patíbulo;
esos los que, armados de su anting-anting, su talismán, rosario, escapulario, huesos de Santos
o dientes de tiburón, desafían a la policía, cometen tropelías y trastornan el orden, fiados
en que triunfarán por la protección de su pintakasi celestial. Ese es el producto, no de las
escuelas sin Dios, sino del Dios sin escuela, imposible y paradójico, cuyo poder se manifiesta
por procedimientos caprichosos y por ejercicios de prestidigitación. Esos individuos son, en
verdad, el producto esperado de la superstición predicada, difundida, ofrecida a pasto a la
ignorancia de la gente que llegó a no temer a Dios ni al Diablo, y que sabe que el castigo
del Infierno solamente alcanza a quien no se enrosca un rosario al cuello y no se afianza a
un pintakasi que garantice su salvación eterna, porque ¡Dios no permite que el devoto de uno
de sus favoritos se condene!

¿Qué clase de ciudadano puede ser en la sociedad un individuo que se ríe del castigo usando
el medio fácil de un abogado celestial? ¿Cómo pueden asustarle las penas del infierno cuando
sabe que por medio de un abogado poderoso, Dios se verá forzado a perdonarle? ¡Y cuando un
hombre conoce el medio de evitar la justicia divina, es claro que para escapar de la justicia
humana recurrirá para conmover la piedad del juez, para evitar el cumplimiento de la ley, para
no cumplir con ningún deber y vivir sólo disfrutando de derechos, recurrirá a usar con las
autoridades humanas los mismos procedimientos de propiciación, halagos, prevaricación, humillaciones
y engaños que dominaron al mismo Dios y vencieron el poder del Demonio!

Jamás lograréis que un hombre supersticioso, máxime si es del tipo que hemos analizado, llegue
a ser un ciudadano útil. ¡Este tipo es desdichadamente el producto de una educación de tres
siglos * * *!

Las escuelas religiosas han dado ya su fruto, también lo han dado las laicas. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document11016</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>382727</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21889</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> (P.
13). As there are here including the U.S. Catholic, the Bureau of Health must remember that such
citizens with non-Catholics who live the Philippines do not enjoy antipestífera protection
of San Roque.

Superstition and crime

In his remarkable study of criminal anthropology in the Philippines, says Dr. Sixto de Los Angeles
(p. 119): "The easy credulity fostered by the overcultivation of religious fanaticism, has constituted
from the beginning until the present one of the flaws, unfortunately quite still widespread
among the natives of the country * * *. Lover of their traditions and habits inherited and lack
of sufficient opportunities to acquire knowledge, the Filipino populace must hold, as is logical
and natural, their beliefs, which, not requiring any effort for comprehension, are worsening
and are rooted in a spontaneous way in his mind. As evidenced by our judicial annals, superstition
holds a significant category between the factors of crime in the country. "Superstitions referred
to by Dr. LA not just those of the old paganism of Filipino missionaries after more than three
centuries, have failed to completely destroy. Superstitions referred in this conference are
those brought by those missionaries who have been easily to intrude on the Philippines, naturally
willing credulity, by effective propaganda and generously spread on the ninth and other booklets
called of devotion.

As to the arrival of American education in the Philippines was always and exclusively religious,
and directed by Roman priests, the persistence of ancient superstitions are a demonstration
of the failure of religious education. Missionaries would have an excuse blame the rude filipino
invincible, we could admit courtesy and to avoid discussions. But the trouble is not that they could
not remove some of the supposed hard head Indian, but the tremendous
wealth of superstitions that for more than three centuries, these
missionaries have the same penetrating head injury so severe in their
minds and morals.

Unwillingness

The sinner unwillingness to restrain their evil deeds said to Jesus, washing hands in divine intervention
and testifying to the lack of sense of responsibility, "Is possible, sweetest Saviour of souls,
making so many every day, only to loss mine you have to prove insensitive?

"(p. 13.) This is part of a compound sentence none other than the Pope Gregory VII in its Practice
Devoted to the Passion of Christ (Manila, 1905).

It is also said to the Virgin: "Cleanse, Virgin Immaculate, my heart from all sin, and let down me everything
that displeases your eyes purest. Purge my soul of love and affected areas. "(pp. 10-11; Franciscan
Crown - the Virgin Mary. Manila, 1902.)

By the intercession of San Francisco the devotee asks God: "I hold in all my disordered passions,
powers and senses, "so that" I can reduce my thoughts, my words to measure and direct my work
to the greatest perfection, "and"

Thou wouldst soften the hardness of my heart. " (Pp. 18, 20 and 21 of the novena to St. Francis
of Assisi. Manila, 1899.)

Afraid of the machinations of Satan, devoted to St. Philomena asks (p. 23, Nov.) "You reach the
Lord who break more and more the forces of my enemies, the demons, and to save me despite myself.
"

Invoke the aid of Santa Filomena saying (p. 25, Nov.): "Make me chaste
is also, In my state, and my mouth utters not any words that according
to St. Paul, should not be named among the faithful.

"

A Santa Ana, mother of Mary, tells his devotee: "Interesaos therefore Santa mine, so I grant
patience in my adversity, tolerance injuries, and around a tranquil mood * * * (IX, pg. 1, Manila,
1893). It is also runs the following plea, "Empeñaos therefore Santa mine, with your sacred grandson
Jesus to be removed from our hearts all disaffected and ill will for God's sake forgive all
injuries * * *. "

It is possible to cultivate a sense of dignity or respect for himself when spread doctrines such
as those resulting from the following examples, the ninth of Santa Rosa de Lima:

"Taken from his humility, was a maid stepped lips," (p. 10). "I loved most the scorn than worldly honors
* * *. "(p. 102), and" wanted to so effectively the others were the vilest thing in the world,
who claimed he deserved to be in hell and that was his own place
for their sins.

If anyone showed not believe it and that was acquit, Nobody knows
me, he added, I only know what I am "(p. 11)."

Hearing after the praise of virtue, it was felt as a faint "(p. 11).

In a prayer to Santa Filomena (Ninth, pg. 16) is said to Santa, asking for their protection: "My
sins I have become a little lower than the angels, much lower than the beasts, as they do not
forget his master's crib, and so appreciate their food and I've forgotten God's house * * *.
"It is not only self-contempt which is of such considerations, but the lack of logic in attributing
to the gratitude of the animals returned to his master's crib, when it is clear that the motive that
drives them is simply hunger.

The wrath of God

Natural phenomena are regarded as manifestations of ignorance of divine wrath, which not come
to occur if someone, in humanity, not caused by his conduct. St. Thomas Aquinas, who is rightly
regarded as the scientific man of his time firmly believed that thunder,
lightning and storms were only manifestations punitive God's anger
against men.

"In his fear of God, was born in the Holy Doctor a kind of fear of
thunder and storms, with that as a reverent son, feared to see angry
Father's face, fearing those storms were not caused by his sins.

"(Military Angelica, Manila, 1907, pg. 21.)

Fear Blind Thomas made him conceive a blind justice of the Divine
because of God guilt triggered a lightning storm and lavished naturally
hurt and annoyed a large number of people suffering because of the
sins of the Holy.

For the simple believer when the Holy wise thought and thought so, there is no reason to reject
explanation, much less suspecting it fair to punish sinners is not work of justice or even common
sense.

Lack of logic

The logical mind can not develop when it promotes and cultivates the absurd, mainly when you
have covered with the false veneer of religion, when based on superstition of a wholly childish
and simple.

In the life of San Vicente Ferrer, printed in the ninth, relate the following miracles and there
is no doubt that whoever believes in them, can not grow in any way
the functions of his intelligence.

"In Valencia, a servant of the Earl of Faure, who was born deaf and without a tongue, was so many
years and one day to worship the relic of San Vicente, cured of deafness, language was born
and spoke on "(p. 17).

"A woman gave birth to a piece of meat without human figure. Offered him to St. Vincent by say
a mass, and the Epistle and had the head, arms to the Gospel, to
embody legs and finally found a beautiful child.

The same thing happened to another lady of Toledo "(p. 34).

"In Lisbon, a lady lived run for being so ugly, it was the laughter of the saw. Went St. Vincent
and awoke one morning very beautiful and graceful, that was so devout San Vicente Lisbon ladies
that do not exceed those of Valencia "(p. 37).

"A merchant went to a show and in the meantime his wife committed
a vulnerability as was * * *.

Sorry was instructed to San Vicente and Santo came back to the path
where the husband with a horse, getting there to scare them by means
of a layer and scattered.

Then her husband lost his time to gather their horses, so when it came to home because his
wife had time out of your care, getting rid of the consequences lack thereof. "This refers
to the most natural immoral and grotesque, it leaves without reason or cause punished the innocent
husband and the Holy run with a mischievous layer only worthy of a rogue stream.

San Ramon is said that taking such an interest in the misfortunes
and sorrows of his devotees and is so extremely compassionate "who
have sweated their images by the distress of the devotees"

(p. 12). "A picture so obviously the Holy sweat while his devoted suffered, that the veil is
stained to be covered, and some soaked in sweat pañolitos wonderfully relieved pain head "(p. 21).

San
Roque has the power to prevent the spread of epidemics.

"Its protection is the preserve us from the plague and many other ailments, which have their
origin in corruption air that we had to preserve life, kills us "(p. 3).

The height of absurdity

Is it possible to invent and involve greater absurdities that mentioned here? No But not to
lengthen this conference presented only a small number of cases cited in abundance in these little
pamphlets distributed extensively in our people. What logic, we can reasonably expect from brain
nourished with such absurd nonsense fed so childish nature is not understood that men have been
told by a simple sense common?

"The mattress in San Vicente died kept under miracles, as lying in him on several occasions more
than 400 patients of different accidents, all managed health " (P. 32).

Once San Antonio de Padua was preaching at the beach, thought that "out of the water fish who heard
him preach and attentive. "No devotee questioned the output of fish nor interested in solving
problems in physics, physiology, linguistics and mainly logic of such an event, but it says the
novena to Santo (P. 20).

Unnecessarily prolong this conference if I mentioned all the absurdities
entered Novenas in which I have a large body which is a positive documentation
very useful for the history of the superstition that only deflowering
here.

With that said there is enough to explain the origin of immorality, the real cause of the predisposition
to addiction, the absence of a sense of responsibility, the natural explanation of the incomprehensibility
composed of a mixture of feelings that the missionaries have been attributed to filipino,
Indian, Spanish and Chinese, all influenced by the malicious spirit
that informs all that literature completely disruptive of reason.

She and non-secular education is responsible phenomenon.

I do not come formulating theories and hypotheses emit capricious. Before an audience like the one
I have the honor of speaking, I need to weigh the value of my words and my judgments. For this
reason I brought facts, repeating texts I have quoted the words, not secular literature Corridos
constituted by the anonymous whose harmful influence is well known, but the authentic texts
of novenas authorized by ecclesiastical censure for failing to contain anything contrary to
sound morality, as stated in the license to print.

Not for a moment I tried to mix religion in my criticism, nor is it
in my hands change the consequences that follow from the facts mentioned
in the ninth, which is the literature responsible for a state of childish
mentality, quite inadequate for moral intelligence, composed of elements,
crippling and not progress.

Morality is nothing more than the victory over himself whereby a man does what he must and not what
you want. In the immoral man there is no struggle between two tendencies, one toward evil
another to the right. There is only an instinctive tendency: no brakes rational object. What self-control
who has to curb his habit and utter dirty words and obscene uses the intervention of a saint?
Lack of will, devoid of the idea same control himself, how can triumph over himself? Plaything of
his passions, seemed that the only thing that could keep him was
the punishment in the afterlife, but that fear not worried, because
while he is threatened with eternal fire, is told how can avoid it,
not to do evil.

The immorality of the ninth

These contain a teaching ninth fatal to the society whose moral foundation
is in the development of individual conditions such as work, compliance
duty, respect for the law, fighting against their own instincts and
passions that requires prior of all the self-control.

Not only are not taught or even mentioned these social obligations, but also encourages all the
wrong ensuring criminal, a sinner, that will be forgiven, which may escape punishment, that evil
act and guilty that that is, without effort, as naturally and easily get what it wants and prevail
on earth, as in the afterlife.

On one hand it scares the individual with the genius of evil, always pushing for the road of vice
and shame: the other is putting blind trust inspired by an Angel
Guard that does not leave him night and day, he says, leads him, "their
intervention so useful that adjust what we were asking God when you
know that our requests are bring us some evil soul or body.

"

What justice can be conceived idea who remembers the spectacle he
witnessed the gentleman Cuzco in the cemetery?

Not only is presented to Mary and Joseph to intercede with all energy for the salvation of the
evil for no reason invoked their names, but neither are moved tested or even soften the cruelty
of Jesus Christ when sudden death sentence and eternal damnation
to the two unfortunate women of evil life.

They did not invoke Mary and Joseph, who only take pity on their customers and act with the
same bias of a chief nationalist or Democrat.

And what does the law does not allow polygamy and pursued when so many wives of Jesus afterlife
virgins waiting to surrender to her husband? What about Mary, wife of Father, his own son, Joseph,
and Santo Domingo?

Mr. Ignacio Villamor concerns in a report to the Committee on Infant Mortality, written when was
Attorney General, several cases of killings of persons considered to be haunted as those killed
by the fans.

The Traiguerra boy who rushed to an ugly old woman by assuming the devil himself, after hearing
a sermon of St. Vincent, is quite the same character as those possessed of asuang referred
by Mr. Villamor.

What about sponsorship of San Isidro, cited by farmers? He gave an example of neglect of duty as a
farmer, because instead of plowing the earth doing the work by paying his master, he spent the
day praying. By a miracle, an angel took the plow and driving the oxen while the saint was praying
and did not work. And in the shadow of our sleeves, trusting in San Isidro, rural people sleep
waiting for the angels to do their job! How to preach it to "eat their bread by the sweat of
your face," when the work that sweat means you do not need?

Unconnected to the Bureau of Education of the Philippine government
have proceeded in the how I have done, not to defend the secular schools
of an unjust accusation and unjustifiable, not to attack people or
religious or political ideals, but to help remove one of the bases,
one of the strongest causes of criminality, corruption, training of
individuals useless and harmful to society: superstition!

And, gentlemen, is not only a superstition worthy of laughter, in any way. It is a superstition
ridiculous, yes, absurd, but tragic, dangerous, because it offers the wicked, the criminal
the ignorant, the means to succeed in life, get away, to get what they want giving them the means
to avoid punishment, on the ground circumventing justice men, and getting God's forgiveness
of eternal damnation, by the simple means of invoking the name of a saint, or a Latin word,
like a sesame, devotee crosses the gates of heaven.

Lamentable failure of the Bishop of Cebu

The prelate accused in the aforementioned manner to public schools, has made a mistake regrettable. For
my part I can assure you that his accusations aroused my curiosity
investigate the causes of immorality and perversion of morals that
the prelate, and we with it, we all regret.

According to those who have studied the mentality of most of our
people, it is evident that superstition is the enemy we to fight,
she is the moral cause of the errors we observe.

Both priests regular and the secular clergy confess that the mass of people is still in bondage superstition
inherited from the ancestors, superstition could be called genuinely Filipino, which comes from the
ancient beliefs in nunu, the asuang and anito and all the spirits of ancient idolatry, before
the introduction of Catholicism by missionaries Spanish.

The failure of the missionaries

According to own admission, these missionaries, after three centuries of preaching, have failed
remove these superstitions embedded in the consciousness of people.

We must accept your statement as an honest witness to the failure of its religious mission.
I'm not interested or argue the point religious views, but the importance of superstition in
society, their influence harmful to the evolution of morality. What is undoubtedly a consequence
of the stories contained in this literature is the only reading of the people is the promotion
of ignorance, spread so effectively in all superstitions above them
and increasing the flow of errors that unfortunately governs mentality
of the masses.

It is not just the so-called Indians are also accused of the superstitions children of Spanish-blooded
or mixed with Indian and Chinese mestizos. All these, we, Filipinos, are included among individuals
infected with leprosy of superstition, encouraged by the absurd miracle
mongering of the novenas, and can not be said to be an evil race of
the Philippines, but the inhabitants of the Philippines in general.

For education to be useful, must be in the individual sense of responsibility through automatic
free exercise of reason. The line of duty will be your goal; to achieve this purpose it is essential
to develop in man's will through which fight against the bestial instincts against sentimental
impulses, against all which is in opposition to the dictates of reason.

Logical

mentality to know what to do in order to chart a fair follow: Will, in order to overcome the dictates
of our reason to the impulses of our desires. This is the subject of secular education, education
in schools without God, here as government schools at the College of Blessed Imelda, led by PP. Dominicans,
under the rule of Japanese ideas translated into mandatory laws, located in Taihoku, capital
of Formosa.

The reading of the so-called miracles of the nature of which I have quoted, makes the impossible
seems possible, thanks to mysterious influences readily available, not work but simply by unworthy
means, demeaning and condemned by the moral, such as humiliation, the praise, propitiation. Do
not ask or expect a benefit through a positive good we do, for the fulfillment of a duty of which is
an asset that is a right; procedures are used for, to win the goodwill of a saint into believing
that he wants, he adores, admires it, trying to enhance his vanity and his mediation God's will to win,
not a benefit provided directly to that request, but consideration
of the merits of mediator.

Can not imagine anything more immoral, more primitive, more despicable. The heavenly court
is a court more corrupt than those of the autocrats that history has condemned, the court of
the Khans, the Sultans, the Byzantine emperors, Mongols, Persians, Tartars, all the barbarians
who have abused humanity and who have personified injustice and justified the revolution and
bloodshed.

A society whose members expect any favoritism, ignores the emulation, when individual is a means
as simple as that offered in the ninth to get what you want, following
the law of least effort, not used to exercise any noble activity and
can not therefore improve their powers or even use, an individual
expected to achieve the absurd, the improbable, can not know the existence
of immutable laws that govern the universe, an individual who expects
to get what he wants through valimiento a celestial pattern, nor can
conceive of a God of justice, nor can in no way be a useful member
of society.

Please, propitiation, exception, protection, grace, preference, predilection,
fight against what should be God, against the ideal of civilization
against the supreme aspiration of Humanity: Justice.

Fatal results

Those who believe in the miracle-absurd, protective of Fools, an accomplice of the lazy, of the
players, the murderers, thieves, of all that through them achieve what they want, these are
criminals who fill our prisons and die on the gallows; those who, armed with his anting-anting,
their talisman, the rosary, scapular bones Santos or shark teeth, defy the police, commit outrages
and disrupt the order, relying they succeed by protecting your pintakasi heaven. That is the
product not of the schools without God, but God out of school, impossible and paradoxical,
whose power is manifested Procedural and capricious exercise of sleight of hand. These individuals
are in Indeed, the expected product of superstition preached, distributed, offered for grass
to ignorance of the people who did not fear God or the devil, and he knows that punishment Hell
not only reaches those who wraps a string around his neck and not
anchored to a pintakasi to ensure their eternal salvation, because
God does not allow a devotee Order your favorites!

What kind of citizen in society can be an individual who makes fun of using punishment the
easy way a lawyer in heaven? How can scare the pains of hell when know that through a forceful
advocate, God is forced to forgive? And when a man knows the way to avoid divine justice, it is
clear that to escape justice human touch upon to the mercy of the judge, to avoid compliance
with the law, Failure to comply with any duty and live only to enjoy rights, resort to use with human
authorities the same procedures of propitiation, praise, prevarication,
humiliation and deception that dominated the same God and defeated
the power of the devil!

Never a superstitious man will succeed, especially if the type listed
above, come to be a useful citizen.

This is unfortunately a product of three education centuries * *
*!

Religious schools have already borne fruit, so have given the
secular</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>