<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01021</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>46427</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22191</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Verdad que siempre quedaba solo en la pelea. Ni por casualidad se dio el caso de que alguna
de sus hijas le apoyase. Tratándose de asuntos ajenos a la dirección rentística de la casa,
muchas veces se partían las opiniones; algunas hijas se ponían de parte de papá contra sus
hermanas. Mas en cuanto asomaba el problema económico, constantemente se veía al Jubilado de
un lado y a las cuatro hijas de otro. D. Cristóbal, como caudillo experimentado, apelaba en
estas refriegas a mil ardides para derrotar a sus contrarios, o para capitular en buenas condiciones.
Un día amanecían las chicas inspiradas, y pedían botinas de tafilete semejantes a las que habían
visto a tal o cual muchacha de la ciudad, generalmente a Fernanda Estrada-Rosa. D. Cristóbal
se replegaba inmediatamente en sí mismo. Se replegaba y meditaba. Por la noche, a la hora de
cenar, deslizaba en la conversación la noticia de que había estado en La Innovadora (zapatería
de lujo). Le habían dicho que las botas de tafilete daban muy mal resultado en Lancia, a causa
de la humedad. Por otra parte, D. Nicanor (médico de la ciudad), que por casualidad estaba
allí, había manifestado que el tafilete era funesto en climas tan fríos y lluviosos, y que
por los pies se pillaban muchísimas veces los catarros que más tarde degeneraban en tisis galopantes,
etc. Antes, mucho antes de que Mateo terminase su diatriba contra el tafilete, se la destripaban
sus cuatro pimpollos con risas irónicas y pesadísimas palabras que dejaban confundido y triste
al pobre viejo. En otras ocasiones, la imaginación acalorada de las niñas exigía que vinieran
de Madrid unos abrigos muy lindos, de los cuales les había dado noticia Amalia: D. Cristóbal
resistía algún tiempo los asaltos, pero viéndose muy apretado, capitulaba al fin. Su mente,
fecunda en trazas, como la de Ulises, le sugería una magnífica para ahorrarse la mitad del
dinero por lo menos. Se fue a Amalia y le rogó que le diese su abrigo por dos o tres días,
a fin de que una de las modistas del pueblo le hiciese otros cuatro iguales. Exigiole, por
supuesto, absoluto secreto, y la señora de Quiñones supo guardarlo. Pero ¡ay! no lo guardaron
los fementidos abrigos, que al llegar muy empaquetaditos de la silla de posta, y al ofrecerse
a las miradas ansiosas y zahoríes de sus cuatro dueños, lo pregonaron muy alto, por lo pobre
de la ornamentación y lo chapucero del cosido.

--Estos abrigos no están hechos en Madrid--dijo resueltamente Micaela, que era la más nerviosa
de las cuatro.

--¡Hija, no desbarres, por Dios! Pues ¿dónde habían de estar?--exclama D. Cristóbal con afectada
sorpresa, sintiendo cierto calorcillo en las mejillas.

--No sé; pero desde luego se puede asegurar que no los han hecho en Madrid.

Y las cuatro ninfas comienzan a dar vueltas entre sus ebúrneos dedos a los abrigos, los estudian,
los analizan con atento cuidado que pone en suspensión y espanto a su progenitor. Se dirigen
miradas significativas, sonríen con desprecio, se hablan al oído. Mientras tanto, los feroces
bigotes del jubilado de Ultramar se erizan, se estremecen con leve temblor que se comunica
a sus labios y de ahí al resto del organismo.

Por fin, aquellas elegantes criaturas sueltan las prendas con descuido escarnecedor sobre las
sillas de la sala y corren a encerrarse en el gabinete de Jovita. Cerca de media hora estuvieron
deliberando secretamente. D. Cristóbal aguardaba inquieto y ojeroso, paseando con agitación
por el corredor como un procesado que espera el veredicto del jurado.

Ábrese finalmente la puerta, y el criminal escruta con ansia el semblante de los jueces. Éstos
guardan actitud reservada, y por sus labios descoloridos vaga una sonrisa enigmática. Dos de
ellas se ponen inmediatamente la mantilla y los guantes y se lanzan a la calle. Al cabo de
un rato tornan al hogar trémulas, con la faz descompuesta y los ojos centellantes. La pluma
se resiste a narrar la cruel escena que se produjo en la dulce morada del Jubilado. ¡Cuánto
grito rabioso! ¡cuánto sarcasmo! ¡cuánta carcajada histérica! ¡qué manoteo! ¡qué crujir de
sillas! ¡qué exclamaciones tan lamentables! Y enmedio de aquel espantoso desorden, de aquel
fragor, capaz de infundir pavura en el corazón más sereno, los cuatro abrigos, causa de tal
carnicería, desgarrados, convertidos en miserables jirones, arrastrándose con ignominia por
el suelo en pago de su delito.

Fuera de estos sacudimientos periódicos con que la sabia naturaleza vigorizaba los nervios
un poco enervados ya del Jubilado, la existencia de éste se deslizaba pacífica y suave. Ni
le faltaban tampoco muchos y esmerados cuidados. Sus hijas se ocupaban a porfía en ponerle
todo lo necesario a punto y en su sitio: la ropa acepillada; las camisas y los calzoncillos
oliendo a frescura; las corbatas, hechas de vestidos viejos, tan flamantes como si saliesen
de la guantería; las zapatillas en cuanto entraba en casa; el agua para lavarse los pies, los
sábados; el cigarro al acostarse; el vaso de agua con limón a la madrugada, etc., etc. Todo
marchaba con la regularidad dulce y mecánica que tanto placer causa a los viejos. Verdad que
entre cuatro bien podían hacerlo sin molestarse mucho, sobre todo teniendo presente que las
niñas no siempre estaban inspiradas. Sólo a la vista de un sombrero caprichoso, o al recibir
la noticia de la llegada de una compañía dramática, o al anunciarse que el Casino daría una
reunión de confianza, ardía súbito en sus corazones el fuego sagrado de la inspiración, despertábanse
sus poderosas facultades poéticas, y en arrebatado vuelo salían de casa y se lanzaban a la
de la modista, a la guantería, a la perfumería, dejando en todos los parajes señales de su
agitación y alguna parte del peculio profecticio. No aliándose bien los arrebatos de la fantasía
con la prosa de los pormenores de la existencia, éstos sufrían alguna alteración. D. Cristóbal
en aquellos periodos de crisis echaba menos, con pesadumbre, algunos retoques. Mas al poco
tiempo sosegaban los espasmos de las pitonisas y las cosas volvían a su ser y la vida seguía
el mismo curso ordenado y tranquilo. El nombre de aquéllas, por orden de edades, era el siguiente:
Jovita, Micaela, Socorro y Emilita. Eran las cuatro, en apariencia, seres insignificantes,
ni hermosas ni feas, ni graciosas ni desgraciadas, ni muy jóvenes ni viejas, ni tristes ni
risueñas. Nada había en ellas que fijase la atención. No obstante, en el seno del hogar el
carácter de cada cual se pronunciaba y adquiría relieve. Jovita era sentimental y reservada;
Micaela tenía el genio violento; Socorro era la más pava, y Emilita la más pizpireta.

Las dos intensas preocupaciones que llenaban la vida espiritual de D. Cristóbal Mateo eran
la reducción del contingente del ejército y el casar a sus cuatro hijas, o por lo menos a dos.
Lo primero llevaba buen camino: de algún tiempo atrás venían los políticos más conspicuos inclinándose
a esa opinión. En cuanto a lo segundo, nos duele confesar que no tenía verosimilitud de ninguna
clase. Ni por sacrificar otras comodidades a los trapos, ni por exhibirse sin medida al balcón
y en los paseos, ni por asistir a los saraos de Quiñones con una constancia digna de ser premiada,
pudieron lograr hasta la hora presente los dones preciados de Himeneo. Cuando algún imprudente
tocaba este asunto en visita, todas ellas decían que mientras viviese su padre les costaría
mucha pena el casarse; que les parecía cruel abandonar a un pobre anciano que tanto las quería
y tanto se sacrificaba por ellas, etc... Aquí venía un elogio caluroso de las dotes espirituales
de D. Cristóbal. Pero éste se encargaba inocentemente de desmentirlas, mostrando tales ganas
de verse abandonado, un deseo tan vivo de experimentar aquella crueldad, que ya era proverbial
en Lancia. Como si no bastasen ellas solas a ponerse en ridículo, el pobre Mateo las ayudaba
eficazmente, metiéndoselas por los ojos a todos los jóvenes casaderos de la ciudad.

Las ponderaciones que el buen padre hacía del carácter, de la habilidad, de la economía y buen
gobierno de sus hijas no tenían fin. Así que llegaba un forastero a Lancia, D. Cristóbal no
sosegaba hasta trabar conocimiento con él, y acto continuo le invitaba a tomar café en su casa
y le llevaba al teatro a su palco y a merendar al campo y le acompañaba a ver las reliquias
de la catedral y la torre y el gabinete de historia natural; todas las curiosidades, en fin,
que encerraba la población. El público asistía sonriente, con mirada socarrona a aquel ojeo,
que ya se había repetido porción de veces sin resultado. La única que logró tener novio durante
tres o cuatro años fue Jovita. Por eso fue también la que se despeñó de más alto. El galán
era un estudiante forastero que la festejó mientras seguía los últimos cursos de la carrera.
Terminada ésta, partió a su pueblo y, olvidándose de sus promesas de matrimonio, lo contrajo
con una paleta rica. Las demás no habían alcanzado este grado excelso de la jerarquía amorosa.
Inclinaciones vagas, devaneos de quince días, algún oseo por la calle; nada entre dos platos.
Poco a poco se iba apoderando de ellas el frío desengaño. Aunque no hubiesen perdido la esperanza,
estaban fatigadas. Aquel pensamiento fijo, único, que las embargaba hacía ya tanto tiempo,
iba convirtiéndose en un clavo doloroso en la frente. Pero D. Cristóbal ni se rendía ni se
le pasaba por la imaginación el capitular. Creía siempre a pie juntillas en el marido de sus
hijas, y lo anunciaba con la misma seguridad que los profetas del Antiguo Testamento la venida
del Mesías.

--En cuanto se casen mis hijas, en vez de pasar el verano en Sarrió, donde se guardan las mismas
etiquetas que en Lancia, me iré a Rodillero a respirar aire fresco y a pescar robalizas.--Atiende,
Micaela, no seas tan viva, mujer... Comprende que a tu marido no le han de gustar esas genialidades;
querrá que le contestes con razones...

--Mi marido se contentará con lo que le den--respondía la nerviosa niña haciendo un gracioso
mohín de desdén.

--¿Y si se enfada?--preguntaba en tono malicioso Emilita.

--Tendrá dos trabajos: uno el de enfadarse y otro el de desenfadarse.

--¿Y si te anda con el bulto?

--¡Se guardará muy bien! ¡Sería capaz de envenenarlo!

--¡Jesús, qué horror!--exclamaban riendo las tres nereidas.

Aquel marido hipotético, aquel ser abstracto salía a cada momento en la conversación con la
misma realidad que si fuera de carne y hueso y estuviera en la habitación contigua.

La que comenzaba ahora a teclear en el piano era Emilita, las más musical de las cuatro hermanas.
Las otras tres estaban ya en pie, cogidas a la manga de la levita de otros tantos jóvenes;
como si dijéramos, en la brecha.

El conde tropezó a los pocos pasos con Fernanda Estrada-Rosa que venía de bracero con una amiga.
Por lo visto no había querido bailar. Era la joven que hacía más viso en la ciudad por su belleza
y elegancia y por su dote. Hija única de D. Juan Estrada-Rosa, el más rico banquero y negociante
de la provincia. Alta, metida en carnes, morena oscura, facciones correctas y enérgicas, ojos
grandes, negrísimos, de mirar desdeñoso, imponente; gallarda figura realzada por un atavío
lujoso y elegante que era el asombro y la envidia de las niñas de la población. No parecía
indígena, sino dama trasportada de los salones aristocráticos de la corte.

--¡Qué elegantísima Fernanda!--exclamó el conde en voz baja, inclinándose con afectación.

La bella apenas se dignó sonreír, extendiendo un poco el labio inferior con leve mueca de desdén.

--¿Cómo te va, Luis?--dijo alargándole la mano con marcada displicencia.

--No tan bien como a tí... pero, en fin, voy pasando.

--¿Nada más que pasando?... Lo siento. A mí me va perfectísimamente; no te has equivocado--repuso
en el mismo tono displicente, sin mirarle a la cara.

--¿Cómo no, siendo en todas partes donde te presentas la estrella Sirio?

--Dispensa, chico, no entiendo de astronomía.

--Sirio es la estrella más brillante del cielo. Eso lo sabe todo el mundo.

--Pues yo no lo sabía... ¡Ya ves, como soy una paleta!

--No es cierto; pero está muy bien la modestia, unida a la hermosura y al talento.

--No; si ya sé de sobra que no tengo talento. No te mortifiques en decírmelo.

--Hija, te acabo de manifestar lo contrario...

En el tono displicente de Fernanda iba entrando un poco de acritud. En el del conde, pausado,
ceremonioso, se advertía leve matiz de ironía.

--Vamos, entonces te he entendido al revés.

--Algo de eso ha habido siempre.

--¡Caramba, qué galante!--exclamó la joven empalideciendo.

--Siempre que has pensado que pudiera decirte algo desagradable--se apresuró a rectificar el
conde, advertido por el cambio de fisonomía de la idea que cruzaba por su mente.

--Muchas gracias. Estimo tus palabras como se merecen.

--Harías mal en no estimarlas sinceras... Además, no necesito yo decirte lo mucho que vales.
Eso lo sabe todo el mundo.

--Gracias, gracias. ¿Te has cansado de jugar?

--Me duelen un poco las muelas.

--Sácatelas.

--¿Todas?

--Las que te duelan, hijo. ¡Ave María!

--¡Con qué indiferencia lo dices! ¿A ti no te importaría nada, por supuesto?

--Yo siento siempre los males del prójimo.

--¡El prójimo! ¡Qué horror! No tenía noticia de haber llegado ya a la categoría de prójimo.

--Qué quieres, chico; los honores vienen cuando menos se piensa.

Apesar de lo impertinente y hasta agresivo del tono, Fernanda no se movía del sitio, teniendo
siempre cogida del brazo a la amiguita, que no desplegaba los labios. Fijándose un poco, se
podría observar que la rica heredera estaba muy nerviosa. Con el pie daba golpecitos en el
suelo, apretaba en su mano con vivas contracciones el pañuelo y sus labios temblaban de modo
casi imperceptible. Alrededor de los hermosos ojos árabes se marcaba un círculo más pálido
que de costumbre. Aquel pugilato la interesaba.

El conde de Onís había sido de sus novios el que más tiempo había durado. Al aparecer Fernanda
en sociedad, y aun antes, cuando era una zagalita que iba con la criada al colegio, produjo
su figura, su elegancia y sobre todo la amenaza de los seis millones que iban a caer, andando
el tiempo, en su regazo, una verdadera explosión de entusiasmo. No hubo joven más o menos gallardo
o acaudalado que por iniciativa propia o por las insinuaciones de su familia no se resolviese
a pasearle la calle, a esperarla a la salida del colegio, a mandarle cartitas y a decirle requiebros
en el paseo. De Sarrio, de Nieva y de otras poblaciones de la provincia acudieron también,
con pretexto de las ferias, algunos golosos. La niña, ufana con tanto acatamiento, embriagada
por el incienso, no se daba punto de reposo tomando y soltando novios. Era raro el galán que
duraba más de un par de meses en su gracia. En realidad ninguno estaba en posición de merecerla.
En Lancia y en el resto de la provincia no había quien tuviera hacienda proporcionada a su
dote. Si alguno existía, no estaba por su edad habilitado para casarse con tan tierno pimpollo.
Sería algún indiano averiado por los ardores tropicales, o mayorazgo rústico y solitario de
los que vivían en sus casas solariegas. Sin necesidad de que su padre se lo advirtiese, la
niña comprendía admirablemente que ninguno le convenía; pero gozaba coqueteando con todos,
haciéndose adorar de la juventud laciense. Entre ésta existía, sin embargo, un mancebo hacia
el cual ninguna doncella de la ciudad había osado levantar los ojos hasta entonces con anhelos
matrimoniales. Era el conde de Onís. Por su alta jerarquía, más respetada en provincia donde
se tributa a la nobleza un culto que delata al villano y al siervo bajo la levita del burgués,
por su cuantiosa renta, por el apartamiento de su vida y hasta por el misterio y silencio de
su palacio antiquísimo, parecía habitar en atmósfera más elevada, al abrigo de las flechas
de todas las beldades indígenas.

Pues por ello precisamente nació en el pecho de Fernanda un deseo, primero vago, después vivo
y anhelante, de rendirle. Esto es muy humano y sobre todo muy femenino: no necesita explicación.
En el fondo de su alma, la hija de Estrada-Rosa sentíase inferior al conde de Onís. Sin embargo,
tanta era la lisonja que había escuchado en poco tiempo, tan refulgente el brillo que esparcía
sobre su vida el dinero del papá, que bien podía aspirar a hacerle su marido. Si no lo pensaba
así, al menos figuraba pensarlo hablando del conde, por detrás, con cierta displicencia y con
afectada familiaridad por delante. En Lancia, como en todas las capitales pequeñas, los muchachos
y muchachas solían tutearse. El conocerse desde niños y haber acaso jugado en el paseo juntos
lo autorizaba. El conde de Onís jamás había cruzado la palabra con Fernanda, aunque la tropezase
a cada momento en la calle. Sin embargo, cuando se encontraron por primera vez en la tertulia
de las de Meré, la hermosa le soltó un tu redondo y suprimió el título. Luis aquí, Luis allá:
parecía que iba a comerle el nombre. A éste le sorprendió un poco la confianza, sin desagradarle.
A nadie le duele oírse tutear por una linda damisela. Apesar de la naturaleza concentrada y
tímida del conde y de su escasa afición a las mujeres, Fernanda se dio maña para hacerle pronto
su novio o al menos para hacerle pasar por tal a los ojos del público. El cual halló tal noviazgo
perfectamente justificado. En Lancia no había otro marido para Fernanda ni otra mujer para
el conde. La distancia que los separaba era retrospectiva; estaba en los antepasados. La población
creía que, en gracia de la belleza, el dinero y la brillante educación de la joven, el conde
de Onís se hallaba en el caso de olvidar los doscientos gañanes que la habían precedido.

Cerca de un año duraron las relaciones. Los novios se veían en la tertulia de las señoritas
de Meré. D. Juan Estrada-Rosa, al decir de sus íntimos, se hallaba muy complacido. Varias veces
se había insinuado con el conde para que entrase en la casa; pero éste no le había comprendido
o había fingido no comprenderle. Fernanda se lo propuso con claridad un día. Él se evadió como
pudo del compromiso. ¿Era timidez? ¿Era orgullo? La misma Fernanda no se daba cuenta de ello.
Pero esta reserva contribuía a encender su afección y anhelo. De pronto, cuando menos se pensaba,
cuando ya el público comenzaba a preguntarse por qué se retrasaba la boda, cortáronse aquellas
relaciones. Se cortaron sin escándalo, de un modo diplomático y sigiloso, tanto, que hacía
ya más de un mes que no existían cuando todavía la población no estaba enterada y los amigos
les seguían embromando. El hecho produjo fuerte sensación; se comentó en todas las tertulias
hasta lo infinito. Nunca se pudo averiguar qué había habido, ni aun a cuál de los dos correspondió
la iniciativa de esta ruptura. Si se preguntaba al conde, afirmaba rotundamente que Fernanda
le había dejado; mas ponía demasiado empeño en esta afirmación para que no empezara a dudarse
de su sinceridad. La heredera de Estrada-Rosa, sin manifestar nada en concreto, corroboró las
palabras de su novio con el tono desabrido que usó hablando de él, lo mismo que al dirigirle
la palabra. Porque siguieron tratándose, si no con tanta frecuencia, con bastante: ambos acudían
a la tertulia donde se conocieron. Además, Fernanda, poco tiempo después, comenzó a asistir
a los saraos de los domingos en casa de Quiñones. Pero nunca más reanudaron sus rotas relaciones.
Los asistentes suspendían la respiración y ponían toda su alma en los ojos siempre que, como
ahora, los antiguos novios se tropezaban y departían un rato. ¿Volverán a las andadas? ¿Habrá,
por fin, boda? El desengaño venía inmediatamente al observar la indiferencia con que se apartaban.

Cuando iba a contestar a las últimas palabras de la orgullosa heredera, los ojos del conde,
derramando una mirada distraída por el salón, tropezaron con otros que se le clavaron lucientes
y celosos. Alargó la mano a su amiga y con sonrisa forzada dijo:

--¡Qué mal me estás tratando, Fernanda! Como siempre, por supuesto... Yo, sin embargo, ya sabes...
el mismo devoto idólatra. Hasta ahora.

--Siento que esa devoción no me cause frío ni calor--replicó ella sin dar un paso para apartarse.

El conde lo dio alzando los hombros con resignación y diciendo:

--¡Más lo siento yo!

Sorteando las parejas de baile, que ya habían comenzado el rigodón, llegó de nuevo adonde estaba
el ama de la casa. Al lado de ésta se hallaba en aquel instante el famoso Manuel Antonio, uno
de los personajes más dignos de mención en la época que estamos historiando. Se le conocía
tanto por el apodo el marica de Sierra como por su nombre.

Esto basta para que sepamos en cierto modo a qué atenernos respecto a sus propiedades morales
y físicas. Manuel Antonio no era joven. Frisaría en los cincuenta años, disimulados con esfuerzo
heroico por toda la batería de afeites conocidos entonces en Lancia, que no eran muchos ni
muy refinados. Una peluca bastante rudimentaria, algunos dientes postizos mal montados, un
poco de negro en las cejas y de carmín en los labios, mucho patchoulí y un traje de fantasía
apropiado para realzar los residuos de su belleza. Ésta había sido espléndida; una rara perfección
de rostro y de talle. Alto, delgado, esbelto, facciones correctas, diminutas, cabellos rubios,
finos, cayendo en graciosos bucles, mejillas sonrosadas y voz atiplada. De este conjunto primoroso
quedaba tan sólo una sombra por donde pudiera adivinarse. La enhiesta espalda se había abovedado;
los hermosos bucles se habían desvanecido como un sueño feliz; algunas arrugas indecorosas
surcaban aquella tersa frente, y la fila de perlas, que ostentaba su boca, se había transformado
en carrera de huesos amarillos, desvencijados, que el tiempo había quintado y el dentista torpemente
sustituido. Por último, aquel pequeño bigote sedoso había engrosado notablemente, se hizo blanco,
cerdoso, indómito; no bastaban el tinte y el cosmético a mantenerlo presentable. ¡Qué dolor
para el hermoso hermafrodita de Lancia y también para los amigos que le habían conocido en
el esplendor de su gracia!

El espíritu permanecía tan juvenil como a los diez y ocho años. Era el mismo ser apasionado
y tierno, dulce unas veces, iracundo y terrible otras, marchando al soplo de sus caprichos,
viviendo en lánguida ociosidad. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07664</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>2399</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20103</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Truth
is always left alone in the fight. Not by chance was if any of his daughters support him. For
matters outside the rentist address of the house often the opinions were based, some daughters
sided with his dad against sisters. But as looming economic problems, constantly looked to
Retired one side and the other four daughters. D. Christopher, as experienced leader, appealed
to These skirmishes with thousands of tricks to defeat their opponents, or to capitulate in
good condition. One day the girls would wake inspired, and called morocco leather boots were similar
to those seen such and such a city girl, usually Fernanda Estrada-Rosa. D. Christopher immediately
retreated into himself. Fell back and meditated. At night, when dinner, slip into the conversation
the news that he had been in The Innovative (shoe estate). He had been told that the boots of
morocco gave very bad result in Lancia, because moisture. Moreover, D. Nicanor (Medical City),
who happened to there morocco had stated that the weather was dismal as cold and rainy, and by
the feet got caught colds many times later degenerated into galloping consumption, etc. Before,
long before Matthew ended his diatribe against morocco, gutted it four buds with ironic laughter
and ponderous words left confused and sad the poor old man. At other times, the heated imagination of
girls required to come Madrid some very nice coats, which had given news Amalia D. Christopher some
time resisted the attacks, but looking very tight, finally capitulated. His mind, rich in trace
amounts, like Ulysses, he suggested to save a magnificent half money at least. He went to Amalia
and begged to give him your coat for two or three days, so that one of the dressmakers of four
other people do him the same. Exigiole by Of course, secrecy, and knew Mrs. Quiñones storage.
But alas! not kept the perfidious coats who arrived very empaquetaditos of the chaise, and
to offer the anxious looks and wizards of its four owners, it was heralded very high, so poor
of ornamentation and of sewing Tinker.

- These wraps are not made in Madrid - resolutely said Michelle, who was the most nervous four.

-
Daughter, no rave, by God! For where they should be? - Exclaims D. Cristobal affected surprise,
feeling a warmth in her cheeks.

- Do not know, but certainly we can ensure that they have not done
in Madrid.

And the four nymphs begin to spin between your fingers ebony coats,
the students, analyze them with attentive care that is suspended and
terror to his father.

They address meaningful glances, smiling contemptuously spoken in his ear. Meanwhile, fierce Overseas
retired whiskers bristle, shudder with slight tremor which communicates to his lips and then
to the rest of the body.

Finally, those elegant creatures carelessly loose garments mocker
on living room chairs and are to be locked in the cabinet of Jovita.

About half an hour were secret deliberations. D. Christopher waited anxious and haggard, walking
with agitation by the broker as a defendant who awaits the verdict of the jury.

Finally open the door, and criminal searches forward to the faces
of the judges.

These keep quiet attitude, and her lips an enigmatic smile faded vague. Two They immediately put
the blanket and gloves and take to the street. After become the home for a while shaking, with
the broken face and sparkling eyes. Pen refuses to tell the cruel scene which occurred in
the sweet home of the retired. Much rabid cry! Much sarcasm! How hysterical laughter! What
manoteo! What gnashing of chairs! Why so sad exclamations! And in the midst of this horrible
disorder, that heat, capable of infusing struck fear in the heart most serene, four shelters,
because of such carnage, torn, made miserable rags, crawling with ignominy by the ground in
return for his crime.

Apart from these periodic shocks to the wisdom of nature invigorated
nerves a bit unnerved and the retired, the existence of this peaceful
and smooth gliding.

Ni also lacked many painstaking care. His daughters were engaged in putting in contention
everything you need ready and in place: planed clothes, shirts and underwear smelling freshness
ties, made of old clothes, as brand new as if saliesen of the glove, sneakers entered the
house as, the water to wash the feet, Saturday, a cigar at bedtime glass of lemon water in
the morning, etc., etc. All regularly marched with the sweet and mechanical cause much pleasure
to the old. Truth four could well do without bothering too much, especially bearing in mind that
girls were not always inspired. Only the sight of a whimsical hat, or receiving news of the
arrival of a dramatic company, or the announcement that the casino would give a Trust meeting,
sudden burning in their hearts the sacred fire of inspiration, despertábanse his powerful poetic
powers, and flight taken out of the house and threw the the dressmaker, the glove, the perfume,
leaving all signs of their sites agitation and profecticio peculio somewhere. While allying
No outbursts of fantasy with the prose of the details of existence, they suffered some alteration. D.
Christopher in periods of crisis missed less, with regret, a few tweaks. More soon time calmed
the spasms of the mediums and things returned to their being and life was the same orderly
and peaceful course. The name of the former, in order of age, was as follows: Jovita, Micaela, Socorro
and Emily. It was four apparently insignificant creatures, neither beautiful nor ugly, neither
funny nor unhappy, neither too young nor old, neither sad nor smiling. There was nothing in
them that fixed the attention. However, within the home the each character and acquired pronounced
relief. Jovita was sentimental and reserved; Micaela had a violent temper, Socorro was the kettle,
and Emily the most pert.

The two strong concerns that filled the spiritual life of D. Christopher Matthew were reduction
of military contingent and their four daughters to marry, or at least two. The first had a good
way: some time ago came the most conspicuous political leaning to
that view.

Regarding the latter, it hurts us to say that he had no likelihood of class. Or by sacrificing
other amenities to rags, or showing up without limit to the balcony and on field trips or to attend
the soirees of Quinones with a constancy worthy of being awarded, could get up to the present time the
precious gifts of Hymen. When a reckless touched this issue in check, all said that while their
father lived cost very sorry to marry, that it seemed cruel to leave an old man who both wanted
and both were sacrificed by them, etc ... Here came a hearty praise of the spiritual gifts D. Cristobal.
But he was in charge of backing out innocently, showing such desire of being abandoned, so lively
a desire to experience that cruelty, which was already proverbial in Lancia. As if they alone
were not enough to make a fool, poor Matthew helped them effectively, through the eyes metiéndoselas
all marriageable young city.

The weights that the good father was the character, skill, economy and good government of their
daughters had no purpose. So a stranger came to Lancia, D. Christopher no calmed to get acquainted
with him and invited him to act continuous coffee at home and brought
him to the theater to his box and snack to the field and accompanied
him to see the relics the cathedral and the tower and the natural
history cabinet, all the curiosities, in short, which contained the
population.

The audience attending smiling, sly look at him leaf through, already had repeated portion of
times without success. The only one that did have a boyfriend for three or four years was Jovita.
So it was also the one that plunged the highest. Heartthrob stranger was a student that was celebrated
as the last years of the race. Been completed, he left his people and, forgetting his promises
of marriage, contracted with a rich palette. The others had not reached that lofty level of
the hierarchy of love. Vague inclinations, dreams of fifteen days, a bone down the street, nothing
between two dishes. Gradually they were coming over the cold disappointment. Although they had
not lost hope, were fatigued. The thought fixed, only that the embargo on so long, was becoming
a painful nail in the forehead. But D. Christopher or surrendered or passed through his imagination
to capitulate. Always believed blindly in the husband of daughters, and announced with the same
security as the Old Testament prophets of the coming the Messiah.

- As my daughters get married, instead of spending the summer in Sarrió, where are kept the same Lancia
cloud that, I'll go Rodillero to fresh air and fishing robalizas .-- Hear, Michelle, do not
be so lively, woman ... Understand that your husband does not have to like these geniuses;
want to answer you with reasons ...

- My husband is content with what you give - answered the girl making
a funny nerve moue of disdain.

- What if he gets angry? - Wondered
Emilita malicious tone.

- It has two jobs: one, the other the angry
and casual.

- What if you walk with the package?

- It will keep
well!

Would be able to poison!

- Jesus, the horror - the three mermaids cried laughing.

One husband scenario, that being abstract out all the time in conversation with same reality
as if it were flesh and blood and was in the adjoining room.

The starting now typing on the piano was Emilita, the most musical
of the four sisters.

The other three were on their feet, holding the sleeve of his coat
of many other young people; as it were, into the breach.

The count ran a few steps with Fernanda Rosa Estrada-coming arm in
arm with a friend.

Apparently it did not want to dance. It was the girl who had more sheen in the city for its beauty
and elegance and her dowry. The only child of D. Juan Estrada-Rosa, the richest banker and
businessman of the province.

Tall, plump, dark brown, good and strong features, eyes large, very black, looking disdainfully,
imposing, graceful figure enhanced by a costume luxurious and elegant that it was the amazement and
envy of the girls in the population. There seemed Indian lady but transported from the aristocratic
salons of the court.

- Fernanda How elegant! - Said the Count quietly, bowing involvement.

Beauty hardly deigned to smile, extending a little lower lip with a slight sneer.

- How are you, Luis? - Said extending his hand with marked indifference.

-
Not as good as you ... but in the end, I have visited.

- Nothing
more than passing?

... Sorry.

I will most perfectly, no you're wrong - said in the same dismissive tone, without looking at his
face.

- How not to be everywhere that show the star Sirius?

- Exemption,
boy, do not understand astronomy.

- Sirius is the brightest star
in the sky.

That's what everybody knows.

- Well, I did not know ... You see, as I am a paddle!

- Not true, but is fine modesty, coupled with the beauty and talent.

-
No, if I know full well that I have no talent.

Do not beat yourself up to tell me.

- Daughter, you express just the opposite ...

The dismissive tone
of Fernanda was entering a bit of bitterness.

In the count's, paused, ceremonious, cautioned slight hint of irony.

-
Come on, then you have understood backwards.

- Some of it has been
forever.

- Wow, what a gallant! - Said the little pale.

- Whenever
you thought you could tell something unpleasant - was quick to rectify
the Earl, warned by the change in appearance of the idea crossed his
mind.

- Thank you.

I believe your words as they deserve.

- You would do wrong not sincere esteem ... Also, I need not tell
you how much you're worth.

That's what everybody knows.

- Thank you.

Are you tired of playing?

- It hurts a little grinding.

- Take it off.

- Are all?

- Those
who hurt you, son.

Ave Maria!

- With what indifference you say!

You do not mind anything, of course?

- I always feel the ills of others.

- The neighbor! What horror!

Was not aware of having already reached the category of neighbor.

- What is it, boy, the honors come when least expected.

In spite of the flippant and even aggressive tone, Fernanda did not move the site, taking always
arm in arm to the friend, who did not open his lips.

By looking a little, might note that the heiress was very nervous. With his foot was tapping on
the floor, clutched in his hand with the tissue contractions alive and his lips trembled so
almost imperceptible. Some Arabs beautiful eyes marked a paler circle than usual. He's interested
in boxing.

The Count de Onis had been of her boyfriends that lasted longer. Appearing Fernanda in society, and even
before, when she was a zagalita the maid was going to school was her figure, elegance and
above all the threat of the six million that were to fall, walking time, in her lap, an explosion
of enthusiasm. There were no more or less handsome young or wealthy on his own initiative or
by the insinuations of his family is not resolved to pasearle the street to meet her at the exit
of the school, to send little notes and compliments tell on the ride. De Sarria, snow and
other towns in the province also attended, under the pretext of the fairs, some greedy. The girl,
boasts with such compliance, drunk with incense, he did not rest point taking and releasing
boyfriends. It was rare that the gallant lasted more than a couple of months in his grace.
In reality none were in a position to deserve it. In Lancia and the rest of the province who
have had their finances provided dowry. If any existed, was not qualified by age to marry so
young bud. Would be some Indian tropical damaged by the heat, or rustic and solitary mayorazgo
those living in their ancestral homes. Without his father warned, the she understood that none
suited him admirably, but he enjoyed flirting with everyone, worship of youth becoming laciense.
Among the latter was, however, a young man to which no city girl had dared to raise his eyes
up with desires then marriage. It was the Count de Onis. Because of its high ranking, most
respected in the provinces where be taxed to the nobility a cult
that reveals the villain and the servant under the coat of bourgeois
with its large income from the apartment of his life and even the
mystery and silence its ancient palace, seemed to dwell in the upper
atmosphere, sheltered from the arrows of all indigenous beauties.

So precisely because he was born in the bosom of Fernanda a desire, first vaguely, then live and
yearning, of surrender. This is very human, and totally feminine needs no explanation. At the
bottom of his soul, the daughter of Rosa Estrada-felt inferior to the Count de Onis. However,
such was the adulation he had heard in some time, as shining the bright scattered about his life
dad money, which might well aspire to make her husband. If you did not think so well, at least figuratively
speaking thought the count, behind, with some disdain and familiarity affected ahead. In Lancia,
as in all small capitals, boys and girls used first-name basis. The known since childhood and have
perhaps played on the tour together authorized it. The Count de Onis had never crossed the floor
with Fernanda, although stumble every moment on the street. However, when they met for the first
time in the party of the de Mere, he gave a beautiful round and deleted your title. Luis here, Luis
beyond: seemed about to eat his name. To him the confidence was a little surprised, not dislike.
No one was hurt tutear heard by a pretty lady. Despite the concentrated nature shy of the count
and his little womanizing, Fernanda he soon contrived to make her boyfriend or at least to make such
a move by the public eye. Who found this dating perfectly justified. In Lancia had another
husband or another woman to Fernanda Count. The distance between them was retrospective, was in the
ancestors. The population believed that, for the sake of beauty, money and education of the
young bright, Count de Onis was in the case of forgetting the two
hundred and farmhands who had preceded them.

About a year lasting relationships. The couple were seen in the gathering of the ladies de Mere.
D. Juan Estrada, Rosa, in the words of his close friends, was very pleased. Several times had
suggested to the county to enter into the house, but he had not understood or had pretended not
to understand him. Fernanda is clearly suggested by one day. He escaped as could compromise. Was
it shyness? Was it pride? The same Fernanda did not realize it. But this book helped rekindle
their affection and longing. Suddenly, when least expected, when the public began to wonder
why the wedding was delayed, those cortáronse relationships. Were cut without scandal, of a
diplomatic and secretive, therefore he did More than a month that did not exist when the population
was not yet aware and friends they were kidding. The fact there was strong feeling, was mentioned
in all gatherings to infinity. Never could figure out what had been, or even which of the two
corresponded the initiative of this break. If you asked the count, said flatly that Fernanda
had left, but went too hard in this statement that did not begin to doubt their sincerity. The
heir-Rosa Estrada, without showing anything in particular, confirmed the words of her boyfriend
with surly tone he used talking about it, as well as to guide word. Because they followed the case,
if not as often, quite: both came to the gathering where they met. In addition, Fernanda, shortly
after, he began attending to the Sunday soirees at the home of Quiñones. But never again resumed
their broken relationships. Attendees suspended breath and put his whole soul into the eyes
if, as Now, former boyfriends encountered and chatted for a while. "Back on track? Will, finally
wedding? The disappointment came immediately to see the indifference with which it departs.

When I went to answer the last words of the proud heir, the Count's eyes, shedding a distracted
gaze around the room, they met others who had stuck into shining
and jealous.

She reached her friend and said with a forced smile:

- How badly are you trying, Fernanda! As always, of course ... I,
however, you know ... the same devoted idolater.

Until now.

- I feel that this devotion does not cause me cold or hot - she replied without taking a step away.

The
count gave him shrugging his shoulders in resignation and saying:

- More I'm sorry!

Sorting dancing partners, who had begun the quadrille, came back to where he was the mistress of
the house. Beside it was at that moment the famous Manuel Antonio, a of the most noteworthy
at the time that we historian. He was known thus the nickname the fag Sierra as its name.

This
is enough to know somewhat what to expect regarding their moral properties and physical. Manuel
Antonio was not young. Frisaría in fifty years, disguised with effort heroic by any battery known
then Lancia cosmetics, which were not many do very refined. A rudimentary wig, some false teeth
fitted incorrectly, a little black on the eyebrows and lipstick, much patchouli and a fancy dress
appropriate to highlight the waste of her beauty. It had been wonderful, a rare perfection of face
and figure. Tall, slim, slim, good features, tiny, blonde hair, fine, falling into graceful
curls, rosy cheeks and high-pitched voice. From this set gorgeous was only a shadow where he could
guess. The back was arched upright; the beautiful curls were gone like a happy dream, some unseemly
wrinkles that furrowed forehead, and the row of pearls, which he held his mouth, had become yellow
bone race, rickety, that time and the dentist was inducted awkwardly replaced. Finally, the
small silky mustache had thickened considerably, it was white bristly, unruly, not enough
dye and cosmetics to keep presentable.

What a pain to the beautiful hermaphrodite Lancia and also for friends who had known him in
the glory of his grace!
The spirit remained as young as ten and eight years. It was the same
to be passionate and tender, sweet at times, angry and terrible other,
marching to the breath of his whims, languid living in idleness</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>