<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>729317</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24031</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> En caso de ataque
submarino, los transportes que llevaban cañones podían salirse de la fila y ayudar á la patrulla
de buques armados, dando cara al enemigo. Los otros debían continuar su rumbo tranquilamente,
sin preocuparse de la agresión. Si el buque de delante ó el que seguía á popa era torpedeado,
no había que detenerse para darle auxilio. Los torpederos y «chaluteros» se encargarían de
salvar á los náufragos, si resultaba posible. El deber del transporte era ir siempre adelante,
ciego y sordo, sin salirse de la formación, sin detenerse, hasta conducir al puerto terminal
la fortuna que llevaba en sus entrañas.

Esta marcha en convoy, impuesta por la guerra submarina, representaba un salto atrás en la
vida de los mares. Ferragut recordó las flotas á vela de otros siglos, escoltadas por navíos
de línea, siguiendo su rumbo á través de incesantes batallas; los remotos viajes de los galeones
de las Indias, saliendo de Sevilla para llegar en rebaño á las costas del Nuevo Mundo.

La doble fila de cascos negros con penachos de humo avanzaba mansamente en las jornadas de
bonanza. Cuando el día era gris, el mar espumeante, el cielo bajo y la atmósfera brumosa, se
esparcían y encabritaban como un tropel de corderos obscuros y asustados. Los guardianes del
convoy, tres barcos pequeños que marchaban á toda máquina, eran los mastines vigilantes de
este ganado marino, precediéndole para explorar el horizonte, quedándose detrás de él ó marchando
á sus costados para mantener intacta la formación. Su ligereza y su velocidad les hacía dar
saltos prodigiosos sobre las olas. Una cinta de humo se enroscaba á continuación de sus dobles
chimeneas. Su proa, cuando no estaba oculta, expelía cascadas de espuma, levantándose hasta
mostrar el principio de la quilla.

De noche navegaban todos con pocas luces: un simple farol á proa para aviso del que marcha
delante y otro á popa para indicar la ruta al siguiente. Estas luces macilentas apenas se veían.
De pronto, el timonel tenía que torcer el rumbo y pedir máquina atrás, viendo que se agrandaba
en la obscuridad la silueta del buque anterior. Unos cuantos minutos de descuido, y entraba
por su popa con un espolonazo mortal. Al amenguar la marcha, el capitán miraba inquieto á sus
espaldas, temiendo chocar á su vez con el que le seguía en la fila.

Todos pensaban en los submarinos invisibles. De tarde en tarde sonaban cañonazos. La escolta
del convoy tiraba y tiraba, yendo de un lado á otro con ágiles evoluciones. El enemigo había
huído, como los lobos ante el aullar de los perros vigilantes. En otras ocasiones era una falsa
alarma, y los cañones herían con sus latigazos de acero el agua desierta.

Había un enemigo más molesto que la tormenta que desordena á los convoyes, más temible que
los torpedos. Era la niebla espesa y blanca como la albúmina, que caía sobre los buques, haciéndolos
navegar á ciegas en pleno día, poblando el espacio de inútiles rugidos de sirena, no dejando
ver el agua que los sustentaba ni los otros barcos cercanos, que podían salir de un momento
á otro de la borrosa atmósfera, anunciando su aparición con un choque y un crujido enorme,
mortal. Así habían de marchar los marinos días enteros; y cuando al fin se libraban de este
sudario, respirando con la satisfacción del que despierta de una pesadilla, otra muralla cenicienta
y nebulosa avanzaba sobre las aguas, envolviéndolos de nuevo en su noche. Los hombres más valerosos
y serenos juraban al ver la barra interminable de la bruma cerrando el horizonte.

Tales viajes no eran del gusto de Ferragut. Le irritaba la marcha en fila, como un soldado,
teniendo que amoldarse á las velocidades de buques despreciables. Aún le encolerizaba más verse
obligado á obedecer al comandante del convoy, que muchas veces era un viejo marino de carácter
autoritario.

A causa de esto, en una de las arribadas á Marsella manifestó á las autoridades marítimas su
firme voluntad de no navegar más de tal modo. Tenía bastante con cuatro expediciones. Resultaban
buenas para los capitanes miedosos, incapaces de salir de los puertos si no llevaban á la vista
una escolta de torpederos, y cuyas tripulaciones, al menor incidente, pretendían echar los
botes al agua, refugiándose en la costa. El se creía más seguro yendo solo, confiado á su pericia,
sin otro auxilio que su profundo conocimiento de las rutas del Mediterráneo.

La petición fué atendida. Era dueño de buque, y temieron perder su cooperación cuando escaseaban
tanto los medios de transporte. Además, el Mare nostrum, por su velocidad, merecía ser empleado
aparte, en servicios extraordinarios y rápidos.

Quedó en Marsella unas semanas esperando un cargamento de obuses, y callejeó como siempre por
la capital mediterránea. Las tardes las pasaba en la terraza de un café de la Cannebière. El
recuerdo de Von Kramer surgió algunas veces en su memoria. «¿Lo habrían fusilado?...» Quiso
saber, pero sus averiguaciones no obtuvieron gran éxito. Los Consejos de guerra eludían la
publicidad de sus actos de justicia. Un negociante marsellés amigo de Ferragut se acordaba
de que, algunos meses antes, había sido ejecutado un espía alemán sorprendido en el puerto.
Tres líneas en los periódicos nada más dando cuenta de su muerte. Se decía que era un oficial...
Y el marsellés pasó á hablar de las noticias de la guerra, mientras Ulises pensaba que el ejecutado
no podía ser otro que Von Kramer.

En la misma tarde tuvo un encuentro. Al marchar por la calle de Saint-Ferreol, mirando los
escaparates de las tiendas, los gritos de varios conductores de coches y automóviles que no
acertaban á hacer pasar sus vehículos en la angosta y repleta vía llamaron su atención. Vió
en un carruaje á una dama rubia, de espaldas á él, acompañada por dos oficiales de la marina
inglesa. Inmediatamente pensó en Freya... Su sombrero, su traje, todo lo que pudo distinguir
de su persona, no le recordaban en nada á la otra. Y sin embargo, cuando se alejó el coche,
sin que él llegase á ver el rostro de esta desconocida, la imagen de la aventurera persistió
en su memoria.

Al fin acabó por irritarse contra él mismo, á causa de la semejanza absurda que había descubierto
sin motivo alguno. ¿Cómo podía ser Freya esta inglesa que iba con dos oficiales?... ¿Cómo la
alemana refugiada en Barcelona podía deslizarse en Francia, donde indudablemente era conocida
de la policía militar?... Aún le irritó más la sospecha de que este parecido fuese un resto
del antiguo amor, que le hacía ver á Freya en toda mujer rubia.

A las nueve de la mañana del día siguiente, cuando el capitán se vestía en su camarote para
bajar á tierra, Tòni abrió la puerta.

Su gesto era fosco y tímido al mismo tiempo, como si fuese á dar una mala noticia.

--Esa está ahí--dijo lacónicamente.

Ferragut le miró con expresión interrogante... ¿Quién era «esa»?...

--¿Quién ha de ser?... ¡La de Nápoles! ¡La rubia del demonio que nos trae desgracia!... A ver
si esa bruja nos deja inmóviles unas cuantas semanas, lo mismo que la otra vez.

Se excusó, como si acabase de cometer una falta en el servicio. El buque estaba unido al muelle
por una pasarela y todos podían entrar en él. El piloto era enemigo de estos amarres, que dejaban
libre el paso á los curiosos y los importunos. Cuando se había dado cuenta de la visita, la
señora estaba ya en la cubierta, cerca de las cámaras. Recordaba bien el camino del salón:
quería seguir adelante; pero él había hecho que Caragòl la detuviese mientras venía á avisar
al capitán.

--¡Cristo!--murmuró éste--. ¡Cristo!...

Y su asombro, su sorpresa, no le permitieron lanzar otra exclamación.

Luego se encolerizó.

--¡Echala!... Que la agarren dos hombres y la pongan en el muelle, aunque sea á viva fuerza.

Pero Tòni vacilaba, no atreviéndose á cumplir tales órdenes, y el impetuoso Ferragut se lanzó
fuera del camarote para realizar por sí mismo lo que había mandado.

Cuando pasó al salón, alguien entró al mismo tiempo por el lado de la cubierta. Era Caragòl,
que intentaba cerrar el paso á una mujer; pero ésta, burlando sus ojos cegatos, iba deslizándose
poco á poco entre su cuerpo y el tabique de madera.

Al ver al capitán, Freya corrió hacia él tendiendo sus brazos.

--¡Tú!--dijo con voz gozosa--. Bien sabía que estabas aquí, á pesar de que estos hombres aseguraban
lo contrario... Me lo decía el corazón... ¡Buenos días, Ulises!

Caragòl volvió los ojos hacia el sitio donde adivinaba la presencia del segundo, como si implorase
su perdón. Con las hembras no se podía cumplir ninguna orden... Tòni, por su parte, parecía
avergonzado ante esta mujer que le miraba hostilmente.

Los dos desaparecieron. Ferragut no pudo darse cuenta de cómo fué la fuga, pero se alegró de
ella. Temía que la recién llegada aludiese en su presencia á las cosas del pasado.

Quedó largo rato contemplándola. Había creído reconocerla de espaldas el día anterior, y ahora
estaba seguro de que hubiera seguido adelante con indiferencia al verla de frente. En realidad,
¿era la misma que acompañaban los dos oficiales ingleses?... Parecía mucho más alta que la
otra, con una delgadez que hacía clarear su cutis, dándole una transparencia enfermiza. La
nariz era más prominente y afilada; los ojos brillaban hundidos en los círculos negruzcos de
sus cuencas.

Estos ojos empezaron á mirar al capitán humildes y suplicantes.

--¡Tú!--exclamó Ulises con extrañeza--. ¡Tú!... ¿Qué vienes á hacer aquí?...

Freya habló con una timidez de sierva. Sí, era ella, que le había reconocido el día anterior
mucho antes de que él la mirase, formando inmediatamente el propósito de venir en busca suya.
Podía pegarle, como la última vez que se vieron; estaba dispuesta á sufrirlo todo... ¡pero con él!

--Sálvame, Ulises; llévame contigo... Te lo pido más angustiosamente que en Barcelona.

--¿Cómo estás aquí?...

Ella comprendió la extrañeza del capitán al encontrarla en país enemigo; la inquietud que sentía
por él mismo al ver á una espía en su buque.

Miró en torno para convencerse de que estaban solos, y habló en voz baja. La doctora le había
enviado á Francia para que «trabajase» en los puertos. A él solo podía revelar el secreto.

Ulises se indignó ante esta confidencia.

--¡Márchate!--dijo con voz colérica--. Nada quiero saber de ti... Lo tuyo no me interesa, no
deseo conocerlo... ¡Fuera de aquí! ¿Por qué me buscas?

Pero ella no parecía dispuesta á cumplir sus órdenes. En vez de marcharse, se dejó caer con
desaliento en uno de los divanes de la cámara.

--He venido--dijo--para rogarte que me salves. Te lo suplico por última vez... Voy á morir;
adivino que mi fin está próximo si tú no me tiendes una mano; presiento la venganza de los
míos... ¡Guárdame, Ulises! No me dejes volver á tierra: tengo miedo... ¡Tan segura que me sentiría
aquí, á tu lado!...

El miedo, efectivamente, se reflejó en sus ojos al recordar los últimos meses de su vida en
Barcelona.

--La doctora es mi enemiga... Ella, que me protegió tanto en otro tiempo, me abandona como
algo viejo que es necesario suprimir. Tengo la certidumbre de que me han condenado en lo alto...

Se estremecía al recordar la cólera de la doctora cuando, á la vuelta de uno de sus viajes,
se enteró de la muerte de su fiel Karl. El capitán Ferragut era para ella una especie de demonio
invulnerable y victorioso, que escapaba á todos los peligros, matando á los servidores de la
buena causa. Primeramente, Von Kramer; ahora, Karl... Como le era necesario desahogar en alguien
su cólera, había hecho responsable á Freya de todas las desgracias. Por ella conocía al capitán
y lo había mezclado en los asuntos del «servicio».

El ansia de venganza hizo sonreír á la imponente dama con una expresión feroz. El marino español
estaba señalado en alto lugar. Ordenes precisas habían sido dadas contra él. «¡En cuanto á
sus cómplices!...» Freya figuraba indudablemente entre estos cómplices, por haberse atrevido
á defender á Ferragut recordando la muerte trágica de su hijo, por no haber hecho coro con
los que deseaban su exterminio.

Semanas después, la iracunda doctora se había mostrado amable y sonriente, lo mismo que en
otro tiempo. «Querida mía: conviene que dé usted un paseo por Francia. Hace falta un agente
que nos entere del movimiento de los puertos, de la salida y entrada de los buques, para que
nuestros sumergibles sepan dónde esperar. Los oficiales de marina son galantes, y una mujer
hermosa puede ganarse su afecto.»

Ella había pretendido desobedecer. ¡Ir á Francia, donde eran conocidos sus trabajos de antes
de la guerra!... ¡Volver al peligro cuando ya se había acostumbrado á la vida segura en los
países neutrales!... Pero sus intentos de resistencia no llegaban á realizarse. Carecía de
voluntad: el «servicio» la había convertido en un autómata.

--Y aquí estoy; sospechando que tal vez marcho á la muerte, pero cumpliendo los encargos que
recibo; esforzándome por ser grata y retardar de este modo el cumplimiento de su venganza...
Soy como un condenado que sabe que va á morir y procura hacerse necesario, para demorar unos
meses su sentencia.

--¿Cómo has entrado en Francia?--preguntó él, sin hacer caso de su acento doloroso.

Freya levantó los hombros. En su oficio se cambiaba fácilmente de nacionalidad. Ahora era ciudadana
de una república de América. La doctora le había proporcionado los papeles necesarios para
pasar la frontera.

--Pero aquí--continuó--me tienen más segura que en una cárcel. Me han dado los medios para
entrar, y sólo ellos me pueden hacer salir. Estoy por completo en su poder. ¿Qué harán de mí?...

El terror le había sugerido en ciertos momentos desesperadas resoluciones. Quería denunciarse
á sí misma, comparecer ante las autoridades francesas relatando su historia, haciendo saber
los secretos de que era poseedora. Pero su pasado le infundía miedo: eran muchas las maldades
que llevaba realizadas contra este país. Tal vez la perdonasen la vida teniendo en cuenta la
espontaneidad de su acto; pero el presidio, la reclusión con el pelo cortado, vestida de ruda
estameña, condenada al silencio, sufriendo tal vez hambre y frío, le inspiraban una repulsión
invencible... No: antes la muerte.

Y continuaba su vida de espionaje, cerrando los ojos ante el porvenir, viviendo el momento
presente, evitando el pensar, considerándose feliz cuando veía por delante unos cuantos días
de seguridad.

El encuentro con Ferragut en una calle de Marsella la había reanimado, dándole nuevas esperanzas.

--Sácame de aquí; guárdame contigo. En tu buque puedo vivir olvidada del mundo, como si hubiese
muerto... Y si mi presencia te disgusta, llévame lejos de Francia, déjame en un país lejano.

Deseaba salir de este aislamiento en tierra enemiga teniendo que obedecer á sus superiores,
como una fiera enjaulada que recibe pinchazos á través de los hierros. La hacía temblar el
presentimiento de su próxima muerte.

--¡Yo no quiero morir, Ulises!... No soy aún vieja para morir. Yo adoro mi cuerpo, soy el primero
de mis enamorados, y me aterro al pensar que puedo ser fusilada.

Pasó por sus ojos un reflejo fosfórico; sus dientes chocaron con el castañeteo del terror.

--¡No quiero morir!--repitió--. Hay momentos en que adivino que me siguen y me cercan... Tal
vez me han conocido y esperan el momento de sorprenderme en pleno trabajo... Ayúdame: hazme
salir de aquí; mi muerte es segura. ¡He hecho tanto daño!...

Calló un momento, como si calculase todos los delitos de su vida anterior.

--La doctora--siguió diciendo--cuenta con el entusiasmo patriótico, que le enardece para continuar
sus trabajos. Yo carezco de su fe: no soy alemana y me repugna ser espía... Siento vergüenza
al considerar mi vida actual; pienso todas las noches en el resultado de mis abominables trabajos;
calculo el empleo que pueden dar á mis avisos y mis informes; veo los buques torpedeados...
¿Cuántos seres habrán muerto por mi culpa? Tengo visiones: mi conciencia me atormenta. ¡Sálvame!...
No puedo más. Siento un miedo horrible. ¡Tengo tanto que expiar!...

Se había levantado poco á poco del diván, y al pedir protección á Ferragut iba hacia él con
los brazos extendidos, humilde y al mismo tiempo acariciadora, por una voluntad de seducción
que predominaba sobre todos sus actos.

--¡Déjame!--gritó el marino--. No te acerques... ¡no me toques!

Sintió la misma cólera que le había hecho ser brutal fin su entrevista de Barcelona. Le irritó
la tenacidad de esta aventurera, que, luego de ejercer una influencia trágica en su vida, deseaba
comprometerle de nuevo.

Pero un sentimiento de fría compasión le hizo contenerse y hablar con cierta bondad.

Si necesitaba dinero para huir, él se lo daría sin regateo alguno. Podía fijar la cifra; el
capitán estaba dispuesto á satisfacer todos sus deseos; pero nada de vivir juntos. Le daría
una suma importante para asegurar su porvenir y no verla más.

Freya hizo un ademán de protesta, al mismo tiempo que el marino se arrepentía de su generosidad...
¿Por qué favorecer á una mujer que le recordaba la muerte de su hijo?... ¿Qué había de común
entre los dos?... Los viles amores de Nápoles harto los había pagado con su desgracia... Que
cada uno siguiese su destino; pertenecían á mundos distintos... ¿Iba á tener que defenderse
toda su vida de esta hembra pegajosa?

Aparte de esto, no estaba seguro de que ahora dijese verdad... Todo en ella era falso. Ni siquiera
conocía con certeza su verdadero nombre y su existencia pasada...

--¡Márchate!--rugió con tono amenazador--. ¡Déjame en paz!

Tendió sus poderosas manazas hacia ella viendo que se resistía á obedecer. Iba á levantarla
del suelo con rudo tirón, á llevarla como un fardo leve fuera de la cámara, fuera del barco,
arrojándola lejos lo mismo que si fuese un remordimiento.

Pero le inspiró una repugnancia invencible este cuerpo abundante en seducciones: tuvo miedo
á su contacto; quiso huir de las sorpresas eléctricas de su carne... Además, él no iba á maltratarla
á cada encuentro, como un bellaco profesional de los que mezclan el amor y los golpes. Recordaba
con tristeza sus violencias de Barcelona.

Y como Freya, en vez de marcharse, se dejaba caer de nuevo en el diván con un desaliento que
parecía desafiar su cólera, fué él quien huyó para dar fin á la entrevista.

Se introdujo en su camarote, cerrando la puerta de golpe. Esta fuga la sacó á ella de su inercia.
Quiso seguirle con un salto de pantera joven, pero sus manos chocaron contra el obstáculo que
acababa de inmovilizarse, mientras seguían sonando en su interior llaves y cerrojos.

Golpeó desesperadamente la puerta. Sus puños se lastimaron en infructuosos empujones.

--¡Ulises, abre!... ¡Oyeme!

En vano gritó como si diese una orden, exasperándose al no verla obedecida. Su cólera se revolvió
impotente contra la solidez inconmovible de la madera. De pronto empezó á llorar. Se había
ablandado su voluntad al sentirse débil é indefensa como una criatura abandonada. Toda su vida
pareció concentrarla en sus lágrimas y su voz suplicante.

Paseó los dedos por la puerta, palpando las molduras, deslizándolos por las superficies barnizadas,
como si buscase á tientas una rendija, un agujero, algo que le permitiese llegar hasta el hombre
que estaba al otro lado.

Instintivamente dobló sus rodillas, pegando la boca al orificio de la cerradura.

--¡Dueño mío!--murmuró con una voz de pordiosera--. ¡Abre!... No me abandones. Piensa que voy
hacia la muerte si tú no me salvas.

Ferragut la oyó, y para huir de su gemido fué alejándose hasta el fondo del camarote. Luego
abrió el ventano redondo que daba sobre la cubierta, ordenando á un marinero que buscase al
segundo.

--¡Don Antòni! ¡don Antòni!--gritaron varias voces á lo largo del buque.

Llegó Tòni, pegando su cara al redondel para recibir las quejas furiosas de su capitán. «¿Por
qué le habían dejado solo con aquella mujer?... Debían sacarla del buque inmediatamente, aunque
fuese á viva fuerza... El lo mandaba.»

El piloto se alejó con aire azorado, rascándose la barba lo mismo que si acabase de recibir
una orden de difícil ejecución.

--¡Sálvame, amor mío!--seguía gimiendo el susurro implorante--. Olvida quién soy... Piensa
únicamente en la de Nápoles... en la que conociste en Pompeya... Acuérdate de nuestra felicidad
á solas, de las veces que me juraste no abandonarme nunca... ¡Tú eres un caballero!

Calló un momento la voz. Ferragut oyó pasos al otro lado de la puerta. Tòni cumplía sus órdenes.

Pero la súplica volvió á reanudarse á los pocos instantes, reconcentrada, tenaz, atenta únicamente
á su deseo, despreciando los nuevos obstáculos que venían á interponerse entre ella y el capitán.

--¿Tanto me odias?... Acuérdate de la felicidad que te di: tú mismo me juraste que nunca habías
sido tan dichoso. Puedo resucitar otra vez el pasado. Tú no sabes de lo que soy capaz por hacerte
dulce la existencia... ¡Y quieres perderme!...

Sonó un choque en la puerta, un roce de cuerpos que se empujaban, una frotación de lucha contra
la madera.

Tòni había entrado, seguido de Caragòl.

--Ya hay bastante, señora--dijo con voz torva, para disimular su emoción--. ¿No se da cuenta
de que el capitán no quiere verla?... ¿no comprende que está estorbando?... Vamos... ¡arriba!

Intentó ayudarla á incorporarse, separando su boca de la cerradura; pero Freya repelió con
facilidad al vigoroso marino. Parecía falto de fuerzas, sin valor para repetir su ruda acción.
Le inspiraba miedo la hermosura de esta mujer; estaba estremecido aún por el contacto de las
firmes redondeces que acababa de rozar durante la corta lucha. Su virtud soñolienta había sufrido
el tormento de una resurrección sin objeto. «¡Ah, no!... Que se encargasen otros de expulsarla.»

--¡Ulises, me echan!--gritó ella pegando otra vez su boca á la cerradura--. ¿Y tú, amor mío,
lo permites?... ¿tú que tanto me amabas?...

Después de este llamamiento desesperado permaneció silenciosa unos instantes. La puerta se
mantuvo inmóvil: detrás de ella no parecía existir ningún ser viviente.

--¡Adiós!--continuó en voz baja, con la garganta hinchada de sollozos--. Ya no me verás...
Voy á morir pronto: me lo dice el corazón... ¡Moriré por ti!... Tal vez llores algún día pensando
que pudiste salvarme.

Alguien había intervenido para arrancar á Freya de su rebelde inmovilidad. Era Caragòl, solicitado
por los ojos implorantes del piloto.

Sus manazas la ayudaron á levantarse, sin que ella repitiese la protesta que había repetido
á Tòni. Vencida y derramando lágrimas, pareció someterse á la ayuda paternal y los consejos
del cocinero.

--¡Arriba, buena señora!--dijo Caragòl--. Un poco de ánimo y no llore... Para todo hay consuelo
en este mundo.

Encerró en su abultada diestra las dos manos de ella, y pasando el otro brazo por su talle,
la fué dirigiendo poco á poco hacia la salida del salón.

--Crea en Dios--añadió--. ¿Por qué busca al capitán, que tiene allá en su tierra á su mujer
propia?... Otros hombres existen que están libres, y puede usted entenderse con ellos sin caer
en pecado mortal.

Freya no le escuchaba. Cerca de la puerta volvió todavía la cabeza, iniciando un retroceso
hacia el camarote del capitán.

--¡Ulises!... ¡Ulises!--gritó.

--Crea en Dios, señora--dijo otra vez Caragòl, mientras la empujaba con su vientre flácido
y su pecho velludo.

Un propósito caritativo llenó su pensamiento. Tenía el remedio para el dolor de esta mujer
hermosa, que la desesperación había hecho más interesante.

--Venga usted, señora... Hágame caso, hija mía.

Al llegar á la cubierta, la fué guiando hacia sus dominios. Freya se sentó en la cocina, sin
saber con certeza dónde estaba. Vió á través de sus lágrimas á este viejo obeso, de una bondad
sacerdotal, yendo de un lado á otro para reunir botellas y mezclar líquidos, agitando una cuchara
en un vaso con alegre retintín.

--Beba sin miedo... No hay disgusto que resista á esta medicina.

El cocinero le ofreció un vaso; y ella, anonadada, bebió y bebió, contrayendo su rostro por
la intensidad alcohólica del líquido. Seguía llorando, al mismo tiempo que su boca paladeaba
una espesa dulzura. Sus lágrimas fueron cayendo en el brebaje que se deslizaba entre sus labios.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01154</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>471068</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21628</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> In case of attack submarine,
transport carrying guns could come off the line and help patrol armed vessels, giving face to the
enemy. The others should continue its way quietly without worrying about the assault. If the
ship that was ahead or astern was torpedoed had to stop to give assistance. The torpedo and "chaluteros"
be responsible for to save the shipwrecked, whether it was possible. The duty of transportation
was always going forward, blind and deaf, without leaving the training, without stopping, to drive
to the port terminal the fortune he had in his heart.

This march in convoys, imposed by the submarine warfare, was a throwback to the life of the
seas. Ferragut recalled the fleets to sail from other centuries, escorted by ships line, following
its course through ceaseless battles, the voyages of the galleons remote of the Indies, leaving
Sevilla to arrive in flocks to the shores of the New World.

The double row of black helmets with plumes of smoke moved gently in the days bonanza. When the
day was gray, foaming sea, the sky low and hazy atmosphere are spread and reared like a herd
of lambs dark and frightened. The guardians of convoy, three small boats in full swing, they
were the mastiffs guards these cattle ocean, preceding it to scan the horizon, leaving behind him
or marching to their sides in order to keep training. Its lightness and speed made them give
prodigious leaps over the waves. A ribbon of smoke curled to continue its double fireplaces. His
bow, when it was hidden, expelling foam falls, rising to show the beginning of the keel.

At night they sailed all the Halls: A simple lantern to bow to notice marching front and a
rear to indicate the path to the next. These lights were barely visible wan. Suddenly, the boat
had to turn the machine back and ask for direction, seeing that grew larger in the dark silhouette
of the vessel. A few minutes of carelessness, and entered by the stern with a deadly espolonazo.
Al amenguar the march, the captain looked irked back, fearing to turn collide with it still in
line.

They thought of the invisible underwater. Now and then gunshots rang. The escort the convoy pulled
and pulled, going from side to side with agile developments. The enemy had fled, as wolves howl
before the watchful dogs. At other times it was a false alarm, and
wounded with guns, steel whip water in the desert.

There was an annoying enemy that storm that disrupts the convoys, more frightening than torpedoes.
The fog was thick and white as albumin, which fell on the ships, making them sail into blind
in broad daylight, filling unnecessary space siren roars, leaving see the water that sustained
no other boats nearby, which could leave a time to another of the blurry atmosphere, announcing
his appearance with a shock and a big crunch, mortal. So the sailors had to march for days, and when
they finally got rid of this shroud, breathing with the satisfaction of waking up from a nightmare,
another wall Cinderella and nebulous advancing on the water, wrapping
them back into night.

The brave men and serene vowed to see the bar closing endless horizon haze.

Such trips were not like Ferragut. Irritated him straight up like a soldier, having to adapt to
the speed of ships negligible.

Will be even more enraged obliged to obey the commander of the convoy, which was often an old
sailor character authoritarian.

Because of this, one of the arrivals to Marseilles to the maritime authorities said their determination
not to sail more so. They had enough four expeditions. Were good for masters fearful, unable to leave
port if they did not in sight an escort of destroyers, whose crews,
the slightest incident, intended to lay the boats into the water,
taking refuge on the coast.

He felt safer going alone, trusting to his skill, no other help than his deep knowledge of the routes
of the Mediterranean.

The request was granted. He owned the ship, and feared losing their cooperation when scarce both
the means of transport. In addition, the Mare Nostrum, for its speed, deserved to be employed
addition, special services and prompt.

It was in Marseille a few weeks waiting for a shipment of shells, and stroll as always the
Mediterranean capital. The afternoons were spent on the terrace of a cafe in the Cannebière.
The Von Kramer remember sometimes arose in his memory. "Do you have shot ?...» wanted know, but
its findings were not very successful. Councils of war avoided the publicity for their acts of justice.
A dealer friend of Ferragut Marseille remembered that, some months
before, had been executed a German spy caught in the harbor.

Three lines in the newspapers just realizing his death. It was said an official ... And Marseille
went on to talk of war news, while Ulysses thought the run could be none other than Von Kramer.

On
the same afternoon he met. Marched down the Rue Saint-Ferreol, looking storefronts, the cries
of various drivers of cars and cars that do not succeeded at passing their vehicles on the narrow,
crowded road caught his eye. Saw in a carriage to a blonde woman with her back to him, accompanied
by two naval officers English. Freya immediately thought ... His hat, his suit, all he could
distinguish of person, not remembered at all to the other. And yet, when he left the car, no
he came to see the face of this unknown, the image of the adventurous
persisted in his memory.

Finally ended up getting angry with himself, owing to the absurd similarity was found no reason.
How could this English Freya who was with two officers? ... How German refugees in Barcelona
could slip in France, where it was clearly known military police?

... Still irritated him the suspicion that this was like a rest the old love, which made him
see Freya throughout blond woman.

At nine o'clock the next day, when the captain dressed in his cabin
for go ashore, Toni opened the door.

His gesture was gloomy and shy at the same time, as if to give bad news.

- That is there - he said laconically.

Ferragut looked at him quizzically ... Who was "that »?...

- Who will it be?

... The Naples! The blonde demon who brings disgrace!

... Let's see if that witch still leaves us a few weeks, like last
time.

He apologized, as if she had a foul in the service. The vessel was attached to the dock by a walkway
and all he could enter.

The pilot was an enemy of these moorings, which left free passage to the curious and importunate.
When he realized the visit, lady was already in the deck near the cameras. He remembered well the
way of living: wanted to go ahead, but he had made the stop as he
came Caragol to warn Captain.

- Christ! - He murmured -.

Christ! ...

And his surprise, surprise, was not allowed to launch another exclamation.

Then

angry.

- Cast it! ... That the two men grab and put in the dock, even by
main force.

But Toni hesitated, not daring to enforce such orders, and the impetuous Ferragut launched outside
the cabin for himself what he had commanded.

As he passed the hall, someone came at the same time by the side of the deck. Was Caragol trying
to block the way to a woman, but she, mocking their short-sighted eyes, was slipping little
by little from his body and the wooden partition.

To see the captain, Freya ran towards him extending her arms.

- You! - Joyful voice said -. Knew you were here, in spite of these
men claimed Otherwise ... Heart told me ... Good morning, Odysseus!

Caragol turned his eyes toward the spot where he guessed the presence of the second, as if imploring
forgiveness.

With females could not enforce any order ... Toni, meanwhile, seemed embarrassed by this woman
who looked hostile.

The two disappeared. Ferragut could not figure out how the leak was, but he was glad it. He feared
that the new arrival in his presence allude to things of the past.

Long time was watching her. He had thought to recognize back the day before, and now I was sure
I would have gone on with indifference at her head. In fact, Was the same two officers who
accompanied the British? ... He seemed much higher than another, with a thinness that made clear his
skin, giving it a sickly transparency.

The nose was prominent and sharp, his eyes sunken in circles shining blackish their watersheds.

These
eyes began to look to the master humble and pleading.

- You! - Ulises
exclaimed in surprise -.

You! ... What are you doing here? ...

Freya spoke with a shyness servant. Yes, it was she who had known the day before long before
he turned, forming immediately in order to come in search of him. He could hit like last time they
met, she was willing to suffer all ... But with him!

- Save me, Ulysses, take me with you ... I ask this more painfully than in Barcelona.

- How you doing here? ...

She understood the captain's astonishment at finding in enemy territory, the concern felt by
him to see a spy on his ship.

He looked around to be convinced that they were alone, and spoke softly. The doctor had sent
to France to "work" in the ports. He alone could reveal the secret.

Ulysses was indignant at this confidence.

- Go away! - Said in an angry voice -. All I hear from you ... I do not care what's yours, no
I want to know ... Out! Why am I looking for?

But she did not seem disposed to do his bidding.

Instead of leaving, he fell with disappointment in one of the couches of the camera.

- I came - he said - to beg you to save me. I beg you seen ... I'm going to die; I guess my end
is near if you do not me a helping hand, I feel the vengeance of
the mine ... Keep me, Odysseus!

Do not let me return to earth: I have fears ... So I feel safe here,
at your side!

...

Fear, indeed, reflected in her eyes, remembering the last months of
his life Barcelona.

- The doctor is my enemy ... She protected me
so much at one time, leaving me as something old that must be abolished.

I have the certainty that I have condemned in the top ...

He shuddered, remembering the anger of the doctor when, at the back of one of his trips, learned
of the death of his faithful Karl. Captain Ferragut was for her a kind of demon invulnerable
and victorious, it escapes all dangers, killing the servers good cause. First, Von Kramer, now,
Karl ... Like I needed someone to vent his anger, Freya had taken responsibility for all the
misfortunes. For she knew the captain and had mixed in the affairs of "service".

The desire for revenge made her smile at the awesome lady with a fierce
expression.

The Spanish sailor was noted in high place. Precise orders had been given against him. "As
to !...» accomplices Freya are undoubtedly among these accomplices, for daring Ferragut to defend
recalling the tragic death of her son for not doing choir those who
wanted to exterminate them.

Weeks later, the angry doctor had been kind and smiling, as in another
time.

"My dear, it is to give you a tour of France. We need an agent we are aware of movement from
ports of exit and entry of ships to our submersible know where to wait. Marine officers are
gallant, and a woman beautiful may win her affection.

"

She had tried to disobey. Go to France, where his works were known
before of war!

... Back to the danger when they had become accustomed to life in safe neutrals! ... But their
attempts to resist were never carried out. Lacked will: the "service" had become an automaton.

-
And here I am suspecting that maybe marched to death, but to fulfill
the orders that receipt, striving to be enjoyable and thus delay the
fulfillment of his revenge ... I'm like a condemned man who knows
he is going to die and try to be necessary to take a few month sentence.

-
How did you come in France? - Asked him, ignoring his accent painful.

Freya shrugged. In his office is easily changed nationality. It was now public of a Republic
of America. The doctor had given him the necessary papers to crossing the border.

- But here - he continued - I have more secure than in a prison. I have been given the means to enter,
and they alone can make me leave. I am completely in their power.

What will you do to me? ...

The terror had suggested at times desperate resolutions.

Wanted to complain to itself, to appear before the French authorities
telling his story, letting them know the secrets of that era possessed.

But he was afraid of his past: there were many evils I have been doing against this country. Perhaps
the spare his life taking into account the spontaneity of his act, but the prison, the prison with
his hair cut, dressed in rough serge, condemned to silence, perhaps
suffering hunger and cold, he inspired a repulsion invincible ...
No: before death.

He continued his life of espionage, a blind eye to the future, living in the moment This, avoiding
thinking, considering happy when I saw a few days ahead security.

Ferragut encounter with Marseille on a street had revived, giving new hope.

- Get me out of here, keep me with you.

In your ship in the world I can live forgotten, as if dead ... And if you dislike my presence, take
me away from France, let me in a distant country.

Wanted out of this isolation in enemy territory having to obey their superiors, like a caged
animal that receives punctures through the bars. The fear had presentiment of his approaching
death.

- I do not want to die, Ulises! ... I'm not even old to die. I love my body, I am the first my love,
and I am terrified to think that I can be shot.

Went through their eyes a reflection phosphoric teeth chattering collided with terror.

- Do not want to die - repeated -. There are times when I guess I follow and surround me ... Such
Once I have known and await the moment of surprise in the middle of work ... Help me: make me
out of here, my death is certain. I have done so much damage! ...

He paused, as if calculating all the crimes of his former life.

-
The doctor - he went - with patriotic enthusiasm, which inflames to
continue their jobs.

I lack your faith: I am German and I am disgusted to be a spy ... I feel ashamed considering my current
life, I think every night in the outcome of my abominable works; employment calculation can
give to my listings and my reports, I see ships torpedoed ... How many beings have died because
of me? I have visions of my conscience torments me. Save me!

... I can not. I feel a terrible fear. I have so much to atone! ...

She had risen gradually from the couch, and would seek protection
Ferragut towards him arms outstretched, while humble and caressing,
by a desire for seduction which prevailed over all his actions.

-
Let! - Shouted the ocean -.

Do not come closer ... Do not touch me!

He felt the same anger that had made him end his interview brutal
Barcelona.

Was irritated the tenacity of this adventure, which, after tragic influence in his life, wanted
engage it again.

But a cold feeling of restraint and compassion made him speak with
some kindness.

If he needed money to flee, he would give it without any haggling.

Could set the figure, the captain was ready to satisfy all your desires, but nothing to live
together.

We would a large sum to secure his future and not see it.

Freya made a gesture of protest, while the marine regretted his generosity
... Why favor to a woman who reminded him of the death of his son?

... What was common between the two?

... Naples vile sick love had paid with their misfortune ... That each follow his destiny belonged
to different worlds ... Was I going to have to defend lifetime of this female sticky?

Apart from this, I was not sure he really say now ... Everything about her was false. Even certainly
knew his real name and his past life ...

- Go away! - Roared menacingly -.

Leave me alone!

He extended his powerful paws to her seeing that refused to obey.

Would raise soil with rough stretch, to take as a slight burden off camera, off the ship,
throwing away the same as if it were a regret.

But an invincible repugnance inspired this body abundant temptations: he was afraid his contact, wanted
to escape the power of his flesh surprises ... In addition, he was
not going to mistreat at every meeting, as a professional scoundrel
who mix love and bumps.

Remembered sadly its violence in Barcelona.

And as Freya, instead of leaving, he dropped back on the couch with a discouragement seemed
to defy his anger, was he who fled to end the interview.

Entered his cabin, slamming the door shut. This flight took her to it its inertia. He wanted to follow
a young panther jump, but his hands struck the obstacle just immobilized,
while still sounding inside keys and locks.

Desperately hit the door. His fists were injured in unsuccessful pushing.

- Ulysses, open!

... Listen!

In vain he cried as if she gave an order, exasperated at not seeing obeyed. His anger was stirred
powerless against the unyielding strength of wood.

Suddenly he began to mourn. Was softened his will to feel weak and helpless as an abandoned
child. All his life seemed to concentrate on her tears and her voice pleading.

Run your fingers through the door, feeling the moldings, sliding on the painted surfaces, as
if you fumble a crack, a hole, which allowed him to reach the man
I was on the other side.

Instinctively bent his knees, hitting the mouth to the opening of
the lock.

- Owner mine! - A voice murmured beggar -.

Breakthrough! ... Do not forsake me. I think to death if you do not save me.

Ferragut heard, and to escape her moan was away to the back of the
cabin.

Then opened the round window that looked out on the deck and ordered to a sailor who seek to
second.

- Don Antonio!

Antonio! - Shouted several voices throughout the ship.

Toni arrived, sticking his face into the arena to get angry complaints of his captain. "Why what
had been left alone with this woman? ... Should immediately remove
the vessel, although were subjected to violence ... He commanded.
"

The pilot walked away with a bewildered air, scratching his beard
the same as if just received difficult to execute a warrant.

- Save
me, my love - still moaning imploring whisper -. Forget who I am ...
Think Only in Naples ... in which met in Pompeii ... Remember happiness
he alone, of the times I swore never to leave ... You are a gentleman!

He
paused voice. Ferragut heard footsteps on the other side of the door.
Toni fulfill your orders.

But the appeal again to resume a few moments,
concentrated, persistent, attentive only his desire to flout the new
obstacles that came to stand between her and the captain.

- Whether
you hate me? ... Remember the happiness you say, you yourself swore
you'd never been so fortunate. I can rise again the past. You do not
know what I can to make you sweet existence ... And want to miss!
...

There was a crash at the door, a touch of bodies pushing an anti-rub
wood.

Toni had entered, followed by Caragol.

- There's enough, ma'am
- "His voice was grim, to hide his emotion -. Did not realize that
the captain did not want to see? ... Do not you see that is clogging?
... We ... Up!

He tried to help him up, separating the mouth of the
lock, but was repelled with Freya easily to the strong ocean. It seemed
lacking in strength, no courage to repeat his tough action. It was
fearful the beauty of this woman was still shaken by the contact of
firm that just touch curves during the short fight. Her virtue had
been sleepy the torment of a resurrection without object. "Ah, no!
... Operated by other ejecting. "

- Ulysses, throw me! - She cried
again hitting his face to the lock -. And you, my love, allow it?
... So what do you love me? ...

After this desperate appeal was silent
a moment. The door remained motionless behind her did not seem to
be any living being.

- Goodbye - continued quietly, his throat swelling
with sobs -. I do not see ... I am going to die soon: heart tells
me ... I will die for you! ... Maybe someday cry thinking you could
save.

Someone had stepped in to start your rebel Freya immobility.
Was Caragol requested by imploring eyes of the pilot.

His big hands
helps her up, without her repeated protests that he had repeated Toni.
Due and shedding tears, seemed to submit to parental help and advice
Cook.

- Up, good lady! - Said Caragol -. A little encouragement and
do not cry ... To everything there is comfort in this world.

Swollen
right hand locked in her two hands, and passing the other arm around
her waist, the directing was little by little to the departure lounge.

-
Believe in God - he said -. Why look for the captain, who is back
in his land to his wife own? ... Other men there that are free, and
you can communicate with them without falling in mortal sin.

Freya
was not listening. Near the door was still the head, initiating a
reverse to the captain's cabin.

- Ulises! ... Ulises! - Screamed.

-
Believe in God, madam - Caragol said again, while pushing with your
flabby belly and his hairy chest.

A charitable purpose filled his
mind. Had a remedy for pain of this woman beautiful, that desperation
had become more interesting.

- Come on, lady ... Trust me, my child.
On reaching the deck, was leading into his domain. Freya sat in
the kitchen, no know with certainty where he was. He saw through her
tears to this old obese, goodness priests, going from one side to
another to collect bottles and mixing liquids, stirring spoon in a
glass with a merry jingle.

- Drink without fear ... There is anger
that resists to this medicine.

The chef offered him a glass, and
she, shocked, drank and drank, his face contracting by alcoholic strength
of the liquid. Still crying, while savoring mouth a thick sweetness.
Her tears were falling in the brew that slid between his lips</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>