<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04335</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>46761</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23394</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Vino luego un exercito de frayles en filas de dos en dos, blancos, negros, pardos, calzados,
descalzos, con barba, imberbes, con capilla puntiaguda, y sin capilla; iba luego el verdugo;
y detras, en medio de alguaciles y duques, cerca de quarenta personas cubiertas con sacos donde
habia llamas y diablos pintados. Eran estos, o judios que se habian empenado en no renegar
de Moises, o cristianos que se habian casado con sus comadres, o no habian sido devotos de
Nuestra Senora de Atocha, o no habian querido dar dinero a los padres capuchinos. Cantaronse
unas devotisimas oraciones, y luego fueron quemados vivos, a fuego lento, todos los reos; con
lo qual quedo muy edificada la familia real.

Aquella noche, quando me iba a meter en la cama, entraron dos familiares de la inquisicion,
acompanados de una ronda bien armada; dieronme un carinoso abrazo, y me llevaron, sin hablarme
palabra, a un calabozo muy fresco, donde habia una esterilla para acostarse, y un soberbio
crucifixo. Aqui estuve seis semanas, pasadas las quales me mando a pedir por favor el senor
inquisidor que me viese con el. Estrechome en sus brazos con paternal carino, y me dixo que
sentia muy de veras que estuviese tan mal alojado, pero que estaban ocupados todos los quartos
de aquella santa casa, y que esperaba otra vez darme mejor habitacion. Preguntome luego con
no menos amor, si sabia porque estaba alli. Respondi al varon santo, que sin duda por mis pecados.
Eso es, hijo mio: ?pero por que pecados? habladme sin rezelo. Por mas que me mataba, no atinaba,
hasta que la caridad del piadoso inquisidor me dio alguna luz. Acordeme al fin de mis imprudentes
palabras, y no fui condenado mas que a exercicios, la disciplina, y treinta mil reales de multa.
Llevaronme a dar las gracias al inquisidor general, sugeto muy afable, que me pregunto que
tal me habia parecido su fiesta. Rospondile que era deliciosisima, y fui a dar priesa a mis
companeros a que saliesemos del pais, puesto que es tan ameno. Habian estos tenido lugar para
informarse de todas las grandes proezas executadas por los Espanoles en obsequio de la religion,
y leido las memorias del celebre obispo de Chiapa, donde cuenta que degollaron, quemaron o
ahogaron unos diez millones de idolatras Americanos por convertirlos a nuestra santa fe. Bien
creo que pondera algo el obispo; pero aunque se rebaxe la mitad de las victimas, todavia queda
acreditado un zelo portentoso.

Atormentabame sin cesar el ardor de viajar, y estaba resuelto a concluir mi peregrinacion de
Europa por la Turquia. Encamineme a esta, con firme proposito de no decir otra vez mi parecer
acerca de las fiestas que viese. Estos Turcos, dixe a mis companeros, son unos paganos que
no han recibido el santo bautismo, y sin duda han de ser mas crueles que los santos inquisidores;
callemonos pues, mientras vivamos entre Moros.

Con este animo iba; pero quede atonito al ver en Turquia muchos mas templos cristianos que
en la isla donde habia nacido, y hasta crecidas congregaciones de frayles, a quienes dexaban
en paz rezar a la virgen Maria, y maldecir a Mahoma, unos en griego, otros en latin, y otros
en armenio. iQue honrada gente son los Turcos! exclame. Los cristianos griegos y los latinos
eran irreconciliables enemigos en Constantinopla, y se perseguian estos esclavos unos a otros
como perros que se muerden en la calle, y que separan a palos sus amos. Entonces el gran visir
protegia a los Griegos: el patriarca griego me acuso de que habia cenado con el patriarca latino,
y fui condenado por el divan a cien palos en la planta de los pies, que rescate a precio de
quinientos zequies. Al otro dia ahorcaron al gran visir; y al tercero su sucesor, que no fue
ahorcado hasta de alli a un mes, me condeno a la misma multa por haber cenado con el patriarca
griego: de suerte que me vi en la triste precision de no frequeentar la iglesia griega ni la
latina. Por consolarme arrende una hermosa circasiana, que era la mas carinosa persona a solas
con un hombre, y la mas devota en la mezquita. Una noche, entre los suaves gustos de amor,
exclamo dandome un abrazo: Alah, Ilah, Alah, que son las palabras sacramentales de los Turcos;
yo pense que fuesen las del amor, y dixe con mucho carino: Alah, Ilah, Alah. Ha, dixo la mora,
loado sea Dios misericordioso; ya sois Turco. Respondile que daba las gracias al Senor que
me habia dado fuerza para serlo, y crei que era muy dichoso. Por la manana vino a circuncidarme
el iman; y poniendo yo alguna dificultad, me propuso el cadi del barrio, hombre de buena composicion,
que me mandaria empalar. Por fin libre mi prepucio y mi trasero por mil zequies, y me escape
corriendo a Persia, resuelto a no oir en Turquia misa griega ni latina, y a no decir nunca
Alah, Ilah, Alah en los ratos de los gustos de amor.

Asi que llegue a Ispahan, me preguntaron si era del partido del carnero negro o del carnero
blanco. Respondi que lo mismo me daba uno que otro, con tal que fuera tierno. Se ha de notar
que todavia estaba dividida la Persia en dos facciones, la del carnero negro y la del blanco.
Creyeron que hacia yo burla de ambos partidos, y me encontre en un terrible compromiso a la
puerta misma de la ciudad, del qual sali pagando una buena cantidad de zequies, por no tener
que ver con carneros.

No pare hasta la China, donde llegue con un interprete que me dixo que era el pais donde se
podia vivir alegre y libre: los Tartaros que le habian invadido todo lo ponian a sangre y fuego,
mientras que los reverendos padres jesuitas por una parte, y los reverendos padres dominicos
por otra, decian que ganaban almas para el cielo, sin que nadie lo advirtiese. Nunca se han
visto convertidores mas zelosos; unos a otros se perseguian con el mas fervoroso ahinco, escribian
a Roma tomos enteros de calumnias, y se trataban de infieles y prevaricadores por un alma.
Habia entre ellos una horrorosa disputa acerca del modo de hacer la cortesia; los jesuitas
querian que los Chinos saludaran a sus padres y madres a la moda de la China, y los dominicos
que fuera a la moda de Roma. Sucediome que los jesuitas creyeron que yo era un dominico, y
le dixeron a Su Magestad Tartara que era espia del Papa. Dio comision el consejo supremo a
un primer mandarin para que me arrestara; el qual mando a un alguacil, que tenia a sus ordenes
quatro corchetes, que me prendiesen, y me atasen con toda ceremonia. Conduxeronme, despues
de ciento y quarenta genuflexiones, ante Su Magestad, que me pregunto si era yo espia del Papa,
y si era cierto que hubiese de venir este principe en persona a destronarle. Respondile que
el Papa era un clerigo de mas de setenta anos; que distaban sus estados mas de quatro mil leguas
de los de su Sacra Magestad Tartaro-China; que su exercito era de dos mil soldados que montaban
la guardia con un para-aguas; que no destronaba a nadie, y que podia Su Magestad dormir sin
miedo. Esta fue la menos fatal aventura de mi vida, pues no hicieron mas que enviarme a Macao,
donde me embarque para Europa.

Fue preciso calafatear el navio en la costa de Golconda, y me aproveche de la oportunidad para
ver la corte del gran Aurengzeb, de quien se contaban entonces mil portentos. Estaba este monarca
en Deli, y goce el gusto imponderable de contemplarle facha a facha el dia de la pomposa ceremonia
en que recibio la celestial dadiva que le enviaba el cherif de la Meca, y era la escoba con
que se habia barrido la santa casa, la caaba, la belh-Alah: escoba que es el simbolo que alimpia
todas las suciedades del alma. Parece que no la necesitaba Aurengzeb, que era el varon mas
religioso de todo el Indostan, puesto que habia degollado a uno de sus hermanos, y dado veneno
a su padre, y habia hecho perecer en un patibulo a veinte rajaes y otros tantos omraes; pero
no queria decir eso nada, y no se hablaba de otra cosa que de su devocion, a la qual la de
ningun otro era comparable, como no fuese la de la sacra magestad, del serenisimo emperador
de Marruecos, Mulcy Ismael, el qual cortaba unas quantas cabezas todos los viernes, despues
de hacer oracion.

No articule yo palabra, que me habian escarmentado los viages, y sabia que no era juez competente
para fallar entre estos dos augustos soberanos. Confieso empero que un frances mozo, con quien
estaba alojado, falto al respeto debido a los emperadores de Indias y de Marruceos, diciendo
con mucha imprudencia que en Europa habia soberanos muy pios que gobernaban con acierto sus
estados, y frequeentaban tambien las iglesias, sin quitar por eso la vida a sus padres y hermanos,
ni cortar la cabeza a sus vasallos. Nuestro interprete dio cuenta en lengua india de las expresiones
impias de este mozo. Instruido yo con lo que en otras ocasiones me habia sucedido, mande ensillar
mis camellos, y me fui con el frances. Luego supe que aquella misma noche habian venido a prendernos
los oficiales del gran Aurengzeb; y no habiendo encontrado mas que al interprete, fue este
ajusticiado en la plaza mayor, confesando sin lisonja todos los palaciegos que era muy justa
su muerte.

Quedabame por ver la Africa para disfrutar de todas las delicias de nuestro hemisferio, y con
efecto la vi. Unos corsarios negros apresaron mi embarcacion. Quejose amargamente mi patron,
y les pregunto por que violaban las leyes de las naciones. Fuele respondido por el capitan
negro: Vuestra nariz es larga, y la nuestra chata; vuestro cabello es liso, y nuestra lana
riza; vuestra cutis es de color ceniciento, y la nuestra de color de ebano; por consiguiente,
en virtud de las sacrosantas leyes de naturaleza, siempre debemos ser enemigos. En las ferias
de Guinea nos comprais, como si fueramos acemilas, para forzarnos a que trabajemos en no se
que faenas tan penosas como ridiculas; a vergajazos nos haceis horadar los montes para sacar
una especie de polvo amarillo que para nada es bueno, y que no vale, ni con mucha, un cebollino
de Egipto. Asi quando os encontramos nosotros, y podemos mas, os obligamos a que labreis nuestras
tierras, y de lo contrario os cortamos las narices y las orejas.

No habia replica a tan discreto razonamiento. Fui a labrar el campo de una negra vieja por
conservar mis orejas y mi nariz, y al cabo de un ano me rescataron. Habiendo visto todo quanto
bueno, hermoso y admirable hay en la tierra, me determine a no ver mas que mis dioses penates:
me case en mi pais, fui cornudo, y vi que era la mas grata condicion de la vida humana.

Fin de los viages de Escarmentado.

       *       *      *       *       *

MICROMEGAS,

HISTORIA FILOSOFICA.

       *       *       *       *       *

CAPITULO PRIMERO.

Viage de un morador del mundo de la estrella Sirio al planeta de Saturno.

Habia en uno de los planetas que giran en torno de la estrella llamada Sirio, un mozo de mucho
talento, a quien tuve la honra de conocer en el postrer viage que hizo a nuestro mezquino hormiguero.
Era su nombre Micromegas, nombre que cae perfectamente a todo grande, y tenia ocho leguas de
alto; quiero decir veinte y quatro mil pasos geometricos de cinco pies de rey.

Algun algebrista, casta de gente muy util al publico, tomara a este paso de mi historia la
pluma, y calculara que teniendo el Senor Don Micromegas, morador del pais de Sirio, desde la
planta de los pies al colodrillo veinte y quatro mil pasos, que hacen ciento y veinte mil pies
de rey, y nosotros ciudadanos de la tierra no pasando por lo comun de cinco pies, y teniendo
nuestro globo nueve mil leguas de circunferencia, es absolutamente indispensable que el planeta
donde nacio nuestro heroe tenga cabalmente veinte y un millones y seiscientas mil veces mas
circunferencia que nuestra tierra. Pues no hay cosa mas comun ni mas natural; y los estados
de ciertos principillos de Alemania o de Italia, que pueden andarse en media hora, comparados
con la Turquia, la Rusia, o la America espanola, son una imagen, todavia muy distante de la
realidad, de las diferencias que ha establecido la naturaleza entre los seres.

Es la estatura de Su Excelencia la que llevamos dicha, de donde colegiran todos nuestros pintores
y escultores, que su cuerpo podia tener unos cincuenta mil pies de rey de circunferencia, porque
es muy bien proporcionado. Su entendimiento es de los mas perspicaces que se puedan ver; sabe
una multitud de cosas, y algunas ha inventado: apenas rayaba con los doscientos y cincuenta
anos, siendo estudiante en el colegio de jesuitas de su planeta, como es alli estilo comun,
adivino por la fuerza de su inteligencia mas de cincuenta proposiciones de Euclides, que son
diez y ocho mas que hizo Blas Pascal, el qual habiendo adivinado, segun dice su hermana, treinta
y dos jugando, llego a ser, andando los anos, harto mediano geometra, y malisimo metafisico.
De edad de quatrocientos y cincuenta anos, que no hacia mas que salir de la ninez, diseco unos
insectos muy chicos que no llegaban a cien pies de diametro, y se escondian a los microscopios
ordinarios, y compuso acerca de ellos un libro muy curioso, pero que le traxo no pocos disgustos.
El mufti de su pais, no menos cosquilloso que ignorante, encontro en su libro proposiciones
sospechosas, mal-sonantes, temerarias, hereticas, o que olian a heregia, y le persiguio de
muerte: tratabase de saber si la forma substancial de las pulgas de Sirio era de la misma naturaleza
que la de los caracoles. Defendiose con mucha sal Micromegas; se declararon las mugeres en
su favor, puesto que al cabo de doscientos y veinte anos que habia durado el pleyto, hizo el
mufti condenar el libro por calificadores que ni le habian leido, ni sabian leer, y fue desterrado
de la corte el autor por tiempo de ochocientos anos.

No le afligio mucho el salir de una corte llena de enredos y chismes. Compuso unas decimas
muy graciosas contra el mufti, que a este no le importaron un bledo, y se dedico a viajar de
planeta en planeta, para acabar de perfeccionar su razon y su corazon, como dicen. Los que
estan acostumbrados a caminar en coche de colleras, o en silla de posta, se pasmaran de los
carruages de alla arriba, porque nosotros, en nuestra pelota de cieno, no entendemos de otros
estilos que los nuestros. Sabia completamente las leyes de la gravitacion y de las fuerzas
atractivas y repulsivas nuestro caminante, y se valia de ellas con tanto acierto, que ora montado
en un rayo del sol, ora cabalgando en un cometa, andaban de globo en globo el y sus sirvientes,
lo mismo que revolotea un paxarillo de rama en rama. En poco tiempo hubo corrido la via lactea;
y siento tener que confesar que nunca pudo columbrar, por entre las estrellas de que esta sembrada,
aquel hermosisimo cielo empireo, que con su anteojo de larga vista descubrio el ilustre Derham,
teniente cura [Footnote: Sabio Ingles, autor de la Teologia astronomica, y otras obras, en
que se esfuerza a probar la existencia de Dios por la contemplacion de las maravillas de la
naturaleza.]. No digo yo por eso que no le haya visto muy bien el Senor Derham; Dios me libre
de cometer tamano yerro; mas al cabo Micromegas se hallaba en el pais, y era buen observador:
yo no quiero contradecir a nadie.

Despues de muchos viages llego un dia Micromegas al globo de Saturno; y si bien estaba acostumbrado
a ver cosas nuevas, todavia le paro confuso la pequenez de aquel planeta y de sus moradores,
y no pudo menos de soltar aquella sonrisa de superioridad que los mas cuerdos no pueden contener
a veces. Verdad es que no es Saturno mas grande que novecientas veces la tierra, y los habitadores
del pais son enanos de unas dos mil varas, con corta diferencia, de estatura. Riose al principio
de ellos con sus criados, como hace un musico italiano de la musica de Lulli, quando viene
a Francia; mas era el Sirio hombre de razon, y presto reconocio que podia muy bien un ser que
piensa no tener nada de ridiculo, puesto que no pasara de seis mil pies su estatura. Acostumbrose
a los Saturninos, despues de haberlos pasmado, y se hizo intimo amigo del secretario de la
academia de Saturno, hombre de mucho talento, que a la verdad nada habia inventado, pero que
daba muy lindamente cuenta de las invenciones de los demas, y que hacia regularmente coplas
chicas y calculos grandes. Pondre aqui, para satisfaccion de mis lectores, una conversacion
muy extrana que con el senor secretario tuvo un dia Micromegas.

CAPITULO II.

Conversacion del morador de Sirio con el de Saturno.

Acostose Su Excelencia, acercose a su rostro el secretario, y dixo Micromegas: Confesemos que
es muy varia la naturaleza. Verdad es, dixo el Saturnino; es la naturaleza como un jardin,
cuyas flores.... Ha, dixo el otro, dexaos de jardinerias. Pues es, siguio el secretario, como
una reunion de rubias y pelinegras, cuyos atavios..... ?Que me importan vuestras pelinegras?
interrumpio el otro. O bien como una galeria de quadros, cuyas imagenes...... No, Senor, no,
replico el caminante, la naturaleza es como la naturaleza. ?A que diablos andais buscando esas
comparaciones? Por recrearos, respondio el secretario. Si no quiero yo que me recreen, lo que
quiero es que me instruyan, repuso el caminante. Decidme lo primero quantos sentidos tienen
los hombres de vuestro globo. Nada mas que setenta y dos, dixo el academico, y todos los dias
nos lamentamos de tanta escasez; que nuestra imaginacion se dexa atras nuestras necesidades,
y nos parece que con nuestros setenta y dos sentidos, nuestro anulo, y nuestras cinco lunas,
no tenemos lo suficiente; y es cierto que no obstante nuestra mucha curiosidad y las pasiones
que de nuestros setenta y dos sentidos son hijas, nos sobra tiempo para aburrirnos. Bien lo
creo, dixo Micromegas, porque en nuestro globo tenemos cerca de mil sentidos, y todavia nos
quedan no se que vagos deseos, no se que inquietud, que sin cesar nos avisa que somos chica
cosa, y que hay otros seres mucho mas perfectos. He hecho algunos viages, y he visto otros
mortales muy inferiores a nosotros, y otros que nos son muy superiores; mas ningunos he visto
que no tengan mas deseos que verdaderas necesidades, y mas necesidades que satisfacciones.
Acaso llegare un dia a un pais donde nada haga falta, pero hasta ahora no he podido saber del
tal pais. Echaronse entonces a formar conjeturas el Saturnino y el Sirio; pero despues de muchos
raciocinios no menos ingeniosos que inciertos, fue forzoso volver a sentar hechos. ?Quanto
tiempo vivis? dixo el Sirio. Ha, muy poco, replico el hombrecillo de Saturno. Lo mismo sucede
en nuestro pais, dixo el Sirio, siempre nos estamos quejando de la cortedad de la vida. Menester
es que sea esta universal pension de la naturaleza. iAy! nuestra vida, dixo el Saturnino, se
cine a quinientas revoluciones solares (que vienen a ser quince mil anos, o cerca de ellos,
contando como nosotros). Ya veis que eso casi es morirse asi que uno nace: es nuestra existencia
un punto, nuestra vida un momento, nuestro globo un atomo; y apenas empieza uno a instruirse
algo, quando le arrebata la muerte, antes de adquirir experiencia. Yo por mi no me atrevo a
formar proyecto ninguno, y me encuentro como la gota de agua en el inmenso oceano; y lo que
mas sonroxo me causa en vuestra presencia, es contemplar quan ridicula figura hago en este
mundo. Replicole Micromegas: Si no fuerais filosofo, tendria, rezelo de desconsolaros, diciendoos
que es nuestra vida setecientas veces mas dilatada que la vuestra; pero bien sabeis que quando
se ha de restituir el cuerpo a los elementos, y reanimar baxo distinta forma la naturaleza,
que es lo que llaman morir; quando es llegado, digo, este momento de metamorfosis, poco importa
haber vivido una eternidad o un dia solo, que uno y otro es lo mismo. Yo he estado en paises
donde viven las gentes mil veces mas que en el mio, y he visto que todavia se quejaban; pero
en todas partes se encuentran sugetos de razon, que saben resignarse, y dar gracias al autor
de la naturaleza, el qual con una especie de maravillosa uniformidad ha esparcido en el universo
las variedades con una profusion infinita. Asi por exemplo, todos los seres que piensan son
diferentes, y todos se parecen en el don de pensar y desear. En todas partes es la materia
extensa, pero en cada globo tiene propiedades distintas. ?Quantas de estas propiedades tiene
vuestra materia? Si hablais de las propiedades sin las quales creemos que no pudiera subsistir
nuestro globo como el es, dixo el Saturnino, no pasan de trescientas, conviene a saber la extension,
la impenetrabilidad, la mobililad, la gravitacion, la divisibilidad, etc. Sin duda, replico
el caminante, que basta ese corto numero para el plan del criador en vuestra estrecha habitacion,
y en todas cosas adoro su sabiduria, porque si en todas veo diferencias, tambien contemplo
en todas proporciones. Vuestro globo es chico, y tambien lo son sus moradores; teneis pocas
sensaciones, y goza vuestra materia de pocas propiedades: todo eso es disposicion de la Providencia.
?De que color es vuestro sol bien examinado? Blanquecino muy ceniciento, dixo el Saturnino,
y quando dividimos uno de sus rayos, hallamos que tiene siete colores. El nuestro tira a encarnado,
dixo el Sirio, y tenemos treinta y nueve colores primitivos. En todos quantos he examinado,
no he hallado un sol que se parezca a otro, como no se ve en vuestro planeta una cara que no
se diferencie de todas las demas.

Despues de otras muchas queestiones analogas, se informo de quantas substancias distintas se
conocian en Saturno, y le fue respondido que habia hasta unas treinta: Dios, el espacio, la
materia, los seres extensos que sienten, los seres extensos que sienten y piensan, los seres
que piensan y no son extensos, los que se penetran, y los que no se penetran, etc. El Sirio,
en cuyo planeta hay trescientas, y que habia en sus viages descubierto hasta tres mil, dexo
extraordina- riamente asombrado al filosofo de Saturno. Finalmente, habiendose comunicado uno
a otro casi todo quanto sabian y muchas cosas que no sabian, y habiendo discurrido por espacio
de toda una revolucion solar, se determinaron a hacer juntos un corto viage filosofico.

CAPITULO III.

Viage de los dos habitantes de Sirio y Saturno

Ya estaban para embarcarse nuestros dos caminantes en la atmosfera de Saturno con muy decente
provision de instrumentos de matematicas, quando la dama del Saturnino, que lo supo, le vino
a dar amargas quejas. Era esta una morenita muy agraciada, que no tenia mas que mil y quinientas
varas de estatura, pero que con sus gracias reparaba lo chico de su cuerpo. iHa cruel! exclamo,
despues que te he resistido mil y quinientos anos, quando apenas me habia rendido, no habiendo
pasado arriba de cien anos en tus brazos, ime abandonas por irte a viajar con un gigante del
otro mundo! Anda, que no eres mas que un curioso, y nunca has estado enamorado; que si fueras
Saturnino legitimo, mas constante serias. ?Adonde vas? ?que quieres? menos errantes son que
tu nuestras cinco lunas, y menos mudable nuestro anulo. Esto se acabo; nunca mas he de querer.
Abrazola el filosofo, lloro con ella, puesto que filosofo; y la dama, despues de haberse desmayado,
se fue a consolar con un petimetre.

Partieronse nuestros dos curiosos, y saltaron primero al anulo que encontraron muy aplastado,
como lo ha adivinado un ilustre habitante de nuestro globulo; y desde alli anduvieron de luna
en luna. Paso un cometa por junto a la ultima, y se tiraron a el con sus sirvientes y sus instrumentos.
Apenas hubieron andado ciento y cincuenta millones de leguas, se toparon con los satelites
de Jupiter. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10957</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>147012</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21420</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Then came an army of friars in rows of two by two, white, black, brown, shoes, barefoot, bearded,
beardless, with pointed hood, and no chapel was then the executioner; and behind, in the midst
of sheriffs and dukes, about forty people covered with sacks where had painted flames and devils.
Were these, or Jews who had insisted on not deny Moses, or Christians who had married with
their Wives, or had not been devoted Nuestra Senora de Atocha, or had not wanted to give money
to the Capuchin Fathers. Cantaronse a most devout prayers, and then were burned alive over a
slow fire, all prisoners, with qual it built the family remained very real.

That night, when I was going to get into bed, came two relatives of the Inquisition accompanied
by a round well-armed; dieronme a loving hug, and took me, without speaking word, a very cool
dungeon where he had a mat to lie down, and a superb crucifix. Here I was six weeks past the
quale sent me to ask please sir Inquisitor saw me with him. Estrechome in his arms with paternal
affection, and told me that I felt very sincerely that was so ill housed, but they were busy
all the quartos of that holy house, and hoped to give me more room again. Ask me later with no
less love, if he knew it was there. Replied the holy man, no doubt for my sins. That is, my
son:? But that sin? Speak without rezelo. For more than kill me, could not manage, until the charity
of the pious inquisitor gave me some light. I remembered the end of my reckless words, and I was
not convicted of more than Exercises, discipline, and thirty thousand pieces of fine. They carried
on to thank the Grand Inquisitor, sugeto very friendly, I wonder what I had thought that her party.
Deliciosisima Rospondile was, and I went for my haste saliesemos companions to the country,
since it is so enjoyable. These had taken place to informed of all the great deeds delivered
again by the Spaniards for the sake of religion, and read the memories of the famous bishop of
Chiapas, where it has beheaded, burned or drowned idolatrous ten million Americans to convert them
to our holy faith. Well I think it weighs something the bishop, but rebaxe although half of
the victims, is still proved a prodigious zeal.

Atormentabame burning constantly traveling, and was determined to
end my pilgrimage to Europe for Turkey.

Encamineme to this, with a firm purpose of not saying my mind again about the parties he had
seen. These Turks, dixe my companions, they're pagans have not received the holy baptism, and
certainly should be more cruel than the holy inquisitors callemonos then, while living among
Moros.

This would encourage, but was astonished to see many more temples in Turkey Christians on the
island where he was born, and even grown congregations friars, who dexaban in peace to pray
to the Virgin Mary, and Muhammad curse, some in Greek, some in Latin, and other in Armenian.
iQue honest people are the Turks! I exclaimed. The Greek and Latin Christians irreconcilable
enemies in Constantinople, and these slaves are chasing each other like dogs that bite in the
street, and that separate suits their masters. Then the grand vizier protected the Greeks: the
Greek Patriarch, who had accused me of dinner with the Latin patriarch, and was convicted of the
divan a hundred sticks on the soles of the feet, to rescue price five hundred sequins. Hanged
the next day the Grand Vizier, and the third his successor, which was not hung up there a month,
I condemn the same fine for having dinner with the patriarch Greek so that I saw in the sad precision
frequeentar not the Greek church or America. For comfort rented a beautiful Circassian, who
was the most affectionate person alone with a man, and the most devout at the mosque. One night,
the soft taste of love exclaimed giving me a hug: Allah, Ilah, Allah, are the sacramental
words of the Turks; I thought you were the love, And I said with much love: Allah, Ilah, Allah.
Ha, he said the delay, Merciful God be praised, and you are Turkish. I replied that he thanked
the Lord that had given me strength to be, and I thought it was very happy. Morning came to
get circumcised the magnet, and I have difficulty putting, I proposed the cadi of the neighborhood,
a man of good composition, I would send impaled. Free at last my foreskin and my back for a thousand
sequins, and I escape running Persia, resolved not to hear Mass in Turkey Greek or Latin, and
if ever Allah, Ilah, Allah in the moments from the likes of love.

So get to Ispahan, I asked if it was the party of black sheep or ram white. Replied that the
same one that gave me another, which makes it tender. It must be noted that Persia was still
divided into two factions, the ram's black and white. I believe that by mocking both parties,
and I found myself in a terrible commitment to gate of the city, of whom I left paying a lot
of sequins, not having to do with sheep.

Do not stop to China, which comes with an interpreter, he said that I was the country where
could live happy and free: the Tatars had invaded it they placed all blood and fire, while the reverend
Jesuit Fathers on the one hand, and the reverend fathers Dominicans second, they said winning
souls for heaven, without anybody noticing. Have never been more zealous converters, are chasing
each other with the most fervent ardor, wrote Rome whole volumes of libel, and tried by a faithless
infidels and soul. There was an awful row between them about how to do the courtesy, the Jesuits
The Chinese wanted to greet their parents to the fashion of China, and Dominicans it was the
fashion of Rome. Sucediome the Jesuits thought I was a Dominican, and they told him that His
Majesty was Tartara spy of the Pope. Commission gave the supreme council a first mandarin
to arrest me, the qual command a sheriff, who had at his command four brackets, which seized
me, and I bound with all ceremony. Conduxeronme, after hundred and forty prostrations, before
His Majesty, I wonder if I was a spy of the Pope and if it was true that the prince had to
come in person to dethrone him. I replied that Pope was a clergyman of more than seventy years,
that his statements were far more than four thousand miles those of his Sacred Majesty Tartaro-China,
that his army was two thousand soldiers standing guard with a para-waters not anyone dethroned,
and I could sleep without His Majesty fear. This was the least fatal adventure of my life, as did
more than send me to Macao, where I embarked for Europe.

It was necessary to caulk the ship off the coast of Golconda, and
I take advantage of the opportunity to see the court of the Aurengzeb,
of whom there were then a thousand wonders.

It was this monarch in Delhi, and enjoy the taste imponderable façade to façade behold the day
of the pompous ceremony that received the heavenly gift that he sent the sheriff of Mecca, and was
the broom which had swept the holy house, the Kaaba, the Belho-Allah: broom is a symbol that alimpia
all the filth of the soul. It appears that did not need Aurengzeb, who was the male more Hindustan
religious whole, since it had beheaded one of his brothers, and given poison his father, and had
destroyed a scaffold twenty Omra rajas and many others, but That did not mean anything, and
nobody talked about anything but his devotion to whom is the of no other comparable, as it was
not that of the sacred majesty of the Most Serene Emperor Morocco, Mulcy Ishmael, qual a quantas
heads cut every Friday, after to prayer.

No article I word that I had chastened the voyages, and knew it was not competent judge to adjudicate
between these two August sovereign.

I confess, however, that a French boy, who locked, lacking the respect due to the emperors of India
and Marruceos, saying with great imprudence in Europe had very principles governing sovereign
rightly his states, and also frequeentaban churches, without taking life so their parents and
siblings or cut the head of his vassals. Our language interpreter realized expressions india
impias of this boy. I trained with him on other occasions I had happened, send saddle camels, and
went with the French. Later I learned that night had come and fetch him great Aurengzeb officials, and
not having found more than the interpreter, was this executed in the main square, without flattery
confessed all that was very fair palace his death.

Quedabame to see the Africa to enjoy all the delights of our hemisphere, and saw effect. Black
corsairs seized my vessel.

My boss complaining bitterly, and ask them for violating the laws of nations. He was answered
by Captain black: Your nose is long, and our flat, your hair is smooth, and our wool curl, your
skin is ashen-gray color and our Ebony, therefore under the sacrosanct laws of nature, we
must always be enemies. At fairs You give us of Guinea, as if we were pack animals, to force
us to work in not that such tough tasks as ridiculous, to vergajazos haceis we pierce the mountains
to get a kind of yellow powder that nothing is good, and that's no good, or very, a chive Egypt.
Quando So you find us, and we can only, I force them to labreis our land, and if not you cut
the noses and ears.

There was replicated as discrete reasoning. I went to the tilth of a black woman by keep my ears and
my nose, and after a year I rescued.

Having seen all quanto good, beautiful and admirable in the earth, I determined to see no
more than my household gods: I married in my country, I was a cuckold, and saw it was the most
pleasant condition of human life.

End of the voyages of castigating.

       

* * * * *

       

MICROMEGAS,

Philosophical history.

* * * * *

CHAPTER ONE.

Journey of a denizen of the world of the star Sirius to the planet Saturn.

There was one of the planets revolving around the star called Sirius, a boy much talent, whom I
had the honor of meeting in the last journey he made to our paltry nest. Micromegas was his
name, a name that falls perfectly to all large, and had eight leagues high, I mean twenty-four
thousand five steps geometric calipers.

Some algebraist, caste people are very useful to the public, to take
this step in my story pen, and calculated that taking the Lord Don
Micromegas, Sirius country dweller, from soles to occiput twenty-four
thousand feet, making one hundred and twenty thousand feet King, and
we citizens of the land going through the community of five feet,
and taking our globe nine thousand miles in circumference, it is absolutely
essential that the planet where our national hero has fully twenty-one
million six hundred thousand times circumference of our earth.

Well, nothing is more common and more natural, and states certain princelings of Germany or Italy,
which may beating in half an hour, compared with Turkey, Russia, or Spanish America, is an image,
still very distant from Indeed, the differences that nature has established among men.

It is the height of His Excellency that we said, where all our painters colegiran and sculptors,
whose body might be about fifty thousand feet in circumference king because is very well proportioned.
His understanding of the most insightful is that you can see he knows a multitude of things, and
some have invented: only bordered with the two hundred and fifty years, while a student at the
Jesuit college of your planet, as there style is common, I guess by the force of his intelligence
over fifty propositions of Euclid, which are eighteen but did Blaise Pascal, the qual having guessed,
according to her sister, thirty and two playing, became, walking the years, fed medium geometry,
and malisimo metaphysical. Age of four hundred and fifty years, but not to get out of childhood,
dissects a very small insects that did not reach a hundred feet in diameter, and the microscopes
were hiding regular, and wrote a book about them very funny, but that he brought not a few surprises.
The mufti of his country, not less ticklish than ignorant, found in his book proposals suspicious,
ill-sounding, rash, heretical, or smelling of heresy, and he chased the death, then tried to
see if the substantial form of fleas from Sirius was of the same nature that of the snails. Micromegas
Defendiose salty, declared the women in their favor, because after
two hundred and twenty years which had lasted the lawsuit, did Mufti
condemn the book for qualifiers that he had not read nor could read,
and was banished court time the author for eight years.

Not much afflicted him out of a court full of intrigue and gossip. He composed a few tenths
very funny against the mufti, that this does not give a damn, and devoted himself to travel
planet to planet, only to perfect his reason and his heart, as they say. Those who are used to
walking in car cufflinks, or chaise was amazed at the carriages up there, because we, in our
ball of mud, do not understand other styles than ours. Fully knew the laws of gravitation and the
forces attractive and repulsive our walker, and he used them so well that now mounted in a sunbeam,
now riding a kite, balloon balloon went he and his servants, as well as a paxarillo flits from
branch to branch. Soon there run the Milky Way; and I regret to confess that never could descry, among
the stars that is planted, that beautiful sky empyrean, who with his spyglass discovered the illustrious
Derham, curate [Footnote: English Wise, author of Theology astronomical, and other works,
who strives to prove the existence of God by the contemplation of the wonders of nature.].
I do not say why that has not been very well Mr Derham, God forbid size of committing mistake,
but after Micromegas was in the country, and was a good observer: I do not want to contradict
anyone.

After many journeys came a day Micromegas the globe of Saturn, and although he was used to see
new things, yet we stop confusing the smallness of this planet and its inhabitants, and could not
release the smile of superiority that can not contain more sane sometimes. Truth is that Saturn is
nine hundred times larger than the earth, and the inhabitants the country are dwarfs of about two
thousand yards, with a short difference in height. Riose to top of them with their servants,
as does an Italian musician Lulli's music, when it comes to France, but Sirius was the man of
reason, and quickly recognized that one could very well be that thought to have nothing of ridiculous,
since there from six thousand feet height. Acostumbrose to Saturninus, after having been shocked,
and became a close friend of the secretary of the Academy of Saturn, a man of great talent,
which in truth nothing was invented, but very nicely gave account of the inventions of others,
and to regularly couplets girls and big load. I'll post here, to the satisfaction of my readers,
a conversation very surprised that the secretary had one day Mr.
Micromegas.

CHAPTER II.

Sirius Talk to the inhabitants of Saturn.

HE went to bed, went up to his face to the secretary, and said Micromegas: We confess that is
very diverse nature. Truth is, he said the Saturnino; is nature as a garden, whose flowers ....
Ha, he said the other, DEXA gardening. As it is, followed the Secretary, as a reunion of blonde
and brunette, whose adornments ..... What do I care about your brunette? interrupted the other.
Or as a gallery of squares, whose images ...... No, Sir, no, replied the traveler, nature is
as nature. ? A what the hell you walk looking for those comparisons? For to rejoice, 'said the
secretary. If I do not want to recreate me, what I want you to teach, "said the traveler. Tell
me what senses are first quantos men of your globe. Nothing more than seventy-two, he said the
academic and everyday We complain about such a shortage, that our imagination is dexa back
our needs, and we believe that with our seventy-two senses, our annulled, and our five moons
do not have enough, and it is true that despite our great curiosity and passion that of our
seventy-two senses are daughters, we have plenty of time to get bored. Well what I think,
he said Micromegas, because on our globe we have about a thousand ways, and we still are not
that vague desires, not that concern, which constantly tells us that we are girl thing, and
that other beings much more perfect. I made a few voyages, and have seen other very inferior
to us mortals, and others who are far superior, but I have seen no with no more desires than real
needs, and more needs satisfaction. Perhaps a day will END a country where nothing is needed,
but I have not been told of this country. Then threw themselves to form conjectures on Saturnino
and Sirius, but after many no less ingenious reasoning uncertain, was forced to re-establish facts.
? Quanto long live? he said the Syrian. Ha, very little, "replied the man from Saturn. The same
is true in our country, 'said the Syrian, we are always complaining about the shortness of
life. Must is that it is universal pension of nature. Alas! our lives, 'said the Saturnino is five
hundred revolutions of the sun movie (coming to be fifteen thousand years, or near, counting
as us.) You see that it is almost die so that one is born: it is our existence one point, a
moment our lives, our globe an atom, and each instruction is just beginning something, when
death snatches before experience. As for me I dare not any draft form, and I am like a drop
of water in the vast ocean, and what more sonroxo cause me in your presence, quan look ridiculous
in this figure do world. Micromegas answered her: If you were not a philosopher, would have, the
apprehension of desconsolaros, telling that is our life seven hundred times more extensive
than yours, but you well know that when has been to restore the body to the elements, and revive
differently Baxo nature that is what you call die, Quando is reached, say, this moment of metamorphosis,
it matters little have lived forever or one day alone, two is the same. I have been in countries
where people live a thousand times more than mine, and I saw that still complained, but are
everywhere sugetos of reason, who can resign, and give thanks to the author of nature, which with
a wonderful kind of uniformity has spread in the universe varieties with an endless profusion.
So par example, all people who think they are different, and they all look in the gift of
thinking and desire. Everywhere is the matter extensive, but each has different properties globe.
? Qantas of these properties have your area? If you speak of the properties without the quale
we could not survive our globe as he is, he said the Saturnino, do not exceed three hundred, to wit
the extension, impenetrability, mobililad, gravity, divisibility, etc.. Without doubt, replied
the walker, which is sufficient for such a short number of breeder plan your intimate room, and in
all things I love his wisdom, because if all I see differences, also provides in all proportions.
Your globe is small, and so are its inhabitants, you have few feelings, and your subject has
a few properties: this is the disposal of Providence. ? Color is your sun well tested? Very ashen white,
'said the Saturnino, and when we divide one of its rays, we find that has seven colors. The
strip our flesh, he said the Syrian, and we thirty-nine primary colors. In all quanta have examined,
I have not found a sun that looks like another, and not on your planet is a face that no differs
from all others.

After many queestiones analog, was reported to be different substances quantas Saturn knew, and
was answered that he had until about thirty, God, space, matter, people who feel large, extensive
beings who feel and think, people they think and are not widespread, which penetrate, and not
penetrate, and so on. The Sirius world in which there are three hundred, and that he had discovered
in his travels up to three thousand, I leave necessarily extraordinary philosopher stunned
to Saturn. Finally, having communicated a quanto another almost all knew and did not know many
things, and having discoursed for space of an entire solar revolution, were determined to make
a short journey together philosophical.

CHAPTER III.

Journey of two people from Sirius and Saturn

They were to board our two walkers in the atmosphere of Saturn with a very decent provision of mathematical
instruments, when the lady of Saturninus, who knew, it came to make bitter complaints. This was
a very graceful brunette, who had no more than fifteen hundred feet high, but repaired with
the boy through his body. iha cruel! exclaimed, I've resisted after fifteen hundred years, when
I had just given up, having no above last hundred years in your arms, go ime abandoned by traveling
with a giant another world! Come on, you're not more than a curious, and have never been in love,
that if you were Saturnino legitimate, most constant serious. Where are you going? ? You want? less
wandering is that you our five moons, and less changeable our annulled.

This is just, I want anymore. Philosopher embraced her, weeping with her, as philosopher, and
the lady, after having fainted, went to console with a dude.

They cut our two curious and jumped first to nullify they found very flattened as you guessed
a famous inhabitant of our globule, and from there they went to moon
in moon. A comet passing close to the last, and threw him with his
servants and instruments. Just had walked a hundred and fifty million
miles, they encountered satellites Jupiter</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>