<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01476</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>4291</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>740</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Recordando la obscuridad
de su origen, se la echaron en rostro y calificaron a su madre de la más infame manera.

El cordero se convirtió entonces de repente en bravo león. Por dicha, no tenía armas, pero
le valieron los puños. Con certero y fuerte golpe derribó por tierra, maltrecho y con la boca
ensangrentada, al primero que le había ofendido. Después siguió peleando él solo contra otros
tres o cuatro, apoyado contra el muro y acosado por ellos.

Fue todo tan rápido, que nadie había acudido a interponerse y a restablecer la paz, cuando
otro de los novicios, de nobilísima alcurnia francesa, intervino en la contienda, diciendo:

--Es cobardía que vayáis tantos contra él; apartáos; dejádmele a mi solo; yo le castigaré como
merece.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02205</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>26688</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>679</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Recalling the darkness of its origin,
is her cast in face and rated her mother of the most infamous way.

The Lamb then became suddenly bravo Leon. For such, it had no weapons, but earned him the cuffs.
With strong and accurate punch shot down by Earth, battered and bloodstained mouth, to the first
who had offended him.

After continued fighting him only three or four, supported against the wall and harassed by them.
It was all so fast that no one had come to be lodged and to restore
peace, when another of the novices, of noble French lineage, took
part in the race, saying:-is cowardice go goals against him; depart
leave me to my only; I will discipline as it deserves.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>