<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10507</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>1007338</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>745</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Si Fernando quería, aún era tiempo. Guardaba ella en un bolso pendiente
de la diestra su dinero, sus alhajillas, todo lo de algún valor que podía servir para la fuga.
Él no tenía más que ordenar que echasen su equipaje a tierra: Nélida abandonaría gustosa el
suyo. Les era fácil escabullirse en la confusión del desembarco.

Ojeda, en vez de contestar afirmativamente, parecía compadecerse de ella, con la misma conmiseración
que si fuese una enferma. ¡Ah, cabeza loca!... Bastante la había hablado en la noche anterior
para hacerla comprender lo absurdo de su proposición. Luego se había marchado cabizbaja, sin
invitarle a que la siguiese a su camarote y sin mostrar deseos de ir al suyo, con visible mal
humor, pero convencida en apariencia. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03346</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>22506</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>676</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> If Fernando wanted, there was still time. He kept it in a bag yet the right
hand of your money, alhajillas, everything of any value that could be used for escape. He had
only ordered to cast their luggage to the ground: It willingly abandon Nelida yours. I was
easy to slip in the confusion of the landing.

Ojeda, instead of answering yes, he seemed to pity her, with the same compassion that if a patient.
Ah, crazy head! ... Pretty had spoken the night before to make her understand the absurdity
of the proposal. Then he had gone head down, without invite you to follow her to her cabin and
showing no desire to go to him, with obvious bad humor, but apparently
convinced</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>