<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01622</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>396065</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17686</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El niño que Julia cuidaba y que había, por decir así, adoptado,
había muerto el día antes por la noche. Magdalena se hizo conducir cerca del ataúd que contenía
el pequeño cadáver y quiso besarlo; al regresar lloró abundantemente y repitió la frase mi
hijo con dolor tan agudo que me dio a conocer hasta muy lejos el alcance de una pena que roía
su existencia y de la cual estaba implacablemente celoso.

Muy temprano me despedí de Julia y dirigí al señor D'Orsel palabras de agradecimiento que procuré
decir con la mayor serenidad posible. Después, no sabiendo en qué ocupar el día y no teniendo
interés, por decir así, en el empleo de una vida que sentía desprenderse de mí minuto a minuto,
fui a ponerme de codos en la balaustrada que caía sobre los fosos y allí permanecí no sé cuánto
tiempo. No sabía en donde estaba Magdalena. De cuando en cuando me parecía oír su voz en los
corredores o verla pasar de un patio a otro, vagando también ella, sin más objeto que moverse.
Había en la base de una de las torrecillas a la manera de una covacha medio obstruida que en
otros tiempos servía de puerta de escape. El puente que la unía a los paseos del parque estaba
destruido. No quedaban de él más que tres pilastras, en parte sumergidas, que el agua cenagosa
del foso ensuciaba de residuos espumosos. No sé qué idea me vino de esconderme allí por el
resto del día. Pasé del uno al otro pilar y me escondí en aquel recinto ruinoso, los pies tocando
la corriente en la semioscuridad lúgubre del vasto y profundo foso por donde corrían las aguas
del lavadero. Dos o tres veces vi a Magdalena que salía y marchaba hacia las alamedas como
quien busca a alguien. Desapareció y volvió otra vez, vaciló entre tres o cuatro caminos que
conducían del parterre a los confines del parque y al fin tomó por uno de ellos, cubierto de
olmos, que terminaba en los estanques. De un salto pasé de una a otra orilla y la seguí. Iba
de prisa, su sombrero de campo mal asegurado sobre las orejas, envuelta en un amplio cachemira
que ceñía al cuerpo como si tuviera mucho frío. Volvió la cabeza al advertir que me acercaba,
de pronto se volvió, desanduvo lo andado, pasó junto a mí sin mirarme, ganó la escalinata del
parterre y subió. La alcancé cuando llegaba a la puerta del saloncito que le servía de tocador
en el cual acostumbraba pasar el día.

--Ayúdeme usted a plegar mi chal--me dijo.

Tenía el alma y los ojos en otra parte. La ancha tela multicolor estaba entre nosotros plegada
en el sentido de su longitud y ya no formaba más que una banda estrecha de la cual cada uno
sosteníamos un extremo. Sea por torpeza o por desfallecimiento, la prenda se escapó de las
manos de Magdalena. Dio un paso, se tambaleó primero hacia atrás, luego hacia adelante y cayó
en mis brazos desvanecida. La agarré, la sostuve algunos segundos así, pegada contra mi pecho,
la cabeza vuelta, los ojos cerrados, los labios fríos, medio muerta y enajenada al influjo
de mis besos.

De pronto una terrible contracción la estremeció, abrió los ojos, se enderezó sobre la punta
de los pies para llegar a mi altura y arrojándose a mi cuello con toda su fuerza fue ella a
su vez la que me besó.

La agarré de nuevo, la reduje a defenderse como una presa que se debate contra un abrazo desesperado.
Tuvo la noción de que estábamos perdidos y lanzó un grito. Vergüenza me da el decirlo: aquel
grito de verdadera agonía despertó en mí el sólo instinto que me quedaba de hombre: la piedad.
Comprendí que la mataba; no distinguía bien si se trataba de su honor o de su vida. No tengo
por qué vanagloriarme de un acto de generosidad que fue casi involuntario, tan poca parte le
correspondió en él a la verdadera conciencia humana. Solté la presa como una bestia que ha
dejado de morder. La querida víctima hizo un supremo esfuerzo. Era trabajo inútil: yo no la
tenía ya. Entonces con un extravío que me ha hecho estimar lo que es el remordimiento de una
mujer honrada, con un espanto que me habría probado, si hubiera estado en situación de reflexionar,
a qué grado de relajamiento me veía ella reducido, como si instintivamente hubiera comprendido
que ya no había para nosotros ni discernimiento del deber, ni consideraciones, ni respeto,
que aquella conmiseración de puro instinto era sólo un accidente que podía desmentirse, con
un gesto que me espantó, que aun envuelve estos viejos recuerdos en un mundo de terrores y
de vergüenza, Magdalena se dirigió rápidamente hacia la puerta andando de espaldas sin apartar
de mí los ojos, como se procede con un malhechor, ganó el pasillo y una vez en él se volvió
y echó a correr.

Yo tenía perdido el conocimiento aunque me mantenía de pie. Como pude me arrastré hasta mi
habitación; sólo tenía un afán, que no me encontraran desmayado en la escalera. Llegado que
hube delante de mi puerta, aun antes de poder abrirla, ya no me fue posible sostenerme más.
Maquinalmente me aseguré de que nadie había en el corredor. El último sentimiento que aun conservé
un instante fue el de que Magdalena estaba en salvo, y me desplomé sobre el suelo.

Allí mismo me recobré una o dos horas después, ya de noche, con el recuerdo incoherente de
una escena espantosa. La campana anunciaba que la comida estaba pronta y hube de bajar. Me
movía, tenía las piernas libres, pero me parecía como si hubiera recibido un golpe en la cabeza.
Gracias a aquella parálisis, muy real, experimentaba una sensación general de gran dolor, pero
no pensaba en ello. El primer espejo al cual me miré, me puso de manifiesto la faz extrañamente
demudada de un fantasma, algo parecido a mí que apenas podía reconocer. Magdalena no acudió
al comedor y me era casi indiferente que estuviera en él o en otra parte. Julia, cansada, apesadumbrada
o inquieta por su hermana, y muy probablemente llena de sospechas, porque tratándose de aquella
singular niña clarividente y reservada todas las suposiciones eran permitidas. Julia no debía
tampoco reunirse con nosotros en el salón. Pasé, pues, solo con el señor D'Orsel, casi la mitad
de la velada; estaba inerte, insensible, y como si se me hubiera helado la sangre; tan poco
sentido me quedaba para reflexionar y tan exhausto de fuerzas estaba para moverme.

Eran cerca de las diez cuando entró Magdalena, cambiada hasta dar miedo, desconocida, con el
aspecto de un convaleciente a quien la muerte ha tocado de cerca.

--Padre mío--dijo con acento de inflexible audacia.--Necesito estar sola un momento con el
señor de Bray.

El señor D'Orsel se levantó sin vacilar, besó fraternalmente a su hija y salió.

--¿Usted partirá mañana?--me dijo, permaneciendo de pie como yo estaba también.

--Sí--le contesté.

--¡Y no volveremos a vernos más!

Nada repliqué.

--Jamás--continuó,--¿lo entiende usted? jamás. He puesto entre nosotros el único obstáculo
que puede separarnos sin idea de retorno.

Me arrojé a sus pies, la tomé las manos sin que resistiera, sollozando. Tuvo un momento de
debilidad que le cortó la palabra, retiró las manos y me las volvió a dar tan pronto como hubo
recobrado su firmeza.

--Yo haré todo lo posible por olvidarle. Usted olvídeme. Eso le será más fácil todavía. Cásese,
más adelante, cuando usted quiera. No imagine que su esposa pueda tener celos de mí, porque
cuando eso pudiera suceder yo estaré muerta o seré feliz--concluyó, con un estremecimiento
que en poco estuvo no la hiciera caer.--Adiós.

Yo estaba de rodillas, los brazos extendidos, esperando una frase más dulce que ella no pronunciaba.
Una postrera reacción de debilidad o de lástima se la arrancó.

--¡Mi pobre amigo! Era fatal llegar a esto. ¡Si supiera usted cuánto le amo! No se lo habría
dicho a usted ayer: hoy puedo confesarlo puesto que es la palabra prohibida que nos separa.

Ella, extenuada poco hacía, había hallado por milagro no sé yo qué recurso de virtud que le
prestaba fuerza suficiente. Yo no tenía ninguna.

Me parece que aún añadió dos o tres palabras que no entendí; luego se alejó dulcemente como
una visión que se desvanece y no la volví a ver, ni aquella noche, ni al siguiente día, ni
nunca más.

Partí al romper el día sin ver a nadie. Evité atravesar París y me hice llevar directamente
a la casa que en un extremo suburbio habitaba Agustín. Era domingo y le hallé con su familia.

Al primer golpe de vista comprendió que me había sucedido alguna desgracia. Supuso que había
muerto Magdalena porque en su perfecta honradez de hombre y de marido, no concebía mayor desventura.
Cuando le referí el verdadero accidente que me reducía a una de esas situaciones que no se
confiesan nunca, me dijo:

--Desconozco esa clase de penas, pero le compadezco con toda el alma.

Y nunca he dudado que me compadeció desde el fondo del corazón, a poco que razonara sobre los
peores desastres que podía presumir en el porvenir incierto de su propia vida.

Trabajaba cuando le sorprendí. Su mujer estaba cerca de él y tenía en el regazo un niñito de
seis meses que les había nacido durante mi destierro. Eran dichosos. Su situación prosperaba:
pude advertirlo en diversas señales de relativa opulencia. La noche fue espantosa: una tempestad
de fin de otoño duró sin interrupción desde la tarde hasta después del amanecer. En el monótono
arrullo de aquel constante y largo rumor del viento y de la lluvia, no hice más que pensar
en el tumulto que producirían en torno a la alcoba y al sueño de Magdalena, si es que dormía.
Mi fuerza de reflexión no iba más allá de esa sensación pueril y puramente física. Disipada
la tempestad, Agustín me obligó a salir desde por la mañana. Podía disponer de una hora antes
de volverse a París. Me llevó al bosque, devastado por el viento de la noche; el agua corría
aún por los senderos anegados y arrastraba las últimas hojas del año.

Caminamos así largo rato antes de que yo pudiera recoger la sombra de una idea lúcida entre
las determinaciones urgentes que me habían conducido a casa de Agustín. Me acordé al fin de
que tenía que despedirme de él. Al principio creyó que se trataba de una resolución desesperada
nacida del insomnio, que no resistiría a la acción de prudentes consideraciones; pero; cuando
se convenció de que mi determinación databa de más lejos, que era el resultado de reflexiones
sin réplica y que la llevaría a cabo más tarde o más temprano, ya no discutió ni la opinión
que de mí mismo tenía yo formada, ni el juicio que había formado respecto de mi época y me
dijo sencillamente:

--Pienso y razono sobre poco más o menos como usted. Me reconozco poca cosa aunque no me considero
muy inferior a la mayoría de las gentes; pero no tengo el derecho que usted tiene de ser consecuente
hasta lo extremo. Usted deserta modestamente; yo me quedo, no por fanfarronería sino por necesidad
y antes que eso por deber.

--Estoy muy cansado y de todos modos necesito reposo.

Nos separamos en París diciéndonos «hasta la vista» como se hace por lo general cuando costaría
mucho esfuerzo pronunciar un adiós definitivo, pero sin prever ni el lugar ni el tiempo en
que podríamos encontrarnos otra vez. Yo tenía pocos asuntos que arreglar y de ellos se encargó
mi criado. Fui tan sólo a despedirme de Oliverio. Se preparaba a abandonar Francia. No me interrogó
acerca de mi permanencia en Nièvres: con sólo verme había adivinado que todo estaba concluido.

No había motivo para hablarle de Julia; él no tenía por qué decirme nada respecto a Magdalena.
Los lazos que nos habían unido por espacio de más de diez años acababan de romperse a la vez,
a lo menos para largo tiempo.

--Trata de ser feliz--me dijo, como si no contara con eso ni para mí ni para él.

Tres días después de mi partida de Nièvres estaba en Ormessón. Pasé la noche cerca de la señora
de Ceyssac, para la cual mi regreso puso en claro muchas cosas, y me dio a entender que había
lamentado mis errores frecuentemente con la tierna lástima de mujer piadosa y casi madre.

Al otro día, sin tomarme una hora de verdadero descanso en aquella deplorable carrera que me
conducía a la yacija como animal herido que se desangra y no quiere desfallecer en medio del
camino; al otro día por la tarde, casi entrada la noche, llegué a Villanueva. Me apeé próximo
ya a la aldea: el coche siguió por la carretera y yo tomé un camino de travesía que me condujo
a mi casa por las marismas.

Hacía cuatro días y cuatro noches que un dolor fijo refrenaba mi corazón y me tenía los ojos
tan secos como si jamás hubiera llorado. Al dar el primer paso en el camino de Trembles tuve
como un recrudecimiento de recuerdos que hizo más acerbo aquel dolor, pero menos tirante.

Hacía mucho frío. La tierra estaba dura, la noche casi había cerrado, de modo que la línea
de las costas y el mar formaban un solo horizonte compacto y casi negro. Un postrer residuo
de luz rojiza se extinguía poco a poco y palidecía de minuto en minuto. A lo lejos, cerca de
la escarpa, pasó un carromato; percibíase el traqueteo y el chirrido de las ruedas sobre el
suelo congelado. El agua de las marismas estaba helada; sólo en algunos sitios, anchos charcos
de agua dulce que no se había helado todavía, continuaban moviéndose suavemente y permanecían
blanquecinos. Dio las seis el reloj de la iglesia de Villanueva. Tan profundos eran ya el silencio
y la oscuridad, que parecía la media noche. Caminaba por encima de los caballones de la tierra
anegada y no sé por qué me vino a la memoria que otro tiempo en aquellos sitios mismos y en
noches semejantes había cazado patos. Oía por encima de mi cabeza el rápido susurro que producen
esas aves volando muy de prisa. Vi un fogonazo y la explosión de un disparo me detuvo. Un cazador
salió de su escondite, bajó hacia la marisma y oí el chapotear de sus pies en el agua; otro
le habló. En aquel cambio de palabras breves y pronunciadas en voz baja, pero que la noche
hacía muy claras, distinguí un timbre de voz que me impresionó.

--¡Andrés!--grité.

Hubo un momento de silencio.

--¡Andrés!--grité de nuevo.

--¿Qué?--me replicó el cazador. Y ya no pude dudar.

Andrés dio algunos pasos hacia donde yo estaba. Le veía apenas aunque sobrepasaba casi con
todo su cuerpo la oscura barranca. Avanzaba lentamente, casi a tientas, por aquel camino hollado
por las patas de los animales, repitiendo: «¿Quién está ahí? ¿Quién me llama?» con creciente
emoción y como si cada momento vacilara menos para reconocer al que le llamaba cuando le creía
tan lejos.

--¡Andrés!--le dije por tercera vez cuando ya no le quedaba dar más que dos o tres pasos.

--¿Cómo? ¿Qué?... ¡Ah, señor, señor Domingo!--dijo dejando caer su escopeta.

--Sí, soy yo, yo mismo, mi viejo Andrés.

Me arrojé en brazos de mi viejo servidor. Al fin de tanta compresión mi corazón, por sí mismo,
estalló v se dilató libremente en sollozos.

XVIII

Domingo había terminado su relato. Se detuvo después de estas últimas palabras, pronunciadas
con la precipitación de un hombre que se apresura, y aquella expresión de pudor entristecido
que sigue generalmente a las expansiones demasiado íntimas. Lo que semejantes confidencias
debieron costarle a una conciencia sombría y por tan largo tiempo cerrada, adivinábalo yo y
se lo agradecía con un ademán conmovido al cual sólo respondía él con una inclinación de cabeza.
Había abierto la carta de Oliverio cuya fúnebre despedida presidía, por decir así, a esta relación
y estaba de pie, los ojos vueltos a la ventana en la cual se encuadraba un tranquilo horizonte
de llanura y de aguas. Permaneció así algún tiempo guardando embarazoso silencio que no quise
romper. Estaba pálido, su fisonomía ligeramente alterada por el cansancio o rejuvenecida por
los resplandores apasionados de otra época, recobraba poco a poco su edad, su expresión peculiar
y su aspecto de gran serenidad. El día avanzaba a medida que la paz de los recuerdos se establecía
también en su rostro. Las sombras iban invadiendo el interior polvoriento y ahogado de la pequeña
habitación en donde se terminaba aquella larga serie de evocaciones de las cuales más de una
había sido dolorosa. De las inscripciones de la pared ya no se distinguía casi nada. La imagen
interior lo mismo que la anterior palidecían al mismo tiempo como si todo aquel pasado resucitado
por casualidad volviese a entrar en el mismo instante y para no volver a salir, en el vago
desvanecimiento de la noche y del olvido.

Las voces de los labradores que pasaban a lo largo de las paredes del parque nos sacaron a
los dos de un apuro real, la duda de callar o reanudar una conversación truncada.

--He aquí la hora de bajar--dijo Domingo, y le seguí hasta la granja en la cual todas las tardes
a aquella misma hora tenía cuidados de vigilancia que llenar.

Los bueyes volvían del trabajo y aquél era el momento en que la granja se animaba. Uncidos
por dos o tres parejas, porque a causa de la pesadez de las tierras mojadas se hacía necesario
triplicar las yuntas, llegaban arrastrando el timón del arado, el hocico hinchado y húmedo,
los cuernos bajos, las fauces agitadas, con barro hasta en el vientre. Los animales de reserva
que no habían trabajado aquel día, mugían en los establos esperando la llegada de sus activos
compañeros. Más allá el rebaño de ovejas, ya encerrado, se removía en el corral, los caballos
piafaban y relinchaban al sentir que el forraje caía en las escalerillas por encima de los
pesebres.

Los trabajadores se alinearon junto al amo, las cabezas descubiertas y con aspecto cansado.

Domingo inquirió minuciosamente si algunos instrumentos de labranza de nueva aplicación habían
dado los resultados que se esperaba; después dio sus órdenes para el día siguiente; las multiplicó,
sobre todo, con referencia a las semillas, y comprendí que no todo el grano cuya distribución
señalaba, estaba destinado a sus propios campos: había mucho perdido, adelantos que hacía o
limosnas.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04163</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>156271</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15565</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Julia took care of the child and had, so to speak, adopted had died
the day before evening. Magdalena was driving near the coffin containing the little corpse and
tried to kiss him, to return wept and repeated the phrase my child with acute pain as I announced
far and wide scope of a gnawing pain that their existence and which was bitterly jealous.

I left early and went to Julia M. D'Orsel words of thanks which I tried say with the greatest serenity
possible. Then, not knowing how to fill the day and not having interest, so to speak, in the
use of a life that I felt detached from minute to minute, I went to put her elbows on the railing
that fell on the trenches and stayed there do not know how time. I did not know where it was Magdalena.
From time to time I could hear his voice in view corridors or moving from one court to another,
it also wandering without purpose other than to move. There at the base of one of the turrets
in the manner of a cave half blocked in other times served as a door to escape. The bridge that
linked the park rides was destroyed. It were not more than three pillars, partly submerged, the
muddy water soiled waste pit sparkling. I do not know what idea came to hide there for the rest
of the day. I went from one to another pillar and hid in that room dilapidated, foot tapping
the current in the dismal gloom of the vast and deep pit where the water ran laundry. Two or three
times I saw Magdalena came out and marched to the malls as who is looking for someone. Disappeared
and returned again, hesitated between three or four roads leading from the parterre to the
confines of the park and finally took one of them covered elms, which ended in ponds. I spent
a jump from one to the other side and followed her. Was quickly, his secured bad field hat over
his ears, wrapped in a cashmere wide that hugged the body like you have very cold. He turned
his head to see that I approached suddenly turned and retraced his steps, passed me without looking
at winning the steps of and rose parterre. I caught when he reached the door of the parlor that
served as a toilet in which I used to spend the day.

- You help me fold my shawl - I said.

He was the soul and eyes elsewhere. The wide color fabric was folded with us in the direction
of its length and it was not just a narrow band which each we held one end. Either by apathy
or weakness, the garment is slipped through Magdalena hands. He took a step backwards first staggered,
then fell forward and fainted in my arms. I grabbed it, held it a few seconds so glued to my chest,
head back, eyes closed, cold lips, half dead and alienated the influence my kisses.

Suddenly a terrible contraction shook her, opened his eyes, sat up on the tip toes to reach up
and throwing my arms around my neck with all her strength she went to turn kissed me.

I grabbed her again, reduced it to defend himself like a dam that is being discussed against a desperate
embrace. He had the notion that we were lost and cried. I feel ashamed to say it: that cry of
agony awakened in me that I was just instinct of man's mercy. I realized that the killing, did
not distinguish whether it was his honor or his life. I have no why boast of an act of generosity
that was almost involuntary, so small a part you it corresponded to the true human consciousness.
I dropped the dam as a beast that has stopped biting. The dear victim made a supreme effort.
Work was useless: I do not already had. Then with a loss that has made me estimate what is
the remorse of a honest woman with a fear that I would have tried, had I been in a position
to reflect what degree of relaxation I saw her small, as if she understood instinctively that there
was for us or discernment of duty, no consideration or respect, that this sympathy of pure instinct
was just an accident that could deny, with a gesture that startled me, that still surrounds
these old memories in a world of terror and shame, Magdalena moved quickly toward the back
door without walking away Me eyes, as we proceed with a criminal, he won the aisle and once
again he and ran.

I had lost consciousness while I remained standing.

As I dragged myself to my room, only had one desire, that I found collapsed on the stairs.
Arrived I had my door, even before opening it, and I was unable to sustain more. Mechanically,
I made sure nobody was in the corridor. The last sentiment that still retains a moment was
that Madeleine was safe, and I collapsed on the floor.

Right there I recovered one or two hours, at night, with the memory inconsistent a dreadful
scene. The bell announced that dinner was ready and had to go down. I moved, his legs were
free, but it seemed as if he had been struck in the head. Thanks to that paralysis, very real, he
felt a general feeling of great sorrow, but not thought about it. The first mirror which looked
at me, showed me the face strangely a haggard ghost, something like that could hardly recognize
me. Magdalena did not attend the dining room and I was almost immaterial whether it was or
elsewhere. Julia, tired, sorry or worried about her sister, and probably full of suspicion, because in
that case unique clairvoyant girl and reserved all the assumptions were allowed. Julia was not
not join us in the lounge. I had therefore only to Mr. D'Orsel, nearly half of the evening, was
inert, insensible, and as if I had frozen the blood, so little sense to think I was so exhausted
and was force to move.

It was about ten when he entered Magdalene, changed to be scary, unknown, with aspect of a convalescent
to whom death has touched.

- My father - said with a tone of unyielding courage .-- I need to
be alone for a moment with M. de Bray.

Mr. D'Orsel rose without hesitation, he kissed his daughter and fraternal
left.

- Do you leave tomorrow? - I said, standing as I was too.

-
Yes - I answered.

- And we will not see each other again!

Nothing I said.

- Never - continued - what do you mean? ever. I put the only obstacle between us that no idea
can separate return.

I threw myself at her feet, took his hands without resist, sobbing. Had a moment of weakness that
cut him short, took his hands and give me them back as soon as there regained its strength.

-
I will do my best to forget. You olvídeme. That will be easier still. Get married, later,
when you want.

Do not imagine that his wife might be jealous of me because when that might happen I'll be dead or I
will be happy - concluded with a thrill that before was not brought
down .-- Farewell.

I was kneeling, arms outstretched, waiting for a sweeter phrase that she uttered. A last reaction
of weakness or pity snatched.

- My poor friend! Achieve this was fatal. If you knew how much I love him! I would not told
you yesterday, today I can confess because it is the forbidden word
between us.

She recently was exhausted, had found a miracle I do not know what that resource under lent strong
enough. I had none.

I think that even added two or three words that I did not understand,
then walked away sweetly as a vision that fades away and not see her
again, or that night or the next day or anymore.

At daybreak I left without seeing anyone.

Avoided through Paris and became lead directly home that lived in a suburb far Augustine. It
was Sunday and found him with his family.

At first glance I realized that something terrible had happened. Assumed that there Magdalena died
because his perfect honesty of a man and husband, could not conceive of greater misery. When
I told him the true accident that reduced me to one of those situations that are not never confess,
I said:

- I do not know that kind of punishment, but I pity you with all my heart.

And I never doubted that I was sorry from the bottom of the heart, little to reason about worst
disasters that could assume the uncertain future of his own life.

He worked when he was surprised. His wife was near him in her lap a little boy six months had
been born during my exile. They were happy. His situation was thriving: I could see several signs
of relative affluence. The night was terrifying: a storm end of autumn lasted without interruption
from the afternoon until after dawn. In the monotonous lullaby of that constant and long sound
of the wind and rain, but did not think in the tumult that occur
around the room and the dream of Magdalena, where he slept.

My strength was not thinking beyond the puerile and purely physical sense. Dissipated the storm, Augustine
forced me out since the morning. Could have an hour before to return to Paris. I took the forest, ravaged
by the night wind, the water ran trails still flooded and swept the last leaves of the year.

And walked a long time before I could pick the shade of a lucid idea
among urgent determinations had led me to the home of Augustine.

I remembered to order I had to say goodbye to him. At first he thought it was a desperate resolution
born from insomnia, do not resist the action of prudential considerations, but, when became
convinced that my determination dated back further, which was the result of reflections no reply
and that would take place later or earlier, and did not discuss or opinion that I myself had formed,
and the trial that had formed on my time and I simply said

- I think and reason about more or less like you. I admit not much but I do not think much lower
than most people, but I have no right you have to be consistent to
the extreme.

You defects modestly, I'm staying, not bragging but by necessity
and before that as a duty.

- I am very tired and need rest anyway.

We parted in Paris saying "au revoir" as is usually done when cost
much effort to pronounce a final farewell, but provide neither the
place nor the time we could meet again.

I had few issues to fix and charge them my servant. I was only to say goodbye to Oliver. He
was preparing to leave France. I asked about my stay in Nièvre: just me had guessed that all
was over.

There was no reason to speak of Julia, he did not need to say anything
about Magdalena.

The ties that had joined us for about ten years had just broken at the same time at least for
a long time.

- Try to be happy - I said, as if not count on it for me or for him.

Three days after my departure was Ormesson Nièvre. I spent the night near Mrs. of Ceyssac, to
which my back made it clear many things and made me understand that there often regretted my
mistakes with the tender pity pious woman and almost mother.

The next day, not take me an hour's rest in this deplorable race I leading to litter like a wounded
animal that bleeds and does not falter in the middle of way, the next day afternoon, almost into
the night, I came to Villanueva. I got out near and the village: the car continued down the
road and I took a road trip that took me my home in the marshes.

For four days and four nights a restraining fixed pain my heart and eyes were as dry as if he
had never cried. By taking the first step on the road had Trembles as a resurgence of memories
that pain was most intense, but less tight.

It was very cold.

The ground was hard, night had almost closed, so that the line the
coast and the sea horizon formed a single compact and almost black.

A last residue red light was dying slowly and pale minute by minute.

In the distance, near the escarpment, he spent a wagon; perceived the clatter and rattling
of the wheels on the frozen soil. The water of the marsh was frozen, and only in some places, wide
puddles fresh water was not frozen yet, still moving slowly and remained whitish. The clock
struck six of the Church of Villanueva. So deep was the silence and and darkness, which seemed
to midnight.

He walked over the ridge of land flooded and not know why I was reminded
of another time on those sites themselves and nights like he had hunted
ducks.

Heard above my head that produce rapid whisper these birds flying
very fast.

I saw a flash and the explosion of a shot stopped me.

A hunter came out of hiding, down to the marsh and I heard the splashing of his feet in the water,
another spoke.

In that brief exchange of words spoken quietly, but that night made
it very clear, I made a tone of voice that impressed me.

- Andrew!
- I cried.

There was a moment of silence.

- Andrew! - I cried again.

- What? - I replied the hunter. And I could not hesitate.

Andrew took a few steps toward me. I looked barely even exceeded almost his whole body the dark
ravine. Moved slowly, almost in the dark, trod that way by the legs of the animal, repeating, "Who's
there? Who calls me? "With increasing emotion and as if each moment hesitate to acknowledge at least
calling him when I thought so far.

- Andrew! - I told him a third time when he had given no more than two or three steps.

- How? What? ... Ah, sir, Mr. Domingo! - Said dropping his gun.

- Yes, I am, myself, my old Andrew.

I threw myself into the arms of my old server. At last my heart so much compression, by itself, v
burst into tears freely dilated.

XVIII

Dominic had finished his story. Stopped after these last words, spoken with the precipitation of
a man who is quick and saddened that expression of modesty that generally follows the expansions
too intimate. What similar confidences must have cost a gloomy consciousness for so long closed,
and I adivinábalo thanked him with a gesture which touched only answered him with a nod. He
had opened the letter from Oliver as funeral presided farewell, so
to speak, of this relationship and was standing, eyes turned to the
window which was framed in a peaceful horizon of plain water.

Remained so for some time keeping awkward silence that I would not
break.

He was pale, his face slightly impaired by fatigue or rejuvenated by the passionate splendor of
another era, gradually regained their age, their peculiar expression and appearance of great serenity.
The day went as peace was established memories also on his face. The shadows were invading the
dusty interior of the little drowned room where they ended that long series of evocations of
which more than one had been painful. From the inscriptions on the
wall and could not tell much of anything. Image inside as well as
the former pale at the same time as if all that past resurrected accidentally
re-entered the moment and not go out in the vague fading of the night
and forgetting.

The voices of the farmers who passed along the walls
of the park took us to two from a real trouble, doubt, shut up or
resume a truncated conversation.

- This is the time to get down -
said Sunday, and followed him to the farm in which each evening at
that hour care monitoring was complete.

The oxen were returning from
work and this was the time when the farm is encouraged. Yoked two
or three couples, for because of the weight of wet lands was necessary
triple yoke, rudder came dragging the plow, his nose swollen and wet
low horns, jaws rough, muddy even in the womb. Stock animals who had
not worked one day, bellowed in the stables waiting for the arrival
of its assets peers. Beyond the flock of sheep, and locked up, stirred
in the corral, horses pawing and neighing to feel that the crop fell
on the stairs above mangers.

Workers lined up next to the master,
bareheaded and looking tired.

Sunday carefully inquired if any new
farm implements application had yielded the expected results, then
gave his orders for the next day, the multiple, especially with reference
to seed, and I realized that not all grain whose distribution pointed
out, was destined to their own fields, had long lost, advances made
or alms</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>