<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>113002</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21021</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Al cabo de poco
tiempo consultaba con su penitenta, no sólo los asuntos piadosos, sino también los domésticos;
era su consejera espiritual y temporal. La joven devota penetraba todos sus pensamientos, a
veces antes de formularse con precisión en su cerebro.

--Padre, hoy está usted de mal humor; es porque no ha podido decir misa en el altar de la Concepción
como otras veces.--Tiene usted ojeras; bien se ve que se ha pasado toda la noche rezando.--Ya
sé por qué dijo la misa el domingo más tarde: esperaba que llegase doña Eloisa.--Ese alzacuello
le aprieta a usted mucho. Está usted incómodo. ¿Quiere que yo se lo arregle?...

Sus vidas se iban compenetrando insensiblemente. No sólo tenían un rato de plática casi todos
los días en el confesonario, sino que por la tarde se veían en la iglesia, al rosario, y por
la noche también a menudo en casa de D.ª Eloisa. Además, de vez en cuando, para algún motivo
piadoso, como una novena, una reunión de la cofradía, etc., la joven iba a la rectoral a consultarle,
aunque le costase siempre un esfuerzo, porque tenía gran miedo a D. Miguel. Se le había metido
en la cabeza que éste la miraba de mal ojo, que la despreciaba. Y acaso no le faltase razón
para suponerlo.

Esta confianza llegó a pecar de excesiva en algunas ocasiones. Al menos así lo pensó el P.
Gil. Obdulia se autorizaba de vez en cuando algunas familiaridades que le chocaban, y en ocasiones
llegaron a turbar momentáneamente la limpidez de su conciencia. Un día le habló de sus apuros
económicos. El padre le daba poco dinero para los gastos de la casa, y como tenía el vicio
de la caridad, de dar limosnas a troche y moche, había contraído deudas, que la mortificaban;
sobre todo había una tendera a quien debía veinte duros, que la molestaba a todas horas y le
amenazaba con decírselo a su papá. ¿No podría él facilitarle por poco tiempo esta cantidad?
El clérigo tampoco los tenía, pero se los pidió a su madrina y se los entregó ruborizado. Ella
los aceptó sin vergüenza alguna, como la cosa más natural. Otro día le llevó a la iglesia el
paquete de cartas del novio que había tenido para que las leyese. Más adelante le pidió el
escapulario que traía al cuello, y tanto le instó y tales pretextos adujo, que concluyó por
obtenerlo. Al día siguiente le confesó, sonriendo, que no había sido para ponérselo a una amiga
que acababa de morir, sino para traerlo ella sobre el pecho. Estas cosas herían e inquietaban
vagamente al joven sacerdote. Las bromitas que la beata se permitía de palabra también rebasaban
algunas veces los límites convenientes. Un día le dijo repentinamente:

--¿Sabe usted lo que estoy pensando, padre? Que el ángel que viene muchas veces a ponerme la
mano sobre la cabeza tiene los ojos muy parecidos a los de usted.

Y soltó la carcajada al decirlo. El clérigo rió también ruborizándose. Luego quedó serio y
de mal humor.

Un suceso extraño, que escandalizó a la villa, vino de un modo indirecto a estrechar aún más
su relación y a inquietar al P. Gil. Cierta noche se despertó despavorido con el ruido de una
detonación dentro de casa. Levantose de un salto y acudió corriendo a la habitación de D. Miguel,
donde se figuró que había sonado. Al llegar a ella quedó petrificado de terror ante la escena
que apareció a su vista. Un hombre se revolcaba en medio de la habitación en un charco de sangre,
mientras D. Miguel, de pie sobre la cama, agitaba triunfante una pistola gritando con sonrisa
feroz:--¡Ya cayó uno! ¡Ya cayó uno!--La mortecina luz de una bujía tirada en el suelo alumbraba
aquella fatídica escena.

El caso había sido que, hallándose el párroco en la cama, un hombre había penetrado en su dormitorio,
le había despertado y le intimó para que le entregase el dinero. D. Miguel sin inmutarse echó
mano al chaleco, sacó la llave y la arrojó al medio de la habitación. Luego, mientras el ladrón
la recogía, sacó una de las pistolas que tenía debajo del colchón y le descerrajó un tiro dejándole
tendido. La bala le había penetrado por los riñones. El excusador, dominando su espanto, se
apresuró a prestarle los auxilios espirituales. Sólo tardó tres horas en expirar.

El suceso se comentó mucho y de muy diverso modo en el pueblo. Algunos aprobaban la conducta
del cura. Estaba en su derecho defendiéndose de un facineroso que Dios sabe lo que haría con
él después de robarle. Otros, los más, la censuraban con acritud. Un sacerdote no puede obrar
como los demás en tal caso. Es un ministro de Jesucristo y debe proceder siempre con caridad
aunque sea en legítima defensa. El P. Gil estaba profundamente indignado, aunque guardaba silencio.
Un sacerdote, antes que ensangrentar sus manos, no sólo debía dejarse robar, sino matar. Nuestro
Señor así lo había enseñado cuando San Pedro cortó la oreja al soldado que venía a prenderle.
Obdulia traslució bien los sentimientos que le agitaban y le aconsejó que dejase la rectoral
y se estableciese en otra casa.

--Usted ya no puede vivir ahí después de lo que ha pasado, padre. El susto que ha llevado ha
sido muy fuerte, y todos los días tiene que renovarse la impresión viendo el sitio.

No era esto precisamente lo que quería decir, sino que un hombre verdaderamente cristiano y
virtuoso debía de padecer mucho viviendo al lado de quien acababa de dar muerte violenta a
un semejante. Pero si no lo decía con las palabras, se dejaba adivinar en la gravedad y tristeza
de su continente. El P. Gil no ansiaba otra cosa hacía mucho tiempo. La compañía del párroco
le era molesta, como ya sabemos. Ahora, después del asesinato (así lo calificaba su conciencia),
se le había hecho insoportable. D. Miguel había incurrido en la censura de la Iglesia, se le
retiraron las licencias para confesar y decir misa: mientras llegase la rehabilitación pasaría
una temporada. Aprovechando aquellos momentos de flaqueza del terrible cura, con la ayuda de
su madrina alquiló una casita no muy lejos de la iglesia y se trasladó a ella. Una antigua
criada de D.ª Eloisa vino a servirle y a ser su ama de gobierno.

Libre ya del temor al párroco, Obdulia empezó a frecuentar la nueva casa del excusador y a
ejercer en ella una alta vigilancia. Enterábase de la ropa blanca, del estado de las sotanas,
de los alimentos que más placían al padre, de las particularidades de su cama. Algunas veces
venía a ayudar al planchado o llevaba para aplanchar en su casa aquellas cosas más delicadas,
como las albas y los roquetes, recosía las medias que se habían roto, quitaba las manchas de
las sotanas, etc. Éstas eran las tareas ordinarias. Pero también se ocupaba en alguna obra
más fina, en bordarle un amito, o unos corporales o cualquier otra prenda de las vestiduras
sacerdotales. D.ª Josefa, el ama de llaves, no aceptaba de buena gana este protectorado; pero
como aún no había echado raíces hondas en la casa y observaba la estrecha amistad que aquella
señorita llevaba con su amo, no se atrevía a protestar. Contentábase con murmurar de ella cuando
iba a visitar a su antigua señora y llamarla entrometida y tonta. Más adelante fue tascando
el freno de peor voluntad aún y concluyó por desbocarse, como ya tendremos ocasión de ver.
Tampoco el P. Gil estaba tranquilo ni satisfecho en la atmósfera de atenciones delicadas, de
afecto y veneración en que la joven le tenía envuelto. Por más que la profesaba viva admiración
y tenía en cuenta sus consejos, sentía un vago malestar cada vez que la veía ocupándose del
cuidado material de su persona. Le parecía a él que esto era rebajar el carácter de aquella
amistad espiritual, formada y sostenida para mejorar sus almas, para ayudarse en el camino
de la perfección. No tenía noticia alguna de que Santa Teresa repasase las medias de San Juan
de la Cruz. Además, no se comprendía muy bien el desprecio de la carne, que tan bien practicaba
ella, con las comodidades de que pretendía rodearle. ¿Por qué había de ser tan severa para
ella y tan blanda para él? ¿Por ventura, le suponía tan débil y cobarde que no podía vivir
sin tales cuidados?

El P. Gil meditaba esto, apoyado en la baranda de un corredor enrejado que su habitación tenía
sobre el mar. El sol declinaba entre celajes carmesíes, envolviendo en una onda de luz tibia
y rojiza el pueblo y la rada. El lienzo de rocas que la cierra allá enfrente alzaba su masa
enorme sobre las aguas, proyectando ya una vasta región de sombra. Y entre aquel negror los
ojos del presbítero percibían el fulgor de las olas, mostrando y apagando a cortos intervalos
su blancura. El muelle estaba desierto: aún no era llegada la hora de la vuelta de las lanchas.
Los pataches y quechemarines cabeceaban dulcemente, aburridos de su inacción. Una gaviota volaba
en círculos concéntricos rozando con sus alas la superficie del agua. El suave lejano rumor
de las olas henchía el ambiente dormido de un murmullo sordo. La pequeña ensenada sólo vivía
del juego movible de la luz que la bañaba de una claridad sangrienta que se iba retirando lentamente
detrás de las peñas.

Tan absorto estaba, que D.ª Josefa necesitó llamarle tres veces desde la puerta para conseguir
que se volviese.

--¿Qué hay?

--Una señora está abajo preguntando por usted. Dice que necesita hablarle en seguida.

--¿Una señora?--replicó el P. Gil abriendo mucho los ojos.--Será la señorita Obdulia.

--No, señor, no es ésa--replicó el ama haciendo con los labios un gesto de desdén.--La señora
que aguarda abajo es mucho más guapa y elegante.

--¿No la conoce usted?--preguntó algo acortado por la intención que advertía en las palabras
de D.ª Josefa.

--No, señor, es forastera.

--Pues hágale usted subir.

Tardó pocos segundos en aparecer una linda joven como de veinticuatro años, rubia, de rostro
blanquísimo y facciones delicadas, vestida con elegancia peregrina. En su vida había visto
el P. Gil, ni aun en Lancia, una dama tan distinguida. Su traje era sencillo, de viaje, pero
tan original el corte y con tal lujo y esmero en los pormenores, que se echaba de ver inmediatamente
la elevada calidad de la persona. Despedía de ella un perfume suave que vino a herir su nariz
así que puso el pie en el cuarto. Mirola con sorpresa, que se convirtió en estupefacción al
ver que la dama avanzó con resolución hasta él, y sin decir palabra se dejó caer de rodillas
a sus pies sollozando.

--¡Señora... por Dios... levántese usted!--dijo aturdido.

La dama no se movió.

--Señora, levántese usted--repitió de nuevo cogiéndola suavemente por un brazo.

La forastera se levantó en silencio y se dejó caer en una silla, alzó el velito del sombrero
que le tapaba los ojos y se los enjugó con el pañuelo. El P. Gil, en pie frente a ella, aguardaba
a que se explicase. Y como no daba señales de hacerlo, antes se tapaba el rostro cada vez más,
aventurose a decir:

--Señora, desearía saber en qué puedo servirla...

Todavía tardó unos instantes en responder. Al cabo dijo, sin apartar el pañuelo de los ojos:

--Soy la esposa de D. Álvaro Montesinos.

El excusador dio un paso atrás involuntariamente.

¿Cómo? ¿aquella dama era la mujerzuela despreciable que había hecho la desgracia de D. Álvaro,
de quien su madrina D.ª Eloisa hablaba siempre con horror? Por ésta conocía la triste historia
del aquel matrimonio. El heredero de la casa de Montesinos se había enamorado como un loco
de una joven de buena familia, pero sin dinero; una de esas chicas que suelen verse en Madrid
en todos los teatros y en todos los saraos a la caza de un marido rico. Aun con serlo Montesinos,
Joaquinita Domínguez (que así se llamaba) le dio cordelejo una temporada, esperando tal vez
que llegase otro con la misma hacienda y mejor figura; porque la del mayorazgo de Peñascosa
era, cierto, de lo más raquítico y desgraciado que pudiera verse. Mas como no llegaba, resolviose
un día a enamorarse perdidamente de él y se lo demostró de un modo que no daba lugar a dudas.
«Todo el Madrid elegante» recordará a una linda rubia abonada al turno primero par del teatro
Real, que se pasaba la noche charlando con un caballero flacucho y pálido sentado en la fila
de atrás; que en el teatro de la Comedia y en el de Apolo no le quitaba los gemelos de encima
desde su platea; que lo llevaba de remolque en el paseo del Retiro, y hasta por las mañanas,
cuando iba de tiendas, se la veía con él, escoltados por la mamá. Enteramente convencido de
su amor, el hidalgo la pidió en matrimonio, y la obtuvo no sin algún trabajo, pues a la mamá
costole muchas lágrimas entregarle aquella joya, que era la alegría de la casa. En los primeros
cuatro meses gastó D. Álvaro la renta de todo el año. Joaquinita quiso coche y palco en los
teatros, y dio reuniones y saraos. Pero estaba tan hermosa y su marido la encontraba tan alegre,
que con el amor frenético que la profesaba no le hubiera rehusado ni la sangre del corazón
si un día se la pidiera después de un beso de amor largo, oprimido, espasmódico, como los que
le daba cuando tenía que pedirle una rivière de brillantes o una sociable de doble suspensión.

A los seis meses justos se le antojó a la joven esposa viajar por Europa, un viaje largo que
había de durar un año o más; visitar toda Francia, Italia, subir luego a Inglaterra, pasar
a Alemania y correrse hasta San Petersburgo. El enamorado Montesinos no puso obstáculos a este
deseo, aunque debiera ponerlos. Necesitábase un capital respetable para realizarlo, atento
a las comodidades y boato con que Joaquinita pretendía viajar. Pidió a préstamo sobre algunas
de sus fincas 30.000 duros y salieron de Madrid. En Hendaya vieron en la fonda del ferrocarril
tomando chocolate a Federico Torres, un sietemesino madrileño hijo de un ministro del Tribunal
de Cuentas. A Joaquinita siempre le había sido muy antipático, sin saber por qué.

--¿Adonde irá este títere?--preguntó por lo bajo, después de corresponder fríamente a su saludo.

Montesinos alzó los hombros con indiferencia.

--¡Qué pelea le tienes a este chico! Yo le encuentro fino y agradable.

--¡Qué horror!--exclamó ella riendo.

En Pau volvieron a verle en la estación, y ya no le vieron más. En Marsella pensaba el matrimonio
detenerse cuatro o cinco días; pero al tercero, viniendo D. Álvaro de la estación de arreglar
el asunto del sleeping-car para el día siguiente, con gran sorpresa no encontró a su esposa
en casa. La sorpresa convirtiose en horrible estupor al observar el desorden de la habitación.
El gran baúl mundo de su mujer había desaparecido. Había diferentes prendas de ropa por el
suelo. Los criados le dijeron que la señora había hecho trasportar el baúl después de irse
él para facturarlo en doble pequeña, según decía. Luego había salido y no había vuelto. Montesinos,
aturdido, horrorizado de la idea que le cruzaba por el cerebro, abrió con mano convulsa el
secreto del cofre donde guardaban el dinero. Ni un céntimo había allí ya. Comprendiendo de
una vez toda su desgracia, cayó al suelo como herido por un rayo. Estuvo algunos días entre
la vida y la muerte. Cuando recobró el conocimiento, hizo telegrafiar a su cuñado D. Martín,
el cual se presentó inmediatamente y le condujo a Peñascosa. No tardó en saberse que Joaquinita
se había escapado con Federico Torres, y que viajaban alegremente por Europa con el dinero
del hidalgo.

Ésta era la mujer que tenía delante el P. Gil. Después de aquel primer movimiento de repulsión,
se rehizo y dijo:

--Serénese usted un poco, señora, y dígame en qué puedo favorecerla.

--Acabo de llegar de Madrid--articuló con trabajo la dama,--y me he dirigido a casa de mi marido,
con quien hace tiempo estoy reñida... Deseaba reconciliarme con él... que concluyese esta separación
tan fea y tan escandalosa... Un criado viejo que tiene... ¡un bruto!... no me permitió verle...
me cogió por el brazo... me arrojó de casa a empellones... ¡sí, a empellones!

Aquí la dama volvió a estallar en sollozos, y se tapó de nuevo el rostro con el pañuelo.

El clérigo esperó a que continuase; pero viendo que no lo hacía, tomó de nuevo la palabra.

--Siento mucho ese percance, señora... Pero no creo que haya motivo para tal desconsuelo. Las
ofensas que se perdonan no se sienten. Perdone usted a ese pobre criado que ha obrado sin saber
lo que hacía, y dígame qué es lo que puedo hacer en su obsequio.

Secose los ojos la esposa infiel. Volvieron a humedecérsele y volvió a secarlos.

--Según me han dicho ahí en la posada, usted es la única persona que visita a mi marido...
Yo le suplico, por lo más sagrado, ya que es usted su amigo, que intervenga para que termine
nuestra separación. Lo deseo hace mucho tiempo con ansia... Confieso que no he sido buena para
él...

--Sí, sí; lo sé todo--interrumpió el clérigo con impaciencia.

La dama se puso fuertemente colorada.

--Confieso que le he ofendido gravemente... Fue un momento de obcecación... una tentación del
demonio... Pero yo siempre le he querido... y le quiero... No tengo inconveniente en humillarme,
en pedirle perdón de rodillas... Ya ve usted, padre, si no le quisiera no me humillaría...
¡Me horroriza la idea de no obtener su perdón, de morir lejos de él sola, maldita! ¡Ah, qué
porvenir tan espantoso!... Si mucho he pecado, crea usted que mucho he padecido en estos últimos
tiempos...

--Señora, ya puede usted comprender si yo tendría satisfacción en unir un matrimonio disuelto...
lo mismo el de usted que cualquier otro. Mi misión es predicar la concordia entre los hombres
y morir por ella si es preciso. Aun sin pedírmelo tengo el deber, por mi cargo, de procurar
en esta parroquia la reconciliación de los matrimonios desavenidos... Pero este caso es delicado.
Aparte de la ofensa gravísima que usted ha inferido a su esposo, del escándalo que la acompañó,
de los que la siguieron, todo lo cual dificulta extraordinariamente la reconciliación, aparte
de eso, repito, hay otra dificultad mayor. Y es que su marido de usted está fuera de la Iglesia
católica. No tengo sobre él otra influencia que la que puede dar una amistad superficial. Ninguno
de los razonamientos a los cuales pudiera yo apelar como sacerdote tiene fuerza sobre su ánimo.
Al contrario, dadas sus ideas, es posible que sirviesen para embravecerle más, o cuando menos
de mofa...

--Sí, sí--interrumpió la dama con voz chillona, malévola,--mi marido ha sido siempre un impío,
un ateo escandaloso.

--Señora, de poco sirve creer si se obra como si no se creyera--replicó severamente el excusador,
a quien había herido el tono agresivo de la dama, tan contrario a la humildad de antes.

Tornó a ponerse colorada y bajó los ojos afectando de nuevo una gran contrición. El P. Gil
prosiguió:

--De todos modos, como cristiano y como sacerdote, estoy dispuesto a hacer todo lo que puedan
mis fuerzas por conseguir lo que usted desea. Dudo mucho del éxito de mi intervención... Sé
también que me expongo a ser arrojado como usted de la casa, pero no me importa. Cumpliré mi
deber, y si no conseguimos nada, me quedará al menos la satisfacción de haberlo cumplido...

Quedose pensativo unos instantes, mientras la dama mantenía sobre él una mirada intensa y ansiosa.
Luego, como si hablase consigo mismo más que con ella, prosiguió:

--El dirigirme ahora a casa de D. Álvaro ofrece inconvenientes. La gente del pueblo es curiosa...
Vendrían las hablillas... después el escándalo... Opino que deberíamos aguardar un rato a que
concluyera de oscurecer, o mejor aún, que yo fuese por delante a tantear el asunto...

--¡No! ¡no!--exclamó la dama.--No le prevenga usted. Se negaría a recibirme. Es necesario cogerle
de improviso; aprovechar el primer movimiento de su corazón, que es generoso. Luego, cuando
reflexiona, se hace malo, burlón...

--Como usted quiera. Entonces, aguardaremos.

Pero en el instante de pronunciar esta palabra se hizo cargo de lo inconveniente de permanecer
tanto tiempo a solas con una mujer, y dijo un poco turbado:

--Usted me permitirá que mientras tanto la deje sola unos momentos... Soy con usted en seguida.

En vez de ser con ella, mandó a su ama para que la acompañase. Sólo cuando la luz se hubo extinguido
por completo subió de nuevo con el sombrero en la mano, preparado a salir. La esposa de D.
Álvaro, así que le vio en esta traza, se levantó de la silla.

Había cerrado ya la noche. La gente de mar se había retirado a sus casas o a las tabernas.
Por la larga, sinuosa calle del Cuadrante circulaban pocos transeúntes. El excusador y la esposa
de Montesinos caminaron un rato en silencio en dirección al Campo de los Desmayos. Al aproximarse
a él ambos se sentían agitados, temerosos. Tanto para calmarse un poco como para prevenirse,
se detuvieron un instante, y metiéndose en el hueco de una puerta, cuchichearon con animación.
El P. Gil insistía en su idea de entrar primero en la casa y explorar el ánimo de D. Álvaro:
tenía miedo a un escándalo. La dama se oponía con calor, convencida hasta la evidencia de que
su marido se negaría en absoluto a recibirla, y tomaría precauciones para que no pisase el
suelo de su casa. Cuando más embebidos se hallaban en la discusión, del hueco de otra puerta
cercana salió una sombra estrecha, elevada, y se aproximó a ellos rápidamente.

--Buenas noches, padre, buenas noches.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>171443</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18717</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> After a short time
consulting with his penitent, pious not only matters but also the home; was his spiritual advisor
and temporary. The devout young pervaded all their thoughts, times before made accurately in
his brain.

- Father, today you are in a bad mood is because it could not say Mass at the altar of the Conception
as usual .-- you have dark circles, it is seen that has spent the entire night in prayer .-- I
know why said later Sunday Mass: Dona Eloisa expected to arrive .--
That collar pinches you very much.

Are you uncomfortable. You want me to fix it? ...

Their lives were wantonly pervading. Not only had time to talk about all day in the confessional,
but by afternoon were in the church, the rosary, and night too often at home of Ms Eloisa. In addition,
from time to time, for any reason pious, as a novena, a meeting of the guild, etc., she went to
the rectory to inquire, always though it cost him an effort, she had a great fear of D. Miguel.
Had got in his head that he looked at her evil eye, which he despised.

And perhaps he was right to guess.

This confidence came to be too excessive at times. At least I thought Fr Gil. Obdulia be authorized
from time to time some relatives who clashed, and sometimes momentarily came to disturb the
clarity of his consciousness. One day he spoke of his troubles economic. The father gave him
some money for household expenses, and as he was vice charity, giving alms to spray and pray,
had contracted debts which the mortified; above all was a shopkeeper who was twenty dollars,
which bothered him at all times and threatened to tell his dad. Could not he provide for a short
time this amount? The cleric also had them, but they are asked to sponsor and handed flushed.
She shamelessly accepted them as a matter of course. Another day took him to church Groom
packet of letters she had for the read. Later he asked the scapular necks, and both urged and
argued such pretexts, which concluded by get it. The next day he confessed, smiling, that was not
to put it to a friend who had just died, but to bring her on the chest. These things hurt and
disturbed vaguely young priest. The little jokes which Blessed be allowed to speak also exceeded
sometimes desirable ranges. One day he said suddenly:

- Do you know what I'm thinking, father?

The angel who comes often to get the hand on the head's eyes are very similar to yours.

And burst out laughing as he said. The cleric also laughed, blushing. Then it was serious and
moody.

A strange incident, which shocked the town, came in an indirect way to further strengthen and
disturb their relationship to P. Gil. One night he woke up terrified by the noise of a detonation
inside the house. Jumped up and ran to the room D. Miguel, where he figured he had come. To reach
it froze in terror at the scene which appeared in sight. A man rolled in the middle of the room
in a pool of blood, while D. Michael, standing on the bed, waving
a pistol shouting triumphant smile fierce - I dropped one!

I dropped one! - The dim light of a candle lit lying on the floor that fateful scene.

The case had been that, being the priest in bed, a man had entered her bedroom, had awakened and
summoned him to give you the money. D. Miguel threw undeterred hand to the vest, took the key and threw
it into the middle of the room. Then, as the thief picked it up, took one of the guns under
the bed and had shot him leaving tended. The bullet had penetrated
through the kidneys.

The toilet, dominating his fright, quick to give spiritual aid. It only took three hours to
expire.

The event is said a lot and very different way in the village. Some approved of the conduct the
cure. Was entitled to defend itself from an outlaw that God knows what would after stealing it. Others,
again, sharply censured. A priest can not work like others in this case. Is a minister of Jesus
Christ and must always act with charity even in self-defense. Fr Gil was deeply shocked, but
kept silent. A priest, before his hands bloodied, was not only to be robbed, but to kill. Our
Lord had taught so when St. Peter cut the ear of the soldier who
came to arrest him.

Obdulia transpired the feelings that agitated him and advised him to leave the rectory and settled
in another house.

- You can no longer live there after what happened, Father. The scare has led been very strong,
and every day has to be renewed the impression viewing the site.

This was not exactly what he meant, but a truly Christian man virtuous living must suffer many things
beside who had just violent death a fellow. But if he did not say with words, was left to guess
at the seriousness and sadness of their continent. Fr Gil longed for a long time otherwise. The
company's pastor I was upset, as we know. Now, after the murder (as he described their conscience)
it had become unbearable. D. Michael had incurred the censure of the Church, he withdrew licenses
for confession and say Mass: the rehabilitation would arrive a season.

Taking advantage of those moments of terrible weakness of the priest, with the help of her
godmother rented a house not far from the church and moved to it. A former Ms Eloisa maid came
to serve and be his housekeeper.

Freed from fear of the pastor, Obdulia began to frequent the new home of Excuses carry on high
surveillance. Enterábase of linen, robes of state, of the foods that most pleased the father,
of the peculiarities of his bed. Sometimes came to help the ironing board ironing or wearing
for those things at home more sensitive as the dawns and rochets, recosía stockings that were
broken, stains removed cassocks, etc.. These were ordinary tasks. But also engaged in some work
thinner, in embroidering a little master, or a body or any other article of clothing priesthood.
Ms Josefa, the housekeeper, not willingly accepted the protectorate, but As yet there was rooted
deep in the house and noted the close friendship that Miss his master had not dared to protest.
Murmur contented with her when went to visit his old lady and call voyeuristic and silly. Later
he was champing will brake even worse and ended by bolt, as we shall see. Neither Fr Gil was calm
and happy atmosphere in the attentions of affection and veneration in which the young man was
involved. As much as the living professed admiration and took into account his advice, I felt
a vague discomfort every time he saw her taking care of material care of his person. It seemed
to him that this was to lower the character of that spiritual friendship, trained and supported
to improve their souls, to help on the way of perfection. I had heard nothing from Santa Teresa
to go over the middle of San Juan de la Cruz. Also, do not really understand the contempt
of the flesh, so well practiced she, with the amenities that surround you intended. Why have
been so severe for and so tender it for him?

Perchance, allowed him so weak and cowardly that he could not live without such care?

Fr Gil pondered this, leaning on the railing of a corridor to his room was lattice above the
sea. The crimson sun was through any veil, wrapped in a warm light wave and red the village
and the bay. The canvas of rock that stood there in front closes its mass great on the water,
casting and a wide area of ??shade. And that blackness between the priest's eyes perceive the glare
of the waves, showing and off at short intervals its whiteness. The pier was deserted, even when
the time was not the return of the boats. The quechemarines pataches and nodded gently, tired
of their inaction. A gull flying concentric circles with their wings touching the water surface.
The soft distant murmur of the waves filled the room asleep a murmur. The small cove only lived mobile
game of light that bathed the bloody clarity would slowly withdraw
behind the rocks.

So absorbed was he that Ms Josefa needed to call three times from
the door to get that return.

- What?

- A lady is downstairs asking
for you.

He says he needs to talk at once.

- A lady? "- Said the P. Gil opening his eyes .-- Will Miss Obdulia.

- No, sir, not that - said he loves doing with her lips a gesture of disdain .-- Mrs. that looks
down is much more beautiful and elegant.

- Did not you know? - Asked
somewhat shortened by the intention that warned of the words Ms Josefa.

-
No, sir, is an outsider.

- Well let you go.

It took a few seconds to display a beautiful young as twenty-four, blonde, face very white and
delicate features, dressed elegantly pilgrim. In his life he had seen Fr Gil, even in Lancia,
a lady so distinguished. His dress was simple, travel, but so original and cutting with such
luxury and attention to detail, was put to immediately see the high quality of the individual. It gave
off a soft scent that came to hurt his nose so he stepped into the room. Miron with surprise,
astonishment became the see that the lady moved resolutely to him, and without a word dropped
to his knees at his feet sobbing.

- Lady ... God ... you get up! - told stunned.

The lady did not budge.

- Lady, get you - repeated again taking her gently by the arm.

The silent stranger stood up and dropped into a chair, raised his
hat candle covering his eyes and wiped with a handkerchief.

Fr Gil, standing before her, waiting to explain.

And showed no signs of it, before covering her face increasingly ventured to say:

- Madam, I would like to know how I can serve ...

Still took a moment
to respond.

Finally he said, without removing the tissue of the eye:

- I am the wife of D. Alvaro Montesinos.

The toilet took a step back involuntarily.

How? "This lady was despicable slut had the misfortune of D. Alvaro of who her godmother Ms
Eloisa always spoke with horror? For it knew the sad story of that marriage. The heir to the house
of Montesinos was in love like crazy a young man of good family, but without money, one of those
girls who are usually seen in Madrid in all theaters and all Sarah to hunt for a rich husband.
Be even with Montesinos, Joaquin Dominguez (that was his name) gave cordelejo a season, perhaps
hoping that came with the same wealth and better shape, because the firstborn of Peñascosa was,
indeed, the most feeble and miserable that could be. When they did not arrive, resolviose one
day to fall in love with him and showed it in a way that left no room for doubt. "All the elegant
Madrid" recalled a cute blonde paid to turn first pair of theater Real, who spent the night
chatting with a skinny, pale gentleman sitting in the row back, that the Comedy Theatre and the
Apollo did not detract top Twins from his audience, taking him on the ride trailer del Retiro,
and up in the morning when she went shopping, she looked to him, escorted by his mother. Entirely
convinced love, the gentleman asked her to marry, and obtained not without some work, because
the mother Costolo many tears give that jewel, which was the joy of the house. In the first D.
spent four months Álvaro income throughout the year. Joachimite wanted
car and box in theaters, and gave meetings and soirees.

But she was so beautiful and her husband was so happy, frantic with love professed that he had
not refused the heart and blood if one day the request after a long loving kiss, pressed,
spasmodic, such as those gave him when he had to ask for a diamond rivière sociable or full suspension.

At
six months just fancied the young wife to travel to Europe, a long trip was to last a year
or more, to visit all of France, Italy, then England go, go to Germany and run to St. Petersburg.
The lover Montesinos placed no obstacles in this desire, but should put them. We needed a respectable
capital to do it, watch the comforts and trappings that Joaquin intended travel. Loan requested
some of 30,000 farms went out hard and Madrid.

In Hendaye at the inn were railroad Federico Torres drinking chocolate,
a half-witted son of a minister Madrid Court Accounts.

A Joaquin had always been very unfriendly, not knowing why.

- Where
will this puppet? - Asked softly, after his greeting coldly match.

Montesinos shrugged indifferently.

- What will you fight this guy! I find it fine and pleasant.

- What horror - she said laughing.

Pau went to see him at the station, and no longer saw him more. In Marseille thought marriage stop four
or five days, but the third, coming D. Álvaro station fix the subject of sleeping-car for
the next day, to his surprise he found his wife not at home. The surprise became all at once
astonished to see the horrible mess of the room. The big Saratoga trunk of his wife was gone.
There were different items of clothing by soil. The servants told him that the woman had been
transporting the chest after leaving He double-billing for small, he said. Then came out and had
not returned. Montesinos, stunned, horrified by the idea that crossed by the brain, opened
with a hand convulsively Secret of the chest where they kept the
money.

Not a penny was there already. Understanding of once all his misfortune, fell to the ground as
if struck by lightning.

It was several days between life and death.

When she regained consciousness, he telegraphed to his brother D. Martin which immediately appeared
and took him to Peñascosa. He soon became known that Joaquin Federico had escaped with Torres, and traveling
merrily around Europe with the money the gentleman.

This was the woman before the P. Gil.

After that first movement of repulsion, was rebuilt and said:

- Serénese you a little lady, and tell me how I can promote it.

- I just returned from Madrid - articulated with the lady working
- and I headed home to my husband with whom I fought long ago ...
Wanted to reconcile with him ... to conclude that separation so ugly
and so outrageous ... An old servant who has ... A brute!

... would not let me see ... grabbed my arm ... I threw to home to shove ... Yes, shoving!

Here
the woman burst into tears again and again covered her face with her handkerchief.

The priest waited to continue, but seeing that he did not, took the
floor again.

- I'm sorry this incident, Mrs. ... But I do not think
there is cause for such despair.

The offenses that do not feel forgiven.

Pardon this poor servant who has done without knowing I did, and
tell me what I can do in your gift.

Dry eyes unfaithful wife. Again and again moisten dry.

- As I have said here at the inn, you're the only person who visits my husband ... I beg, for the
most sacred, and that you are his friend, to intervene to end our
separation.

I want it long ago with anxiety ... I confess that I was not good for he ...

- Yes, yes, I know everything - impatiently interrupted the cleric.

The lady was highly colored.

- I confess that I have offended seriously ... It was a moment of blindness ... a temptation demon
... But I've always wanted ... and I love him ... I have no objection to humiliate to ask forgiveness
on his knees ... You see, father, if you do not humiliate me like no ... I am appalled at the idea
of ??not getting his forgiveness, dying away from him alone, damn! Oh, future so awful! ... If
anything I have sinned, believe me I have suffered much in recent
times ...

- Lady, and can you understand if I would join a satisfaction
in marriage dissolved ... the same thing to you than anyone else.

My mission is to preach harmony between men and die for it if necessary. Even without asking me
I have the duty, my responsibility, to strive in this parish reconciliation
among quarreling marriage ... But this case is sensitive.

Apart from the extremely serious offense that you have inflicted on her husband, the scandal that
accompanied it, of those who followed, all of which make it extremely
difficult reconciliation apart that, again, there is another major
difficulty.

And is that your husband is out of the Church Catholic. I have no other influence on him than
he can give a superficial friendship.

None of reasoning to which I could appeal as a priest has power over his mind. On the contrary,
given their ideas, it is possible that served to embravecerle more, or at least derision ...

-
Yes, yes - the lady interrupted shrilly, malevolent, - my husband has always been a wicked,
an atheist outrageous.

- Lady, is of little use to believe if you act as if no thought -
said severely toilets, who had wounded the aggressive tone of the
lady, so contrary to humility before.

To be turned red and dropped his eyes back to affect a great contrition.

Fr Gil continued:

- Anyway, as a Christian and a priest, I am willing to do all they
can my power to get what you want.

I doubt much of the success of my speech ... I know I also expose
you to be cast as the house, but I do not care.

Keep my duty, and if you do not get anything, I will be at least the satisfaction of having fulfilled
...

He remained thoughtful for a moment, while the lady kept on him a look intense and anxious. Then, as
if speaking to himself rather than with her, continued:

- The address is now home to D. Alvaro has drawbacks. The common people are curious ... Came
the gossip ... after the scandal ... I think we should wait a while to concluded dark, or better
yet, that I was ahead to test the matter ...

- No! No! - Exclaimed the lady .-- will not prevent you. Would refuse to receive me. It is necessary
to take him suddenly, take the first movement of his heart that is generous. Then, when reflects,
it is bad, mocking ...

- As you wish. So we will wait.

But the moment of pronouncing the word took over the inconvenience
of staying much time alone with a woman, a little embarrassed and
said:

- You will allow me to leave her alone while a few moments
... I'm with you shortly.

Instead of being with her, sent her love
to accompany her. Only when the light was extinguished completely
up again with hat in hand, prepared to leave. The wife of D. Álvaro,
so I saw this trace, rose from his chair.

He had already closed the
night. Seafarers had retired to their houses or taverns. In the long,
winding street a few passers-circular dial. The toilet and wife Montesinos
walked a while in silence towards the Field of fainting. Approaching
he both felt agitated, fearful. Both to calm down a bit as a precaution,
paused a moment, and getting into the hollow of a door, whispered
with animation. Fr Gil insisted on his idea first entered the house
and explore the spirit of D. Álvaro: afraid of a scandal. The lady
was opposed by heat, convinced beyond all doubt that her husband would
refuse to receive it at all, and take precautions to avoid the pisase
floor of his house. The more embedded in the discussion were of another
door opening near a shadow came close, high, and approached them quickly.

-
Good evening, Father, good night</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>