<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01159</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>390622</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23224</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Juega tambien, no solo en la corea
alcohólica, sino en el baile de San Vito, en el que casi siempre es útil. Importante es advertir
que para que la parálisis requiera la nuez vómica, necesita la circunstancia de tener por causa
una grande escitacion de la accion nerviosa, así como la gangrena en el arsénico debe ser el
resultado de una inflamacion escesiva. Hé aquí, pues, la razon de que la nuez vómica no puede
estar completamente escluida del tratamiento de los estreñimientos rebeldes debidos á la falta
de esfuerzos y á la parálisis de los esfínteres, cuando este estado es el resultado de una
irritabilidad elevada hasta el esceso y que conduce á la atonía, á la inercia.

14.º Asma.--Esta afeccion es una de las en que menos se puede prescindir de la nuez vómica
para su tratamiento. Este medicamento parece obrar sobre los músculos que concurren á la respiracion
y tambien sin duda sobre el pneumogástrico, mientras que el arsénico obra principalmente sobre
el último, sobre la inervacion pulmonal; del carácter neurálgico y convulsivo resulta el que
se alternen con frecuencia estos dos medicamentos para la curacion del asma esencial y de la
mayor parte de las afecciones asmáticas. Varios son los medicamentos eficaces en el asma, segun
que domine el elemento congestivo, paralítico, inflamatorio, nervioso, tales son: la ipecacuana,
el tártaro estibiado, la brionia, la lobelia, etc.....

15.º Afecciones cutáneas. Irritaciones crónicas de las mucosas esternas.--La accion de la nuez
vómica sobre la piel tiene algo de agudo, segun lo espresa el estado general de espasmo febril
ó convulsivo, el eretismo sanguíneo, el gastricismo, la afeccion del hígado y de la nutricion.
Por eso se observa la piel fria, azulada con manchas de este mismo color, prurito picante y
quemante por la mañana y por la tarde, sensaciones de escoriacion tambien quemante, forúnculos
por erupcion sucesiva, acné, color amarillo ó ictérico, sensacion de quemazon en los puntos
escoriados los cuales se ponen tumefactos y encendidos, y en las úlceras que dan sangre, erupciones
miliares pruritosas, ó marasmo rápido. Hé aquí, pues, otras tantas circunstancias que indican
la nuez vómica en las hepatitis crónicas, erupciones gástricas, el acné pustuloso, forúnculos
que se reproducen, etc.....

Se la emplea tambien en ciertos casos de secrecion sebácea en los párpados, de irritacion del
borde libre de los mismos y de la conjuntiva, en las personas entregadas á las bebidas, en
algunas estomatitis, aun con aftas, y en las irritaciones crónicas de la mucosa de la boca
con tumefaccion de las encías y frecuentes ulceraciones aftosas, especialmente si están muy
sensibles. Se observa en este caso cierta insidiosa disposicion del estómago ó de los intestinos
en armonía con este estado de la boca, y dolores quemantes, en fin, que acompañan á todas las
irritaciones mucosas de la nuez vómica. Es tambien eficaz en las fisuras del ano con contractura,
dolor quemante, irritabilidad general, en los prolapsus del recto, sobre todo de los niños,
á consecuencia de los esfuerzos en la espulsion de materiales durísimos ó tenesmo disentérico.

=Dósis.=--La nuez vómica está indicada en tantas enfermedades, que es necesario variar las
dósis de 1 á 10 gotas y aun mas de la tintura, hasta unos glóbulos de la trigésima atenuacion,
debiéndose usar las mas pequeñas en los sugetos mas irritables y en los desórdenes funcionales
y las afecciones neurálgicas y eréticas.

Indicarémos además, que aparte de las consideraciones de edad, de sexo, de temperamento, de
género de vida, de clima, que ya hemos manifestado estar en armonía con los efectos de la nuez
vómica, hay otras que conviene tener presentes en su administracion: la nuez vómica obra mejor
por la mañana, y al efecto, cuando es posible, se la administra al anochecer; sus efectos son
entonces mas suaves, particularmente en las dismenorreas eréticas, en las menstruaciones escesivas,
en las afecciones neurálgicas, el estreñimiento..... Administrada por la mañana en casos de
este género en personas muy irritables, su accion molesta y provoca con frecuencia la agravacion
de una multitud de síntomas que se manifiestan por la mañana. Se evita tambien el darla despues
de comer en personas que padecen calambres de estómago, gastralgias, afecciones gástricas,
neurálgicas ó venosas, y ciertos estados congestivos, porque justamente entonces se desarrollan
mas los padecimientos ó se presentan. En el asma se administra por el dia, y en todo tiempo
en las enfermedades agudas rápidas, aun en los accesos de dolor. Creemos útil, en fin, hacer,
una vez para siempre, la indicacion aplicable tambien á otros medicamentos, pero con especialidad
á la brionia, á la manzanilla, al azufre...., que á pesar de la debilidad de la dósis, es preciso
contar con las agravaciones que pueden sobrevenir, si se desprecian estas precauciones en las
personas irascibles, vivas, muy irritables, de fibra seca y tirante.

El acónito, la brionia y el árnica son medios convenientes para calmar la irritabilidad exasperada
por la nuez vómica, ya presente un carácter mas sanguíneo que nervioso, ó vice-versa, ó ya
que se estienda á la contractilidad. La manzanilla y la brionia templan la irritacion que la
nux produce en los órganos digestivos; el café y el alcohol, la del cerebro; el arsénico y
la brionia, la del aparato respiratorio; la estafisagria y la manzanilla modifican la morosidad
y la irascibilidad; la coca de Levante y el árnica, los accidentes paralíticos.

OPIUM

§ I.--Historia[14].

Esta sustancia es el jugo seco de las cabezas verdes de la amapola somnífera de la familia
de la papaveráceas, Juss.--De la poliandria monogínea, Linn.--El opio, en las obras de terapéutica
moderna, tiene un capítulo de sus efectos fisiológicos, pero que casi únicamente se refieren
á los tóxicos, perturbadores, eliminadores, y no á los realmente fisiológicos y especiales,
que se estienden á todos los aparatos, á todo el organismo por una continuidad de efectos tranquilos,
que, desde la primera impresion en la economía, se eleva hasta la plenitud de su accion, á
la cronicidad y la discrasia. Ya hemos consignado varias veces los débiles resultados de estos
estudios incompletos, por lo cual no insistirémos, permitiéndonos tan solo manifestar que el
opio es uno de los medicamentos menos conocido, ó mas incompletamente estudiado, lo cual confesará
todo hombre instruido, si conoce las estrañas divergencias en las opiniones que los autores
han emitido sobre este medicamento.

El opio á dósis grandes calma ciertos dolores, estingue el sentimiento de otros, y algunas
veces alivia el insomnio; muchos prácticos se han concretado á esto, y como el dolor y el insomnio
son síntomas comunes á la mayor parte de las enfermedades, el opio ha sido empleado en casi
todas ellas. Se le da en la tisis para calmar la tos; en el período prodrómico de las fiebres
eruptivas, para producir el sueño, y en otros muchos casos agudos en los que solo puede conseguirse
con su uso la agravacion del malestar, el aumento de la fiebre, del eretismo y el peligro.

Se le ha administrado sucesivamente con mas ó menos éxito, en las neuralgias, neuroses, epilepsia
y otras varias afecciones convulsivas, en el asma, la corea, el delirium tremens, el tétanos,
la demencia, la diarrea, la disentería, las hemorragias uterinas..... No debemos pasar en silencio
la incalificable práctica de dar el opio mezclado con otros medicamentos en la creencia de
hacer tolerables las dósis fuertes y administrar este enemigo de todo movimiento espansivo
en las fiebres eruptivas y otras enfermedades indicadas anteriormente.

§ II.--Efectos fisiológicos.

El opio es entre todos los medicamentos el que con mas claridad presenta sus efectos especiales
como procedentes de la escitacion de los sistemas nervioso y sanguíneo, escitacion que conduce
á la inercia de uno y otro sistema, á las congestiones pasivas, á la insensibilidad. En su
accion aguda, se exalta la sensibilidad, y se debilita en la crónica. La sangre está mas oxigenada
y escitada en la accion aguda, y menos en la crónica; y la lentitud del curso de este líquido
contribuye á realzar su cualidad venosa, cualidad que la hace impropia para la escitacion normal
de los órganos.

El opio no es un narcótico; pues si obra electivamente sobre el cerebro y los nervios de relacion,
lo hace por la mediacion del sistema ganglionar á el que se dirige primeramente, y tan solo
al parecer para influir sobre el cerebro. Los efectos de este medicamento y la especialidad
de su accion se pueden resumir en los síntomas siguientes:

Sensacion de fuerza y de vigor, insomnio, calofríos seguidos de calor, irritabilidad escesiva
de los músculos que están bajo el imperio de la voluntad, pulso lleno y frecuente, chispas
delante de los ojos, tintineo en los oidos, aturdimiento, pesadez de cabeza, alegría, grande
afluencia de ideas, descaro, sequedad de la boca, exaltacion del apetito venéreo, calor y constriccion
en el pecho, agilidad de los miembros. Estos síntomas de escitacion privativos del opio son
de mas ó menos duracion y aumentan segun las dósis; así es que se observa: inquietudes en los
miembros, cara encendida ó que cambia rápidamente de color, calor quemante y prurito en todo
el cuerpo, pulso duro y acelerado, somnolencia, tranquilidad de espíritu, divagacion ó delirio,
vértigos con calor, congestion en la cabeza y fuertes pulsaciones, alteracion de la vista,
pesadez en el estómago y en el vientre con latido, estreñimiento, disuria, escitacion de los
órganos génito-urinarios y poluciones con erecciones, dificultad en la respiracion, presion
en el pecho.

A estos síntomas siguen los siguientes: indiferencia, delirio, pérdida de los sentidos, sueño
comatoso, cara rubicunda, ardorosa y como abotagada, sequedad en la piel y aumento de las orinas
ó deposiciones diarréicas, sudor caliente algunas veces y supresion de las escreciones, cargazon
de la cabeza con necesidad de cerrar los ojos, oscurecimiento de la vista, palabra difícil
y lenta, náuseas, vómitos, dolores en el estómago, éstasis amorosos é impotencia, opresion
con angustia ó respiracion lenta y ruidosa, tumefaccion de las venas. Estos mismos síntomas,
si las dósis son grandes, se hacen más y más narcóticos: insensibilidad general, temblores,
sacudidas, accesos de sofocacion, hinchazon azulada de todo el cuerpo, sueño comatoso con ronquido,
ojos abiertos y convulsivos, cara encendida y tumefacta, labios azulados é hinchados, pulso
lento é intermitente, pérdida de los sentidos, relajacion de los músculos de la cara y del
cuerpo, movimientos convulsivos, frio general, timpanitis, deposiciones involuntarias, párpados
y labios péndulos, parálisis de la lengua y de las estremidades.

A dósis bastante pequeñas para poder continuar en su uso por mucho tiempo, los síntomas espresan
la alteracion de la sensibilidad y de la contractilidad, la lesion de las fuerzas digestivas,
el incremento del sistema venoso y la alteracion de la sangre, como se ve por los siguientes:
cefalalgia, tenesmo, vértigos y pinchazos dolorosos en la cabeza, neuralgias vivas y rápidas
que pasan de un punto á otro, tirones dolorosos en los miembros, sacudidas espasmódicas, calor
quemante en el abdómen, en el pecho, en la region precordial, dolores calambróides en las estremidades,
gastralgias, calambres en el estómago y la matriz, accesos de sofocacion, constriccion dolorosa
en el pecho, agitaciones musculares, grande debilidad y relajacion de la fibra. Al negar Hahnemann
al opio la propiedad de escitar dolores, procedió así sin duda por haberle esperimentado á
dósis muy débiles ó muy fuertes; pues la facilidad con que hemos producido el síntoma dolor
ya mencionado, y las observaciones que hemos hecho sobre dos personas saturadas de opio, nos
hacen temer que otros esperimentadores no hayan dirigido sus investigaciones hácia este punto.

La accion crónica del opio ofrece síntomas notables: enflaquecimiento general, sensibilidad
escesiva al frio, piel y cara pálida y terrosa, hinchazon de las venas, infiltracion serosa
de todo el cuerpo, prurito de la piel, hinchazon azulada de los dedos de piés y manos, y especialmente
del dedo gordo del pié, sueño angustioso, inconstancia moral, carácter asustadizo, debilidad
de las facultades intelectuales, errores de imaginacion, turbacion de la cabeza, escitabilidad
nerviosa, zumbido de oidos, dientes vacilantes, encías tumefactas y que sangran con facilidad,
salivacion, gusto amargo, repugnancia á los alimentos, lentitud y debilidad de la digestion,
gastralgia, facilidad á vomitar, flatulencia, estreñimiento tenaz, orinas escasas y oscuras,
poluciones sin ereccion, tos seca por accesos.

Los que abusan del opio están flacos; sus movimientos nutritivos y escretorios son lentos,
los nervios ganglionares no animan al parecer á los órganos de la nutricion y de las secreciones,
y tampoco influyen activamente en los nervios de relacion. Pero de que al lado de esta inercia
se observe cierta irritabilidad nerviosa del cerebro y de la médula oblongada, no se puede
deducir que el opio ejerce una accion opuesta en las dos vidas, orgánica y de relacion, como
quieren algunos médicos. Esta opinion no tiene en su apoyo razon alguna fundada; pues la diversidad
de fenómenos que dejamos indicados y que corresponden á las dos vidas, puede muy bien depender
de que la influencia de la voluntad en los órganos sometidos á la misma no esté en armonía
con la fuerza que les anima; y en todo caso, puede esplicarse por las contracciones automáticas
y por la lesion asténica de la contractilidad; la inervacion cérebro-espinal está tan debilitada
como la inervacion ganglionar. La irritabilidad moral y la de la fibra, en el opio, son puramente
asténicas y de la misma naturaleza que la de la manzanilla.

§ III.--Efectos terapéuticos.

=A.= Afecciones nerviosas.--Los resultados clínicos sancionan completamente los datos que sobre
la accion del opio hemos recogido y espuesto, y bastará por lo tanto que nos limitemos al estudio
de los hechos, con abstraccion de todas las teorías muy eruditas á veces, pero mucho menos
sencillas que los procedimientos de la naturaleza.

El opio es el medicamento mas apto para combatir el ataque brusco y como fulminante de la actividad
vital producido por la indignacion; pero de la indignacion pasiva, es decir, cuando el organismo
sufre el espanto sin que el moral se reaccione, no de la indignacion que despierta la cólera
ó un sentimiento afectivo como exige el acónito. El opio sobreescita la fibra para sumirla
en la inercia é insensibilidad; la indignacion produce los mismos efectos, predominando á veces
el último hasta el punto de ser el único que puede apreciarse, como sucede cuando el espanto
parece que paraliza, que produce deposiciones ú orinas involuntarias, que tiende al aborto,
que suprime los loquios, las reglas. Aquí no hay ni efecto primitivo, ni secundario, sino tan
solo un efecto simple y progresivo de la tension á la inercia por una misma accion. Por la
astenia final que caracteriza su accion, corresponde el opio exactamente á las congestiones
producidas por la concentracion del susto ó miedo en las diversas vísceras, impidiendo de este
modo el desarrollo de una reaccion febril muchas veces terrible, y en la que es preciso usarle,
sin olvidar el acónito ó el árnica por lo mismo.

La epilepsia nocturna, el insomnio, la hemicránea, las personas pletóricas con sentidos obtusos
y afectados de incomodidades, de ardores en las cavidades viscerales, son propias del opio,
así como el delirium tremens de los borrachos en el segundo período, secundado con el estramonio
y despues el árnica ó café. El cólico de plomo halla en el opio su mejor remedio; el platino
es con frecuencia útil despues de él.

No queremos omitir el indicar los escelentes resultados del opio en los espasmos de los niños
con respiracion difícil y éstasis sanguíneo en los capilares, ó cuando se presentan simplemente
por accesos, precedidos de gritos, y que la manzanilla, la belladona y la ignacia no han sido
suficientes. Se debe recurrir al opio en ciertas neuroses con temblor de las estremidades,
insomnio, agitacion, ansiedad en los miembros, estreñimiento, y en la manía ó enajenacion mental
caracterizadas por el cambio frecuente de calor en la cara, por la alternacion de postracion
y estilacion, con inyeccion venosa de los ojos muchas veces, movimientos convulsivos, estreñimiento.

En sugetos debilitados por largas y frecuentes escitaciones cerebrales con marasmo, piel seca
y terrosa ó amarilla, apetito pervertido ó nulo, atonía digestiva, abultamiento de las venas,
escasez de las secreciones, se usará con buenos resultados el opio en las neuralgias de los
aparatos sensoriales, ya sean puramente nerviosas ó que tengan un carácter congestivo, ó bien
calambróides, lancinantes, fijas, ó que tengan un curso irregular, constante, intermitente.
El opio combate igualmente las neuralgias de las personas pletóricas, y de los viejos en los
que la receptividad medicinal está debilitada y la influencia cerebral disminuida. El opio,
en fin, está indicado en las neuralgias que se desarrollan sobre un fondo de eretismo con exaltacion
de la irritabilidad é impresionabilidad de los sentidos, con la condicion de que se le administre
á las dósis mas atenuadas y pequeñas. Si la práctica de los médicos antiguos no confirma este
dato, y si prácticos modernos desprecian esta propiedad del opio, es porque su masiva posologia
es casi la misma en todos los casos, y porque no varian las dósis.

Este medicamento en general es apto á despertar la sensibilidad en personas refractarias á
la accion medicamentosa, aun en las enfermedades agudas, si bien estas solo corresponden á
la insensibilidad debida al estado de plétora ó de congestion cerebral. El mercurio tiene,
como el opio y el azufre, el privilegio de escitar la vitalidad; pero el opio obra mejor en
la insensibilidad, y los otros en la inercia, y los tres, en los dos estados reunidos.

Entre los casos que reclaman mas justamente el opio, se halla el asma pletórico ó por congestion
pulmonal, y sobre todo el estreñimiento crónico sin tenesmo y esfuerzos espulsivos, aun en
los niños y las mujeres embarazadas. En los casos rebeldes es preciso insistir en su uso y
ayudar á veces su accion con varias dósis intercurrentes de nuez vómica, de plomo, de cantárida.
Hay pocas afecciones, que, como en este estreñimiento, sea necesario emplear mas medios curativos
y con mas perseverancia, especialmente si se ha abusado de las lavativas y de los baños tibios.

No indicarémos los efectos del opio en algunos casos de hernia estrangulada y de vólvulo, porque
este medicamento es absolutamente inferior á la nuez vómica, á la belladona sobre todo, y aun
al plomo; pero harémos mencion de su uso en el cólico saturnino en el que tiene una importancia
esencial, é indicarémos su eficacia en algunos flujos pasivos por inercia y falta de inervacion
ganglionar, tales como cierta diarrea acuosa, reciente ó antigua, la salivacion, hasta la mercurial,
el tialismo de los viejos, el esceso de orinas poco elaboradas y acuosas, la leucorrea de la
misma naturaleza y unida á algun principio especial de enfermedades crónicas.

=B.= Afecciones del sistema sanguíneo.--Ya hemos indicado que la astenia nerviosa propia del
opio no carece de alguna irritabilidad de la fibra, ó mejor aun, que no está exenta de cierta
alteracion de la contractilidad. La astenia es la tendencia y el fondo de todos los efectos
del opio, es el resultado final y directo: es esencial á su accion, y en esto se diferencia
de la de la nuez vómica, que es indirecta. Hé aquí los caractéres diferenciales de la astenia
del opio: espasmos clónicos, automáticos, postracion general, insensibilidad; los éstasis venosos
que resultan, no se limitan al sistema capilar, la congestion se estiende á los grandes vasos
y hasta el corazon, cuyos movimientos paraliza.

Sin embargo, corresponde al opio toda estancacion venosa con color azulado, sin aumento de
calor, y limitada á una parte dada, aunque sea crónica: esta es la única afeccion en que este
medicamento se adapta á la forma crónica; tales son los sabañones con hinchazon roja oscura
sin prurito ni dolor, ciertas gangrenas seniles en el período de congestion pasiva, afecciones
en las que el opio auxiliado del centeno de cornezuelo es de innegable eficacia.

Pero los casos en que el opio está con mas frecuencia y mas directamente indicado, es en las
congestiones pasivas, venosas, sin sensacion de ardor, y desarrolladas en un órgano cualquiera
por la indignacion ú otra emocion pronta, triste y enervante, especialmente si hay espasmos,
como en las mujeres paridas y en los niños, y en los movimientos convulsivos con estancacion
en los capilares cutáneos, frio y azulamiento de la piel, ojos fijos, pupilas dilatadas, congestion
cerebral y relajacion de las fuerzas. El opio juega en el coma soporoso, si hay sacudidas convulsivas
ó movimientos espasmódicos, agilidad de los miembros con rigideces parciales y momentáneas,
hinchazones azuladas ó negruzcas de la cara, lividez de las estremidades, labios péndulos,
pulso pequeño ó intermitente, respiracion suspirosa.

Está contraindicado por el estado cataléptico con pupilas contraidas, sin grande cambio en
la calorificacion y coloracion de la piel: pero está indicado en la asfixia de los recien nacidos
con cianosis, y en la asfixia por submersion con éstasis sanguíneo en la periferia ó apoplegía
capilar, en la apoplegía cerebral con insensibilidad y otros síntomas referidos anteriormente,
particularmente si la congestion es debida á la emocion paralizante de una grande indignacion,
ó á una costumbre de las congestiones que dispone á la postracion y á la congestion pasiva
propias de este medicamento.

=C.= Afecciones febriles.--Hay fiebres cuyos prodromos son notables por el frio, las sugilaciones,
el azulamiento de los dedos de las manos, por temblores musculares ó espasmos, por la somnolencia,
por la detencion y postracion que precede al desarrollo del calor y de la reaccion: estas fiebres,
intermitentes ó continuas, exigen el uso del opio, que en dósis débiles decide la reaccion,
la regulariza y disipa el estado de congestion pasiva de los centros nerviosos. No titubeamos
en manifestar que el opio transforma así desde el principio las fiebres nerviosas y llenas
de peligros en fiebres simples y de ninguna gravedad; es uno de los mas satisfactorios triunfos
del médico, si bien las circunstancias no permiten á los que son profanos á su arte el apreciar
sus actos y sus resultados.

El delirio con temblor de los músculos, relajacion de las fuerzas, ojos fijos, en la fiebre
tifoídea y nerviosa pútrida, cede al opio que disipa la astenia nerviosa á la par que el éstasis
sanguíneo del cerebro. Los accesos comatosos de las fiebres perniciosas están en este caso,
cuando empiezan por la aberracion de los sentidos, la agitacion, la divagacion de la imaginacion
ó el menosprecio á los objetos mas usuales; el coma se apodera poco á poco del sugeto; hay
inmovilidad completa, calor vivo, sudor abundante y caliente; el calor va desapareciendo, el
sudor se hace frio y la muerte sucede irremediablemente en medio de una insensibidad completa.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1057827</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20550</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Play well, not only in Korea alcoholic,
but in the St. Vitus dance, which is almost always helpful. Important is to warn The paralysis that
requires the nux vomica, the fact needs to be because a great nervous excitement of the action,
and gangrene in the arsenic must be result of excess inflammation. Here, then, the reason that
can not nux vomica be fully deactivated when the treatment of constipation due to lack rebels
efforts and to the paralysis of the sphincter, when this state is the result of a high irritability
to excess and leads to the sluggishness, inertia.

14. No Asthma .-- The condition is that the least you can do without the nux vomica for treatment.
The drug seems to act on the muscles of respiration concur and also no doubt about pneumogastric, while
arsenic mainly work the latter, on the pulmonary innervation, nerve and convulsive character was
the fact that frequently alternate with these two drugs to cure asthma and essential Most asthmatic
conditions. There are several effective medications for asthma, according to congestive dominating
element, paralytic, inflammatory, nervous, such are the ipecac tartar emetic, the bryony, lobelia,
etc. .....

15. No skin ailments. Chronic irritation of the mucous terns .-- The action of the walnut vomica
on the skin has some sharp, according to it expresses the general state of feverish spasm or seizure,
the erethism blood, gastric cancer, the affection of the liver and nutrition. So there is cold
skin, blue stained the same color, spicy and itching burning in the morning and afternoon,
burning sensations also excoriation, boils by successive eruptions, acne, yellowing or jaundice,
burning sensation at the points excoriated them get swollen and turned on, and giving blood
ulcers, rashes miliary pruritus, or slump quickly. Here, then, that many circumstances that indicate
nux vomica in chronic hepatitis, gastric eruptions, pustular acne, boils that reproduce, etc
.....

It is used also in certain cases of sebaceous secretion in the eyelids, irritation of free edge
of the same and conjunctiva, in persons given to drink in some stomatitis, even with thrush,
and chronic irritation of the lining of the mouth with swelling of the gums and canker sores
frequently, especially if they are very sensitive. Observed in this case some insidious provision
of the stomach or intestines in harmony with this state of the mouth, and burning pains, finally,
that accompany all mucosal irritation nux vomica. It is also effective in anal fissures with
contracture, burning pain, general irritability, in the rectum prolapsus, especially children, in
consequence of the efforts in the expulsion of very tough materials or dysenteric tenesmus.

=
Dose .=-- Nux is indicated for many diseases, it is necessary to
vary the doses of 1 to 10 drops and even more of the dye, until globules
of the thirtieth attenuation, debiéndose use the smallest in the sugetos
more irritable and functional disorders and neuralgic affections and
ESRD.

It also indicates that apart from considerations of age, sex, temperament, way of life, climate,
we have already said to be in harmony with the effects of walnut
vomica, there are others that should be considered in his administration:
nux vomica works best morning, and the effect, if possible, it is
given in the evening, their effects are then softer, particularly
in the dismenorreas ERETES periods in excess, in neuralgic affections,
constipation ..... Administered in the morning in case of this genre
in very irritable, angry and their action often causes aggravation
a multitude of symptoms seen in the morning.

It also avoids the then giving eating in people with stomach cramps, stomach pain, gastric,
neuralgic or venous, and some states congested, because just then develop but the sufferings or
presented. In asthma is administered by the day, and at all times in acute fast, even at the entrance
of pain. We believe it useful, in short, doing, once and for all, the sign also applies to other
drugs, but especially to the bryony, to the camomile, the sulfur ...., that in spite of the weakness
of the dose, it is necessary have the aggravations that can occur if these precautions are
neglected in ornery people live, very irritable, dry fiber and tight.

Aconite, the bryony and arnica are suitable means for calming the exasperated irritability
the nux vomica, and submit a blood character more nervous, or vice-versa, or as which extends to
contractility. Bryony chamomile and irritation that tune nux occurs in the digestive organs,
coffee and alcohol, the brain, the arsenic and the bryony, the respiratory tract, and chamomile
Staphysagria modify the default and irritability, the coca de Levante and arnica, accidents paralyzed.

OPIUM

§
I. - History [14].

This substance is the dried juice of the green heads of the poppy
family somnifera the poppies, Juss .-- In monogínea polyandry, Linn
.-- Opium, in therapeutic work modern, has a chapter of its physiological
effects, but almost only refer to toxins, disruptive, disposers, and
not to the physiological and really special which extend to all appliances
throughout the body by a continuous peaceful purposes, that since
the first impression in the economy rises to the fullness of his action,
chronicity and dyscrasia.

We've listed several times weaker results of these incomplete studies, so we do not insist, allowing
only state that the Opium is one of the drugs less known or more incompletely studied, which
confess every educated man, if you know the strange differences in the views of authors issued
on this product.

Large doses of opium to calm some pain, extinguishes the feeling of
others, and some sometimes relieves insomnia, many studies have materialized
to this, and as pain and insomnia symptoms are common to most diseases,
opium has been used in almost all of them.

Is given in phthisis to relieve cough, in the prodromal period of
fever eruptive, for inducing sleep, and many other acute cases in
which can only be achieved to use the aggravation of discomfort, increased
fever, the erethism and danger.

He has managed successively more or less success, neuralgia, neuro, epilepsy and several other convulsive
affections, in asthma, chorea, delirium tremens, tetanus, dementia, diarrhea, dysentery, uterine
bleeding ..... We should not pass over in silence the unspeakable practice of giving opium
mixed with other drugs in the belief tolerable dose to administer stronger and the enemy of all movement
Espansiva in the eruptive fevers and other diseases listed above.

Physiological effects .-- § II.

Opium is among the drugs that more clearly presents its special effects as from the excitement
of the nervous system and blood, driving excitement to the inertia
of the two systems, to passive congestion, to the insensitivity.

In its Acute action, it enhances the sensitivity, and weaker in the chronicle. The blood is
more oxygenated Scythians in the action and acute, and less on chronic and slow the course of this
fluid contributes to enhance their quality vein, a quality that makes it unfit for normal excitation
organs.

Opium is a narcotic, for if elective work on the brain and nerves
of relation, does it for the mediation of the nodal system which is
addressed first, and only apparently to influence the brain.

The effects of this medicine and specialty its action can be summarized in the following symptoms:

Feeling
of strength and vigor, sleeplessness, chills followed by heat, excess irritability of the muscles
that are under the command of the will, pulse full and frequent, sparks before the eyes, ringing in
the ears, lightheadedness, heaviness of head, joy, great flow of ideas, adventuresome, dry
mouth, excitement of sexual appetite, heat and constriction chest, agility of the members.
These symptoms of excitement are proprietary opium of more or less
duration and increases with the dose, so it shows: concerns in Member,
flushed face or color changes quickly, burning heat and itching all
over the body, hard and fast pulse, drowsiness, peace of mind wandering
or delirium, heat dizziness, congestion in the head and strong beats,
altered vision, heaviness in the stomach and abdomen with heartbeat,
constipation, dysuria, excitation of genito-urinary and pollution
with erections, difficulty in breathing, pressure chest.

These symptoms are the following: indifference, delirium, loss of consciousness, sleep comatose,
ruddy face, burning and a puffy, dry skin and increased the urine or loose stools, sometimes
hot sweat and suppression of escreciones, heaviness of the head with a need to close the eyes, darkening
of the light, difficult word and slow, nausea, vomiting, stomach aches, and impotence ecstasy
love, oppression with anxiety or slow and noisy breathing, swelling of the veins. These same symptoms,
if the doses are large, they become more and more narcotics: general
insensitivity, tremor, shaking, bouts of suffocation, swelling of
the whole body blue, comatose sleep with snoring, eyes open and seizure,
flushed face and swollen, blue and swollen lips, pulse slow and intermittent,
loss of consciousness, relaxation of the muscles of the face and body,
convulsive movements, usually cold, tympanitis, involuntary bowel
movements, eyelids and pendulous lips, tongue and paralysis of the
extremities.

A very small dose to continue in use for a long time, expresses symptoms alteration of the sensitivity
and contractility, the lesion of the digestive forces, increasing
the venous system and the alteration of the blood, as shown by the
following: headache, tenesmus, dizziness and pain in the head punctures,
neuralgia and fast living moving from one point to another, pulling
pain in the limbs, spasmodic jerks, heat burning in abdomen, chest,
the chest region, cramping pains in the extremities, gastralgias,
stomach cramps and the matrix, the disclosures of suffocation, constriction
painful chest, agitation, muscle weakness and large relaxation of
the fiber.

By denying Hahnemann opium property of exciting pain, and without doubt proceeded undergoes him
to dose very weak or very strong, because the ease with which we have produced the symptom
pain already mentioned, the comments we made about two opium-saturated, we raise fears that
other experiments have not addressed their research to this point.

The chronic action of opium has noticeable symptoms: emaciation general, sensitivity excess to
the cold, pale skin, chalky face, swelling of the veins, serous infiltration throughout the
body, itching skin, swelling blue fingers and toes, and especially the big toe, distressing dreams,
moral inconsistency, scary character, weakness of the intellectual faculties of imagination
errors, perturbation of the head, excitability nervous, ringing in the ears, teeth hesitant
and swollen gums that bleed easily, salivation, bitter taste, aversion to food, slow and weak
digestion, gastralgia, easy to vomiting, flatulence, constipation,
persistent, low, dark urine, Pollutions without erection, dry cough
hits.

Opium abusers are weak, their nutritional and excretory movements are slow, ganglionic nerves apparently
no encouragement to the organs of nutrition and fluids, and not actively influence the relationship
nerves. But that aside from this inertia will observe some of the brain and nervous irritability
of the medulla oblongata, you can not deduce that opium exerts an action opposite in the two
lives, organizational and relationship, as want some doctors. This opinion does not support
any founded reason: for diversity phenomena that we indicated and correspond to the two lives may well
depend that the influence of the will in the organs subjected to the same not in harmony with
the force that animates them, and in any case, can explanations for automatic contractions
and the contractility asthenic injury, cerebro-spinal innervation is so weak as the nodal innervation.
Irritability and moral fiber in opium, are purely asthenic and the
same nature as the chamomile.

§ III .-- therapeutic effects.

= A. = Nervous affections .-- fully sanctioned clinical outcomes data on the action of opium have
collected and esponse, and therefore sufficient to limit ourselves to the study of the facts, all theories
abstraction very scholarly at times, but much less simple processes of nature.

Opium is the drug most suitable for combat as sharp and explosive attack activity life produced
by the indignation, but the passive indignation, that is, when the body suffer the horror without
the moral react, not the indignation aroused anger affective or feeling as required by aconite.
Opium sobreescita fiber to plunge in inertia and insensitivity, the
indignation produce the same effects, sometimes dominate the last
to the point of being the only one that can be seen, as when terror
seems paralyzed, which produces involuntary stool or urine, which
tends to abortion that suppresses the lochia, the rules.

Here there is no original effect, or secondary, but as just a simple and progressive effect
of the tension to inertia by the same action. By final fatigue that characterizes its action,
corresponds exactly to opium congestion produced by the concentration of fright or fear in the various
organs, impeding Thus the development of a febrile reaction often terrible, and where necessary
use, without forgetting the aconite or arnica for the same.

Nocturnal epilepsy, insomnia, migraine, people with senses obtuse plethoric and suffering from
discomfort, burning in the visceral cavities are solely those of opium, and the delirium tremens
of the drunks in the second period, assisted with datura and after
arnica or coffee.

Lead colic is at its best cure opium, the platinum is often useful after him.

We do not want to omit the results indicate opium eSCelente spasms children with difficult breathing
and blood stasis in the capillaries, or when they have just by fits, preceded by screaming,
and chamomile, belladonna and have not been ignacia sufficient. Should be resorted to opium
in certain Neuroses with trembling of the extremities, insomnia, agitation, anxiety in the limbs, constipation,
and in mania or mental alienation characterized by frequent change of heat in the face, by the
alternation of prostration and estilacion, with venous injection of the eyes many times, convulsive
movements, constipation.

In sugetos weakened by long and frequent excite brain with marasmus, dry skin and earthy or yellow,
or null perverted appetite, gastrointestinal weakness, swelling of
the veins lack of secretion, be used with good results Opium neuralgias
of sensory apparatus, whether purely nervous or who have congestive
character, or else Cramp, lancinating, fixed, or that have irregular
course, constant, intermittent.

Opium also combat neuralgia plethoric persons, and the old in that
receptivity medicinal influence is weakened and diminished brain.

Opium in short, is indicated for neuralgia that develop on a background with excitement erethism
of irritability and impressions of the senses, with the condition that they be given to the more
attenuated and small doses. If the ancient medical practice does not confirm this data, and
if practical modern opium despise this property is because the massive
dosage is almost the same in all cases, and why not vary the dose.

This medicine is generally suitable to raise awareness in people refractory to drug action, even
in acute disease, although these only correspond to insensitivity due to the state of fullness
or of cerebral congestion. Mercury has, such as opium and sulfur, the privilege of exciting vitality,
but work better in opium insensitivity, and the other in the inertia, and three in the two states
combined.

Among the cases that demand more precisely the opium is replete asthma or by congestion pulmonary,
and especially chronic constipation without urgency and effort expelled, even children and
pregnant women. In stubborn cases it is necessary to ensure their use and sometimes help their
action with various doses of nux vomica intercurrent, lead, Spanish fly. There are few conditions,
which, as in this constipation is necessary to use more healing means
and with more perseverance, especially when abused enemas and warm
baths.

Not indicate the effects of opium in some cases of strangulated hernia and volvulus, because this
drug is quite inferior to the nux vomica, belladonna to about everything, and even lead, but
we will mention its use in colic which is important essential and
indicated their effectiveness in certain liabilities flows by inertia
and lack of innervation node, such as certain watery diarrhea, recent
or old, salivation, to the mercurial the ptyalism of old, the excess
of urine produced little watery, vaginal discharge of nature and linked
to any special principle of chronic disease.

= B = blood system disorders .-- We have already indicated that the fatigue of the nerve itself
Opium is not without some irritability of fiber, or better yet, it is not without some alteration
of contractility. Fatigue is the trend and the background of all effects Opium is the final result
and direct: it is essential to their action, and this difference that of nux vomica, which is
indirect.

Behold the differential characters of fatigue Opium: clonic spasms, automatic, general prostration,
insensibility, the venous stasis which are not limited to the capillary system, the congestion
extends to the great vessels and to the heart, which paralyzes movement.

However, for the opium all bluish venous stagnation, with no increase heat, and limited to a
given part, albeit chronic, this is the only condition in which the medication is adapted to
the chronic form, these are the dark red and swelling chilblains no itching or pain, gangrene
senile certain period of passive congestion, conditions where the opium assisted rye ergot is undeniably
effective.

But where opium is more frequently and more directly stated, is in passive congestion, venous, no
burning sensation, and developed in any organ by emotion, or other
prompt indignation, sad and unnerving, especially if there spasms
and in postpartum women and children, and convulsive movements with
stagnation capillaries in skin, cold and blue skin, eyes, dilated
pupils, congestion Brain relaxation of forces.

Opium plays Soporous coma, convulsive shock if or jerky movements, agility of the members
with partial and momentary rigidity, bluish or blackish swelling of the face, pallor of the
extremities, lips pendulous small or intermittent pulse, sighing respiration.

Is contraindicated cataleptic state with constricted pupils, without
much change in calorification and coloration of the skin, but is indicated
in the suffocation of newborn with cyanosis, and asphyxia by submersion
with blood stasis in the periphery or apoplexy capillary in the cerebral
apoplexy with numbness and other symptoms described above, particularly
if the congestion is due to the crippling emotion of a great indignation,
or to a custom of the congestion that has to prostration and to the
passive congestion characteristic of this drug.

= C = Conditions febrile fevers whose Prodrom .-- There are remarkable for the cold, the sugilaciones,
The blues of the fingers, and muscle tremors or spasms, and drowsiness, for the detention and prostration
which precedes the development of heat and reaction: these fevers, intermittent or continuous, requiring
the use of opium in small doses decided by the reaction, regulates
and dissipates the state of passive congestion of nerve centers.

Do not hesitate in showing that opium thus transformed from the start and filled with nervous fever
Hazard simple fevers and no gravity, is one of the most satisfying wins the physician, although
the circumstances do not allow those who are uninitiated to appreciate his art their actions and
their results.

Delirium tremor of the muscles, relaxation of the forces, eyes fixed on the mouth typhoid and
nervous putrid opium yields to fatigue dissipates nervous at the
same stasis blood to the brain.

Comatose accesses of fevers are harmful in this case, when starting with the aberration of the
senses, the agitation, the wandering of the imagination or contempt to the more unusual items,
the comma is possession of sugeto little by little, there complete immobility, direct heat,
profuse sweating and hot, the heat wears off, the sweat is cold and death inevitably occurs
in the midst of a full insensibidad.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>