<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04696</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>99117</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22204</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Después que hubo saludado, Gonzalo fué a sentarse cerca de Pablito, y pasándole la mano familiarmente
por encima del hombro, le dijo al oído:

--¿Cuál es la que más te gusta?

Y al inclinarse hacia su futuro cuñado, clavaba una mirada intensa en Venturita, que correspondió
a ella con otra muy singular. Después ambos las convirtieron a Cecilia. Esta no había levantado
la cabeza del bastidor.

--Nieves--respondió Pablo sin vacilar, y en el mismo tono de falsete.

--Lo sabía, y te aplaudo el gusto--dijo riendo Gonzalo.--¡Qué cutis de raso!... ¡Qué dentadura!

--¡Y qué andares! Pasi-corta, ¿sabes?

Ambos miraban a la bordadora. Esta levantó la cabeza, y comprendiendo que se trataba de ella,
les hizo una mueca con la lengua.

--Vamos, no vale hablarse al oído--dijo doña Paula con la susceptibilidad vidriosa que caracteriza
a las mujeres del pueblo.

--Déjelos usted, señora--replicó Nieves.--Están hablando de mí: no hay que quitarles el gusto.

--Cierto; Pablo me hacía notar el color rojo de ciertos labios, la transparencia de cierto
cutis, un pelo dorado a fuego...

--Valentina, entonces hablaban de ti--dijo Nieves ruborizada tocando en el muslo a su compañera.

--¡Qué gracia! No te apures, mujer. ¡Si ya sabemos que eres la más guapa!--dijo la otra visiblemente
picada.

--¡Paz, paz, señoras!--exclamó Gonzalo.--Verdad que Pablo comenzó hablándome de las perfecciones
de Nieves; pero también es cierto que pensaba continuar con las de todas las demás, si no se
le hubiese interrumpido... ¿No es eso, Pablo?

--Desde luego: contaba seguir con Valentina...

Esta levantó la cabeza y le miró con aquel gracioso ceño burlón que daba carácter a su rostro.

--Ten cuidado, Nieves, que estos señoritos se pierden de vista.

Pablo, sin hacer caso de la interrupción, prosiguió:

--Después con Teresa y Encarnación, Elvira y Generosa. Hablaría también de Venturita (para
ponerla, por supuesto, por los pies de los caballos). De Cecilia no, porque está comprometida,
y algo diría también de mi señora doña Paula, que, sin ofender a nadie, es la más hermosa de todas.

--¡Qué pillastre!--exclamó ésta admirada del donaire de su hijo.

Pablo se había levantado de la butaca, y abrazó a su madre con efusión.

--¡Quita, quita, adulador!--dijo ella riendo.

--Ve aflojando el bolsillo, mamá--dijo Venturita.

--¡Lo ves! La pata de gallo de siempre--exclamó iracundo el joven, volviendo la cabeza hacia
su hermana, mientras ésta se reía maliciosamente sin levantar la suya del bastidor.

--Mucho has trabajado--dijo Gonzalo en voz baja, sentándose al lado de su novia.

--Así, así--respondió Cecilia fijando en él sus ojos grandes, llenos de luz.

--Mucho, sí; ayer no tenías bordado ese clavel... digo, me parece que es clavel...

--Es jazmín.

--Ni esas dos hojas más.

--¡Bah! Eso no es nada.

--¿Y qué es lo que estás bordando?

Cecilia siguió moviendo la aguja sin contestar.

--¿Qué es lo que bordas?--preguntó Gonzalo en voz, más alta, pensando que no le había oído.

--Una sábana... ¡calla!--replicó la joven levantando un poco los ojos hacia las costureras
y volviendo a abatirlos rápidamente.

Al mismo tiempo, los de Gonzalo y Venturita se tropezaron por encima de la cabeza de Cecilia,
y de ellos brotó una chispa.

--Ya ven ustedes que hay para todas--decía Pablito mirando al mismo tiempo fijamente a Nieves,
como diciendo: «No hagas caso, esto lo digo por cumplir».

--¿Qué es lo que hay para todas, don Pablo?--preguntó Valentina con tonillo irónico.

--Flores, criatura.

--Écheselas usted al Santísimo.

--Y a las niñas guapas como tú.

--Si no soy guapa, paso delante de las guapas y no les hago la venia, ¿sabe usted?

--¡Demonio! No hay que acercarse a esta Valentina; se levanta de atrás--exclamó el apuesto mancebo.

El símil, aunque nada culto, y acaso por eso, hizo reir a las costureras.

--A Valentina no le gustan los señoritos--manifestó Encarnación.

--Hace bien; de los señoritos no se saca más que parola, tiempo perdido y a veces la desgracia
para toda la vida--dijo sentenciosamente doña Paula sin acordarse de que ella había sacado
la felicidad.--Tocante a eso, Sarrió está perdido. Apenas hay muchacha que se deje acompañar
de uno de su igual. El mozo ha de traer por lo menos corbata y hongo, y ha de fumar con boquilla...
aunque no tenga plato en que comer. Ninguna se oculta ya para ir al obscurecer acompañada de
algún señorito, y a la vuelta de las romerías da grima verlas venir colgadas del brazo de ellos
cantando al alta la lleva... ¡Pobrecillas! No sabéis lo que os espera. Porque el hijo de don
Rudesindo se casó con la de Pepe la Esguila y el piloto de la Trinidad con la de Mechacan,
se os figura que todo el monte es orégano. Al freir será el reir... Mirad, mirad a Benita la
del señor Matías el sacristán. ¿Qué linda está y que compuestita, verdad?

--Benita está escriturada--dijo Encarnación.

--Escriturada, ¿eh? ¡Ya veréis de qué le vale la escritura!

--Señora, el novio no puede dejarla; si la deja, va a presidio por toda la vida.

--Calla, calla, bobalicona; ¿quién os ha metido esas bolas por la cabeza?

--Eso se sabe... vamos. Benita está consultada.

--Mire, señora--dijo Teresa, la morena sentimental,--la verdad en que nosotras corremos peligro;
tiene usted razón... ¿Pero qué quiere que hagamos? Los artesanos de esta villa ¡están tan echados
a perder! El que más y el que menos pasa el domingo y el lunes en la taberna, y algún día también
por la semana. ¿Cuántos son los que traen el jornal a casa y lo entregan a su mujer, dígame
por su vida? Si es marinero, se le ve una vez cada año; trae cuatro cuartos, y hala, otra vez
para allá. Los cuartos se concluyen, y la infeliz mujer se ve arrastrada, trabajando para dar
un pedazo de pan a sus hijos... Y luego, ¿qué saben ellos de dar estimación ni un poco de gracia
a la mujer? Si salen con ella un domingo por la tarde, se van parando en todas las tabernas
del camino, dejándola, si se tercia, a la pobrecilla a la puerta, o llamándola para que oiga
alguna sandez, que la pone más colorada que una amapola... ¡Calle, calle, señora, si hay cada
mostrenco que, como Dios me ha de juzgar, no vale el pan que come!... El otro día encontró
a Tomasina... ya sabe, la del tío Rufo, que no hace tan siquiera un año que se casó con un
oficial de Próspero... Pues iba en aquel mismo instante a por dos reales en casa de su padre
para comprar un pan, porque en todo aquel día no había comido un bocado. Su marido se bebe
casi todo el jornal, y a mitad de semana, ¡claro! tiene la infeliz que apretarse la barriga...
¡Válgate Dios! Y las más de las noches viene borracho perdido a casa, y le da cada sopimpa
que la deja por muerta. ¡Cuántas veces se va la pobrecilla a la cama sin cenar y harta de palos!...
Luego quieren que una, viendo estas cosas... ¡Vaya, más vale callar! Lo que yo digo, ¡caramba!
ya que la lleve a una el diablo, que la lleve en coche.

--Oye, tú--saltó Valentina levantando el rostro con su ceño habitual algo más pronunciado,--no
te pongas tan fanfarrona. Di que te gustan los señoritos, bueno... yo no me meto en eso; pero
no vengas quitando el crédito a los rapaces de tu igual... Se emborrachan, los que se emborrachan...
Más de un señorito y mas de dos he visto yo venir como cabras para su casa... Y pegan a sus
mujeres, también los que pegan... Si ellas no tuvieran la lengua larga, no las llevarían la
mitad de las veces... Atiende; y don Ramón el maestro de música cuando llegaba a casa por la
noche ¿daba bizcochos a su mujer? Tú lo debes de saber... bien cerca vivías.

--Mujer, yo no hablo por todos--repuso Teresa amainando por el temor de que su díscola compañera
le sacase a relucir el acompañamiento nocturno de Donato Rojo, el médico de la Sanidad,--sólo
digo que los hay muy brutos...

--Bueno, pues déjalos en paz y no te acuerdes de ellos, que ellos tampoco se acuerdan de ti.
Cada una es cada una, y la que más y la que menos sabe por dónde corre el agua del molino.

--Oyes, Valentina--dijo Elvira sonriendo maliciosamente,--cuando te cases, ¿piensas llevarlas
de Cosme?

--Si las merezco las llevaré... Más quiero llevar dos bofetadas de mi Cosme que el desprecio
de un señorito, ¡alza!

--Así me gusta; ¡aprended, aprended, chiquillas!--dijo Pablito.

Gonzalo, después de un rato de conversación en voz baja con su novia, se levantó, dió tres
o cuatro vueltas por la sala, y vino a sentarse al lado de Venturita, con la cual solía tener
jarana. Gustaban ambos de embromarse y retozar después que había nacido la confianza. La niña
estaba dibujando unas letras para bordar.

--No vengas a hacer burla, Gonzalo. Ya sabemos que dibujo mal--dijo clavándole una mirada provocativa,
relampagueante, que obligó al joven a bajar la suya.

--No es cierto eso; no dibujas mal--respondió él en voz baja y levemente temblorosa, acercando
el rostro al papel que Venturita tenía sobre el regazo.

--Pura galantería. Convendrás en que podía estar mejor.

--Mejor... mejor... todo puede estar mejor en el mundo. Está bastante bien.

--Te vas haciendo muy adulador. Yo no quiero que te rías de mí, ¿lo oyes?

--¡Oh! yo no me río de nadie... pero mucho menos de ti...--repuso él sin levantar los ojos
del papel, con voz cada vez más baja y visiblemente conmovido.

Venturita tenía siempre los ojos fijos en él con una expresión maliciosa, donde se leía claramente
el triunfo del orgullo satisfecho.

--Vamos, dibújalas tú, señor ingeniero--dijo alargándole con gracioso despotismo el papel y
el lápiz.

El joven los tomó y osó levantar la vista hacia la niña; pero la bajó en seguida como si temiera
electrizarse. Plantó el libro, que ella tenía en el regazo, sobre sus rodillas, aplicó encima
un papel blanco, y se puso a dibujar. Mas en vez de las letras, comenzó a trazar con soltura
la cabeza de una mujer. Primero el pelo partido en dos trenzas, después la frente estrecha
y bonita, luego una nariz delicada, una boca pequeña, la barba admirablemente recortada unida
a la garganta por una curva suave y elegante... Se parecía prodigiosamente a Venturita. Esta,
apoyada sobre el hombro de su futuro hermano, seguía los movimientos del lápiz. Poco a poco
se iba esparciendo por su rostro una sonrisa vanidosa. Después de trazar la cabeza, Gonzalo
siguió con el busto. Le puso el peinador o matinée que la niña vestía, y se entretuvo buen
rato a dibujar minuciosamente los lazos de seda con que se sujetaba por delante. Cuando el
retrato estuvo terminado. Venturita le dijo con acento picaresco:

--Ahora, pon debajo quién es.

El joven levantó la cabeza y sus miradas chocaron sonrientes. Luego, con viveza y decisión,
escribió debajo de la figura: Lo que más quiero en el mundo.

Venturita tomó el papel entre las manos y lo contempló unos instantes con deleite. Después,
haciendo una mueca de fingido desdén, se lo alargó otra vez diciendo:

--Toma, toma, embustero.

Pero antes de llegar a manos de Gonzalo, Cecilia extendió la suya y se lo arrebató riendo.

--¿Qué papelitos son ésos?

Venturita, como si la hubieran pinchado, brincó en el asiento y sujetó fuertemente la muñeca
de su hermana.

--¡Trae, trae, Cecilia! ¡Deja eso!--exclamó con el rostro echando fuego, contraído por forzada
sonrisa.

--No; quiero verlo.

--Ya lo verás después; ¡suelta!

--Quiero verlo ahora.

--Vamos, niña, déjaselo ver. ¿Qué te importa?--dijo doña Paula.

--No quiero que me lo quite nadie por fuerza--gritó poniéndose seria. Después, comprendiendo
la imprudencia de esto, tornó a ponerse risueña.

--Vamos, Cecilia, suelta; no seas mala.

--¡Vaya un empeño! ¡Suelta tú, que me lastimas!

--¿Quién eres tú para quitarme el papel de la mano?--profirió con rabia, poniéndose esta vez
seria de verdad.--¡Suelta, suelta, fea, narices de cotorra, tonta!... ¡Suelta, o te araño!--añadió
con los ojos centelleantes y la faz descompuesta por la cólera.

Al verla de aquel modo, la risa que agitaba el pecho de Cecilia paralizóse súbito, y abriendo
sus grandes ojos donde se pintaba la sorpresa, exclamó:

--¡Jesús! Pareces loca, niña. Toma, toma, no vaya a darte algo.

Y soltó el papelito que arrugaba en el puño. Venturita, la faz alterada aún, lo hizo mil trozos.

--¡En los días de mi vida he visto una criatura más loca!--exclamó doña Paulina santiguándose.--¡Ave
María! ¡Ave María! ¿De quién has sacado ese genio, chiquilla?

--Sería de ti--respondió Venturita enfoscada, sin mirar a nadie.

--¡Desvergonzada!... ¡Si no fuera mirando a que hay gente delante!... ¿Cómo contestas de ese
modo a tu madre, picara? ¿No sabes los mandamientos de la ley de Dios? Mañana mismo te llevo
a confesar con don Aquilino.

--Bueno, dale memorias a don Aquilino.

--¡Espera, espera, grandísima picara!--gritó la señora haciendo ademán de levantarse para castigar
a su hija.

Pero en aquel instante aparecía en la puerta la figura de don Rosendo con bata multicolor y
gorro de terciopelo con borla de seda.

--¿Qué pasa?--preguntó sorprendido viendo la actitud airada de su esposa.

Esta le puso al corriente, sofocada por los sollozos, de la falta de respeto de su hija.

Don Rosendo se creyó en el caso de arrugar el entrecejo, y decir con tono solemne:

--Eso está mal hecho, Ventura. Ve a pedir perdón a tu mamá.

Se le conocía que estaba distraído, absorto por algún pensamiento, y que aquel suceso doméstico
no conseguía más que a medias arrancarle de su preocupación.

Sin embargo, al ver a la chica inmóvil, en actitud altiva y desdeñosa, dijo de nuevo, con más
firmeza:

--Vamos, hija, ve a pedirla perdón, ya que la has ofendido.

La niña hizo su peculiar mohín de desprecio con los labios, y murmuró muy bajito:

--¡Sí, en eso estoy pensando!

--Vaya, Ventura, ¿qué murmuras ahí? Anda, antes que me enfade.

--Anda, anda, Venturita. Ve allá. No seas así--le dijeron por lo bajo las costureras.

--No me da la gana. ¿Queréis dejarme en paz?--les respondió ella en voz baja también, mas con
acento iracundo.

--¿No quieres ir?--preguntó don Rosendo con afectada severidad.--¿No quieres ir?

La niña permaneció inmóvil y silenciosa.

--¡Pues sal de aquí ahora mismo! ¡Quítate de mi vista!

Venturita se levantó de la silla, pasó por el medio del concurso erguida y enfurruñada, y salió
de la sala dando un gran portazo.

Don Rosendo, después de permanecer un momento inmóvil con los ojos puestos en la puerta por
donde su hija había salido, volvióse diciendo:

--Siento mucho estar tan fuerte con mis hijas... pero algunas veces no hay más remedio.

VII

QUE TRATA DE DOS TRAIDORES

Borróse súbito de su noble faz pseudomarítima la temerosa expresión que la obscurecía, y apareció
de nuevo aquella otra distraída, signo de constantes meditaciones.

--Gonzalo, si no te molesta, te rogaría que pasases conmigo al despacho--manifestó dirigiéndose
a su futuro yerno.

Este, que durante la anterior escena había empalidecido y vuelto a su ser varias veces, tornó
a desconcertarse. Nada menos se le ocurrió que don Rosendo se había percatado de la instabilidad
de sus sentimientos amorosos, y le iba a pedir de ello estrecha cuenta. Fuese, pues, detrás
de él cabizbajo y receloso, y penetró en el escritorio. Era una estancia espaciosa, amueblada
con lujo de comerciante rico: gran mesa de caoba maciza, armarios de caoba también, donde había
más legajos de papeles que libros, alfombra de terciopelo, divanes forrados de brocatel, y
escribanía de plata enorme como un monumento. Cerca de la cuarta parte de esta cámara ocupábalo
un montón de paquetitos envueltos en papel de varios colores, que para cualquiera que por primera
vez entrase en ella, sería un misterio. No lo era para Gonzalo ni para ninguno de los íntimos
de la casa. Aquellos paquetes guardaban palillos de dientes.

¿Cómo?--preguntará el lector.--¿Don Rosendo Belinchón, un negociante de tanto fuste, comerciaba
también en palillos de dientes? No, don Rosendo no comerciaba con ellos, los fabricaba. Y esto
no con el fin de especular, cosa indigna de su categoría, sino por pura y desinteresada inclinación
de su espíritu. Desde muy joven se le había manifestado. Las asiduas ocupaciones del comercio
y las vicisitudes por que había pasado su existencia, no le habían consentido satisfacer esta
pasión sino de una manera precaria en los ratos materialmente perdidos. Pero desde que pudo
dejar el escritorio confiado a algunos fieles dependientes, entregóse de lleno con alma y vida
a tan útil y honesta distracción. Por la mañana en la tienda de Graells, por la tarde en el
Saloncillo, por la noche en su casa o en la de don Pedro Miranda, siempre trabajando. Su criado
ocupaba una gran parte del día en cortarle unos tacos de avellano seco perfectamente iguales,
de donde su mano diestra había de sacar la gala de los palillos.

Y como no se daba punto de reposo, ni aun en los días festivos, la producción era excesiva.
No había bastantes consumidores en la villa, y se veía necesitado a remitir paquetes de ellos
a los amigos de la capital, cuando el montón del despacho llegaba al techo. Gracias a los esfuerzos
nobilísimos de este claro representante de su comercio, podemos decir con orgullo que Sarrió,
en tal ramo interesante del progreso, se hallaba a la altura de las grandes capitales. Ninguna
otra villa española o extranjera podría sufrir con ella competencia. En casa del rico, como
en la del menestral, jamás faltaba un bien abastecido palillero, testimonio indiscutible de
la refinada cultura de sus habitantes.

Señaló don Rosendo un diván a su hijo en ciernes, y éste, asustado, dejóse caer en él hundiéndole
profundamente. Acercó después el comerciante una silla con ademán misterioso, y sentándose
frente al joven y mirándole entre risueño y avergonzado, dijo, dándole al propio tiempo una
palmadita en el muslo:

--Vamos a ver, Gonzalito: ¿qué te parece de la cuestión del matadero?

--¿El matadero?--preguntó aquél abriendo unos ojos como puños.

--Sí, el nuevo matadero; ¿crees que debe emplazarse en la Escombrera, o en la playa de las
Meanas detrás de las casas de don Rudesindo?

Gonzalo vió el cielo abierto, y, sonriendo de placer, respondió:

--Yo creo que en la playa de las Meanas estaría bien... Muy abierto aquello... muy ventilado...

Pero notando que la frente de su suegro se fruncía, y en sus ojos se apagaba repentinamente
la sonrisa, añadió balbuciendo:

--Tampoco me parece que estaría mal en la Escombrera...

--Mucho mejor, Gonzalo... ¡Infinitamente mejor!

--Puede, puede.

--Hombre, tan puede ser, que reservadamente te diré que el emplazarlo en la playa lo juzgo
(hazme el favor de guardar reserva sobre esta opinión), lo juzgo... una verdadera insensatez...
u-na ver-da-de-ra in-sen-sa-tez--repitió señalando mejor todas las sílabas.

--Y esta opinión mía--añadió--no vayas a figurarte que es de ayer mañana, sino de toda la vida.
Desde que fuí capaz de entender ciertas cosas, comprendí que el matadero no debía estar donde
hoy está. En una palabra, que debía trasladarse. ¿Dónde? Una voz interior me decía siempre
que a la Escombrera. Antes de poder dar ninguna razón científica, estaba tan convencido como
ahora de que allí debía emplazarse, y no en otra parte. Hoy que la resolución del problema
se aproxima, me creo obligado a sostener esta opinión, a comunicar al pueblo mi pensamiento
y el resultado de mis meditaciones. Si no tienes que hacer voy a leerte la carta que dirijo
con este motivo al Progreso de Lancia.

Y en efecto, sin aguardar la contestación de Gonzalo, se dirigió a la mesa, tomó unos pliegos
de papel que había sobre ella, se puso las gafas, y acercándose al balcón dió comienzo, no
sin cierta emoción que se le traslucía en la voz, a la lectura de la carta.

Estaba escrita en papel comercial, grande y rayado. Todas las que desde hacía años dirigía
al Progreso de Lancia y a otros periódicos de la capital de la provincia, iban escritas en
el mismo papel por las dos caras. Aun no sabía que para la imprenta debía escribirse por una
solamente. Pero muy pronto adquirió este precioso conocimiento, como hemos de ver.

Casi al mismo tiempo que la de los palillos de dientes había nacido en don Rosendo Belinchón
la afición a escribir comunicados a los periódicos: es decir, que databa de una remota antigüedad.
Ardiente partidario de los progresos humanos, de las reformas en todos los órdenes, de la discusión
y de la luz, claro está que la prensa había de infundirle respeto y entusiasmo. Los periódicos
habían sido siempre un elemento indispensable de su existencia. Estaba suscripto a muchos nacionales
y extranjeros; porque, como educado para el comercio, conocía bastante bien el francés y el
inglés, y nunca le había faltado, ni aun en los días más ocupados, un par de horas que dedicar
a su lectura. Estas horas se aumentaron considerablemente desde hacía algunos años, no sin
que se resintiese por ello el bacalao. El goce que nuestro héroe experimentaba por las mañanas
después de tomar el chocolate tragándose los artículos de fondo del Pabellón Nacional, los
sueltos de La Política y las Nouvelles à la main del Fígaro era tan vivo, que le quedaba impreso
largo tiempo en el rostro, hasta que por la irradiación se iba perdiendo en la atmósfera.

Como todos los hombres de miras amplias y elevadas, no era exclusivista en sus gustos periodísticos.
Amaba el periódico por el periódico, por ser una muestra gentil del progreso de la razón humana,
o como él decía mejor, «una manifestación levantada de la conciencia pública». Las opiniones
que cada cual defendía, eran cosa secundaria. Estaba suscripto a periódicos de todos colores,
y los gozaba por igual. Si alguna predilección mostraba, era únicamente por los artículos y
sueltos intencionados. Porque eso de decir una cosa aparentando expresar la contraria y retorcer
las frases de modo que una cláusula inocente en la apariencia llevase dentro «una saeta envenenada»
llenaba de admiración a don Rosendo y le volvía loco de alegría. ¡Cuántas veces al leer en
La España algún párrafo por el estilo:--«Ayer apareció por fin la circular del señor Presidente
del Supremo a sus subordinados. Felicitamos al general O'Donnell, presidente de esta situación
liberal, al señor Negrete, que en algún rato lúcido ha dado cima a obra tan colosal, y a los
demócratas protectores de este Gobierno»,--hubo exclamado agitando el periódico en las manos:--¡Qué
intención! ¡Caracoles! ¡¡Qué intención!!
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06722</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>346148</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20251</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

After he had saluted, Gonzalo went to sit by Pablito, and passing his hand familiarly over his shoulder,
whispered:

- What is your favorite?

And bending over his future brother-nailed an intense look in Venturita,
corresponding her with something very unique.

Then both the converted Cecilia.

This had not raised head of the frame.

- Snow - Paul replied without hesitation, and in the same tone of falsetto.

- I knew it, and I applaud you taste - Gonzalo laughed .-- What skin satin '... What teeth!

- And to walk! Pasi-short, you know?

Both looked to the embroidery.

This raised his head, and realizing that it was her I grimaced with his tongue.

- Come on, it does not speak in his ear - "Dona Paula with susceptibility
characterizing glassy Village women.

- Let you, ma'am - Nieves said
.-- They are talking about me: do not take away the taste.

- Of course,
Paul would make me aware of certain red lips, a certain transparency
Skin, hair ormolu ...

- Valentina, then talking about you - blushing
Nieves said playing in the thigh with his partner.

- What a joke!

Do not worry, girl. If you know you're the prettiest! - Said the other visible chopped.

- Peace, peace, ladies! - Truth .-- Gonzalo said Paul began talking
of the perfections Nieves, but it is also true that she would continue
with all other, if not would have stopped ... Is not that, Paul?

-
Of course, had to continue with Valentina ...

This raised his head
and looked at him with mocking scowl that was funny character to his
face.

- Be careful, Nieves, that these gentlemen are out of sight.

Paul, ignoring the interruption, continued:

- After Teresa and Encarnacion, Elvira and Generous. Venturita also speak (for put it, of course,
by the feet of the horses). Cecilia no, because it is committed, and some would also say my lady
Dona Paula, that, without offending anyone, is the most beautiful of all.

- What a rascal! - Said it admired the grace of his son.

Paul had risen from his chair and hugged his mother with effusion.

-
Remove, remove, flatterer! - "She laughed.

- Go loosening his pocket,
Mom - Venturita said.

- You see!

Houndstooth ever - said the young man angrily, turning her head his sister, while she laughed
maliciously without lifting his frame.

- Many have worked - Gonzalo said softly, sitting next to his girlfriend.

- So, so - Cecilia said fixing her large eyes full of light.

- A
lot, yes, yesterday I had this pink embroidery ... I say, I think
it's pink ...

- It's jasmine.

- Neither the two leaves.

- Bah!

That's nothing.

- What is it you're embroidering?

Cecilia continued to move the needle blank.

- What is it that overboard? - Gonzalo said aloud, the higher, thinking
that he had not heard.

- A sheet ... Shut up! - Said the young woman
lifting her eyes a little to the seamstresses and returning to bring
them down quickly.

At the same time, Gonzalo and Venturita stumbled over the head of Cecilia, and they came out a
spark.

- You see there for all - Pablito said while staring fixedly at Nevis
as saying: "Never mind, I say to meet."

- What is there for all,
Don Pablo? - Valentina asked with ironic twang.

- Flores, creature.

-
Écheselas you the Blessed Sacrament.

- And pretty girls like you.

-
If I'm not pretty, passing through the beautiful and did not do it
please, you know?

- Demon!

We must not approach this Valentina; rises from behind - said the
handsome young man.

The simile, though nothing cult, and perhaps for that reason, made me laugh to the seamstresses.

- Valentina does not like the gentlemen - said Encarnacion.

- You are right, the gentlemen will not take off more than parola, lost time and sometimes
unfortunately lifetime - Donà said Paula forgetting that she had taken happiness .-- Concerning
to that, Sarrió is lost. There are hardly any girl who is left to accompany one of his equal. The boy
has to bring at least a tie and fungus, and smoking has nozzle ... although it has no plate
to eat. Nothing is hidden, and to go at dusk accompanied by a gentleman, and just around the pilgrimages
to see them come da grime clinging to them takes singing high ... Poor thing! Do not know what
awaits you. For the son of Don Rudesindo married Esguila Pepe and the pilot of Mechacan Trinity,
I figure that is the whole mountain is oregano. When frying is the laugh ... Look, look at Benita
Mr. Matthias the sexton. How cute is that compuestita, right?

- Benita is notarized - Encarnacion said.

- Writing, eh? You'll see what it is worth writing!

- Lady, the groom can not leave, if you leave, go to prison for life.

- Hush, hush, goofy, how come you got those balls in your head?

- That you know ... go. Benita is consulted.

- Look, lady - said Teresa, the brunette sentimental - the truth that we are in danger; you are right
... But what do we do? The craftsmen of this village are so lying to lose! The most and the
least happens on Sunday and Monday in the tavern, and some day per week. How many are those
who bring their wages home and deliver it to his wife, tell me for his life? If a sailor, he
is seen once every year, brings four quarters, and pulled again there. The rooms are completed,
and the unfortunate woman is dragged, working to give a piece of bread to their children ...
And then what do they know of to estimate even a bit of grace women? If they go with her one
Sunday afternoon, will stop at every tavern the road, leaving, if the opportunity arises,
the poor girl at the door, or call to hear some nonsense, which puts more than a poppy red ...
Street, street, ma'am, if each mostrenco that as God will judge me, not worth the bread they
eat! ... The other day I found to Tomasina ... already know, Uncle Rufus, who does even a year married
a Prospero's official ... Well, at that moment was a real home for two of his father to buy bread,
because in all that day had not eaten a bite.

Her husband drinks most of the wage, and half weeks, of course! has the unfortunate to squeeze
the belly ... Válgate God! And most of the night comes home drunk, and gives each sopimpa that
leaves it for dead. How often will the little girl to bed without supper and fed up with sticks! ...
Then they want that, seeing these things ... Oops, better shut up! What I say is, wow! and
to take her to the devil to take her car.

- Hey you - jumped Valentina lifted his face with his usual frown
more pronounced - no look so boastful.

Say you like gentlemen, well ... I did not get into that, but removing the credit do not come to
raptors your equal ... They get drunk, those who get drunk ... More than a gentleman and more
than two I've seen goats come as home ... And beat their women, even
those who stick ... If they do not have the long tongue, do not carry
the half the time ... Serves, and Don Ramon, the music teacher when
she came home for "biscuits night was his wife?

What you should know ... lived very close.

- My dear, I do not speak for everyone - said Teresa subsiding by the fear that his wayward partner
deliver him to light the night accompanying Donato Red, Medical Health,
- only I say that there is gross ...

- Well, let them alone and do
not remember them, they do not remember you.

Each is each, and the most and the least know where the water flows from the mill.

- Listen, Valentina - Elvira said grinning - when you marry, do you
think carry Cosme?

- If deserve the take ... More want to take a
couple times in my contempt Cosme a gentleman, rising!

- I like that,
learn, learn, little girls! - Pablito said.

Gonzalo, after a moment of whispered conversation with his girlfriend, got up, took three or four
laps around the room, and sat down beside Venturita, with whom I
used to have revelry.

Both liked to tease and frolic after the trust was born. The girl I was drawing some letters for embroidery.

-
Do not come to mock, Gonzalo.

We know that bad drawing - said stabbing a provocative look, bolt, forcing the young to lower
theirs.

- It is true that, do not draw wrong - he said softly, shaking slightly,
bringing face to the role Venturita her lap.

- Pure gallantry.

Will agree that it could be better.

- Best ... more ... everything can be better in the world.

It's pretty good.

- You'll make very flattering. I do not want to laugh at me, do you hear?

- Oh! I laugh at anyone ... but much less than you ...-- he said without looking up paper, his voice
growing low and visibly shaken.

Venturita was always staring at him with a malicious expression, which clearly read the triumph
of satisfied pride.

- Come on, you draw them, Mr. Engineer - said handing him the paper with funny despotism and
pencil.

The young man took them and dared to look up at the girl, but then lowered it as if afraid
electrocuted.

He planted the book, which she had in her lap, on his knees, applied
over white paper, and began to draw.

But instead of letters, began to draw with ease the head of a woman. First the hair parted
into two braids, then the forehead and beautiful, then a delicate
nose, small mouth, his beard trimmed admirably united to the throat
by a smooth curve and elegant ... Venturita seemed prodigiously.

This, resting on the shoulder of his future brother, followed the movements of the pen. Slowly
it expanded a smile on his face vain. After outlining the head, Gonzalo
continued with the bust.

He put the hairdresser or the girl wearing matinee, and entertained
good while carefully drawing silk ties that are holding ahead.

When portrait was finished. Venturita accent told picaresque:

- Now, who is put under.

The young man raised his head and smiling eyes clashed. Then, with brilliance and decision wrote
under the picture: What I love most in the world.

Venturita took the paper in his hands and stared for a moment with
pleasure.

Then with a grimace of disdain handed it back saying:

- Take, take, liar.

But before reaching the hands of Gonzalo, Cecilia extended his and
snatched him laughing.

- What are those pieces of paper?

Venturita, as if it had a flat tire, jumped on the seat and held her
wrist tightly of his sister.

- Give, give, Cecilia!

Stop it! - Said breathing fire with his face, made by forced smile.

- No, I see it.

- You'll see later, go!

- I see it now.

- Come on, girl, Leave it to see. What do you care? - Said Dona Paula.

- I do not want anyone to force it off - cried becoming serious.

Then, realizing the recklessness of this, turned to be cheerful.

- Come on, Cecilia, loose, do not be evil.

- What a commitment! Drops you who hurt me!

- Who are you to take my hand paper? - Uttered in anger, turning this
time really serious .-- Loose, loose, ugly parrot noses, silly!

... Let go, or I scratch you! - Added with flashing eyes and the
face broken by anger.

Seeing her in that way, the laughter that shook his chest suddenly paralizóse Cecilia, and opening
her large eyes which was painted surprise, exclaimed:

- Jesus!

You look crazy, girl. Take, take, will not give you something.

And dropped the crumpled piece of paper that in the fist.

Venturita have altered the face, he did a thousand pieces.

- In the days of my life have I seen a wild creature! - Crossing himself
exclaimed Dona Paulina Ave .-- Mary!

Ave Maria! Who did you get that genie, girl?

- Would you - plastered Venturita said, without looking at anyone.

-
Shameless!

... If not there are people looking forward! ... How do you answer that So your mother, naughty?
Do not you know the commandments of God's law?

Tomorrow I will Don Aquilino to confess.

- Well, give reports to Don Aquilino.

- Wait, wait, very great rascal! - Called Mrs. doing started to rise
to punish her daughter.

But at that moment appeared at the door of Don Rosendo with multicolored robe velvet hat with silk
tassel.

- What? - Asked amazed watching his wife's angry attitude.

This will put the current, choked with sobs, the lack of respect for his daughter.

Don Rosendo was believed in the case of frown, and say solemnly:

- That's wrong, Ventura. Go to apologize to your mom.

He knew he was distracted, absorbed in some thought, and that domestic
incident could not wring more than half of their concern.

However, to see the girl still in haughty and dismissive, he said again, more firmly

- Come, daughter, go to ask for forgiveness, because you have offended.

The girl made his peculiar grimace of contempt in his lips, and whispered softly:

- Yes, that's what I'm thinking!

- Go, Ventura, what muttering there? Go, before I get angry.

- Go, go, Venturita. Go there. Do not be so - he said under his seamstresses.

- I do not want. Will you leave me alone? - She answered quietly, too, but with angry tone.

- Do not want to go? - Asked Don Rosendo with severely affected .-- Do not you want to go?

The girl stood motionless and silent.

- Then get out of here now! Get out of my sight!

Venturita rose from his chair, went through the middle of the upright
and sulking competition, and went the room making a big bang.

Don Rosendo, after remaining motionless for a moment with eyes fixed on the door where his
daughter had gone, he turned, saying:

- I'm sorry to be so strong with my daughters ... but sometimes no choice.

VII

THAT IS OF TWO TRAITORS

Sudden blurred pseudomarítima his noble face the fearful expression that darkened and appeared
distracted again that another sign of constant meditation.

- Gonzalo, if you do not mind, I ask you to pierce me at the office - said addressing to his future
son.

This, that during the previous scene was pale and returned to his being repeatedly turned at
confusing. Nothing less struck him that Rosendo was unaware of the instability their feelings
of love, and I would ask it close consideration. Was, therefore, behind his head bowed and
suspicious, and entered the desktop. It was a spacious room, furnished with rich merchant class:
large solid mahogany table, mahogany cabinets, too, where there bundles
of papers more than books, velvet carpet, couches lined with brocade,
and massive silver inkstand as a monument.

About a quarter of this camera ocupábalo a lot of packets wrapped in several colors, to whoever
first Once entered into it, would be a mystery. Gonzalo was not for or to any of the intimate
of the house. Those packages kept toothpicks.

How? - Ask the reader .-- Don Rosendo Belinchón, a dealer in both stem, traded also on toothpicks?
No, Don Rosendo not traded with them, make them. And this not to speculate, unworthy of its
kind, but pure and selfless inclination of his spirit. From a very
young man had told him.

The regulars trade occupations and the vicissitudes through which he passed his existence, had
not consented to meet this passion but in a materially poor at times lost. But since she could leave
the desktop to some of the faithful entrusted dependent entregóse full heart and soul a distraction
so helpful and honest. In the morning at the store Graells, in the afternoon Saloncillo in the
evening at home or in the Don Pedro Miranda, always working. His servant occupied much of the day in
court a few blocks of dry hazel perfectly equal, where his right hand had to take the show
of the sticks.

And was not about to rest, even on holidays, production was excessive. There were not enough consumers
in the village, and saw packages needed to recall them friends of the capital, when the pile
reached the ceiling clearance. Thanks to the efforts noblest of the clear representative of their
trade, we can proudly say that Sarrio in this interesting field of
progress, was at the height of the big cities.

No other Spanish town or foreign competition could suffer with it. Home of the rich, as in the artisan,
never missing a well-stocked toothpick, undisputed testimony the refined culture of its inhabitants.

Rosendo
said a couch to his son in infancy, and he was frightened and let himself fall into it sinking
deeply. After the trader approached a chair with an air of mystery, and sitting front of the
young and looking between smiling and embarrassed, he said, giving the same time a pat on the
thigh

- Let's see, Gonzalito: how about the issue of slaughter?

- Is the slaughter? - Said it opened his eyes wide as fists.

- Yes, the new slaughterhouse, do you think should be placed in the dump, or on the beach of Meanas
behind the houses of Don Rudesindo?

Gonzalo saw heaven opened, and,
smiling with pleasure, he replied:

- I believe that the Meanas beach
would be nice ... Very open that ... well ventilated ...

But noting
that his father's forehead was wrinkled, and her eyes suddenly subsided
smile, said stammering:

- Nor do I think it would be wrong with the
spring ...

- Much better, Gonzalo ... Infinitely better!

- Can,
can.

- Man, so it may be, I will tell you privately that the location
on the beach I judge (Please save me the reservation on this opinion),
I judge ... a veritable folly ... u-na do-da-de-ra in-sen-sa-skinned
- all the best pointing repeated syllables.

- And this opinion of
mine - he said - do not go to refiguring it yesterday morning, but
throughout life. Since I was able to understand certain things, I
realized that the slaughterhouse would not be where is today. In a
word, that should be moved. Where? An inner voice always told me that
the dump. Before you can give any scientific reason, I was as convinced
as that there was now located, and not elsewhere. Now that the resolution
of the problem approaches, I think I have to hold this view, to communicate
my thoughts to the people and the result of my musings. If you do
not have to do I will read your letter I am writing Progress on this
occasion the Lancia. 

And indeed, without waiting for the answer
to Gonzalo, he went to the table, picked up a specification paper
that was on it, put on his glasses, and stood on the balcony gave
beginning, not without some emotion that is reflected by the voice,
reading the letter.

Commercial paper was written in large, striped.
All that for years led the Advancement of Lancia and other newspapers
in the capital of the province, were written in the same role on both
sides. Although he did not know that the press was written by a only.
But soon acquired this precious knowledge, as we shall see.

Almost
simultaneously with that of toothpicks Rosendo was born in Belinchón
the fans to write press releases to newspapers: that is, dating from
a remote antiquity. Ardent supporter of human progress, reforms at
all levels, from the discussion and light, it is clear that the press
had to command respect and enthusiasm. Newspapers had always been
an essential element of their existence. He was signed to many national
and foreign, because, as taught to trade, was well acquainted with
French and English and had never missed, even in the busiest days,
a couple of hours to spend to read. These times are significantly
increased for some years, but not that it would suffer by cod. The
enjoyment that our hero felt in the morning after taking the chocolate
swallowing the substantive articles of the national flag, the Loose
Politics and the Nouvelles à la main of Figaro was so vivid, it was
printed long in the face until the radiation was being lost in the
atmosphere.

Like all men of broad and lofty view, it was not exclusive
in their tastes newspaper. He loved the daily newspaper, as a kind
shows the progress of human reason or as he put it best, "a demonstration
raised public awareness." Opinions which each defended, were a secondary.
I was subscribed to newspapers in all colors, and equally enjoyed.
If you showed any predilection, it was only for the items loose meaning.
Because that's saying one thing and pretending to express the opposite
twist phrases so that a clause carry innocent appearance in a "poisoned
arrow" was in awe of Don Rosendo and drove him crazy with joy. Read
many times The Spain one paragraph with the style: - "Yesterday it
was finally the circular of the President Supreme of their subordinates.
Congratulations to General O'Donnell, president of this situation
liberal, Mr. Negrete, who has given a lucid moment atop a colossal
work, and Democrat protection of this Government "- had exclaimed
waving a newspaper in his hands: - What intention! Caracoles! What
intention</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>