<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08503</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>506122</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22535</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>     |  98| 34| 16| 148| 108|
34| 10| 152| 300| |Agosto.    | 101| 19| 14| 134|  77| 19| 21| 117| 251| |Setiembre. | 108|
26| 10| 144|  76| 35| 21| 132| 276| |Octubre.   |  84| 31|  9| 124|  84| 33| 12| 129| 253|
|Noviembre  | 106| 34| 15| 155|  88| 29|  9| 126| 281| |Diciembre. |  71| 26| 20| 117|  83|
19| 15| 117| 234| |-----------+----+---+---+----+----+---+---+----+----| |     Total |1215|335|176|1726|1039|353|169|1561|3287|
+-----------+-----------------+-----------------+----+

No habiendo encontrado épocas bien distintas, de los fallecimientos segun las edades y los
sexos, me limito á presentar aquí, sin distincion entre los resultados máximo y mínimo, los
totales estraidos del estado precedente.

+-------------------------------------------------+ |         |         FALLECIMIENTOS.   
| |  AÑOS.  |---------------------------------------| |         |RESULTADO MÁXIMO. |  RESULTADO
MÍNIMO. | |---------|---------------------------------------| |         |Junio     146    
|  Octubre    63     | |  1828   |Julio     107     |  Noviembre  70     | |         |Marzo
183     |  Agosto     76     | |---------|---------------------------------------| |      
|Junio     121     |  Diciembre  60     | |  1829   |Julio     103     |  Agosto     69   
| |         |Noviembre 101     |  Enero      78     | |---------|---------------------------------------|
|         |Mayo      111     |  Enero      62     | |  1830   |Noviembre 110     |  Febrero
78     | |         |Agosto    106     |  Marzo      85     | |---------|---------------------------------------|
| Resúmen |Junio     559     |  Enero     229     | | de los  |Julio     300     |  Diciembre
234     | |tres años|Mayo      292     |  Agosto.   251     | +-------------------------------------------------+

En la provincia de Moxos, los resultados máximos de los fallecimientos han tenido siempre lugar
durante los meses de mayo, junio y julio; es decir, en el período de los tres meses mas secos
y frios del año, época subsecuente á aquella en que las aguas que cubren la provincia se evaporan
dejando superficies inmensas llenas de pantanos y de charcos estancados y fétidos. Bien pudiera
por lo tanto atribuirse el resultado máximo de los fallecimientos, durante la estacion de seca;
1° á los vientos del invierno, naturalmente frios para unos hombres acostumbrados á un temperamento
tan caluroso y que andan siempre casi desnudos; 2° á las enfermedades (fiebres intermitentes)
que determinan los miasmas mortíferos de que se halla entónces recargado el aire.

Es ciertamente curioso que el resultado máximo de los fallecimientos se produzca en Europa,
de igual modo que bajo la zona tórrida, en la estacion mas fria del año. (Véase la obra ya
citada del señor Quetelet, t. II, pág. 310 y t. I, pág. 188.) Así pues, haciendo abstraccion
de las influencias locales que acabo de indicar, acontece en Europa, respecto de los fallecimientos,
lo mismo que se observa en América.

En Moxos, la época del resultado mínimo de los fallecimientos concuerda con el momento en que
abundan las lluvias; es decir, con el período en el cual las faenas del navegante son ménos
penosas, siendo mas cortas las comunicaciones, y en el que cesan tambien las exhalaciones pútridas
de los lugares pantanosos.

Salubridad de la provincia.

Si como corolario de lo que acabo de decir relativamente al movimiento de la poblacion y á
los fallecimientos, se quiere echar una rápida ojeada sobre la salubridad de la provincia,
veremos que su dilatada superficie es mucho mas sana de lo que pudiera suponerse en vista de
la gran cantidad de pantanos que por el tiempo de seca exhalan todos los años vapores corrompidos:
y efectivamente, no se conoce en la provincia una sola enfermedad especial; y el número de
personas atacadas por las fiebres intermitentes, en los meses de marzo y abril, es ciertamente
muy reducido, sobre todo en las orillas del Mamoré. Estas fiebres no presentan jamas un carácter
maligno y son mucho ménos intensas que en las provincias de Mizqué y de Valle Grande.

Algunas veces el esceso de humedad suele causar disenterias. Esta enfermedad, en otro tiempo
muy temida por los indígenas, es hoy en dia mucho ménos frecuente, y pasa fácilmente con los
refrescos.

La estraordinaria mortandad que se advierte en Moxos proviene de dos accidentes; ó del frio,
tan pernicioso para las criaturas; ó de alguna de las muchas fiebres eruptivas, como las viruelas,
el sarampion y la escarlatina que hacen sus estragos entre las personas de todas edades. Todos
los indígenas atacados por la fiebres de invasion, sintiendo interiormente un calor que los
abrasa, creen hallar algun alivio con ir á tomar un baño; de donde resulta desde luego una
repercusion hácia el interior, que ocasiona la muerte. Entre tanto, para hacer cesar semejante
mortandad bastaria que los curas y administradores ejerciesen una vigilancia activa.

Una gran parte de las criaturas mueren á los diez dias de haber visto la luz, ya por la falta
de cuidados, ya por la accion demasiado fria de los vientos del sud. Las mugeres entregadas
sin descanso á las faenas que les imponen los administradores, sea por su propia cuenta, sea
por cuenta del gobierno, se ven obligadas á desatender á sus reciennacidos, que mueren por
los sufrimientos á que los espone su edad y esta especie de abandono.

Administracion de la provincia.

Hasta 1842, la provincia estubo regida por gobernadores subordinados al prefecto de Santa-Cruz,
y que ejercian sus funciones tan despóticamente como se le antojaba. Un gobernador tiene bajo
sus órdenes, en la capital, un administrador general que hace las veces de secretario, y en
cada poblacion, un administrador particular investido de ciertos poderes de que abusa con tanto
mas descaro cuanto que se encuentra apartado de los que pudieran reprender su conducta, no
haciendo caso de las órdenes que les transmiten los superiores. Son ellos los jueces y árbitros
de los indígenas á quienes hacen castigar algunas veces sin escuchar mas voz que la de sus
caprichos. Bajo las órdenes de cada uno de estos administradores hay un cacique indígena y
varios otros gefes subalternos que existian en tiempo de los Jesuitas, no habiéndose alterado
á este respecto, como ya lo dije, las instituciones de aquellos religiosos.

Tiene la provincia de Moxos un vicario general, nombrado por el obispo de Santa-Cruz; y hay
en cada mision uno ó dos curas encargados del gobierno espiritual. Muy á menudo suelen hallarse
estos en rivalidad de poderes con los administradores, lo que origina mil disturbios y disputas
que escandalizan y sirven de mal ejemplo á las misiones.

Costumbres, usos y estado moral de la provincia.

Si bajo la administracion de los curas se viéron obligados los indios de Concepcion[1] á hacer
oficio de caballos, tirando del carruage en que iba el cura de esta mision ; si mas tarde los
gobernadores españoles no se sentaban á la mesa sin mandar venir una tropa de músicos que los
divirtiesen durante la comida, ó no se dejaban ver de sus súbditos sino sentados bajo un dosel;
aun se tributan hoy en dia muchos de estos honores exagerados á los mandatarios de la provincia.

Cuando el gobernador de la provincia va de viage, los administradores y curas de las misiones
hacen adornar con flores las canoas, colocando en ellas un tambor para anunciar la alta categoría
del viagero. Así que este avista el puerto suenan las cajas, y los curas y administradores,
seguidos de los principales magistrados de la mision, se adelantan á su encuentro. Monta el
gobernador á caballo, y se encamina al pueblo con toda esta comitiva, á la que precede un indio
que toca la caja yendo á todo galope. Al aproximarse á la mision repican las campanas para
dar aviso de la llegada del gefe de la provincia, y salen entónces los jueces y demas empleados
á recibirlo con acompañamiento de músicos. Conducido triunfalmente hasta el colegio, se van
presentando á él sucesivamente todas las autoridades indígenas, cuyas harengas le son traducidas
por un intérprete. En seguida vienen á ofrecerle flores las jóvenes indias. Miéntras dura la
comida no cesa la música un solo instante; y cuando llega la noche se organiza un baile en
el que muchas veces hacen bailar por fuerza á los indios jóvenes y á las muchachas. Las tambores
anuncian con un redoble la llegada de los bailarines que entran por parejas, al compas de la
marcha ejecutada por la música que los precede: atravesando luego toda la sala con mesurado
andar y afectando una gravedad imperturbable, desfilan por delante del gobernador, y despues
de haberlo saludado van sucesivamente á colocarse en línea para bailar la contradanza española.
En Trinidad y en Loreto las mugeres bailan descalzas y llevan un vestido de zaraza, ó simplemente
el tipoi, de esta misma tela, ceñido á la cintura; su cabello va sostenido por un peine colocado
en la parte superior de la cabeza. Los danzarines, mancebos por lo regular de catorce años,
visten pantalon y camisa, y llevan un gorro blanco ni mas ni ménos como las mugeres de Normandía.
Despues de haber ejecutado su contradanza con mucha seriedad, saludan otra vez al gobernador
y toman todos asiento. Los negociantes y los otros blancos que se encuentran por acaso en la
mision, suelen tomar parte en estas diversiones, cortejando á las bailarinas, las que se animan
un poco cuando llega el ponche, y no se hacen ya de rogar para ejecutar las diversas danzas
usadas en Santa-Cruz.

Los Bolivianos blancos que viajan en la provincia van en canoas hechas de un solo tronco ahuecado:
estas embarcaciones que tienen generalmente de nueve á doce varas de largo, sobre una ó dos
de ancho, son muy bajas de bordo en el medio y rara vez, estando cargadas, sobrepasan de dos
ó tres pulgadas á la superficie de las ondas; por manera que al menor choque contra algun árbol
flotante, entra en ellas el agua con abundancia. Las canoas de un tamaño regular admiten generalmente
cuatro ó cinco baules, y á lo mas tres pasageros que se ponen á cubierto del sol ó de las intemperies
bajo un toldo de cuero donde apénas se puede estar sentado. El número de remeros varia segun
el largo de la embarcacion; para dirigirla, se mantienen de pié en la parte trasera el capitan
de la canoa y su ayudante; otros dos indios van sentados en el estremo opuesto, cuidando de
prevenir y evitar los embarazos. Los remeros, colocados en medio de á dos en dos, no dejan
de mano en todo el dia los grandes y anchos remos de que se sirven para impulsar la pequeña
barca. Todos estos indios principian la jornada dándose un baño, y al rayar el el dia están
ya en marcha: hacen alto á cosa de las ocho para almorzar, y ántes de pasar adelante toman
un segundo baño. Al medio dia se detienen otra vez por una hora para comer, y navegan en seguida
hasta la noche. Cuando el viagero es un personage de distincion, envian los administradores
una canoa cargada de comestibles, en la que se prepara la comida á las horas de regla, sin
perder tiempo en detensiones. En todo el tránsito desempeñan los indios sus tareas con el mayor
celo posible, y no es dado hacerse una idea de los prolijos cuidados con que atienden á los
viageros, estando siempre alertas para adivinar y prevenir sus menores deseos.

Cuando se tiene que subir un rio, generalmente se andan de ocho á diez leguas por dia; y cuando
se voga rio abajo suele doblarse esta distancia; mas esto depende de la mayor ó menor rápidez
de la corriente, variable en cada rio, y tambien de los remeros, cuya destreza y actividad
no en todas partes son de igual grado. Cada nacion tiene su manera particular de remar: los
Itonamas van sentados y reman con mucha precipitation; los Cayuvavas, tambien sentados, reman
pausadamente pero con fuerza, en tanto que los Baures se mantienen de pié como para dar mayor
impulsion á los remos. De todas estas naciones los Cayuvavas son los remeros mas afamados,
y tratan de conservar su reputacion, esforzándose por sobrepujar en celeridad á todas las embarcaciones
estrangeras que encuentran sobre su paso. Tienen la costumbre estos naturales de bañarse tres
veces al dia cuando van de viage; para practicarlo, se detienen de pronto, se arrojan al agua,
zambullen y vuelven, á vestir su camisa de cortezas, continuando en seguida la marcha. Toda
vez que los Moxos entran á bañarse, enseñan sus espaldas cubiertas de cicatrices que parecen
quemaduras, y que no son sino el resultado de las flagelaciones de la semana santa. Entre ellos
mismos se manifiestan ufanos de llevar sobre sus cuerpos semejantes señales, mofándose con
cierta ironía de aquellos que no las tienen.

Cuando el tiempo es hermoso, el calor que reina á eso del medio dia en el estrecho callegon
formado por los árboles coposos y antiquísimos, que guarnecen las orillas de los rios, jamas
llega á ser templado por la mas leve y pasagera brisa; el viagero echando entónces de ménos
el aire vivificador de la pasada mañana, desea la noche con impaciencia; pero tan luego como
esta envuelve la tierra, densos vapores se levantan del rio, y se encuentra uno tan mojado
por la mañana como si hubiese llovido de recio toda la noche. Cuando en el curso del dia llueve
sin que haya tempestad, salen de los bosques millares de mosquitos, y refugiándose en las canoas,
torturan á los pobres viageros que demasiado sufren por las noches semejante molestia. Si el
tiempo se pone sumamente malo, construyen los indios á toda prisa una choza de cañas, bajo
la cual se ponen los viageros á cubierto contra los torrentes de lluvia; si esta continúa,
construyen tambien para ellos cabañas espaciosas; de modo que en pocos instantes se transforma
el campamento en una aldehuela donde permanecen muchos dias hasta que se apacigua el viento.
Las fuertes oleadas que promueven los vientos en los grandes rios no son, como ya lo hemos
dicho, los únicos peligros á que está espuesto el viagero que transita por aquellos lugares.
Las barrancas arenosas suelen desplomarse derrepente sobre las aguas, arrastrando en su caida
alguno de los árboles gigantescos que se alzan en las orillas, y cuyas enormes raices llevan
tras sí una inmensa mole de terreno. Si todos estos escombros caen por casualidad sobre la
frágil embarcacion, la hacen desaparecer completamente; pero cuando esto no suceda, bastarian
para hacerla zozobrar las olas de proyeccion, que tales derrumbamientos exitan en el seno de
las ondas.

Algunas veces, subiendo los rios en la estacion lluviosa, se aventuran los indios á pasar por
en medio de los brazos que forman las islas, y en los que la corriente se manifiesta ménos
rápida; empero, estos brazos suelen hallarse obstruidos en sus remates por gruesos troncos
que han amontonado las aguas; si los remeros tratando de salvar el paso se meten por los pequeños
estrechos donde la corriente es muy impetuosa, se enreda la canoa entre las ramas, y se llena
de agua en un momento: justamente alarmados se echan desde luego al rio, y ya nadando, ya soliviándose
sobre las ramas, sostienen la embarcacion sin que se hunda, hasta que llegan en su ausilio
las demas canoas. Es en tales ocasiones cuando los superticiosos Cayuvavas echan por tierra
una espiga de maiz en accion de gracias á la suprema Providencia por haberlos libertado del
peligro.

Si estos viages son penosos para los Españoles, lo son aun mucho mas para los pobres indios,
continuamente espuestos á las intemperies, y obligados muchas veces á pasar la noche en las
llanuras anegadas, suspendidos sobre el agua en sus hamacas.

Innumerables trozos de vegetacion, ocultos bajo las aguas, hacen zozobrar á menudo las canoas:
detiénense entónces los indios sobre algun banco de arena para poner á secar las mercancía.
Muy rara vez llega algun indio á perecer en estos trances; pues todos ellos nadan como si las
ondas fuesen su elemento natural. Pero hay otros peligros á que está espuesta su vida en estos
viages: citaré como uno de los principales el encuentro con los tigres. Cuando descubren sobre
las playas los rastros de esta fiera, levantan inmediatamente su campamento, yendo á buscar
mas léjos la no muy completa seguridad; y si en medio de la noche oyen sus bramidos, van á
recoger inmediatamente toda la leña que pueden, y encienden grande fogatas; pero esto no siempre
los pone á cubierto contra los funestos accidentes, sobre todo cuando la espedicion ne se compone
mas que de indios. Un administrador de Magdalena habia enviado en cierta ocasion unos cuantos
indios, para que fuesen á recoger en los bosques los gajos de un árbol, cuya ceniza suministra
una potasa escelente para la fábrica del jabon. Muchas dias habia que estos indios, enteramente
desprovistos de armas, se hallaban acampados y contraidos á su trabajo, cuando de improviso
se presentó una noche en medio de ellos un tigre hambriento, y arrojándose sobre un indio que
yacia dormido en su hamaca, se lo llevaba para devorarlo léjos de allí; empero, asustado con
la grita tumultuosa de los otros indios que despertaron á los quejidos de la víctima, echó
á correr, dejando en tierra al pobre indio con la cabeza hecha pedazos y con muy pocos instantes
de vida. Este hecho es como un reproche á esa medida absurda, que, so pretesto de evitar las
pendencias con los blancos, prohibe[1] llevar armas á unos hombres constantemente espuestos
á los mayores peligros en medio de esos desiertos, cuyo imperio pertenece todavía á los animales
feroces. Es de notar que el tigre jamas enviste á las personas cuya cabeza no alcanza á ver,
y no hay un solo ejemplo de que algun viagero, estando bien escondido bajo su mosquitero, haya
perecido víctima de su voracidad.

Las riberas del Mamoré, de ordinario sumamente silenciosas, ven pasar una vez al año infinidad
de canoas reunidas que se dirigen de Moxos á Santa-Cruz, y dando eco á la grita tumultuosa
y alegre de los navegantes, cobran una animacion que bien puede llamarse deliciosa. Hizo la
casualidad que yo me hallase tambien de viage en el momento de una de estas espediciones. Copiaré
aquí el punto de mi diario que á este pasage se refiere.

«... Mas de cuarenta canoas se aprestaban á partir á la vez del puerto de Loreto, componiendo
una verdadera flota. Los curas y negociantes que iban incorporados á la espedicion, quisieron
que yo me encargarse de conducir la marcha, viajando en compañía; y como podia practicarlo
tanto mejor, cuanto que mis remeros eran los mas hábiles, acepté desde luego el honor que se
me conferia. Al fin de la jornada hicimos alto para pasar la noche sobre un espacioso banco
de arena, no léjos de un bosque. Entónces me fué dado gozar de un halagüeño punto de vista,
mientras llegaban las canoas poco á poco y sucesivamente, saludadas por los gritos triunfales
ó de mofa de los que se hablan anticipado. Todos los indios se dispersaron luego dentro del
bosque, y volvieron trayendo leña, algunas cañas con que armaron camas para los viageros, y
gruesas estacas que clavaron simétricamente en tierra para suspender, por grupos separados,
las hamacas pertenecientes á los remeros de cada canoa: en el centro de estos grupos se encendió
una fogata; y en la parle de afuera brillaban ya de trecho en trecho otros fuegos donde se
preparaba la cena.»

«Nuestro campamento, que reunia mas de seiscientas personas, presentaba el aspecto mas curioso
que pudiera imaginarse. Hablábanse en él casi todas las lenguas de la provincia, sin confundirse
unas con otras las diferentes naciones. Todos los blancos nos habiamos congregado en el centro,
en tanto que, aquí y acullá, los Baures, los Itonamas, los Movimas, los Cayuvavas, los Canichanas
y los Moxos formando diversos grupos, platicaban en sus respectivos dialectos. La playa poco
ántes solitaria era el transuto del teatro mas animado. Cada grupo de hamacas blanquecinas,
colgadas en derredor de una hoguera encendida, contrastaba con los mosquiteros de los viageros
y con la hilera de piraguas que se estendia magestuosamente á lo largo de la orilla[1]: sentados
todos sobre la arena cenamos luego en comunidad, suscitando mil alegres conversaciones, á que
la estrañeza de los diferentes lenguages daba mas originalidad. Cada individuo, apartándose
de Moxos, se hallaba ya escento de temores y dejaba ir libremente su lengua; las indiscreciones
de los unos daban pié á las recriminaciones de los otros; así es que me fueron revelados en
aquella noche todos los secretos sobre la conducta privada de los empleados, y supe mas cosas
en una sola hora, que en algunos meses de permanencia en la provincia.»

«Acabada la cena, todos los indios se reunieron como de costumbre para orar en comunidad. Estos
cánticos religiosos que tantas veces me habian sorprendido agradablemente en medio de aquellas
soledades, resonaron á mi oído en aquel momento con tal discordancia, que tuve que retirarme
á un lado; y no podia resultar ménos de la confusion de aquellas entonaciones en diferentes
dialectos, que se producian todas á la vez en el silencio de la noche. Los indios, sin cubrirse
con otra ropa que sus tipois, se acuestan en sus hamacas, y pasan la noche espuestos á las
picaduras de los encarnizados mosquitos, y sobre todo al fuerte rocio que cae en las regiones
calurosas sobre las orillas de los rios. Apénas raya el dia, se levantan y despues de haber
descolgado sus hamacas, entonan en coro y con el mayor recogimiento la súplica de la mañana.»

Cuando se viaja con un séquito compuesto de una sola nacion, y que se hace alto en el bosque
de las riberas, estas preces de la noche suelen tener un encanto inexplicable. No puedo prescindir
de traer al caso la espresion consignada en mi diario, de las sensaciones que la solemnidad
de un acto semejante imprimió una vez en mi espíritu. «La noche era ciertamente una de las
mas oscuras, y su lobreguez aun parecia mayor bajo la bóveda formada por el tupido follage.
Brillaban de distancia en distancia los fuegos de los indios acampados, esparciendo una claridad
incierta sobre los objetos que nos rodeaban y dando un colorido mágico al silvestre recinto.
A cosa de las ocho mis setenta indios entonaron en coro sus cánticos religiosos, que en el
silencio de la noche y en aquellos lugares tomaron un carácter de tanta magestad que me sentí
profundamente conmovido; jamas me habian parecido tan sencillos á la par que imponentes: su
duracion fué demasiado corta para mi arrobamiento, y largo tiempo despues que habian cesado,
aun buscaba mi oido sus místicos acordes. Apoderóse de mi espíritu una dulce melancolía que
se armoniaba con la vaguedad de mi pensamiento y sobre todo con el respeto que me inspiraba
la belleza virginal de aquellos lugares. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>660625</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19606</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> | 98 | 34 | 16 | 148 | 108 | 34
| 10 | 152 | 300 | | August. | 101 | 19 | 14 | 134 | 77 | 19 | 21 | 117 | 251 | | September.
| 108 | 26 | 10 | 144 | 76 | 35 | 21 | 132 | 276 | | October. | 84 | 31 | 9 | 124 | 84 | 33
| 12 | 129 | 253 | | November | 106 | 34 | 15 | 155 | 88 | 29 | 9 | 126 | 281 | | December.
| 71 | 26 | 20 | 117 | 83 | 19 | 15 | 117 | 234 | |-----------+----+---+---+----+----+---+-- -+----+----| | Total | 1215 | 335
| 176 | 1726 | 1039 | 353 | 169 | 1561 | 3287 | +-----------+-----------------+-----------------+-
--- +

Having found very different times of the deaths according to
the ages and sexes, I merely present here, without distinction between
the maximum and minimum results, the Drawn from the preceding state
total.

+------------------------------------------------- + | | DEATH.

| | YEAR. |---------------------------------------| | | MAXIMUM RESULTS. | RESULT MINIMUM.
| |---------|-------------------------------------- - | | | June 146 | October 1963 | | 1828 |
July 107 | November 1970 | | | March 183 | August 1976 | |---------|----------------------------------
-----| | | June 121 | December 1960 | | 1829 | July 103 | August 1969 | | | November 101 |
January 1978 | |---------|------------------------------ ---------| | | May 111 | January
1962 | | 1830 | November 110 | February 78 | | | August 106 | March 1985 | |---------|-----------------------------
----------| | Summary | June 559 | January 229 | | of the | July 300 | December 234 | | three years | May
292 | August. 251 | +----------------------------------------------- - +

In the province of Moxos maximum results of deaths have always been rather during the months of
May, June and July, ie during the period of the three driest months
and cold of the year, a period subsequent to that in which the waters
that cover the province evaporate leaving huge areas full of swamps
and stagnant pools and fetid.

It may well therefore claim the maximum results of deaths during the dry season; 1, the winds of
winter, naturally cool to men accustomed to a temperament so hot and are always nearly naked,
2 ° to the disease (intermittent fevers) determining the deadly miasma that is then re-air.

It is certainly curious that the maximum result of the deaths occurring in Europe just as the torrid
zone, in the coldest season of the year. (See the work and cited Mr. Quetelet, t. II, pg. 310 and t.
I, pp. 188.) Thus, disregarding of local influences just mentioned, takes place in Europe for
the deaths, the same as seen in America.

In Moxos, the minimum time of the deaths result is consistent with the time abundant rainfall,
ie the period in which the navigator's tasks are less painful, with shorter communications,
and which also stop the putrid exhalations swampy places.

Health of the province.

If, as a corollary of what I said on the movement of the population and deaths, is to take a quick
glance at the health of the province We find his vast area is much
healthier than it might be assumed in view of the large amount of
wetlands that dry time every year exhale fumes corrupt: and yes, it
is not known in the province one particular disease, and the number
of people attacked by intermittent fever, in the months of March and
April, is certainly very small, especially on the banks of the Mamore.

These fevers have no character ever malignant and are much less intense
than in the provinces of Mizque and Valle Grande.

Sometimes the excess moisture often causes dysentery. This disease, once much feared by the natives,
is today much less frequent, and easily passes the refreshments.

The extraordinary mortality that is seen in Moxos from two accidents, or the cold, so harmful to
the creatures, or of any of several eruptive fevers, such as smallpox, measles and scarlet fever
having their toll on people of all ages.

All Indians attacked by the fever of invasion, feeling the heat inside the burns, believe finding
some relief to go and take a bath where it is certainly a repercussions for the interior, causing
death.

Meanwhile, to halt such mortality would be sufficient that the priests and administrators to
have an active surveillance.

Much of the creatures die at ten days have seen the light, and the lack care, and too cold by
the action of winds from the south. The women delivered tirelessly to the tasks imposed on
them by administrators, either by his own account, whether for the government, are forced to neglect
their neonates, who die the suffering that exposes their age and
this kind of abandonment.

Administration of the province.

Until 1842, the province ruled by governors estubo subordinate to
the prefect of Santa Cruz, and who exercised their functions as despotic
as he pleased.

A governor has under their orders in the capital, a general manager
who acts as secretary, and each population, a particular administrator
vested with certain powers that much abused more brazen as that is
separate from that might rebuke their conduct, not Ignoring the orders
they have passed their superiors.

They are the judges and referees the Indians to punish those who do not listen sometimes more than
their voice whims. Under the orders of each of these managers is an indigenous cacique several
other subordinate chiefs who existed in the time of the Jesuits, not having been altered In
this regard, as I said, those religious institutions.

Moxos province has a vicar general, appointed by the Bishop of Santa-Cruz, and there in each mission
one or two priests in charge of spiritual government. Very often tend to be these powers in
rivalry with the managers, resulting in riots and disputes thousand which shock and serve
as a bad example to the missions.

Customs, practices and moral status of the province.

If under the administration of the priests were forced Indians Concepcion [1] to make office of
horses pulling the carriage in which he was the priest of this mission,
if later the Spanish governors did not sit at the table without sending
a troop of musicians come to the amused during the meal, or not allowed
to see their subjects, but sitting under a canopy; be taxed even today
many of these honors exaggerated to the leaders of the province.

When the governor of the province journey goes, administrators and priests of the missions make
canoes decorated with flowers, placing them a drum to announce the senior the traveler. So this
sighting sound port boxes, and the priests and administrators, followed by the chief magistrates
of the mission, are ahead of their meeting.

Mounts Governor on horseback, and heads to town with all these committees, which precedes an
Indian touching the box going at full gallop. Approaching the mission bells ring for give notice
of the arrival of the chief of the province, and then leave the judges and other employees
welcome to the accompaniment of musicians. Triumphantly driven to school, go presented to him
on all the indigenous peoples, which are translated harangue him by an interpreter. Then come to
Indian girls offer flowers. The duration of food not the music stops for a moment, and when
night is a dance in which often make it dance by force the Indians to young girls. The drums with
a roll advertising the arrival of the dancers that come in pairs, the rhythm of the motion
carried by the music that precedes them: then through the entire room with moderate affecting walking
and imperturbable gravity, parade in front of the governor, and then if any are welcomed to
register online on to dance the quadrille Spanish. Trinidad and Loreto in the women dance
barefoot and wear a calico dress, or simply the tipoi, this same fabric around her waist, her hair
is held in place by a comb at the top of the head. The dancers, usually young men of fourteen
dress pants and shirt, and wear a white cap and more or less as the women of Normandy. After
having executed his contradanza very seriously, welcome back to the governor and take every
seat. Traders and other targets found by chance in mission, usually take part in these amusements,
courting the dancers, who dare a bit when it's punch, and are not to pray and to perform the different
dances used in Santa Cruz.

Bolivians white van traveling in the province in canoes made from a single hollowed log: These vessels
are generally nine to twelve yards long, on one or two wide, are very low in the middle board
and rarely, being charged, beyond two or three inches to the surface of the waves, and so that
the minor crash into a tree floating water enters them in abundance. The canoes of a regular size
generally recognized four or five trunks, and at most three passengers to take cover from the
sun or from bad weather under a canopy of leather where you can barely
sit.

The number of rowers VARIES the length of the vessel, to direct, remain standing in the rear the captain
Canoe and his assistant, two other Indians are sitting on the opposite extremity, being careful
prevent and avoid pregnancy. The rowers, placed in the middle of them two by two, do not leave
hand throughout the day's big and wide paddles which serve to promote small boat. All these Indians
begins the day with a swim, and scratch the day are already underway: the top to make about eight for
lunch, and before going any further take a second bathroom. At noon they stop again for an hour for lunch,
and then navigate until evening. When the traveler is a personage of distinction, send administrators
a canoe loaded with food, where food is prepared hours to rule without detensiones waste time.
In all traffic Indians play their tasks with greater heat as possible and not given an idea
of ??the lengthy care that cater to travelers, while always alert to guess and to prevent
their children wishes.

When you have to climb a river, usually go from eight to ten miles per day, and when Vogue
downstream is usually double this distance, but this depends on the varying speed current, variable
in each river, and also of the rowers, whose skill and activity not all parts are of equal
rank. Each nation has its particular way of paddling: the Itonama will sit and paddle with
lots of precipitation; the Cayuvava, also seated row slowly but forcefully, while the Baures remain
standing as if more Drive to the oars. Of all these nations the Cayuvava are more famous rowers,
and try to preserve their reputation, striving to excel in speed
to all vessels foreigners who are on their way.

These natives have a habit of bathing three times a day when they go on journey, to practice, they
stop suddenly, thrown into the water, dive and return, to peel his shirt dress, then continued
walking. All Once Moxos come to bathe, teach their backs covered with scars that appear to
burns, and which are simply the result of the flogging of Holy Week. Among them manifest themselves
proud of carrying such signs on their bodies, mocking with certain irony for those who do not.

When
the weather is beautiful, the heat which prevails to this noon in the narrow callegon formed
by flakes and ancient trees that adorn the banks of rivers, never come to be tempered by the
slightest breeze and passengers, the traveler then throwing less vivifying air of the past week, want the
night with impatience, but as soon as This involves land, dense vapors rising from the river,
and is a very wet morning as if it had rained all night tough. When it rains during the day with
no storm, leaving thousands of mosquitoes forests, and taking refuge in canoes, torture to
the poor travelers, who too suffer such discomfort at night. If time becomes extremely bad,
the Indians built a hut haste cane under which the travelers to get insured against the torrents
of rain, and if this continues, They also built for spacious cabins, so that in a few moments
becomes camp in a hamlet where many days remain until the wind subsides.

The waves that promote strong winds in the large rivers are not, as we have said, the only danger
to which the traveler is nswer passing through those places. Sandy gullies derrepente usually
subside over the water, dragging down one of the giant trees that stand on the banks, whose
roots are huge behind a huge mass of land. If all this debris falling by chance on fragile boat,
make it disappear completely, but when this happens, would be sufficient to make waves capsized
the projection, which excite such collapses within waves.

Sometimes up rivers in the rainy season, the Indian venture to go through among the arms that
form the islands, where the current is less evident fast, however, these arms are often found
in their shots blocked by thick trunks that have piled up the waters, if the rowers trying
to save the way they get by small narrow where the current is very impetuous, tangle the canoe
through the branches, and is filled water at a time: just alarmed are cast into the river course,
and I swam, and Bolivia on the branches, holding the boat without sinking, until they reach
their assistance in the other canoes. It is on such occasions when the superstitious Cayuvava
demolish an ear of corn in thanksgiving to the supreme providence for having liberated the danger.

If
these journeys are painful for the Spanish, they are still much more to the poor Indians, ESPONSE
TO the weather constantly, and often forced to spend the night in floodplains, suspended over
water in their hammocks.

Countless pieces of vegetation, hidden beneath the waters, they often
capsize canoes: Then the Indians detiénense on some sandbar to put
out the merchandise.

Very rarely get any Indian to perish in these trances, they all swim like if waves were his natural
element. But there are other dangers to which his life is in such esponse Voyages: cite as
a major encounter with the tigers. When they discover about Beaches traces of this beast,
immediately raised his camp, going to seek not further the comprehensive security, and if in the
middle of the night, hear their roars, go to immediately collect all the firewood they can and
large lit bonfires, but this is not always the take cover against the fatal accidents, especially when
the expedition consists ne more than Indians. Magdalena A manager had sent in one occasion
a few Indians to go and collect the cuttings in the woods of a tree, which provides ash eSCelente
for a potash soap factory. Many days that these Indians had entirely unarmed, were camped and
cons to your job, when suddenly there was a night among them a hungry
tiger, and throwing himself on an Indian lay asleep in his hammock,
I had to devour far from there, however, afraid the tumultuous cries
of the other Indians awoke to the cries of the victim, threw to run,
stranding the poor Indian head pieces and with very few moments of
life.

This is like a reproach to the absurd extent that, under the pretext of avoiding quarrels with
the whites, prohibited [1] to carry weapons to men constantly nswers to the greatest dangers
in the midst of those deserts, whose empire still belongs to animals
fierce.

It is noteworthy that the tiger never enviste to people whose head can not see, and not a single
example of any traveler, be well hidden under his mosquito net, there victim died of his hunger.

The
banks of the Mamore, usually very quiet, come once a year to spend countless canoes that go together
Moxos to Santa-Cruz, and giving to the screams echo tumultuous and gay sailors, paid an animation
whose name might be delicious. Made I happen also to journey I found myself at the time one of
these expeditions. Will copy here the point of my diary that refers to this passage.

"... More than forty boats were preparing to depart at once from the port of Loreto, composing a
veritable fleet. Priests and traders who were incorporated into the expedition, they wanted I ordered
me to lead the way, traveling in company, and how could practice better, since my rowers were
the ablest, of course I accepted the honor they gave me. At the end of the day we stopped for
the night on a roomy bench Sandy, not far from a forest. Then I was taken to enjoy a promising
perspective, canoes as they came slowly and successively greeted by triumphant shouts or derision
of those who speak in advance. All Indians then scattered into the forest, and bringing back
wood, some with canes that armed beds for travelers, and symmetric key stakes thick on the ground
to suspend, for separate groups the beds belonging to the rowers in each boat: in the center
of these groups went on a fire, and the outside parle shone at intervals, and other fires where
making dinner. "

"Our camp, which brought together over six hundred people, had the most curious aspect I could imagine.
They spoke to him almost all the languages ??of the province, without being confused each other
different nations. All the white people had gathered in the center while here and there, the Baures,
the Itonama, the Movimas, the Cayuvava, the Canichana Moxos and forming
various groups, conversing in their respective dialects.

The little beach transuto lonely before the theater was the most animated. Each group of white
beds, hanging around a bonfire, in contrast with the nets of travelers and the row of canoes
which extended majestically along the banks [1]: sitting all on the beach after dinner in the
community, raising thousands cheerful conversation, to which the strangeness of different lenguages
??was more originality.

Each individual, away Moxos, was already escento fears and let your tongue go free, the indiscretions
of the one giving rise to the recriminations of the other, so they were revealed in That night
all the secrets about the private conduct of employees, and I knew most things In one hour,
which in some months in the province. "

"Finished dinner, all the Indians gathered as usual to pray in community. These religious songs
so many times I had been pleasantly surprised in the midst of those wilderness, sounded to my
ear at that time with such disagreement, I had to retire to one side, and could not be less
than the confusion of those different intonations dialects, which occurred all at once in the
silence of the night. The Indians, without covering with other clothes that their tipois, lie
in their hammocks, and spend the night ESPONSE TO THE fierce mosquito bites, and especially the
heavy dew that falls in the regions hot on the banks of rivers. Hardly bay day, rise and,
after hook their hammocks, sing in chorus and the more reflective
the appeal of the morning.

"

When traveling with an entourage consisting of a single nation, and that is high in the forest the
banks, these prayers of the night often have inexplicable charm. I can not spare to bring the case
to the expression recorded in my diary of the sensations that the solemnity of such an act once
printed in my mind. "The night was certainly one of the darker, and the gloom seemed even more
under the arch formed by the thick foliage. Shone distance away in the fires of the Indians encamped,
spreading clarity uncertain about the objects around us and giving a wild magical colorful enclosure.
A thing of my seventy-eight Indians in chorus sang their hymns, which in the silence of the night,
in those places took a character that I felt so much majesty deeply moved, I had never seemed
so simple at the same time imposing: his duration was too short for my bliss, and long after they
had ceased, still looking for my ear their mystic chords. Took possession of my mind a sweet
melancholy are harmonious with the vagueness of my thoughts and especially with the respect they
inspired me virginal beauty of those places

.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>