<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>41871</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>756</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Aún no es tarde... Entérese usted».

Y cogió un libro, y después otro, y los fue mostrando a la Benina, que se acercó para ver tanta
maravilla numérica.

«Fíjese usted. Aquí apunto el gasto de la casa, sin que se me pase nada, ni aun los cinco céntimos
de una caja de fósforos; los cuartos del cartero, todo, todo... En este otro chiquitín, las
limosnas que hago y lo que empleo en sufragios. Limosnas diarias, tanto. Limosnas mensuales,
cuánto. Después lo paso todo al Mayor, donde se puede saber, día por día, lo que gasto, y hacer
el balance... Usted calcule: si Francisca hubiera hecho balance, no estaría como está.

--Cierto, señor, muy cierto. Y yo le digo a la señora que haga balance, que lleve todo por
apuntación, lo que entra como lo que sale. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05976</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>327313</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>705</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Not too late ... Learn about you. "

And took a book, then another, and was showing the Benina, who came
to see as much digital marvel.

"Look you. Here I point the cost of the house, without anything happening to me, even five cents
of a matchbox, the rooms of the postman, everything, everything ... In this other little boy, the
alms to do and what employment votes. Daily alms, so much. Alms monthly
how much.

Then they spend all the staff, where you can learn, day by day, what I spend, and make the
balance ... You figure, if Frank had taken stock would not be as
it is.

- Certainly, sir, very true. And I tell the lady to take stock,
to take everything apuntación, which enters as what comes out</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>