<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02359</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>3922</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21931</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Hasta una cajilla de fósforos de a perro chico le derribaría
al suelo, atolondrado de pasmo y de sorpresa; pero de seguro que no hallaría entre todas las
heteras de París una más discreta, distinguida y guapa que Aspasia, y la Magdalena le parecería
una triste parodia del Partenón, y la torre Eiffel un feo y monstruoso engendro.

Yo confieso que, si se reuniesen las más selectas poesías líricas de los grandes poetas de
hoy y Perícles pudiese leerlas y entenderlas, había de hallarlas superiores a las de Píndaro.
Prolijo sería explicar el por qué. Baste con que yo reconozca que en lo lírico sobrepujamos
a los antiguos. No así en lo demás. La misma abundancia de conocimientos y el prurito de analizar
las cosas y de mirar por todos lados cada objeto, quitan gracia, ligereza y nitidez al estilo
y le hacen pesado, confuso y difuso. Acostumbrado Perícles a la rapidez de la narración de
Herodoto, no podría aguantar ni al grande historiador Macaulay, el cual, si hubiera continuado
su historia de Inglaterra hasta nuestros días, hubiera tenido que dar a la estampa centenares
de volúmenes de la edición Tauchnitz, y hubiera sido menester, hasta para un lector inteligente
y asiduo, el empleo de algunos años de vida sólo para leer a Macaulay y enterarse a medias
de lo que dice. Acostumbrado, además, Perícles a la concisión en el narrar de tantas y tan
bellas fábulas, leyendas y tradiciones de su patria, yo apostaría mil contra uno a que no sufriría
con paciencia, sin bostezar y sin dormirse, las pesadísimas e interminables descripciones de
una novela de Zola.

Es cierto que cualquiera me dirá para contestarme que Zola no escribe para que le lea Perícles,
sino para que le lean los hombres del día. Y como los hombres del día gustan mucho de sus novelas,
Zola tiene grandísimo mérito, y lo que yo digo, nada prueba en contra.

Mi réplica es clara. Yo no quiero inferir ni infiero nada contra el mérito de las novelas de
Zola. Escritas han sido para agradar en el día, y esto se ha logrado. Bastante mérito es esto.
Lo único que yo pretendo demostrar es el indiscutible progreso de la ciencia y el sobrado discutible
progreso del arte. Es evidente que Perícles se admiraría y gustaría del teléfono; pero también
es evidente o casi evidente que no se admiraría ni gustaría de casi ninguna de nuestras novelas.

Para mayor evidencia aún, acudamos a otra bella arte: a la escultura. Nadie me negará que aquel
glorioso personaje que dio nombre a su siglo y que tenía tan claro entendimiento y tan delicado
gusto, recordaría el Júpiter y la Minerva de su amigo Fidias, y todas las estatuas de nuestras
plazas, templos y paseos le parecerían menos que medianas. Supongamos ahora que al resucitado
Perícles le sirve de cicerone un sabio de los más profundos del día, muy convencido de la incomparable
superioridad de todo lo de hoy sobre todo lo antiguo, y muy al corriente de los adelantos de
la ciencia y de las invenciones novísimas más ingeniosas. Este sabio lleva al olímpico Perícles
a un gabinete o museo de figuras de cera y me le deja estupefacto y aturdido. ¿Qué tienen que
ver Minerva y Júpiter, donde el oro, el marfil y el mármol sólo imitan lo exterior de la Naturaleza,
y aun esto incompletamente y sin todos sus pelos y señales, como en las figuras de cera? Pues
no digamos nada si el sabio da cuerda a las figuras, y como la mayor parte de ellas son automáticas,
se sueltan a andar y hasta abren la boca y saludan en griego al ilustre tourista. Y aún será
mayor el asombro de éste cuando su sabio guía toque ciertos resortes, abra ventanillas en el
vientre y en el pecho a las figuras mencionadas y hasta les levante con suavidad y sin el menor
daño la tapa de los sesos. El ateniense exclamará entonces, como el personaje de una aplaudida
zarzuela:

      Hoy las ciencias adelantan
    que es una barbaridad.

En efecto; gracias a una mecánica habilísima, auxiliada de la química y de otras maravillosas
disciplinas, en lo interior de cada figura empieza el corazón a moverse, corre la sangre por
arterias y venas, el pulmón recoge aire y hace mil operaciones con él, y, por último, y para
no cansar, suben hasta los sesos muchos átomos de fósforo y de otras esencias volátiles, se
cuelan allí, como Pedro por su casa, en varias celulillas, y a poco rato, como de los gusarapos,
orugas y otros gusanillos, salen mariposas, beatillas y mosquitos, brota multitud variada de
pensamientos y sentimientos buenos y malos, que no tardan en convertirse en crímenes o en hazañas,
en sermones morales o en discursos subversivos, en obras de caridad o en estupros y asesinatos.

Perícles tendrá que confesar entonces que esto es exquisito y profundo, como llama el señor
Reyles a su arte. Lo que no confesará, lo que negará a pies juntillas, es que sea bella arte
semejante diablura.

Y todavía iremos de mal en peor, en esto de bella arte, si las figuras que el cicerone enseña
a Perícles están fabricadas para el estudio de la patología interna, y se ve dentro de ellas
cómo se forman tumores, fístulas, llagas, excrecencias y todo linaje de pupas. El pobre Perícles,
que imaginaba tal vez erradamente que las bellas artes servían para deleitar, serenar y levantar
el espíritu, sólo consigue con esta flamante arte bella que se le levante y revuelva el estómago,
y le fuerce a hacer una libación en honor de Esculapio con el vino de Chipre que bebió en su
última cena al lado de su bella Aspasia, que ha conservado en el sepulcro, durante veintitantos
siglos, y que le ha hecho soñar allí mil divinos primores.

Apliquemos ahora a la amena literatura lo que de la estatuaria hemos dicho. Fácil es sacar
las siguientes consecuencias:

Que a tal literatura se le debe quitar el epíteto de amena.

Que si no es amena no es útil tampoco, porque nos desazona y aflige mostrándonos el mal, con
todos sus asquerosos y horribles pormenores y no nos ofrece remedio alguno.

Que aun suponiendo que esta literatura de moda es muy científica, exquisita y profunda, todavía
se puede negar que sea bien encaminada literatura, sino mera extravagancia, ya que no propende
a deleitar, sino a enseñar, fin que se cumple mejor que con novelas, con disertaciones fisiológicas,
patológicas, histológicas y teratológicas.

Y que los que sostienen el raro progreso de la amena literatura, fundado en las novelas a la
moda, presuponen, no un retroceso en todo lo restante, que esto sería menos malo, sino un progreso
y horrible crecimiento de la perversión y corrupción humanas, cuya minuciosa pintura es el
asunto de las novelas susodichas.

Si hubiese demostrado la ciencia que el mal es irremediable, que por el determinismo se explican
los vicios y las virtudes, que la imaginación y la fe deben ya desecharse como facultades anacrónicas
y que apenas nos queda esperanza ni en la tierra ni en el cielo, muy desconsolador y diabólico
progreso hubiera realizado la ciencia; pero al fin progreso sería y tendríamos que respetarle,
y tendríamos que bajar la cabeza y que resignarnos. Todo lo que esta ciencia aflictiva nos
enseñase, metiéndonos el corazón en un puño, y llenándonos de miedo y de asco, estaría bien
consignado en trataditos científicos, cursos y epítomes; pero en las novelas escritas a menudo
por gente que no ha ganado ninguna borla en las Universidades, todo podía salir trabucado,
y aunque no saliera, no saldría novela tampoco, sino bodrio de ciencia mal digerida, puesta
al alcance de todos, y que sólo interesaría y conmovería, no como las obras de un arte sencillo
y sano, sino sobreexcitando nuestros nervios como las pociones y linimentos farmacéuticos,
que nos hacen ver visiones espantosas y a las cuales nos aficiona una curiosidad perversa.

Siento que se me quede aún en el tintero muchísimo que decir; pero no logro evitarlo, y haciendo
aquí punto, lo dejo para otro día.

III

Había yo pensado no molestar de nuevo a los lectores de El Liberal discurriendo y meditando
sobre cuestiones estéticas con relación a las novelas; pero como padezco de cierta dolencia,
que antes llamaban scribendi cacohetes y hoy llaman grafomanía, había ya redactado mi tercer
artículo sobre El progreso en el arte de la palabra, y no me había atrevido a enviarle a El
Liberal. Mi intento era y es escribir sobre el particular cuanto se me ocurra y reunirlo luego
en un librito, imprimiendo de él muy corto número de ejemplares. Así las cosas, veo hoy en
El Liberal un artículo en que mi ilustre amiga, Doña Emilia Pardo Bazán, trata de impugnar
lo que he dicho y hasta lo que no he dicho. No poco me lisonjea que doña Emilia se emplee en
esto; pero no quiero pasar porque me atribuya opiniones que no he emitido. Jamás he afirmado
yo que las novelas de Zola, Daudet, Goncourt, Tolstoï, Ibsen, etcétera, sean malas. Al contrario,
he dicho que tal vez serán tan buenas y tan excelentes, que cuanto escribimos, la misma doña
Emilia, Pereda, Galdós, Jacinto Octavio Picón, Armando Palacio Valdés y otros varios, sin que
yo me excluya, serán obrillas insubstanciales, epidérmicas y absolutamente desprovistas de
enseñanza y de trascendencia. Pero esto consistirá en que España y los españoles estamos decaídos
y hasta dejados de la mano de Dios, de suerte que, así como no hay ahora Gonzalos de Córdoba,
Corteses, Pizarros y Cisneros, no hay tampoco Cervantes. Y no consistirá en que haya un arte
exquisito y profundo recién inventado, que produce fuera de España esas maravillas, dejándonos
turulatos y patidifusos, y moviéndonos a remedar a los autores de tales maravillas, a ver si
atinamos a descubrir el novísimo procedimiento con que las hacen y a atolondrar al mundo todo
con nuestras novelas como le atolondran ellos. Yo no he dicho ni más ni menos que lo que repito
ahora, aunque sea pesadez; pero aunque sea pesadez, ya que doña Emilia me da ocasión para ello,
voy a continuar mis meditaciones estéticas, insertando aquí mi tercer artículo, que por miedo
de fatigar al público permanecía inédito, y que es como sigue:

Lo único que me apesadumbra y que a veces me mueve a arrepentirme de haberme puesto a tratar
asunto tan complicado, es la multitud de aspectos bajo los cuales importa considerarle y la
extensión que por consiguiente tengo que dar a este escrito. Por lo demás, mi convicción es
cada vez más firme mientras más pienso en ello, sin que yo crea inútil ni de poca importancia
explicar y defender lo que en mi pensamiento se presenta como verdad contra opiniones que me
parecen falsas y aun absurdas. No estoy excitado por el amor propio nacional ni singular; no
niego ni afirmo, pero doy de barato, para allanar el camino de la discusión, quitando tropiezos
del medio, que las novelas francesas y rusas del día son mucho mejores que las que en España
se escriben. El ingenio, la inspiración, y el chiste, habrán acaso emigrado de España. No quiero
negarlo; me limito a lamentarlo. Lo que yo niego, y esta es la cuestión, es que las bellas
artes progresen como progresa la química o la cirugía, y que la superioridad de las novelas
francesas y rusas sobre las nuestras, consista en que aquéllas están escritas siguiendo los
preceptos de un arte exquisito y profundo recién inventado.

Yo quiero conceder que en todo, hasta en las bellas letras, hay progreso, en lo que pudiéramos
llamar técnico o del oficio, pero, no bien lo reconozco, cuando reconozco igualmente que lo
técnico y progresivo de la literatura, apenas tiene importancia, comparado con lo esencial
de ella, en que no cabe progreso. Recapacítese bien y se verá que, en ninguna época colocados
los hombres en el nivel de la más vulgar y mediana cultura que entonces había, se han requerido
más especiales estudios ni más largos años de aprendizaje para ser poeta o novelista que para
ejercer otro oficio cualquiera. Todos los hombres, por ejemplo, saben hablar y escribir, pero
no todos manejan la lezna y el tirapié, como no se apliquen a ello con ahínco y constancia.
De aquí que, en cierto sentido, pueda bien afirmarse que es más difícil hacer un zapato que
componer un poema. Y todavía es más fácil, y requiere menos propedéutica componer una novela,
para la cual, la prosodia, el arte métrica y el diccionario de la rima importan poco o nada.
Así se concibe, sin el menor asombro, la inmensa cantidad de novelas que se componen ahora
en inglés, en francés, en ruso, en italiano, en alemán, en húngaro, en polaco, en suma, en
casi todas las lenguas que se hablan y se escriben en los diversos países civilizados de las
cinco partes del mondo. El oficio es fácil de aprender y el instrumento que vale para la confección
o fabricación, o sea la lengua o la pluma, se maneja con menos esfuerzo y más naturalmente,
no ya que el cincel o el pincel sino que el azadón o el almocafre, por donde toda persona algo
educada escribe o puede escribir novelas. Hasta el material que se gasta en escribirlas cuesta
menos y está más al alcance de todos que el que se gasta en los demás menesteres. Por tres
pesetas se compran mil cuartillas de papel, en las cuales, aunque no se emborronen sino por
un lado, caben con holgura dos novelas de no cortas dimensiones.

¿Será acaso que por esta misma abundancia de novelas se necesite emplear un arte exquisito
y profundo para que sobresalga entre todas las demás la que nosotros escribamos? Yo lo niego
redondamente. El buen gusto, el delicado juicio estético, si no está en contradicción crea
notable confusión en este punto. Para toda persona refinada y culta, Próspero Mérimée y Teófilo
Gauthier, por ejemplo, son mejores novelistas que Eugenio Sue y Ponson du Terrail, y, sin embargo,
ni Colomba, ni El Capitán Fracasse, han logrado la vigésima parte del favor del público, de
la venta y del aplauso que Los Misterios de París, o las interminables aventuras de Rocambole.
¿Consistirá esto en que Sue y Ponson du Terrail emplean el arte exquisito y profundo que Gauthier
y Mérimée ignoran o en que la generalidad del público tiene un gusto pésimo, está muy atrasada
aún y prefiere lo burdo a lo fino? ¿O consistirá esto en que el verdadero arte exquisito y
profundo no ha llegado a descubrirse, sino muy recientemente, cuando Merimée y Gauthier estaban
ya muertos y enterrados, y por virtud de dicho arte al público se le han abierto los ojos del
entendimiento para comprender lo bueno, y a Zola, Daudet, Bourget, Ibsen y Tolstoï, se les
han abierto los veneros y fuentes de la inspiración legítima para producir obras, que no sólo
agraden en el día, sino que ya contengan en germen, cuando no en flor, la sublime novela del
porvenir, en cuya comparación es el Quijote una obra superficial, epidérmica, sin trascendencia,
sin enseñanza y de mero pasatiempo?

Si las cosas fuesen así, la moda dejaría ya de ser moda. El recto camino, el arte infalible
para escribir novelas estaría hallado, y por nada del mundo deberíamos apartarnos de él, para
no extraviarnos o quedarnos a la zaga.

Yo advierto, no obstante, que estas novelas, escritas con el arte exquisito y profundo que
tanto encomia el señor Reyles, aunque son leídas, admiradas e imitadas por cuantos siguen fanáticamente
la moda de París, es de presumir que caigan en olvido, y hasta en menosprecio, cuando la moda
pase y venga otra moda. Posible es que entonces todo lo que hoy se tiene por sutileza, novedad
y profundidad, parezca falso relumbrón y pesado amaneramiento.

Lo cierto es, que las novelas más populares, las que se han vendido más en el mundo en estos
últimos años, las que han tenido en apariencia al menos, mayor influjo en los sucesos políticos
y sociales, no se han escrito en París, ni siguiendo la moda de París, sino poniéndose en determinada
e impetuosa corriente de la opinión, dejándose arrebatar por ella, acrecentando su brío y extendiendo
más su acción sobre el espíritu humano. De esta suerte, novelas, no ya de arte exquisito y
profundo, sino con poco o ningún arte, aunque escritas en un momento dichoso y oportuno, han
logrado más éxito, han tenido mayor resonancia, han importado más en los cambios sociales y
en los grandes hechos históricos, que toda esa novelería tan encomiada por el señor Reyles.

Valga como muestra de lo que digo La cabaña del tío Tomás, de la señora Beecher Stowe, de la
que se vendieron en seguida centenares de miles de ejemplares, que se tradujo en todos los
idiomas, que tal vez enardeció los sentimientos abolicionistas y que entró por algo en las
causas de la tremenda guerra de secesión.

No es, pues, ni el arte profundo y exquisito, ni la sutil y peregrina enseñanza de inauditas
verdades, ni la superior inspiración, ni el refinamiento de la última moda de París, ni el
primor del estilo, ni otras raras prendas literarias, lo que da la palma y corona de laurel
a un autor de novelas: es el llegar a tiempo oportuno y el dejarse arrastrar sin miedo por
la corriente.

Otra prueba de la misma verdad nos ofrece una novela del Sr. Bellamy, ciudadano anglo-americano
también, novela de la que se vendieron cerca de cuatrocientos mil ejemplares, a poco de ver
la luz pública. La novela era lo que podemos llamar una utopia socialista o comunista. La imaginó
el autor en porvenir no muy distante. La revolución social se había ya realizado. El nuevo
sistema marchaba regular y lindamente. El mundo todo se había convertido en una verdadera ciudad
de Jauja, y el humano linaje comía, bebía, se divertía y trabajaba poco, sin apuros ni miserias.
La novela del Sr. Bellamy llegó a tiempo y a esto debe su éxito. Bien pudiera decirse de ella
lo que con mucho menos motivo dicen que dijo Voltaire de las Cartas persianas de Montesquien:
¡esas cartas persianas tan fáciles de componer! ¡...!

No pretendo rebajar ni ensalzar aquí el mérito de las novelas francesas y rusas, que encomia
el Sr. Reyles, ni de estas otras novelas americanas que yo he citado. Digo sólo que han sido
oportunas, y ya es esto un gran mérito. También, yo, cuando escribo novelas, procuro ser oportuno,
y si no lo soy, es porque no atino con la oportunidad. Pero ¿qué tiene que ver la oportunidad
con un arte exquisito y profundo recién inventado, con hacer sentir con nuestras novelas oportunas
a los hombres de nuestra época más hondamente que lo que con otras novelas oportunas hicieron
sentir otros autores al público de los pasados siglos en que ellos vivieron? Esta es la farsa
que yo no admito y de la que se deja seducir el Sr. Reyles. Esta es la hablerie y (permítaseme
la expresión) la blague parisina, por la cual, sea dicho con el debido respeto, me parece que
está también algo seducida mi discreta y elocuente amiga doña Emilia Pardo Bazán, que todavía
escribiría mejor de lo que escribe y compondría obras más originales y espontáneas, si se dejase
influir menos por dicha blague.

La blague sube de punto si se sostiene además que la novela del día debe estar atiborrada de
enseñanza, debe ser conjunto de documentos humanos y debe contener más honda doctrina que la
de los libros destinados a enseñar y no a deleitar. Sería curioso que alguien estudiase historia
en Alejandro Dumas, geología y cosmografía en Julio Verne, sociología en Zola, en Bourget psicología,
y patología interna en otros varios novelistas.

Claro está que quien escribe una novela, así como toma para elementos o materiales con qué
escribirla los casos de la vida vulgar y ordinaria observados por él, también puede tomar las
doctrinas, creencias, aspiraciones, ensueños, ideas religiosas y metafísicas, y en resolución,
todo cuanto cabe en la mente humana y la agita. Pero al tomar todo esto como elementos de su
arte, no conviene a mi ver, que se empeñe en ser didáctico, porque se expondrá a enseñar menos
y peor que lo que enseña el más pobre de los manuales y a faltar a su vocación de artista,
sin crear la belleza y sin producir el deleite estético por el vano empeño de patentizar y
divulgar inauditas verdades.

Es de notar, por último, que en esto de contener la ciencia en el arte, lejos de haber progreso,
en cierto modo hay retroceso. La ciencia se ha ensanchado tanto que no cabe en los moldes artísticos,
por más que los moldes se ensanchen también y hasta se deformen, como ocurre en la novela,
donde un autor puede discurrir libremente sobre todas las cosas y otras muchas más.

Con todo, una obra perfecta de arte literario no puede menos de encerrarse dentro de ciertos
términos. Lo que fuera de ellos se ponga tendrá algo de impertinencia monstruosa. Y en este
sentido no negaré yo que en una novela pueda enseñarse terapéutica, economía política, teología
mística, metalurgia o cuanto se quiera.

Si está de moda embutir en las novelas todas estas cosas, la novela gustará mientras la moda
dure, tal es el poder de la moda; pero pasada ésta, no habrá ser humano que sufra la novela
docente. La que gustará en todas las edades, y será siempre leída y celebrada, será la que
trate sólo de crear la belleza, ya con elementos de la vida vulgar, ya tomando para elementos
las ideas, las doctrinas y las creencias que mueven la mente del autor y la mente de los otros
hombres. Aun así, en esto de encerrar en una novela o en un poema el saber, no con fin didáctico,
sino con fin estético, los antiguos nos llevan enorme ventaja. Homero pudo poner en la Iliada
cuanto en su tiempo se sabía y no poco de lo que estaba en germen y en lo futuro debía saberse
o inventarse. Ya la Divina Comedia, del Dante, es harto menos comprensiva de ciencia. Yo admiro
mucho al Dante; pero no puedo menos de creer que sólo están indicadas en su poema las teologías
y las filosofías que con mayor amplitud, claridad, fundamento y orden pueden estudiarse en
San Anselmo, San Bernardo, Pedro Lombardo, San Buenaventura, Santo Tomás de Aquino y otros
doctores de la Edad Media. Conque si así pienso del Dante, ¿qué pensaré yo de Zola y qué creeré
yo que pueda enseñarme Zola, que no se aprenda mejor en cualquier diccionario enciclopédico
manual: en el Bouillet, pongamos por caso?

Y basta con lo dicho, porque parece cosa de broma y de risa el aducir pruebas y argumentos
para sostener verdades tan de sentido común y tan palmarias.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05976</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>226776</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19720</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Even a box to fit a small dog matches to topple him the ground,
dazed with awe and surprise, but it sure would not find among all Paris hetairae a more discreet,
distinguished and beautiful that Aspasia, and you seem Magdalena a sad parody of the Parthenon
and the Eiffel Tower an ugly and monstrous freak.

I confess that, if brought together the finest lyrical poetry of great poets Pericles today and
could read and understand, was to find them superior to those of Pindar. Neat would explain
why. Suffice it that I recognize that in the lyric outbid the old. Not so in the rest. The same wealth
of knowledge and the itch to analyze things and look all around each object, remove grace, lightness
and sharpness style and make it heavy, confusing and vague. Pericles accustomed to the speed
of the narration Herodotus could not stand or the great historian Macaulay, who, if he had continued
history of England until now, have had to give the stamp hundreds volumes of the Tauchnitz edition,
and would have been necessary, even for an intelligent reader and regular, the use of some years
of life just to read and learn half Macaulay of what he says. Used also to the conciseness
Pericles in the telling of so many beautiful fables, legends and traditions of their homeland,
I'd bet a thousand to one that would not suffer with patience, without yawning and without sleep,
the ponderous and endless descriptions a novel by Zola.

It is true that anyone will tell me to answer that Zola does not write for me to read Pericles,
but to read to the men of the day. And as men of the day like many of his novels, Zola has great merit,
and as I say, no evidence against it.

My reply is clear. I do not want to infer or infer anything about the merits of the novels Zola.
Were written to please in the day, and this has been achieved. Is it enough credit. All I hope to demonstrate
is the undisputed progress of science and the above discussed progress of art. It is clear that
Pericles is admire and like the phone, but also is clear or almost
clear that not admire or like almost any of our novels.

For even more evidence, we turn to other fine art: a sculpture. Nobody will deny that glorious
character who gave his name to his century and was so clear and delicate understanding like,
remember the Jupiter and Minerva of Phidias friend, and all the statues of our plazas, temples and tours
will seem less than medium. Now suppose that the resurrected Pericles cicerone serves as a sage
of the deepest in the day, very convinced of the incomparable superiority of everything today on
all the old, and very aware of the advances Science and brand new most ingenious inventions.
This leads to the Olympic wise Pericles to a cabinet or museum of wax figures and lets me shocked and
stunned. What have see Minerva and Jupiter, where gold, ivory and marble exterior only imitate
what Nature and even that incompletely and without all his hair and signals, as wax figures? Well say
nothing if the wise man winds up the figures, and as most of them are automated, are released
to walk and even open their mouths and greet the distinguished Greek Tourist. And still be the
more the wonder of it when his wise guidance touch certain springs, open windows in belly and chest
to the figures mentioned above and to lift them gently and without any damage the brains out.
The Athenian then exclaim, like the character in a celebrated zarzuela:

Today
the advance science that is an outrage.

      
    

Indeed, thanks to a skillful mechanics, aided by the wonderful chemistry and other disciplines,
in the interior of each figure starts to move the heart, blood flows by arteries and veins,
lungs and air takes with him a thousand operations, and, finally, and not tired, go up the brains
many atoms of phosphorus and other volatile essences are sneak in there like he owned the place,
several celulillas, and little time, as the Gusarapo, worms and other caterpillars, butterflies
come, Beatilla and mosquitoes, many varied flows thoughts and feelings, good and evil, which
can quickly become crimes or deeds, in moralizing or subversive speeches, works of charity or rapes
and murders.

Pericles then have to confess that this is exquisite and deep, as he calls Mr. Reyles to his
art.

What does not confess, which blindly deny, is that it is fine art such mischief.

And still we go from bad to worse in this matter of fine art, if the figures shows that the cicerone
Pericles are made for the study of internal diseases, and is within them how they form tumors, fistulas,
ulcers, growths and all sorts of pupae. The poor Pericles, perhaps wrongly imagined that the arts
serve to amuse, soothe and lift spirit, just get with this brand new art fair to be up and upset
your stomach, and force him to make a libation in honor of Aesculapius with Cyprus wine you had
on your last supper next to his beautiful Aspasia, which has been
preserved in the tomb, for twenty centuries, and that made you dream
a thousand divine beauties there.

Now apply to the pleasant literature of the statues which have said.

Easy is to get the following consequences:

That such literature should you remove the epithet enjoyable.

If it is not pleasant is not helpful either, because it upsets us and afflicts the poor showing, with
all disgusting and horrible details and does not offer any remedy.

That even if this literature is very scientific fashion, exquisite and deep, yet can deny that
it is well underway literature, but mere extravagance, and tends
not to amuse, but to teach, in order to be fulfilled better than novels,
with physiological lectures, pathological, histological and teratological.

And

those who sustain the progress of threatened rare literature, novels based on the fashion, assume,
not a decline in everything else, this would be less bad, but progress and growth horrible perversion
and corruption of the human, whose paint is thoroughly Case of the novels above.

If science had shown that evil is inevitable, which is explained by determinism vices and virtues,
imagination and faith schools should be dismissed as anachronistic and and that only we have
hope or on earth or in heaven, very dismal and evil Science had made progress, but progress would
end and we should respect him, and we should bow our heads and resign. All this science distressing
us teach, digging a heart in a fist, and full of fear and disgust, it would be nice entered
in scientific treatise, courses and epitomes, but in the novels often by people who has not won
a tassel at the universities, all could go Trabucador and although it came out, would not
novel either, but poorly digested hodgepodge of science, fantastic
accessible to all, and would stir interest only and not as a simple
art works and healthy, but our nerves overwrought like potions and
liniments pharmaceutical that make us see horrific visions and to
which we fans a perverse curiosity.

I feel that the ink is still a lot to say, but I can not help it,
and making point here, I leave for another day.

III

I had thought not to bother again readers of The Liberal flowing and meditating aesthetic issues
in relation to novels, but as I suffer from some ailment, before and today called cacohetes
scribendi graphomania call, had already written my third article on progress in the art of
the word, and I had not dared to send him to The Liberal. My intent was and is writing on the
subject as I come up and then reunite in a book, printing it very small number of copies. So,
now I see The Liberal an article in which my illustrious friend, Doña Emilia Pardo Bazán, seeks to
challenge what I said and even what I have said. Me not a little flattered that Dona Emilia
is used in this, but I will not pass because it gives me views that I have not delivered. I never
said I that the novels of Zola, Daudet, Goncourt, Tolstoy, Ibsen, etc., are bad. On the contrary,
I said that may be so good and so excellent, that the writing, the same donut Emilia, Pereda, Galdós,
Jacinto Octavio Picon, Armando Palacio Valdés and several others, without I exclude, will obrillas
insubstantial, and absolutely devoid of epidermal education and transcendence. But this would
be that Spain and the Spanish are decayed and even left hand of God, so that, just as there is
now Gonzalo de Cordoba, Polite, Pizarro and Cisneros, there is also Cervantes. And there will
be that there is an art exquisite and profound just invented out of Spain produced such wonders,
leaving bewildered and bowlegged, and moving to mimic the perpetrators of such wonders, to see
if bothered to find out the brand new procedure that make them giddy and the whole world with our
novels as you giddy them. I did not say neither more nor less than what I repeat now, albeit
heavy, but even if it is heavy, as Dona Emilia gives me the opportunity
to do so, I will continue my meditations aesthetic, inserting here
is my third article for fear that of exhausting the public remained
unpublished, and is as follows:

The only thing I am truly sorry and
that sometimes leads me to regret having made deal very complicated
issue is the multitude of aspects under which substantial amount and
extension therefore I have to give this writing.

Moreover, my conviction is ever stronger the more I think about it, but I believe useless or
of little importance explain and defend what my thinking is presented as true opinions against
me seem false and even absurd. I'm not excited about the national pride and singular, not affirm
nor deny, but I for cheap, to pave the way for the discussion, removing tripping medium, in French
and Russian novels of the day are much better than those in Spain are written. Ingenuity, inspiration,
and a joke, have perhaps migrated from Spain. I do not want deny it, I'm just sorry. What I
deny, and that is the question, is that fine progress as it progresses arts chemistry or surgery,
and the superiority of the novels French and Russian on our own, are that those are written
in the precepts of fine art and newly invented deep.

I will concede that in everything, even in the fine points, there is progress, as we technician
or call the office, but, well I admit, I recognize also that technical and progressive literature,
little importance compared with the essential it, in which there
is no progress.

Recapacítese well and see that at no time placed men in the level of the most vulgar and culture
medium was then, it has taken more special studies or more years of learning to be a poet or
novelist that exercise any other occupation. All men, for example, can speak and write, but
not all drive the awl and tirapié, and may not apply to it with zeal and perseverance. Hence,
in a sense, may well be argued that it is more difficult to make a shoe that compose a poem. And
it is still easier and requires less propaedeutic writing a novel for which, prosody, art meter
and rhyming dictionary care little or nothing. So conceived, without any surprise, the vast number
of novels that make up now English, French, Russian, Italian, German, Hungarian, Polish, in
short, almost all the languages ??spoken and written in the various civilized countries of
the five parts of mondo. The office is easy to learn and the better instrument for making or
manufacture, or tongue or pen, is handled with less effort and more naturally, not because the
chisel or the brush but the spade or hoe, where something everyone educated type or write
novels. So the material cost is spent on writing them less and is more affordable to everyone
that spent on other duties. For three thousand pesetas bought sheets of paper, which, while
not smearing but one hand comfortably fit two novels not short dimensions.

Could it be that this same abundance of novels need to employ an exquisite art and deep to stand
out from all others which we write? I deny roundly. Good taste, the delicate aesthetic judgments,
if not in contradiction creates considerable confusion on this point. For anyone refined and
cultured, Prosper Mérimée and Theophilus Gauthier, for example, are best novelists that Eugene
Sue and Ponson du Terrail, and yet, and Colomba, or Captain Fracasse
have been the twentieth part of the favor of the public, sale and
the applause that The Mysteries of Paris, or the endless adventures
of Rocambole.

"This will consist in Sue and Ponson du Terrail use the fine art and deep Gauthier and Mérimée
ignored or that of the general public has a bad taste, is long overdue and still prefer the
coarse to fine? Or does it consist in the real fine art and depth has not come to be discovered,
only recently, when Mérimée and Gauthier were already dead and buried, and by virtue of the public
art have opened the eyes of minds to understand the good, and Zola, Daudet, Bourget, Ibsen and Tolstoy,
they have opened the springs and legitimate sources of inspiration to produce works that not
only pleasing in the day, but that already contain the germ, if not in flower, the sublime novel
future, compared with which Don Quixote is a work surface, epidermal inconsequential, without education
and pastime?

If things were like, fashion and would be fashionable. The right way, art infallible to write novels
would be found, and for the world should stay away from him, not mislead us or stay behind.

I warn you, however, that these novels, written with exquisite art and deep commends both Mr.
Reyles, but are read, admired and imitated by those who are fanatically Paris fashion, presumably
falling into oblivion, and even contempt, when fashion go and come another fad. It is possible that
then everything today is subtlety, novelty and depth, look flashy
and heavy false affectation.

The truth is, the most popular novels, which have been sold in the
world right recent years they have had in appearance at least, the
more influence on political events and social, not written in Paris
and the fashion in Paris, but putting in a certain and impetuous current
of opinion, leaving away by it, increasing its spirit and spreading
over its action on the human spirit.

Thus, novels, not of fine art and deep, but with little or no art, though written in a happy
moment and appropriate, have achieved more success, have had greater resonance, they imported more on social
changes in the great historical facts, that all this novelty as praised by Mr. Reyles.

Take for example of what I say Uncle Tom's Cabin, by Mrs. Beecher
Stowe, the which is then sold hundreds of thousands of copies, resulting
in all languages, perhaps inflamed abolitionist sentiments and went
for something in causes of the terrible Civil War.

It is, therefore, not deep and exquisite art, or the subtle and unprecedented teaching peregrina truths,
nor more than inspiration, and the refinement of the latest fashions from Paris, nor the delicacy of
style, and other rare pieces of literature, giving the palm and laurel wreath an author of
novels, is to reach a timely manner and without fear of being dragged current.

Further evidence of the truth itself gives us a novel of Mr. Bellamy,
Anglo-American citizen also, a novel which sold nearly four hundred
thousand copies, a little to see the public.

The novel was what we call a socialist or communist utopia. Imagined the author in the not too
distant future. The social revolution had already been done. The new system regular and going
nicely. The whole world had become a real city of Cockaigne, and the human race eat, drink,
be entertained and worked little, without haste or misery.

The novel Mr. Bellamy came on time and it owes its success. Well it could be said so with much
less reason to say that Voltaire said blinds Montesquien Letters: These letters blinds so
easy to compose! ¡...!

I do not intend to lower or praise here the merits of French and Russian
novels, which commends Mr. Reyles, or these other American novels
that I have mentioned.

I say only that they have been timely, and is this a great achievement. Also, I when I write novels,
I try to be timely, and if I'm not, it's because you miss the opportunity. But what does the
opportunity a fine art and newly invented deep with our novels make you feel appropriate men of our
time more deeply than it did with other appropriate novels others feel the public of past
centuries in which they lived? This is the farce I do not admit and that seduced Mr. Reyles. This
is the hablerie and (let me the expression) the Parisian blague, why, is that with all due respect,
I think is also somewhat discreet and eloquent seduced my friend Dona Emilia Pardo Bazan, who
still write better than they write and compose original works and spontaneous, if left less influenced
by such blague.

La blague up point if further argues that the novel of the day should be crammed education, all
documents should be human and contain more profound doctrine that of books intended to teach and not
to delight. Would be curious if anyone studies history in Alexandre Dumas, geology and cosmography
in Jules Verne, Zola sociology, in psychology Bourget, and internal pathology in several other novelists.

Course,
who writes a novel, and takes for items or materials which write cases of ordinary life and ordinary
observed by him, you can also take doctrines, beliefs, hopes, dreams, religious and metaphysical
ideas, and resolution everything fits in the human mind and shakes. But taking all this as elements
of Art is not appropriate in my view, that strives to be didactic, because they expose you to
teach less and worse than what you teach the poorest of the manuals and go back on his vocation
as an artist, without creating the beauty and aesthetic delight without producing the vain efforts
of patenting and unprecedented disclose truths.

It is noteworthy, finally, that it contain the science in art, far from progress in a way no turning
back. Science has broadened so much that does not fit the mold artistic even though the mold and also
widen to become deformed, as in the novel, where an author can flow
freely over all things and many more.

However, a perfect work of literary art can not but confined within certain terms. What put them
off to have some monstrous impertinence. And in this meaning I will not deny that a novel therapy
can be taught, political economy, theology mystical metallurgy or as desired.

If it is fashionable stuff in all these novels, novels like fashion while duration, such is
the power of fashion, but beyond it, no human being who suffers the
novel teacher.

The sure to please all ages and will always be read and celebrated, will be the concerned only to
create beauty, and with elements of common life, and taken to elements ideas, doctrines and beliefs that
drive the author's mind and the minds of others men. Even so, it's enclosed in a novel or
a poem to know, not didactic purpose, but with aesthetic, former
lead us tremendous advantage.

Homer in the Iliad was able to As in his time was known and not a little of what was in germ
and in the future should be known or invented. And the Divine Comedy of Dante, is well less
comprehensive science. I admire much to Dante, but I can not believe they are only mentioned in
his poem theologies and philosophies that in more detail, clarity,
substance and can be studied in order San Anselmo, San Bernardo, Peter
Lombard, St. Bonaventure, St. Thomas Aquinas and other Doctors of
the Middle Ages.

So if I think of Dante, what do you think of Zola and what I believe Zola who can teach me,
not learn best in any encyclopedic manual: the Bouillet, for example?

And just what was said, because it seems like a joke and laugh the evidence and arguments adduced
to hold true as common sense and so overt.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>