<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05189</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>705436</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22032</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Confirmaba este rumor el que no salía de casa y el que sus
amigos íntimos no conseguían verle cuando iban a visitarle.

En tales circunstancias, bien por un arranque de su temperamento impetuoso o porque no faltara
entre sus íntimos quien se lo aconsejara, Clementina se resolvió a dar un golpe decisivo que
de una vez zanjase el litigio y todos los problemas a él anejos. "Mi padre está secuestrado--dijo--.
Yo voy allá y arrojo a esa mujer de casa". Osorio trató de disuadirla, pero inútilmente.

Una mañana se hizo trasladar en su coche al palacio de Requena. Pasmo del portero al abrir
la verja y encontrarse con la señorita Clementina, y visible alegría también. Porque, aunque
no era tan llana como la ex florista ni tan pródiga, el sentimiento de justicia obligaba a
los criados del duque a despreciar a ésta y respetar a aquélla. La orgullosa dama se contentó
con decir, sin mirarle: "Hola, Rafael", y se dirigió rápidamente a la escalinata.

¿Cómo está papá?--preguntó al criado que halló en el recibimiento.

Tan aturdido quedó que no pudo responderle inmediatamente.

--¡Vamos, hombre!--repitió con impaciencia--. ¿Qué tal papá? ¿Está en las oficinas o en sus
habitaciones?

--Dispense V.E. ... el señor duque está bueno.... Me parece que aún está en su gabinete....

En aquel momento una doncella, que desde el fondo del corredor la vió y escuchó sus preguntas,
corrió toda azorada a avisar a la señora. Clementina también subió con pie rápido la escalera
del piso principal. Antes de llegar a la puerta del gabinete de su padre, la Amparo se interpuso
delante de ella, pálida, mirándola fijamente, con ojos agresivos.

--¿Dónde va usted?--preguntó con voz ligeramente ronca por la emoción.

--¿Quién es usted?--respondió la dama alzando la cabeza con soberano desdén y mirándola de
arriba abajo.

--Yo soy la señora de esta casa--repuso la malagueña poniéndose aún más pálida.

--Querrá usted decir la secuestradora. No tengo noticia de que aquí haya señora alguna.

--¡Ah! Viene usted a insultarme a mi misma casa--exclamó la ex florista poniéndose en jarras
como en la plazuela.

--No; vengo a arrojarte de ella antes que llegue la policía a hacerlo.

--¡No me tutee usted o me pierdo!--gritó la Amparo arrebatada de furor, presta a arrojarse
sobre su orgullosa enemiga.

--Repito que vengo a echarte de esta casa y del puesto que usurpas--repuso ésta con tranquilidad
amenazadora, desafiándola con la mirada.

La Amparo hizo un movimiento de arrojarse sobre ella, pero deteniéndose súbito se puso a gritar
con voces descompasadas:

--¡Pepe, Gregorio, Anselmo! A ver, que vengan todos. ¡Pepe, Gregorio! ¡Echadme esta tía de
casa, que me está insultando!

A los gritos acudieron algunos criados, que se detuvieron confusos, atónitos, contemplando
aquella escena extraña. También se abrió la puerta del gabinete y apareció en ella la figura
del duque, de bata y gorro. En poco tiempo había envejecido de un modo sorprendente. Tenía
los ojos apagados, el color caído, las mejillas pendientes y flácidas.

--¿Qué es eso? ¿qué pasa aquí?--preguntó con torpe lengua. Y al ver a su hija dió un paso atrás
y todo su cuerpo se estremeció.

--Esta mujer, que después de pedir que te declaren loco viene a insultarme--gritó Amparo con
voz chillona de rabanera colérica.

--Papá, no hagas caso--dijo Clementina yendo hacía él.

Pero el duque retrocedió, y extendiendo al mismo tiempo sus manos convulsas, exclamó:

--¡Fuera! ¡Fuera! ¡No te acerques!

--¡Escucha, papá!

--¡No te acerques, ingrata, perversa!--repitió el duque con voz temblorosa y tono melodramático.

--Fuera de aquí, sin vergüenza. ¿Tiene usted valor para presentarse después de lo que ha hecho
con su padre?--chilló la malagueña animada por la actitud del viejo.

Clementina quedó petrificada, lívida, mirándoles con ojos donde se pintaba más el espanto que
la cólera. Hubo un instante en que estuvo a punto de perder el sentido, en que todo comenzó
a dar vueltas en torno suyo. Pero su orgullo hizo un esfuerzo supremo y permaneció clavada
al suelo, inmóvil como una estatua de yeso, y tan blanca. Luego giró lentamente sobre los talones
por miedo a caerse y dió algunos pasos hacia la escalera, que comenzó a bajar con pie vacilante.
Su padre, excitado por los gritos de la Amparo, avanzó hasta la barandilla y siguió repitiendo,
cada vez más colérico, extendiendo su mano trémula como un barba de teatro:

--¡Fuera! ¡Fuera de mi casa!

Mientras, su querida vomitaba una sarta de injurias acompañadas de movimientos de caderas,
risas sarcásticas y tal cual interjección del repertorio antiguo.

Cuando llegó a poner el pie en el jardín, las mejillas de Clementina comenzaron a echar fuego.
Se apoyó un instante en la columna de uno de los faroles, y en seguida se dió a correr como
una loca hacia su coche. Montó en él de un salto y cayó en un ataque de nervios. La sacaron
en malísimo estado y la subieron a su cuarto entre dos criadas. Cuando Osorio se presentó no
pudo enterarle más que con palabras sueltas e incoherentes de lo que había acaecido. Ocho o
diez días estuvo postrada en la cama. Al fin salió de ella con un deseo tal de vengarse, que
algunos pensaron que se había vuelto loca.

El pleito, con el hábito de venganza que ella sopló sobre él, encendióse de un modo imponente.
Llegó a ser en Madrid un acontecimiento público. Acerca de la locura del duque hubo pareceres
encontrados de los médicos más insignes, españoles y extranjeros. Los unos le ponían de idiota,
degenerado y embrutecido que no había por dónde cogerlo. Los otros declaraban que su inteligencia
brillaba cada día más clara, que era un portento de penetración y buen sentido. Pero todos
coincidían en exigir, por sus dictámenes, disparatados honorarios. La prensa intervino en favor
de una u otra de las partes. Clementina subvencionaba algunos periódicos. La Amparo (porque
el duque, en realidad, ya no se hallaba en estado de dirigir el asunto) tenía comprados otros.
Y desde las columnas de ellos se decían, más o menos veladas, mil insolencias; se sacaban a
relucir en cuentos alegóricos muchas historias escandalosas.

En esta guerra la hija llevaba la peor parte: no podía ser tan liberal como la querida. Amparo
distribuía los billetes de Banco a manos llenas. En cambio, a Clementina le ayudaban los acreedores
de su marido, sus amigas Pepa Frías, que no cesaba un momento de ir y venir visitando a los
médicos, a los magistrados, a los periodistas, la condesa de Cotorraso, la marquesa de Alcudia,
su cuñado Calderón, sus amigos el general Patiño y Jiménez Arbós, y más que todos ellos, como
quien más obligación tenía, su amante Escosura. Este, por el alto puesto que ocupaba, ejercía
considerable influencia en la marcha del litigio.

¡Qué agitación! ¡qué vida afanosa y miserable! Clementina no comía, no dormía: siempre en conferencias
con el abogado, con el procurador, siempre escribiendo cartas. Hasta en sus tertulias o comidas
no sabía hablar de otra cosa. De suerte que algunos, los indiferentes, murmuraban e iban desertando
de su casa. Pero a otros logró comunicarles su fuego: eran sus parciales apasionados y traían
y llevaban cuentos y daban consejos y prorrumpían en exclamaciones de indignación cada vez
que en cualquier parte oían nombrar a la Amparo. Aunque Clementina, en general, no era simpática
a la sociedad madrileña por su carácter altanero, como al fin representaba el derecho y la
moral, su causa era la popular. Contribuyó a hacerla más la estupidez de su enemiga, que se
presentaba en todas partes queriendo deslumbrar con su lujo, llevando a su lado aquel viejo
imbécil y degradado.

Porque el duque de Requena se desmoronaba a ojos vistas. Después del período de exaltación
y violencia en que parecía un loco furioso, vino el aplanamiento de los nervios. Poco a poco
se acercaba al completo idiotismo. Perdió la vivacidad del espíritu y hasta la facultad de
comprender los negocios. Quedaron en manos de Llera. Esto no era malo: pero sí que la Amparo
se ingiriese en ellos con autoridad, porque no hacía más que disparates. Se daba, sin embargo,
bastante maña para ocultar la locura de su querido. Los días en que le veía sobrexcitado o
incoherente en sus palabras teníale encerrado. Sólo cuando estaba más tranquilo y racional
se aventuraba a salir con él en coche y procurando que no hablase con nadie.

Mas a la postre tales precauciones resultaron inútiles. Salabert se escapó de casa en distintas
ocasiones y dió públicas señales de su enajenación. Una vez se le halló a las cuatro de la
mañana cerca de Carabanchel. Otra vez entró en una joyería, y después de ajustar algunas alhajas
sustrajo otras creyendo que no le veían. El joyero lo advirtió perfectamente, pero no le dijo
nada porque le conocía. Lo que hizo fué enviar la cuenta de las alhajas robadas a la Amparo.
Esta se apresuró a pagarlas y vino en persona a rogarle que no divulgase el hecho.

Pronto se persuadió el público de que, a pesar de los pareceres encontrados de los médicos,
la locura del duque era evidente. Comenzó a susurrarse que el fallo del tribunal así lo declararía.
Dos días antes de que se publicase, la Amparo abandonó el palacio de Requena después de haberlo
puesto a saco. Se llevó multitud de objetos de gran valor. Su hacienda ascendía ya a una porción
de millones. En previsión de lo que podía suceder la había sacado del Banco de España y la
tenía en valores extranjeros. Pocos días después se marchó a Francia. Algunos meses más tarde
circuló por Madrid la noticia de que se casaba con el marqués de Dávalos.

La misma tarde del día en que la Amparo huyó (porque huída se puede llamar) de la casa de Requena,
entró Clementina con su marido y se posesionó de ella. Halló a su padre en un estado tristísimo,
completamente idiota. Hablaba como si la hubiera visto el día anterior y no hubiera pasado
nada; le preguntaba con mucho interés por la Amparo y hasta algunas veces la confundía con
ella. El corazón de la hija, hay que confesarlo, no padeció gran cosa. Aquella desgracia no
apagaba por entero el rencor que despertaba en su alma el recuerdo de los amarguísimos días
que acababa de pasar. Su venganza no estaba satisfecha porque veía a la Amparo rica y feliz.
Quería a todo trance perseguirla criminalmente, mientras su marido, satisfecho con la fortuna
colosal que caía en sus manos, no se preocupaba poco ni mucho de semejante cosa.

El duque de Requena, el célebre banquero que tuvo atentos y admirados durante veinte años a
los negociantes españoles y extranjeros, el hombre que había dado tanto que decir al público
y a la prensa, pasó muy pronto a ser en el palacio de Osorio un trasto inútil y despreciable.
Por no dar que murmurar, o por asegurarse mejor de su persona, o quizá por un vago temor de
que pudiera curarse, los esposos Osorio no le enviaron a un manicomio: tuviéronle guardado
en casa. Salabert se había convertido en niño. No se preocupaba ya de otra cosa que del alimento.
Hablaba poco. Pasaba horas y horas mirándose las uñas o frotándose una mano con la otra, dejando
escapar de vez en cuando gritos extraños, inarticulados. Tenía cerca un criado que, cuando
se mostraba desobediente y se enfurecía, le castigaba. Pero a quien más respeto tenía, y aun
puede decirse verdadero temor, era a su hija. Bastaba que Clementina le mirase ceñuda y le
dirigiese una seca reprensión para que el loco se sometiese repentinamente. En cambio, no hacía
caso alguno de su yerno.

Cuando el criado que le cuidaba, viéndole tranquilo iba a recrearse un poco con sus compañeros,
el loco acostumbraba a vagar por las habitaciones del palacio mirándose con atención a los
espejos. Su manía principal era la de recoger los pedacitos de pan que hallaba y amontonarlos
en un rincón de su cuarto hasta que allí se pudrían. Cuando el montón era ya demasiado grande,
los criados venían a recogerlos en cestos y lo tiraban al carro de la basura. Al entrar en
su habitación y echarlo de menos se enfurecía. Necesitaba su guardián hacer uso de algún medio
violento para volverle el sosiego.

Cierta tarde, poco después de almorzar los señores (el loco almorzaba en su cuarto), se hallaban
reunidos tres o cuatro criados en el gran comedor del palacio limpiando la vajilla y colocándola
en los aparadores. Estaban de buen humor y retozaban cambiando latigazos con los paños que
tenían en la mano, corriendo en torno de la mesa y soltando sonoras carcajadas. La señora no
podía escucharles porque estaba arriba. En esto apareció el loco en la puerta con una bandeja
en la mano, la bandeja en que acostumbraba a transportar los mendrugos, como preciosa mercancía,
a su habitación. Vestía una bata grasienta ya y traía la cabeza descubierta. Pero aquella cabeza,
a pesar de sus blancos cabellos, no era venerable. Las mejillas pálidas, terrosas, los labios
amoratados y caídos, la mirada opaca sin expresión alguna, no reflejaban la ancianidad que
tiene su hermosura, sino la decrepitud del vicio siempre repugnante y la señal de la idiotez,
aterradora siempre.

Permaneció un instante indeciso al ver tanta gente. Al fin se resolvió a entrar; fué derecho
a los cajones de los aparadores y comenzó con afán a registrarlos sacando todos los mendrugos
que había y colocándolos en su bandeja. Los criados le contemplaban sonrientes con mirada burlona.

--Busca, busca--dijo uno--. ¿Cuándo nos convidas a gazpacho, tío lipendi?

El viejo no hizo caso: siguió afanoso en su tarea.

--Gazpacho, no--dijo otro--. Mejor será que nos convides a un billete de cien pesetas.

--A ti no te convido. A Anselmo, sí--dijo el duque tartamudeando mucho y mirándole airado.

--¡Toma! ya sé por qué convidas a Anselmo; porque te anda con el bulto. Descuida, que si es
por eso ya me convidarás.

Los otros soltaron la carcajada. El más joven de ellos, un chico de diez y seis años, al verle
con la bandeja colmada y dispuesto a marcharse, se fué por detrás, y dándole un manotazo hizo
saltar todos los mendrugos, que cayeron esparcidos por el suelo. El duque se enfureció terriblemente,
y lanzando gritos de cólera, y echándoles miradas de fiera acosada, se tiró al suelo y se puso
a recoger de nuevo los mendrugos, mientras los criados celebraban con algazara la gracia de
su compañero. Cuando ya los tenía todos en la bandeja y corría hacia la puerta para librarse
de sus burlas, el mismo rapaz se fué tras él y otra vez se los tiró. El furor del loco no tuvo
límites. Convulso, rechinando los dientes, con los ojos encendidos, se arrojó sobre el burlador;
pero los demás le sujetaron. El pobre demente comenzó entonces a lanzar bramidos que nada tenían
de humanos.

En aquel instante se oyó en el corredor la voz irritada de Clementina.

--¿Qué es eso? ¿Qué hacen ustedes a papá?

Los criados soltaron al loco y se dieron a correr desapareciendo del comedor.

XVI

#Amor que se extingue.#

Los amores de Raimundo estaban presos por un hilo. En los últimos tiempos, Clementina, enteramente
embargada por su anhelo de triunfo y venganza, apenas hacía caso de él. Veíanse a menudo, porque
el joven no dejaba de frecuentar la casa; pero sus citas amorosas eran cada día más raras.
Cuando aquél se quejaba tímidamente de su abandono, la dama se disculpaba con los celos de
Escosura. Por más que hacía no lograba convencer a éste de que se hallaban rotas sus antiguas
relaciones; la vigilaba con disimulo, espiaba sus pasos; el día menos pensado averiguaría la
verdad. "Ya ves, el engaño sería muy feo: tendría razón para ponerse furioso".

El pobre Raimundo estaba tan perdido que aceptaba como buenas estas razones o aparentaba aceptarlas.
En medio de aquella abyección vivía feliz forjándose la ilusión de que su ídolo le prefería,
le amaba en el fondo del alma; que sólo mantenía relaciones con el ministro por el interés
del pleito. Contribuía a conservarle en ella el que de vez en cuando Clementina, por arrancarse
quizá momentáneamente a sus afanes y enojos, le escribía una cartita diciéndole: "Hoy a las
cuatro", o bien: "Vé por la tarde a la Casa de Campo". Y en estas entrevistas, acometida de
súbito capricho, recordando las primeras y gozosas etapas de su amor, se mostraba tierna y
cariñosa, le juraba eterna fidelidad. ¡Oh, Dios! ¡qué infinita, qué celestial felicidad experimentaba
el joven entomólogo oyendo tales juramentos de aquellos labios adorados!

Pero toda felicidad es breve en este mundo. La de él, brevísima. Al día siguiente de aquel
deliquio amoroso, encontraba a su dueño frío como el mármol, displicente, y, lo que es peor,
en largas y reservadas pláticas con Escosura allá por los rincones del salón. Creía inocentemente
que al terminar el pleito cambiaría su suerte, que Clementina, no necesitando ya al ministro,
volvería de nuevo a ser enteramente suya, sin aquel odioso reparto que le entristecía aún más
que le avergonzaba. Sus esperanzas se desvanecieron como el humo. Terminóse el pleito del modo
más feliz para ella; y no obstante, lejos de despedir a su amante oficial, cada día se mostraba
hacia él más respetuosa y enamorada.

Cierta mañana, dos meses después de haberse fallado el litigio, recibió un billetito que decía:
"Voy esta tarde a las dos". Le dió un salto el corazón. Hacía más de quince días que su adorada
no parecía por el entresuelito del Caballero de Gracia. A la una ya estaba aguardándola. Y
en cuanto la columbró de lejos, corrió a abrirla con la misma emoción que si fuese una reina
y con mucha mayor ternura. Mostróse ella reconocida, afectuosa; recibió con agrado sus vivas
y apasionadas caricias.

Al cabo de una hora, hallándose los dos sentados en el pequeño sofá donde tantos coloquios
amorosos habían pasado, ella le dirigió una larga mirada compasiva y le dijo con sonrisa triste:

--¿Sabes una cosa, Mundo?... Que hoy es el último día que nos vemos así solos y juntos.

El joven la miró con estupor, sin comprender, o sin querer comprender.

--Sí; ... no puedo continuar manteniendo estas relaciones secretas contigo.... Escosura ya
está advertido y se ha ofendido mucho con razón.... Además, me parece feo el tener dos amantes....
Eso queda para Lola Madariaga. Hasta ahora he pasado por ello porque comprendo que me has querido
y que me quieres mucho.... Yo también te he demostrado siempre amor verdadero. No puedes quejarte.
Si a algún hombre he querido de corazón es a ti.... La prueba de ello es lo que han durado
nuestras relaciones.... Pero nada es eterno en el mundo.... Puesto que ya nuestros amores están
desde hace tiempo medio deshechos (porque el amor es exclusivo y no admite repartos), lo mejor
es que lo rompamos por completo... Así como así me voy haciendo vieja, Mundo.... Tú eres un
muchacho. Si yo no diese la voz de separación, tarde o temprano la darías tú. Esta es la vida....
Hoy, todavía me encontrarás bonita: son las últimas llamaradas. Necesito despedirme de las
muchas locuras que hemos hecho.... Pero siempre las recordaré con placer, te lo juro.... Tú
reprensentarás en mi vida, tal vez la época más feliz... Seamos de aquí en adelante buenos
amigos. Tendría un placer inmenso en poder serte útil, en que me debieses algún favor de importancia,
ya que te debo yo tantos momentos de dicha...

El joven escuchó todas estas infamias inmóvil, atónito. Una densa palidez iba cubriendo sus
facciones.

--¿Pero hablas de veras?--concluyó por preguntar con voz temblorosa.

--Sí, querido, sí; hablo de veras--respondió la dama con la misma sonrisa triste y protectora.

--¡Eso no puede ser!... ¡no puede ser!--profirió él con energía, levantándose del asiento y
mirándola colérico y espantado al mismo tiempo.

Aquella mirada bastó para remover la soberbia de Clementina.

--¡Vaya si puede ser!--replicó en tonillo irónico que resultaba en aquella ocasión de una crueldad
feroz.

Quedó helado. Permaneció en pie unos instantes mirándola con indefinible expresión de angustia
y terror: por fin se dejó caer a sus pies exclamando con las manos cruzadas:

--¡Oh, por Dios, no me mates! ¡no me mates!

El semblante de Clementina se dulcificó y la voz también.

--Vamos, no seas niño, Mundo.... Levántate.... Tenía que suceder.... Tú hallarás mujeres que
valgan mucho más que yo....

Pero el joven se había abrazado a sus rodillas con fuerza y se las besaba con transportes frenéticos,
y lo mismo los pies, sacudido su cuerpo por los sollozos.

--¡Esto es horrible! ¡es horrible!--repetía--. ¿Qué te hice para que así me mates?

Vamos, Mundo, vamos.... Arriba.... Seamos formales--decía ella dulcemente, acariciándole los
cabellos--. ¿No comprendes que es ridículo?

--¡Qué me importa el ridículo!--replicaba el desgraciado entre sollozos, con el rostro pegado
a la seda de su vestido--. Por ti me pondría en ridículo delante del mundo entero.

Clementina hacía esfuerzos por calmarle, pero sin apiadarse. No hay fiera más cruel que una
mujer hastiada. Le dejó desahogarse un rato, y cuando le vió más sosegado, se levantó del sofá.

--Te agradezco muchísimo ese sentimiento, Mundo.... Yo también he tenido que luchar bastante
tiempo con mi corazón para resolverme a separarme de ti....

--¡Mientes!--dijo él de rodillas aún, con los codos apoyados sobre el sofá--. Si me hubieses
querido no serías tan cruel, ¡tan infame!

La dama permaneció un instante silenciosa mirándole por la espalda con ojos irritados. Al fin,
venciendo la compasión, dijo:

--Te perdono esas groserías por el estado de exaltación en que te hallas. Por mucho que me
injuries no lograrás que deje de recordarte siempre con cariño.... Algún día cuando tú ya me
hayas olvidado por completo, todavía tu imagen y los dichosos momentos que hemos pasado juntos
estarán grabados en mi corazón.... Pero ahora conviene formalizarse--añadió cambiando de tono--.
Concluyamos de un modo digno, Raimundo.... Me vas a hacer el favor de tomar un coche, ir a
tu casa y traer todas las cartas que te he dirigido para que las quememos. Yo no conservo ninguna
tuya. Ya sabes que las rompo en cuanto las recibo.

Raimundo no se movió. Después de esperar unos momentos, Clementina se acercó a él por detrás,
se inclinó silenciosamente y le puso las dos manos en las mejillas, diciéndole con acento dulce:

--¡Retonto! </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08737</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>20028</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19930</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Confirming this rumor that never left the house and its failed
to close friends when they went to visit him.

In such circumstances, either by a burst of impetuous temperament or because they lacked among
his close friends who advise him, Clementina was resolved to deal a decisive blow to to resolve the
dispute once and all the problems attached to it. "My father is kidnapped
- he said -.

I go there and throw that woman out of home. "Osorio tried to dissuade her, but to no avail.

One
morning it was move your car to the palace of Requena. Awe from the doorman to open the gate
and meet Miss Clementina, and joy also visible. For, although was not as smooth as the former
florist or so lavish, the sense of justice forced Duke's servants to despise it and respect it.
The proud lady contented to say, without looking at him, "Hey, Rafael,"
and hurried to the stairs.

How's Dad? - Asked the servant found in the hall.

Was so stunned that he could not respond immediately.

- Come on, man! - Repeated impatiently -. What about Dad? Are you in the office or in their Breakfast?

-
Dispense VE ... Mr. Duke is good .... I think that is still in his cabinet ....

At that moment a maid, who since the end of the corridor he saw and
heard their questions, ran all embarrassed to tell the lady.

Clemence also came up with the fast foot ladder the main floor. Before reaching the door of
the cabinet of his father, Amparo was filed before her, pale, staring,
eyes aggressive.

- Where are you going? - His voice slightly hoarse
with emotion.

- Who are you? - Said the woman lifted her head and
looking at her sovereign contempt top to bottom.

- I am the lady
of the house - said the Malaga getting even paler.

- You mean the
kidnapper.

I have no news that there is no lady here.

- Ah! You come to insult me ??to my own house - said the former florist putting in jars as in
the square.

- No, I come to throw you of it before the police arrive to do so.

- Tute I miss you or me! - Amparo snatched cried with rage, ready to throw on his proud enemy.

- Again I come to you out of this house and the post to usurp - said it calmly threatening, challenging
to the eye.

The Amparo made a motion to throw over it, but stopping suddenly cried
out unrhythmicity voices:

- Pepe, Gregory, Anselm!

Come on, come all. Pepe, Gregory! Throw me this aunt house, which is insulting me!

The cries came some servants, who stopped confused, stunned, staring this strange scene. Also
opened the cabinet door and appeared in her figure Duke's coat and
hat.

Soon he had aged in a surprising way. Had dull eyes, the color down the slopes and flabby cheeks.

-
What is that?

What happens here - asked awkward language. And to see her daughter took a step back and his
whole body shivered.

- This woman, who after asking declare you come to insult me ??crazy
- shouted Amparo Rabanera shrill angry voice.

- Dad, do not pay attention
- said he was going Clementina.

But the Duke stepped back, and while extending his hands convulsively, he exclaimed:

- Out! Out! Stay away!

- Look, Dad!

- Stay away, ungrateful, wicked! - Repeated the Duke, trembling voice and melodramatic.

- Out of here, without shame. Do you have the courage to happen after what he has done with his
father? - Malaga screamed encouraged by the attitude of old.

Clementina was frozen, pale, looking at her eyes where terror was painted more than anger.
There was a moment when he almost lost consciousness when it all
began to spin around.

But his pride made a supreme effort and remained stuck the ground, motionless as a plaster, and
so white. Then he turned slowly on his heels for fear of falling and took a few steps toward
the stairs, which began to walk down hesitantly. His father, excited by the shouts of Amparo,
walked to the railing and kept repeating, increasingly angry, extending his hand trembling as
a theatrical beard:

- Out! Outside of my house!

Meanwhile, his beloved spewed a string of injuries accompanied by movements of the hips, sarcastic
laughter and interjection of the repertoire as it is old.

When he got to set foot in the garden, Clementina's cheeks began to take fire. He leaned a
moment on a column of lanterns, and then was given a run as crazy to your car. Mounted it in one
leap and fell into a nervous breakdown. The removed in very bad condition and went to her room
between two maids. When Osorio presented no could learn more than loose and incoherent words of
what had happened. Eight or ten days was bedridden. At last she left such a desire for revenge,
which some thought it was crazy.

The lawsuit, with the habit of revenge she breathed on him, kindled a mighty way. Madrid became a public
event. About the duke was the insanity views found of most illustrious doctors, Spanish and
foreign. The one you put an idiot, degenerated and brutalized that he had not where to get it.
Others declared that his intelligence shone ever more clear, it was a marvel of insight and good
sense. But all agreed to require, for their opinions, outrageous fees. The press spoke in favor
of either party. Clementina subsidized newspapers.

The Amparo (because Duke, in fact, was no longer in a state to address the issue) had purchased others.
And from the columns of them said more or less veiled, thousand insolence; were removed to allegorical
stories surfaced in many scandalous stories.

In this war the daughter had the worst part: I could not be as liberal as the mistress. Amparo
Bank distributed the tickets hand over fist. Instead, he helped creditors Clementina her husband,
her friends Pepa Frias, who kept a time to come and go visiting the doctors, judges, journalists,
the Countess of Cotorraso, the Marquise de Alcudia, Calderón his brother, his friends and Jiménez
Patiño Arbós general, and most of all, as who else was required, her lover Escosura. This,
for the high office he held, exercised considerable influence on
the course of litigation.

What excitement! How busy and miserable life! Clementina was not eating, not sleeping, always
at conferences with the lawyer, the prosecutor, always writing letters. Even in their gatherings
or meals could not speak about something else. So that some, indifferent, murmured and were deserting
from home. But others managed to communicate his fire: passionate and his partisans were brought
and had stories and gave advice and burst into shouts of indignation every time heard that
name anywhere in the Amparo.

Although Clementina, in general, was not sympathetic the society of Madrid for his haughty character,
and the order represented the right and moral, his cause was popular. Helped make it the stupidity
of his enemy, which presented everywhere trying to dazzle with his estate, taking his hand that
old imbecile and degraded.

Because the Duke of Requena crumbling before our eyes.

After a period of excitement and violence in that looked like a madman, came the flattening
of the nerves. Slowly approached to complete idiocy. He lost his quickness of mind and to the right
understand the business. Remained in the hands of Llera. This was not bad, but it's Amparo be swallowed
them with authority, because he did nothing but nonsense. There was, however, cunning enough to
hide the madness of his beloved. The days when he looked overexcited or inconsistent in his
words teníale locked. Just when I was more calm and rational ventured out with him in the car
and trying not to speak with anyone.

But in the end such precautions were unnecessary. Salabert ran away from home in different public
occasions and gave signs of his alienation. Once he was found at four of the Carabanchel morning
near. Again entered into a jewelry store, and after adjusting some jewelry subtracted others
believe that did not see him. The jeweler said it perfectly, but did not tell because he knew
nothing. What he did was send the bill of jewelry stolen from the Amparo. This was quick to
pay and came in person to beg him not to disclose the fact.

He soon persuaded the public that, despite the views of doctors found,
Duke's insanity was obvious.

He began to whisper that the court's ruling so declare. Two days before it was published, the
Amparo left the palace after it Requena as a sack. It took many valuables. His estate had risen
to a portion of millions. In anticipation of what might happen had taken the Bank of Spain and
was in foreign securities. A few days later he went to France. Some months later Madrid circulated
the news that she married the Marquis de Dávalos.

The same afternoon of the day fled for protection (because flight can be called) of the house of
Requena, Clementina and her husband came and took possession of it. He found his father in
a sad state, complete idiot. He spoke as if he had seen the day before and had not passed nothing,
I asked with great interest by the Amparo and even sometimes confused with it. The heart of
the daughter, it must be confessed, did not suffer much. That unfortunately does not entirely extinguished
that aroused resentment in his heart the memory of the days amarguísimos
that just happened.

His revenge was not happy because I saw the Amparo rich and happy. I wanted at all costs to criminal
prosecution, while her husband met with fortune colossal fell into his hands, did not care
less or more of such a thing.

The Duke of Requena, the famous banker who was attentive and admired for twenty years Spanish
and foreign merchants, the man who had given so much to say to the public and the press, soon
to be passed in the palace of Osorio a useless and worthless junk.

Not to give than to murmur, or more sure of himself, or perhaps by a vague fear that could be cured,
spouses Osorio was sent to an asylum: tuviéronle saved at home. Salabert had become a child. He
was not worried as anything other than the food. He spoke little. Spend hours rubbing her
nails or a hand with the other, leaving escape from time to time strange cries, inarticulate.
I had about a servant who, when showed disobedient and got mad, he was punished. But who had
more respect, and even real fear is true, was his daughter. Clementina was enough for him and he
looked grim Dry address a rebuke to subdue the madman suddenly. In contrast, there was If any of
his son.

When the servant who looked after him, seeing him calm was to recreate a little with his companions,
the fool I used to wander the palace's rooms looking with attention
to mirrors.

His main hobby was to collect bits of bread and pile was in a corner of his room until there
were rotting. When the pile was too big the servants came to collect them in baskets and thrown
to the garbage truck. Entering his room and miss him raged. Guardian
needed to use any means violent to get back to the peace.

One afternoon, shortly after lunch the gentlemen (the crazy lunch
in her room), were meeting three or four servants in the large dining
room of the palace cleaning the dishes and placing in the windows.

Were in good humor and frolicked with whipped changing cloths had
in hand, running around the table and dropping loud laughter.

The lady I could hear them because I was up. In this crazy appeared at the door with a tray
in hand, the tray I used to carry the crumbs, as a precious commodity
to your room.

He wore a robe and brought greasy and bareheaded. But this head, despite his white hair, was not
honored. Cheeks pale, earthy, lips bruised and fallen, the expressionless look dull, old age
did not reflect that has its beauty, but the hideous decrepitude of the service provided and the signal
of idiocy, always terrifying.

Stood for a moment to see so many people undecided. Finally he decided to enter, was right the
drawers of the dressers and began eagerly to register removing all crusts had and putting them
on his tray. The servants watched him smiling with a quizzical look.

- Look, look - "one -.

When invited us to gazpacho, lipendi uncle?

The old man ignored: continued painstaking in their work.

- Gazpacho, no - said another -.

I'd better invite us to a hundred-peseta note.

- You do not mind conv. A Anselmo, yes - "said the duke stammered and looking very angry.

- Takes! I know why ConVidas Anselmo, because it goes with the package. Worry, that if and why
they invited me.

The others laughed. The youngest of them, a boy of sixteen years, seeing him with a tray filled and ready
to go, went back, and was giving him a slap jump all the crumbs that fell scattered on the floor.
The Duke was terribly angry, and shouting in anger, and pouring looks cornered beast, threw
himself down and put to pick up the crumbs again, while the servants celebrated with gaiety grace
his companion. When he had them all in the tray and ran out the door to escape their jokes,
the same predator went after him and threw it again. The fury of the mad was not limits. Tumultuous,
gnashing his teeth, his eyes shining, he threw himself on the seducer; but the others held
him. The poor man then began to throw insane roar that had nothing humans.

At that moment he heard the voice in the running sore of Clementina.

- What is that? What are you doing Dad?

The servants released the mad and were disappearing from the dining room to run.

XVI

# Love is extinguished. #

The Loves Raymond were imprisoned by a thread. In recent times, Clementina, entirely seized
by the desire for victory and revenge, he hardly heeded. Could be seen often, because the young
did not stop frequenting the house, but their dating was becoming increasingly rare. When he
complained that his abandonment timidly, he apologized to the lady's
jealousy Escosura.

As much as was I could not convince him that their old were torn relations, was watching furtively,
watched his steps, when you least expect would find out the truth.

"You see, the trick would be very ugly, would be right to get angry."

Poor Raymond was so lost that he accepted as good or seemed to accept these reasons. In the
midst of abject living happily forging the illusion that he preferred his idol, I loved him in the
depths of the soul, which only had relations with the minister for the interest litigation. It helped
keep him in it that occasionally Clementina, by plucking perhaps momentarily to their desires and
anger, he wrote a little note saying, "Today at four ", or" Go in the afternoon at the Casa
de Campo ". And in these interviews, Rush sudden whim and joyful remembering the first stages of
love, tender and showed affectionate, he swore eternal fidelity. Oh, God! What infinite happiness
which felt heavenly the young entomologist heard such oaths of those beloved lips!

But all happiness is short in this world. His, brief. The day after that rapture of love, its
owner was cold as marble, dismissive, and even worse, reserved in long talks with Escosura
back corner of the room. Innocently thought that the end of the litigation would change his
luck, Clementina, and the minister need not, would again be entirely his own, without that odious deal
that he was saddened even more that he was ashamed.

Their hopes vanished like smoke. The lawsuit was finished as happier for her, and yet, far
from dismissing her official lover, every day is showing more respectful
to him and in love.

One morning, two months after the dispute failed, received a little note that said: "I'm going
this afternoon at two." He jumped up the heart.

More than two weeks ago that his beloved entresuelito not appear
by the Caballero de Gracia.

At one I was waiting for her. Y discerned in the distance, ran to open it with the same emotion as
if it were a queen and with much more tenderness.

She presented herself acknowledged, affectionate, welcomed their living and passionate caresses.

After
an hour, being the two sat on the small couch where so many conversations
love had gone, she gave him a long look compassionate and said with
a sad smile:

- Guess what, world?

... Today is the last day and we are alone together.

The young man looked at her with amazement, not understanding or not
wanting to understand.

- Yes, ... I can not continue to maintain
these relationships secret with you .... Escosura and been warned
and has rightly offended a lot .... I also think having two lovers
ugly .... That's for Lola Madariaga.

So far I've gone through it because I understand that you loved me and that I love very much .... I also
have always shown true love. You can not complain.

If I wanted a man of heart is to you .... The proof of this is what
they have lasted our relationships .... But nothing is eternal in
the world .... Since our loves are as average time for waste (because
love is exclusive and does not support deals), the best is that they
break completely ... Just as well I'm getting old, World .... You
are a boy.

If I did not give voice apart, sooner or later would give you. This is the life .... Today,
I still find beautiful, are the latest flare-ups.

I need to say goodbye to the we have done many crazy things .... But always remember with pleasure,
I swear .... You reprensentarás in my life, perhaps the happiest
time ... Let us from now on good friends.

Would have an immense pleasure to be helpful in debieses me a favor of importance and I owe
you many moments of joy ...

The boy heard all these outrages motionless, stunned.

A dense covering his pallor was factions.

- But you talk so? - Concluded by asking in a trembling voice.

- Yes, dear, yes, I speak of really - said the lady with the same sad smile and protective.

-
That can not be! ... Can not be - he uttered it with energy, rising from his seat and looking
angry and scared at the same time.

That look was enough to stir the pride of Clementina.

- Go if you can be - at twang said it was ironic that at that time
of cruelty fierce.

Froze. He stood a moment looking at her with an indefinable expression
of anguish and terror was finally dropped at his feet with folded
hands, exclaiming:

- Oh, my God, do not kill me! Do not kill me!

Clementina's
face and voice softened as well.

- Come on, do not be a child, World
.... Arise .... It had to happen .... You will find women worth much
more than me ....

But the young man had hugged her knees tightly
and kissed them with transport frantic and the same foot, his body
shaken by sobs.

- This is horrible! Is horrible! - Repeat -. What
made you so you kill me?

We, World, going .... Top .... Let's formal
- she said softly, caressing hair -. Do not you realize it's ridiculous?

-
What I care about the ridiculous - replied the miserable, sobbing,
her face stuck the silk of her dress -. For you I would look ridiculous
in front of the world.

Clementina made efforts to calm him down,
but no pity. There is no beast more cruel than a jaded woman. It let
off steam for a while, and when I saw more sedate, rose from the couch.

-
I really appreciate that sentiment, World .... I've had to struggle
a lot time with my heart to leave you solved ....

- Lie! - Said he
still kneeling, with his elbows on the couch -. If you had wanted
would not be so cruel, so vile!

The lady remained silent for a moment
looking at him in the back with burning eyes. Finally, overcoming
compassion, said:

- I forgive such rudeness by the state of exaltation
in which you stand. As much as I Injuries will never get to stop always
remember you fondly .... Someday when you and me 've completely forgotten,
yet your picture and the happy times we spent together be engraved
in my heart .... But now it should be formalized - added a change
of tone -. Conclude in a dignified way, Ray .... I'll do the favor
of taking a car, go to your house and bring all that I have addressed
letters to burn. I do not keep any yours. You know that the break
in the receipt.

Raymond did not budge. After waiting a few moments,
Clementina approached him from behind bowed silently and put both
hands on the cheeks, telling her sweet accent:

- Dumber</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>