<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04335</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>19182</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16064</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

No conservaba menos enojo contra lo demas de la nacion, puesto que se habia reconciliado con
los literatos. Sois un extrangero, le dixo el hombre juicioso que le hablaba, y se os presentan
de tropel los abusos, mientras que se os esconde el bien oculto, y que no pocas veces de estos
mismos abusos resulta. Supo entonces que habia entre los literatos muchos que no eran envidiosos,
y hasta entre los magos algunos que eran virtuosos. Al fin entendio que estos grandes cuerpos,
que con sus choques preparaban al parecer su ruina comun, eran en la realidad fundaciones provechosas;
que cada asociacion de magos era un freno para sus emulas; que si a veces estas diferian de
opinion, todas ensenaban una moral misma; que instruian el pueblo, y sujetas a las leyes: semejantes
a los preceptores que zelan los hijos de casa, mientras que a ellos los zela el amo. Trato
a muchos, y encontro entre ellos almas celestiales; y supo que entre aquellos mismos locos
que querian poner guerra al Gran Lama, habia varones eminentes. Sospecho al cabo que podian
ser lo mismo las costumbres de Persepolis que sus edificios, que unos le habian parecido dignos
de lastima, y otros le habian sobrecogido en admiracion.

Dixo un dia al literato: Ahora conozco que los magos, que por tan peligrosos habia tenido,
pueden ser muy provechosos, especialmente quando un prudente gobierno estorba que se grangeen
sobrado influxo: ?pero que utilidades, pueden resultar de las colosales riquezas de los asentistas
y agentes del fisco? Aquel mismo dia vio que la opulencia de estos, que tanto le habia repugnado,
producia a veces mucho fruto, porque habiendo necesitado dinero el soberano, hallo en una hora
por su medio lo que por las vias ordinarias no hubiera en seis meses encontrado; y se convencio
de que estas pardas nubes, alimentadas con el rocio de la tierra, le restituian en lluvias
lo que de ellas recibian: aparte de que los hijos de estos hombres nuevos, por lo comun mas
bien educados que los de las mas antiguas familias, valian mucho mas que estos; porque tener
por padre un buen calculador no quita que sea uno juez recto, valiente soldado, o habil estadista.

Poco a poco perdonaba Babuco la codicia del asentista, que en la realidad no es ni mas ni menos
codicioso que los demas, y que es indispensable; disculpaba la locura de disipar su caudal
por hacer la guerra, que era origen de tantas belicas proezas; y perdonaba los zelos de los
literatos, entre quienes se hallaban sugetos que ilustraban el mundo: se reconciliaba con los
magos ambiciosos y tramoyistas, que con pequenos vicios juntaban grandes virtudes; puesto que
le quedaban no pocos escrupulos, especialmente sobre los galanteos de las damas, y las horrendas
consequeencias que infaliblemente habian de producir, y que le llenaban de horror y sustos.

Queriendo examinar todos los estados, hizo que le llevaran a casa de un ministro, y en el camino
iba temblando de ver alguna muger asesinada por su marido en presencia suya. Llego a la antesala
del hombre de estado, y estuvo dos horas aguardando a que dixeran que estaba alli, y otras
dos despues que lo hubieron dicho, haciendo en este tiempo firmisimo proposito de recomendar
al ministro y sus insolentes concierges al enojo del angel Ituriel. Estaba la antesala atestada
de damas de todas clases, de magos de todos colores, de jueces, mercaderes, oficiales y pedantes,
que todos estaban quejosos del ministro. Decian el avariento y el logrero: No hay duda de que
roba este hombre las provincias; afeaba sus rarezas el extravagante; decia el sensual que solo
con sus gustos tenia cuenta; y esperaban las mugeres que en breve le sustituiria otro ministro
mas mozo.

Oia Babuco todas estas razones, y no pudo menos de decir: iQue hombre tan dichoso es este!
Todos sus enemigos los tiene en su antesala; su potencia abruma a sus envidiosos, y mira a
sus plantas a quantos le detestan. Al fin entro en su gabinete, y vio a un viejecito agobiado
de anos y quehaceres, pero vivo todavia, y muy inteligente. Gustole Babuco, y a Babuco le parecio
un sugeto muy digno de estimacion. Fue muy interesante la conferencia: el ministro le confeso
que era el hombre mas desgraciado; que le tenian por rico, y era pobre; que le creian omnipotente,
y para todo encontraba impedimentos; que todos sus beneficios habian sido pagados con ingratitudes,
y que en quarenta anos de continuas faenas habia tenido apenas un rato de satisfaccion. Enterneciose
Babuco, y dixo entre si que si habia cometido algunos yerros este hombre, y por ellos le queria
castigar el angel Ituriel, bastaba con dexarle su cargo, sin exterminarle.

Estaba razonando con el ministro, quando entro desatentada la hermosa dama en cuya casa habia
comido Babuco, manifestando su rostro y sus ojos los sintomas del dolor y el enojo. Prorumpio
en amargas quejas contra el hombre de estado; vertio lagrimas; se lamento amargamente de que
hubieran negado a su marido un cargo a que podia aspirar por su cuna, y de que le hacian acreedor
sus heridas y servicios; y hablo con tanta energia, se quejo con tal gracia, desvanecio con
tal mana los reparos, con tal eloqueencia esforzo sus razones, que no salio del gabinete hasta
haber conseguido la fortuna de su marido.

Salio Babuco dandole la mano, y le dixo: ?Es posible, senora, que os hayais tomado tanto trabajo
por un hombre que no quereis, y que tanto teneis por que temer? ?Como es eso que no le quiero?
replico la dama: sabed que mi marido es el mejor amigo que tengo en este mundo, y que sacrificare
por el todo quanto tengo, como no sea mi amante; lo mismo que hiciera el, menos sacrificar
a su querida. Quiero que la conozcais, que es una muy linda senora, muy discreta, y de excelente
genio; esta noche cenamos juntos con mi marido y mi amiguito el mago: venid a participar nuestro
gusto.

Llevose la dama consigo a Babuco, y el marido que estaba sumido en el mas hondo dolor recibio
a su muger con raptos de gratitud y alborozo, dando mil abrazos a su muger, a su dama, al mago,
y a Babuco. El banquete le animaron el contento, las gracias y los donayres. Sabed, le dixo
la hermosa dama con quien cenaba, que las que a veces califican de mugeres sin honra casi siempre
poseen las virtudes de un hombre honrado; y en prueba de ello, venid manana a comer conmigo
en casa de la hermosa Teone. Algunas vestales viejas murmuran de ella, pero mas obras de beneficencia
hace ella sola que todas juntas las que la muerden; no cometiera la mas leve injusticia por
todos los intereses del mundo; a su amante le da siempre consejos generosos; solo su gloria
la ocupa, y se sonrojaria el si en su presencia malograra una sola ocasion de obrar bien; porque
no hay mayor estimulo para virtuosas acciones, que tener por juez y testigo de su conducta
una amada cuyo aprecio anhela uno a merecer.

No falto Babuco a la cita, y vio una casa que era el emporio de los placeres. En ellos reynaba
Teone; con cada uno hablaba el idioma que entendia: su natural entendimiento dexaba explayarse
el de los demas; agradaba casi sin querer; tan amable era como benefica; y para dar mas lustre
a todas sus dotes, era muy hermosa.

Conocio Babuco, puesto que era Escita y enviado por un genio, que si se detenia mas tiempo
en Persepolis, le haria Teone olvidarse de Ituriel. Cogia carino a la ciudad cuyos vecinos
eran afables, corteses y beneficos, aunque murmuradores, insustanciales y vanidosos. Temia
ya que fuese condenada Persepolis, y hasta temia la cuenta que a dar iba. Asi para darla hizo
lo siguiente: mando al mejor estatuario del pueblo, que le fundiera una estatua pequena, compuesta
de todos metales, y de las tierras y piedras mas preciosas y mas viles; y se la llevo a Ituriel.
?Hareis pedazos, le dixo, esta linda estatua, porque no es toda ella de oro y diamantes? Comprendio
Ituriel el emblema, y se determino a no tratar ni siquiera de enmendar a Persepolis, y dexar
que anduviera el mundo como anda, diciendo: Si no todo es bueno, a lo menos todo es tolerable.
Subsistio pues Persepolis; y Babuco estuvo muy distante de quejarse, como hizo Jonas que se
enfado porque no fue destruida Ninive. Verdad es que quien ha pasado tres dias en el vientre
de una ballena, no gasta tan buen humor como el que ha estado en la opera, en la comedia, y
ha cenado con gente de fino trato.

Fin de la vision de Babuco.

       *       *       *       *       *

MEMNON,

o LA CORDURA HUMANA.

Pusosele en la cabeza a Memnon un dia la desatinada idea de ser completamente cuerdo: que pocos
hombres hay a quien no haya pasado por la cabeza semejante locura. Memnon discurria asi: Para
ser muy cuerdo, y a consequeencia muy feliz, basta con no dexarse arrastrar de las pasiones:
cosa muy facil, como nadie ignora. Lo primero, nunca he de querer a muger ninguna, y en viendo
una beldad acabada dire en mi interior: Un dia se ha de arrugar ese semblante; ese turgente
y redondo pecho se ha de tornar fofo y lacio; esa tan bien poblada cabeza ha de quedarse calva:
y me basta con mirarla desde ahora como la he de ver entonces, para que esa linda cabeza no
me haga perder la mia.

Lo segundo, siempre sere sobrio, por mas que me tiente la golosina, los exquisitos vinos, y
el incentivo de la sociedad. Me figurare las resultas de la glotoneria, la cabeza cargada,
el estomago descompuesto, perdida la razon, la salud y el tiempo; y asi solo comere lo que
necesite, disfrutare sana salud, y tendre siempre claras y luminosas las ideas. Cosa es esta
tan facil, que no es meritorio salirse con ella.

Luego, continuaba Memnon, es necesario no descuidar su caudal: mis deseos son moderados; tengo
mi dinero que me produce buenos reditos y con buenas fianzas en poder del tesorero general
de Ninive, y me basta para vivir sin depender de nadie, que es la mayor fortuna, porque nunca
me vere en la cruel precision de ir a besar manos de palaciegos; a nadie tendre envidia, y
de nadie sere envidiado: cosa no menos facil. Amigos tengo, dixo en fin, y los conservare,
porque nunca les hare mal tercio; no se enfadaran jamas conmigo, ni yo con ellos: tampoco en
esto se ofrece dificultad.

Formado asi su planecico de moderacion dando paseos por su quarto, se asomo Memnon a la ventana,
y vio dos senoras que iban por unas calles de platanos, que inmediatas a su casa habia. Era
vieja la una, y no la aquejaba al parecer nada; la otra era moza, linda, y tenia trazas de
estar muy apesadumbrada: suspiraba, y lloraba, y eso mismo le daba mas gracia. Moviose mucho
nuestro sabio, no con la beldad de la dama (porque estaba seguro de no rendirse a tal flaqueza),
mas si por el desconsuelo en que la via. Baxo, y se acerco a la Ninivita joven, con animo de
darle prudentes consuelos. Contole esta hermosa con la mas ingenua y tierna expresion los perjuicios
que le hacia un tio que no tenia, con que artificio la habia privado de un caudal que nunca
habia poseido, y los temores que le causaban sus arrebatos. Vos me pareceis hombre discreto,
le dixo, y si me hicierais el favor de venir hasta mi casa, y examinar mis asuntos, estoy cierta
de que me sacariais del cruel apuro en que me veo. No tuvo reparo Memnon en acompanarla, para
examinar con madurez sus asuntos, y darle buenos consejos.

Llevole la afligida senora a un retrete bien aromado, y le obligo con mucha cortesia a sentarse
en un muelle sofa, donde estaban las piernas cruzadas uno enfrente de otro. Hablaba la dama
con los ojos baxos; de quando en quando se le iban las lagrimas, y quando los levantaba, siempre
topaba con las miradas del cuerdo Memnon. Eran sus razones carinosas en demasia, y mucho mas
quando ambos se miraban. Memnon tomaba muy a pechos sus asuntos, y a cada instante crecia en
el el anhelo de servir a tan hermosa y desdichada persona. Con el calor de la conversacion
dexaron poco a poco de encontrarse uno enfrente de otro, y de tener cruzadas las piernas, aconsejandola
Memnon tan de cerca, y siendo tan carinosos sus consejos, que ni uno ni otro podian hablar
de asuntos, ni sabian donde estaban.

Estando en esto, llega, como ya el lector se ha podido imaginar, el tio, el qual venia armado
de punta en blanco; y lo primero que dixo fue que iba a matar, como era justo, al sabio Memnon
y a su sobrina; y lo ultimo, que podria perdonarlos, si le daban mucho dinero. Viose precisado
Memnon a darle quanto tenia, y gracias a que en aquellos venturosos tiempos no habia peores
resultas que temer; que aun no estaba descubierta la America, ni eran las hermosas damas afligidas
tan peligrosas como ahora.

Confuso y desesperado Memnon se volvio a su casa, donde encontro una esquela convidandole a
comer con unos amigos intimos. Si me quedo solo en casa, dixo, tendre preocupado el animo con
mi triste aventura, no comere, y caere malo; mas vale hacer una frugal comida con mis amigos
intimos, y con su amena compania olvidarme del disparate que esta manana he cometido. Fuese
al convite; y viendo que estaba algo triste, le obligaron a que bebiese para disipar su melancolia.
El vino usado con moderacion es medicina para el animo y para el cuerpo: asi pensaba el sabio
Memnon, y se emborracho. Proponenle jugar una mano de sobremesa: un juego, donde se atraviesa
poco, es una inocente diversion. Juega, y le ganan quanto traia en el bolsillo, y quatro veces
mas sobre su palabra. Originase una contienda sobre el juego, irritanse los animos, le tira
uno de sus intimos amigos a la cabeza un cubilete que le saca un ojo, y traen a casa al sabio
Memnon borracho, sin dinero, y con un ojo menos.

Habiendo dormido un poco el lobo, envia a su criado a casa del tesorero general de rentas de
Ninive, a que le diera dinero para pagar a sus intimos amigos; y le trae el criado la nueva
de que aquella manana habia hecho una quiebra de mala fe su deudor, con la qual dexaba por
puertas a cien familias. Despechado Memnon se va a palacio con un parche en el ojo y un memorial
en la mano, pidiendo justicia al rey del fallido; y encuentra en una sala a muchas damas, todas
como peonzas al reves, con elegantes tontillos de veinte pies de circunferencia, y batas de
treinta de cola. Una que le conocia algo, dixo mirandole al soslayo: iJesus, que horror! Y
otra que le conocia mas: Buenas tardes, senor Memnon; de veras, senor Memnon que me alegro
mucho de veros: ?como es que estais tuerto, senor Memnon? y dicho esto, se fue sin aguardar
respuesta. Agazapose Memnon en un rincon, esperando a poderse echar a los pies del monarca.
Llego su magestad, beso Memnon tres veces el suelo, y le dio su memorial, que tomo el soberano
con mucha afabilidad, y se le alargo a uno de sus satrapas, para que le diera cuenta. Llama
el satrapa a Memnon aparte, y le dice con tono de mofa y ademan de insulto: Donoso tuerto sois,
pues os atreveis a dar al rey un memorial que no ha pasado por mi mano, y cometeis con eso
el atentado de pedir justicia de un fallido muy honrado, que esta baxo mi amparo, y es sobrino
de una doncella de servicio de mi querida. No deis mas paso en el asunto, si no quereis perder
el ojo sano que os queda.

De esta suerte, habiendo Memnon renunciado por la manana de mozas, de comilonas, de juego,
de contiendas, y sobretodo de palacio, antes de anochecer habia sido enganado y estafado por
una herniosa dama, se habia emborrachado, habia jugado, le habian sacado un ojo, y habia ido
a palacio donde se habian reido de el.

Confuso, absorto, y rendido al peso de su sentimiento, se volvia medio muerto a su casa, y
al ir a entrar, la encontro llena de alguaciles y escribanos que cargaban con los muebles a
nombre de sus acreedores. Parose casi sin sentido debaxo de un platano, y se encuentra con
la linda dama de aquella manana, que se andaba paseando con su amado tio, y que no se pudo
tener de risa al ver a Memnon con su parche. Cerro la noche, y se acosto Memnon sobre un monton
de paja, cerca de las paredes de su casa: entrole calentura, se aletargo con la fuerza de ella,
y se le aparecio en suenos un espiritu celestial; el qual era resplandeciente como el Sol,
y tenia seis hermosas alas, pero sin pies, ni cabeza, ni cola, y no se parecia a cosa ninguna.
?Quien eres? le dixo Memnon. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09333</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>181668</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14919</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

No less anger kept the rest of the nation, since it had reconciled with the literati. You are
a foreigner, he said to the wise man who spoke, and it will show of crowd abuse, while you hide
the well hidden, and that often these same abuses it. He knew then that there was among many who
were not writers envious and even among some who were virtuous wizards. Finally understood that these
large bodies clashes with its apparently preparing common ruin, were in fact beneficial foundations;
each association of wizards was a brake on his rivals, for if sometimes these differed from opinion, all
teach the same morals, who taught the people and subject to the laws, such Zelan the preceptors
that the children at home, while the master Zela them. Treatment many, and found among them heavenly
souls, and knew that among those same crazy they wanted to bring war to the Grand Lama, had
great men. I suspect they could after same thing Persepolis customs of their buildings, which
had seemed a worthy of pity, and others had overwhelmed in astonishment.

One day he said to the writer: Now I know that the Magi, which had
been so dangerous, can be very helpful, especially Quando a prudent
government that hinders grange Influx left:? but profits may result
from the colossal wealth of the contractors and agents of the Treasury?

That same day saw the opulence of these, which had so disgusted, sometimes produces much fruit,
because having the sovereign needed money, I find in one hour through him as through regular
channels in six months had not found, and conventional that these brown clouds, fed with the dew of
the earth, I returned in rain what they received them: besides that the children of these new men,
usually more well educated than those of the oldest families, worth more than these, because having
a father a good calculator does not remove a judge who is right, brave soldier, and skilled statesman.

Slowly
forgive Babuca greed of the settlement, which in reality is neither more nor less greedy than
the others, and is indispensable; apologized to dispel his madness flow for war, that war was
the source of many exploits, and forgave the jealousy of writers, among whom were sugetos illustrating
the world is reconciled with ambitious magicians and stagehands,
who gathered with small vices great virtues, since you were not unscrupulous,
especially on wooing the ladies, and the horrendous consequeencias
that inevitably had to produce, and filled him with horror and fright.

Wanting to examine all statements made to bring him home from a minister, and on the way would
see a woman shaking her husband murdered by his presence. I get to third base of the statesman,
and spent two hours waiting for Dixer he was there, and other two after they had said, by this
time very firm purpose to recommend the minister and his insolent anger of the angel concierges
Ituriel. Was the crowded waiting room ladies of all kinds of wizards
of all colors, judges, merchants, officials and pedantic everyone
was complaining to the minister.

They said the greedy and profiteers: There is no doubt that this guy steals the provinces; disfigured
his flamboyant oddities, said the only sensual has had his tastes, and hoped the women would soon
replace him another minister more handsome.

Babuca heard all these reasons, and could not say, iQue is this man so happy! All your enemies have
them in your waiting room, their power overwhelms their envy, and looks quantos plants to hate him.
At last came into his cabinet, and saw an old man overwhelmed of years and chores, but still
alive, and very smart. Babuca Gustole because it seemed Babuca one worthy of esteem sugeto. The
conference was very interesting: the minister confessed it was most unfortunate man, who had by
rich and poor was, that he believed omnipotent and all was impaired,
that all benefits had been paid with ingratitude, and in forty years
of continuous tasks had been just a bit of satisfaction.

Enterneciose Babuca, and said among themselves that if he had made some mistakes this man,
and they loved him Ituriel punish angel, dexarle enough to charge, not exterminate.

I was arguing with the minister, when I enter the beautiful lady inattentive in whose house had Babuca
eaten, showing his face and eye symptoms of pain and anger. Burst out in bitter complaints against
the statesman, shed tears, lamented bitterly that her husband had denied a charge that could achieve
on its cradle, and that they made him creditor his wounds and services and speak with so much energy,
complained with such grace, faded with mana such objections, provided eloqueencia strengthened their
reasons, that left the cabinet until having the fortune of her husband.

Salio Babuca giving his hand and said to him: Is it possible, madam, that you have taken so much
work you by a man who you want, and how much you have to be afraid? ? How is it you do not love
him? replied the lady, know that my husband is the best friend I have in this world, and that
sacrificeth quanto by all I have, as it is not my lover to do the same thing, less sacrifice his
sweetheart. I want you to know it, it's a very nice lady, very quiet, and excellent genius
had dinner tonight with my husband and my friend the magician: come to join our taste.

She took the lady with him Babuca, and the husband who was plunged into deep grief over received
to his wife in a fit of gratitude and joy, give thousand hugs to his wife, his lady, the magician,
and Babuca. The banquet is encouraged by the happy, thanks and Donayre. Know, he told him the beautiful
lady who was having dinner, which is sometimes described as almost always women without honor
possess the virtues of an honest man, and in proof of this, come dine with me tomorrow home of the
beautiful Theon. Some old Vestal whisper it, but most charities do that together herself that the
bite; not commit the slightest injustice all interests in the world,
to her lover gives advice always generous, just glory by it, and would
blush if their presence on one occasion broken? to do good, because
there is no greater stimulus to virtuous actions, which have the judge
and witness of his conduct which longs for a beloved one to deserve
appreciation.

Do not miss Babuca the appointment, and saw a house that was the emporium of delights. They
queen Teona, with each spoke the language he understood: his natural understanding dwell dexaba that
of others; liked almost without meaning was so kind and charitable, and to give more luster
all his skills, was very beautiful.

Babuca met since it was Scythian and sent by a genius, if more time stopped in Persepolis, Teona
would make him forget Ituriel. Affection took the city whose residents were friendly, courteous
and good, but gossips, frivolous and vain. Feared Whether it was ordered to Persepolis, and
even feared the bill that would give.

Did so to give it the following: statutory command to the best of people, who founded a small
statue, made of all metals, and land and most precious stones and more vile, and it took Ituriel.
? You will make pieces, said to him, this beautiful statue, it is not all gold and diamonds? Comprehended
Ituriel emblem, and was determined not to amend or even try to Persepolis,
and dexar that walked the world as it goes, "If all is not well, at
least everything is tolerable.

Persisted as Persepolis, and Babuca was far from complaining, as did Jonas that anger that
was not destroyed Nineveh. True, who has spent three days in the womb of a whale, do not spend
such a good mood as he has been in the works, in comedy, and have dinner with people from
fine deal.

End Babuca vision.

* * * * *

Memnon

HUMAN or sanity.

He placed on the head one day Memnon the wrongheaded idea of ??being
completely sane, that few There are men who have not passed through
the head like crazy.

       Memnon went thus: For be very sane and very happy consequeencia,
simply drag dexarse ??no passions: something very easy, as everyone
knows.

First, I will never love any woman, and seeing dire finished a beauty
inside me: One day is the face wrinkling; this turgid and round chest
has to turn soft and straight, that as well populated bald head has
to stay: and just look at me now as I see then, so that pretty head
is not it makes me lose mine.

Secondly, I will always be sober, but I tempted by the candy, exquisite wines and the incentive
of society. I is listed the result of gluttony, head charged stomach upset, loss of reason,
health and time, and so only eat what need, I will enjoy sound health, and will always clear and
bright ideas. Thing is this so easy, it is not worthwhile to get away with it.

Then continued Memnon, one must not neglect their flow: my desires are moderate, I have my money
that I feel good yields and good bonds held by the General Treasurer
of Nineveh, and I need to live without depending on anyone, which
is the greatest fortune, because he never I see you in the cruel precision
of going to kiss the hands of courtiers, no one will envy, and I'll
be the envy of anyone, if not more easy.

I have friends, he said finally, and he remains, it never makes bad third; not ever be angry
with me, nor I with them, even in This provides difficulty.

Formed so its planecico of moderation and hike for its fourth, is Memnon hint to the window and
saw two ladies who went through streets of bananas, which had immediate
home.

Was old one, and not afflicted apparently nothing, the other girl was cute and had traces of be
very sorrowful, sighing, and crying, and that it gave him more grace. Hastened away much our
wise, not with the beauty of the lady (he was sure not to surrender to this weakness) but if
by the despair in which the track. Baxo, and approached the young Ninevites, with the intention
of prudent to give consolation. Contol is beautiful with the most naive and tender expression
of damage it to a guy who had not, with that device had been deprived of a flow that never had
possessed, and fears that caused his outbursts.

You seem to me prudent man said to him, and if I hicierais Please come to my house, and discuss
my issues, I am certain that I sacariais the cruel predicament I see. Memnon did not hesitate
to camp out for maturely discuss its affairs, and give good advice.

The bereaved lady brought him a well-scented toilet, and forced him to sit very courteous sofa on
a dock, where they were cross-legged facing each other. The lady spoke Eye shoals, Quando Quando
in it were the tears, and when the up, always ran into the eyes of sane Memnon. His reasons were loving
too much, and much more Quando both looked. Memnon took to heart his affairs, and every moment
growing up in the desire to serve the beautiful and unhappy person. With the warmth of the conversation
dexaron little by little found opposite each other, and having crossed legs, advising Memnon so
closely, and being so affectionate advice, that neither could speak affairs, and knew where they
were.

While in this comes, as the reader has imagined, the uncle, came armed qual to the nines, and
the first thing he said was he would kill, as was just, the wise Memnon and his niece, and the last
thing that could forgive, if given a lot of money. Saw himself pointed Quanto Memnon had to
give, and thanks to those fortunate times worse had not result to fear that even America was
not discovered, nor were the beautiful women afflicted as dangerous as now.

Confused and desperate Memnon was returned to his home, where he found a note inviting me to
intimate dinner with some friends.

If I stay home alone, he said, will have concerns with the mood my sad adventures, eating, and
falling evil, but it make a frugal meal with my friends intimate, and with his pleasant company
to forget the nonsense that this morning I made. Was to treat, and seeing that I was a bit sad,
he was forced to drank to dispel his melancholy. The wine used in moderation is medicine for
the encouragement and for the body, so I thought the wise Memnon, and got drunk. Proponenle desktop
play a hand: a game where you go through recently, is an innocent
diversion.

Play and win him quanto had in his pocket, and four times more about his word. Give rise to
a dispute about the game, the spirits irritans, throws one of his intimate friends a cup head
you take out an eye, and bring home the wise Memnon drunk, penniless, and with an eye less.

Having
slept a little wolf, sent his servant to house the treasurer general of income Nineveh, to
give him money to pay his close friends, and the servant brings new that that morning had made a bad
faith bankruptcy debtor, with the qual dexaba by doors a hundred families. Memnon be spiteful
palace with a eye patch and a memorial in hand, asking for justice to the king of the bankrupt,
and is in a room with many ladies, all backwards like tops with elegant tontillos twenty feet
in circumference, and gowns thirty tail. One that he knew something, he said the sideways facing
you: iJesus, how awful! Y another that he knew more: Good afternoon, sir Memnon, really, I'm
glad Mr. Memnon much to see you:? like that you are one-eyed, Mr.
Memnon? and said this, he left without waiting for response.

Agazapose Memnon in a corner, waiting to be able to throw at the feet of the monarch. His Majesty
arrived, Memnon kiss the ground three times, and gave his memorial, which took the sovereign
with great kindness, and handed him one of his lieutenants, to give her account. Call The
satrap of Memnon aside, and says in a tone of mockery and gesture of insult: Donoso eyed you are,
because you dare to give the king a memorial that has not passed through my hands, and you commit
to it the bombing of a failed demand justice honored that this Baxo my fortress, and nephew
a maid service to my dear. Do not give more step in the matter, at your peril good eye you
have left.

Thus, having given up in the morning Memnon of girls, of feasting, games, of contention, and
most of the palace before nightfall had been deceived and cheated by a herniosa lady, had drunk,
he had played, he had an eye removed, and had been to the palace where he had laughed at him.

Confused,
lost, and surrendered to the weight of his sorrow he was returning home half dead, and going to
enter, he found it full of sheriffs and clerks who carried the furniture behalf of its creditors.
Paros almost meaningless vnder a banana, and meets the lovely lady that morning, which was still
walking around with her beloved uncle, and could not be have to laugh at the sight of Memnon with
his patch.

Night fell, and lay down on a heap Memnon straw, near the walls of his house Entrol fever,
is lethargic with the strength of her and appeared in a dream a heavenly spirit, And he shone
like the sun, and had six beautiful wings but no feet, no head or tail, and not like any thing.
Who are you? Memnon said to him

.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>