<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03553</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>112611</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19692</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Se ordenó la procesion,
  cargando la estàtua del Santo el clero, mesclado con los PP. de
  la Compañía, que alternaban con los PP. Dominicos hasta que se
  llegó á la iglesia parroquial, que es la principal de la ciudad,
  resonando continuamente las armas de fuego, cohetes y la armonia
  de la música. Luego que se llegó á la iglesia que, toda adornada
  con primor de luces y lamparas muy hermosas, relucia iluminada
  interiormente, hecha señal con la campana para visperas, y
  colocado el Santo en el mismo presbiterio sobre una mesa, que
  para esto estaba adornada, se cantaron por punto las visperas en
  que oficiaron nuestros mejores músicos, asistiendo á ellas todo
  el clèro y los PP. Jesuitas y Dominicos: concluidas las
  ceremonias, en el mismo òrden, aparato y solemnidad, fué llevado
  el simulacro del Santo à nuestra iglesia, en donde se cantó el
  Te-Deum solemnemente, resonando los cañones de fuego, y
  música, y tambien las campanas: y dicha la oracion acostumbrada,
  se terminó por este dia la solemnidad acordada. Despues á las
  Ave-Marias y final de la fiesta, se encendieron algunos cientos
  de lámparas, se iluminó la torre parroquial, y tambien la
  nuestra tenia muchas banderas, que con hermosura batian el
  viento y se mesclaban con las làmparas. Estando la noche mas
  oscura iluminaron el aire los cohetes voladores y se oyò el
  estrépito de las armas.

  69. Al dia siguiente, desde la aurora, los sacerdotes que no
  eran de casa, digeron misa hasta las 9, y mas adelante, estando
  siempre la iglesia llena de pueblo de todo género, de condicion
  y estado. Despues cantó la misa solemne el Dr. Leiva, párroco de
  la ciudad, la que mucho antes habia pedido por un singular
  beneficio recibido: lo que llevò pesadamente el Vicario. Un
  sugeto de nuestra Compañìa predicó, y muy bien. Estuvo desde
  ayer, y todo el tiempo de la misa, la imàgen del Santo sobre el
  altar mayor, en un rico trono de oro y plata, reluciendo todo el
  altar con este metal, y la efigie del Santo, y principalmente la
  mesita donde estaba, toda cubierta de piedras preciosas, perlas
  y diamantes. Y aunque todas las matronas de Santa Fé juntaron
  sus riquezas para este ornato, con todo, sobrepujò cierta noble
  muger, advenediza del reino de Chile, que habia venido á esta
  ciudad: la cual, como ya no hubiese lugar en el altar, colocò
  bajo de las gradas del presbiterio una mesita con un niño Jesus,
  en quien lucian cosas tan preciosas, en oro, diamantes, y
  tambien por el arte singular con que las habia dispuesto, que à
  todos arrebataba, dejando muy atras à las demas Señoras
  patricias. Concluida la solemnidad de la misa, que durò hasta el
  mediodia, se sacò del altar mayor la efigie del Santo, y cantado
  otra vez el Te-deum los Padres de Santo Domingo, fué colocada
  (con increible gozo y alegria de todo el pueblo y ciudad, y
  principalmente de nuestros Padres, de que fueron testigo los
  reiterados y solemnes repiques de campanas) en su altar propio,
  que le habian preparado los afligidos indios; el cual, fuera de
  su propia hermosura, estaba grandemente adornado con alhajas de
  los vecinos. Se concluyó finalmente la solemnidad, pero no la
  devocion: porque ademas de ocurrir nuestros Jesuitas cada dia
  con mayor fervor al poderoso patronicio del Santo contra los
  murmuradores, tambien no era pequeño el concurso de los de toda
  la ciudad en las aflicciones y calumnias que por todas partes se
  suscitaban contra los indios, que han sido cometidos por Dios à
  nuestra fé y doctrina, y por eso mismo tambien contra nosotros,
  como defensores de esta justa causa.

  70. Cuando estas cosas sucedian por Mayo en la ciudad de Santa
  Fè en honor del taumaturgo de Bohemia, el pueblo de San Miguel,
  distinguièndose entre todos, se preparaba á cumplir con otro
  semejante altar (excepto las riquezas) sus promesas hechas á
  Nuestra Señora de Loreto, cuya descripcion omitimos, por haber
  referido la anterior: pero despues por su òrden se referirá,
  cuando hayamos hablado de lo que sucediò por Julio; habiéndose
  pasado casi tranquilamente el resto de Mayo, y tambien Junio.

  71. Dijimos casi tranquilamente, porque no hubo hostilidad
  alguna: aunque no por esto dejaron los enemigos de maquinarlas,
  pues siempre su descanso es una asechanza, y aunque no hagan
  hostilidades, las estan disponiendo y proyectando. Por esta
  causa, para privar á la confederacion de los auxilios que debian
  dar à los Guaranis las infieles tropas de Guanoas gentiles, (las
  que deben ser tenidas como enemigas, aun cuando son amigas, pues
  à ninguno, ni aun à Dios, guardan fé) llamaron á ciertos
  caciques de ellos, y los llevaron á un castillo que estaba mas
  inmediato, para persuadirles lo que querian:--lo que es facil de
  conseguir de una gente pobre, y deseosa de donecillos, regalos y
  vestidos de ante ò coletos. Fueron algunos à dicho fuerte por
  las dàdivas, y tambien (lo que entre cristianos es abominable y
  vedado por excomunion) casi los violentaron con las armas, y se
  dijo que tambien los habian corrompido ó sobornado. Así lo
  contaron despues á nuestros Miguelistas otros caciques de los
  Minuanes, que habian participado de los dones ó regalos. Que
  algunos de los suyos habian sido pagados para la guerra, y
  principalmente uno llamado Moreira, para que en la siguiente
  expedicion custodiase los bagages de los Portugueses con su
  gente. Que tenian mucha ropa, armas, y se veian armados, y estar
  instruidos con alfanges para este fin. Fuera de esto que los
  Portugueses, confiados en esta esperanza, erigian un fuertecillo
  que habia de servir de oportuno presidio à los reales que se
  habian de formar en las montañas de San Miguel, cercanos à las
  estancias de Santa María, las que se llaman de Yacegua: pero que
  tambien otros caciques de la nacion se escusaban, y que por
  tanto avisaban con anticipacion á los amigos lo que se habia
  tratado. Por esto fueron despues señalados exploradores
  católicos ò cristianos del pueblo de San Miguel, los cuales con
  la guarnicion que estaba en los últimos términos de la
  jurisdiccion, debian correr la tierra. Recorriéronla, y avisaron
  que no parecia enemigo alguno, y reconviniendo al mismo Moreira,
  afeándole su hecho, confesò que verdaderamente él habia sido
  llamado de los Portugueses, y solicitado con dones por las cosas
  sobredichas, pero que de ninguna suerte habia consentido: por lo
  cual se habia retirado, habiendo los Lusitanos con furor,
  hèchole muchas amenazas. Esto decia èl, mas si fuese verdad lo
  que decia se esperaba lo probase el efecto, si se ofreciese la
  ocasion; mas por entonces así se creyó.

  72. Tambien esparcieron los Portugueses con estas cosas no pocas
  mentiras contra los indios, y principalmente que muchísimos se
  habian pasado à ellos, y que numerosas cuadrillas á menudo se
  iban huyendo de la tirania de los PP., y que ya se contaban y
  numeraban algunos cientos de los dichos. Fingian estas cosas con
  el fin de provocar á los Españoles á volver à emprender la
  guerra, pero despues se descubrieron reos ó autores de la
  mentira, cuando por mano del Provincial de la provincia del
  Brasil enviaron la lista de los indios que moraban entre ellos:
  de los cuales algunos estaban casados, y otros lo pedian: pero
  no contaban mas de 50, de los cuales muchos tenian apellidos del
  pueblo de San Borja, pero discrepaban en los nombres. Se hallò
  tambien que otros, que estaban insertos en dicha lista por su
  nombre y apellido, ya se habian restituido otra vez à sus
  pueblos. Los Portugueses andaban solícitos en persuadir á los
  Españoles estas cosas, mas à los indios les constaban otras: es
  á saber, que el Padre Ràbago, (en quien ponian los indios en lo
  humano alguna esperanza de su patrocinio) habia sido privado del
  confesionario del Rey, que habia caido de gracia, y à mas de
  esto, que estaba preso: pero despues avisaron de Europa, que era
  impostura y mentira de los Portugueses.

  73. Ya fenecia Julio, cuando en el puerto de Montevideo apareciò
  una embarcacion mercantil el dia 27 de Julio, la cual traia 150
  soldados presidarios para aquel castillo, y 70 Misioneros de la
  Compañia, 40 para la provincia de Chile, y 31 para la nuestra;
  quedàndose en España los demas, que casi eran otros tantos, con
  el procurador que reside en la Corte, y tiene à su cuidado los
  negocios de la Provincia y Misiones. En verdad que no causò à
  todos poco consuelo esta noticia, especialmente por haberse
  llenado la provincia de noticias prósperas, y tambien de cartas
  que anunciaban todo favorablemente. Parecia que estaba el
  negocio concluido, que la Corte habia desecho el inicuo tratado,
  que se regocijaba ò deleitaba con nuestra fidelidad y
  obediencia, que habia aceptado la apelacion por parte de los
  pueblos, que mandaba se suspendiesen las cosas. Asì se decia à
  los principios: mas como las noticias tristes suelen seguirse à
  las pròsperas, los Comisarios reales de este negocio divulgaron
  todo lo contrario: que estaba aprobada la guerra hecha à los
  rebeldes, como ellos decian; que tambien se daban las gracias á
  los Ministros por el celo y gasto hecho para sugetar á los
  contumaces; que las cosas que se habian dicho favorables, habian
  salido de charcos, y no de la fuente; que se habia de proseguir
  la guerra y se habia de hacer mas cruda. Para este fin fueron
  expedidos nuevos decretos é intimaciones á nuestro Prelado
  inmediato, fulminando estragos, y amenazando llevarlo todo á
  sangre y fuego, sino se rendian los pueblos.

  74. Remitiò estas intimaciones al Gobernador de la Concepcion,
  Nenguirù, la Curia, Consejo ó junta doméstica, porque de otro
  modo se desconfiaba que se pudiesen publicar: para que este,
  interponiendo la autoridad que tiene entre ellos, pasando el
  rio, las intimase y promulgase à las provincias y pueblos
  obligados à mudarse. Mas este, no confiando del pueblo airado, y
  previendo y conociendo que no habia de hacer otra cosa que
  aumentar tropas de amotinados, volvió otra vez à remitir à la
  Curia todos los papeles, suplicando à los Prelados no diesen
  lugar á que la provincia, poco apaciguada, se alborotase aun
  todavia mas; ni tampoco obligasen à su cabeza, ó Gobernador, á
  exponerse à peligro cierto de muerte. Se aquietaron, y
  despreciadas dichas amenazas, se esperaba lo que habia
  de suceder.

  75. Entretanto por todo Agosto, Septiembre y Octubre, se
  reclutaban soldados en las ciudades de españoles y portugueses:
  pero en las nuestras no habia sino paz y quietud, y se proveia
  que, en tanto que se aquietasen las cosas, se despachasen para
  todas partes exploradores como en otro tiempo, y que estuviesen
  con mas vigilancia.

  76. A fines de Octubre, ó por mejor decir á principios de
  Noviembre, el Gobernador de Buenos Aires, pasando el ancho álveo
  del rio, llegò á la ciudad de Montevideo, en donde debia
  juntarse todo el ejército de Españoles. Tambien se decia que
  caminaban hácia Montevideo 200 soldados que habian sido
  despachados de la ciudad de las Corrientes, y otros tantos de la
  de Santa Fè; pero si esto es cierto ó no, el tiempo lo dirá: que
  de los 200 Correntinos no habian quedado sino 80, y que los
  demas se habian desertado. Asimismo, que entre los desertores se
  habian vuelto à su casa algunos Abipones que el Comandante habia
  traido como exploradores, siendo muy baqueanos. Tambien en Santa
  Fé, habiendo el teniente convidado para la liga á los Mocobís,
  se negó el cacique bàrbaro, y no diò respuesta de tal, porque
  dijo:--que él no habia abrazado la ley de Cristo para hacer
  guerra contra inocentes cristianos, y que antes bien favoreceria
  à los oprimidos, à no ser que se lo impidiese aquel gran rio.

  77. Que á unos y otros, esto es, Santafecinos y Correntinos, se
  les habian disparado los caballos, y se les habian perdido por
  los inmensos campos: que por todas partes, y especialmente en
  Buenos Aires, cada dia se morian y perecian á centenares; y por
  esta razon algunos dudaban del eficaz progreso del ejército. No
  obstante, aunque es cierto que la Corte no dudaba de la
  iniquidad, y que tambien trabajaba en la disolucion ò nulidad de
  los pactos, no obstante, como no enviasen algun cierto y
  deliberado decreto sobre sì se habia de suspender ó continuar la
  guerra, los Ministros de ambas Cortes que estan aquì, mueven con
  mayor actividad las cosas de la guerra: y como los españoles,
  con dificultad, y casi violentados, eran llevados à esta
  expedicion y, como decian, eran obligados y constreñidos á ella
  por solas unas razones políticas, procedian con lentitud, ó
  procuraban irse despacio. Por esto, estando muy adelantado
  Noviembre, aun estaban en la ciudad de Montevideo, y no sabian
  si con sinceridad ò con doblez se divulgaban acà, donde yo
  estaba, ciertos avisos secretos, que no deseaban otra cosa los
  españoles sino que las fuerzas de los indios se les opusiesen, y
  quemasen los campos por donde habian de pasar, para que se les
  diese ocasion de dar por escusa el defecto de los pastos, y
  retroceder, ó á lo menos retardarse, en tanto que llegase de la
  Corte alguna cosa cierta. Aunque sea dudando, no sin fundamento,
  de la posibilidad del expediente, porque los pastos maduros en
  estas tierras, y la paja que es apta para el fuego, no lo son
  para los animales, pero una vez quemadas, como poco despues
  vuelven y reverdecen, con ansia los comen los caballos y los
  gustan grandemente; asì se sospechó, y no vanamente, por
  algunos, que era estratagema, y que bajo el pretesto de ponerles
  miedo, se le pedia favor, y aun auxilio al enemigo:
  especialmente siendo así que los campos y llanuras quemadas
  mostrarian mejor el camino á los viajantes, cuando por lo
  contrario estaria embarazado è impracticable, lleno de maleza.

  78. Mas como ya no quedase duda alguna acerca de los
  preparativos de la expedicion, y tardasen los navios de Europa,
  se acordò que, estando desprevenida la provincia, para evitar
  que fuese atacada de los enemigos, se preparasen aquí las cosas,
  para su defensa, y se vigiasen con mas diligencia los caminos:
  tambien pareció del caso que se incendiasen ó quemasen
  los campos.

  79. Constaba suficientemente, no como al principio por mentiras,
  que eran 1,500 Españoles, y con los socorros de las otras
  ciudades, casi 2,000: que los Portugueses eran 3,000; por tanto
  el total era 5,000: pero que uno y otro ejército todo junto
  llegaria á 3,000, lo escribió el gefe de esta gente, (el
  Gobernador de Montevideo, el que, como se decia, venia en lugar
  del de Buenos Aires, y habia de tener cuidado de este negocio) á
  cierto Jesuita amigo suyo, que algunas veces le fué piedra de
  escándalo, y que ya no está en aquella ciudad: en verdad que el
  testigo es idóneo, y vale por todos. Tambien se tenia por
  cierto, que el ejército español habia de hacer el camino desde
  el castillo de San Felipe, via recta, á las cabeceras del Rio
  Negro, y hácia el pago de Santa Tecla, término y guardia de los
  Miguelistas, y que de allí habia de penetrar, con grandes
  rodeos, por provincias desiertas, hasta una fortaleza
  portuguesa, situada en el rio Yacuy; la cual poco antes no tenia
  nombre, y ahora, por la invasion que se les frustró á los
  indios, la llaman (pero mal) el Fuerte de la Victoria: y que
  finalmente, unidas las fuerzas, habian de caminar al pueblo de
  San Angel. Así se determinó en el Consejo de ambas naciones, y
  aunque estas determinaciones parecian á los baqueanos ó peritos
  de los caminos muy violentas, y casi impracticables en la
  ejecucion, con todo se tuvo por conveniente proveer todas las
  cosas, y prevenirse contra los insensatos conatos ó esfuerzos de
  los Portugueses. No debalde se juntaron los capitanes, corriendo
  ya Enero, y aunque no se sentia movimiento alguno del enemigo,
  determinaron no obstante muy de antemano, que toda la gente de
  los pueblos vecinos se juntase y viniese al socorro. Y despues
  despacharon cartas y un correo á los de la Concepcion y de Santo
  Tomé, las que estos debian despachar mas adelante á los otros
  pueblos, para que se acercasen mas, y pusiesen exploradores por
  todas partes, y principalmente porque en los yerbales no sé que
  hacian los enemigos: sospecho que los fuegos que se habian visto
  no fuese que maquinasen alguna irrupcion, ó que componian los
  caminos. Luego al punto se destinaron diez Juanistas, y casi
  otros tantos de San Angel, para que fuesen hácia los montes,
  adonde se haria alto; y del pueblo de San Miguel, un capitan del
  campo que estaba de guardia en Santa Tecla, para que avisase á
  los suyos el estado en que estaban las cosas: porque se decia
  que por aquella parte amagaban los enemigos, y que ya habia dos
  meses que caminaban, á saber, desde el 5 de Diciembre.

  80. Cuando por este tiempo todo este aparato parecia se quedaba
  en pareceres ó disposiciones, y por otra parte se confirmaba la
  venida del enemigo con cuotidianos correos, y los curas se
  estaban durmiendo ó en inaccion, hubo quien empezó á mover el
  negocio, exponiendo que no se debia andar con negligencia, y que
  se debian juntar tropas, ponerlas listas y despacharlas á los
  términos de la jurisdiccion, para que no entrase el enemigo á
  los campos remotos de las estancias ó crias, destrozándolas y
  matando, sin ser castigado, y no estorbándoselo nadie. Con
  dificultad se consiguió esto, despues de muchas razones que se
  expusieron: es á saber, que llegaria tarde el ejército para
  salir al encuentro desde casi 100 leguas de distancia, si
  entonces se empezaban á juntar tropas, cuando ya el enemigo
  acometiese: que el enemigo podia andarlo todo, y los reales
  portugueses se andarían camino recto, por medio de las estancias
  que destruirian: que cerrarian la comunicacion á los indios, y
  les quitarian la comida, cuya falta ya se empezaba á sentir; y
  finalmente que siempre es mejor atacar primero al enemigo que no
  ser atacado de él. Por estas razones al fin se consiguió que se
  despachasen nueve correos ó postas, los que por todas partes
  avisáran y movieren á los confederados. Tambien el capitan de la
  Concepcion estaba ya con una partida de 150 hombres en sus
  estancias que confinan con las de San Miguel, y para completar
  dicha partida se enriaron otros 60 del pueblo. Pusieron en
  movimiento á los escuadrones auxiliares, que debian venir de los
  pueblos de Santana, del de San Carlos y de los Angeles, 60, del
  de los Mártires, 60, del de San Javier, y de Santa María, 30.
  Arregladas de repente por aquella parte las cosas, repuesto el
  capitan que poco antes lo habian quitado, habièndose vuelto á
  sus casas sus gentes, que andaban esparcidas por diversos
  pueblos, se creia que el Consejo doméstico habia obrado esta
  mudanza, la que luego surtió buen efecto.

  81. En los demas pueblos del Uruguay, como avisase el posta que
  poco antes habia enviado y ya estaba de vuelta, que no habia
  rumor, ni se sentia el enemigo, se daban prisa para esperarlo
  los escuadrones de los otros pueblos. Mas, á 20 de Enero llegó
  un correo impensadamente, que avisó que el dia 16 del mismo mes,
  en las cabeceras del rio Negro, por aquella parte en que hay una
  angosta entrada, entre los rios Negro y Yacuy, en las tierras de
  San Miguel, la cual entrada ó puerta de la tierra llaman los
  indios Ibiroqué, habia aparecido el ejército de los españoles
  cuando menos se pensaba: que habiéndolo visto cinco
  exploradores, les habian confesado que venian 2,000 españoles á
  esperar á los portugueses. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01408</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>870169</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17390</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> It ordered the procession
  carrying the statue of the saint the clergy, mixed with PP. of
  Company, which alternated with the PP. Dominicans until arrived
  at the parish church, which is the main city continuously booming
  guns, rockets and harmony music. After it arrived at the church,
  all decorated the lights neatly and very beautiful lamps, shone
  bright inside, made with bell signal for vespers, and Santo placed
  in the presbytery on a table, for it was adorned, was chanted
  by the eve point in who served our finest musicians, attending
  to them all the clergy and the PP. Jesuits and Dominicans, concluding
  ceremonies, in the same order, pomp and circumstance was taken
  the simulacrum of the Holy to our church, where he sang
  Te Deum solemnly echoing cannon fire, and music, and also the bell
  and said the usual prayers, was eventually agreed that the feast
  day. Then at Ave-Marias and end of the party, burned a
  few hundred lamp, lighted the tower parish, and also the we had
  many flags, which beat the beauty wind and mixed with the lamps.
  While the night more dark air rockets lit up the fliers and heard
  din of arms.
  
  69. The next day, from dawn, the priests who do not were at home,
  digeron Mass until 9, and later, being always the church full
  of people of all kinds of condition and state.

  After the solemn mass sung Dr. Lewis, pastor of the city, which
  long before had asked for a singular benefit received, leading
  the Vicar heavily. A sugeto of our company predicts, very well.
  Was from yesterday, and all the time of the Mass, the saint's image
  on altar in a rich gold and silver throne, glittering all
  altar with this metal, and the effigy of the saint, and especially
  the table where I was, all covered with precious stones, pearls
  and diamonds. And though all the matrons of Santa Fe together their
  wealth for this ornament, however, exceeding a certain noble woman,
  upstart kingdom of Chile, who had come to this city ??which, as
  we had no place at the altar, placed on the steps of the chancel
  a table with a child Jesus who looked at things so precious,
  gold, diamonds, and also for the unique art with which he had prepared,
  which all snatched, leaving far behind the other Ladies patrician.
  After the solemnity of the Mass, which lasted until noon, was
  removed from the altar the effigy of the saint, and sung again Te
  Deum Parent Santo Domingo, was placed (With incredible joy
  and happiness of all the people and city, and mainly of our Fathers,
  that witnessed the repeated and solemn ringing of bells)
  in his own altar, he had prepared the afflicted Indians, who, outside
  her own beauty, was greatly adorned with jewels neighbors. Was finally
  concluded the ceremony, but not devotion, because, besides our
  Jesuit happen every day with greater fervor the powerful patronage
  of Holy against whisperers, also was not small the assistance
  of all City in distress and slander that is everywhere aroused
  against the Indians, who have been committed by God our faith and
  doctrine, and therefore also against us as defenders of this just
  cause.
  
  70. When these things happened in May in the city of Santa Faith
  in honor of the caster of Bohemia, the town of San Miguel, distinguish
  between all, was preparing to meet another similar altar (except
  the rich) its promises made to Our Lady of Loreto, whose description
  is omitted, having mentioned above: but after their order shall
  cover when we talked about what happened in July, having quietly
spent almost the rest of May and June also.

  
  
  71. We said almost quietly, because there was no hostility some,
  but not this machine left by the enemy, the rest is as always
  a trick, and although not made hostilities, are available and
  projected. For this cause, to deprive the Confederacy of the
  assistance that debian Guaranis give the infidel troops Guano
  Gentiles (the that should be taken as enemies, even though they are
friends, because anyone, not even God, keep faith) called to certain
caciques of them, and took them to a castle that was more immediately,
to persuade them what they want - which is easy getting a poor, and
eager to donecillos, gifts and ò dresses with pigtails.

  Were provided for that hard for handouts, and also (which
  among Christians is abominable forbidden by excommunication) almost
  violent with weapons, and said he, too, had corrupted or bribed.
  So then counted to our Miguelistas other chiefs of Minuanes,
  who had participated in the gift or gifts. That some of his men
  had been paid for the war and Moreira mainly one called for in the
  next expedition to guard the baggage of the Portuguese with people.
  They had a lot of clothes, weapons, and were armed, and
  be trained with cutlass for this purpose. Out of this that Portuguese,
  trusting in this hope, erected a Fuertecillo which was to serve
  as appropriate to the real prison that had to train in the mountains
  of San Miguel, close to the Santa Maria stays, which are called
  Yacegua: but also other chiefs of the nation is excused, and that
  much advance notice to his friends what had been treaty. For browsers
  that were identified after Catholics and Christians from the
  town of San Miguel, which with The garrison was in the last terms
  of jurisdiction, were to run the earth. Recorriéronla, and told
  that did not seem any enemy, and upbraiding the same Moreira,
  afeándole the fact, confessed that he had been truly call of
  the Portuguese, with gifts and asked for things sobredichas,
  but no luck that had consented: so which he had retired, having
  the Lusitano with fury, done it many threats. This he said,
  but if it were true which said it expected to test the effect, if
  offered the Used, but then so was thought.
  
  72. Also spread the Portuguese with these few things lies against
  the Indians, and that many are primarily had happened to them,
  and many teams often were fleeing the tyranny of the PP., and
  already had and numbered a few hundred of those. Pretending
  these things In order to provoke the Spanish to return to undertake
  war, but was discovered after criminals or perpetrators
  of lie, when by the hand of the Provincial of the Province Brazil
  sent the list of Indians who lived among them: some of whom were
  married, and others called for: but had no more than 50, many
  of whom had surnames town of San Borja, but they disagreed over
  the names. Is also others, which were inserted in the list by name,
  already had returned again to the peoples. The Portuguese
  went endeavoring to persuade the Spanish these things, but the
  Indians they know others, but namely, that the Father Rabago,
  (in whom they placed the Indians in any hope of human sponsorship)
had been deprived of King's confession, which had fallen from grace,
and to over this, he was arrested, but later warned of Europe, which
was deception and lies of the Portuguese.

  
  
  73. And he ended in July, when the port of Montevideo appeared
  a commercial vessel on the 27th of July, which was bringing 150
  convicts soldiers to the castle, and 70 Missionaries Company, 40
  for the province of Chile, and 31 for ours; others remained
  in Spain, which were almost as many, with the attorney who
  resides in the Court, and takes care of businesses and Misiones
  Province. In truth it does not cause All this news is little consolation,
  especially as they news filled the prosperous province, and also
  letters announcing all welcome. It seemed that was the business
  concluded, the Court had rejected the iniquitous treaty to rejoice
  or delight in our loyalty and obedience, which had accepted the
  appeal by peoples, who commanded things were suspended. So
  he told principles: but as the sad news usually follows prosperous,
  the royal commissioners reported this business quite the opposite:
  that the war was adopted as a reference to rebels, as they said,
  which is also gave thanks to Ministers for the zeal and expense
  made for sugetar to the contumacious, that things had been said
  in favor, had out of puddles, and not the source, who had to continue
  the war and had to make more raw.

  To this end were issued new decrees and intimacy to our Prelate
  immediately, crushing havoc, and threatening to take everything
  blood and fire, but surrendered the people.
  
  74. These formal notices sent to the Governor of Concepcion, Nenguirù,
  the Curia, or Council meeting domestic, because otherwise So that
  might be suspicious issue: For this, interpose the authority
  having between them, passing the River, the intimate and enacted
  in the provinces and towns forced to move. But this, not trusting
  the people angry, and anticipating and knowing that there
  was to do another thing increase mutinous troops, he returned again
  to refer to the Curia all papers, begging the prelates
  not giving rise to the province, little appeased, even fusses
  still more, or require her head, or Governor, to exposed to real
  risk of death. At rest, neglected these threats, what had been
  expected happen.
  
  75. Meanwhile throughout August, September and October, soldiers
  recruited in the cities of Spanish and Portuguese: but in
  ours, but there was no peace and quiet, and provided that, while
  things settled down, is dispatched to scouts everywhere as in the
  past, and were with more surveillance.
  
  76. In late October, or rather at the beginning of November,
  the Governor of Buenos Aires, from the wide riverbed the river, reached
the city of Montevideo, where he was to together all the Spanish army.

  Also stated that walked towards Montevideo 200 soldiers who had
  been dispatched from the city of Corrientes, and as many of the
  Santa Fe, but if this is true or not, time will tell, that Correntinos
  the 200 had not been but 80, and that others had deserted. In
  addition, between the deserters had returned to his home
  some Abipones that the commander had brought as scouts, being very
  local scouts. Also in Santa Faith, having invited the lieutenant
  for the league to the Mocobís, refused the barbarian chieftain,
  and did not respond as such, because said - that he had not
  embraced the law of Christ to war against innocent Christians,
  and rather would favor the oppressed, unless he is prevented from
  that great river.
  
  77.

  Than to each other, that is, province of Santa Fe and Corrientes,
  is I had shot the horses, and they had lost vast fields: that everywhere,
  especially in Buenos Aires, every day they died and perished by
  hundreds, and this reason some doubted the effective progress
  of the army. No However, although it is true that the Court did
  not doubt the iniquity, and also worked in the dissolution or annulment
of covenants, however, as not to send any true and Decree deliberated
whether it would suspend or continue war, the Ministers of both courts
that are here, move more active things in the war as the Spanish with
difficulty, and almost violent, were brought to this expedition and,
as they said, were bound and constrained to it for some political
reasons alone, he proceeded slowly, or tried to go slowly.

  Therefore, being well advanced November, were still in the
  city of Montevideo, and did not know whether with sincerity or with
  bending were known here, where I was, certain notices secrets,
  they did not want anything the Spanish forces but the Indians
  were opposed, burn the fields where I had to go to them
  to give occasion to excuse the default by pastures, and back, or
  at least delayed, as he reached the Cut something true. Although
  it is doubtful, not without reason, the possibility of the
  file, because grasses mature these lands, and the straw that is
  suitable for the fire, they are not for animals, but once burned,
  as soon after and turn green again, eagerly eaten by horses and
  like greatly, so it was suspected, and not in vain, for some,
  it was ploy, and that under the pretext of bringing them fear,
  he asked for, and even help the enemy especially being so burned
  fields and plains best show the way to the travelers, when at otherwise
  would be impracticable pregnant and full of weeds.

  
  78. But as there was no doubt about preparations for the expedition,
  and took the ships from Europe, It was agreed that the province
  still unprepared to prevent it was attacked by the enemy, prepare
  things here, for defense, and lookouts with more diligence roads:
  case also seemed to be fire or burn fields.
  
  79. Consisted enough, not at first lies 1.500 were Spanish,
  and the relief of the other cities, about 2,000: that the Portuguese
  were 3.000 and therefore the total was 5.000, but both armies all
  together reach 3.000, wrote the chief of these people (the Governor
  of Montevideo, which, as was said, came in place of Buenos
  Aires, and had to take care of this business) to a Jesuit friend,
  sometimes it was stone scandal, and that is no longer in that
  city: in fact the witness is competent, it by everybody. Also
  be had by Incidentally, the Spanish army was to make the journey
  from San Felipe Castle, via straight to the headwaters of
  the Rio Black, and towards the payment of Santa Tecla, term and
  watch the Michael, and that there had to penetrate large rodeos,
  deserted by province until a fortress Portuguese Yacuy located
  on the river, which shortly before had no name, and now for
  the invasion that they were frustrated the Indians call it (but
  evil) Fort Victoria, and finally joined forces, had to walk to town
  San Angel. This was determined by the Council of both nations,
  and Although these findings seemed to the cowboys or experts
  the roads very violent, and almost impassable in execution,
  yet it was to provide all appropriate things, and fools to guard
  against efforts near misses or the Portuguese. Debalde not
  joined the captains, running and January, and although not felt
  any movement of enemy determined well in advance however,
  that all people neighboring villages gather together and come
  to the rescue. And then letters and dispatched a courier
  to the de la Concepcion and Santo Tomé, where these were to later
send to the other peoples to come closer, and verifications explorers
everywhere, mainly because I do not know the yerbales they made enemies:
I suspect that the fires that had been lest any irruption machines,
or who composed the roads.

  Then the point was for ten Johannine, and almost as
  many of San Angel, that were towards the mountains where they would
  make high, and the town of San Miguel, a captain field was on
  duty in Santa Tecla, to be warned their own state in which things
  were: it was said which menaced the enemy that part, and already
  there were two months walking, namely, from December 5.

80.
  When this time all this equipment seemed to be left in views or measures,
and partly confirming the coming of the enemy with emails everyday
of, and cures were asleep or in inaction, some people began to move
business, stating that one should not go neglected, and debian is
gather troops and dispatch them to the list terms of jurisdiction,
not to enter the enemy to remote fields of the farms or calves, and
destroying them killing, without being punished, and not block anyone.

  With got this difficulty, after many reasons exposed: to wit, the
  army would be late for leave the meeting from almost 100
  miles away, if then began to gather troops, when the enemy undertaken,
  that the enemy could tread it all, and actual Portuguese would
  walk straight path through the rooms that would destroy,
  they would close the communication to the Indians, and would take
  away the food, the lack of which is already beginning to feel, and
  finally it's always better to attack the enemy first that being
  attacked him. For these reasons he finally succeeded in dispatched
  nine post or posts, which everywhere alert and inclined to
  join the Confederates. Also the captain of the Concepcion was
  already a party of 150 men in their stays confined to those of
  San Miguel, and to complete this item is retted another 60 of the
  people. Put in motion to the auxiliary squadrons, which were
  to come from Santana villages of San Carlos and Los Angeles,
  60, des Martyrs, 60, of San Javier, and Santa Maria, 30. Suddenly
  arranged on that side of things, put the captain who had
  it removed shortly before, having returned to home its people,
  who were scattered throughout various peoples, it was believed
  that the Council had acted this home moving, then surti good effect.

81.
  On the other peoples of Uruguay, such as warnings that the post
  shortly before and already had sent back, who had not rumor,
  nor felt the enemy were hurrying to wait the armies of other
  nations. But, to January 20 was unexpectedly mail, which warned
  that the day 16 of month in the headwaters of Black River, that
  part which is a narrow entrance, between the Black and Yacuy rivers,
  in land San Miguel, which entrance or door of the earth called
  Ibiroqué Indians, had appeared to the Spanish army when least
  expected, that having seen five explorers, had confessed that they
  came to Spanish 2.000 wait till the Portuguese.
 </suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>