<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document00669</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>24068</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24582</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Mas viendo que todo era en vano, tomó la determinacion
de marcharse sin el consentimiento de su madre, sin que llegase á oidos de su padre, y si era
posible, sin que se enterasen mas que los conductores de su carruaje. A aquellas personas en
quien tenia depositada su confianza dió las órdenes oportunas para que á la mayor brevedad
preparasen los útiles mas necesarios de marcha. Todo se encontraba ya dispuesto; pero quiso
la casualidad fuese avisada Doña Isabel de esta resolucion inesperada, por lo cual mandó inmediatamente
á Don Juan de Fonseca, obispo de Córdoba, para que la suplicase en su nombre no marchara. A
punto de subir al carruage estaba ya Doña Juana cuando llegó el enviado de la reina. Un momento
despues no la hubiera encontrado. Mandó al instante D. Juan de Fonseca se retirase el carruage,
y en seguida se fue á ver á la archiduquesa, á la cual encontró ya á la puerta del palacio
de la Mota, preparada á marchar en trage de camino. Con el acatamiento que requeria su posicion,
la hizo sabedora de la órden de la reina Católica, intimándola á que volviese á su aposento,
mas la archiduquesa no se hallaba ya en el caso de guardar consideraciones de ningun género,
asi es que no contestó una palabra; en el calor de su vehemente pasion no encontraba mas que
misterios, agentes secretos de su rival y de su infiel esposo, que no tenian otro entretenimiento
que retardar su partida. El obispo de Córdoba apuraba en vano sus instancias aun presentándole
á cada palabra el nombre de su madre, pero ya cansada de escuchar desobedeció la órden y los
ruegos de este, y preparándose á salir: «Dejadme, dijo, es un deber sagrado el que no me detenga
á nada en este viage.» Entonces el obispo mandó á cerrar la puerta, dejando de la parte de
dentro á la desgraciada Doña Juana.

Viéndose encerrada esta señora llegó al colmo de su desesperacion, y empezó á proferir tanto
denuesto y tan insolentes frases, que D. Juan de Fonseca se fue sumamente irritado, á pesar
de haberlo mandado llamar á la archiduquesa por medio de su gentil-hombre de cámara, D. Miguel
de Ferrera. No quiso volver, sino que tomó el camino de Segovia, donde á la sazon se hallaba
la reina Doña Isabel.

Llegado que hubo D. Juan de Fonseca á donde estaba la reina le dió parte de todo lo ocurrido
con la princesa; Doña Isabel, á pesar de lo débil que se hallaba y de la multitud de negocios
que le proporcionaba su alta posicion, se puso en camino para la Mota de Medina del Campo,
presumiéndose que tal vez su presencia haria desistir á su hija de un proyecto para ella tan
sensible. Despues de los cumplimeintos de costumbre y á los cuales no prestaba atencion esta,
la prometió que muy pronto iria á reunirse con su marido. «Nunca quiera Dios, decia la reina,
que mi voluntad ni la del rey vuestro padre sea la de apartaros del lado de vuestro esposo,
y si otra cosa sobre este particular se han atrevido á deciros, despreciadla.»

Estas y otras razones le esponia Isabel, y ella en su frenesí, no respondió mas que: «Son inútiles
los ruegos del mundo entero: no cejaré ni un ápice... El padre de mis hijos!... yo quiero verlo»...

Pronunciaba estas palabras, y anegada en lágrimas, se arrojaba al suelo, rechazando los cuidados
que todos trataban de prodigarle.

Terminadas ya las Córtes de Aragon, no creyó prudente el rey Fernando, detener por mas tiempo
su viage, porque ya era sabedor de lo que sucedia con su hija, cuya enagenacion mental se fomentaba
cada dia, y era muy posible que el detenerla mas, hubiera sido causa de declarar su locura.

Premeditando esto mismo, mandó aprestar una armada en el puerto de Laredo concediendo al mismo
tiempo á su hija, el permiso para que practicase su espedicion á Flandes.

Los trasportes de alegria que esperimentó Doña Juana con la última voluntad de su padre, son
indescriptibles, y pocos dias despues se preparaba á hacer su deseada espedicion.

                    CAPITULO III.

Del mal temporal que fue causa para que el viage de Doña Juana se hiciese mas largo, y de la
entrevista que tuvo con la querida de Felipe el Hermoso.

El dia 15 de marzo de 1504, se dirigió Doña Juana acompañada de sus padres para el punto donde
se iba á embarcar (Laredo), pero todo parecia venirle en contra, todo parecia revelarse á su
voluntad. Un recio y continuo temporal impidió poder darse á la vela. Esto hacia crecer los
tormentos de la princesa, y revestirla mucho mas de indignacion, porque todo parecia combinarse
para evitar la reunion con su esposo. Dos meses tuvo que residir en Laredo, que fueron los
que duró la tempestad; dos meses que fueron dos siglos, si se atiende la disposicion en que
se hallaba esta señora, y que agravaron muchísimo sus constantes padecimientos. A mediados
de abril logró hacerse á la vela, llegando en nueve dias felizmente á Vergas, distante tres
leguas y media de Brujas.

En este punto la estaba esperando su esposo, el cual manifestó un indecible júbilo al volverla
á abrazar; y ella, segun el cariño que este la pintaba, pareció completamente olvidada de un
resentimiento tan justo. A pesar de darse los dos mútuas pruebas de amor y contento, abrigaban
ambos fatales y mortificadoras pasiones; el archiduque, por el vehemente amor con la camarista;
y por los mas rabiosos celos, Doña Juana. Pero vivian con la esperanza el primero de que jamás
esta se enteraria de sus amores: y la segunda, de vengarse de una mujer que tan grandes sinsabores
la habia hecho sufrir.

Desde Brujas se trasladaron á Bruselas y en este punto fijaron su residencia por entonces.

¿Quién puede ocultarse lo suficiente de las investigadoras pesquisas de una mujer perspicaz?
Esta reflexion debió hacer Felipe el Hermoso. ¿Quién puede ocultarse tampoco de las escudriñadoras
miradas de los dependientes de un palacio, donde es una especie de comercio los chismes y enredos,
dando publicidad en su provecho á todos los defectos de sus soberanos?

Grande paz pareció reinar al principio desde la llegada de Doña Juana; el archiduque hacia
por no dar á conocer á nadie lo que ocupaba su imaginacion, disimulando en cuanto podia el
amor de su rubia, pero se engañaba; ni aun sus pasos mas recónditos se escapaban á la penetracion
de su esposa. Los mismos palaciegos daban parte diario á su señor de si lo celaba su esposa;
y estos mismos palaciegos cercioraban á la archiduquesa detalladamente de cuanto podia contribuir
á irritarla mas. Por uno de estos llegó á saber que una de las cosas que mas habian encantado
á su esposo de la camarista, era su hermosísima poblada y rubia cabellera. Mas no contento
aun con esta declaracion, le indicó los sitios y horas donde comunmente se daban las citas.

Con la relacion anterior llegó á agotarse completamente la paciencia de la archiduquesa, porque
acabó de conocer, que habia empleado en vano todos los recursos que le proporcionara su acendrado
amor, para ver si de esta suerte hacia desaparecer de su marido una pasion que ella jamás creyó
arraigada, porque la creia un capricho. Sus celos, refrenados por algun tiempo, eran desde
este dia un violento frenesí que aumentaba sus padecimientos. Alguna que otra vez ya habian
mediado varias palabras entre los esposos, pero el archiduque, muy enamorado de su rubia, hacia
por disculparse, practicándolo con la mayor sangre fria. Estas cosas era imposible durasen
asi largo tiempo, porque ni el uno podia satisfacer su amor, ni el otro soportar tantas humillaciones
y desvío, y tampoco porque las pasiones de ánimo no se pueden contener.

Una escena terrible, por un descuido de Felipe, tuvo lugar. Le sorprendió su esposa con la
querida... Grande fue el escándalo que circuló por toda la Córte, y grande fue el trabajo que
le costó contener la furia de su mancillada esposa, porque esta ya no pensaba mas que en la
venganza. ¡Y cosa admirable en esta mujer!... De esta venganza no queria fuese participe su
esposo, pues aunque habia llegado á notar el despego y descaro con que solia tratarla, no obstante
lo idolatraba de todo corazon. Su furia era espresamente dedicada para su adversaria, para
aquella indigna mujer que le habia arrebatado lo que mas adoraba en la tierra. Y gracias que
la timidez de abandonar del todo el amor de su marido, la reprimia en parte.

Ya era testigo el palacio de Bruselas de los descompasados gritos, repetidas contiendas, y
descompuestas palabras de los jóvenes príncipes, sin embargo de poner cuanto estaba de su parte
por disimular el archiduque, para evitar los escándalos.

Los celos habituales de la infanta daban orígen á que no cesase de acechar el momento de realizar
su venganza, mas llegó por desgracia. Un dia ¡dia fatal! que pasando su errante mirada por
todos los objetos que la circundaban, se encontró con la camarista, echó mano de unas bien
afiladas tijeras, de que siempre iba armada, se lanzó sobre ella cual el águila sobre su presa,
y antes de que su contraria lo hubiera podido evitar, ya la habia despojado de su dorada cabellera.
No satisfecha aun, la llenó de contusiones y arañazos, y podemos asegurar que si los gritos
de la camarista, no hubiesen hecho acudir al lugar de la sangrienta escena á todos los dependientes
del palacio, y hasta á su mismo marido, era probable hubiese acabado con la que habia sido
causa de sus sufrimientos.

Felipe, viendo despojada á su querida del objeto que mas lo entusiasmara, se llenó de indignacion:
y fueron tantos los improperios, tantas las palabras ofensivas é insultantes que dirigió á
su esposa, que no se le hubieran dicho iguales á la muger mas despreciable de la sociedad.

El haber visto que Felipe la trataba de aquella manera, contribuyó en gran modo á trastornar
completamente su juicio. Jamás podia creer Doña Juana semejante trato en su esposo.

La escandalosa escena que acabamos de pintar, no tardó en llegar á oidos de la reina Isabel,
y tuvo tan gran sentimiento, que fue la causa de que se agravase mas su enfermedad. Sin embargo,
procuró por todos los medios que estuvieron á su alcance, introducir la paz entre sus hijos,
ni siéndola posible lograrlo por algun tiempo: la archiduquesa tenia una herida que no era
fácil cicatrizar. Por fin, alcanzaron sus sùplicas hacer la reconciliacion. Se unieron los
esposos, pero no por esto recobró Doña Juana su tranquilidad.

Entretanto la salud de Doña Isabel decaia por instantes. Sus padecimientos eran tan continuos,
que ya no se dudaba de su pronta muerte. Uno de los principales personajes de la córte, única
heredera del reino de Castilla á su hija Doña Juana, y en defecto de esta á D. Cárlos, su nieto;
pero advirtiendo que si la primera se hallaba imposibilitada, y Cárlos no tenia veinte años,
gobernase D. Fernando, hasta que aquel llegara á esta edad.

Efectivamente, el dia 26 de noviembre de 1504 falleció en Medina del Campo la reina Isabel
la Católica, y al siguiente dia ordenó D. Fernando proclamar por reina de España á su hija
la archiduquesa de Austria. Las Córtes verificadas en Toro el 11 de enero de 1508, fueron las
primeras que juraron á Doña Juana por reina propietaria de los vastos dominios de España. No
pudieron por entonces los archiduques abandonar á Flandes, tanto por los innumerables asuntos
pendientes en él, como por el avanzado estado de preñez de la reina; habiendo nacido á poco
tiempo la princesa Doña María.

Restablecida Doña Juana de su parto, pusiéronse en camino; mas un fuerte temporal, los hizo
arribar á Inglaterra, en cuyo reino fueron perfectamente recibidos. Pocos dias despues partieron
con direccion á España, llegando el 26 de abril de 1506 á la Coruña; donde esperaba la mayor
parte de la grandeza á recibirlos y rendir un justo homenaje á sus nuevos monarcas. A su paso
por Valladolid fueron jurados, y alli disfrutaron de las fiestas que habian prevenido en su
obsequio.

Parecia estar en esta época sumamente aliviada Doña Juana, no tratando mas que de complacer
á su esposo en todo, y dejándole gobernar el reino á su gusto. Pero ¡cuán poco le duró esta
felicidad! Asi que se concluyeron las Córtes de Valladolid, determinaron recorrer las principales
capitales de España para darse á conocer, porque asi lo exigian de todas partes. Empezaron
su carrera por Burgos; pero ¡oh desgracia! En una de las tardes que salian á pasear, se acaloró
tanto D. Felipe en una partida de pelota, que le sobrevino una pulmonía, de cuyas resultas
fue víctima á los seis dias, dejando embarazada á Doña Juana de seis meses. Falleció Felipe
el Hermoso el dia 29 de setiembre de 1506, cuando contaba apenas veinte y ocho años.

Tal fue el poderoso influjo que obró en la imaginacion de la nueva reina la inesperada muerte
de su esposo, que muchos dias estaba fuera de sí, y encerrada en el aposento que á ella le
parecia mas lóbrego y triste. Durante este enagenamiento, se habian hecho los funerales, y
por consiguiente el cadáver del monarca sepultado en la cartuja de Miraflores. En cuanto esto
llegó á su noticia, mandó se lo trajesen en una caja bien dispuesta y embetunada, porque no
queria vivir lejos de él. Asi se practicó, y no permitia que nadie entrase, llevándose los
dias y las noches contemplando los restos del ídolo de su amor.[*] Ninguna clase de ruegos
la hacian desistir de alejarse del cadáver. En vano eran las amonestaciones del cardenal Cisneros;
inútiles tambien las de las damas y principales personajes, advirtiéndole la necesidad de ocuparse
de los negocios del reino. Cerróse por dentro de la habitacion y mandó hacer una ventanita
para que por alli pudiesen mandarla algunos alimentos.

[*Véase el grabado que vá al frente de esta historia.]

Muchas veces iban los grandes á hacerla saber la alteracion en que se hallaba España, y contestaba
que si su hijo estaba en disposicion, viniese á gobernarla, y que si no, su padre; que ella
tenia otros deberes mas sagrados que cumplir como viuda.

Varios de los personajes creian, al oirla hablar con cordura algunas veces, si la querida de
su esposo habria usado de algunos maleficios para hacerla padecer tan terriblemente. ¡Qué credulidad
la de aquella época! No trascurrió mucho tiempo sin que á la misma reina Doña Juana le pareciera
insoportable aquella existencia; y poco despues llamó al cardenal Cisneros, haciéndole saber
que no podia vivir por mas tiempo en la capital donde habia muerto su marido; pero el cardenal
queria suspender por entonces su determinacion, á causa de hallarse en un estado avanzado de
preñez; mas como la voluntad de Doña Juana fue siempre decidida, no se atrevio á oponerse á
su mandato. Se trasladó la córte á Valladolid, por órden espresa de la reina.

Haciendo jornadas muy cortas salió de Burgos el 20 de diciembre de 1506, acompañada de un crecido
número de vasallos con hachas encendidas, muchos frailes franciscanos tambien con luces, el
prior de la cartuja y algunos monges que decian misas diarias por el alma del soberano, cuya
caja iba en medio de esta fúnebre comitiva, seguida del coche de la desdichada Doña Juana y
de las damas y caballeros de su palacio. De esta manera marcharon hasta llegar á Torquemada,
donde la reina no quiso pasar adelante, alojándose en casa de un clérigo, y esponiendo que
el estado de su salud no la permitia seguir. El 14 de enero de 1507 parió en este pueblo á
la infanta Doña Catalina.

Triste y desconsolador fue este año para España. A consecuencia de una miseria y escasez grandes,
se desarrolló una peste que causó innumerables estragos. ¿Y se creerá que á pesar de ser el
pueblo de Torquemada uno de los mas invadidos por la epidemia, no bastasen los ruegos del cardenal
á que continuara la reina su camino? Muchas y muy reiteradas fueron las instancias que á este
le costó, hasta lograr que á fines de abril se volviese á emprender la marcha con el mismo
aparato que al principio; pero pronto se cansó de viajar. Al llegar á Hornillos distante dos
leguas de Torquemada, quiso fijar su residencia en él, esponiendo viviria con mas comodidad
que en una grande poblacion. De manera que volvió á encerrarse en este pequeño pueblo con el
inanimado cuerpo de su esposo, no cesando de hablarle, ya con cariño, ya con quejas, ya con
reconvenciones, que aumentaban mas su incurable locura.

Todo seguia de este modo, hasta que la dieron noticias de la venida de su padre á España. Esta
noticia la recibió con gran placer, porque al momento manifestó deseos de salir á encontrarse
con D. Fernando, en Castilla, advirtierdo que habia de ser en cortas jornadas y con el mismo
cortejo fúnebre. Inútilmente se cansaba el regente del reino, arzobispo de Toledo, para hacerla
viajar de dia, sin el cuerpo de su esposo; todo era en vano: de suerte que no habia otro recurso
que repetir todas las noches el entierro. Asi caminaron hasta entrar en Tórtoles, poblacion
donde tuvo su padre el gusto de abrazarla. Pero cuál fue la sorpresa de D. Fernando al encontrar
á su hija mas querida en aquella situacion; aquellos ojos desencajados, aquel rostro cadavérico,
y aquella errante mirada! Cuando se le venia á la memoria lo que habia sido causa de que su
hija estuviera en aquel estado, la pena lo ahogaba, y gruesas lágrimas surcaban sus mejillas.
Doña Juana estaba inmóvil: Llorais, padre de mi corazon? le dijo: vuestra hija no puede ya
imitaros. Cuando sorprendí á la querida de mi esposo, se me agotaron las lágrimas. ¡Considerad
cuál seria mi tristeza!

Doña Juana habia llegado al último grado de locura, estaba enteramente loca; mas sin embargo
era la reina propietaria de España y su nombre y consentimiento eran necesarios para dar algun
carácter á los actos del gobierno. Esta consideracion movió al rey Católico á entrar en algunas
consultas con su hija para el mejor arreglo de los negocios y volver otra vez á gobernar los
dominios de España. Doña Juana, por su parte, admitió sin réplica alguna cuanto le propuso
su padre, poniendo solamente una condicion, que la habian de dejar permanecer en la villa de
Arcos, «en completa libertad, sin tener que intervenir en otro negocio, que pasar los dias
que la restaban de esta vida, al lado del cuerpo de su esposo.» Mucho trabajaron por hacerla
variar de este pensamiento, pero siendo todo inútil se le concedió el permiso, mandando prepararle
una casa en Arcos, digna de la persona que la iba á habitar.

Mas de año y medio residió Doña Juana en la villa de Arcos sin que se hubiese mejorado en nada
su locura. Era de ver, segun afirman algunos, las animadas conversaciones que esta infeliz
señora, tenia con el cadáver de su esposo; conversaciones que aumentaban mas su delirio, y
que en lugar de aliviarla, la agravaban. «Por qué no me respondeis, Felipe? le decia: callais!...
todavia me sereis infiel!...» Estas palabras proferia á su marido, y otras que causaria lástima
escucharlas.

Desde Santa María del Campo le escribió D. Fernando á su hija advirtiéndole de la necesidad
que tenia de marcharse á Tordesillas y haciéndola saber era poblacion mas salubre que la villa
de Arcos, y que por consecuencia habia determinado, se pusiese en camino para este punto. Doña
Juana, se encontraba perfectamente, segun la contestaba, en Arcos. De manera que viendo el
rey Católico que su hija no accedia á sus súplicas tomó la determinacion, de ir en busca de
ella para ver si con su presencia lograba lo acompañase hasta Tordesillas. Asi lo hizo D. Fernando
habiendo podido con el influjo que ejercia sobre su hija hacer se marchase á dicho punto, pero
viajando con el mismo aparato que en las otras espediciones. Sea el haber mudado de temperamento,
sea que el viaje no fue de su agrado, lo cierto es que la reina Doña Juana estaba mas furiosa
cada vez, y tomó mas incremento su ya incurable enfermedad.

El anciano Luis Ferrer era el que estaba encargado del cuidado de Doña Juana, y al cual esta
no podia ver; por eso encontraba en ella una oposicion enorme á todo lo que la encargaba hiciera,
complaciéndose en ejecutarlo al contrario. Si la rogaba, por ejemplo, se acostase en su cama,
lo hacia en el suelo; si disponia que se trasladase á otra habitacion mas decente y ventilada,
cerraba con mas fuerza los cerrojos de la en que estaba. Cuando hacia frio, desechaba las pieles
y objetos de abrigo que le proporcionaban, y cuanto mas la suplicaba Luis Ferrer se vistiese
y asease, con mas empeño andaba sucia y mal vestida. Poco tiempo despues se le puso en la cabeza
la mania de no comer ni beber; y hubo ocasion de que pasasen tres dias sin tomar nada; hasta
que acosada por el hambre, tomaba algo, empeñándose que los platos donde le mandaban las viandas
no saliesen de su habitacion; de suerte que estos objetos sucios con otros, daban un olor insoportable
á aquella morada, é imposible por tanto de aguantarlo. Momentos habia en que despues de un
gran delirio, gozaba de alguna razon, y se lamentaba de que habian arrancado la corona de sus
sienes, y no contentos sus enemigos con un rapto de este género, la habian sepultado en un
calabozo tan hediondo y custodiada por un carcelero tan despreciable.

Estas palabras llegaron con la velocidad del relámpago á oidos del Católico D. Fernando, asi
es que al siguiente año de 1510, cuando pasaba para las Córtes de Monzon, hizo por visitarla,
y cerciorado de todo lo que ocurria reunió un consejo de los grandes para deliberar sobre el
método que se debia observar en adelante con su hija, porque sabia que la presencia de D. Luis
Ferrer la martirizaba; del consejo salió, que despues de haberla provisto de todo lo necesario
de aseo, ropas y alimentos, se eligiesen doce señoras para que cuidasen continuamente de ella,
y cada una se quedara una noche en vela para obligarla á vestirse, desnudarse y mudarse de
camisa, aun en contra de su voluntad. Veinte dias estuvo el rey Católico acompañando á Doña
Juana, en los cuales estuvo menos mal; pero despues que se la obligaba á ejecutar lo pactado
por su padre, se apoderaba de ella una furia tan grande, que nadie podia permanecer á su lado.
Mas previsor el cardenal Cisneros que los grandes de que se habia compuesto el consejo, creyó
oportuno jubilar á D. Luis Ferrer, porque opinaba que tal vez nombrando á otro lo pasaria mejor
Doña Juana; asi lo hizo sustituyéndolo con Don Fernando Ducos de Estrada. Este caballero fue
tal la habilidad que mostró en el desempeño de su encargo, que á poco tiempo logró que comiese
y bebiese, que durmiera en su lecho, que se aseara y vistiera, y hasta que mudara de habitacion,
porque ya la suya no era mas que un fétido muladar. Se llegó á fortalecer su físico, porque
con su habitual finura y modales, logró este caballero el que fuese á misa y que asistiese
á varios actos religiosos.

Ya sus accesos de locura eran menos constantes, asi es que determinaron apartar de su vista
el féretro de su esposo, siendo conducido algunos dias despues á Granada, y aunque fue grande
su exasperacion cuando lo echó de ver, pudo al fin D. Fernando Ducos de Estrada tranquilizarla.
Pero no se crea que por este llegó á ponerse buena del todo; jamás esta infeliz reina llegó
á recobrar su perdida calma. Sin embargo, el Católico rey le escribió á Estrada, dàndole las
mas afectuosas y repetidas gracias por el servicio que habia hecho á su hija.

En esta época no habia ya una sola persona que no estuviese enterada de la enfermedad de la
reina Doña Juana; pero no obstante, conservaban alguna esperanza de alivio, hija mas bien del
deseo de sus súbditos, que de la posibilidad.

En las Córtes que se celebraron en Valladolid por enero de 1518, se decretó que si en algun
tiempo la reina Doña Juana se hallaba en disposicion de mandar los vastos dominios de España,
cesase de su gobernacion el Católico rey D. Fernando; y que Doña Juana fuese la soberana absoluta.

                    CAPITULO IV.

De las disensiones que habia en España, y muerte de Doña Juana.

Eran muchas las disensiones que habia en España con varios partidos que empezaron á formarse
unos á favor de Doña Juana, otros al de su hijo D. Cárlos, otros al de su padre, y algunos
otros que deseaban viniese á gobernar el emperador Maximiliano I, su suegro, asi es que ya
en 1520 peleaba la España por su libertad agonizante. Los partidarios de Cárlos V levantaron
en Castilla el pendon de la independencia, y los gefes de unos y otros partidos para dar valor
á sus determinaciones acudian á Doña Juana. El cardenal Cisneros, entonces regente y gobernador
del reino, fue el primero que determinó apelar á la reina para ver si se podia salir de las
apuradas circunstancias en que los partidos habian colocado á las provincias y particularmente
á Valladolid.

Cuantos iban á tratar sobre asuntos tan delicados con la reina, salian sumamente descontentos
por no obtener nunca una contestacion digna de aplacar los ánimos de los revolucionarios. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03264</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>6185</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22320</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> But seeing that all was in vain, made the determination
to leave without the consent of his mother, without reaching the ears of his father, and if possible,
without them knowing more than his chariot drivers. To those people who had placed their trust
gave the necessary orders for as soon as prepare the tools needed to start over. Everything
was already prepared, but did chance Isabel was advised of this resolution unexpectedly, which
immediately sent Don Juan de Fonseca, bishop of Cordoba, that the plea in his name does not go away. A
about to board the carriage was already Doña Juana when it was sent to the Queen. A moment
then failed to find. Sent instantly D. Juan de Fonseca to retire the carriage, and then went to
see the Archduchess, to which he found already at the door of the palace de la Mota, prepared to
march in costume on the road. That required compliance with its position, made her knowledgeable
of the order of the Catholic Queen, intimidated to return to his apartment, but the Archduchess
was not already the case to keep considerations of any kind, so do not said a word, in the heat
of his fiery passion was no more than mysteries, secret agents from rival and her unfaithful
husband, who had no other entertainment to delay their departure. The Bishop of Cordoba hurried
in vain even presenting its instances at every word the name of his mother, but already tired of
hearing disobeyed the order and prayers of this, and preparing to leave: "Let me, he said, is
a sacred duty that I will not stop Anything in this journey. "Then the bishop sent to close
the door, leaving the part of in at the unhappy Juana.

Seeing this lady was confined to the height of his despair, and began
to utter both and that insolent insult phrases, D. Juan de Fonseca
was extremely angry, in spite of having been summoned to the Archduchess
through his camera gentleman, D. Miguel Ferrera.

He would not return, but took the path of Segovia, where he then was Queen Isabel.

When he came D. Juan de Fonseca to where she was the queen gave him part of what has happened with
the princess Isabella, in spite of what was weak and many businesses that gave him his high
position, he set out for Mota in Medina del Campo, presumed that
perhaps his presence would give up his daughter as a project for her
sensitive.

After the usual Fulfilment and to which no attention is paid, promised it would go very soon
to join her husband. "You never want to God, he said the queen, my will or that the king your
father is that of you from the side of your husband, and if anything else on this subject
have dared to say, despreciadla. "

These and other reasons we esponia Isabel, and she in her frenzy, but that did not respond: "They
are useless the prayers of the world: I will not give one iota ... The father of my children!
... I want to see "...

Spoke, and in tears, threw herself on the floor, refusing care all treated to lavish.

Completed and the Cortes of Aragon, did not think it prudent to King
Ferdinand, stop for longer his journey, because it was knowing what
was happening with her daughter, whose mental alienation fostered
every day, and it was quite possible that the detainees, had been
due to declare their folly.

Premeditating this very reason, make available a fleet commanded the
Laredo port of giving the same time his daughter, permission to practice
his expedition to Flanders.

The transports of joy that undergoes Doña Juana with his father's last wishes are indescribable,
and few days later he prepared to make your desired expedition.

                    

CHAPTER III.

The bad weather that was cause for the journey of Doña Juana is made more long, and interview he
had with the mistress of Philip the Fair.

On March 15, 1504, Juana went accompanied by their parents to the point where went to boarding (Laredo),
but everything seemed to come against all seemed to reveal his will. A strong and continuing
to be stopped temporarily sail. This to grow torments of the princess, and take many more of
indignation, because everything seemed to combine to prevent the reunion with her husband.
Two months had to reside in Laredo, which were the the storm lasted, and two months they were
two centuries, if we see the disposition in which was this lady,
and greatly aggravated their ongoing suffering.

Mid April did set sail, arriving in nine days happily to Dicks, a distance of three leagues and
a half of Bruges.

At this point she was expecting her husband, who expressed an unspeakable joy as he turned to embrace,
and she, according to the affection that the painting, he seemed completely oblivious of a so
just resentment. Although the two mutually give evidence of love and happy, entertained both fatal
and mortifications passions, the Archduke, for the passionate love
affair with the maid; and the more rabid jealousy, Doña Juana.

But lived with the hope that the first ever this would know of his
love: and second, to avenge a woman as big disappointments had made
it suffer.

Moved from Bruges to Brussels and here took up residence at the time.

Who can hide enough of the researchers insightful investigations of a woman? This reflection
should make Philip the Fair. Who can not hide from the scrutinizing looks dependents of a
palace, where trade is a kind of gossip and tangles, giving publicity to their advantage to all the
faults of their rulers?

Great peace seemed to reign at first since the arrival of Doña Juana, the Archduke to not disclose
to anyone what was in his imagination, dissembling as could the love of her blonde, but he
was wrong, not even his most hidden steps escaped the penetration
of his wife.

Palace gave them to his master daily report if jealous of his wife; and these same palace to satisfy
themselves as Archduchess detail could help to irritate it more. For one of these came to know that
one of the things that I had loved his maid's husband was her beautiful blond hair populated. But
not content even with this statement, he indicated the places and times where it commonly
gave appointments.

With the previous relationship came to completely exhausted the patience of the Archduchess,
because had fully recognized that he had employed in vain all the resources to provide its unblemished
love to see if this sort to disappear from her husband a passion
she never thought rooted, because he believed a whim.

His jealousy, restrained for some time, were from This day a violent frenzy that increased
their suffering. Occasionally they had already mediated several words between the spouses, but
the Archduke, very in love with his blonde, to yourselves, practicing with the greatest coolness.
These things it was impossible lasted so long, because no one could meet his love, and the
other suffered such humiliation and diversion, and also because the passions of mind can not be contained.

A
terrible scene, through an oversight of Philip, took place. He surprised his wife with dear
... Great was the scandal that circulated throughout the Court, and great was the work cost
him the fury of his wife tarnished because this was not thinking
more than in the revenge.

And something admirable about this woman! ... This revenge was involved did not want his husband,
as though he had come to notice the indifference and disdain that used to treat, however idolized
him wholeheartedly.

His anger was expressly dedicated to her opponent, to outraged that woman who had taken what most
loved on earth. And thanks to the timidity of abandoning all the love of her husband, partly
repressed.

It was seen the palace in Brussels on simply out cries, repeated contentions, and broken words of the
young princes, but as I was putting on his part to hide the archduke, to avoid scandal.

The usual jealous princess who gave rise to not cease to haunt the time of revenge, but unfortunately
arrived.

One day fatal day! that moving your eyes from wandering all the objects that surrounded, he found
the maid, he picked up a well- sharp scissors, I always was armed, she was launched on which
the eagle on its prey, and before her opponent would have been avoided,
and had been stripped of his golden hair.

Not satisfied yet, filled her with bruises and scratches, and we can assure that if the screams
the maid, had not been visiting the site of the bloody scene to all
dependents the palace, and even to the same husband, it was likely
he had killed the she had been cause of their suffering.

Felipe, seeing his beloved stripped of the object that most excites you, filled with indignation:
and were so many insults, so many offensive and insulting words directed to his wife, who
had said he was not equal to the most despised woman in society.

Having seen that Felipe was in this way, contributed a great way to disrupt full trial. Juana could
never believe such treatment in her husband.

The shocking scene you just painted, he soon reached the ears of Queen Elizabeth, and had such
a great feeling that was the cause of his illness was further aggravated.

However, sought by all means at its disposal, to introduce peace among their children, not
be so possible to achieve for some time: the Archduchess had a wound that was not easy to
heal. Finally, they reached their pleas to reconciliation. Joined husbands, but not so Juana
regained peace of mind.

Meanwhile Isabel's health waned by the minute. His sufferings were so continuous no longer doubted
his early death.

One of the main characters of the court, only Crown of Castile to his daughter Juana, and failing
this to D. Charles, his grandson; but warning that if the first was prevented, and Charles did not
have twenty years govern D. Fernando, until he came to this age.

Indeed, on 26 November 1504 Medina del Campo died in Queen Elizabeth Catholic, and the next
day ordered D. Fernando proclaimed by Queen of Spain to his daughter
Archduchess of Austria.

The Court shall in Toro January 11, 1508, were First they swore to Queen Juana by owner of
vast estates in Spain. No could then leave the Archduke of Flanders, both for the many issues
pending therein, for the advanced state of pregnancy of the queen being born by little time by Princess
Mary.

Juana reset your delivery, they stood in the way, but a heavy storm, he made arrival to England,
whose kingdom was well received. A few days after split with direction to Spain, arriving on
April 26, 1506 La Coruna, where he expected most part of the greatness
to receive and pay a fitting tribute to their new monarch.

On their way Valladolid were sworn in, and there enjoyed the festivities that had prevented its
gift.

He seemed extremely relieved at this time Doña Juana, no more than trying to please to her husband
in everything, and leaving him to rule the kingdom to his taste. But how little it lasted this
happiness! So that concluded the Cortes of Valladolid, determined through the main capital
of Spain to become known, because so required everywhere. Began Burgos his race, but unfortunately
oh! In one afternoon they went for a walk, heated up therefore D. Felipe in a game of ball, which
he suffered pneumonia, whose result was subjected to six days, leaving Juana pregnant six months.
Felipe died Beautiful day on September 29, 1506, when he was only twenty-eight years.

Such was the powerful influence that worked in the imagination of
the new Queen's unexpected death her husband, that many days was beside
himself, and locked in the room that she looked more gloomy and sad.

During this alienating, they had made the funeral and therefore the king's body buried in the Charterhouse
of Miraflores. Once this came to his notice, sent it bring in a clearly arranged and bituminized,
because I wanted to live away from him.

So was performed, and not allow anyone to enter, carrying the days and nights looking at the
remnants of the idol of his love. [*] No kind of prayers made her withdraw away from the body. In vain
were the warnings of Cardinal Cisneros; useless against those of women and main characters, noting
the need to address business of the kingdom. Remained closed from inside the room and ordered
a window for which there could send some food.

[* See the engraving that goes in front of this story.]

Many times it would great to know that the alteration was Spain, and answered if your child was ready,
came to rule, and if not, his father, that she had other the most sacred duties to fulfill
as a widow.

Several of the characters believed, to hear her talk to sanity sometimes, if the mistress of
her husband would have used some spells to make her suffer so terribly. What credulity of
the time! Not long before no deviation to the same Queen Juana will appear unbearable that
existence, and shortly after called Cardinal Cisneros, informing
him I could not live any longer in the capital where her husband was
dead, but the Cardinal I wanted to suspend his determination then,
on account of being in an advanced state of pregnancy, but the will
of Doña Juana was always determined, dared not oppose its mandate.

The court moved to Valladolid, by order of Queen expresses.

Using very short days left Burgos on 20 December 1506, accompanied by an increased number of subjects
with lighted torches, many Franciscan friars also with lights, Prior of the Carthusian monks
who were saying and some daily Masses for the soul of the sovereign, whose carton was in the
midst of this funeral procession, followed by car and unhappy Juana Ladies and gentlemen of
the palace. Thus movement until Torquemada where the queen would not go on, staying at the
home of a cleric, and exposes that health status not allowed to continue. On January 14, 1507
gave birth to this town The Infanta Doña Catalina.

Sad and heartbreaking was this year for Spain. A consequence of poverty and lack large developed
a fever that caused innumerable damage. "And you believe that in spite of being the Torquemada
people one of the most invaded by the epidemic were not enough the entreaties of Cardinal Queen
to continue its path? Were many and repeated instances that to this cost, to make late April to
return to starting out with the same device at first, but soon tired of traveling. On arriving at
two distant Plates Torquemada leagues, he wanted to take up residence in it, would live with
more comfort exposes in a large population. So he returned to shut himself up in a small village
with lifeless body of her husband, not ceasing to speak, and with affection, and with complaints,
and with counterclaims, which further increase their incurable madness.

Everything remained so until the news gave her father's coming to Spain. This news was received
with great pleasure, because at the time expressed a desire to find out with D. Fernando, in Castile,
advirtierdo which was to be in short stages and with the same funeral
procession.

Unnecessarily tired ruler of the kingdom, archbishop of Toledo, to make day travel without the
body of her husband, all was in vain, so that there was no other resource repeat every night burial.
So they walked to enter Tórtoles, population where his father was pleased to embrace. But what
was the surprise of D. Fernando to find his dearest daughter in that situation, those wild eyes,
his face cadaverous and that wandering eye! When it came to mind was what had caused his daughter
was in that state, it choked off, and big tears streaked her cheeks. Juana was motionless, weeping,
father of my heart? said, your daughter can no longer imitate. When I surprised my husband's
mistress, I ran out of tears. Consider what would my sadness!

Juana had reached the last degree of madness, was completely crazy,
but nevertheless owner was Queen of Spain and his name and consent
were necessary to give some character to the acts of government.

This consideration prompted the Catholic king to enter into some consultations with their daughter
for the best deal of business and back again to govern dominions of Spain. Joanna, meanwhile,
admitted without any reply as he proposed his father, putting only one condition, that had
to leave to stay in the village of Arcos, "in complete freedom, without having to intervene in another
business, to spend the day the rest of this life, next to the body of her husband. "Much of it
worked vary from this thought, but being useless was granted permission
by sending prepare a house in Arcos, worthy of the person who was
going to live.

Over a year and a half Juana lived in the village of Arcos but nothing had been improved his madness.
Was to see, say some, the animated conversations that this unfortunate lady, had the corpse
of her husband talks that further increase their delirium, and that instead of alleviating,
aggravates it. "Why no answer, Philip? he said: Callais! ... I still sereis !...» These words Proferia
unfaithful to her husband, and others that would cause shame listen.

From Santa Maria del Campo wrote D. His daughter Fernando warning of the need I had to leave to
Tordesillas and making it more healthy population know was that the
village Arcos, and consequently had determined, to receive on their
way to this point.

Dona Juana, was perfectly, according to the answer, in Arcos. So seeing the Catholic king that
his daughter did not accede to his entreaties made the determination, to go for her to see if their
presence could accompany him to Tordesillas. So did D. Fernando Having failed with the influence
exercised over her daughter goes to make that point, but Traveling on the same apparatus in the
other expeditions. Be the temperament to have changed, Whether the trip was not to his liking, the
fact is that Queen Juana was more furious each time, and took more increase its already incurable
disease.

The old Luis Ferrer was the one responsible for the care of Doña Juana, and which is I could not
see, that's why it was a huge opposition to all that the charge made, pleasure in executing the contrary.
If the pleading, for example, lie down in bed did in the ground and if available to be moved
to another room, but decent and well ventilated closed with more strength bolts of it was. When
it was cold, skin discarded and objects that provided shelter, and the more we begged to dress
Luis Ferrer and asease, walking harder dirty and badly dressed.

Shortly after he put on his head the mania of eating and drinking, and there was occasion for
them to go three days without taking anything up that beset by hunger, took something, striving
for dishes where the food sent to him not go out of his room, so that these objects soiled with
others, gave a foul odor to that dwelling, and impossible for both to bear it. There were moments
when, after a great delusion, enjoyed some reason, and lamented that they had torn the crown of
temples and is not happy his enemies with a burst of this kind, had been buried in a so stinking
dungeon guarded by a guard as negligible.

These words came with lightning speed to the ears of the Roman Catholic D. Fernando, so is that
the next year of 1510, when he passed to the Cortes of Monzon, made by visiting, and made sure
everything came together a great council to discuss the method was to look forward to his daughter,
he knew that the presence of D. Luis Ferrer's tormented, the board came out, that after having
provided all necessary toiletries, clothes and food, would be elected twelve ladies for continuing
care of her, and every night to stay awake to compel her to dress, undress and move from shirt,
even against their will. Twenty days was accompanying the King Catholic Doña Juana, which was less
badly, but after that they are obliged to execute the agreement by his father, seized her in
a rage so great that no one could stay at his side. More proactive Cardinal Cisneros greats
who had made the council believed Don appropriate Jubilee Luis Ferrer,
because they thought that maybe it would happen appoint another better
Doña Juana did so by substituting it with Don Fernando Ducos de Estrada.

This gentleman was that the ability he showed in the performance of their duties, which he recently
managed to eat and drank, they slept in their bed, which aseara and dress, and until they moved
from room, because his was not more than a foul dunghill. It was to strengthen their physical,
because with his usual finesse and manners, did this gentleman to go to Mass and attending
to various religious activities.

And his fits of madness were less consistent, so is that certain sections of sight the coffin
of her husband, a few days after being taken to Granada, and although it was great his exasperation
when he perceived, he finally D. Fernando Estrada Ducos reassurance.

But do not think that this came to be good at all, never reached this unhappy queen to regain
its lost cool. However, the Catholic king wrote to Estrada, giving the more affectionate and
repeated thanks for the service he had done to his daughter.

                    

At this time there was already one person who was not aware of the
disease Queen Juana, but nevertheless retained some hope of relief,
but rather the daughter desire of his subjects, that of possibility.

In the Cortes held in Valladolid in January 1518 decreed that if any Queen Juana time was in
a position to command the vast domains of Spain cease his governorship the Catholic King D.
Fernando, and that Joanna was the absolute sovereign.

CHAPTER IV.

The splits that were in Spain, and death of Doña Juana.

There was much dissension in Spain with several parties that began
to form a favor de Doña Juana, others to his son D. Charles, others
to his father, and some others who wanted to come to govern the Emperor
Maximilian I, his father, so I already Spain in 1520 fighting the
dying for their freedom. Supporters of Charles V raised in Castile
the banner of independence, and the chiefs of each other party to
give value flocked to his determination to Doña Juana. Cardinal Cisneros,
then regent and governor the kingdom, was the first appeal to the
queen decided to see if they could leave the hurried circumstances
in which the parties had placed to the provinces and particularly
to Valladolid.

How many were going to discuss such sensitive matters
with the queen, came out very unhappy not ever get a reply worthy
of placate the revolutionaries</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>