<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>165721</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19953</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Entonces le salen a usted por una friolera. ¿Se puede saber quién es el señor tan generoso...

--No es señor; es señora.

Otra miradita.

--¡Ah, pícaro! Ya sabía yo que gozaba usted de gran favor entre las damas.

Por la fisonomía alegrísima de D.ª Serafina corrió una nube que la oscureció momentáneamente.

--Es regalo de D.ª Serafina, con motivo de ser hoy mi cumpleaños--se apresuró a decir el presbítero.

--¡Ya me parecía a mí que venían ustedes hoy demasiado contentos!... Con tan fausto motivo
hubo juerga, ¿verdad?

--¿Cómo juerga?--preguntó D. Joaquín con cierta inquietud, temiendo la franqueza militar de
su amigo.

--Sí, una comidita íntima con algunos platos extraordinarios y un par de botellas de burdeos.

--No fue burdeos--replicó D. Joaquín riendo,--Fue borgoña.

--Mejor que mejor.

--¡Ya lo creo!--exclamó D.ª Serafina, comiéndose con los ojos a su capellán.

Y volvió a comenzar entre ellos el tiroteo de miraditas y guiños, prodigándose mil atenciones
tiernas que denotaban un estado de felicidad perfecta.

La llegada de D.ª Rita no turbó poco ni mucho su éxtasis delicioso. Esta señora, pequeña y
regordeta, con grandes ojos negros sin expresión y dientes grandes también, sanos y amarillos,
entraba siempre con un cesto donde guardaba la labor. Sacábala con lentitud, trabajaba media
hora en silencio escuchando atentamente todo lo que se decía, y al cabo recogía de nuevo los
bártulos y se iba a hacer lo mismo a otra parte. De este modo recorría en la noche tres o cuatro
casas. Era su manía la de saber; saberlo todo, hasta lo más trivial e insignificante. Se la
toleraba bien en todas partes, porque a pesar de su desmedida febril curiosidad nunca hubo
disgusto alguno por su causa. Gozaba con saber tan solamente: era un placer desinteresado,
intenso, como el de los hombres de ciencia que no miran el resultado que sus conocimientos
les puede dar. Como el avaro amontona en su caja monedas de oro sin pensar en utilizarlas jamás,
así D.ª Rita atesoraba en su cerebro cuantas noticias privadas podía recoger en sus peregrinaciones
por la villa, sin molestar a nadie con ellas. Pocos se guardaban, pues, de hablar secretos
en su presencia; pero si alguno lo hacía y llegaba a notarlo, le acometían tales ansias y congojas
por conocer lo que le ocultaban, que no dormía, ni descansaba un momento; andaba pálida, ojerosa,
se hacía grosera, intratable. Una vez que descubría el ansiado secreto, aunque fuese la cosa
más baladí, recobraba la calma y serenidad, volvía a su ser dulce, pacífico, inofensivo. Algunos
sujetos maleantes, como don Martín, el P. Narciso, D. Joaquín y otros, solían embromarla fingiendo
algún misterio entre ellos, la atormentaban, le hacían perder el juicio de pura curiosidad.

Pero cuando entró el P. Narciso, D. Joaquín se puso más grave, ocultando a su compañero aquella
dicha inefable, que le retozaba dentro del alma, evitando encontrarse con los ojos alegres,
chispeantes de su antigua ama. Aquél sintió en seguida en la nariz el tufillo aromático del
cigarro, dirigió una mirada escrutadora a su colega, otra a D.ª Serafina y se puso al tanto.

--Hubo gaudeamus, ¿verdad?--preguntó por lo bajo.

D. Joaquín negó descaradamente.

Unos tras otros fueron llegando Consejero, Cándida, D.ª Filomena, el P. Melchor, Marcelina
y, en suma, casi todos los tertulianos habituales. Formáronse pronto los grupos de siempre,
se disgregaron los elementos de aquella sociedad, operándose en ella el fenómeno químico de
las afinidades electivas. Mas esta operación no se efectuaba sin las violentas conmociones
y sacudidas que se observan en el seno de la naturaleza, sin las acciones y reacciones a que
da origen toda fermentación. Aquella noche Cándida, la huesuda señorita que ya conocemos, en
vez de ir a besar la mano al P. Melchor y sentarse a su lado y cuchichear toda la velada, fue
a hacer lo mismo con el P. Norberto. ¿Por qué esta deserción? En la tertulia nadie lo sabía
más que los interesados y D.ª Rita. El P. Melchor había tenido la imprevisión de decir en una
casa que los roquetes que le hacía la citada joven eran escasos de manga, y que le costaba
trabajo con ellos doblar el brazo. En cambio, había elogiado calurosamente un alzacuello que
le había regalado D.ª Marciala. El caso era grave, como cualquiera comprenderá, y debía producir
este triste resultado. D.ª Marciala, viendo al padre Narciso cada vez más inclinado a admitir
y agradecer la fervorosa admiración de D.ª Filomena, mostraba su sentimiento y despecho, acercándose
a D. Melchor y hablándole con afectado cariño. D.ª Filomena, después de algunos años de adoración
resignada, silenciosa, había llegado, cuando ya no lo esperaba, a la meta de sus aspiraciones.
Tanta atención, tanto cariño habían logrado al fin cautivar el espíritu del elocuente capellán
de Sarrió, quien daba claras muestras a la viuda de su afecto. Después de haberlo intentado
en vano muchas veces, aquélla había recabado de él que fuese preceptor de su hijo, y que tomase
el cargo con afición. Su temperamento dominante y fogoso se manifestó en seguida. El pobre
niño tuvo que experimentar no sólo un trabajo excesivo, superior a su edad, sino una serie
de castigos crueles, malévolos, refinados. Y D.ª Filomena, que era la dulzura personificada,
que jamás había levantado la mano sobre su hijo, consentía impasible que aquel hombre lo azotase
despiadadamente. Acallaba su conciencia diciéndose que era para su bien.

Marcelina, que había soñado con suplantar a D.ª Serafina en el corazón de D. Joaquín (y en
realidad había cierto fundamento para este sueño, pues el joven presbítero no cesaba de distinguirla
entre todas), andaba ya bastante desengañada. Adquirió el convencimiento de que aquél la tomaba
como instrumento para hacer padecer un poco a su ama y tenerla más atenta y sumisa. Tal convicción
la empujó de nuevo hacia D. Narciso, a quien hacía tiempo había abandonado; pero éste, que
nunca le había profesado gran afición, como a Obdulia, la rechazó sin miramientos. Si embargo,
la ex-joven seguía luchando bravamente con D.ª Filomena. Hacía pocos días había regalado al
capellán una colcha de crochet que era una verdadera maravilla de trabajo pacienzudo y habilidoso.
Por cierto que la viuda, al verla sobre la cama del clérigo, experimentó un vivo disgusto y
lloró muchas lágrimas en secreto.

Estas agitaciones espirituales, estas luchas de sensibilidad y abnegación entre las piadosas
damas que allí asistían, eran precisamente las que daban algún interés dramático a aquel mundo
sereno, inocente. No eran ciertamente las competencias groseras que se establecen en las sociedades
profanas, donde las intrigas afectan un carácter violento, donde las relaciones del varón y
la hembra tienen su fundamento siempre en la explosión de los sentidos, llevan el sello abominable
de la animalidad. Aquí todo se efectuaba de un modo suave, inocente, espiritual: los pequeños
sacudimientos de que hemos hecho mención semejaban el leve rizado de un lago trasparente y
hermoso. Era aquella tertulia como una antesala del cielo, donde las relaciones de los ángeles,
de los santos y las santas alcanzan el supremo grado de la pureza inmortal.

Lo que estaba pasando por el alma de la hija de Osuna confirma bien la idea que acabamos de
formular. Después de experimentar aquel trastorno gástrico, hijo de la excitación en que se
hallaba, cayó en profundo desfallecimiento físico y moral. Sentía la impresión de si hubieran
cometido con ella una gran perfidia, y aunque su pensamiento le decía vagamente lo absurdo
de tal sensación, no podía minorar su intensidad, ni menos desecharla. Odiaba al P. Gil, le
odiaba con toda su alma. Daría algo por vengarse. ¿De qué? No se lo decía; pero allá en el
fondo del alma estaba persuadida de que tenía razón para ello. Formó resolución inquebrantable
de no confesar más con él. ¡Con él! ¡Un sacerdote que entra de noche en los portales a cuchichear
con mujeres hermosas y elegantes! ¡Puf! Sería vergüenza el hacerlo. Obdulia estaba bien segura
de que la mujer que hablaba con su confesor era linda. Esta seguridad la torturaba. Por supuesto
que, si tenía el atrevimiento de venir a hablarle, le daría un desaire de los gordos, le volvería
la espalda. Y confesaría otra vez con D. Narciso. Y diría a sus amigas en qué situación le
había visto con una señora desconocida y elegante. Porque no cabía duda de que vestía con elegancia,
bien lo había reparado. Aquel abrigo largo no estaba hecho en Peñascosa. ¿Quién sería? Alguna
de Lancia, seguro, que vendría a hacerle una visita. Y ¿por qué se viene de lejos a visitar
a un sacerdote no siendo su madre, o su hermana o su deuda? ¿No sabe esa señora que la fama
de los sacerdotes es muy delicada y cualquier cosa la quiebra? El cerebro de la joven no cesaba
de dar vueltas y más vueltas a estas ideas y a otras análogas, mientras su cuerpo permanecía
inmóvil, abatido, clavando los ojos obstinadamente en las manos de D.ª Marciala, que no dejaba
un momento su calceta. Sentíase enferma, deseaba irse; pero una vaga esperanza, que no podía
definir, la retenía a su pesar.

Mientras tanto el P. Norberto estaba sorprendido y confuso por las inusitadas atenciones de
que era objeto por parte de Cándida. El pobre no estaba acostumbrado a que se las prodigasen.
El bello sexo de Peñascosa le profesaba cierto desdén compasivo. Teníasele por un sacerdote
virtuoso, pero de muy cortos alcances. Sus mismos compañeros, cuando hablaban de él, lo hacían
sin dejar de los labios una sonrisa medio protectora, medio burlona. Para las damas, la virtud
del P. Norberto no tenía poesía, carecía de ese encanto especial que en otros sacerdotes la
hace contagiosa, era una virtud pedestre, que no se traducía en conceptos delicados y sublimes
como en el P. Narciso, el P. Gil y otros. Así que rara era la joven que se confesaba con él,
ni menos la que apeteciese su conversación o tuviese gusto en envolverle entre nubes de incienso,
como hacía Cándida en aquel momento. Su misma inclinación a rescatar las mujerzuelas perdidas,
por más que se respetase, no le hacía simpático a las señoritas. Verdad que él se pasaba admirablemente
sin esta simpatía y no le quitaba de engordar cada día más y pasar la vida riendo. Las lisonjas
que le estaba vertiendo al oído con voz insinuante su nueva hija de confesión, en vez de agradarle,
le turbaban, le molestaban visiblemente. Fue una de las pocas veces en que pudo vérsele serio.
Hacía rechinar la silla, cambiando de postura a cada instante, y restallaba los nudillos de
las manos de un modo formidable, tosía, se ponía colorado, y de vez en cuando dejaba escapar
de la garganta un leve bufido con que su modestia alarmada protestaba. Por último, solicitado
vivamente por la dulce perspectiva del tresillo, aprovechó una pausa de la doncella para levantarse
y decir torciendo un poco las caderas a guisa de saludo:

--Con permiso de usted, señorita.

En cuanto salió de aquella situación angustiosa, su faz sanguínea se dilató y volvió a aparecer
en ella la sonrisa de benevolencia universal que le servía de principal ornamento. Su llegada
al grupo donde estaban Consejero, D. Martín, Osuna y otro caballero militar de Lancia fue acogida
con alegría.

--Te presento--dijo D. Martín a su amigo forastero, bajando la voz y echando una mirada recelosa
alrededor para cerciorarse de que no le oía su mujer,--al padre Norberto, un cura que te podrá
informar de todos los chamizos de la población, si deseas conocer alguno.

--¡Oh, oh! ¡D. Martín, por Dios!

--¡Atrévase usted a decir que no los conoce!

--Hombre, sí... de algunos sé... Por desgracia, necesito entrar en ellos alguna vez...

--Este señor se dedica a las jóvenes extraviadas--continuó D. Martín, dirigiéndose a su compañero,
que sonreía lleno de asombro.

--¡Jesús! Considere, D. Martín, que este señor no me conoce...

--Pues para que le conozca a usted hablo.

D.ª Eloisa, de lejos, echaba miradas de terror a su marido, observando la confusión de D. Norberto
y la risa de los otros.

--Bueno--prosiguió el señor de las Casas, haciéndose prudente y conciliador,--yo no diré, D.
Norberto, que usted vaya con mala idea a esas casas de perdición; pero lo que sostendré siempre
es que les está usted prestando un gran servicio: está usted haciendo su agosto.

--¿Cómo, cómo?--preguntó asustado el clérigo.

--Pues muy sencillo; ayudando a que se eleve el precio de la mercancía. Recuerde el ejemplo
de Carmen la zapatillera...

Ésta era una muchacha a quien el P. Norberto había conseguido sacar de una casa de prostitución
y llevar a un convento. Al cabo de algún tiempo se salió y volvió a la mala vida. Tornó D.
Norberto a persuadirla al arrepentimiento, y otra vez ella se vino del asilo y se entregó al vicio.

--¿Y qué tiene que ver?...

--Voy a explicárselo, padre, voy a explicárselo... Atiendan ustedes... Cuando usted catequizó
a Carmen, no me negará que la mercancía estaba bastante depreciada ya...

--¡Yo no sé! ¡Qué cosas tiene usted, D. Martín!--exclamó el clérigo azorado.

--Me consta, padre, me consta. Pues bien, después que estuvo un año por allá y engordó un poco
en el convento y volvió rodeada de cierta aureola de honradez, el precio se elevó notablemente.
Vuelve usted a llevársela cuando ya estaba un poco estropeadilla y la demanda había mermado
hasta un punto que hacía temer por la bucólica, y ahora que viene otra vez gordita y santificada,
se cotiza de nuevo como en sus mejores tiempos.

--¡Jesús! ¡Jesús! ¡Vaya todo por Dios!--exclamó el clérigo tapándose los oídos, pero sin enfadarse.--No
sea usted tan malo, D. Martín.

D.ª Eloisa, que bien advertía lo que estaba pasando, se levantó al fin de la silla y vino hacia
ellos, preguntando con mal humor:

--¿No juegan hoy al tresillo?

--Vamos allá, vamos allá--respondió su marido, sofocando la risa que le fluía del cuerpo, como
a los demás.

Sentáronse Consejero, D. Norberto y él a la mesa, y no tardaron en abstraerse de todos los
ruidos mundanales bajo la influencia fascinadora de la espada, la mala y el basto. Poco después
Consejero rechinaba los dientes y se tiraba cruelmente del bigote, encontrándose dos veces
seguidas con el tres de bastos, su enemigo personal. Hacía ya muchos años que se tenían declarada
una guerra a muerte. Cada vez que le venía a las manos, Consejero se crispaba, juraba sordamente
como un carretero. El tres de bastos, malintencionado y socarrón como ningún otro naipe, gozaba
al parecer con verle irritado, y se colaba bonitamente siempre que podía en el montoncillo
que le repartían. No sólo en la tertulia, sino en toda la villa era conocida esta antipatía.
Algunos, con ciertas precauciones por supuesto, porque D. Romualdo se disparaba fácilmente,
le embromaban con ella. En cierta ocasión, pescando con caña detrás de la iglesia, sacó en
el anzuelo un naipe que resultó ser el tres de bastos. No le cupo duda de que lo habían tirado
allí con intención, pero no dijo palabra para que no se rieran.

Mientras tanto Osuna había ido a frotarse un poco contra D.ª Eloisa. Entre todas las damas
que asistían a aquella tertulia no había más que dos gordas, D.ª Teodora y D.ª Eloisa. Estaba
también en buenas carnes D.ª Rita, pero era blanda, amarilla. Las demás «escocia pura,» como
él llamaba a las flacas, aludiendo al bacalao. Así que no tenía fin el desprecio que nuestro
jorobado profesaba a aquella sociedad degenerada y exhausta de tejido adiposo. Sólo iba por
allí a buscar a su hija, o cuando materialmente no sabía dónde refugiarse. D.ª Eloisa miraba
con benevolencia (como lo miraba todo la buena señora) aquella pasión que el monstruo parecía
sentir hacia ella. Cuando se le acercaba demasiado, separábase dulcemente, sin extinguirse
por eso su sonrisa bondadosa. En cambio D.ª Teodora le tenía un gran miedo, verdadero terror.
Lo mismo era aproximarse Osuna, que ya estaba la casta jamona sofocada, inquieta, un color
se le iba y otro se le venía. Pero era tal la vergüenza que sentía, que no hubiera declarado
a su mismo padre las insinuaciones del sucio contrahecho. ¡Qué diferencia entre este indecente
y el sereno, majestuoso y romántico D. Juan Casanova! Ni con D. Peregrín podía comparársele,
con ser éste, en concepto de la madura doncella, un sujeto mucho más voluptuoso y terrestre.

D. Peregrín había llegado, según costumbre, de los últimos. Y si la tertulia no advirtió en
la mayor estridencia de sus bufidos nasales, en su parpadear infinitamente más solemne y en
la grave manera de poner una pierna sobre otra y echarse hacia atrás que algo importante, importantísimo,
tenía que comunicar, fue que no quiso advertirlo. Aguardó pacientemente, como todos los hombres
seguros del éxito, a que hubiese una pausa, y cuando llegó, profirió con su voz gangosa, penetrante,
encarándose con el ama de la casa:

--¿A que no sabe usted a quién acabo de ver entrar en casa de su hermano, en compañía del excusador?

A Obdulia le dio un salto tan recio el corazón, que pensó caer al suelo. Los demás, incluso
D.ª Eloisa, alzaron la cabeza con curiosidad.

--¿Quién era?

--Su cuñada Joaquina--gritó más que dijo el ex-gobernador interino de Tarragona, como si anunciara
el juicio final.

Profundo estupor en toda la tertulia.

--¡Mi cuñada!--exclamó.

--Su misma cuñada--confirmó D. Peregrín con trompeteo horrísono.

--¡No puede ser!--dijo D.ª Eloisa.

--¡No puede ser!--exclamó su marido, suspendiendo el juego.

--¡No puede ser!--repitió D.ª Serafina Barrado.

El ex-gobernador de Tarragona dejó escapar por la nariz algunos resoplidos fragorosos, como
una locomotora que desaloja el vapor sobrante, y repuso:

--¿Creen ustedes, señores, que no tengo ojos en la cara?

Esta pregunta trascendental, acompañada del adecuado fruncimiento de cejas, produjo bastante
impresión entre los interruptores.

--Bien pudo usted haberse equivocado--dijo el inválido.

--¡Es tan fácil!--exclamó D.ª Eloisa.

--La he visto como les veo a ustedes ahora, a tres pasos de distancia. Venía yo de hablar con
el sacristán para la cuestión del aniversario de mi señor padre, cuando al embocar la calle
del Cuadrante veo al P. Gil con una señora que me pareció forastera. Quise saber quién era,
y me detuve un poco cerca del farol, ocultándome detrás del quicio de una puerta. Era Joaquinita,
sin duda alguna. Esperé un poco y los seguí con la vista hasta que entraron en casa de Montesinos.

--Pero ¿usted la conoce bien?--preguntó el P. Narciso.

--Lo mismo que a usted.

--Peregrín, debes tener presente que no le has hecho más que una visita en Madrid, y por la
noche, según me has dicho--apuntó tímidamente D. Juan.

El ex-gobernador arrojó a su hermano una mirada de indecible desprecio.

--Juan, no metas la pata.

--Peregrín, no sé por qué...

--¡Juan!...

--¡Peregrín!...

--¡Que no la metas! ¡Que no la metas! A esa señora la he visto después de visitarla otra porción
de veces en la calle, y la he saludado. Por lo tanto, me veo en la triste necesidad de manifestarte
que lo que acabas de decir es una impertinencia. Cuando he asegurado que conocía a esa señora,
es porque la conocía. Yo no hablo nunca a humo de pajas. Si fuera un hombre ligero y sin fundamento,
no hubiera podido ocupar las posiciones que he ocupado. Sírvate de gobierno.

--Ahora que me acuerdo--dijo Cándida,--hoy he visto apearse de la diligencia a una señora rubia
con un traje muy elegante.

D. Peregrín alzó los hombros con un gesto de profundo desdén, como si quisiera decir: «¿A qué
viene usted en mi apoyo para contrarrestar los absurdos de este necio?»

Aquel dato y aquel gesto concluyeron de aniquilar a D. Juan, cuyo rostro expresó el abatimiento.
Pero D.ª Teodora, con sus grandes ojos serenos, le clavó una mirada tan afectuosa que las facciones
del caballero, contraídas por la pesadumbre, se fueron dilatando gradualmente, y una plácida
sonrisa melancólica concluyó por esfumarse en sus labios. La frente de D. Peregrín, en cambio,
quedó surcada instantáneamente por una porción de arrugas. La innegable superioridad que tenía
sobre su hermano, ¿de qué le servía? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04809</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>93644</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17742</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Then I go out to you for a trifle. Can you tell who is the lord so generous ...

- No sir, it is lady.

Another peek.

- Ah, rogue!

I knew you enjoyed great favor with the ladies.

On the face of Ms Serafina alegrísima ran a dark cloud that momentarily.

- It is gift of Ms Serafina, due to be my birthday today - was quick
to say the priest.

- It seemed to me that you came too happy today!

... To celebrate this there partying, right?

- How to spree? - Asked D. Joaquín with some trepidation, fearing
military openness his friend.

- Yes, an intimate comidita special
dishes and a couple of bottles of claret.

- It was burgundy - said
D. Joaquin laughing - was burgundy.

- Better and better.

- Yes!
- Ms Serafina said, ogling his chaplain.

He returned to start including the shooting glances and winks, lavishing attention thousand tender
denoting a state of perfect bliss.

The arrival of Ms Rita did not disturb her ecstasy, less or more delicious. This lady, small
and plump, with big black eyes and big teeth expressionless also healthy and yellow always
entered with a basket where he kept the job. Sacábala slowly, working half hours quietly listening
carefully to everything that was said, and picked up again after the belongings and went to
do the same elsewhere. This ran in the night three or four houses. It was his habit of knowing,
knowing everything, even the most trivial and insignificant. It well tolerated everywhere, because
despite his boundless curiosity never had febrile for any disappointment caused. Know as only
he enjoyed: he was a disinterested pleasure, intense as that of the scientists who do not look at
the result that their knowledge can give them. As the miser piled up in the box without thinking
of gold coins in use ever Ms Rita and treasured in his mind many private reports could pick
up on his travels through the town, without disturbing anyone with them. A few were kept, then,
to talk secrets in his presence, but if someone did it and came to notice him rushing these desires
and anxieties to know what he hid, he had not slept or rested for
a moment, walked pale, haggard, be made rude and intractable.

Once discovered the coveted secret, even if the thing flimsiest grew calm and serenity, returned
to its sweet, peaceful, harmless. Some subject thugs, as Don Martin, P. Narciso, D. Joachim
and others used to tease pretending a mystery among them, tormented, made him lose his mind
on a whim.

But when he entered the P. Narciso, D. Joaquin became more serious,
that fellow hiding ineffable joy, he frolicked in his soul, his eyes
avoiding find cheerful sparkling with his former mistress.

He felt at once in the nose a whiff aromatic cigar, looked searchingly at his colleague, Ms
Serafina other and began to date.

- There Gaudeamus, right? - Asked softly.

D. Joaquin blatantly refused.

One after another were coming director, Candida, Mrs. Filomena, P. Melchor, Marcelina and, in
short, almost all regular commentators. Soon Formáronse groups always disintegrated the elements
of that society, operating in it the chemical phenomenon elective affinities. But this operation
was done without the violent upheaval and shocks that are observed in the bosom of nature, without
the actions and reactions to gives rise by fermentation. That night, Candida, the bony Miss you
already know, in Instead of going to kiss the hand of the Father Melchor and sit beside him and
whispering all evening, was to do the same with Fr Norberto. Why this drop? In the gathering nobody
knew more than interested and Ms Rita. Fr Melchor had the foresight to say in a rochets house that
made him the youngest cited were limited in breadth, and it cost him work with them to bend the
arm. Instead, he warmly praised a collar that had given Ms Marciala. The case was serious, as
anyone will understand, and should produce this sad result. Ms Marciala, Father Narciso seeing
more and more inclined to admit and thank the fervent admiration of Ms Filomena, showed his emotion
and indignation, approaching D. Melchor and speaking with an affected baby. Ms Filomena, after
several years of worship resigned, quiet, had arrived, when they did not expect the goal of
their aspirations. Much attention, so much love had finally managed to captivate the spirit
of telling chaplain Sarrió, who gave clear evidence to the widow of his affection. After having
tried in vain many times, it had sought from him that was tutor to
his son, and to take office with fans.

His fiery temperament is dominant and then said. Poor child had to experience not only too
much work, beyond his years, but a series of cruel, malicious, refined. And Ms Filomena, who was the
sweetest, I had never raised his hand on his son, impassive man consented to whip mercilessly.
Quieted his conscience by saying that it was for good.

Marcelina, who had dreamed to replace Ms Serafina in the heart of D. Joaquín (and actually had
some basis for this dream, as the young priest did not stop to distinguish among all), he was
already quite disappointed. Became convinced that it took her as a tool for getting a little to your
love and have it more attentive and submissive. This conviction pushed back to D. Narciso,
who had long been abandoned, but this, that he had never professed
great fondness, as Obdulia, unceremoniously rejected.

If, however, ex-girl still struggling bravely with Ms Filomena. A few days earlier had given
the Chaplain crochet a bedspread that was a marvel of pacienzudo and skilled labor. Certainly
the widow, seeing her on the bed of the clergy, underwent a lively displeasure and cried many tears
in secret.

These spiritual turmoil, the struggles of sensitivity and pious devotion among ladies who attended
there were precisely those that gave a dramatic interest in that world serene, innocent. Skills
were certainly not rude down in societies profane, where a violent intrigues affect where the relations
of man and the female are based always on the explosion of the senses,
bear the stamp abominable animality.

Everything was done in a soft, innocent, spiritual small shocks that we have mentioned were
like the soft ripple of a lake and transparent beautiful. It was that gathering as a prelude
to heaven where the angels relations, of holy men and women reach the highest degree of purity
immortal.

What was happening for the soul of Osuna's daughter confirms that idea just made. After that
experience gastric upset, son of the excitement that was, fell into a deep physical and moral
weakness. I felt if they had the impression she committed a great treachery, and though his mind
told him vaguely absurd in a sense, could not lessens its intensity, or less discarded. P. hated
Gil, you hated with all his soul. I'd give anything for revenge. What? Not tell her, but beyond
the depths of the soul was convinced he was right to do so. He was unshakable resolution not to confess
to him anymore. With him! A priest comes by night in doorways whispering with beautiful women
and elegant! Ugh! Would be ashamed to do so. Obdulia was quite sure a woman talking to her confessor
was cute. This assurance was torturing. Of course that if he had the audacity to come to talk,
give him a cold shoulder from the fat, I would back. And confess again with D. Narciso. And
tell his friends in what situation you had seen a lady unknown and elegant. Because there was
no doubt who was dressed elegantly While he had repaired. Long coat that was not done in Peñascosa.
Who would? Some Lancia, sure, that would pay him a visit. And why do you come from afar to visit
a priest, not his mother or his sister or his debt? Do not you know that lady that fame Priests
are very delicate and anything bankruptcy? The brain of the young did not stop spinning and
turning these ideas and the like, while his body remained motionless,
dejected, staring stubbornly at the hands of Ms Marciala, leaving
no a time when his sock.

He felt ill, wanted to leave but a vague hope that he could not define the retained despite
himself.

Meanwhile Fr Norberto was surprised and confused by the unusual attention of it was subjected by
Candida. The poor man was not accustomed to being the lavish. The fair sex of her professed disdain
Peñascosa compassionate. Teníasele by a priest virtuous, but very short-sighted. His own companions,
when they talked about it, they did while the protective lips half smiling, half-mocking. For
the ladies, virtue Fr Norberto was not poetry, it lacked the charm that other priests becomes
contagious, was a pedestrian under that did not translate into delicate and sublime concepts as in
P. Narciso, P. Gil et al. So rare was the girl who confessed to him not least that felt like it
had the taste in conversation or envelop in clouds of incense, Candida as he did at that time. His own
inclination to rescue the lost sluts, much they respected, was not sympathetic to the ladies. Truth
that he spent admirably Without this sympathy and did not detract from fat each day and spend my life
laughing. Flattery he was pouring his ear with his new daughter insinuating voice of confession,
instead of pleasing, troubled him, annoyed him visibly. It was one of the few times he could
seriously seen lounging. It was grinding the seat, changing position every minute, and Knuckles
crackled hands in a formidable, coughed, blushed, and occasionally let out of the throat with
a slight snort alarmed protested his modesty. Finally, as requested strongly by the sweet prospect
of sitting, took a break from the maiden to rise and say a little
twisting hips by way of greeting:

- With your permission, Miss.

As
distressing situation that left his face and dilated blood reappeared
in it the universal benevolent smile which was his principal ornament.

Arrival the group where they were Counsellor, D. Martin, Osuna and
another military gentleman was greeted Lancia with joy.

- I present
- said D. Stranger to his friend Martin, lowering his voice and glancing
suspiciously around to make sure his wife could not hear him - the
father Norbert, a priest who will be able report all the huts of the
people, if you want to know any.

- Oh, oh! D. Martin, by God!

-
Dare you to say they do not know!

- Well, yes ... some know ... Unfortunately,
I need to enter them once ...

- This man is dedicated to the lost
youth - continued D. Martin, addressing his companion, smiling in
amazement.

- Jesus!

Consider, D. Martin, who this gentleman does not know me ...

- But that knows you talk.

Ms Eloisa, by far, cast glances of terror to her husband, noting the confusion of D. Norberto and
the laughter of others.

- Well - continued Mr. de las Casas, becoming cautious and conciliatory,
- I will not tell, D. Norbert, you go with bad idea to these houses
of iniquity, but what always argue is that it is you provide a great
service: you're making a killing.

- How, how? - Scared the cleric
asked.

- Very simple, helping to raise the price of the commodity.

Recall the example Carmen the zapatillera ...

This was a girl whom
Fr Norberto had managed to get a house of prostitution and lead to
a convent.

After some time he went out and returned to the bad life.

D. became Norberto to persuade her to repent, and again she came and gave asylum to vice.

- And what does that matter? ...

- I'll explain, Father, I will explain ... Meet you ... When you catechized Carmen, I do not deny that
the merchandise was quite undervalued and ...

- I do not know!

What things have you, D. Martin! - Said the cleric embarrassed.

- I know, father, I know.

Well, after he spent a year there and a bit fatter in the convent
and became surrounded by an aura of honesty, the price rose significantly.

You take it back when I was a bit estropeadilla and demand had diminished to a point raised
fears for the bucolic, and now it comes again chubby and sanctified
is quoted again as in their heyday.

- Jesus!

Jesus! Go all for God - said the priest covered their ears, but not angry .-- you will be very
bad, D. Martin.

Ms Eloisa, it warned that what was happening, finally rose from his
chair and came toward them, asking in a bad mood:

- Do not play today
ombre?

- Here we go, here we go - her husband said, stifling laughter
that flowed from the body, such as others.

They sat Adviser, D. Norbert and he was at table, and soon block out
all worldly sounds fascinating under the influence of the sword, the
bad and the rough.

Shortly after Councillor gnashed his teeth and mustache pulled cruelly, being twice followed with
three clubs, his personal enemy. Many years ago that had declared a war to death. Every time I
came to the hands, twitched Chief, swore silently like a trooper. The three of clubs, malicious
and cunning as any other card, enjoyed apparently irritated him, and whenever he could sneak nicely
in the pile he distributed.

Not only in the party, but in the whole village was known this antipathy. Some, with certain precautions,
of course, because D. Romualdo easy shooting I teased her.

On one occasion, angling behind the church, pulled in hook a card that turned out to be the three
of clubs.

He had no doubt that he had thrown there on purpose, but said nothing
so as not to laugh.

Osuna meantime had gone to rub a little against Ms Eloisa. Among all the ladies attending that
gathering there were only two fat, Ms Teodora and Ms Eloisa. Was also good meat Ms Rita, but it
was soft, yellow. Other "pure Scotland," as he called the skinny, referring to cod. So there
was no end to our contempt Hunchback professed that degenerate society and exhausted from adipose
tissue. Just going by there to find his daughter, or materially did not know where to shelter. Ms
Eloisa looked sympathetic (as I watched all the good lady) the passion that the monster seemed
feel to it. When you are too close, gently parted without extinction so his kindly smile.
Ms Teodora Instead you had a great fear, real fear. The same approach was Osuna, who was already
suffocating caste buxom, restless, color it was and another was coming. But such was the shame
he felt, had not declared to his own father's dirty insinuations misshapen. What is the difference
between this indecent and serene, majestic and romantic D. Juan Casanova! D. Ni Peregrin could
compare with, to be the latter, by way of the mature girl, a subject
much more voluptuous and land.

D. Pilgrims had arrived, as usual, in the past. And if the gathering is not warned most strident
of nasal snorts, as infinitely more solemn blink and the serious way to put a leg over the other
and lean back to something important, important, had to communicate was that he did not want
to notice. He waited patiently, like all men sure of success, to have a break, and when he arrived,
he uttered with his shrill voice, piercing, turning to the lady of the house:

- Do not you know whom I have just seen entering the house of his brother, accompanied by excused?

A
Obdulia he jumped so hard the heart that thought hit the ground. Other, including Ms Eloisa,
looked up curiously.

- Who was that?

- Your sister Joaquina - cried more that said former acting governor of Tarragona, as announced
Judgement Day.

Deep stupor throughout the party.

- My sister! - Exclaimed.

- His own sister - confirmed D. Peregrin with trumpeting horrid.

- There can be - said Ms Eloisa.

- There can be - said her husband,
suspending the game.

- There can be - repeated Ms Serafina Barrado.

The ex-governor of Tarragona let out through the nose some deafening
snorts as an engine that displaces the excess steam, and said:

-
Do you think, gentlemen, I have no eyes in his head?

This momentous question, accompanied by the appropriate frown, produced
enough impression among the switches.

- Well you could have been
mistaken - said the invalid.

- It's so easy! - Said Ms Eloisa.

-
I've seen as you see them now, three steps away.

I came to talk to the clerk to the issue of the anniversary of my
father, when the hole street Quadrant I to P. Gil with a lady who
seemed a stranger.

I wanted to know who he was, and I paused a little near the lantern,
hiding behind a doorway.

It was Joaquin, no doubt. I waited a bit and followed with his eyes until he entered the house
of Montesinos.

- But you know well? - Asked P. Narciso.

- The same as you.

- Peregrin, please note that you have not done more than a visit to Madrid, and the night, as
I've said - she said timidly D. Juan.

The ex-governor threw his brother a look of unutterable contempt.

- John, do not put the leg.

- Peregrin I do not know why ...

- John! ...

- Peregrin! ...

- Do not the goal!

Not the goals! A lady that I saw after visiting another portion times in the street, and I welcomed.
Therefore, I feel the sad need to show yourself what you just said is an impertinence. When assured
that I knew this lady, is because the know. I never talk to smoke with straw. If I were a man
light and baseless could not occupy the positions I have occupied. Sírvate of government.

- Now I remember - Candida said, - today I have seen alighting from the coach to a blond lady with
a very elegant dress.

D. Peregrin shrugged with a gesture of disdain, as if to say: 'What
you come in my support to counter the absurdities of this fool?

"

That data and concluded that gesture to annihilate D. John, whose face expressed dejection. But
Ms Theodora, with her large calm eyes, he plunged a look so warm that the factions knight, contracted
with grief, went gradually dilating, and a placid concluded by a melancholy smile on his lips
disappear. The head of D. Peregrin, however, was instantly crossed
by a portion of wrinkles. The undeniable superiority was about his
brother, what he used</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>