<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05565</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>41146</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>741</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Remitió Andronico
los dos Embajadores á Roger concertando el casamiento, y le llevaron las insignias de Megaduque,
que es lo mismo entre nosotros General de la mar: dignidad grande de aquel Imperio, pero no
de las mayores.

CAPITULO VI.

Señala sueldo el Emperador á la gente de guerra, y hace muchas honras y mercedes á su Capitanes.

Señaló Andronico las pagas segun la diferencia de las armas y ocupacion, cuatro onzas de plata
cada mes á los hombres de armas, á los caballos lijeros dos, y lo mismo á los pilotos y gente
de mandoneros una onza, y que siempre que llegasen á la costa de alguna Provincia del Imperio,
se les diesen cuatro pagas, y cuando quisiesen volver á sus casas juntos, ó divididos, se le
librasen dos para el viaje. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07899</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>29232</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>716</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Andronico sent the
two Ambassadors to Roger arranging the marriage, and brought him the insignia of Grand Duke, which
is the same between us General of the sea: great dignity of the empire, but not the majors.

CHAPTER
VI.

Points paid the Emperor to the people of war, and makes many honors and favors to his captains.

Andronico said the pay according to the difference of the arms and occupation, four ounces of
silver each month to the men at arms, their horses Thin two, and so the pilots and people of mandoneros
an ounce, and provided that they reach the coast of a province of the Empire they were given
four pay, and when they wanted to return to their homes together,
or split, you fought two for the trip</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>