<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08913</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>160210</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21527</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> No pienso hacer nada por ti. Cuando murió tu segundo marido me prometiste
ser un modelo de economía y prudencia; y yo fui tan tonto, que perdí el tiempo y hasta algún
dinero para poner a flote tu fortuna, que hacía agua por todas partes como un barco viejo....
Déjame acabar, Manuela; no me interrumpas. ¿Quieres hacerme creer que aún lo conservas todo
libre de trampas, tal como yo te lo entregué? ¡Quia, hija mía! En este siglo no hay milagros,
y con quince mil duros de capital no se sostiene un carruaje ni el boato que tú gastas. Lo
sé todo; y si no, escucha.

Y don Juan, con gran abundancia de detalles, como hombre versado en los negocios, fue describiendo
a su hermana el estado de su fortuna. No tenía un pedazo de tierra libre del peso de una hipoteca;
las rentas apenas si daban para los réditos, y hasta la misma casa en que ella vivía era una
finca que producía poco, por culpa de su vanidad.

--Cuando al quedar viuda te pusiste en mis manos, vivías en una de las dos habitaciones del
piso segundo y tenías alquilado este principal. Un duro diario es una gran cosa, y más en tu
situación. Pero tú no podías acostumbrarte a ser señora de muchos escalones, como dices en
tu jerga; querías tu salón y tu carruaje, como en los tiempos de loco despilfarro, y con el
pretexto de que las niñas crecían y era preciso pollear y mentir, bajaste a este piso, y bajó
la renta también aumentando los gastos. Ya que no podías tener un tronco, carretela y berlina,
como en otra época, vendiste un campo para comprar la galerita y el caballo y mantener a ese
bigardón, hijo de la tía Quica, que os roba la cebada y las algarrobas.... Sé que te fastidia
oír todo esto, pero te lo digo para que sepas que no me chupo el dedo ni se me engaña fácilmente....
Nunca me he forjado la ilusión de convertirte. Tú serás siempre la misma Manuela, la loca,
la pretenciosa, y morirás cuando gastes el último céntimo. Cada uno nace con su carácter, y
tú eres de aquellos a quienes el pobre papá cantaba la antigua copla:

/*
       Arròs y tartana,
     casaca a la moda,
     ¡y ròde la bola
     a la valensiana!
*/

Y como si la cancioncilla del tío fuese la señal para que comenzase la música de las niñas,
éstas atronaron el salón con el tecleo del piano y los gorjeos esforzados.

Don Juan cobró ánimos con este estrépito. Al ver que los muchachos sólo atendían al piano,
siguió hablando, pero levantó más la voz, con gran alarma de su hermana.

--Marchas a tu perdición, Manuela. Cuando estés en la miseria, siempre me acordaré de que soy
tu hermano, y tendrás donde comer tú y los tuyos.... Pero dinero, ¡ni un céntimo!

Doña Manuela levantó la cabeza con altivez, mostrando la mirada ardiente y las mejillas rubicundas.

--Gracias por la limosna--dijo con ironía--. Pero aún no he llegado ahí.

--Llegarás, llegarás--repuso don Juan sin perder la calina--. Estás en el camino. Hoy todavía
puedes sostenerte, y al ver que te niego los ocho mil reales, buscarás a doña Clara, esa bruja
prestamista, o a otra persona de la clase, y firmarás un pagaré por doce o catorce mil. Estás
metida en el barro y no saldrás nunca de él; por más esfuerzos que hagas te hundirás. Si no
te conociera tanto, te daría la mano; pero no: «una y no más, Santo Tomás»; me acuerdo mucho
de la atención con que seguiste mis consejos.

La señora estaba indignada por el lenguaje rudo de su hermano. Era muy dueño de no darle aquella
miseria; al fin, resultaba lo que ella había creído siempre: un avaro sin corazón. Pero su
demanda no le autorizaba para aburrirla con tanto sermoneo.

--Cállate, Juan; me pones nerviosa con tus groserías.

--Callaré, hija; no quiero molestarte en un día como éste. Pero sólo me resta hacerte una advertencia.
Los que están tan ahogados como tú, se agarran a un clavo ardiendo. Juanito posee una finca
que vale algo: el huerto de Alcira, que has tenido que respetar en calidad de bienes reservables.
Como ahora el chico es mayor de edad y te quiere tanto, te advierto que si para hacer dinero
lo mezclas en tus líos tendrás que vértelas conmigo. Yo soy su tutor, por encargo de su pobre
padre, y aunque mi misión ha terminado legalmente, me creo en el deber de defenderlo, pues
es un bonachón al que engaña cualquiera.... Y no te digo más.

Los dos hermanos callaron. Se hundió él en su sillón, mirando a los chicos, y ella quedó con
los ojos fijos en el suelo, el ceño fruncido y las mejillas de un rojo violáceo, como si la
rabia le produjese erisipela.

Rafael había salido del salón, Juanito jugueteaba con Miss, cada vez más inquieta y ladradora,
y Roberto, apoyado en el piano, hablaba con Concha, que sonreía, tecleando nerviosamente, haciendo
escalas que parecían cabriolas e iniciando temas conocidos, que se confundían fantásticamente.

--¿Dónde diablos están los otros?--pensaba el tío, paseando su vista por el salón.

Y los otros, o sea Amparo y Andresito, estaban en un balcón, mirando a la calle con la nariz
pegada al vidrio y protegidos por los cortinajes. El bebé, con sus ingenuidades de loquilla,
tenía una habilidad diabólica para salirse siempre con la suya. Había maniobrado hábilmente
para llevarse al hijo de Cuadros hacia aquel balcón, donde estaba la niña como en su casa,
lejos de miradas indiscretas y oídos curiosos.

Primero, habían hablado del tiempo, riéndose de los arabescos caprichosos que trazaban las
gotas de lluvia escurriéndose por el cristal; pero el joven, pálido y tembloroso, como si le
atormentase algún pensamiento oculto, guiaba la conversación insensiblemente, y Amparito se
dejaba arrastrar, segura de que por cualquier camino llegaría siempre adonde ella deseaba.

El tío miraba atentamente el cortinaje del balcón y las piernas de Andresito, que era lo único
visible de la pareja. En un momento que Concha cesó de teclear, oyó la voz de Amparo, que sonaba
lejana, como amortiguada por las cortinas.

--Pero Andresito... ¡si somos tan jóvenes!

¡Jóvenes! ¿Y qué importaba eso? Para el amor no hay edades, así como tampoco existían clases.
Lo aseguraba él, que era persona competente en tal materia, por ser poeta y no inédito, pues
sus triunfos había alcanzado en la Juventud Católica. Además, él no era ningún niño; dentro
de cuatro años sería abogado, y después, ¿quién sabe...? Su imaginación veía confusamente en
lontananza ese algo que acarician todos los aprendices de legistas. Un sillón de magistrado,
una poltrona de ministro o un taburete de escribiente... cualquier cosa; lo importante era
sentarse en algún sitio.

No, no eran jóvenes para amarse. Ya lo había dicho él en un soneto y media docena de quintillas
escritas con el pensamiento puesto en Amparito. El amor no tiene edad. Él la adoraba con la
inmensa pasión de los grandes poetas; y hablaba de Dante y Beatriz, de Petrarca y Laura, de
Ausias March y Teresa. Amparito escuchaba sonriente, complacida por esta letanía de poetas.
Todos muy señores míos, pero que los oía mentar por vez primera, a excepción de Ausias March,
por ser su nombre el de la calle donde ella tenía su modista.

A él le era imposible vivir si Amparito se negaba a amarle; necesitaba, para no aborrecer la
vida, que ella se decidiese a ser su musa, su inspiración. Y el lindo bebé, aunque por costumbre
seguía riendo, sentíase muy satisfecha en su interior de ser musa de alguien, honor que jamás
alcanzaría su hermana Concha. La consideración de hacerse superior a su hermana era lo que
más la empujaba a decir que sí. Además, un novio no se presenta a cada instante, y aunque existe
el inconveniente de que ella era hija de un doctor famoso--según afirmaba la mamá--, y los
padres de Andresito eran unos ordinarios--también según doña Manuela--, confiaba que, con el
tiempo, la brillante posición que se proponía conquistar el chico lo allanaría todo.

Y cuando con más calor hablaba Andresito de sus tormentos amorosos, la niña le interrumpió,
diciéndole con su tonillo bromista, como quien accede a tomar parte en un juego:

--Bueno; seremos novios... pero ¡por Dios! que nada sepa la mamá.

IV

El Carnaval de aquel año fue muy alegre para la familia de doña Manuela.

Las niñas se divirtieron. Rafaelito era socio de todos los círculos distinguidos y decentes
donde se baila, mientras arriba, en una habitación con luces verdes, guardada y vigilada como
antro de conspiradores, rueda la ruleta con sus vivos colorines o se agrupan los aficionados
en torno de las cuatro cartas del monte.

¡Qué noches aquéllas de emociones, de nerviosas alegrías, de mareos voluptuosos, y después
de aplastamiento, de brutal cansancio...! Juanito era el encargado de abrir la puerta cuando
la familia volvía del baile. En la madrugada, cerca de las cuatro, oía chirriar los pesados
portones, entraba el carruaje en el patio, con gran estrépito, y él saltaba de la cama metiéndose
los pantalones. La entrada de la familia le deslumbraba, sintiendo el infeliz una impresión
de vanidad. Las hermanitas, vestidas unas veces con trajes de sociedad, obra de una modista
francesa, y que todavía estaban por pagar; graciosamente disfrazadas otras de labradoras, de
pierrots o de calabresas; Rafael, de etiqueta, embutido en un gabán claro, tan corto de faldones
que parecía una americana; y la mamá satisfecha del éxito alcanzado por sus niñas, y a pesar
del cansancio, sonriente y majestuosa con su vestido de seda, que crujía a cada paso, y encima
el amplio abrigo de terciopelo, Juanito contemplaba con el cariño de un padre este desfile
desmayado que iba en busca de la cama, arrojando al paso en las sillas los adornos exteriores.
La mamá era siempre para él un ídolo, un ser superior, y los hermanos, al verlos tan elegantes,
le hacían recordar la época en que él, pequeño, pero avispado por el desvío maternal, les servía
de niñera cuidadosa, llevándolos en sus brazos y sufriendo con sublime abnegación sus infantiles
caprichos.

Levantábase mal arropado, tosiendo y tembloroso, a abrir la puerta, pues era preciso dejar,
dormir a las criadas, para que al día siguiente el cansancio no las entorpeciera en sus trabajos.
Además, la vista de su familia parecía traerle algo de los esplendores de la fiesta, el perfume
de las mujeres, los ecos de la orquesta, el voluptuoso desmayo de las amarteladas parejas,
el ambiente del salón, caldeado por mil luces, y el apasionamiento de los diálogos. Y después
de aspirar ese perfume fantástico de un mundo desconocido que su familia parecía traerle entre
los pliegues de sus ropas, el pobre muchacho volvía a la cama, para dormir tres horas más y
emprender después el camino de la tienda, mientras la mamá y los hermanos roncaban su primer
sueño con la fatiga propia de las noches de baile.

Después, a la hora de la comida, eran los comentarios, los recuerdos agradables, los berrinches
por supuestas ofensas que en el primer instante habían pasado inadvertidas, y que, agrandándose
ahora en la imaginación, pedían venganza. Las dos niñas recordaban la ligera sonrisa de las
de López al examinar sus disfraces de calabresas. ¡Reírse de ellas! ¡Las muy cursis! Mejor
harían en darse una vueltecita alrededor de ellas mismas, pues no es muy chic ir siempre a
los bailes con el mismo dominó blanco, de modo que al entrar con la careta puesta, toda la
pollería gritaba: «¡Ya están ahí las de López!»

Aparte de estos disgustos colectivos, las dos niñas los sufrían también particularmente. Conchita
estaba furiosa contra Roberto del Campo, «el pollo bonito», como le llamaban algunas. Mucha
palabrería, requiebros a granel; pero de declaración seria y formalmente... ¡ni esto! Bailaba
con ella, y a lo mejor abandonaba a su pareja y salía del salón, para no reaparecer hasta la
hora del galop final. Su excusa era siempre la misma: tenía algo que arreglar con Rafaelito.

--¿Dónde os metéis, condenados?--preguntaba la hermana al día siguiente--. ¿Qué diversión es
esa que os hace tan groseros?

--Mujer, son cosas de hombres. Mientras vosotras bailáis, nosotros nos dedicamos a ocupaciones
más serias.

Serias, sí; tan serias eran, que Rafaelito tenía frita a la mamá--según propia expresión--,
pidiéndola cinco duros al día siguiente de los bailes. El Carnaval tenía para él mala pata,
y al susurro de la orquesta que sonaba abajo, salía bailoteando siempre la carta contraria
y se llevaba al montecillo del banquero las pesetas de mamá.

Amparo también tenía sus disgustos. Lo que a ella le pasaba no podía ocurrirle a nadie. Aquello
no era tener novio ni tener nada. Vamos a ver: ¿para qué tiene novio una muchacha? Para lucirlo,
para que lo vean las amigas y rabien un poco... ¿no es verdad? Pues ella no podía darse tal
placer. Andresito no tenía un cuarto y no era socio de los círculos donde iba ella. Sus papas
lo llevaban bastante elegantito, eso sí, pero limitábanse a darle los domingos tres pesetas
y un sermón encargándole que no fuese derrochador ni calavera, que mirase en qué gastaba su
dinero... y mucho cuidadito con meterse en sitios malos. Mendigaba alguna invitación en las
redacciones de los periódicos, y si la conseguía, iba al baile, pero sólo hasta la una. ¿Ha
visto usted? Hasta la una, la hora en que iban llegando las amigas y el baile comenzaba a animarse.
Sólo una vez consiguió que Andresito se esperase hasta las dos, pero al día siguiente sospechó
con fundamento que en Las Tres Rosas habían estado a la espera, tras la puerta, unos ásperos
bigotes y una vara de medir, para dar las «¡buenas noches!» en las costillas al bailarín rezagado....
¿Era esto un novio serio? Y luego, aunque se quede usted sólita en el baile, mucho cuidado
con aceptar invitación de tantos pollos amables, porque si el señor sabe que se ha bailado,
pone un hocico inaguantable y habla de un tal Otelo, y dispara un soneto en que le pone a una
de pérfida, perjura e infiel, que no hay por dónde cogerla.... No señor; la cosa no puede seguir
así. Ella se tenía la culpa, por no hacer caso de mamá, que decía que los de Las Tres Rosas
eran unos ordinarios. Andresito era un buen chico, pero ella no podía estar en ridículo y que
las amigas le preguntasen irónicamente por su novio. Como se decidiera otro que estaba a la
vista, era cosa hecha: plantaba a Andresito.

Llegaron los tres días de Carnaval. Por las mañanas, entre las estudiantinas y comparsas que
corrían las calles, pasaban las familias ostentando a algún niño infeliz enfundado en la malla
de Lohengrin, el justillo de Quevedo o los rojos gregüescos de Mefistófeles. Los ciegos y ciegas
que el resto del año pregonan el papelito en el que está todo lo que se canta iban en cuadrilla,
guitarra al pecho, vestidos de pescadores u odaliscas, mal pergeñados, con mugrientos trajes
de ropería.

Muchachos con pliegos de colores voceaban las décimas y cuartetas, alegres y divertidas, para
las máscaras, colecciones de disparates métricos y porquerías rimadas, que por la tarde habían
de provocar alaridos de alegre escándalo en la Alameda. En la puerta del Mercado vendíanse
narices de cartón, bigotes de crin, ligas multicolores con sonoros cascabeles, y caretas pintadas,
capaces de oscurecer la imaginación de los escultores de la Edad Media, unas con los músculos
contraídos por el dolor, un ojo saltado y arroyos de bermellón cayendo por la mejilla; otras
con una frente inmensa, espantosa; caras de esqueletos con las fosas nasales hundidas y repugnantes;
narices que son higos aplastados, o que se prolongan como serpenteante trompa con un cascabel
en la punta; sonrisas contagiosas que provocan la carcajada y carrillos rubicundos a los que
se agarra un repugnante lagarto verde.

Los estudiantes, con el manteo terciado, tricornio en mano y ondeante en la manga el lazo de
la Facultad, corrían las calles como un rebaño loco, asediando a los transeúntes para sacarles
el dinero en nombre de la caridad. Por la plazuela de las de Pajares desfilaron los de Medicina
y Derecho, y en torno de la enhiesta bandera amarilla o roja, las músicas rompieron a tocar
alegres valses, que rápidamente poblaban los balcones.

La expansión ruidosa de la juventud libre y sin cuidados invadía la plaza como una atronadora
borrachera. Volaban los tricornios a los balcones; cada cara bonita provocaba floreos interminables,
en los que la hipérbole dilatábase hasta lo desconocido; y había muchacho que, impulsado por
alguna copita traidora, despreciaba la vulgar invitación de las escaleras y se encaramaba por
la fachada, agarrándose a las rejas, para entregar un ramo de flores a la niña y pedirle un
duro a la mamá. Concha y Amparo recibían una ovación y doña Manuela, roja de orgullo, repartía
sonrisas y pesetas a todo el enjambre de diablos negros, voceadores y gesticuladores que se
agolpaba bajo el balcón. A espaldas de ellas estaba Andresito Cuadros, que acababa de entrar
en el salón con el manteo terciado, una bayeta infame que tiznaba de negro la camisa y la cara.
Llevaba ramos para la mamá y las niñas, y estuvo locuaz, atrevido, aunque, con gran desencanto
de Amparito, no intentó como los otros, subir por la fachada, sistema que a ella le parecía
muy interesante.

Por la tarde, Nelet enganchaba la galerita, y a la Alameda, donde la fiesta tomaba el carácter
de una saturnal de esclavos ebrios.

El disfraz de labrador era un pretexto para toda clase de expansiones brutales; y acompañados
por el retintín de los cascabeles de las ligas, trotaban los grupos de zaragüelles planchados,
chalecos de flores, mantas ondeantes y tiesos pañuelos de seda. Un berrido ensordecedor, un
«¡che... e...e!» estridente, prolongado hasta lo infinito, como el grito de guerra de los pieles
rojas, conmovía las calles. Las criadas, endomingadas, huían despavoridas al escuchar el vocerío;
y pasaba la tribu al galope, dando furiosos saltos, con sus caretas horriblemente grotescas
y esgrimiendo por encima de sus cabezas enormes navajas de madera pintada con manchas de bermellón
en la corva hoja. Revueltos con ellos, iban los disfraces de siempre: mamarrachos con arrugadas
chisteras y levitas adornadas con arabescos de naipes; bebés que asomaban la poblada barba
bajo la careta y al compás del sonajero decían cínicas enormidades; diablos verdes silbando
con furia y azotando con el rabo a los papanatas; gitanos con un burro moribundo y sarnoso
tintado a fajas como una cebra; payasos ágiles, viejas haraposas con una repugnante escoba
al hombro, y los tíos de «¡al higuí!» golpeando la caña y haciendo saltar el cebo ante el escuadrón
goloso de muchachos con la boca abierta.

Toda esta invasión de figurones que trotaba por la ciudad, voceando como un manicomio suelto,
dirigíase a la Alameda, pasaba el puente del Real envuelta con el gentío, y así que estaban
en el paseo, iban unos hacia el Plantío para dar bromas insufribles, sonando las bofetadas
con la mayor facilidad. La galerita de las de Pajares, a pesar de su cubierta charolada, de
los arneses brillantes y de sus ruedas amarillas, tan finas y ligeras que parecían las de un
juguete, aparecía empequeñecida y deslustrada en el gigantesco rosario de berlinas y carretelas,
faetones y dog-carts que, como arcaduces de noria, estaban toda la tarde dando vueltas y más
vueltas por la avenida central del paseo.

Rafaelito habíase disfrazado de clown, y con otros de su calaña ocupaba un carro de mudanzas,
sobre cuya cubierta hacían diabluras y saludaban con palabras groseras a todas las muchachas
que estaban a tiro de sus voces aflautadas. ¡Vaya unos chicos graciosos!

El carruaje de doña Manuela llevaba escolta. Un buen mozo con negro dominó, montando un caballo
de alquiler, marchó toda la tarde como pegado a la portezuela, hablando con Concha, mientras
la mamá y Amparo miraban las máscaras. Era Roberto del Campo, el cual, a pesar de su gallardía,
iba resultando un posma, que sólo sabía decir floreos, sin llegar nunca a declararse. La mamá
comenzaba a no encontrar tan seductor a aquel espantanovios. Dios sabe cuántas proposiciones
habría perdido la niña por culpa de aquel hombre, que gozaba todas las intimidades de un novio,
sin decidirse nunca a serlo. Pero Conchita se mostraba sorda a los consejos de mamá. Ella lo
pescaría; los hombres que las echan de listos caen cuando menos lo esperan: todo era cuestión
de tiempo y de presentar buena cara.

Pasó el Carnaval y doña Manuela se vio en plena Cuaresma. Era la hora de purgar los derroches
y las alegrías de la temporada anterior. La modista francesa presentaba la cuenta de los trajes
de las niñas, y además hacía falta dinero para los gastos de la casa. Total, que doña Manuela
necesitaba tres mil pesetas.

Su amiga doña Clara, la corredora de los prestamistas, de la que don Juan hablaba pestes, no
encontraba dinero para la viuda de Pajares.

--Francamente, doña Manuela: ¡tiene usted por ese mundo tantos pagarés renovados y con intereses
que no siempre se cobran...! Mis amigos se niegan a dar un céntimo. ¡Si usted encontrase una
persona con garantías que quisiera avalar su firma...!

¡Persona con garantías...! No era tan fácil encontrar esto, que los prestamistas pedían con
tanta sencillez. Allí estaba su hermano, que solamente con una palabra podía sacarla del apuro;
pero no había que pensar en semejante miserable, capaz de dejar perecer a toda su familia antes
que desprenderse de una peseta. ¡Qué angustiosa situación! ¡Y que una persona distinguida como
ella tuviera que verse en tal aprieto por unas cuantas pesetas, cuando tantos miles había arrojado
por la ventana en otros tiempos...!

Había que pagar a la modista; la idea de que ésta podía decir la verdad a sus parroquianas,
todas señoras distinguidas, horrorizaba a la viuda, a pesar de que no tenía la menor amistad
con ellas. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04591</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>62060</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19240</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I will not do anything for you. When did your second husband promised me be
a model of economy and prudence, and I was so dumb, I lost time and to some money for launching
your fortune, which was water everywhere as an old boat .... Let me finish, Manuela; not interrupt
me. Do you want me to believe that still preserves all free of traps, as I gave it to you?
Quia, my daughter! In this century there are no miracles, and fifteen thousand dollars of capital
does not hold a carriage or the pageantry that you spend. The know everything, and if not,
listen.

And Don Juan, with a wealth of detail, as well versed in business, was describing her sister state
of his fortune. I had a piece of land free from the burden of a mortgage; income only if they
gave for revenues, and the very house in which she lived was a farm
that produced little, because of his vanity.

- When you got to be
a widow in my hands, lived in one of two rooms had rented the second
floor and head east.

A hard day is a great thing, and more on your situation. But you could not get used to be lady
of many steps, as you say in your jargon; wanted your room and your coach, as in the days of
crazy waste, and the pretext that the girls were growing and needed cock and lie, go down
to the floor and fell income also increased costs. Because you could not have a trunk, pull
carts and sedan, and in another time, sold a field to buy the galerita and the horse and keep
that bigardón, son of Aunt Quica, which robs you of barley and carob .... I know it bothers you
hear this, but I tell you to know that I suck my thumb or easily fooled me .... I have never
cast the illusion of becoming. You will always be the same Manuela, mad, the pretentious, and
die when you spend the last penny. Everyone is born with his character, and you are of those poor old
father singing the song:

/ * Arròs and trap, coat to fashion, It wraps around the ball the
valensiana!

*
       /
     
     And as if the tune's
     uncle was the signal
to start the music for girls they deafened the room with the click
of the piano and warbling strained.

Don Juan took courage with this crash. Seeing that the boys only attending the piano, went
on, but it raised more voice, with great alarm of his sister.

- Marching to your doom, Manuela.

When you're in misery, always remember that I am your brother, and
you have to eat you and yours .... But money, a penny!

Doña Manuela raised his head proudly, showing the burning eyes and ruddy cheeks.

- Thanks for the charity - said wryly -. But I have not got there.

- Reaching, reaching - "don Juan without losing the haze -.

You're on the road. Even today can endure, and you refuse to see that the eight thousand pieces,
you will seek to Dona Clara, the witch lender or other person in the class, and will sign
a promissory note for twelve or fourteen thousand.

You stuck in the mud and will never leave him much effort you do
you will sink.

If not I knew you both, I'd hand, but not "one and no more, St. Thomas', I remember a lot care with which
you followed my advice.

The lady was incensed by the rough language of his brother. It was very owner of not giving that
misery, at last, was what she had always believed: a heartless miser. But his demand not authorized
to bore you with so much preaching.

- Shut up, John, I get nervous with your rudeness.

- Silent, daughter does not want to bother you on a day like this.

But I can only get a warning. Those who are so drowned like you cling to straws. Juanito has a
farm worth anything: the garden of Alcira, you had to respect as All rights reserved. As now the boy
is older and you want both, I warn you that if to make money you
mix in your deals will have to Vertel me.

I am your guardian, on behalf of his poor father, and my mission
is finished but legally, I believe in the duty to defend because which
is a good-natured fool anyone .... And do not tell you more.

The two brothers were silent. He sank into his chair, watching the kids, and she was left with
eyes on the ground, frowning and purplish-red cheeks, as if erysipelas produjese anger him.

Rafael
had left the room, playing with Miss Juanito increasingly restless,
barking, and Robert, leaning on the piano, talking to Concha, who
smiled nervously typing, making scales seemed to prance and initiating
familiar topics that blended beautifully.

- Where the hell are the
others? - Thought the man, his eyes wandering around the room.

And the other, or Andresito Amparo and were on a balcony overlooking the street with his nose
pressed against the glass and protected by curtains.

The baby, with its naive Loquillo, had a devilish ability to always get his way. Had maneuvered
deftly to be the son of blocks to the balcony, where the child was at home, away from prying eyes
and curious ears.

First, had spoken of the time, laughing at the capricious arabesques traced the raindrops trickling
through the glass, but the young, pale and trembling, as if torment some hidden thought, guided
the conversation insensibly, and Amparito is drag left, sure that either way would always where
she wanted.

The guy looked closely at the curtain of the balcony and legs Andresito, which was all visible
partner.

At a time that Shell stopped typing, Amparo's voice, which sounded distant, as buffered by the
curtains.

- But Andresito ... If we are so young!

Young! And what of that? For love there is no age, nor were no classes.

I assured him that he was quite competent in this matter, being a poet and not unheard of for
his triumphs were achieved in the Catholic Youth. In addition, he was no child inside four years
would be a lawyer, and then who knows ...? His imagination saw confusedly the distance that something
that caress every apprentice lawyers. An armchair judge an easy chair or stool Minister clerk
... anything, it was important sit down somewhere.

No, they were young to love. I had told him in a sonnet and a half dozen stanzas written with
the thought put into Amparito. Love has no age.

He loved to immense passion of the great poets, and spoke of Dante and Beatrice, Petrarch and
Laura Ausias March and Teresa. Amparito listened smiling, pleased
with this litany of poets.

All very gentlemen, but that lie for the first time I heard, with
the exception of Ausias March, because his name from the street where
she had her dressmaker.

To him it was impossible to live if Amparito refused to love, need, not abhor life, she decided
to become his muse, his inspiration. And the cute baby, but the habit still laughing, he felt
very happy to be inside someone's muse, honor ever Concha reach his sister. Be considering her
sister was more than what pushed further to say yes.

In addition, a no-show boyfriend every moment, and although there the disadvantage that she
was the daughter of a famous doctor - as claimed by the mother - and the Andresito parents were
just ordinary - also according to Dona Manuela - was confident that with the time, the brilliant
position to win the boy intended to pave everything.

And when he spoke hotter Andresito its torments of love, the girl interrupted telling your twang
joker, as he agrees to take part in a game:

- Well, we'll be lovers ... but by God! Mom knows nothing.

IV

The Carnival of that year was very happy for the family of Dona Manuela.

The girls had fun. Rafaelito was a partner in all circles distinguished and decent where dancing,
while upstairs in a room with light green, guarded and monitored
as den of conspirators, the roulette wheel with its bright colorful
or fans are grouped around the four letters of the mountain.

What nights those emotions, joys nerve, voluptuous dizziness, and then crushing, brutal tired ...!
Johnny was responsible for opening the door when The family returned the ball. At dawn, about
four, I heard screeching heavy gates, entered the carriage in the courtyard, with a crash, and
he jumped off the bed getting pants. The entrance of the family was dazzled, feeling unhappy impression
vanity. The sisters, sometimes dressed in costumes of society, the work of a dressmaker French,
and were still payable; gracefully disguised other Labrador to pierrots or Calabrese, Rafael,
tag, embedded in a clear coat, so short skirts seemed like an American,
and the mother satisfied with the success of their children, despite
Fatigue, smiling and majestic with her silk dress, which creaked at
every step, and above the large velvet coat, Johnny watched with a
father's love this show that was passed out in search of the bed,
throwing chairs to step in the exterior trim.

The mom was always for him an idol, a superior being, and the brothers, seeing them as smart, did
you remember the time when he, small but smart by diverting maternal served them careful babysitting,
taking them in her arms and struggling with their children's sublime abnegation whims.

Inadequate clothing rose up, coughing and trembling, to open the door, it was necessary to
leave, the maids sleep, so tired the next day not hindered in their work. In addition, the
sight of his family seemed to bring some of the highlights of the
festival, the perfume women, the echoes of the orchestra, the faint
of infatuation voluptuous pairs the classroom environment, heated
by a thousand lights, and the passion of the dialogues.

And then vacuuming the great perfume from an unknown world that seemed to bring his family from the
folds of their clothes, the poor boy back to bed to sleep three hours and then take the path
of the store, while mom and brothers snored his first sleep with fatigue own dance night.

Then, at the lunch were the comments the pleasant memories, tantrums
for alleged offenses in the first moment had passed unnoticed, and
that widening now in the imagination, calling for revenge.

Both girls remembered the slight smile of Lopez to examine their Calabrian costumes. Laugh at
them! The very cheesy!

Best in would be a turn around themselves, it is not always going to chic dancing with the same
white domino, so to get the mask on, all poultry shouted: "You are
there those of Lopez!"

Apart from these collective disappointment, the two girls the also suffered particularly. Conchita
Roberto was furious at the Field, "the nice chicken," as some call
it.

Many verbiage, compliments bulk, but serious and formal declaration ... Or this! Dancing with it,
and maybe abandoned his partner and left the room, not to reappear until time of final galop. His
excuse was always the same: I had something to settle with Rafaelito.

- Where you meteis, damned? - Asked his sister the following day -. What fun is that makes you
so rude?

- Women are things of men. While you bailáis, we are dedicated to jobs more serious.

Serious, yes, how serious they were, they had fried Rafaelito the mother - as self-expression -
five dollars a day asking her after the dance. The Carnival was bad luck for him, and the murmur
of the orchestra that sounded down, always dancing around the letter went contrary and took the mound
of the PTA mom's banker.

Amparo also had its disappointments. What happened she could not happen to anyone. What was not
having a boyfriend or have anything. Let's see: what a girl has a boyfriend? To wear it, for you
to see the friends and rage a little ... Is not it? As such it could not be pleasure. Andresito
had no room and it was not a member of the circles where it was. Her parents I had quite elegantito,
yes, but give limitábanse three pesetas Sunday and entrusting a sermon that was not wasteful
or skull, which looked into how he spent his money ... and very carefully
with getting into bad places.

Begging any invitation in newspaper offices, and if succeeded, went to the dance, but only until
one o'clock. Has you see? Until one, the time they arrived the friends and dance began to cheer.
Only once got Andresito wait until two o'clock, but the next day suspected Based in Las Tres Rosas
had been waiting, behind the door, some rough whiskers and a measuring stick to give the "good evening"
in the ribs behind the dancer .... Was this a serious boyfriend? And then, if you stay alone
in the dance, very careful to accept his kind invitation of so many
chickens, because if the Lord knows who has danced put a muzzle unbearable
and Othello speaks of one, and shoot a sonnet in which he puts a of
perfidious, perjured and faithless, no where to pick it up .... No,
sir, the thing can not continue well.

She was to blame for not heeding mom, saying that the Three Roses were just ordinary. Andresito
was a good kid, but she could not be a fool and her friends ask him ironically by her boyfriend.
As another who was to decide the view was done: planting a Andresito.

They arrived three days of Carnival. In the morning, between the student music and bands that
ran the streets, flaunting families spent some unhappy child wrapped in the mesh Lohengrin,
the doublet of Quevedo or the red breeches of Mephistopheles. The blind and blind the rest of the year
touting the piece of paper on which you are all that were sung by a gang, guitar to the chest,
or belly dancers dressed as fishermen, poorly arranged, with dirty clothes of ropería.

Sheets of colored boys hawked with tenths and quatrains, happy and fun to masks, collections
of nonsense and rubbish rhymed metric that afternoon had to provoke howls of outrage in the Alameda
happy. At the door vendíanse Market cardboard noses, whiskers Mane, leagues multicolored bells
sound and painted masks, able to obscure the imagination of the sculptors of the Middle Ages,
some with muscles incurred by the pain, eye vermilion jumped and
streams running down his cheek, others with a huge front, frightful
faces of skeletons with sunken nostrils and disgusting; figs noses
are crushed, or extend as winding tube with a bell at the tip causing
contagious smiles and laughter to those ruddy cheeks grabs a nasty
green lizard.

Students, with the raw cloak, tricorn hat in hand and waving his sleeve loop School, ran the
streets like a mad herd, harassing passers-by to extract money on behalf of charity. By the square
of the Pajares paraded Medicine and Law, and around the erect yellow or red flag, broke the
music playing merry waltzes, who quickly populated the balconies.

Noisy expansion of youth care free and invaded the place as a deafening drunkenness. Three-cornered
hats flew onto the balconies, each pretty face flourishes caused endless where the hyperbole dilatábase
to the unknown, and boy was driven by a treacherous shot, he despised the vulgar invitation of
the stairs, climbing the front, holding onto the bars, to deliver a bouquet of flowers to the
girl and ask a drive to the mother.

Concha y Amparo received a standing ovation and Dona Manuela, red with pride, divided ESP smiles
and the whole swarm of black devils, hawkers and gestures that crowded
under the balcony.

Behind them was Andresito Cuadros, who had just entered in the cloak room with plywood, a cloth
smeared with black infamous shirt and face. He carried bouquets for Mom and girls, and was talkative,
bold, though, with great disappointment Amparito, did not try like the others, climbing the
facade, a system that she thought very interesting.

In the afternoon, the galerita nelet hooked, and Alameda, where the party took the character
a drunken slave Saturnalia.

The costume of a peasant was a pretext for all sorts of brutal expansions, and accompanied
by the jingling of the bells of the leagues, groups breeches trotting ironed flowers vests,
blankets waving and stiff silk scarves. A deafening howl, a "Che ... e. .. e! "shrill, extended
to infinity, as the battle cry of the skin red, touched the streets. The maids, Sunday best,
they fled in panic upon hearing the shouting; and spent the tribe at a gallop, taking furious jumps,
with its horribly grotesque masks and brandishing over their heads
huge painted wood blades with vermilion spots the curved blade.

Scrambled eggs with them, were the costumes as always: doodles with wrinkled Levites hats and
decorated with arabesques of cards, babies poking their beard under the mask and rattle in
time to the cynical saying enormities, whistling Green Devils with anger and lashing with
its tail to fool; Roma with a mangy donkey dying tinted stripes like a zebra, clowns agile,
with a nasty old ragged broom shoulder, and uncles' to Higui! "hitting the pole and blowing
up the bait before the squad sweet boys with their mouths open.

All this invasion of dummies who jogged around the city, shouting
like a lunatic asylum loose headed to the Alameda, passed the bridge
of the Royal involved with the crowd, and so they were on the promenade,
going around to the plantation to give unbearable joke, sounding slaps
with the greatest ease.

The galerita of Pajares, despite its varnished cover of harnesses and bright yellow wheels, so
thin and light that looked like a toy, appeared shrunken and dull at the huge chain of saloons
and spools, Factories and dog-carts, as arcaduces the wheel, were
all late round and round the central avenue of the ride.

Rafaelito had disguised themselves as clowns, and their ilk occupied a moving car, on the cover
of which mischief were greeted with rude words and all the girls they were within range of their
voices piping. Look at those funny guys!

The coach of Dona Manuela had an escort. A handsome man with black domino, riding a horse rent,
went all afternoon and stuck to the door, talking to Shell, while Amparo watching mom and masks.
It was Roberto del Campo, which, despite its elegance, was becoming
a postmodern, which flourishes only knew that, but never declared.

Mom beginning to find not so appealing to that espantanovios. God knows how many propositions
have lost the child because of this man, who enjoyed all the intimacies of a boyfriend never to
be undecided. But Conchita is deaf to the advice from Mom. She would fish, men ready to lay them
to fall when you least expect it: everything was a matter time and
present a good face.

Passed and Dona Manuela Carnival was in full Lent. It was time to purge the wastage and joys of the
season. The French couturier had the account suits for girls, and also needed money for household
expenses. Total, Dona Manuela needed three thousand.

Her friend Donna Clara, the broker lenders, of which Don Juan spoke pests, not found money for the
widow of Pajares.

- Frankly, Dona Manuela: you have so many notes that world, and renewed interest not always charge
...! My friends refuse to give a penny.

If you found a person with guarantees that would endorse his signature ...!

Person guarantees ...! It was not so easy to find this, asked lenders
to so simply. There was his brother, only with a word could get her
out of trouble; but had to think about such miserable, able to leave
his entire family perish before Losing a peseta. What a plight! And
as a distinguished person she had to put in a predicament for a few
pesetas, when so many thousands had thrown through the window at other
times ...!

Had to pay the dressmaker, the idea that it could tell
the truth to their parishioners, all ladies who, horrified by the
widow, although she had no friends with them</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>