<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document00476</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>3118</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>1515</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Sea como sea, y sin dar el fallo, nadie niega que Shakspeare es un ingenio de primer orden.
Ni Voltaire ni Moratin lo negaron.

La gloria de este poeta empezó cuando vivía y escribía sus dramas. Después no se ha eclipsado
nunca y ha ido e irá creciendo cada vez más con el andar del tiempo. Pero la grandeza de las
montañas no se ve ni se mide de cerca. Aunque se sabe poco de la vida de Shakspeare, parece
probable que le conocieron y trataron muchos hombres eminentes de la brillante época en que
vivió Raleigh, Bacon, el conde de Essex, Milton, Hales, Keplero, Belarmino, Alberico Gentile,
Paolo Sarpi, Vieta y otros mil le conocían. Ninguno despreció su talento: ninguno dejó de estimar
el mérito de sus dramas; pero ninguno tampoco le rindió aquel culto, aquella adoración que
hoy le rinde lo más ilustre, instruido, inteligente y dichoso del linaje humano. Hasta que
llegó el siglo XIX, exclaman sus más fervientes admiradores, hasta que llegó este siglo, cuyo
genio es Hamlet viviente, no pudo haber lectores que entendiesen la tragedia de Hamlet. Ahora
la literatura, la filosofía y el pensamiento todo, son Shakspeare. Su espíritu es el horizonte
más allá del cual nada vemos, nada descubrimos, aunque nos esforcemos con ansia por columbrar
lo venidero.

Singular sería que siendo Shakspeare tan adorado entre los extraños, lo fuese menos entre los
propios; entre los ingleses, que son tan patriotas. En Inglaterra ha tenido el gran dramático
multitud de biógrafos, críticos, comentadores y panegiristas. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01045</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>27067</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>1455</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Whatever the case, and without giving the ruling, no one denies that Shakspeare is a first order
wit. Neither Voltaire nor Moratin denied.

The glory of the poet began when he lived and wrote his plays. After it has not been eclipsed
and never has been and will grow increasingly with the passage of time. But the greatness of
mountains were not seen or measured closely. Although little is known about the life of Shakspeare,
it seems likely knew him and tried many eminent men of the brilliant period in which Raleigh lived,
Bacon, the Earl of Essex, Milton, Hales, Kepler, Bellarmine, Alberico Gentile, Paolo Sarpi,
Vieta and a thousand others who knew him. None despised his talent did not consider it any
the merit of his plays, but no one paid him no worship, worship that now pays the most famous,
educated, intelligent and blessed the human race. Until was the nineteenth century, his most
fervent admirers exclaim, until he reached this age, whose Hamlet genius is living, readers could
not have understood the tragedy of Hamlet. Now literature, philosophy and thinking everything
is Shakspeare.

Your mind is the horizon beyond which we see nothing, nothing found, while we strive forward
by descry what is to come.
Singular Shakspeare would be so adored being among strangers, it
was less among themselves, among the English, who are so patriotic.
In England has had the great dramatic many biographers, critics, commentators,
and apologists</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>