<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>195883</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22330</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

El cocinero no admitía críticas y protestas. Este milagro era innegable. El lo había visto
con sus ojos cuando estaban buenos; lo había visto en un cuadro antiguo del monasterio del
Puig, y todo aparecía en la tabla con el relieve de la verdad: la galera, el rey, el peixòt,
y la Virgen en lo alto dándole la orden.

La brisa levantaba el faldón del narrador, apareciendo su abdomen partido en dos hemisferios
por la tirantez del botón único.

--Tío Caragòl, ¡que se le escapa!--avisaba una voz burlona.

El santo hombre sonreía con la calma seráfica del que se ve más allá, de las pompas y vanidades
de la existencia.

--Déjalo: ya no vuela.

Y emprendía el relato de un nuevo milagro.

Ferragut asimilaba estas exaltaciones del cocinero á su ligereza de ropa en todo tiempo. Ardía
en su interior un fuego incesantemente renovado. En los días brumosos subía al puente con unos
vasos de bebida humeante que él llamaba calentets. Nada mejor para los hombres que habían de
pasar largas horas á la intemperie, en inmóvil vigilancia. Era café mezclado con aguardiente
de caña, pero en desiguales proporciones, siendo más el alcohol que el líquido negro. Tòni
bebía rápidamente todos los vasos ofrecidos. El capitán los rechazaba, pidiendo café puro.

Su sobriedad era la del antiguo nauta: la sobriedad del padre Ulises, que mezclaba el vino
con agua en todas sus libaciones. Las divinidades del viejo mar no amaban las bebidas alcohólicas.
Anfitrita y las nereidas sólo aceptaban en sus altares frutos de la tierra, sacrificios de
palomas, libaciones de leche. Tal vez á causa de esto los marineros del Mediterráneo, siguiendo
una preocupación hereditaria, veían en la embriaguez el más vil de los rebajamientos. Los que
no eran sobrios evitaban emborracharse francamente como los marineros de otros mares, disimulando
la rudeza del brebaje alcohólico con el café ó con el azúcar.

Caragòl era el encargado de beberse todos los «calentitos» despreciados por el capitán, con
otros más que se dedicaba á sí mismo en el misterio de la cocina. En los días calurosos confeccionaba
refresquets, y estos «refrescos» eran vasos enormes, mitad de agua, mitad de caña, sobre un
grueso lecho de azúcar, mixtura que hacía pasar fulminantemente, sin gradaciones, de la vulgar
serenidad á una angélica embriaguez.

El capitán le reñía al ver sus ojos inflamados y enrojecidos. Iba á quedarse ciego... Pero
él no se conmovía ante la amenaza. Necesitaba celebrar á su modo la prosperidad del buque.
Y de esta prosperidad, lo más interesante para él era poder abusar del aceite y de la caña,
sin miedo á recriminaciones en el momento de las cuentas. ¡Cristo del Grao, que durase siempre
la guerra!...

El tercer viaje de la América del Sur á Europa vino á terminarlo el Mare nostrum en Nápoles,
donde desembarcó trigo y cueros. Una colisión á la entrada del puerto con un buque-hospital
inglés que iba á los Dardanelos abolló su popa, rompiéndole además una aleta de la hélice.

Tòni rugió de impaciencia al enterarse de que tendrían que permanecer cerca de un mes en forzosa
inmovilidad. Italia no había intervenido aún en la guerra, pero sus precauciones defensivas
acaparaban todas las industrias navales. No era posible hacer antes la reparación. Ferragut
calculó lo que representaba para sus negocios esta pérdida de tiempo. Le esperaban valiosos
fletes en Marsella y Barcelona. Pero queriendo tranquilizarse á sí mismo y aplacar á su segundo,
repetía muchas veces:

--Inglaterra nos indemnizará... Los ingleses son generosos.

Y para adormecer su impaciencia, se trasladaba á tierra.

Nápoles no le parecía gran cosa al compararla con otras ciudades célebres italianas. Su verdadera
belleza era el golfo inmenso, entre colinas de naranjos y pinos, con un segundo marco de montañas,
una de las cuales extendía sobre el azul del cielo su eterna cimera de vapores volcánicos.

El caserío no abundaba en edificios famosos. Los monarcas de Nápoles habían sido las más de
las veces extranjeros que residían lejos y gobernaban por delegación. Las mejores calles, los
palacios, las fontanas monumentales, procedían de los virreyes españoles. Un soberano de origen
mixto. Carlos III, castellano de nacimiento y napolitano de corazón, había hecho lo mejor de
la ciudad. Sus entusiasmos de constructor embellecían aún los barrios antiguos con obras semejantes
á las que había levantado años después en España al ocupar su trono.

Luego de admirar en los museos la estatuaria griega y los objetos desenterrados que revelaban
la vida íntima de los antiguos, corrió Ulises las arterias tortuosas y muchas veces sombrías
de los barrios populares.

Eran calles en pendiente, formando rellanos, flanqueadas de casas estrechas y altísimas. Todos
los huecos tenían balcones, y de una baranda á la de enfrente se tendían cuerdas, empavesadas
con ropas de diversos colores puestas á secar. La fecundidad napolitana hacía hervir de gentío
estas callejuelas. En torno de las cocinas al aire libre se agolpaban los clientes, comiendo
de pies los macarrones hervidos ó los pedazos de carne.

Anunciaban los vendedores sus géneros con pregones melódicos semejantes á romanzan, y de los
balcones bajaban á su encuentro cordeles rematados por castillos. Los regateos y compras eran
desde el fondo de la calle-zanja á los séptimos pisos. En cambio, los rebaños de cabras subían
las escaleras tortuosas, con la agilidad de la costumbre, para dejarse vaciar las ubres en
todas las mesetas.

Los muelles de la Marinela atraían al capitán por su «color» de puerto mediterráneo. La unidad
italiana había derribado y reconstruido mucho, pero aún quedaban en pie varias filas de casitas,
bajas de techo, con la fachada blanca ó rosada, las puertas verdes y el piso bajo más avanzado
que el superior, sirviendo de sostén á una galería con balaustres de madera. Todo lo que en
ellas no era ladrillo era carpintería gruesa, igual al trabajo de los calafates. El hierro
no existía en estas construcciones terrestres que recordaban el buque de vela. Las piezas eran
obscuras como camarotes. Por las ventanas se veían grandes caracolas de mar sobre las cómodas,
cuadros de pintura dura y pueril representando fragatas, conchas multicolores traídas de lejanos
mares.

Estas viviendas se repetían en todos los puertos del Mediterráneo, como si fuesen obra de la
misma mano. Ferragut las había visto de niño en el Grao de Valencia, y todavía las encontraba
en la Barceloneta, en los suburbios de Marsella, en la Niza vieja, en los puertos de las islas
occidentales, en las marinas de la costa africana ocupadas por malteses y sicilianos.

Sobre el caserío alineado á lo largo de la Marinela, las iglesias de Nápoles asomaban sus cúpulas
y torres con tejas barnizadas, verdes y amarillas. Más que techos de templos cristianos, parecían
remates de baños orientales.

Ya no existía el lazarone descalzo y con gorro rojo, pero la muchedumbre--vestida como los
trabajadores de todos los puertos--se aglomeraba aún en torno del cartelón pintarrajeado que
representaba un crimen, un milagro ó un específico prodigioso, escuchando en silencio el relato
del narrador ó el charlatán. Los viejos recitantes populares declamaban con heroicos manoteos
las octavas épicas del Tasso. Sonaban arpas y violines acompañando la última romanza que Nápoles
había puesto de moda en el mundo entero. Los puestos de los ostricarios esparcían un perfume
orgánico de ola muerta. En torno de ellos, las conchas vacías de las ostras destacaban sobre
el barro los redondeles de su cal nacarada.

Junto á la antigua Capitanía del puerto--palacete de Carlos III, blanco y azul, con una imagen
de la Inmaculada--se aglomeraban los carros del desembarque. Ferragut los encontraba lo mismo
que años antes, con sus tiros de híbrida originalidad. Las varas estaban ocupadas por un buey
blanco, lustroso, con cuernos enormes y muy abiertos, un animal semejante á los que figuraban
en las ceremonias religiosas de los antiguos. A su derecha iba enganchado un caballo, á su
izquierda un asno grande y enjuto. Y este triple y discordante enganche se repetía en todos
los carros inmóviles ante los buques á lo largo de los muelles ó volteando sus pesadas ruedas
por la pendiente que conduce á la ciudad alta.

A los pocos días, el capitán se sintió fatigado de Nápoles y su bullicio. En los cafés de la
calle de Toledo y de la Galería de Humberto I tenía que defenderse de unos mozos inquietantes,
con chaleco de gran escote, corbata de mariposa y un pequeño fieltro ladeado sobre las guedejas,
que le proponían en voz baja espectáculos inauditos organizados para recreo de los extranjeros.

Bastante había visto también las pinturas y objetos domésticos de las ciudades antiguas desenterradas.
Las lubricidades del gabinete secreto acababan por irritarle. Le parecía un recreo de invertido
contemplar tantas fantasías pueriles de la escultura y la pintura teniendo el falo como personaje
principal...

Una mañana tomó el tren, y luego de faldear la montaña humeante del Vesubio, pasando entre
pueblos de color de rosa circundados de viñas, bajó en una estación: Pompeya.

De los hoteles y restoranes, en fúnebre soledad, surgieron los guías como un enjambre de avispas
súbitamente despertadas. Se lamentaban de la guerra, que había cortado la circulación de viajeros.
El era tal vez el único que iba á llegar en todo el día. «¡Señor, á cualquier precio!...» Pero
el marino siguió adelante. Siempre, al acordarse de Pompeya, había formulado el deseo de volver
á verla solo, absolutamente solo, para recibir una impresión directa de la vida antigua.

Su primera visita había sido diez y siete años antes, cuando era piloto de un velero catalán,
surto en el puerto de Nápoles, aprovechando la baratura de precios de un domingo. Todo lo había
visto confundido en un grupo que se empujaba y pisaba por escuchar al guía de más cerca.

Al frente de la expedición iba un sacerdote joven y elegante, un monseñor romano vestido de
seda, y con él dos damas extranjeras y guapetonas, que se plantaban en los lugares más altos,
teniendo sus faldas algo levantadas por miedo á las salamanquesas que serpenteaban en las ruinas.
Ferragut, con la humildad de la admiración, se quedaba siempre abajo, viéndolo todo al través
de sus piernas. «¡Ay! ¡veintidós años!...» Luego, cuando oía hablar de Pompeya, se verificaba
en su memoria una superposición de imágenes: «Muy hermoso, muy interesante.» Veía las calles,
los palacios, los templos, pero en segundo término, como un fondo esfumado, mientras se destacaban
en primera línea cuatro piernas magníficas, una columnata humana de fustes esbeltos forrados
en seda negra que transparentaba la blancura de la carne.

La soledad tantas veces deseada para su segunda visita le salió al encuentro. La ciudad muerta
no tenía otros ruidos que el aleteo de los insectos sobre las plantas, que empezaba á vestir
la primavera, y el correteo invisible de los reptiles bajo las capas de hiedra.

En la Puerta Herculana, el guardián del pequeño museo dejó que Ferragut examinase en paz los
vaciados de los cadáveres seculares: varios pompeyanos de yeso en la actitud del terror en
que los había sorprendido la muerte. No abandonó la silla para molestarle con sus explicaciones;
apenas levantó los ojos del diario que tenía delante. Le absorbían las noticias de Roma, las
intrigas de los diplomáticos alemanes, la posibilidad de que Italia entrase en la guerra.

Luego, en las calles solitarias, el marino tropezó con la misma preocupación. Retumbaban sus
pasos bajo la luz del sol con una sonoridad igual á la de los subterráneos de huecas tumbas.
Al detenerse, renacía el silencio: «un silencio de dos mil años», según pensaba Ferragut. Y
en este silencio antiguo sonaban voces lejanas con la violencia de una agria discusión. Eran
los guardianes y los empleados de las excavaciones, que, faltos de trabajo, gesticulaban y
se insultaban en sus asientos de veinte siglos, profundamente separados por el entusiasmo patriótico
ó el miedo á los horrores de la guerra.

Ferragut, con el plano en la mano, pasó ante estos grupos, sin que nadie se levantase para
guiarle. Durante dos horas pudo creerse un vecino de la antigua Pompeya que había quedado solo
en la ciudad en un día de fiesta dedicado á las divinidades campestres. Su mirada iba hasta
el último extremo de las rectas calles, sin tropezar con personas ni cosas que le recordasen
los tiempos modernos.

Pompeya le pareció más pequeña en esta soledad. Era un cruzamiento de vías estrechas con altas
aceras pavimentadas de bloques poligonales de lava azul. En sus intersticios formaba la fecundidad
primaveral apretados cordones de hierba moteados de florecillas. Carruajes milenarios, de los
que no quedaba ni el polvo, habían abierto con sus ruedas profundos relejes en este pavimento.
En todas las encrucijadas se encontraba una fuente pública con un mascarón que había arrojado
agua por su boca.

Ciertos letreros rojos de las paredes eran anuncios de elecciones verificadas en los principios
de la era actual: candidaturas de edil ó de diunviro que se recomendaban á los electores pompeyanos.
Unas puertas ostentaban el falo, para conjurar el mal de ojo; otras un par de serpientes enroscadas,
símbolo de la vida familiar. En los rincones de las callejuelas, un verso latino grabado en
el muro rogaba al transeúnte que se abstuviese de sucios desahogos. Vivían aún en las paredes
de estuco caricaturas y monigotes, obra de los pilluelos del siglo de César.

Las casas estaban construídas á la ligera sobre un suelo en el que se habían sucedido los temblores,
hasta la llegada de la catástrofe final. Sólo tenían de ladrillos ó de cemento el piso bajo.
Los otros eran de maderos, y habían sido devorados por el fuego volcánico, quedando únicamente
las escaleras.

En esta ciudad graciosa, de vida amable y fácil, más griega que romana, todos los pisos bajos
de las casas plebeyas habían estado ocupados por pequeños comercios. Eran tiendas con la puerta
del mismo tamaño que el establecimiento: cuevas cuadradas, iguales á las de los zocos árabes,
que dejan ver hasta sus últimos rincones al comprador detenido en la calle. Muchas guardaban
aún sus mostradores de piedra y sus tinajas de barro. Los edificios particulares carecían de
fachada. Sus muros exteriores eran lisos, inabordables, con algún que otro tragaluz enrejado
y alto, lo mismo que en los palacios de Oriente. La puerta se asemejaba á un portillo de escape;
toda la vida estaba vuelta hacia el interior, afluyendo las riquezas y magnificencias al patio
central, adornado con piscinas, estatuas y arriates de flores.

El mármol era raro. Las columnas, construídas con ladrillos, estaban cubiertas de un estuco
que ofrecía su superficie á la pintura. Pompeya había sido una ciudad policroma. Todas las
columnas, rojas ó amarillas, tenían capiteles de diversos colores. Predominaba en los muros
el negro charolado con el rojo y el ámbar, ocupando su centro un pequeño cuadro, las más de
las veces erótico. En los frisos cabalgaban amores y tritones entre emblemas campestres y marítimos.

Cansado de su excursión por la muerta ciudad, Ferragut se sentó en un banco de piedra entre
las ruinas de un templo. Miraba el plano puesto sobre sus rodillas, saboreando los títulos
con que habían sido designadas las construcciones más interesantes á causa de un mosaico ó
de una pintura: villa de Diómedes, casa de Meleagro, de Adonis herido, del Laberinto, del Fauno,
del Muro Negro. Los nombres de las calles no eran menos interesantes: vía de las Termas, vía
de las Tumbas, vía de la Abundancia, vía de los Teatros.

Un ruido de pasos hizo levantar la cabeza al marino. Dos señoras marchaban precedidas por un
guía. Eran de alta estatura y andar firme. Llevaban el rostro cubierto con el velo del sombrero
y otro velo más grande cruzaba sus espaldas, sostenido por los brazos á guisa de chal. Ferragut
adivinó una diferencia importante en las edades de las dos. La más gruesa se movía con disimulada
pesadez. Su paso era vivo, pero apoyaba en el suelo con cierta autoridad sus pies voluminosos,
calzados ampliamente y con tacones bajos. La joven, más alta y esbelta, caminaba á pequeños
saltos, como un ave que sólo sabe volar, contoneándose sobre sus empinados talones.

Las dos miraron con inquietud á este hombre que surgía inesperadamente entre las ruinas. Mostraban
el aire preocupado y temeroso del que va á un lugar prohibido ó medita una mala acción. Su
primer movimiento fué de retroceso; pero el guía continuó impasible su camino, y acabaron por
seguirle.

Ferragut sonrió. Sabía adónde iban. La callejuela de los Lupanares estaba próxima. El guardián
abriría una puerta, quedándose luego en acecho, con dramática ansiedad, como si expusiera su
empleo por esta complacencia á cambio de una propina. Y las dos señoras iban á ver unas pinturas
borrosas que demuestran cómo no hay nada nuevo y original en este mundo: figuras amarillentas
y desnudas, iguales á primera vista, sin otra novedad que el exagerado abultamiento del sexo
diferencial.

Media hora después, Ulises abandonó su banco con las ojos fatigados por la inmovilidad severa
de las ruinas. En la calle de las Termas volvió á visitar la casa del poeta trágico; luego
admiró la de Pansa, la más grande y lujosa de la ciudad. Este Pansa había sido, indudablemente,
el burgués más ostentoso de Pompeya. Su vivienda ocupaba toda una ínsula. El xystos, jardín
adosado á la casa, había sido replantado con una vegetación griega de cipreses y laureles entre
cuadros de rosas y violetas.

Al seguir el muro exterior del jardín, Ferragut encontró á las dos señoras. Cotemplaban las
flores á través de los barrotes de una puerta. La más joven expresaba en inglés su admiración
por unas rosas que balanceaban su púrpura en torno del pedestal de un viejo fauno.

Ulises experimentó un irresistible deseo de mostrarse intrépido y galante. Quiso interesar
á las dos extranjeras con un homenaje teatral. Sintió esa necesidad de llamar la atención con
algo gallardo y atrevido que agita á todo español lejos de su patria.

Con una agilidad de trepador de arboladuras, salvó de un salto la tapia del jardín. Las dos
señoras dieron un grito de sorpresa, como si presenciasen algo inaudito. Esta audacia pareció
trastornar las ideas de la más vieja, acostumbrada á la vida en pueblos disciplinados que respetan
duramente todas las prohibiciones establecidas. Su primer movimiento fué de fuga, para no verse
complicadas en el atentado de este desconocido. Pero á los pocos pasos se detuvieron. La más
joven sonreía mirando á la tapia, y al reaparecer sobre ella el capitán, casi palmoteó de entusiasmo,
como si celebrase una arriesgada suerte de gimnasia.

El marino las creía inglesas, y habló en su idioma al entregarlas las dos rosas que llevaba
en la mano. Eran unas flores como todas, nacidas en una tierra igual á las otras tierras; pero
el marco de las tapias milenarias, la vecindad de los cubículos y taberne de la casa edificada
por Pansa en tiempo de los primeros Césares, les daban el mismo interés que si fuesen rosas
de dos mil años, milagrosamente conservadas.

La más grande y lozana se la dió á la joven, y ella la aceptó sonriendo, como algo que le correspondía
indiscutiblemente. Su compañera, una vez pasada la primera impresión del regalo, mostró impaciencia
por alejarse de este desconocido. «¡Gracias... gracias!» Y empujó á la otra, que aún no había
terminado su sonrisa, marchándose las dos precipitadamente. Una esquina adornada con una fuente
las ocultó á los pocos pasos.

Cuando Ulises, después de un ligero almuerzo en el restorán Diómedes, llegó corriendo á la
estación, el tren iba á partir. Deseaba ver Salerno, célebre en la Edad Media por sus médicos
y sus navegantes, y á continuación los templos ruinosos de Pestum. Al subir en el primer vagón
que encontró al paso, le pareció ver los velos de las dos señoras desapareciendo detrás de
una portezuela que se cerraba.

En la estación de Salerno volvió á columbrarlas ocupando un carruaje de alquiler que se perdía
en una calle próxima. Luego, en el resto de la tarde, se tropezó con ellas forzosamente, por
la atracción que sufren los viajeros dentro de una ciudad pequeña.

Se encontraron en el puerto, mortalmente amenazado por las barras de movible arena; se vieron
en los jardines cercanos al mar, junto al monumento de Pisicane, el romántico duque de San
Juan, un precursor de Garibaldi, muerto en plena juventud por la libertad de Italia.

La joven sonreía al encontrarle. Su compañera pasaba adelante, con la mirada vaga, queriendo
ignorar su presencia.

En la noche se vieron á más corta distancia. Vivían en el mismo hotel, un alojamiento igual
á todos los de los pequeños puertos, con excelente comida y dormitorios inmundos. Sus mesas
estaban próximas, y Ferragut, después de un saludo fríamente contestado, pudo contemplar á
las dos señoras, que hablaban poco y en voz baja, temiendo ser escuchadas por el vecino.

Al ver á la de más edad con el rostro libre de velos, no sufrió ninguna decepción. Su enemiga
tal vez habría perturbado en otro tiempo la tranquilidad de los hombres, pero ahora podía continuar
impunemente sus gestos hostiles y alojadores: el capitán no pensaba entristecerse por ello.

Debía estar más allá de los cuarenta años. Sus carnes abundantes guardaban cierta frescura,
obra de los cuidados higiénicos y los ejercicios gimnásticos. En cambio, su rostro, de blanca
piel, transparentaba una inundación subcutánea amarillenta, que parecía formada con olas de
salvado.

Sobre la antigua cabellera, de un tono rojo, se amontonaban los rizos artificiales ocultando
calvicies y canas. Sus pupilas, verdes, tenían la opacidad calmosa de los ojos bovinos cuando
quedaban libres de unos lentes de miope. Pero apenas estos cristales montados en oro se interponían
entre ella y el mundo exterior, las dos gotas glaucas tomaban una agudeza perforadora de personas
y objetos. Otras veces esparcían en torno un vacío altivo y glacial, semejante al círculo que
traza una espada.

La joven era menos adusta. Parecía sonreír con las comisuras de sus ojos, mientras estaba medio
vuelta de espaldas á Ferragut, agradeciendo su admiración muda y escrutadora. Llevaba la cabellera
en desorden, como una mujer que no teme las indiscreciones de su peinado y deja que surjan
bajo el sombrero las mechas serpenteantes con toda su rebeldía natural.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01154</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>408182</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19562</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

The cook did not allow criticism and protest. This miracle was undeniable. He had seen their
eyes when they were good, he had seen an old painting of the monastery Puig, and all appeared
in the table with the relief of the truth: the galley, the king, Peixoto and the Virgin at the
top giving the order.

The breeze lifted the skirt of the narrator, popping his abdomen split
into two hemispheres by the tightness of one button.

- Uncle Caragol,
which escapes! - Warned a mocking voice.

The holy man with the calm seraphic smile which looks beyond the pomp
and vanities of existence.

- Let: no longer flies.

And began the story of another miracle.

Ferragut assimilated these exaltations lightly cook his clothes at all times. Burning inside
a fire incessantly renewed. On foggy days up to the bridge with a smoking drinking glasses he
called calentets. Nothing better for men who were to to spend long hours outdoors in stationary
surveillance. It was coffee mixed with rum cane, but in unequal proportions,
with more alcohol than the black liquid.

Toni quickly drank all the vessels offered. The captain refused, demanding black coffee.

His sobriety was the old sailor, the sobriety of the father Ulysses, who mixed wine with water
in all its libations. The gods did not love the old sea spirits. Amphitrite and the Nereids only
accepted on their altars fruits of the earth, sacrifices pigeons, libations of milk. Perhaps
because of this the Mediterranean coast, following a concern hereditary drunkenness saw the lowest
of the recesses.

Those who were not really drunk sober avoided like the sailors of other seas, hiding the roughness
of the alcoholic beverage or coffee with sugar.

Caragol was drunk in charge of all the "warm" despised by the captain, others who are engaged himself
in the mystery of the kitchen.

On hot days tailored refresquets, and these "soft" were large vessels, half water, half sugar
cane on a thick bed of sugar mixture that fulminant posing without gradations, from the vulgar
an angelic serenity to drunkenness.

The master scolded him when he saw her eyes swollen and red.

I was going to go blind ... But he was not moved to the threat. Needed to hold his own way prosperity
of the ship. And this prosperity, the most interesting to him was able to abuse the oil and
sugarcane, without fear of recrimination at the time of the audit.
Grao Christ, which lasted forever War!

...

The third trip of South America to Europe came to finish the Mare Nostrum in Naples wheat and
hides where he landed. A collision at the entrance of the harbor with a ship-hospital Englishman
who went to the Dardanelles dented its stern, also breaking a fin of the propeller.

Toni roared with impatience to learn that they would have to stay
close to a month in forced immobility.

Italy had not yet intervened in the war, but his defensive precautions
monopolized all naval industries.

It was not possible before the repair. Ferragut cash figure for their business this waste of time.
We expect valuable freight in Marseilles and Barcelona. But trying to calm himself and placate his
mate, repeated many times:

- England will indemnify ... The English are generous.

And to numb his impatience, was moved to the ground.

Naples does not look like much when compared to other famous Italian
cities.

Its true beauty was the huge gulf between hills of orange and pine trees, with a second frame
of mountains, one of which extended over the eternal blue sky, its summit of volcanic vapors.

The
village was scarce in famous buildings.

The monarchs of Naples had been more than often foreigners residing far and ruled by proxy. The
best streets, palaces, monumental fountains, came from the Spanish viceroys. A sovereign source
mixed. Carlos III, Castilian Neapolitan by birth and heart, had the best of the city. His enthusiasm
constructor old neighborhoods still embellished with similar works which had risen to years
later in Spain to take his throne.

After admiring the statues in the Greek museums and the objects unearthed that revealed the intimate
life of the ancients, Ulises ran tortuous arteries and often bleak popular neighborhoods.

Were steep streets, forming landings, flanked by narrow houses and
towering.

All holes had balconies, and a railing at the front were stretched strings, buntings clothes of
different colors to dry. Fertility Neapolitan crowd was boiling these streets. Around the outdoor
kitchens crowded customers eating boiled macaroni feet or pieces of meat.

Advertised vendors hawking their wares with similar melodic ballads to, and down to meet him
balconies topped by castles strings. The haggling and shopping were from the bottom of the street-ditch
to the seventh floor. In contrast, herds of goats rose winding stairs with the agility of habit,
to be left empty the udder all plateaus.

Marinela springs attracted the captain for his "color" of the Mediterranean port. The unit Italian
had knocked down and rebuilt much, but still left standing several rows of houses, low ceiling,
pink or white façade, green doors and the floor under more advanced the top, serving to support
a gallery with wooden balustrades. Everything in them was not was
carpentry brick thick, equal to the work of the shipwrights.

Iron there was no land in these buildings they remembered the ship sailing. The pieces were as dark
cabin. Through the windows were large sea shells on the comfortable, paint pictures depicting hard
and childish frigates, multicolored shells brought from distant seas.

These homes were repeated in all ports of the Mediterranean, as if they were the work of the same
hand. Ferragut had seen a boy in the Grao of Valencia, and still found them in Barceloneta, in
the suburbs of Marseille, in the old Nice, on the island ports Western navies in the African coast
occupied by Maltese and Sicilian.

On the village aligned along the Marinela, the churches of Naples
domes protruding and towers with glazed tiles, green and yellow.

More than Christian churches roofs seemed auction of oriental baths.

Lazaron there was no longer barefoot and red cap, but the crowd - clad as all port workers - are
still crowded around the poster defaced that was a crime, a prodigious miracle or a specific,
listening in silence the story the narrator or the charlatan. The old popular reciters declaimed
with heroic gesticulations Tasso's epic octaves. Accompanied by harps and violins sounded the
last romance that Naples had become fashionable in the world. The positions of the scattered
ostricarios perfume dead organic wave.

Around them, the empty shells of oysters out against mud the rounds of his pearly lime.

Next to the former Captain of the Port - palace of Charles III, white and blue with an image of the
Immaculate Conception - the cars were crowded landing.

Ferragut the same thing was that years before, with their original hybrid shots. The rods were occupied
by an ox white, lustrous, with huge horns and wide, an animal similar to those contained in religious
ceremonies of the ancients. To his right was towing a horse, his left a big ass and lean. And this
triple and discordant coupling was repeated in all stationary cars
to ships along the docks or flipping their heavy wheels the slope
that leads to the upper town.

A few days later, the captain felt fatigued and bustle of Naples. In the cafes of Toledo Street and
the Gallery of Umberto I had to defend some boys troubling with low-cut vest, tie wing and felt a
little lopsided on the locks, proposed that quietly organized recreational events unheard of foreigners.

Pretty
had also seen the paintings and household objects unearthed from ancient cities. The secret cabinet
lewdness ended by irritating.

It seemed an inverted recess look so childish fantasies of sculpture and painting as a character
having the phallus Main ...

One morning I took the train, and then skirting the smoking mountain of Vesuvius, passing between
Pink villages surrounded by vineyards, dropped in a season: Pompeii.

Hotels and restaurants, in mournful solitude the guides came like a swarm of wasps suddenly awakened.
They lamented the war, which had cut the flow of travelers. He was perhaps the only one who was
coming in all day. "Lord, at any price !...» But the sailor continued. Always, remembering Pompeii,
had made the desire to return to see her alone, all alone, to receive a direct impression of ancient
life.

His first visit was seventeen years before, when I was piloting a glider Catalan anchored in the
port of Naples, using the cheap price of a Sunday. All had been confused in a group that pushed
and stepped on by listening to the guide more closely.

Leading the expedition was a young priest and elegant, a Roman Bishop Dress silk, and with
him two foreign ladies and goons that were planted on higher ground having their skirts lifted for
fear of some geckos that snaked among the ruins. Ferragut, with the humility of wonder, it was
always down, seeing all the means of his legs. "Ay! Twenty years
!...»

Then, when he heard of Pompeii, is checked in his memory an image overlay "Very beautiful, very
interesting." He saw the streets palaces, temples, but secondly, as a fund vanished, while highlighting
first-line four magnificent legs, a slender shafts human colonnade lined black silk that was
transparently the white meat.

The loneliness so often desired for his second visit he was met. The Dead City had no other noise than
the flutter of insects on the plants, who began to wear spring, and
reptiles running around invisible under layers of ivy.

At the Herculaneum Gate, the guardian of small museum Ferragut let alone consider the emptied
of secular bodies: several Pompeii plaster in the attitude of terror that death had surprised
them.

He did not leave the chair to bother with explanations; barely looked up from the day before him.
I absorbed the news of Rome, intrigues of German diplomats, the possibility that Italy entered the
war.

Then in the empty streets, the sailor stumbled with the same concern. Echoed their steps under
the sunlight with a sound equal to that of the hollow underground
tombs.

When stopped, the silence was reborn, "a silence of two thousand years", he thought Ferragut. Y
in the old silent voices sounded far with the violence of a bitter argument. Were guards and employees
of the excavations, which, deprived of work, gesticulating and insulted in their seats twenty centuries,
deeply alienated by the patriotic enthusiasm or the fear of the horrors of war.

Ferragut, with the plane in hand, went to these groups, no one should
rise to guide.

For two hours might believe a neighbor of the ancient Pompeii was left alone in the city on a holiday
dedicated to the gods countryside. His gaze went up the extreme end of the straight streets,
without running into people or things to be reminded modern times.

Pompeii seemed smaller in this solitude. It was a narrow crossing paths with high sidewalks paved
with polygonal blocks of lava blue. In the interstices formed fertility laces tight spring grass
dotted with flowers. Ancient carriages, the that there was not dust, had opened with deep wheel
ruts in the pavement. In all the moments he was a public fountain with a mask he had thrown
your mouth water.

Certain red signs advertising the walls were verified in the early elections of the current era:
mayor candidates or of diunviro recommending that voters Pompeii. Phallus wielded doors to ward
off the evil eye, others a couple of coiled snakes, symbol of family
life.

In the corners of the streets, a Latin line engraving the wall begging the passer to refrain
from dirty outbursts. Were still living in the walls stucco cartoons and puppets, designed
by Cesar urchins century.

The houses were built at the light on a floor which had happened the
tremors, until the arrival of the final catastrophe.

They only had brick or cement the ground floor. The others were of wood, and had been devoured
by the volcanic fire, leaving only stairs.

In this city, funny, friendly and easy life, more Greek than Roman, all lower floors plebeian houses
had been occupied by small shops. Were stores with the door the same size as the establishment:
caves square, equal to those of the Arab souks, that show to its
farthest corners of the buyer arrested in the street.

Many kept even your stone countertops and earthen jars. The buildings had no particular facade.
Its outer walls were smooth, unaffordable, with the odd lattice skylight and high, as in the palaces
of the East. The door was like a gate to escape; whole life was turned inward, flowing wealth and
magnificence to the yard central, adorned with pools, statues and flower beds.

The marble was rare. The columns, constructed of brick, were covered with stucco offered to
the paint surface. Pompeii was a city polychrome. All columns, red
or yellow, were capitals of different colors.

Predominated in the walls the black patent leather with red and amber, occupying its center a small
table, over often erotic. In the friezes and newts rode love between rustic and maritime emblems.

Tired
of your trip through the dead city, Ferragut sat on a stone bench between the ruins of a temple.
I looked at the plane put on their knees, sipping titles that had
been designated the most interesting buildings on account of a mosaic
or of a painting village of Diomede, home of Meleager, Adonis wounded,
the Labyrinth of the Faun Black Wall.

The street names were not less interesting: by the Baths, via of the Tombs, route of Plenty, Theaters
pathway.

The sound of footsteps roused her head to sea. Two women march preceded by a guide. They were
walking tall and strong. Had their faces veiled hat and a larger veil crossed behind his back,
sustained by the arms by way of a shawl.

Ferragut guessed a major difference in the ages of the two. The thickest covert was moving heaviness.
His step was alive, but rested on the floor with your feet some authority bulky widely shoes
with low heels. The younger, tall and slender walking small bounds, like a bird that only knows
how to fly, strutting on the steep heels.

The two watched with concern to this man who suddenly emerged from
the ruins.

Showed air worried and fearful of going to a prohibited place or meditate wrongdoing. His first
impulse was to retreat, but continued to guide his way unmoved, and eventually follow.

Ferragut smiled. I knew where they were going. The lane of the brothels was next. The Guardian
open a door, leaving after watching, with dramatic anxiety, as if set out its pleased to use
this for a tip.

And the two ladies were going to see some paintings fuzzy showing how there is nothing new
and original in this world: yellow figures and naked, the same at first glance, no other news
that the exaggerated bulge sex differential.

Half an hour later, Ulysses left his bench with tired eyes and severe immobility the ruins. In
the streets of the Spa again visited the house of the tragic poet, then Pansa admired, the largest and
most luxurious of the city.

This Pansa had undoubtedly been the most ostentatious bourgeois Pompeii. Your home occupied
an entire island. The xystos, garden attached to the house, had been replanted with vegetation
Greek cypresses and laurels among pictures of roses and violets.

By following the outer wall of the garden, Ferragut found the two
ladies.

Cotemplaban the flowers through the bars of a door. The younger English expressed his admiration by a
swaying his purple roses around the pedestal of an old faun.

Ulysses felt an irresistible desire to be bold and gallant. He wanted interest to the two foreign
theatrical tribute.

He felt the need to draw attention something dashing and daring Spanish waving to all far
from home.

With an agile climber masts, saved from a jump the garden wall. The two ladies gave a cry of
surprise, as if to witness something unprecedented.

This boldness appeared subvert the ideas of the oldest, accustomed to life in disciplined people
who respect hard all prohibitions. His first impulse was to escape, to avoid being complicated
in the bombing of the unknown. But a few footsteps stopped.

The most Young smiled, looking at the wall, and reappear on it Captain, almost clapped with enthusiasm,
as if to hold a risky kind of gymnastics.

The British navy believed them, and spoke their language to deliver both wearing pink in hand.
There were flowers and all, born in a land equal to the other lands,
but under the ancient walls, the vicinity of the stalls and the house
built tavern by Pansa time of the first Caesars, were given the same
interest as if they were roses two thousand years, miraculously preserved.

The

largest and most luxuriant gave it to her, and she accepted it, smiling, as something that belonged
without question. His partner, once the first impression of the gift, showed impatience to
get away from this stranger. "Thanks ... thank you! "and pushed the other, had not yet finished
his smile, the two abruptly walking away. A corner adorned with a
fountain hide them from the few steps.

When Odysseus, after a light lunch in the restaurant Diomedes, came
running to the station, the train was to depart.

He wanted to see Salerno, famous in the Middle Ages for their physicians and navigators, and
then the crumbling temples of Paestum. Going up in the first car who found the way, he seemed
to see the veils of the two women disappeared behind a door that closed.

In Salerno station returned to descry occupying a hired carriage that was lost in a nearby street.
Then in the rest of the afternoon, he met with them necessarily, by the attraction experienced
by travelers in a small town.

They met at the port, mortally threatened by the movable bar sand were in the gardens near the
sea, near the monument Pisicane, the romantic Duke St. John, a precursor
of Garibaldi, who died in his youth for the freedom of Italy.

The girl smiled to find. His companion went ahead, his eyes wandering, wanting ignore their
presence.

At night they saw shorter distance. They lived in the
same hotel, same accommodation to all the small ports with excellent
food and unclean rooms. Its tables were close, and Ferragut, after
a greeting coldly replied, he beheld the two ladies, who spoke little
and quietly, fearing to be heard by a neighbor.

On seeing the older
with the free face veil, suffered no disappointment. Your enemy maybe
in another time would have disturbed the peace of men, but could continue
hostile gestures with impunity and hosters: Captain did not think
so sad.

Should be more than forty years. Its abundant bore some fresh
meat, work on care and gymnastic exercises. Instead, his face, white
skin, transparent yellowish subcutaneous flood, which seemed formed
with waves saved.

On the old hair, a red hue, artificial curls piled
hiding baldness and gray hair. Her eyes, green, had the opacity of
bovine eyes calmly when were free of myopic glasses. But just these
crystals mounted in gold were interposed between it and the outside
world, the two took a sharp drop glaucous punch people and objects.
Sometimes scattered around a vacuum haughty, icy, similar to the circle
draw a sword.

The girl was less grim. Seemed to smile with the corners
of his eyes, while half Ferragut her back, thanking his admiration
moving and searching. She wore her hair in disarray, as a woman who
is not afraid of the indiscretions of her hair and let it emerge fuses
under his hat winding with all his rebellious nature</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>