<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08503</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>1930</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18172</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Por otra parte, la sola idea
de recorrer la América bajo tan lisonjeros auspicios me alhagaba sobremanera, y encendia mi
ardiente imaginacion, ofreciéndome de antemano mil cuadros á cuales mas seductores. Merced
á los benévolos consejos de los señores Cuvier, Brongniart, Cordier, Isidoro Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire,
y del célebre viagero baron de Humboldt, me fué dado entrever cual seria el circulo de mis
investigaciones. Las ciencias naturales eran el objeto principal; mas considerando como complemento
indispensable la geografía, la etnología y la historia, me propuse no desechar nada, cuando
estuviese en aquellos lugares, para traer conmigo el tesoro mas completo de materiales relativos
á estos ramos importantes de los conocimientos humanos.

El 29 de julio de 1826 me embarqué en Brest á bordo de la Meuse, fragata del Estado, y dí principio
á mi peregrinacion trasatlántica. Hice escala en las Canarias, en donde durante algunos dias
pude estudiar, á la vista del famoso pico de Teide, las producciones de la isla de Tenerife,
así como sus crestas desgarradas. Dos meses despues divisábamos las costas del Brasil, y un
ambiente embalsamado con el perfume de mil flores llegaba ya hasta mi, haciéndome gustar inefables
y dulces emociones. Iba yo al cabo á echar pié sobre el mundo de Colon, sobre esa tierra de
prodigios, cuya exploracion habia siempre ansiado aun en medio de los sueños de mi infancia.
Tomé finalmente asiento en América por espacio de ocho años.

El Rio Janeiro con sus montañas de granito y sus bellas y vírgenes selvas fué el primer teatro
de mis exploraciones. Montevideo, Maldonado y toda la república oriental del Uruguay, ocupada
entónces por los Brasileros, me enseñó luego sus campos, que se asemejan á los de Francia.
Atravesando la Banda oriental pasé á Buenos-Aires, y me embarqué en seguida en el Paraná, para
trasportarme á las fronteras de la provincia del Paraguay, declarada hoy dia Estado independiente.
Subi como trecientas cincuenta leguas por este inmenso rio, cuya magestuosa corriente es de
esperar que algun dia se verá surcada por centenares de embarcaciones, las que impulsadas por
el vapor ascenderán hasta Chiquitos, haciendo así mas inmediata la comunicacion de Bolivia
con la Europa.

Las ondas de este caudaloso rio, que tiene mas de una legua de ancho, corren sobre un lecho
cuyas márgenes é innumerables islas se ven adornadas de vistosos boscages, en donde la graciosa
palmera entretege su follage con el de los árboles mas variados y bellos.

Recorrí durante un año entero todos los puntos de la provincia de Corrientes y de Misiones,
y despues de haber penetrado en el Gran-Chaco, dí la vuelta por las provincias de Entre-Rios
y de Santa-Fé. De regreso á Buenos-Aires, quise encaminarme á Chile ó á Bolivia; mas calculando
lo difícil que me seria atravesar el continente con toda seguridad, por las turbulencias que,
despues de la paz con el Brasil, minaban aquel estado, me decidí á pasar á la Patagonia, tierra
misteriosa, cuyo solo nombre encerraba en ese entónces un no sé que de mágico. Me transporté
pues allí á fines de 1826, y permanecí en ella durante ocho meses.

Pude efectuar mis primeras investigaciones con bastante sosiego, por mas penoso que fuese el
recorrer un pais de los mas áridos, y en donde la falta de agua se hace sentir á cada paso
en el corazon de esos monótonos é interminables desiertos; pero los indios Puelches, Aucas
y Patagones se sublevaron inopinadamente contra la naciente colonia del Cármen, situada á orillas
del rio Negro, y me ví entónces precisado á reunirme á sus habitantes para cooperar á la defensa
comun. Habiendo vuelto por segunda vez á Buenos-Aires, hallé este pais en tan completa anarquia,
que, reconociendo la absoluta imposibilidad de pasar á Chile atravesando las pampas, tomé el
partido de doblar el cabo dé Hornos. A mi llegada á Valparaiso encontré tambien á la república
Chilena en un estado de agitacion nada propicio para los viages científicos, y provisto entónces
de las recomendaciones del cónsul general de Francia en este Estado, pasé á Bolivia, de cuyo
gobierno debia yo esperar una buena acogida, y los medios de proseguir mi exploracion continental.

Cobija, puerto de Bolivia, me saludó desde luego con el imponente aspecto de las montañas que
lo coronan. Poco despues me desembarqué en Arica para dar principio á mis viages por tierra.
Abandonando bien pronto las costas, me encaminé á Tacna, y en seguida emprendí mi ascension
á las cordilleras por el camino de Palca y de Tacora; mas, en vez de tropezar allí con esas
empinadas y agudas crestas, que se ven figuradas en los mapas, me encontré sobre una dilatadísima
planicie, colocada á la altura de cuatro mil quinientas varas sobre el nivel del mar, y en
la que únicamente se apercibian de trecho en trecho algunas moles cónicas cubiertas de nubes.
Atravesando este encumbrado llano, vine á encontrarme luego en la cima de la cadena del Chulluncayani.
Al contemplar desde allí la dilatadísima extension que se desplegaba ante mis ojos, y la tan
grande variedad de objetos que las miradas alcanzaban á dominar á la vez, yo saboreaba un sentimiento
de indefinible admiracion. Es cierto que se descubren paisages mas pintorescos en los Pirineos
y en los Alpes; pero nunca ví en estos un aspecto tan grandioso y de tanta magestad. El llano
Boliviano, que tiene mas de treinta leguas de ancho, te dilataba á mis piés por derecha é izquierda
hasta perderse de vista, ofreciendo tan solo pequeñas cadenas paralelas, que parecian fluctuar
como las ondulaciones del Oceano sobre esta vastísima planicie, cuyo horizonte al norueste
y al sudeste no alcanzaba yo á descubrir, al paso que hácia el norte veia brillar, por encima
de las colinas que lo circunscriben, algunos espacios de las cristalinas aguas del famoso lago
de Titicaca, misteriosa cuna de los hijos del sol. De la otra parte de tan sublime conjunto
se divisaba el cuadro severo, que forma la inmensa cortina de los Andes, entrecortados en picos
agudos, representando la figura exacta de una sierra. En medio de estas alturas se levantaban
el Guaina Potosí, el Illimani y el nevado de Sorata mostrando su cono oblicuo y achatado, estos
tres gigantes de los montes americanos, cuyas resplandecientes nieves se dibujan, por sobre
las nubes, en el fondo azul oscuro de ese cielo el mas transparente y bello del mundo. Hácia
el norte y el sud la cordillera oriental va declinando poco á poco hasta perderse totalmente
en el horizonte. Si me habia yo sentido lleno de admiracion en presencia del Tacora, aquí me
hallaba transportado, y sin embargo no era esta sino una de las faces de aquel cuadro; pues
volviendo hácia otra parte, se me revelaba un conjunto de no menores atractivos. Yo descubria
aun el Chipicani, el Tacora, y todas las montañas del llano occidental, que acababa de trasponer,
y sobre las que mi vista se habia tantas veces detenido durante los tres dias de mi tránsito
por la cordillera.

Bajé al llano Boliviano, situado aun á la altura de cuatro mil varas sobre el nivel del mar,
y que es la parte mas poblada de la república. Llegué á la ciudad de La-Paz, la antigua Choquehapu
(campo de oro), nombre que, por su abundancia de minas en este metal, le dieron los Aymaraes.
Este valle favorecido por la proximidad de los Yungas, y que se encuentra á tres mil setecientas
varas de elevacion, ostenta á un mismo tiempo en sus mercados todos los frutos de los paises
frios, de los templados y de la zona tórrida. Escribí inmediatamente al gobierno, remitiéndole
mis cartas de recomendacion. En respuesta me ofreció él su proteccion, y fondos si los necesitaba,
proponiéndome ademas un oficial del ejército y dos jóvenes para acompañarme. No queriendo abusar
de tan generosas ofertas, acepté, con la mayor gratitud, solamente los dos últimos, así como
las facilidades de trasporte por toda la república; y desde aquel instante, me consideré ya
seguro de poder recorrer con fruto esta bella y rica parte del continente americano.

Impaciente por ver la provincia de Yungas, de la que se me decian tantas maravillas, dirijíme
á Palca, y una vez puesto sobre la cumbre de la cordillera oriental, me sentí deslumbrado de
tal manera por la magestad del conjunto, que desde luego no vi sinó la extension inmensa, sin
poder darme cuenta de los detalles. Ya no era una montaña nevada la que yo creia asir, ya no
era un dilatado llano, sin nubes como sin vegetacion activa.... Todo era aquí distinto. Volviéndome
hácia el lado de La-Paz aun vela las áridas montañas y ese cielo siempre puro, característico
de las elevadas planicies. Por todas partes, al nivel en que me hallaba, alturas vestidas de
hielo y de nieve; mas qué contraste por el lado de los Yungas! Hasta quinientas ó seiscientas
varas debajo de mí, montañas entapizadas de verde terciopelo, y que parecian reflejarse en
un cielo transparente y sereno á esta altura, una cenefa de nubes blancas, que representaban
un vasto mar azotando los flancos de las montañas, y por sobre las cuales se desprendian los
picos mas elevados, figurando islotes. Cuando las nubes se entreabrian, yo descubria á una
inconmensurable profundidad debajo de esta zona, límite de la vegetacion activa, el verdor
azulado oscuro de las vírgenes selvas, que guarnecen por todas partes un terreno tan accidentado.
Lleno de regocijo al verme rodeado de una naturaleza, tan diferente de la que me habian presentado
la vertiente occidental y los llanos de la cordillera, quise, ántes de ocultarme bajo esta
bóveda de nubes, vagar libremente algunos instantes por sobre la region del trueno.

Visité sucesivamente Yanacachi, Chupi, Chulumani, Irupana, etc., pasando alternativamente del
lecho de los rios á la cumbre de las montañas. La pomposa vegetacion del Rio Janeiro se vé
reproducida en estos sitios, pero con mas esplendor; una caliente humedad fomenta en ellos,
hasta sobre las mas escarpadas rocas, plantas prodigiosas. Despues de haber estudiado detalladamente
esta provincia, tan abundante en producciones, seguí por la misma vertiente occidental, recorriendo
el terreno desigual, pero rico en minas de plata, de las provincias de Sicasica y de Ayupaya,
pasando por Cajuata, Suri, Inquisivi, Cavari y Palca hasta trepar nuevamente la cordillera
oriental, de donde cayeron de repente mis miradas, á algunos millares de piés, sobre los ricos
valles de Cochabamba y de Clisa. Qué singular contraste aquel con el de los riscos donde me
encontraba! Era la imágen del caos al lado de la mas grande tranquilidad: era la naturaleza
triste y silenciosa en presencia de la vida mas animada. Yo veia pues, en medio de áridas colinas,
dos extendidos llanos cultivados y guarnecidos por todas partes de casuchas y bosquecillos,
entre los que se distinguian gran número de aldeas, y una grande ciudad á la que hacian sobresalir
sus edificios como á una reina en medio de sus vasallos. Nada puede efectivamente compararse
á la sensacion que produce el aspecto de esas llanuras, cubiertas de caseríos, de plantaciones
y de cultura, circunscriptas por una naturaleza montañosa y estéril, que se extiende á mas
de treinta leguas á la redonda perdiéndose confusa en el horizonte. Se creeria ver allí la
tierra prometida en el seno del desierto. Si habia yo probado ántes vivísimas impresiones en
presencia de las bellezas salvages de esa naturaleza grandiosa del llano Boliviano, y de la
cordillera oriental, en donde la vida no entra para nada en el conjunto, pues que nada se encuentra
allí de lo que respecta al hombre, cuánto mayores no serian ellas, al descubrir yo estos lugares
animados, estas llanuras sembradas de edificios, esos campos ricos y abundosos que despertaban
en mi mente la imágen de mi patria!

Cochabamba y sus cercanías fueron por algun tiempo el teatro de mis investigaciones; prosiguiendo
luego mi marcha hácia el este, traspuse cien leguas de montañas bastante áridas, pero cortadas
por fértiles y profundos valles. Durante este viage reconocí sucesivamente las provincias de
Clisa, de Mizqué y del Valle-Grande, siguiendo por el camino de Punata, Pacona, Totora, Chaluani,
Chilon, Pampa-Grande y Samaypata (el poyo del descanso), último punto habitado de las montañas,
de donde solo distaban treinta leguas las fértiles pampas del centro continental. Pocos dias
despues se descubria, de la cumbre de la cuesta de Petaca, el extendido horizonte de unos llanos
calurosos cubiertos de bosques, en cuyo centro se ve sentada la tranquila ciudad de Santa-Cruz-de-la-Sierra.

El estudio de esta ciudad y de sus notables contornos ocupó mi atencion por algunos meses:
pasados estos, me resolví á penetrar mas adentro en las tierras habitadas. Me encontraba ya
como á trecientas leguas del mar; pero anhelando tambien conocer las poblaciones puramente
indígenas, volví mi marcha al este, hácia la provincia de Chiquitos, atrevasando el Monte-Grande,
cuya espesa frondosidad cubre una extension de mas de sesenta leguas, y en donde vanamente
se buscarian otros huéspedes que los animales salvages.

La provincia de Chiquitos, colocada en el centro del continente americano, tiene mas de diez
y ocho mil leguas de superficie, y siendo muy fértil su terreno, pueden cultivarse en ella
todos los frutos de los paises cálidos, al mismo tiempo que en las montañas de Santiago pudieran
sembrarse trigos y plantarse la viña. Visité sucesivamente San-Javier, Concepcion, San-Miguel,
Santa-Ana, San-Ignacio, San-Rafael, San-José y Santiago, y precisamente vine á encontrarme
sobre esas montañas, en la primavera de aquellas regiones.

En tanto que un sol abrasador tostaba las llanuras circunvecinas, algunas benéficas nubes,
posándose sobre la cima de las montañas, habian operado un cambio total en el aspecto de la
naturaleza. Los árboles se cubrian de un tierno follage y de diversidad de flores; la campiña
desplegaba lujosamente sus primorosos ropages. En nada absolutamente pudiera compararse la
bella estacion de Europa á un tal momento bajo las zonas tórridas. En Francia, por ejemplo,
las hojas van brotando poco á poco, y el frio y la ausencia de dias hermosos se hacen frecuentemente
sentir aun despues de bien entrada la primavera. En aquellos lugares, esta no es sino el cambio
súbito de una decoracion. La naturaleza se halla muerta, inanimada; un cielo demasiado puro
ilumina un campo triste y casi desolado; pero sobreviene un aguacero, y al punto, como por
encanto, todas las cosas toman una vida nueva. Bastan pocos dias para esmaltar los prados de
verdura y de flores olorosas, y revestir los árboles con esas hojas de un verde tierno, ó con
las flores que las preceden, dando á cada uno de ellos un color vivo y uniforme. Si la campiña,
ostentando su bella alfombra, embalsama el aire con los mas suaves perfumes, los bosques presentan
otro carácter no ménos halagüeño de belleza y variedad. Aquí un árbol cargado de largos racimos
purpúreos contrasta con las copas, ya celestes, ya del dorado mas puro; allá sobresale una
cima blanca como la nieve junta al rosado mas tierno. Con cuánto regocijo trepaba yo por esas
laderas, donde tan lindos vegetales se engalanaban, con sus joyeles, ó recorria los prados
sin saber á que sitio dar la preferencia, pues que cada uno de ellos me ofrecia un encanto
que le era particular, un tipo diferente. Confieso que nunca me habia sentido tan maravillado
en presencia de las bellezas de ese suelo, cubierto por un dosel tan espléndido.

Dejando muy luego el pueblecillo de Santiago, y atravesando bosques inmensos y el rio de Tucabaca,
destinado probablemente á suministrar ricas minas de oro, llegué á Santo-Corazon, que es el
punto mas oriental de los lugares habitados de la república. Santo-Corazon era efectivamente
por aquella parte el extremo del mundo, pues que nadie podia entónces pasar mas adelante. Así
pues, calculando las grandísimas ventajas que resultarian de la navegacion del Paraguay para
el tráfico comercial y para la civilizacion de la provincia de Chiquitos, y anhelando ser el
primer instrumento de esta gigantesca empresa, recogí todos los datos posibles de los indígenas
acostumbrados á recorrer las florestas, é hice abrir un camino hácia las ruinas del antiguo
Santo-Corazon, en donde corre el Rio Oxuquis, formado de los rios San-Rafael y Tucabaca, llegando
á cerciorarme que los altos ribazos de esta corriente podrian proporcionar, en todas estaciones,
un puerto cómodo y situado á muy poca distancia del Rio Paraguay, en el cual desemboca un poco
mas arriba del fuerte de la Nueva-Coimbra. En 1831 comuniqué estos importantes datos al gobierno
de Bolivia, haciéndole ver el cambio favorable que, para aquella provincia y para toda la república,
resultaria de una nueva via de comunicacion, por el Rio de la Plata, con el Oceano atlántico.

Deseoso de recorrer otro punto de Chiquitos, atravesando bellas selvas me puse en la mision
de San-Juan, y retorné en seguida á San-Javier, de donde me aparté diciendo tambien adios á
la provincia, al cabo de seis meses que me habia dedicado á su estudio.

En medio de las inmensas y sombrías selvas que separan las vastas provincias de Chiquitos y
de Moxos, y en un espacioso recinto, que se halla indicado en nuestros mejores mapas como desconocido,
corre un rio tambien ignorado aunque navegable: este rio es el San-Miguel. Sus orillas cubiertas
de una vegetacion tan lujosa como activa, están habitadas por una nacion muy notable; tales
son los Guarayos, que realizan en América, por su franca hospitalidad y por sus costumbres
sencillas y enteramente primitivas, el poético ensueño de la edad de oro. Entre estos hombres
de la simple naturaleza, á quienes jamas atormentó la envidia, el robo, esta plaga moral de
las civilizaciones mas groseras como de las mas refinadas, tampoco es conocido. Si algunas
veces habia yo suspirado viendo yacer en el abandono campos magníficos, miéntras que en Europa
tantísimos infelices labradores perecen de miseria, cuánto mas agudo no debió ser mi sentimiento
en presencia de aquellos lugares, los mas abundosos que yo habia encontrado hasta entónces,
y en donde una naturaleza tan prodigiosa, y de un lujo de vegetacion extraordinario, parece
estar pidiendo brazos que vengan á utilizarlos por medio del cultivo productor!
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03762</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>87619</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16386</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Moreover, the very idea touring
America under such flattering auspices Alhague me greatly, and lit my ardent imagination, offering
pre-thousand pictures each as attractive. Merced to the benevolent advice of Messrs. Cuvier,
Brongniart, Cordier, Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, and the famous traveler Baron de Humboldt, I was
given a glimpse of what would be the circle of my research. The natural sciences were the
main object, but seen as complementary indispensable geography, ethnology and history, I decided not
to discard anything, when were in those places, to bring me the most complete treasury of material
relating to these important branches of human knowledge.

On July 29, 1826 in Brest, I embarked on board of the Meuse, frigate of the State, and gave first to
my transatlantic pilgrimage. I stop in the Canaries, where for several days I study, in sight
of the famous peak of Teide, the productions of the island of Tenerife, and their ragged peaks.
Two months later we could see the coast of Brazil, and environment embalmed with the perfume
of a thousand flowers arrived and to me, making me like ineffable and sweet emotions. I was going
to throw after standing on the world of Columbus, on that ground wonders, as he had always
longed for exploration in the midst of the dreams of my childhood. Finally took a seat in America
for eight years.

The Rio de Janeiro with its mountains of granite and its beautiful and unspoiled forests was the
first theater of my explorations. Montevideo, Maldonado, and all the Eastern Republic of Uruguay,
busy So by the Brazilians, then showed me their fields, which are similar to those of France.
I went across the Banda Oriental to Buenos-Aires, and then I embarked on the Parana, to transporting
to the borders of the province of Paraguay, today declared an independent state. Subi as three
hundred and fifty leagues for this immense river, whose current is majestic hope that some day
will crisscrossed by hundreds of boats, which driven the steam will rise up Chiquitos, making
communication more immediate in Bolivia with Europe.

The waves of this mighty river, which has more than a mile wide, running
over a bed and innumerable islands whose shores are adorned with colorful
boscages, where the graceful entretege their foliage palm tree with
the most varied and beautiful.

I walked for a whole year all parts of the province of Corrientes and Misiones, and after having
entered the Gran-Chaco, turned around by the provinces of Entre Rios and Santa Fe. Back to Buenos-Aires,
I wanted to aim for a Chile or Bolivia, but calculating how difficult it would cross the continent
to be sure, by the turbulence, after the peace with Brazil, undermining that state, I decided
to go to Patagonia, land mysterious, whose name alone locked up then
I know not that magical.

I was transported for there to the end of 1826, and stayed there for eight months.

I made my first research with fairly calm, for it was the most painful go one of the most arid
country, and where water shortage is felt at every step in the heart of these monotonous and endless
deserts, but the Indians Puelches Aucas and Patagones unexpectedly revolted against the rising colony
of Carmen, located on the banks Black River, and I saw then compelled to meet its inhabitants to
cooperate to the defense common. Having returned for a second time to Buenos-Aires, I found
this country in such a complete anarchy, , recognizing the absolute impossibility of passing through
the pampas to Chile, took the game round Cape Horn. Upon my arrival to Valparaiso found also to
the republic Chilean in a state of agitation anything suitable for scientific voyages, and then
provided the recommendations of the consul general of France in this
State, I went to Bolivia, whose government should I expect a warm
welcome, and the means to continue my exploration mainland.

Cobija, Bolivia port, greeted me of course with the impressive appearance of the mountains the
crown. Shortly after I landed in Arica for beginning to my journeys by land. Leaving the coast
soon, I went to Tacna, and then began my ascension to the ridges on the road and Tacora Palca, but
instead of tripping over there with those steep and sharp ridges, which are figured on the
maps, I found myself on a very extensive plain, placed at a height of four thousand five hundred
yards above sea level, and which only became aware of a few moles here and there cloud-covered cone. Crossing
this exalted level, I came to meet then at the top of the chain of Chulluncayani. Contemplating
from there the very extensive extension that unfolded before my eyes, and so large variety of objects
that looks amounted to dominate the time, I savored a sense of indefinable admiration. It is true
that most picturesque landscaping are found in the Pyrenees and the Alps, but never saw these
look so great and so much majesty. Plain Bolivia, which has more than thirty miles wide, you dilated
at my feet by right and left out of sight, offering only small parallel ridges, which seemed to
fluctuate the ocean like ripples on the vast plain, where the north-west horizon and the Southeast
did not meet me to discover, while they looked towards the north shine above of the hills that
limited, some areas of the crystalline waters of the famous lake Titicaca, the mysterious home
of the children of the sun. On the other side of such a sublime set could see the severe symptoms,
which form the vast curtain of the Andes, interrupted with peaks acute, representing the exact
shape of a saw. Between these heights are raised the Guaina Potosi, Illimani and Sorata snowy
cone showing her oblique and flattened, these three giants of American forests, which are drawn
glowing snow, above the clouds in the dark blue background of the sky more transparent and
beautiful in the world. Towards North and South Eastern Cordillera is declining gradually until
completely lost on the horizon. If I had I felt full of admiration in the presence of Tacora,
here I was carried, and yet this was not only one of the faces in that picture, because back
towards the other hand, showed me a set of not less attractive. I discovered even the Chipicani,
the Tacora, and all the mountains of western plain, which had just transpose, and on which my
eyes had been arrested many times during the three days of my traffic of the Cordilleras.

I went to the Bolivian plains situated even at the height of four
thousand yards above sea level, and that is the most populated of
the republic.

I came to the city of La-Paz, the former Choquehapu (Gold country), named for its abundance
of this metal mines, gave the Aymara. This valley favored by the proximity of the Yungas, which is
three thousand seven hundred lifting beam, holds to the same time all the fruit markets of the
countries cold, the temperate and torrid zone. Immediately wrote to the government, forwarding my
letters of recommendation. In response he offered me his protection, and funds if needed, also
proposes a military officer and two youths to accompany me. Not wanting to abuse of such generous
offers, I accepted, with the greatest gratitude, only the last two and transportation facilities throughout
the republic, and from that moment, I considered and sure you can go with this beautiful and rich
fruit of the American continent.

Eager to see the province of Yungas, which they said to me many wonders,
dirijíme to Palca, and once placed on the summit of the Cordillera
Oriental, I was dazzled so by the majesty of the whole, which certainly
did not see but the vast extension without to realize the details.

It was no longer a snowy mountain that I thought to grab, no was a wide plain, cloudless and
without active vegetation .... Everything was different here. Turning towards the side of La-Paz
still sailing the arid mountains and the sky is always pure, typical the high plains. Everywhere,
at the level where I was, clad heights ice and snow, but what a contrast by the side of the
Yungas! Until five or six hundred yards below me, upholstered in green velvet mountains, and that seemed
reflected in clear skies and calm to this point, a border of white clouds, representing a vast
sea battering the flanks of the mountains, and above which rise to all highest peaks, appearing
islets. When the clouds parted, I discovered a unfathomable depth below this zone, the limit
of vegetation on, the green dark blue of the virgin forests that adorn everywhere so rugged
terrain. Full of joy at being surrounded by nature, so different from the one I had submitted
the western slopes and plains of the mountain, I want first to hide under this canopy of clouds,
a few moments to roam freely over the region of thunder.

I visited on Yanacachi, Chupi, Chulumani Irupana, etc., Alternately passing the riverbed to the top
of the mountains. The pompous vegetation of Rio de Janeiro you go away reproduced in these sites,
but with more splendor in a warm moisture encourages them even on the most rugged rocks, plants
prodigious.

After having studied in detail this province, so rich in production, followed by the same western
side, crossing uneven terrain, but rich in silver mines in the provinces of Sicasica and Ayupaya,
through Cajuata, Suri, Inquisivi, and Palca Cavaria to climb the mountain again east, where
my eyes fell suddenly, to a few thousand feet, on the rich valleys of Cochabamba and Clisa. What a singular
contrast with that of the cliffs where I was! It was the image of chaos next to the largest peace:
it was the nature sad and silent in the presence of more vibrant life. I saw it in the midst
of barren hills two extended plains cultivated and trimmed on all sides of huts and groves,
among which were distinguished large number of villages, and a great city to which we excel their
buildings as a queen among his vassals. Nothing can effectively compare to the sensation that
produces the appearance of these plains, covered with villages, plantations and culture, circumscribed
by a mountainous and barren nature, extending to more thirty leagues around the horizon lost confused.
One would think there's see promised land within the wilderness. If I ever tried had vivid
impressions presence of the beauties of that savage nature Boliviano great plain, and Eastern Cordillera,
where life does not fit all in all, it is nothing there regarding the man, they would not be
much higher, finding these places I animated, these buildings strewn plains, these rich fields
abound that aroused in my mind the image of my country!

Cochabamba and its surroundings were for a time the theater of my research, continuing then my
march towards the east, walked through a hundred miles of mountains quite dry, but cut of fertile
and deep valleys. During this journey I recognized on the provinces of Clisa, Mizque and the Valle
Grande, following the path of Punata, Pacon, Totora, Chaluani, Chilon, Pampa Grande and Samaypata
(the bench rest), the last inhabited place in the mountains of which only thirty leagues were
far from the fertile plains of the continental center.

Few days Later it was discovered, the top of the slope of Flask, the extended horizon of a flat hot
covered with forests, in whose center is granted the quiet town of Santa-Cruz-de-la-Sierra.

The study of this remarkable city and its contours occupied my attention for several months: past
them, I resolved to penetrate deeper in the lands inhabited. I was already as to three hundred
leagues from the sea, but also longing to know the pure populations Indians, I turned my place
on the east, towards the province of Chiquitos, atrevasando the Monte Grande, whose thick foliage
covers an area of ??more than sixty leagues, where vain Guests will seek out other savage animals.

Chiquitos Province, placed in the center of the Americas, has over ten and eight thousand miles
in area, and being very fertile their land, it can be grown all the fruits of the hot countries,
while in the mountains of Santiago could sown wheat and planted vines. I visited on San-Javier, Concepcion,
San-Miguel, Santa Ana, San-Ignacio, San-Rafael, San-José and Santiago, and just came to find
on these mountains in the spring of those regions.

While the hot sun toasted the surrounding plains, some charities clouds perched on top of the
mountains, had operated a total change in the appearance of nature. The trees were covered in a
sweet variety of foliage and flowers, the countryside luxuriously deployed its exquisite ropages.
Absolutely nothing could compare the beautiful station in Europe to a certain moment in the
torrid zones.

In France, for example, the leaves are sprouting little by little, and the cold and lack of
beautiful days are often feel even after late spring. In places, this is but the change Suddenly
a decoration. Nature is dead, lifeless, a very pure sky field illuminates a sad and almost deserted,
but a downpour occurs, and to the point, as charm, all things take a new life. Requires only
a few days for glazing Meadows greenery and fragrant flowers, and trees coated with these tender
green leaves, or with the flowers that precede them, giving to each one of them a bright color and smooth.
If the countryside flaunting their beautiful carpet, embalmed the air with perfumes softer, forests
have less other non-flattering beauty and variety. Here a tree laden with long clusters purple
contrasts with the glasses, and sky, and the purest gold, there stands a snow-white summit
meeting to more tender pink. I climbed with much rejoicing by those slopes, where vegetables
are so beautiful façade, with its jewels, or walked the meadows without knowing which site to
give preference, as each of them offered me a charm it was particular, a different type. I confess
that I never felt so amazed in the presence of the beauties of the ground covered by a canopy so splendid.

Leaving
very soon the little town of Santiago, and through immense forests and the river of Tucabaca, probably
intended to deliver rich gold mines, arrived at Saint-Heart, which is the easternmost point
of the inhabited places of the republic. Holy Heart was actually end that part of the world because
no one could then spend more later. So Therefore, calculating the massive benefits that would
result from the navigation of the Paraguay to commercial traffic and to the civilization of
the province of Chiquitos, and longing to be the first instrument of this giant, picked up all
possible data of indigenous used to traverse the forests, and I open
a way towards the ruins of ancient Holy Heart, where the river runs
Oxuquis, consisting of rivers and Tucabaca San-Rafael, reaching to
make sure that the high steep banks of this stream could provide,
in all seasons port and comfortable hotel within walking distance
of the Paraguay River, which flows a bit above the fort of New-Coimbra.

In 1831, these important data communicated to the government of Bolivia, making him see the positive
change that for the province and the whole republic would result in a new way of communication,
by the Rio de la Plata, the Atlantic Ocean.

Eager to explore another point of Chiquitos, through beautiful forests in the mission I set San-Juan,
and returned at once to San-Javier, where I also said goodbye to departed the province, after
six months I had dedicated to his study.

Amid the vast and gloomy forests that separate the vast provinces of Chiquitos and Moxos, and a large
complex, which is indicated in our best maps and unknown runs a navigable river but also ignored:
this river is the San-Miguel. Its banks covered of vegetation as luxurious as active, are inhabited
by a remarkable nation, such Guarayos are, they do in America, for their open hospitality and customs
quite simple and primitive, the poetic dream of a golden age. Among these men of simple nature, who
never tormented jealousy, theft, this moral plague grossest civilizations
as the more refined, it is not known.

If some I had often longed to lie in the abandonment seeing magnificent countryside, while
Europe so many unhappy peasants perish in misery, how much more acute sense should not be my
in the presence of those places, the most abundant that I had found
until then, and wherein a prodigious nature, and a special class of
vegetation, it seems be asking to use arms to come through the crop
producer!
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>