<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02112</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>29808</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>686</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Este contestaba:--Un fuego en
Jesús del Monte; el otro:--Un levantamiento de negros en la tenería de Xifré; aquél:--Un robo
en la calle de las Figuras; quién:--Un matado.

El último en hablar fue el único que se acercó a la verdad, confirmando la noticia algo después
de las tres de la tarde, con muchos aspavientos y palabras inconexas, el carretillero o aguador
Polanco. Muy conocido en el barrio, su aparición en la calle Ancha fue saludada con un escopeteo
graneado y cruzado de preguntas de ventana a ventana. Ocioso era aquel trabajo, porque él de
motu propio venía anunciando la muerte alevosa de Tondá, delante de la zapatería de la calle
de Manrique esquina a la de la Maloja.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05270</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>15650</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>674</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> This answered:-A fire in Jesus on
the mount; the other:-an uprising of black in the tannery of Xifré; one:-A theft on the streets
of the figures; who:-A killed.

The last talk was the only one that approached the truth, confirming the news something after three
in the afternoon, with many fanfare and disjointed words, the carretillero or waterseller Polanco.
Well known in the neighborhood, his appearance in the high street was greeted with an escopeteo
grained and crossed of questions from window to window. Idle was that job, because of their own
initiative came announcing the death alevosa of Tondá, in front
of the shoe of the Manrique street corner to the Maloj</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>