<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09022</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>520582</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20228</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
La guardia de la cárcel andaba en el ajo. No había más que presentarse, y los mismos soldados
abrirían las puertas, poniendo en libertad a todos los compañeros presos.

El gigantón quedó un momento pensativo, rascándose la frente, como si quisiera ayudar con estos
restregones la marcha de su pensamiento embrollado.

--Está bien--exclamó después de larga pausa.--Esto es cuestión de ser hombres, o de no serlo:
de meterse en la ciudad, y salga lo que saliere, o de marcharse a dormir.

Brillaba en sus ojos la fría resolución, el fatalismo de los que se resignan a ser conductores
de hombres. Echaba sobre él la responsabilidad de una rebelión que no había preparado. Sabía
tanto del movimiento sedicioso, como aquella gente que parecía absorta en la penumbra del crepúsculo,
sin acertar a explicarse qué hacía allí.

--¡Compañeros!--gritó imperiosamente.--¡A Jerez los que tengan riñones! Vamos a sacar de la
cárcel a nuestros pobres hermanos... y a lo que se tercie. Salvatierra está allí.

El primero en aproximarse al improvisado caudillo, fue Paco el de Trebujena, el bracero rebelde,
despedido de todos los cortijos, que andaba por el campo con su borriquillo vendiendo aguardiente
y papeles revolucionarios.

--Yo voy contigo, Juanón, ya que el compañero Fernando nos espera.

--¡El que sea hombre, y tenga vergüenza, que me siga!--continuó Juanón a grandes gritos, sin
saber ciertamente adonde conducir a los compañeros.

Pero a pesar de sus llamamientos a la virilidad y la vergüenza, la mayor parte de los reunidos
se hacía atrás instintivamente. Un rumor de desconfianza, de inmensa decepción, elevábase de
la muchedumbre. Los más, pasaban de golpe del entusiasmo ruidoso al recelo y al miedo. Su fantasía
de meridionales, siempre dispuesta a lo inesperado y maravilloso, les había hecho creer en
la aparición de Salvatierra y otros revolucionarios célebres, todos montados en briosos corceles,
como caudillos arrogantes e invencibles, seguidos de un gran ejército que surgía milagrosamente
de la tierra. ¡Asunto de acompañar a estos auxiliares poderosos en su entrada en Jerez, reservándose
la fácil tarea de matar a los vencidos y adjudicarse sus riquezas! Y en vez de esto, les hablaban
de entrar solos en aquella ciudad, que se dibujaba en el horizonte, sobre el último resplandor
de la puesta del sol y parecía guiñarles satánicamente los ojos rojizos de su alumbrado, como
atrayéndolos a una emboscada. Ellos no eran tontos. La vida resultaba dura con su exceso de
trabajo y su hambre perpetua; pero peor era morir. ¡A casa! ¡a casa!...

Y los grupos comenzaron a desfilar en dirección opuesto a la ciudad; a perderse en la penumbra,
sin querer oír los insultos de Juanón y los más exaltados.

Estos, temiendo que la inmovilidad facilitase las deserciones, dieron la orden de marcha.

--¡A Jerez! ¡A Jerez!...

Emprendieron el camino. Eran unos mil; los obreros de la ciudad, y los hombres-fieras, que
habían ido a la reunión oliendo sangre y no podían retirarse, como si les empujase un instinto
superior a su voluntad.

Al lado de Juanón, entre los más animosos, marchaba el Maestrico, aquel muchacho que pasaba
las noches en la gañanía, enseñándose a leer y escribir.

--Creo que vamos mal--decía a su vigoroso compañero.--Marchamos a ciegas. He visto hombres
que corrían hacia Jerez, para avisar nuestra llegada. Nos esperan; pero no para nada bueno.

--Tú te cayas, Maestrico--repuso imperiosamente el caudillo, que, orgulloso de su cargo, acogía
como una irreverencia la menor objeción.--Te cayas; eso es. Y si tienes miedo, te najas como
los otros. Aquí no queremos cobardes.

--¡Yo cobarde!--exclamó con sencillez el muchacho.--Adelante, Juanón. ¡Pa lo que vale la vida!...

Marchaban silenciosos, con la cabeza baja, como si fuesen a embestir a la ciudad. Trotaban
cual si deseasen salir lo antes posible de la incertidumbre que les acompañaba en su carrera.

El Madrileño explicaba su plan. A la cárcel seguidamente: a sacar a los compañeros presos.
Allí se les uniría la tropa. Y Juanón, como si no se pudiera ordenar nada que no fuese por
su voz, repetía a gritos:

--¡A la cárcel, muchachos! ¡A salvar a nuestros hermanos!

Dieron un largo rodeo para entrar en la ciudad por una callejuela, como si les avergonzase
pisar las vías anchas y bien iluminadas. Muchos de aquellos hombres habían estado en Jerez
muy contadas veces, desconocían las calles y seguían a sus conductores con la docilidad de
un rebaño, pensando con inquietud en el modo de salir de allí si les obligaban a escapar.

La avalancha negra y muda avanzaba con sordo tropel de pasos que conmovía el piso. Cerrábanse
las puertas de las casas, apagábanse las luces en las ventanas. Desde un balcón los insultó
una mujer.

--¡Canallas! ¡Gentuza ordinaria! ¡Ojalá os ahorquen, que es lo que merecéis!...

Y en los guijarros del pavimento, resonó el choque de una vasija de barro rompiéndose, sin
que los fragmentos alcanzasen a nadie. Era la Marquesita, que desde el balcón del ganadero
de cerdos, indignábase contra aquella gentuza, antipática por su ordinariez, que osaba amenazar
a las personas decentes.

Sólo unos pocos levantaron la cabeza: Los demás siguieron adelante, insensibles a la ridícula
agresión, deseando llegar cuanto antes al encuentro de los amigos. Los que eran de la ciudad
reconocieron a la Marquesita, y al alejarse contestaron sus insultos con palabras tan clásicas
como impúdicas. ¡Pero qué punta aquella! De no ir de prisa, la hubieran dado una zurra por
debajo de las enaguas...

La columna sufrió cierto reflujo al subir la cuesta que conducía a la plaza de la Cárcel: el
sitio de peor sombra de la ciudad. Muchos de los rebeldes se acordaban de los camaradas de
La Mano Negra: allí les habían dado garrote.

La plaza estaba solitaria: el antiguo convento convertido en cárcel tenía cerradas todas sus
aberturas, sin una luz en las rejas. Hasta el centinela se había ocultado detrás del gran portón.

Detúvose la cabeza de la columna al entrar en la plaza, resistiendo el empujón de los que venían
detrás. ¡Nadie! ¿Quién iba a ayudarles? ¿Dónde estaban los soldados que debían unirse a ellos?...

No tardaron en saberlo. De una reja baja partió una llama fugaz, una línea roja disolviéndose
en humo. Un trallazo enorme y seco conmovió la plaza. Después, otro y otro, hasta nueve, que
a la gente, inmóvil por la sorpresa, le parecieron infinitos en número. Era la guardia, que
hacía fuego antes de que ellos se pusieran delante de los fusiles.

La sorpresa y el terror dieron a algunos un cándido heroísmo. Avanzaban gritando, con los brazos
abiertos.

--¡No tiréis, hermanos, que nos han vendío!... ¡Hermanos: que no venimos por la mala!...

Pero los hermanos eran duros de oreja, y seguían tirando. De pronto se inició en la turba el
pavor de la fuga. Corrieron todos cuesta abajo, cobardes y valientes, empujándose unos a otros,
atropellándose, como si les azotasen las espaldas aquellos disparos que seguían conmoviendo
la plaza desierta.

Juanón y los más enérgicos, contuvieron al doblar una esquina el torrente de hombres. Los grupos
se rehicieron: pero más pequeños, menos compactos. Ya no eran más que unos seiscientos hombres.
El crédulo caudillo blasfemaba con voz sorda.

--A ver: que venga el Madrileño: que nos explique esto.

Pero fue inútil buscarle. El Madrileño había desaparecido en la dispersión, se había ocultado
en las callejuelas al sonar los disparos, como todos los que conocían la ciudad. Sólo quedaban
al lado de Juanón los que eran de la sierra y marchaban a tientas por las calles, asombrados
de ir de un lado a otro, sin ver a nadie, como si la ciudad estuviese deshabitada.

--Ni Salvatierra está en Jerez, ni sabe nada de esto--dijo el Maestrico a Juanón.--Me paece
que nos la han dao.

--Lo mismo creo--contestó el atleta.--¿Y qué vamos a jacer? Ya que estamos aquí, vámonos al
centro de Jerez, a la calle Larga.

Emprendieron una marcha en desorden por el interior de la ciudad. Lo que les tranquilizaba,
infundiéndoles cierto valor, era no encontrar obstáculos ni enemigos. ¿Dónde estaba la guardia
civil? ¿Por qué se ocultaba la tropa? El hecho de permanecer encerrada en sus acuartelamientos,
dejando la ciudad en poder de ellos, les infundía la absurda esperanza de que aún era posible
la aparición de Salvatierra, al frente de las tropas sublevadas.

Llegaron sin ningún obstáculo a la calle Larga. Ninguna precaución a su llegada. La vía estaba
limpia de transeúntes; pero en los casinos los balcones mostrábanse iluminados; los pisos bajos
no tenían otro cierre que las cancelas de cristales.

Los rebeldes pasaban ante las sociedades de los ricos lanzándolas miradas de odio, pero sin
detenerse apenas. Juanón esperaba un arrebato de cólera del rebaño miserable: hasta se preparaba
a intervenir con su autoridad de jefe para aminorar la catástrofe.

--¡Esos son los ricos!--decían en los grupos.

--Los que nos engordan con gazpachos de perro.

--Los que nos roban. ¡Míalos cómo se beben nuestra sangre!...

Y después de una breve detención, seguían su desfile apresuradamente, como si fuesen a alguna
parte y temieran llegar con retraso.

Empuñaban las terribles podaderas, las hoces, las navajas... ¡Que saliesen los ricos y verían
cómo rodaban sus cabezas sobre el adoquinado! Pero había de ser en la calle, pues todos ellos
sentían cierta repugnancia a empujar las cancelas, como si los cristales fuesen un muro infranqueable.

Los largos años de sumisión y cobardía pesaban sobre la gente ruda al verse frente a sus opresores.
Además, les intimidaba la luz de la gran calle, sus anchas aceras con filas de faroles, el
resplandor rojo de los balcones. Todos formulaban mentalmente la misma excusa para disculpar
su debilidad. ¡Si pillasen en campo raso a aquella gente!...

Al pasar frente al Círculo Caballista, aparecieron tras los cristales varias cabezas de jóvenes.
Eran señoritos que seguían con inquietud mal disimulada el desfile de los huelguistas. Pero
al verles pasar de largo, mostraron cierta ironía en sus ojos, recobrando la confianza en la
superioridad de su casta.

--¡Viva la Revolución Social!--gritó el Maestrico, como si le doliese pasar silencioso ante
el nido de los ricos.

Los curiosos desaparecieron, pero al ocultarse reían, causándoles la aclamación gran regocijo.
¡Mientras se contentasen con gritar!...

Llegaron en su marcha sin objeto a la plaza Nueva, y al ver que el jefe se detenía, agrupáronse
en torno de él, con la mirada interrogante.

--¿Y ahora qué hacemos?--preguntaron con inocencia.--¿Adónde vamos?

Juanón ponía un gesto feroz.

--Podéis diros donde queráis; ¡pa lo que hacemos!... Yo a tomar el fresco.

Y arrebujándose en la manta, apoyó la espalda en la columna de un farol, quedando inmóvil,
en una actitud que revelaba desaliento.

La gente se esparció, dividiéndose en pequeños grupos. Improvisábanse jefes, guiando cada uno
a los camaradas en distinta dirección. La ciudad era suya: ¡ahora comenzaba lo bueno! Aparecía
el instinto atómico de la raza, incapaz de acometer nada en conjunto, privada del valor colectivo,
y que únicamente se siente fuerte y emprendedora cuando cada individuo puede obrar por inspiración
propia.

La calle Larga se había oscurecido: los casinos estaban cerrados. Después de la ruda prueba
sufrida por los ricos, viendo pasar el desfile amenazante, temían éstos un reculón de la fiera,
arrepentida de su magnanimidad, y todas las puertas se cerraban.

Un grupo numeroso se dirigió al teatro. Allí estaban los ricos, los burgueses. Había que matarlos
a todos: un drama de verdad. Pero al llegar los jornaleros ante la puerta iluminada, detuviéronse
con un temor que tenía algo de religioso. Nunca habían entrado allí. El aire, caliente, cargado
de emanaciones de gas, y el rumor de innumerables conversaciones que se escapaban por las rendijas
de la cancela, intimidábanles como la respiración de un monstruo oculto tras las cortinas rojas
del vestíbulo.

¡Que salieran! ¡que salieran y sabrían lo que era bueno!... ¿Pero, entrar allí?...

Asomaron a la puerta varios espectadores, atraídos por la noticia de la invasión que llenaba
las calles. Uno de ellos, con capa y sombrero de señorito, osó avanzar hasta aquellos hombres
envueltos en mantas, que formaban un grupo frente al teatro.

Cayeron sobre él, rodeándolo, con las podaderas y las hoces en alto, mientras los otros espectadores
huían, refugiándose en el teatro. ¡Ya tenían, por fin, lo que buscaban! Era el burgués, el
burgués ahíto, al que había que sangrar, para que devolviese al pueblo toda la substancia que
había sorbido...

Pero el burgués, un joven robusto, de mirada tranquila y franca, les contuvo con un gesto.

--¡Eh, compañeros! ¡Que soy un trabajador como vosotros!

--Las manos: a ver las manos--rugieron algunos braceros, sin abatir sus armas amenazantes.

Y por entre los embozos de la capa, aparecieron unas manos fuertes, cuadradas, con las uñas
roídas por el trabajo. Uno tras otro, iban aquellos hombres acariciando las palmas, apreciando
sus duricias. Tenía callos: era de los suyos. Y las armas amenazadoras volvían a ocultarse
bajo las mantas.

--Sí, soy de los vuestros--siguió diciendo el joven.--Soy carpintero, pero me gusta vestir
como los señoritos, y en vez de pasar la noche en la taberna, la paso en el teatro. Cada cual
tiene sus aficiones...

Esta decepción causó tal desaliento en los huelguistas, que muchos de ellos se retiraron. ¡Cristo!
¿dónde se ocultaban los ricos?...

Marchaban por las calles anchas y por las callejuelas apartadas, en pequeños grupos, deseando
encontrar a alguien, para que les enseñase las manos. Era el mejor medio de reconocer a los
enemigos del pobre. Pero ni con callos ni sin ellos, encontraban a nadie ante su paso.

La ciudad parecía desierta. La gente, viendo que la fuerza armada seguía oculta en los cuarteles,
corría a encerrarse en sus casas, exagerando la importancia de la invasión, creyendo que eran
millones de hombres los que ocupaban las calles y los alrededores de la ciudad.

Un grupo de cinco braceros tropezó en una calleja con un señorito. Eran de los más feroces
de la banda; hombres que sentían una impaciencia homicida, al ver que transcurrían las horas
sin que corriese la sangre.

--Las manos; enséñanos las manos--rugieron rodeándole, elevando sobre su cabeza las cuchillas
cuadradas y relucientes.

--¡Las manos!--contestó de mal humor el joven, desembozándose.--¿Y por qué he de enseñarlas?
No me da la gana.

Pero uno de ellos le agarró los brazos con sus zarpas, y de un violento tirón, le hizo enseñar
las manos.

--¡No tié callos!--exclamaron con lúgubre alegría.

Y se hicieron un paso atrás, como para caer sobre él con mayor ímpetu. Pero les detuvo la serenidad
del joven.

--No tengo callos, ¿y qué? Pero soy un trabajador como vosotros. Tampoco los tiene Salvatierra,
¡y para que seáis más revolucionarios que él!...

El nombre de Salvatierra pareció detener en lo alto las pesadas cuchillas.

--Dejad al muchacho--dijo a espaldas de ellos la voz de Juanón.--Yo le conozco y respondo de
él. Es el amigo del compañero Fernando; es de la idea.

Aquellos bárbaros abandonaron a Fermín Montenegro con cierta pena, viendo malogrado su placer.
La presencia de Juanón les imponía respeto. Además, por el fondo de la calleja avanzaba otro
joven. Aquel no sería de la idea; algún retoño de burgués, que se retiraba a su casa.

Mientras Montenegro agradecía a Juanón su oportuna presencia, que le salvaba de la muerte,
verificábase un poco más allá el encuentro de los braceros con el transeúnte.

--Las manos, burgués; enséñanos las manos.

El burgués era un adolescente pálido y desmedrado, un muchacho de dieciséis años, con el traje
raído, pero con gran cuello y vistosa corbata; el lujo de los pobres. Temblaba de miedo al
enseñar sus pobres manos finas y anémicas, manos de escribiente encerrado a las horas de sol
en la jaula de una oficina. Lloraba, al excusarse con palabras entrecortadas, mirando las podaderas
con ojos de terror, como si le hipnotizase el frío del acero. Venía del escritorio... había
velado... estaban en el trabajo del balance...

--Gano dos pesetas, señores... dos pesetas. No me peguen... me iré a casa; mi madre me espera...
¡aaay!...

Fue un alarido de dolor, de miedo, de desesperación, que conmovió toda la calle. Un aullido
espeluznante, al mismo tiempo que estallaba algo como una olla rota, y el joven caía de espaldas
en el suelo.

Juanón y Fermín, estremecidos de horror, corrieron hacia el grupo, viendo en el centro de él
al muchacho, con la cabeza en un charco negro que crecía y crecía, y las piernas estirándose
y contrayéndose con el estertor agónico. Una podadera le había abierto el cráneo, rompiendo
los huesos.

Los brutos parecían satisfechos de su obra.

--Mialo--decía uno de ellos.--¡El aprendiz de burgués! Se muere como un pollo... Ya vendrán
luego los maestros.

Juanón prorrumpió en blasfemias. ¿Esto era todo lo que sabían hacer? ¡Cobardes! Habían pasado
ante los casinos, donde estaban los ricos, los verdaderos enemigos, sin ocurrírseles más que
dar voces, temiendo romper los cristales que eran su única defensa. Sólo servían para asesinar
a un niño, a un trabajador como ellos, a un pobre zagal de escritorio, que ganaba dos pesetas
y tal vez mantenía a su madre.

Fermín llegó a temer que el atleta cayese navaja en mano sobre sus compañeros.

--¡Aonde ir con estos brutos!--rugía Juanón.--Premita Dios u el demonio que nos cojan a todos
y nos ajorquen... Y a mí el primero, por bestia; por haber creído que servíais pa algo.

El desdichado hombretón se alejó, queriendo evitar un choque con sus feroces camaradas. Estos
escaparon también, como si las palabras del jayán les hubiesen devuelto la razón.

Montenegro, al verse solo frente al cadáver, tuvo miedo. Comenzaban a crujir algunas ventanas
después de la fuga precipitada de los matadores y huyó, temiendo que le sorprendiesen los vecinos
junto al muerto.

No se detuvo en su fuga hasta llegar a las calles grandes. Allí creía estar mejor guardado
de las fieras sueltas, que iban exigiendo que las enseñasen las manos.

Al poco rato pareciole que la ciudad despertaba. Sonó a lo lejos un estruendo que hacía temblar
el suelo, y poco después pasó al trote un escuadrón de lanceros por la calle Larga. Luego,
al extremo de ésta, brillaron las hileras de bayonetas y avanzó la infantería con rítmico paso.
Las fachadas de las grandes casas parecían alegrarse abriendo de golpe sus puertas y balcones.

La fuerza armada extendíase por toda la ciudad. La luz de los faroles hacía brillar los cascos
de los jinetes, las bayonetas de los infantes, los tricornios charolados de la guardia civil.
En la penumbra se destacaban las manchas rojas de los pantalones de la tropa y los correajes
amarillos de los guardias.

Los que habían contenido en el encierro a estas fuerzas, creían llegado el momento de esparcirlas.
Durante algunas horas, la ciudad se había entregado, sin resistencia, fatigándose en una monótona
espera por la parsimonia de los rebeldes. Pero ya había corrido la sangre. Bastaba un solo
cadáver, el cadáver que justificaría las crueles represalias, para que despertase la autoridad
de su sueño voluntario.

Fermín pensaba, con honda tristeza, en el infeliz escribiente, tendido allá en la callejuela,
víctima explotada hasta en su muerte, que facilitaba el pretexto buscado por los poderosos.

Comenzó por todo Jerez la cacería de hombres. Pelotones de guardia civil y de infantería de
línea, guardaban inmóviles la entrada de las calles, mientras la caballería y fuertes patrullas
de a pie ojeaban la ciudad, deteniendo a los sospechosos.

Fermín iba de un lado a otro sin encontrar obstáculos. Su exterior era de señorito, y la fuerza
armada sólo daba caza a las mantas, a los sombreros de campo, a los chaquetones rudos; a todos
los que tenían aspecto de trabajadores. Montenegro los veía pasar en fila, camino de la cárcel,
entre las bayonetas y las grupas de los caballos, unos abatidos, como si les sorprendiese la
aparición hostil de la fuerza armada «que había de unirse a ellos»: otros, asombrados, no comprendiendo
cómo las cuerdas de presos despertaban tal alegría en la calle Larga, cuando habían desfilado
por ella horas antes como triunfadores, sin permitirse el menor atropello.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08120</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>201569</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17938</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The
prison guard was walking in the garlic. There was only presented, and the soldiers doors would
open, releasing all imprisoned comrades.

The giant was thought for a moment, rubbing his forehead as if to
help with these Progress rubs his muddled thinking.

- Okay - after
a long pause said .-- This is a matter to be men, or not to be: getting
into the city and what comes out, that or go to sleep.

Shone in his eyes cold resolution, the fatalism of those who resign themselves to be drivers men.
Poured on him the responsibility of a rebellion that had not prepared. Knew much of seditious
movement, and those people who seemed absorbed in the twilight, without being able to explain why he
was there.

- Comrades! - Shouted imperiously .-- A Jerez those with kidney!

Let's get the our poor brothers prison ... and what is third. Salvatierra is there.

The first to approach the makeshift leader, was Trebujena Paco, the
bracero rebel dismissed from all the villages, as he walked the field
with his donkey selling liquor and revolutionary roles.

- I'm going
with you, Juanon, as the mate Fernando ahead.

- He who is man, and
be shy, follow me! - Continued Juanon large screams, no certainly
lead to know where peers.

But despite appeals to manhood and shame, most of those gathered is
backwards instinctively.

A murmur of distrust, of immense disappointment, elevábase of the crowd. Most, passed suddenly
noisy enthusiasm to suspicion and fear. Her fantasy of southern, always ready for the unexpected
and wonderful, had made them believe in the emergence of Salvatierra and other famous revolutionaries,
all mounted on spirited steeds, as arrogant and invincible warlords, followed by a large army
which miraculously emerged land. Subject to accompany these powerful aids in its entry into Jerez,
reserving the easy task of killing the vanquished, and awarded her wealth! And instead of this,
I spoke to go alone in that city, that drew on the horizon, over the last glow of the setting sun and
seemed to wink satanically his eyes red lighting, as drawing them into an ambush. They were not fools.
Life was hard on her too much work and perpetual hunger, but worse was to die. A house! Home!
...

And the groups began to march in the direction opposite to the city
to get lost in the shadows, not wanting to hear the insults and the
most exalted Juanon.

These, fearing defections facilitate immobility gave the marching orders.

- A Jerez! A Jerez! ...

Out on the road.

Were a thousand city workers, and men-beasts that The meeting had been smelling blood and they
could not withdraw, as if instinct urges them superior to his will.

Juanon Next, among the most courageous, walked the Maestrico, the boy who passed night in the Gañanía,
teaching reading and writing.

- I think we're going wrong - he said to his companion .-- vigorous
march blindly.

I have seen men running at Jerez, to warn our arrival. We expect, but not for anything good.

-
You will Cayas, Maestrico - said imperiously leader, who, proud of
his office, welcomed as the least objection .-- irreverence Cayas
you, that is.

And if you fear, as you najas others. Here we are not cowards.

- I coward - the boy simply said .-- Forward, Juanon.

Pa what life is worth! ...

They marched in silence, with bowed head, as if they would attack the city. Trotting as if
he wished to leave as soon as possible to the uncertainty that accompanied them in their career.

The
Spaniard explained his plan. A jail then: to get the fellow prisoners.
There they join the troop.

And Juanon, as if he could order anything that was not for his voice, he repeated loudly:

- A prison, boys!

To save our brothers!

They took a long detour to get into the city by a street, as if they were ashamed treading
the well-lit wide roads. Many of these men had been in Jerez very few times, unaware of the streets
and followed their conductors with docility a herd, thinking concerns
the way out of there if they were forced to flee.

The avalanche was moving black deaf and dumb crowd of steps that touched the floor. Cerrábanse
the doors of the houses, apagábanse the lights in the windows. From a balcony insulted a woman.

-
Scoundrels! Ordinary riffraff!

Hopefully I'll be damned, that's what you deserve! ...

And in the stones of the pavement, echoed the shock of breaking a
clay pot without that the fragments reached anyone.

Marcasite was that from the balcony of livestock pigs, indignant against that mob, unpleasant
for its ordinariness, who dared threaten decent people.

Only a few raised their heads: The others followed later, insensitive
to the ridiculous aggression, anxious to reach as soon as possible
to meet friends.

Those who were in the city recognized the Marquis, and answered his insults away with words so
classic as immodest. But what that tip! Not to hurry, she had been given a spanking by under
skirts ...

The column was somewhat reflux to the top of the hill leading to the square of the Prison: The worst
site shadow of the city.

Many of the rebels remembered the comrades La Mano Negra: there had given them stick.

The square was deserted, the ancient convent converted in prison had closed all openings, with no
light bars. Until the guard was hiding behind the big gate.

He stopped the head of the column to enter the plaza, resisting the push from those who came behind.
No! Who would help? Where were the soldiers who were to join them? ...

They soon know. Broke down a fence shooting a flame, a red line dissolving
in smoke.

A huge, dry whiplash shaken the plaza. Then another and another until nine, which people, still
in shock, seemed infinite in number. It was the guard, made fire before they were put in front
of the guns.

Surprise and terror gave some a naive heroism. Advanced screaming, arms open.

- Do not throw, brothers, that we have sold! ... Brothers, do not come from poor! ...

But the brothers were hard to ear, and kept shooting. Suddenly the crowd started in the fear
of leakage. They ran all downhill, cowardly and brave, pushing each other, violated, as if they
whipped their backs those shots that were shaking the empty square.

Juanon and more energetic, turning a corner contained the flood of
men.

Groups rallied, but smaller, less compact. They were no more than a hundred men. The gullible
leader swore in a low voice.

- To see: the coming of Madrid: we explain this.

But it was useless to look for.

The Madrid had disappeared in the dispersion, was hidden in the streets
to the sound of gunfire, as everyone who knew the city.

There were only Juanon beside those who were marching from the mountains
and grope through the streets, amazed to go from side to side, seeing
no one, as if the city were deserted.

- Ni Salvatierra is in Jerez,
or know anything about this - said .-- I Maestrico to Juanon paece
that have us harm.

- So I think - said the athlete .-- What we JACER?

Since we're here, let's go to center of Jerez, to Long Street.

Undertook a march in disarray inside the city. What were relieved, instilling a certain value,
was not encountering obstacles or enemies. Where was the guard civil? Why hide the troops? The
fact remain locked in their barracks, leaving the city in their hand,
they infused the absurd hope that it was still possible the emergence
of Salvatierra, in front of the rebel troops.

They arrived without any obstacle to Larga street. No precaution on arrival. The road was clean
transients, but in casinos showed themselves illuminated balconies,
the lower floors had no other close to the gates of crystals.

The rebels went to the societies of the rich hate glancing, but not just stop. Juanon expected
an outburst of anger of the miserable herd: to be prepared to interfere
with his authority as chief to mitigate the disaster.

- These are
the rich! - Said in the groups.

- Those of us who grow fat gazpacho
dog.

- Those who steal from us.

Mial how to drink our blood ...

And after a brief detention, the parade continued hastily, as if they were to some party and feared
arriving late.

Wielding the terrible shears, sickles, knives ... To go aside the
rich and would how rolling their heads on the pavement!

But there was to be on the street, they all felt some reluctance
to push the gates, as if the crystals were an insurmountable wall.

The long years of subservience and cowardice weighed on the rude people to be against their
oppressors.

In addition, they intimidated the light of the high street, wide sidewalks with rows of lanterns,
the red glow of the balconies. All mentally formulated the same excuse to excuse its weakness.
If caught in the open to those people! ...

Passing the Caballista Circle, crystals appeared after several heads
of youngsters.

They were gentlemen who were still ill-concealed concern the parade of strikers. But to see
them pass by, show some irony in his eyes, regaining confidence in the superiority of their caste.

-
Viva Social Revolution! - Maestrico shouted, as if you ache to go
silent the nest of the rich.

The curious disappeared, but the hidden laughed, causing great rejoicing acclamation. While content
with shouting! ...

They came on their way superseded the Plaza Nueva, and seeing that
the head stopped, agrupáronse around him, his eyes questioning.

-
So now what we do - asked innocently .-- Where do we go?

Juanon put a fierce gesture.

- You can Diros wherever you want, what we do pa! ... I to take the air.

And wrapped in the blanket, leaned against a lamp column, remaining motionless revealed an attitude
that disappointment.

People scattered, divided into small groups. Improvisábanse heads,
leading each comrades in a different direction.

The city was his, now began a good thing! Appeared atomic instinct of the race, unable to undertake
anything as a whole, private collective value, and only feels strong and enterprising when each
individual can work for inspiration own.

Long Street has been obscured: the casinos were closed. After the ordeal suffered by the rich,
watching the parade threatening, they feared a reculón of the beast sorry for his magnanimity,
and all doors closed.

A large group went to the theater. There were the rich, the bourgeois. Had to kill them all: a
real drama. But when he arrived at the door laborers lit they stopped with a fear that had
something religious. They had never gone there.

The air, hot, loaded of gas fumes and the sound of countless conversations that escaped through the
cracks gate, intimidábanles as the breath of a monster hiding behind the red curtains the lobby.

That
came out! Come out and know what was good! ... But, get in there? ...

Looked out the door several spectators, attracted by the news of the invasion that filled the
streets.

One of them, with cape and hat, sir, these men dared to advance to wrapped in blankets, who formed
a group outside the theater.

Fell on him, surrounding him with pruning shears and sickles in the air, while other spectators
fled, taking refuge in the theater.

They had, at last, what they wanted!

It was the bourgeoisie, the sated bourgeois, who had to bleed, to repay the people all the substance
had sucked ...

But the bourgeois, a robust young man, looking calm
and frank, I held with a gesture.

- Eh, mates!

That I am a worker like you!

- Hands: to see hands - roared some braceros, without threatening
their arms folded.

And through the fold of the cloak, appeared strong hands, square, fingernails eaten by the job.
One after another, these men were stroking the palms, appreciating their corns. Callus was:
it was yours. And threatening weapons again to hide under the covers.

- Yes, I am yours - continued the young .-- I am a carpenter, but
I like to dress as the gentlemen, and instead of spending the night
at the tavern, the step in the theater.

Each have their hobbies ...

This disappointment caused such dismay at the strikers, many of them retired. Christ! Where
they hid the rich? ...

Marched through the streets broad and narrow streets away, in small groups, looking find someone
to teach them hands.

It was the best way to recognize enemies of the poor. But not with tripe or without them, find anyone
at her pace.

The city seemed deserted.

People saw that armed force was hidden in the barracks, running to stay at home, exaggerating
the importance of the invasion, believing they were million men who filled the streets around
the city.

A group of five braceros stumbled into an alley with a gentleman.

Were the most ferocious of the band, men who felt a homicidal impatience, seeing that the hours
passed without bloodshed.

- Hands, teach hands - roared round her,
raising her head on the blades square and shiny.

- Hands! - Answered
the young man in a bad mood, overt .-- Why should I teach?

I do not want.

But one of them grabbed her arms with his claws, and a violent jerk, teach him hands.

- They have no calluses! - Dreary cried with joy.

And he made a step back, to fall upon him with greater momentum.

But I stopped serenity the young.

- I have no calluses, so what? But I am a worker like you. Nor has Salvatierra And for you to
be more revolutionary than he is! ...

Salvatierra's name at the top seemed to stop the heavy blade.

- Let the boy - said behind them the voice of Juanon .-- I know him and vouch for him. It is the
friend of teammate Fernando, is the idea.

Fermin barbarians left Montenegro with some regret, watching spoiled
his pleasure.

The presence of Juanon they commanded respect. In addition, the bottom of the lane advanced another
young. That would be the idea, a scion of bourgeois, who would retire to his home.

While thanking Montenegro Juanon their timely presence, which saved
him from death, verificábase just beyond the meeting of the transient
laborers.

- Hands, bourgeois teach hands.

The bourgeois was a pale, stunted teenager, a boy of sixteen, with the suit shabby, but with
long neck and flashy tie, the luxury of the poor. Trembling with fear teach her poor thin hands
and anemic clerk hands locked daylight hours in the cage of an office.

Crying, to excuse himself with broken words, looking at the pruning shears with eyes of terror,
as if mesmerized by the cold steel.

It came from the desktop ... had veiled ... were at work in the balance ...

- Won two pesetas, gentlemen ... two pesetas.

Do not hit me ... I will go home, my mother expected me ... Oooh! ...

It was a scream of pain, fear, despair, which moved across the street. A howl creepy, while something
like a pot broke broken and the girl fell back on the ground.

Juanon and Fermin, shuddering with horror, ran towards the group, seeing in the middle of it the
boy, his head in a black puddle that grew and grew, and stretching
legs and contracting with the death rattle. A trimmer had opened the
skull, breaking bones.

Brutes seemed satisfied with their work.

-
Mial - said one of them .-- The Apprentice bourgeois! It dies like
a chicken ... They'll come then teachers.

Juanon burst into curses.
"This was all they knew to do? Cowards! It had been to the casinos,
where they were the rich, the real enemies, not only occur to to cry,
fearing that breaking windows was his only defense. Only served to
kill a child, a worker like them, a poor lad in desk, he earned two
pesetas and perhaps kept his mother.

Fermin came to fear that the
athlete falling knife in hand over their competitors.

- Aonda go
with these brutes! - Roared Juanon premit .-- God or the devil to
catch us all and we ajorquen ... And to me the first, beast, for believing
that something worshiped pa.

The big man walked away unhappy, wanting
to avoid a clash with fierce comrades. These escaped too, as if the
words of the giants they had returned the right.

Montenegro, finding
himself alone in front of the corpse, he was afraid. Began to crack
some windows after the precipitate flight of the murderers and fled,
fearing the neighbors catch him next to the dead.

He did not stop
in his flight up to the big streets. There believed to be best kept
loose wild beasts, who were demanding that teach hands.

After a while
it seemed that the city awoke. Sounded in the distance a roar that
shook the ground, and soon moved to a squadron of lancers trotted
down the street long. Then the end of it, the rows of bayonets gleamed
and moved the infantry with rhythmic step. The facades of the great
houses suddenly seemed happy opening their doors and balconies.

The
armed forces spread throughout the city. The lamplight shone helmets
riders, the bayonets of the infants, patent-leather tricorn civil
guard. In the gloom stood out the red spots of the troop pants and
belts yellow guards.

Those who had held in confinement at these forces,
believed the time to scatter. For a few hours, the city had surrendered
without resistance, fatigue in a monotonous waiting for the parsimony
of the rebels. But I had gotten blood. It took one body, the body
that would justify the cruel reprisals, to awaken the authority your
dream volunteer.

Fermín thought, with great sorrow, the unhappy writer,
lying there on the street, victim exploited even in death, which provided
the pretext sought by the powerful.

Jerez began hunting around men.
Platoons of civil guards and infantry line input still kept the streets,
while the cavalry and heavy patrols ojeaban ordinary city, arresting
the suspects.

Fermin went back and forth without impediment. Its
exterior was Master, and strength hunted armed only with blankets,
hats field, the coats are rough all who looked like workers. Montenegro
saw them pass in a row on his way to jail between the bayonets and
the rumps of horses, some killed, as if surprised by the hostile appearance
of armed force "which was to join them 'others, stunned, not understanding
chain gangs how aroused such joy in Long Street, where they paraded
for her hours before as victors, not allowing the child abuse</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>