<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02128</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>109381</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17058</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Me la llevaré conmigo, la educaré.--

Las mujeres aquellas eran muy pobres. Gran cariño les inspiraba Clarita; pero al tenerla á
su lado la condenaban á ser pobre como ellas para toda la vida. Consideraban á don Elías como
persona de posición y carácter, y no dudaron, por lo tanto, en dejarle la niña.

Permaneció, sin embargo, en Sahagún hasta 1812, época en que el realista dejó las armas y se
retiró á Madrid. Entonces le acompañó Clara, que no pudo separarse de sus pobres amigas sin
llorar mucho, ni pudo acostumbrarse tampoco á mirar cara á cara á su protector, porque le daba
mucho miedo.

Grande fué su tristeza cuando al despertar en un hermoso día de Mayo se encontró entre las
obscuras paredes de la casa que conocemos en la calle de Válgame Dios; y esta tristeza aumentó
cuando la llevaron al convento-colegio de ciertas hermanas de una Orden famosa, que enseñaban
á las niñas del barrio lo poquito que sabían. Tenía la escuela todo lo sombrío del convento,
sin tener su claustro melancólico y su dulce paz. Dirigíanla unas cuantas viejas, entre quienes
descollaba por su displicencia, fealdad y decrepitud una tal madre Angustias, que usaba una
caña muy larga para castigar á las niñas, y unas antiparras verdes, que más que para verlas
mejor, le servían para que las pobrecillas no conocieran cuándo las miraba.

Las niñas se levantaban muy temprano, y rezaban; almorzaban unas sopas de ajos, en que solía
nadar tal cual garbanzo de la víspera, y después pasaban al estudio, que era ejercicio de lectura,
en el cual desempeñaba el principal papel la caña de doña Angustias. Trazaban luego, por espacio
de dos horas, sendos garabatos en un papel rayado; y después de contestar de memoria á las
preguntas de un catecismo, cosían tres horas largas, hasta que llegaba la del juego. El recreo
tenía lugar en un patio obscuro y hediondo, cuya vegetación consistía en un pobre clavel amarillento
y tísico que crecía en un puchero inservible, erigido en tiesto de flores. Las niñas jugaban
un rato en aquella pocilga, hasta que la madre Angustias sonaba desde su cuarto una siniestra
campanilla, que reunía en torno á su caña á los tristes ángeles del muladar.

Después de comer llevaba el rosario la madre Brígida, por no poder hacerlo la madre Angustias,
á causa del asma que la afligía, entrecortándole la voz. Aquel rosario era interminable, porque
detrás de sus infinitos paternóster venían las letanías, llagas, misterios, jaculatorias, oraciones,
gozos y endechas místicas. La noche las sorprendía en aquel devoto ejercicio, y era muy común
que alguna de las chiquillas, rendida bajo el peso moral de tan monótono y cansado rezo, bostezara
tres veces y se durmiera al fin benditamente. Parapetada detrás de sus antiparras, la madre
Angustias observaba los bostezos y acariciaba su caña dictatorial sin decir palabra á la culpable,
esperando á que se durmiera, y entonces ¡ira de Dios! le sacudía un cañazo, seguido de una
retahila de insinuaciones coléricas. Las otras niñas, que no esperaban más que un motivo de
distracción y entretenimiento, al ver la triste figura que hacía su compañera al despertar
bruscamente, soltaban la risa, se interrumpía el rezo, gruñía la madre Brígida, cacareaba la
madre Angustias, y llovían los cañazos á diestra y siniestra. Al anochecer continuaban las
lecciones y el catecismo. La madre Angustias les decía: "Ahora el ca ... ca ... tecismo. Madre
Brí ... Brí ... Brígida, la que no lo sepa, al ca ... ca ... caramanchón."

Y se marchaba á acostar, porque padecía de ciertos ahoguillos, y tenía que ponerse todas las
noches paños calientes en el estómago.

Clarita y otras niñas de la escuela creían á pie juntillas que la madre Angustias no tenía
ojos, y que todas sus facultades ópticas residían en aquellos dos temibles vidrios verdes,
engastados en una armazón rancia y enmohecida; y acontecía que para imitarla cortaban dos redondeles
de papel verde del forro del catecismo y se lo pegaban con saliva en los ojos, con lo cual
se morían de risa. Como no podían ver gota con aquellos parches, sorprendiólas un día la madre
Petronila, que era un vinagre, y después de darles muchos coscorrones, las condenó á no comer
ni jugar aquel día, ¡Qué horas pasaron las pobres!

Otra vez se hallaban todas en el patio, y ocurriósele á un pajarito muy flaco meterse allí
por el tejado y posarse, después de chocar en los muros, en el entristecido clavel. ¡Qué algazara
se armó! Aquél fué el mayor acontecimiento del año. Con pañuelos, con mantos, con cuanto hallaron
á mano, le persiguieron hasta cogerle; atáronle un hilo en una de las patas, y Clara le guardó
muy bien en un cajoncillo donde tenía la costura. A escondidas le echaban de comer por las
noches; pero el animalito enflaquecía y se ponía más triste cada vez. Una noche, en el momento
en que el rezo iba á principiar, Clara tenía abierto el costurero, y fingiendo arreglar dentro
de él alguna cosa, se ocupaba en abrirle la boca al pajarito y meterle á la fuerza unas migajas
de pan que había guardado en el bolsillo, cuando de repente alzó el vuelo el animal, revoloteó
por la habitación con el hilo atado en la pata, y fué á pararse ¿dónde creeréis? en la misma
cabeza de doña Angustias, que al verse profanada de aquel modo, tomó tal cólera, que el asma
le ahogó la voz y estuvo gesticulando en silencio diez minutos, roja como un tomate. Clara
se quedó yerta de miedo.

"Cla ... Cla ... Cla ... rita--exclamó la madre Angustias ciega de furor.--¡Niña mal ... mal
criada! ¡Qué desaca ... ca ... cato es éste? Esta noche al ca ... ca ... caramanchón."

Clara fué condenada aquella noche á dormir en el caramanchón, última pena que sólo se aplicaba
muy de tarde en tarde á los más negros y raros delitos. Doña Angustias continuó en su cacareo
hasta que vió cumplida la terrible orden; y á la hora en que acostumbraban á recogerse, Clara
fué llevada al presidio, que era un desván obscuro, fétido y pavoroso. La pobrecilla no cabía
en sí de miedo al verse sola en aquel tugurio, entre mil objetos cuya forma no podía apreciar,
tendida en un miserable jergón y expuesta al aire colado, que por una ventanilla entraba. En
su desvelo, sintió las pisadas de los ratones que en aquellos climas vivían; pisadas que en
sus oídos resonaban como si fueran producidas por los pies de un ejército de gigantes. Se encogió,
se envolvió toda en su manta, escondiendo los pies, las manos y la cabeza; pero las ratas corrían
por encima, y saltaban, iban y venían con una algarabía espantosa. También contribuyó á aumentar
el pavor de la niña una disputa que en el tejado vecino se trabó entre dos gatos bullangueros
que lanzaban maullidos lúgubres y desentonados. La pobre no pudo dormir, y el día la encontró
hecha un ovillo, empapada en sudor frío y temblando de miedo.

Entre estos sucesos extraordinarios y la diaria tarea del estudio y la costura, aterrada siempre
por la fascinación terrible de los espejuelos de la madre Angustias, pasó Clara cuatro años,
hasta que, cumplidos los once, vino Elías por ella y se la llevó á su casa.

El realista no sabía al principio qué hacer de aquella niña: ocurrióle hacerla monja; pero
impulsado por un repentino egoísmo, resolvió conservarla á su lado. Era solo: su casa necesitaba
una mujer. ¿Quién mejor que Clara? Su inteligencia no estaba bien cultivada, pues no sabía
sino leer, escribir y hacer algunas cuentas; pero, en cambio, cosía muy bien y entendía de
toda clase de labores.

La hija de la Chacona creció en casa de Coletilla, y fué mujer. Creció sin juegos, sin amables
compañeras, sin alegrías, sin esas saludables y útiles expansiones que conducen felizmente
de la niñez á la juventud. Elías no la trataba mal, pero tampoco era muy cariñoso son ella.

Los domingos la solía llevar á la Florida ó á la Virgen del Puerto; una vez la llevó al teatro,
y Clara creyó que era verdad lo que estaban representando. Los paseos dominicales cesaron cuando
Elías tuvo ocupaciones y preocupaciones que le apartaban de su casa: entonces ella se limitó
á oír misa muy de mañana en las monjas de Góngora, y en esta expedición lo acompañaba, una
criada alcarreña llamada Pascuala, que Coletilla había tomado á su servicio.

Este encierro perpetuo hubiera agriado y pervertido tal vez otro carácter menos dulce y bondadoso
que el de Clara, la cual llegó á creer que aquella vida era cosa muy natural, y que no debía
aspirar á otra cosa; así es que vivía tranquila, melancólicamente feliz, y á veces alegre.
Y, sin embargo, semanas enteras pasaban sin que una persona extraña penetrara en la casa del
fanático. Parecía que toda la sociedad quería huir de aquella jaula en que estaba encerrado
su mayor enemigo.

Sólo una excepción existía en aquel aislamiento normal. Ya hemos dicho que don Elías fué amigo
y servidor de una antigua é ilustre casa. Después de la ruina de los Porreños y Venegas, sólo
quedaron tres individuos, tres dueñas venerables que conservaron relaciones amistosas con el
realista. Muy de tarde en tarde iban á visitarle. Tenían un trato seco; eran intolerantes,
rígidas, orgullosas. Nunca hablaban á Clara sino con palabras solemnes, que daban tristeza
y abatían el ánimo. No podían prescindir de la etiqueta, ni aun delante de una pobre muchacha
y eran tan ceremoniosas y tiesas, que Clara les llegó á tomar antipatía, porque siempre que
iban á la casa dejaban allí una sombra de tristeza que duraba mucho tiempo en el alma de la
huérfana.

En los últimos años, Coletilla entraba, como hemos dicho, en el período álgido de su frenesí
político; la cólera era su estado normal, y era cosa imposible que en su fanáticas obsesiones
pudiera aquella alma irascible tener cariños y finezas para la pobre compañera que tanto las
necesitaba. Por el contrario, mostrábase muy duro con ella; se estaba sin hablarle semanas
enteras; otras veces la reprendía con acrimonia y sin motivo: la llamaba frívola y casquivana.
Un día, al ver que la desventurada se había peinado con menos sencillez que de ordinario, y
se había vestido, reformando un poco su natural elegancia con el poderoso instinto de la moda,
que las mujeres más apartadas del mundo poseen, la riñó, repitiéndole muchas veces esta frase
que le costó lágrimas á la infeliz: "Clara, te has echado á perder." Otras veces le daba al
viejo por vigilarla, y le prohibía asomarse al balcón y abrir la puerta, es decir, la abandonaba
ó la martirizaba, según el estado de aquel espíritu perturbador y cruel.

Clara se puso mala; se iba agostando con lentitud como el clavel que crecía difícilmente en
el patio de la escuela. Su melancolía creció, se puso descolorida y extenuada, y llegó á hacer
temer graves peligros para su salud. Coletilla no pudo permanecer indiferente á la enfermedad
de su protegida, y trajo un médico el cual expresó su dictamen muy brevemente, diciendo: "Si
usted no manda á esta chica al campo se muere antes de un mes."

El realista pensó que la muerte de aquella muchacha sería un contratiempo. Recordó que su hermana
vivía en Ateca con su familia, y formó su plan.

Escribió dos letras y algunos días después Clara entraba en el pueblo con el corazón rebosando
de alegría.

Benéfica reacción se verificó en su salud, y su espíritu, tanto tiempo abatido por el fastidio
y el encierro, se reanimó con el pleno goce de la Naturaleza y el trato de personas alegres
que la atendían y la amaban. Aquellos días fueron una segunda vida para la desdichada mártir,
porque se regeneró materialmente, adquiriendo lozanía, frescura y vigor: sus ojos, acostumbrados
á la obscuridad de cuatro paredes, recorrían ya un largo horizonte: sus pasos la llevaban á
grandes distancias: su voz era escuchada por amigas joviales y francas, por jóvenes sencillos,
por viejos cariñosos; su alegría era comprendida y compartida por otros; sus inocentes deseos
satisfechos; conocía la amistad, la vida familiar, la confianza; gozaba de un cielo hermoso,
de un aire puro, de un bienestar sobrio y tranquilo, de felices y no monótonos días, de sosegadas
y apacibles noches.

Pero durante la permanencia de Clara en Ateca pasaron cosas que influyeron poderosamente en
el resto de su vida. Vamos á referirlas, porque de ellas se deriva casi toda esta historia;
y por tan importantes y graves, las dejamos para el capítulo siguiente, donde las verá el lector,
si está decidido á no abandonarnos.

CAPÍTULO VI

#El sobrino de Coletilla.#

Marta, la hermana de Elías, había quedado viuda con un hijo llamado Lázaro, que después de
estudiar Humanidades en Tudela, pasó á la Universidad de Zaragoza. Era éste un mozo como de
veintitrés á veinticinco años, de agradable presencia, de ingenio muy precoz, de imaginación
viva, de palabra fácil y difusa, muy impresionable y vehemente, y de recto y noble corazón.

Las nuevas ideas, que entonces conmovían profundamente el corazón de la juventud, habían hallado
en el joven Lázaro un creyente decidido. Era uno de los que, brotados en el tumulto de un aula
de Filosofía militaban con pasión generosa en las filas de los propagadores políticos, entonces
tan necesarios.

Sucedió que los estudiantes zaragozanos trabaron una pendencia con los socios de cierto club
político; el asunto tomó proporciones, intervino la autoridad universitaria, y Lázaro se vió
obligado á salir de Zaragoza, perdiendo curso. Esto pasaba en los días en que, destituido Riego
del mando de capitán general de Aragón, hubo en aquella ciudad tumultos y manifestaciones,
que el Gobierno quiso reprimir. Lázaro, que estaba á punto de concluir la carrera, conoció
la gravedad de su situación y el disgusto que tendrían su madre y su abuelo, á quienes amaba
mucho. Quiso reclamar, pero fué inútil, y tuvo que retirarse á su pueblo, triste, avergonzado
y lleno de dudas y temores.

Pero al entrar en su casa, agitado por la zozobra y los remordimientos, vió en compañía de
su madre á una persona desconocida que desde el primer momento le produjo una secreta impresión
de alegría, imponiéndole, sin saber por qué, consuelo y esperanza. Confesó lo que le pasaba,
sin disminuir la gravedad del caso, por lo cual don Fermín, su abuelo paterno, se puso serio
y quiso enfadarse, y su madre lloró un poco. Pero la persona desconocida, que parecía estar
allí para alegrar la casa, disipó la cólera del primero y secó las lágrimas de la segunda,
mientras Lázaro, con la cabeza baja y humedecidos los ojos, permanecía inmóvil delante de sus
jueces y de su defensor sin decir palabra, aunque á la verdad no era preciso, porque la joven
le defendía muy bien sin desplegar gran elocuencia, ni emplear otros recursos que su claro
y natural sentido, su acrisolado y generoso sentimiento.

El pobre Lázaro estaba tan turbado, que se le figuraba que aquella persona era una aparición,
un ser enviado del cielo para ampararle en aquellos apurados momentos. Esperaba verla desaparecer
al concluir su misión, y la miraba con ese estupor silencioso que causa lo sobrenatural y desconocido.
No tenía antecedentes de aquella joven, ni había sospechado que existiera y se encontrara allí.
Pero la imagen no se desvanecía, y, por el contrario, continuaba viéndola adornada con todos
los encantos físicos y morales que pueden poseer los ángeles de este mundo.

No se habló más del asunto. Lázaro fué perdonado, pero no salió de sus confusiones. Explicáronle
quién era Clara y por qué estaba allí; más no por eso pudo dominar el estudiante la respetuosa
y fuerte sorpresa que le había producido.

Estuvo encogido y como asombrado todo el día, y temblóle la voz cuando quiso hablar con ella,
y se calló al fin por temor de decir mil disparates. Al día siguiente despertó con una alegría
exaltada, á la que sucedía bruscamente una tristeza sin igual. Su aturdimiento tomaba fases
muy diversas tan pronto se veía atacado de un apetito insaciable de verbosidad que no podía
contener; tan pronto hacía esfuerzos inauditos para pronunciar una palabra, sin llegar á conseguirlo.
Era un polaticómano ferviente, y en Zaragoza se había distinguido por sus elocuentes arengas
en los clubs, que le habían dado mucha celebridad; en sus conversaciones privadas se expresaba
también con mucho entusiasmo y corrección pero esta vez de todo hablaba menos de política.
Parecía que no existían ya para él ni la revolución francesa, ni el Emilio, de Rousseau, ni
las Carta de Talleyrand, ni el Diccionario, de Voltaire. Se había olvidado de todo esto, y
sólo pensaba en la fórmula más expresiva y exacta para decirle á Clara que la había visto en
sueños aquella noche. Recurrió al sistema de las circunlocuciones, pensó después en decirlo
á secas y sin ambajes, acordóse de que las alegorías se habían inventado para aquel caso, y
probó todos los medios sin lograr con ninguno su objeto.

Pasaron dos ó tres días sin que hallara un modo de ser explícito. Cuando estaba solo, sí; entonces
hablaba, hablaba consigo mismo, y aun parecías entablar misteriosos diálogos con aquel hermoso
espíritu, que encontraba siempre en todas partes, acompañándole en sus soledades é insomnios;
espíritu lleno de luz y con formas de mujer, que brotaba del seno mismo de la noche para mirarle
inmóvil, callado y sereno. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07664</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>47905</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15707</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I'll take with me, will educate .--

Those women were very poor. Inspired great affection I Clarita, but to have it beside the condemned
to be poor like them for life.

Don Elijah considered as person's position and character, and did not hesitate, therefore, in
leaving the child.

He remained, however, in Sahagun until 1812, when the realist left
their weapons and retired to Madrid.

Clara then accompanied him, unable to leave their poor friends without mourn much, and could
not get used to not looking face to face to your protector, because he was very afraid.

Great was their sorrow when waking on a beautiful day in May was found between dark walls of
the house that we know in the street Oh my God, and this sadness increased when taken to the convent-school
of some famous sisters of an Order that taught girls in the neighborhood to what little they
knew. I had school all the gloom of the convent, cloister without melancholy and sweet peace.
Dirigíanla a few old, among whom stood out for his carelessness,
ugliness and decrepitude such a distraught mother, who used a very
long cane to punish girls and a green goggles, which more than to
see better, he served for the poor things did not know when I looked
at them.

The girls woke up very early, and prayed, ate lunch a soup of garlic, I used as they swim the day
before Garbanzo, and then went to the studio, I was reading exercise, in which played the
main role of Donna Angus cane. Then traced by space two hours, two separate scribble on scratch
paper, and after answering a memorial to the questions of a catechism, sewing three long hours, until
it was the game. Recess took place in a dark and smelly courtyard, where the vegetation was
a poor yellow carnation consumptive and growing in a pot unusable, erected in flowerpot. The
girls played a while in that pigsty until the distraught mother from
her room sounded an ominous bell, which gathered around his cane to
the sad angels from the ashes.

After dinner wearing the rosary Bridget's mother, not to do this, the distraught mother, asthma to the
afflicted, broken voice. That rosary was endless, because behind her came the endless litany
paternoster, sores, mysteries, aspirations, prayers, mystical joy and lamentation. The night was surprised
at the pious exercise, and very often that some of the girls, delivered under the moral weight
as monotonous and tired prayer, yawn three times and finally slept blissfully. Sheltered behind her
glasses, the mother Distresses observed yawns and dictatorial stroked his rod without a word
to the culprit, waiting for him to sleep, and then God's wrath! shook him a rum, followed by
a string of angry insinuations. The other girls, they did not expect more than a source of
distraction and entertainment, seeing the sad figure who was his companion on awakening abruptly
burst out laughing, prayer was interrupted, the mother Bridget growled, cackled the Angus
mother and showered the rum to the right and left. In the evening continued the and catechism
lessons. The distraught mother told them: "Now the ca ... ca ...
tecismo.

Mother Bri ... Bri ... Bridget, you do not know, the ca ... ca ... garret. "

And going to bed, because he suffered from certain ahoguillos, and had to get all stopgap nights
in the stomach.

Clarita and other school girls blindly believed that the mother had no Sorrows eyes, and all
optical powers residing in those two dreaded green glass, frame embedded in a stale and moldy,
and it was so cut two rounds to imitate green paper backing of the catechism and I stuck with
saliva in the eyes, which died of laughter.

Since they could not see drop with those patches, one day the mother watched; Petronilla,
who was a pickle, and after many coscorrones them, condemned them to not eat or play that day, what
hours passed the poor!

Again they were all in the yard, and it occurred to a skinny little bird get there the roof
and resting after crashing into the walls, the sad carnation. What uproar plucked! He was the
biggest event of the year. With scarves, robes, with what they found at hand, chased him catch
you, atáronle a thread on one leg, and Clara kept Cajoncillo well in a seam where it was. In secret
they took him to eat by nights, but the animal became more enflaquecía and sad every time. One
night, when as the prayer was about to begin with, Clara had opened the sewing, and pretending
to be arranged within something from him, was engaged in opening the mouth to the bird and put
him to force a few crumbs of bread he had in his pocket, when suddenly the animal took wing,
flew the room with the thread tied on the leg, and went to stand
where will you believe? in the same Dona head of Sorrows, which by
being desecrated in this manner, took such anger, that asthma he drowned
his voice and gesticulating was ten minutes in silence, as red as
a tomato.

Clara it was stiff with fear.

"... Cla Cla Cla ... ... rita - distraught mother cried .-- blind rage ... bad bad girl maid! What
deactivated ... ca ... cato is this? Tonight at ca ... ca ... garret. "

Clara was ordered that night to sleep in the garret, last sentence applied only very now and then
to the darkest and rare crimes. Mrs. Anguish continued in his cackling until he saw terrible performance
of the order, and even the time that used to be collected, Clara was taken to prison, which
was a dark attic, foul and frightening. The poor thing could not be itself for fear of being
alone in that slum, one thousand objects whose form could not see, lying on a miserable pallet and
exposed to air cast, which entered through a window. In wakeful, he felt the footsteps of mice living
in those climates, steps in his ears rang as if they were produced by the feet of an army of giants.
He shrugged, all wrapped in a blanket, hiding the feet, hands and head, but the rats ran above,
and jumping, came and went with a terrible din. It also increases the dread of a dispute that
girl on the roof neighbor cat got stuck between two noisy mournful
meowing and throwing out of tune.

The poor could not sleep, and the day he found balled up, drenched in cold sweat and trembling with
fear.

Among these extraordinary events and the daily task of study and sewing, always terrified by
the terrible fascination of the mother glasses Sorrows, Clara spent four years until he met the
eleven, Elijah came and took her to his house.

Realists do not know at first what to make of the girl: it occurred
to a nun, but driven by a sudden selfishness, decided to keep him.

He was alone: ??his house needed a woman. Who better to Clara? His intelligence was not well cultivated,
not knowing but read, write and do some accounts, but instead sewed well and understand the
all kinds of work.

Chacona's daughter grew Coletilla house, and was a woman. He grew up without games, without friendly
partners, without joy, without these healthy and lead happy useful expansions from childhood
to youth. Elijah was not bad, but neither is she was very affectionate.

On Sundays he would take to Florida or to the Virgen del Puerto, once took her to the theater, and
Clara thought it was really what they were representing. Sunday walks ceased when Elijah had
occupations and concerns which shut him out of his house: then she just listen to early morning
Mass at the nuns of Gongora, and accompanied him on this expedition, a Alcarrian maid named
Pascual, who Coletilla had taken into his service.

This perpetual imprisonment had soured and warped maybe another character so sweet and kind that
of Clara, who came to believe that life was something very natural, and should not aspire to
something else, so they lived peaceful, happy melancholy, and sometimes joyful. Yet, whole weeks
passed without a stranger gets into the house fanatic. It seemed that all the society wanted
to escape from the cage in which was enclosed their greatest enemy.

Only one exception was at the normal insulation. We have said that Mr. Elias was a friend and
servant of an ancient and illustrious house. After the ruin of the Porreno and Venegas, only
were three individuals, three venerable ladies kept friendly relations
with the realistic.

Very now and then went to visit him. They had a dry treatment, were intolerant rigid, proud.
Never talked to Clara but solemn words, which gave sadness and brought down the mood. They could
not do without the label, even in front of a poor girl and were so ceremonious, stiff, that
they came to take Clara dislike, because whenever went to the house left there a shadow of
sadness that lasted long into the soul of the orphan.

In recent years, Coletilla entered, as we said, at the height of his frenzy political, the anger
was normal, and it was something impossible in his fanatical obsessions irascible soul that could
have affection and finesse for the poor fellow that both needed. On the contrary, showed himself
very hard on her, he was not talking weeks whole, sometimes with acrimony and scolded her for no
reason: he called frivolous and frivolous.

One day, seeing that the hair had been unhappy with less ease than usual, and had dressed a
little reforming its natural elegance with the powerful instinct of fashion that women have the
world's most remote, scolded her, repeating many times this phrase that cost him tears to the
unhappy: "Clara, you've ruined." Sometimes gave the old by watching her, and forbade him out
on the balcony and open the door, ie the left or the tormented, depending
on the status of that spirit disturbing and cruel.

Clara became ill, was going slowly withered as the growing difficulty in carnation the schoolyard.
His melancholy increased, it became pale and exhausted, and came
to do fear serious health hazards.

Tagline could not remain indifferent to the disease of his protege, and brought a doctor who expressed
his opinion very briefly, saying: "If you do not send this girl to the field to die within
a month. "

The realist thought that the death of that girl would be a setback. He recalled that his sister
Ateca lived with his family, and formed his plan.

Wrote two letters and a few days after Clara entered the village with a heart overflowing joy.

Charitable
reaction occurred in their health, and spirit, so long afflicted by boredom and closure, was revived
with the full enjoyment of nature and treatment of gay people that
attended and loved.

Those days were a second life for the unfortunate martyr regenerated because materially, becoming
freshness, freshness and vigor, his eyes, accustomed to darkness with four walls, and traveled
a long horizon, his steps led to the distances: her voice was heard by friends jovial and frank,
by young singles, caring for old, his joy was understood and shared
by others, his innocent wish Satisfied knew friendship, family life,
trust, enjoyed a beautiful sky, of clean air, a sober and quiet well,
as happy and not monotonous days of quiet and peaceful nights.

But during the stay of Clara Ateca things happened that powerfully influenced the rest of his
life. Will refer to, because they derive most of this history; and so important and serious,
we leave to the next chapter, where you will see, if it is determined not to abandon.

CHAPTER VI

#'s Nephew Coletilla. #

Martha, the sister of Elias, was a widow with a son named Lazarus, who after studying Humanities
in Tudela, went to the University of Zaragoza. He was a boy as twenty-three to twenty-five,
with a pleasant presence, very precocious wit, imagination live, easy and fuzzy word, very impressionable
and eager, and rectum and noble heart.

New ideas, then profoundly moved the hearts of youth, had found in the young believer Lazarus
decided. He was one of those who sprouted in the tumult of a classroom of generous military philosophy
with passion in the ranks of political propagators, then as necessary.

It

happened that students Zaragoza struck up a quarrel with some club members policy, the matter
took proportions, the university authorities intervened and saw Lazarus forced to leave Zaragoza,
losing progress. This happened in the days, dismissed Irrigation the command of captain general
of Aragon, was in that city riots and demonstrations, that the government wanted to suppress.
Lazarus, who was about to finish the race, he met the gravity of his situation and disgust
that would have her mother and grandfather, whom he loved much. Wanted to complain, but it
was useless and had to retire to his people, sad, embarrassed and full of doubts and fears.

But when he entered the house, shaken by the anxiety and remorse, he saw in the company of
his mother to an unknown person from the moment he was a secret printing
of joy, imposing, without knowing why, comfort and hope.

He confessed what was happening, without diminishing the seriousness of the case, so don Fermín,
his paternal grandfather, was seriously and wanted to get angry, and his mother cried a little. But
the stranger, who seemed there to brighten up the house, cleared the wrath of the first and dried the
tears of the second while Lazarus, with his head down and moistened eyes, remained motionless in
front of their judges and defense counsel said nothing, but in truth it was not necessary, because
the young defended him very well without displaying great eloquence,
or use other resources that its clear and natural sense, the refiner
and generous feeling.

Lazarus was so upset that he imagined that this person was an apparition,
a being sent from heaven to rely on those hurried moments.

Expected her to disappear to complete its mission, and watched with amazement the noise that
causes the supernatural and unknown. He had no history of that young, or had suspected that existed
and was there. But the image is not faded, and, conversely, continued to see her adorned with
all the physical and moral charms may have the angels in this world.

Nothing more was said about it. Lazarus was forgiven, but never left their confusion. Explicáronle
Who was Clara and why he was there, but not why the student was able to dominate the respectful
and strong surprise that he had produced.

He shrugged and how amazed all day, and temblóle voice when he wanted to talk to her, and finally
fell silent for fear of saying a thousand blunders. The next day woke up with joy exalted, to
that which happened suddenly a sadness like no other. Her stunning stage took very different
as soon as I saw an insatiable appetite attacked verbosity could not contain, as soon made
extraordinary efforts to pronounce a word, without being able to
get it.

He was a fervent polaticómano, and Zaragoza had distinguished himself by his eloquent speeches in
clubs, they had given him much fame, in private conversation expressed also with much enthusiasm
and correction but this time all spoke less of policy. It seemed that no longer existed for him
or the French Revolution, and Emile, Rousseau, or the Charter of Talleyrand, and the Dictionary
of Voltaire. He had forgotten all this, and only thinking of more
expressive and accurate formula to tell Clare that had seen dreams
that night. Resorted to circumlocutions system, thought then to say
to dry and Ambassy, ??remembered that the allegories were invented
for that case and all media tested without reaching to any object.

It
was two or three days without finding a way to be explicit. When I
was alone, yes, then talked and talked to himself, and even seemed
to engage in dialogue with that beautiful mysterious spirit that was
always everywhere, accompanying him in his loneliness and insomnia;
spirit filled with light and female forms, flowing from the bosom
of the night to watch him still, quiet and serene</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>