<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02451</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>91127</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18844</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Y luego mandó Inca Yupanqui, que por cuanto
eran orejones, que luego les fuesen trasquilados sus cabellos; y ansí ellos mismos se trasquilaron
todos, viendo la voluntad del Inca y viendo que les hacia merced en aquello, y porquel traje
de Inca Yupanqui y de los del Cuzco era andar atusados. Y esto hecho, mandóles que se fuesen
todos á su pueblo, é que viviesen en paz; y mandó á sus capitanes que no consintiesen que á
aquestos de Xaquixaguana nadie les hiciese enojo ninguno ni les tomasen cosa, y si alguna cosa
de sus haciendas en aquel despojo les fuese tomada, luego se la hiciesen volver.

Y luego mandó que todos los prisioneros fuesen traidos delante de sí; á los cuales, como allí
fuesen, les preguntó ¿qué habia sido la causa, constándoles que era su poder grande, que con
él hiciesen otra vez batalla? Y siendo allí entre los prisioneros que allí fueron habidos los
cuatro capitanes de Uscovilca que habian ido á descubrir, como ya la historia os ha contado,
[dijeron, respondieron?] que la causa que les movió hacer la junta que hicieron en dar aquella
batalla, que fué haber visto que su ventura era grande en las jornadas que habian andado é
tierras que habian conquistado, dándole allí razon de las batallas y recuentros que en tal
jornada cada uno dellos habia habido, y que en ninguna de ellas nunca habian habido desgracia,
sino que siempre habian sido victoriosos; y como esto les hubiese acaescido, teniendo que siempre
su vitoria estaba en pié, que habian querido dar aquella batalla, pensando restaurar aquella
pérdida de su Señor y vengar su muerte. Á lo cual respondió Inca Yupanqui, que lo habian mirado
mal, é que si fueran gentes de entendimiento, que habian de presumir, que si habian habido
vitoria por la tierra que le decian que habian andado, que habian de considerar que la habian
habido en ventura de su Señor Uscovilca, que en la tal demanda los habia inviado, y que como
viesen y hobiesen sabido que su Señor era desbaratado y muerto, que habian de presumir que
ya les era acabada la ventura, y que él ni ellos no la tenian ya; y que para que ellos fuesen
castigados y otros mirasen é oyesen, que en aquel sitio serian castigados ellos y todos los
demás; é porque no fuesen otra vez [á] hacer gente, la cual á él le desasosegase y fuesen causa
ellos de que otros questaban inocentes de se hallar en semejantes casos por donde perdiesen
las vidas, como habia sido muy muchos que ellos [á] aquella junta habian hecho juntar, que
en aquel sitio serian castigados. Y ansí, los mandó llevar de delante de sí, y que en el sitio
do la batalla se diera, y para que della hobiese memoria, en presencia de todos los de su campo
mandasen hincar muchos palos de los cuales fuesen ahorcados, y despues de aderezados [ahorcados],
les fuesen cortadas las cabezas y puestas en lo alto de los palos; y que sus cuerpos fuesen
allí quemados y hechos polvos, y desde los cerros más altos fuesen aventados por el aire, para
que desto hobiesen memoria. Y ansí mismo mandó que ninguno fuese osado de enterrar ningun cuerpo
de los enemigos que ansí habian muerto en la batalla, porque fuesen comidos de zorros y aves
y los gusanos [huesos] de los tales fuesen allí vistos todo el tiempo. Todo lo cual fué hecho
generalmente en la manera que habeis oido.

Y esto acabado, mandó hacer Inca Yupanqui que se recogiese todo el despojo y joyas de oro y
plata que en el tal despojo se habia habido, todo lo cual fué fecho; y traido delante dél y
visto por él, mandó que ansí junto como estaba, lo llevasen á la ciudad del Cuzco, donde lo
pensaba repartir y dar á sus amigos. Todo lo cual fué ansí llevado á él y se partió juntamente
con ello para la ciudad del Cuzco, donde, llegado que fué, dió y repartió el tal despojo á
los suyos, dando á cada uno lo que le paresció que le bastaba y conforme á la calidad de su
persona. Y esto hecho y repartido, mandó que de su ropa é grandes ganados que en la ciudad
habia, [é] de otros bastimentos, mandó (así) que le fuese allí traido cierta cantidad, la que
á él le parescia que á todos bastase; todo lo cual ansí traido, mandó á sus capitanes que lo
repartiesen entre toda su gente; todo lo cual fué repartido.

Y hechas estas mercedes y otras muy muchas más que á sus capitanes él hizo, mandó que se fuesen
á sus tierras á descansar, y agradecióles el favor y ayuda que le habian dado, y ansí se fueron
todos, é Inca Yupanqui quedó en su ciudad con los suyos. É al tiempo que dél se despedian los
tales señores para se ir á sus tierras, le rogaron que los quisiese rescibir debajo de su amparo
y merced y por sus tales vasallos, é que querian tomase la borla del Estado y ser de Inca;
todo lo cual les agradesció Inca Yupanqui y respondióles, que al presente era vivo su padre
y Señor, y que no era justo que mientras su padre viviese, él tomase la borla del Estado; que
si al presente estaba allí, que era porquél era capitan de su padre; y que les rogaba dos cosas
que por él hiciesen, que era la una, que de allí, ansí como iban, fuesen á do su padre estaba
y le respetasen y hiciesen lo que él les mandase como tal Señor que era; y ellos dijeron que
ansí lo harian. É que la otra era, que le tuviesen á él por su tal amigo y hermano, y que cada
y cuando que por él les fuese inviado á les rogar, que lo hiciesen; y ellos dijeron que ellos
no tenian otro Señor sino era él, y como á sus tales vasallos, de ellos podia hacer aquello
que bien le estuviese; y él se lo agradeció.

Y ansí, se partieron[32], y Inca Yupanqui se quedó en la ciudad, y los tales señores caciques
se fueron de allí derechos do Viracocha Inca estaba; y despues de le haber hecho su debido
acatamiento, como Inca Yupanqui se lo habia mandado, le dijeron cómo Inca Yupanqui los inviaba
allí a que viesen en qué era servido que ellos le sirviesen; y como Viracocha Inca los viese
delante de sí y tan gran multitud de señores y de tanto poder, holgóse mucho de ello, porque
dellos tenia gran necesidad al presente, para que le favoresciesen con algun tanto de sus rentas,
para edificar aquel pueblo que allí queria hacer; é díjoles que fuesen muy bien venidos, é
levantóse de su asiento y abrazólos á todos y tornóse á sentar en su silla, y mandólos á todos
que ansí se sentasen; y mandó que sacasen muchos vasos de chicha, y que les diesen á beber;
y luego les hizo sacar mucha cantidad de coca, una yerba preciada que ellos siempre traen en
la boca, la cual yerba la historia adelante dirá. Y ansí repartida entre aquellos señores,
levantóse en pié Viracocha Inca, [y] considerando, que pues su hijo le inviaba aquellos señores
y ellos tanto le amaban y le querian por Señor, que era justo que él ansimismo en ello les
animase, les hizo cierta oracion, por la cual él de su parte les agradescia lo que por él y
por su hijo habian hecho, y que ya sabian y habian oido decir que él hasta allí habia sido
Señor del Cuzco, é que él se habia salido dél por causas que para ello le movieron; y que de
allí adelante Inca Yupanqui, su hijo, habia de ser Señor en la ciudad del Cuzco, y que á él
obedeciesen y respetasen, como su tal Señor, y que él desde allí se desestia de la insignia
y borla real y la ponia en la cabeza de su hijo Inca Yupanqui. Todo lo cual oido por los señores,
se levantaron en pié, y uno á uno fueron á él y le dieron grandes gracias, y mostraron que
rescibian en gran merced ellos el hecho del tal desistirse de la tal dignidad y darla á su
hijo Inca Yupanqui, que ellos tanto amaban é querian por Señor; y esto hecho, se tornaron á sentar.

Y Viracocha Inca les rogó, que por cuanto él queria allí en el peñol do estaba edificar un
pueblo, y que para ello tenia necesidad de su ayuda y gente, que les rogaba que tuviesen por
bien de darle aquella ayuda; á lo cual le respondieron aquellos señores, que ellos habian venido
allí para que él viese lo que ellos le pudiesen hacer algun servicio, como su Señor Inca Yupanqui
se lo habia mandado; é que aquello y otra cualquier cosa que él mandarles quisiese estaban
prestos de lo hacer; que les dijese el tiempo y mes en que queria comenzar [á] hacer su obra,
para que ellos inviasen allí sus principales é indios para que entendiesen en la hacer y hiciesen
los tales edificios; y que él, entretanto, diese la traza del tal pueblo, y hiciese hacer de
barro la figura de los tales edificios, que ellos le inviarian allí maestros que los supiesen
bien hacer, ansí de cantería, como de la manera quél los quisiese. Y Viracocha Inca su hijo
(así) se lo agradeció á todos ellos, y luego mandó sacar muchas cosas, como fueron hondas y
petacas de coca, y ciertas piezas de ropa fina y otras muchas cosas entre ellos muy preciadas;
todas las cuales fueron traidas delante dél, y siendo, él allí mesmo por sus manos las dió
y repartió á aquellos señores; y esto hecho, mandóles dar á beber, y que asímesmo les fuese
repartida cierta cantidad de coca. Y esto hecho, Viracocha Inca se levantó en pié y les agradeció
la voluntad y amor que á él y á su hijo le mostraban y tenian; y díjoles el mes y tiempo en
que habian de enviarle sus indios y gentes para que edificasen su pueblo; é ansí, los señores
se levantaron en pié, é quedando con él de se los inviar, como dicho tenian, le hicieron su
acatamiento, é ansí se despidieron dél; donde le dejaremos, y hablaremos de Inca Yupanqui.

Salidos que fueron aquellos señores caciques de donde Inca Yupanqui estaba, y fueron á do Viracocha
Inca estaba, como ya la historia os ha contado, é Inca Yupanqui quedase solo en su ciudad con
los suyos, despues de haber reposado dos dias, parescióle que tenian ya ociosidad, é habia
tomado por recreacion el ejercer de su persona; é ansí, salió un dia de mañana de la ciudad
del Cuzco, é llevando consigo los señores que allí consigo tenia, anduvo aquel dia todas las
tierras que en torno de la ciudad eran, y lo mismo hizo otro dia siguiente; [y] despues de
las haber bien visto y mirado, vió la mala reparticion é arte que el tiempo que allí su padre
estuvo ellas tenian. El tercero dia, tambien ansímismo anduvo mirando, juntamente con los señores,
el sitio donde la ciudad del Cuzco estaba fundada, todo lo cual, ó lo más dello, eran ciénagas
y maniantales, como ya la historia os lo ha contado, y las casas de los moradores della eran
pequeñas y pajizas é mal edificadas y sin proporcion de arte de pueblo que calles tuviese;
y bien ansí como es el dia de hoy junto á esta ciudad un pueblo que llaman Cayaucachi, era
en aquel tiempo las casas y pueblo que agora es la gran ciudad del Cuzco.

Y como Inca Yupanqui viese tan mal parado este pueblo del Cuzco, é ansímismo las tierras de
labranzas que en torno dél eran, parescióle, viendo que tenia tiempo y gran aparejo para de
nuevo reedificarla, y que primero que en el pueblo hiciese casa, ni el reparto de las tierras,
que seria bien hacer y edificar una casa al sol, en la cual casa pusiesen y fuese puesto un
bulto en el lugar do el sol reverenciasen y hiciesen sacrificios; porque, aunque ellos tienen
que haya uno que es el Hacedor, á quien ellos llaman Viracocha Pachayachachic, que dice Hacedor
del mundo, y ellos tienen que éste hizo el sol y todo lo que es criado en el cielo y tierra,
como ya habeis oido; caresciendo de letras, y siendo ciegos del entendimiento en el saber,
casí muchos varian en esto en todo y por todo, que unas veces tienen al sol por hacedor, y
otras veces dicen que el Viracocha; y por la mayor parte, en toda la tierra y en cada provincia
della, como el Demonio les traiga ofuscados, y en cada parte que se les demostraba les decia
mil mentiras y engaños, y ansí los traia engañados y ciegos, y en los tales lugares do ansí
le vian ponian piedras en su lugar, á quien ellos reverenciaban y adoraban. Y como les dijese
unas veces que era el sol, y á otros en otras partes decia que era la luna, y á otros que era
su Dios y Hacedor, é á otros que era su lumbre que los calentaba y alumbraba, é que ansí lo
verian en los volcanes de Arequipa[33]; en otras partes decia que era el Señor que habia dado
el ser al mundo, y que se llamaba Pachacama, que dice, Dador de ser al mundo; y ansí los traya,
como tengo dicho, engañados y ciegos.

Y volviendo á nuestra historia, este Señor Inca Yupanqui, como quisiese hacer casa y adoratorio
á quien él reverenciase y los demás de su pueblo, quiriendo lo hacer á reverencia y semejanza
del que habia visto ántes de su batalla, y considerando él quel que ansí viera, á quien él
llamaba Viracocha, que le vió con gran resplandor, segun ellos dicen, y en tanta manera que
le paresció que todo el dia era allí delante dél y su lumbre, lo cual viendo delante de sí,
dicen que hubo gran pavor, y que nunca le dijo quién fuese; considerando él en sí, cuando esta
casa queria edificar, que aquel que viera, segun la lumbre que en él habia visto, que debia
de ser el sol, y que como llegase á él y la primera palabra que le dijese "Hijo, no tengas
temor," y ansí los suyos, como la historia os ha contado, le llamaron despues Hijo del Sol;
y tiniendo él ansí lo que ya habeis oido, propuso de hacer esta Casa del Sol.

Y como la propusiese, llamó los suyos y los señores de la ciudad del Cuzco que allí consigo
tenia, y díjoles lo que ansí tenia pensado y que queria edificar esta casa; y ellos le dijeron
que diese la órden y traza del edificio della, porque tal casa como aquella, ellos, los naturales
y propios de la ciudad del Cuzco la debian edificar é hacer; é Inca Yupanqui les dijo que la
casa debia ser edificada luego, porque él ansí lo tenia pensado. Y visto por él el sitio do
á él mejor le paresció que la casa debia de ser edificada, mandó que allí fuese traido un cordel,
y siéndole traido, levantáronse del lugar do estaban él y los suyos, y siendo ya en el sitio
do habia de ser la casa edificada, él mismo por sus manos con el cordel midió y trazó la Casa
del Sol; y habiéndola trazado, partió de allí con los suyos y fué á un pueblo que dicen Salu[34],
que es casi cinco leguas de esta ciudad, ques do se sacan las canteras, y midió las piedras
para el edificio desta casa, y ansí medidas, de los pueblos comarcanos pusieron las piedras
que les fué señaladas y las que fueron bastantes para el edificio desta casa; y juntamente
con esto, trujeron todo lo demás que para el edificio desta era necesario; y siendo ya allí,
pusieron por obra el edificio della, bien ansí como Inca Yupanqui la habia trazado y imaginado.
Andó él siempre y los demás señores encima de la obra, mirando cómo la edificaban, y ansí él
como los demás, trabajaban en el tal edificio; la cual obra, como allí tuviese juntos los materiales
y menesteres della, que en breve tiempo fué acabada.

Y como ya fuese acabada esta otra Casa del Sol que habeis oido, mandó Inca Yupanqui que luego
fuesen juntas quinientas mujeres doncellas, y como allí fuesen traidas, ofreciólas al sol,
para que allí siempre estas tales doncellas sirviesen al sol y estuviesen allí dentro, bien
ansí como las monjas son encerradas; y luego, allí, llamando á un señor anciano y natural de
la ciudad del Cuzco que á él le pareció que era hombre honesto y de buen exemplo y fama, que
estuviese y regiese allí en la Casa del Sol, y que fuese mayordomo del sol y de la tal casa.
Y luego mandó que allí fuesen entregados doscientos mozos de servicio del sol; y ansímismo
en aquella hora señaló ciertas tierras para el sol, en que sembrasen estos doscientos yanaconas.

Y esto hecho, mandó Inca Yupanqui á los señores del Cuzco que, para de allí á diez dias, tuviesen
aparejado mucho proveimiento de maíz, ovejas y corderos, y ansímismo mucha ropa fina, y cierta
suma de niños y niñas, que ellos llaman Capacocha, todo lo cual era para hacer sacrificio al
sol. Y siendo los diez dias cumplidos y ésto ya todo junto, Inca Yupanqui mandó hacer un gran
fuego, en el cual fuego mandó, despues de haber hecho degollar las ovejas y corderos, que fuesen
echados en él, y las demás ropas y maíz, ofreciéndolo todo al sol; y los niños y niñas que
ansí habian juntado, estando bien vestidos y aderezados, mandólos enterrar vivos en aquella
casa, que en especial era hecha para donde estuviese el bulto del sol; y con la sangre que
de los corderos y ovejas habian sacado, mandó que fuesen hechas ciertas rayas en las paredes
desta casa; todo lo cual hacia y los sus tres amigos é otros; todo lo cual sinificaba una manera
de biendecir y consagrar esta casa; en el cual sacrificio andaba Inca Yupanqui y sus compañeros
descalzos y mostrando gran reverencia á esta casa y al sol. É ansímismo con la misma gente
[sangre?] el Inca Yupanqui hizo ciertas rayas en la cara [á] aquel señor que era señalado por
mayordomo desta casa, y lo mismo hizo á aquellos señores, sus tres amigos, y á las mamaconas
monjas que para el servicio del sol eran allí. Y luego mandó que todos los de la ciudad, ansí
hombres como mujeres, viniesen á hacer sus sacrificios allí á la casa del sol; los cuales sacrificios
que ansí la gente comun hizo, fué quemar cierto maíz y coca en aquel fuego que ansí era hecho,
entrando cada uno destos uno á uno y descalzos, los ojos bajos; y al salir que ansí salian,
despues de haber hecho su sacrificio, á cada uno destos por sí mandó Inca Yupanqui que aquel
mayordomo del sol hiciese la raya misma que habeis oido, con la sangre de las ovejas, en los
rostros destos que ansí salian, á los cuales les era mandado, que desde aquella hora hasta
que el bulto del sol fuese hecho de oro, todos estuviesen en ayuno, y que no comiesen carne
ni pescado ni áun guisallo, ni llegasen á mujer, ni comiesen verdura ninguna, y que solamente
comiesen maíz crudo y bebiesen chicha, sopena que el que el ayuno quebrantase, fuese sacrificado
al sol y quemado en el mismo fuego. El cual fuego mandó Inca Yupanqui que siempre estuviese
ardiendo de noche y de dia; la leña del cual fuego mandó Inca Yupanqui que fuese labrada y
quemada mientras al ídolo se hiciesen en el fuego sacrificios, los cuales mandó que durante
este tiempo hiciesen las mamaconas del sol; las cuales ansímismo estaban en grande ayuno y
lo mismo el Inca Yupanqui y los demás señores.

Y esto hecho y proveido, mandó Inca Yupanqui que viniesen allí los plateros que en la ciudad
habia, y los mejores oficiales, y dándoles todo aparejo allí en las Casas del Sol, les mandó
que hiciese un niño de oro macizo y vaciadizo, que fuese el tamaño del niño del altor y proporcion
de un niño de un año y desnudo; porque dicen que aquel que le hablara cuando él se puso en
oracion estando en el sueño, que viniera á él en aquella figura de un niño muy resplandeciente,
y que él vino á él despues, estando despierto, la noche ántes que diese la batalla á Uscovilca,
como ya os he contado, que fué tanto el resplandor que vió que dél resultaba, que no le dejó
ver qué figura tenia; y ansí mandó hacer este ídolo del tamaño y figura de un niño de edad
de un año; el cual bulto se tardó de hacer un mes, en el cual mes tuvieron grandes sacrificios
y ayunos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01121</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>32483</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17431</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> And then sent Inca Yupanqui, that because were
dried apricots, then they were shorn her hair and so they themselves were shorn all, seeing the will
of the Inca and seeing them to worship in it, and brought Becausethe Inca Yupanqui and Cuzco
was twirling ride. And this was done, commanded them that they were all his people, and to live
in peace, and he ordered his captains not consenting to aquesta of Xaquixaguana they should
be made no anger or being taken, any thing, and if anything of their estates in that they were
taken spoil, then the hiciesen return.

And then ordered that all prisoners were brought before him, to whom, as there were, asked what
had been the cause, provided that, was his great power, which hiciesen battle it again? And still
there among the prisoners there were incurred the Uscovilca four captains who went to discover,
as history has told you, [Said, responded] that the cause that moved them to the board that they
did in giving battle, which was to have seen his fortune was great in the days that had gone
é land they had conquered, giving reason for the battles there and in such recuentros day
each of them had been, and that none of them had never been unfortunately but had always been
victorious, and how it had acaescido them, having to always his victory was on foot, who had wanted
to give this battle, thinking that restore loss of their Lord, and avenge his death. In reply
Inca Yupanqui, who had looked wrong, and that if they were men of understanding, which were to
presume that if they had been victory for the land that they said they had gone, they had
to consider that had been in their Lord Uscovilca chance that in such demand had winters, and
as hobiesen they saw and learned that his Lord was defeated and dead, who had presumably I was
finished and the chance, and that he did not already have them, and that they were é mirasen
punished and others hear it, that this place would be punished them and all other: and again
because they were not [to] make people, which to him were uneasy and cause them that other
orchestras will be found innocent in such cases where they lost lives, as had been very many of
them [to] the junta had done together, which at that site would be punished. And thus, he sent
them to bring before him, and that the site would do the battle, and for hobiese della memory,
in the presence of all its field should command drive many clubs which were hanged, and after
seasoned [hanged] their heads were cut and placed on top of the sticks, and their bodies were burned
there and made powders, and from the highest hills were dispersed through the air, desto hobiesen
that memory. And thus it was ordered that none dared to bury any body of the enemy that longs
had died in battle, because they were eaten by foxes and birds and worms [bones] of such views
were there all the time. All this was done usually in the way that you heard.

And it finished, he ordered Inca Yupanqui was collected all the spoil and gold jewelry silver
in the plunder that had been there, all of which was dated, and brought
in front of and seen by him, ordered ANSI time as it was, it brought
into the city of Cuzco, where the divide and give thought to their
friends.

All of which was eagerly taken to him and snapped together thus for the city of Cuzco, where,
where it was, just gave and shared the spoils to their own, giving each one his paresció that
was enough and according to the quality of person. And that made and distributed, ordered his
clothes and big wins in the city had, [and] of other provisions, ordered (so) that brought him
there was a certain amount, which parescia to him that all were enough, all of which brought
ANSI, he commanded his captains that divided among all his people, all of which was distributed.

And
these grants and others made very many more than he did to his captains, who were sent to
their land to rest, and thanked him for the favor and help they had given, and so he went all,
and Inca Yupanqui was in town with his family. É while Se dismissed their these gentlemen for
going to their land, they begged him that wanted to receive me under
his protection and such mercy and its vassals, and that he wanted
to take the fringe of the state and be of Inca all of which are agradesció
Inca Yupanqui and answered them that this was his father alive and
Lord, and it was not fair that while his father lived, he would take
the fringe of the State, that if this was there, that was Becausethe
was captain of his father, and begged them both that he did, it was
the one, from there, I long as they were, they were to do his father
was and respected him and do what they command them as such he was
Lord, and they said would do so.

É the other was, that they had to him by such a friend and brother, and that each and when that
he will be shipped to beg them, which they did, and they said they had no other Lord but he was,
and as such to their vassals, they could do that was good to him and he thanked him.

And thus, the left [32], and Inca Yupanqui stayed in the city, and such gentlemen caciques
went from there do Viracocha Inca was right, and after you have done your due compliance, as
Inca Yupanqui had commanded him, told him how the winters Inca Yupanqui there for them to see
what was served that they serve him, and saw them as Inca Viracocha front of him and such a multitude
of lords and so much power, much of it rejoiced because Dell had this great need for favoresciesen
him with some much of his income to build that people there wanted to do: and told them that
they were very welcome, é arose from his seat and embraced them all and it became to sit in his
chair, and commanded them to all that longs to sit down, and commanded them to put many glasses
of chicha, and gave them to drink; and then they brought out a large amount of coca, an herb
prized that they always bring in mouth, which tell the story along
grass.

And thus divided between those gentlemen, Viracocha rose standing, [and] considering that as
your child masters those invia and they both loved him and wanted him as Lord, it was just
that he ansimismo it will encouraged, we did some prayer, by which he in turn agradescia them
what he and his son had done, and already knew and had heard that he had been up there Lord
of Cuzco, é he had gotten off to do so for reasons that moved him, and that Inca Yupanqui then
on, his son, was to be Lord in the city of Cuzco, and that to him obey and respect, such as their
Lord, and from there he Desesti logo and real fringe and put it on the head of his son Inca
Yupanqui. All of which is heard by the lords, stood up, and one by one went to him and gave him
great thanks, and showed that rescibian large grant them the fact of such waiver of such dignity
and give your son Inca Yupanqui, which they both loved é wanted by the Lord, and this fact,
it turned to sit.

Viracocha Inca and begged them, that because he wanted there in the Peñol do was build a people,
and that this had need of your help and people, he begged them who had them well to give that
assistance, to which the gentlemen replied that they had come there so that he could see what
they could do him some service, as Lord Inca Yupanqui had commanded him: and that this and any
other thing he wanted was to send ready for what to do, to tell them the time and wanted to
start the month in which [to] do its work for them to invest their principal and Indians there
that they might understand the how and hiciesen of such buildings, and he, meanwhile, give the trace
of such people, and make hiciese clay figure of such buildings, they will inviarian teachers
who knew there doing good ANSI stonework as chelate the way I wanted. And his son Viracocha
(So) was grateful to them all, and then sent out many things, as
they were deep and suitcases of cocaine, and certain pieces of fine
clothes and other things between them very valuable; all of which
were brought in front of him, and being, he mesmo there got their
hands and distributed to those men and this fact, he commanded them
to drink, and that they be provided himself distributed a certain
amount of coca.

And this fact, Viracocha Inca stood up and thanked them the will and love to him and his son
and had showed him, and said the month and time they had to send his Indians and people to build
their people, and so he, Mr. rose on foot, and was staying with him in winter, and that they had,
they made their compliance, and so he will leave of him, where we will leave, and talk of Inca Yupanqui.

These
gentlemen were coming out of where Inca Yupanqui chiefs was, and went to do Viracocha Inca
was, as history has told you, and Inca Yupanqui left alone in the city their own, after having
rested two days, they had already parescióle idleness, E had recreation taken by the exercise of
his person, and so he came out one day in the city tomorrow Cuzco, é carrying the gentlemen
who had him there, he walked all that day land around the city were, and so did another the next
day, [and] after the well have seen and watched, saw the poor distribution é art that while
there his father was they had. The third day, also went looking ansímismo, together with the
gentlemen, the site where the city of Cuzco was founded, all of which, or as dello were swamps
and maniantales, as history has told you, and the houses of the inhabitants were della é thatched
small and poorly built and no proportion of street art that people had; ANSI well as in the
present day near this city a village called Cayaucachi was At that time the houses and people that
now is the great city of Cuzco.

And Inca Yupanqui saw too badly this town of Cuzco, land ansímismo é Around the crops that were
parescióle, seeing that he had time and a great rig for the new rebuilt,
and that first house in the village hiciese nor the distribution of
land, it would be okay and to build a house in the sun, in whose house
verifications and was wearing a package in place and revere the sun
do hiciesen sacrifices because, although they have there is one who
is the Maker, whom they called Viracocha Pachayachachic, says maker
the world, and they have it made the sun and all that is raised in
heaven and earth, as we have heard; caresciendo of letters of understanding
and being blind in the know, almost many variants on this at all and
everything, which sometimes have the sun by maker, and sometimes say
that the Viracocha, and for the most part, the whole earth and every
province della, as the Devil brings you befuddled, and each party
told them they showed thousand lies and deceptions, and so they brought
them deceived and blind, and in such places do ANSI Vian will they
placed stones in place, whom they revered and worshiped.

And as I say sometimes it was the sun, and to others elsewhere said it was the moon, and to others
that it was their God and Maker, E to others it was their fire that the heat and light, that
they crave é would see the volcanoes of Arequipa [33] in other parts said it was the Lord
who had given Being the world, and was called Pachacamac, he says, Giver of being the world,
and so he's brought, as I have said, deceived and blind.

And back to our history, the Lord Inca Yupanqui, and wanted to make home and shrine whom he revered
and others of his people, Quiros what to do reverence and likeness which had been before his battle,
and considering he craves quel see, whom he called Viracocha, who saw him brightly, they say,
and in such a way that paresció that he was there all day and before the fire, which saw before
him say there was great fear, and never told him who it was, considering it as such, when
this House wanted to build, than that which saw, according to the fire that he had seen, which
was to to be the sun, and how to get there and the first word he
said "Son, do not be fear, "and so they own, as history has told you,
he was called after Son of the Sun tiniendo he craves and what we
have heard, proposed to the House of the Sun

And as proposed, called
his men and the lords of the city of Cuzco to get there had, and said
they look forward had thought and wanted to build this house, and
they said to give the order and trace the building of it, because
such a house like that, they, the natives and own the city of Cuzco
to the debian build é, é Inca Yupanqui said that house was to be built
then, because he had thought they crave.

And seen him do site paresció it to him better than the house was to be built, he ordered that
there be brought a string, and being so brought, rose up the place do were he and his men,
and now the site do was to be the house built, he himself by his hands with the line measured
and drew the House the Sun, and having drawn, left there with his family and went to a people
who say Salu [34] which is nearly five miles from this city parks do is take the quarries, and
measured the stones for the building of this house, and so he measures in the neighboring villages
began stones them was identified and those were enough for the building of this house, and together
with this, they brought everything else to the building Desta was necessary, and being already
there, put to work building della either ANSI as the Inca Yupanqui had traced and imagined.
Ando he provided the other lords over the work, watching the builders, and longing as others working
in this building, which work together as there had material and necessities of it, which was
finished in short time.

And as I was finished the other house of the sun that you have heard, then sent Inca Yupanqui
together five hundred women were virgins, and as there were brought, offered him the sun, so
that there are always such to worship the sun and maidens were in there, well ANSI as the nuns
are enclosed, and then, there he called an old man and natural Cuzco that he thought he was honest
and of good examples and fame, which and regiese was there at the
Casa del Sol, and to be steward of the sun and that house.

And then ordered that there be handed over hundred porters of the sun, and ansímismo at that time
said some land for the sun, who planted these two hundred yanaconas.

And this fact, Inca Yupanqui sent to the lords of Cuzco, and from there to ten days, they had
much proveimiento rigged corn, sheep and lambs, and ansímismo much fine clothes, and some amount
of children, they call Capacocha, all of which was to make sacrifice sun. And since the ten days
of age and this and all together, Inca Yupanqui ordered a large fire, which sent fire, after
having made slaughter sheep and lambs, which were thrown into it, and other clothing and corn,
offering all the sun, and the children who ANSI had assembled, being well dressed and seasoned,
mandolin buried alive in that house, which was especially made for
where was the bulk of the sun, and with blood lambs and sheep had
taken, he ordered them to be made certain lines on the walls this
house, all of which made it and his three friends and others, all
of which sinificaba way of biendecir and consecrate this house, in
which sacrifice was walking Inca Yupanqui and his companions Barefoot
and showing great reverence to this house and the sun.

É ansímismo with the same people [Blood?] The Inca Yupanqui had some scratches on the face
[to] this man who was identified by steward of this house, and so did those gentlemen, his three
friends, and to the virgins nuns to serve the sun were there. And then ordered that all city, ANSI
men and women, should come and make their sacrifices there to the house of the sun, which sacrifices
craves the common people did was burn some corn and coca craves that fire was made, entering
every one of these one by one and barefoot, looking down, and leaving it craves Salian, after making
his sacrifice, to every one of these on their Inca Yupanqui ordered that Butler hiciese sun
stripe same as you have heard, with the blood of sheep, in faces of these who craves Salian,
whom I was commanded, that from that time until the bulk of the sun were made of gold, they were
all fasting, and not to eat meat or fish or even his cooking, and reaching women, nor eat any
vegetables, and only eat raw corn and drink chicha, Sopena that would break the fast, were
sacrificed the sun and burned in the fire itself. The Inca Yupanqui ordered that fire was
always burning night and day, the wood fire which sent Inca Yupanqui was wrought and while the
idol was burned in the fire hiciesen sacrifices, which he commanded during this time would go all
the virgins of the sun, which ansímismo were big and fast the same as the Inca Yupanqui and
other masters.

And this fact and provided, Inca Yupanqui ordered them to come there silversmiths in the city
had, and the best officers, and tackle them all there in the Casas del Sol, I sent that would
make a child-cast solid gold, it was the child's size and proportion of altor a one year old
and naked, for they say that he who would speak when he stood in prayer while in the dream,
to come to him at that figure of a very bright child, and he came to him later, while awake,
the night before the battle to give Uscovilca, as I told you that was so much glare that you
saw the result, which left him no see what shape he was, and so they sent to the idol of the
size and shape of a child aged a year which it took to package a
month, which month had the great sacrifices and fasting.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>