<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01622</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>360085</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24452</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Y acaso la cólera fue lo que me salvó. Ella me prestó energías
para reaccionar y adoptar un partido extremo. Aquel mismo día escribí dos o tres cartas diciendo
que me ausentaba de París. Me mudé de casa, fui a ocultarme en un barrio alejado, llamé en
mi auxilio lo que me quedaba de razón, de inteligencia y de amor al bien, y volví a empezar
una nueva prueba cuya duración no sabía, pero que en cualquier caso debía ser la última.

XVI

Este cambio se operó de la noche a la mañana y fue radical. No era ya el momento de vacilar
y enfriarse. Tenía horror a las medias tintas. Me gustaba la lucha. La energía superabundaba
en mí. Rechazada en una parte, mi voluntad tenía necesidad de revolverse en otro sentido, de
buscar un nuevo obstáculo que vencer, en pocas horas, por decir así, y lanzarse sobre él. El
tiempo se me hacía eterno. Aparte toda cuestión de tiempo me sentía, si no envejecido, a lo
menos muy maduro. No era yo un adolescente a quien el menor pesar clava, todo dolorido, sobre
las blandas pendientes de la juventud. Era un hombre orgulloso, impaciente, herido, aguijoneado
por los deseos y las pesadumbres, que caía, de repente, en lo mejor de su vida--como un soldado
al mediodía de la jornada decisiva,--con el corazón henchido de agravios, el alma amargada
por la impotencia, el cerebro en plena explosión de proyectos.

No volví a poner los pies en el mundo, a lo menos en aquella parte de la sociedad en donde
arriesgaba hacerme notar y encontrar recuerdos, que me hubieran tentado. No me encerré tampoco
demasiado estrecho porque hubiera muerto ahogado; pero me circunscribí en un círculo de hombres
activos, estudiosos, especiales, absortos, enemigos de quimeras, que se dedicaban a la ciencia,
a la erudición o al arte como aquel ingenuo Florentín que creó la perspectiva y por las noches
despertaba a su mujer para decirle: «¡Qué dulce son es la perspectiva!» Desconfiaba de los
extravíos de la imaginación y la puse en orden. En cuanto a mis nervios, que yo había cuidado
tan voluptuosamente hasta entonces, los castigaba de la manera más ruda por el desprecio a
todo lo que es enfermizo y el propósito firme de no estimar más que lo que es robusto y sano.

La claridad de la luna a orillas del Sena, el sol dulce, los ensueños asomado a la ventana,
los paseos bajo los árboles, el malestar o el bienestar causados por un rayo de sol o por una
gota de lluvia, las asperezas del genio que me ocasionaba el aire un poco vivo y los buenos
pensamientos que me inspiraba la ausencia de viento, todas esas blanduras de corazón, esa esclavitud
del espíritu, esas sensaciones exorbitantes fueron examinadas y del examen resultó decretar
que eran indignas de un hombre, y rompí todos aquellos hielos que me envolvían en un tejido
de influencias y de fragilidades.

Hacía una vida muy activa. Leía enormemente. No me malgastaba, me economizaba. El sentimiento
repulsivo de un sacrificio se combinaba con el atractivo de un deber que tenía que llenar con
respecto a mí mismo. Obtenía de esto cierta satisfacción sombría que no era alegría, menos
aún plenitud, pero que mucho se asemejaba a lo que debe ser el altanero placer de un voto monacal
bien cumplido. No juzgaba que hubiera nada pueril en una reforma que tenía causa tan grave
y que podía tener un resultado muy serio. Hice de mis lecturas lo mismo que había hecho de
otras mil cosas: considerándolas como alimento importantísimo de mi espíritu, las expurgaba.
Ya no sentía la necesidad de aclaraciones en asuntos del corazón. No merecía la pena de reconocerme
en libros conmovedores cuando huía de mí mismo. Tenía que encontrarme mejor o peor; si mejor,
la elección era superflua y, si peor, era un ejemplo que no debía ser buscado. Me formaba,
por decir así, una especie de colección saludable entre lo que el talento humano ha dejado
de más fortificante, más puro, desde el punto de vista moral, más ejemplar en materia de raciocinio.
En fin, le había prometido a Magdalena poner a prueba mis fuerzas y quería mantener mi promesa
aunque sólo fuera para demostrarle que había en mí potencialidad sin empleo y para que pudiese
medir bien la duración y la energía de una ambición que no era en el fondo más que amor convertido.

Al cabo de algunos meses de este régimen inflexible, llegué a un estado de salud artificial
y de solidez de espíritu que me parecía apropiada para emprender mucho. Comencé por saldar
mis cuentas con el pasado. Ya sabe usted que había tenido la manía de los versos. Sea por complacencia
involuntaria de los días amables y añorados, sea por avaricia, no quise que aquella parte viviente
de mi juventud fuera enteramente destruida. Me impuse la tarea de revolver aquel viejo repertorio
de cosas infantiles y de sensaciones apenas despertadas. Fue una especie de confesión general
indulgente, pero firme, sin ningún peligro para una conciencia que se juzga. De aquellos innumerables
pecados de otra edad compuse dos tomos. Les puse un título que determinaba el carácter un poco
primaveral de la obra. Los encabecé con un prefacio ingenioso que debía, por lo menos, ponerlos
a cubierto del ridículo y los publiqué sin firma. Aparecieron y desaparecieron. No esperaba
más de ellos. Nada hice para salvarlos del total olvido, convencido de que toda cosa que es
abandonada merece serlo y que no hay un solo rayo de verdadero sol perdido en todo el universo.

Hecho este barrido de conciencia, me ocupé de tareas menos frívolas. Se hacía entonces mucha
política por doquier y particularmente en el medio observador en que yo actuaba. Había en el
ambiente de aquella época una multitud de ideas en estado de nebulosa, problemas en estado
de esperanzas, generosidades en movimiento que debían condensarse más tarde y formar lo que
ahora se llama el cielo tempestuoso de la política moderna.

Mi imaginación casi desarbolada, pero no del todo apagada, encontraba en aquel objetivo algo
que la seducía. La posición de hombre de Estado era--en la época de que le hablo a usted,--el
coronamiento necesario, hasta cierto punto, el advenimiento al título de hombre útil para todo
aquel que tenía gran capacidad intelectual, talento o sencillamente ingenio. Me enamoré de
la idea de llegar a ser útil después de haber sido dañino tanto tiempo. Y la ambición de ser
ilustre también me invadió poco a poco--pero, ¡sabe Dios por qué!--Comencé por hacer una especie
de estadía en la antecámara misma de los asuntos públicos, es decir en medio de un pequeño
parlamento compuesto de jóvenes voluntades ambiciosas, de muy jóvenes abnegaciones dispuestas
a ofrecerse, en el cual se reproducían en diminutivo una parte de las polémicas que agotaban
entonces a toda Europa. Alcancé éxitos, puedo decirlo sin orgullo hoy que nuestro parlamento
mismo está olvidado. Me parecía que mi camino estaba trazado. En él hallaba medio de desplegar
la actividad devoradora que me consumía. No sé qué insuperable esperanza me quedaba de volver
a encontrar a Magdalena. No me había dicho ¿adiós o hasta la vista? Entendía que me vería mejor
transformado, con un brillo más vivo para ennoblecer mi posición. Todo se mezclaba así entre
los estímulos que me aguijoneaban. El encarnizado recuerdo de Magdalena zumbaba en el fondo
de mis ambiciones y momentos había en que no me era dado distinguir en mis prematuros ensueños
de poderío, lo que emanaba del filántropo y lo que procedía del enamorado.

Todas aquellas ideas y sentimientos las resumí en un libro que apareció bajo un nombre supuesto.
Pocos meses después publiqué otro. Los dos tuvieron más resonancia que la que yo esperaba.
En poco tiempo estuve a punto de ver trocada en celebridad la oscuridad en que estaba. Saboreaba
con delicia el placer vanidoso, furtivo y absolutamente íntimo, de oírme alabado en la personalidad
de mi pseudónimo. El día que el éxito fue indiscutible le llevé mis dos libros a Agustín. Me
abrazó de todo corazón, me declaró que tenía un gran talento, se asombró de que se hubiera
revelado de golpe y tan pronto y me predijo como cosa infalible, una posición moral, capaz
de enloquecerme. Me propuse que Magdalena gozase los primeros augurios de mi celebridad y le
mandé mis libros al señor De Nièvres. Le rogaba que no me hiciera traición; le daba explicaciones
plausibles de mi retirada: era excusable desde el momento que estaba demostrado que había tenido
un objeto.

La contestación del señor De Nièvres no contenía más que frases de agradecimiento y elogios
calcados sobre los que corrían en el público. Magdalena no añadía ni una palabra a las de su
marido.

La leve turbación de mi espíritu que siguió al dichoso comienzo de mi vida literaria se desvaneció
muy de prisa. A la efervescencia excitada por una producción pronta, arrastradora, casi irreflexiva,
sucedió una gran calma, es decir, un momento de serenidad y de examen singularmente lúcido.
Había en mí un antiguo yo mismo de quien ya hace largo tiempo que no le hablo a usted, que
callaba pero que sobrevivía. Aprovechó aquel momento de reposo para reaparecer usando un severo
lenguaje. Con los avasallamientos de mi corazón me había emancipado por completo. Él volvió
a ocupar su alta posición en cuanto se trató de asuntos más discutibles y se dio a deliberar
fríamente los intereses más positivos de mi espíritu. En otros términos: analicé con calma
lo que de legítimo había en el fondo de mi éxito, y preciso era que en conclusión estimara
si en ello existía razón para animarme. Hice el balance--muy definitivo--de mi saber, es decir,
de los recursos adquiridos y de mis dones, o lo que es igual, de mis fuerzas vivas, comparé
lo ficticio con lo nativo, pesé lo que pertenecía a todo el mundo y lo poco que había mío propio.
El resultado de esta crítica imparcial, hecha tan metódicamente como una liquidación de negocios,
fue que yo era un hombre distinguido y mediocre.

Había sufrido decepciones más crueles: aquella otra no me causó la más leve amargura. Por otra
parte, apenas si era tal decepción. Para muchos habría sido más que satisfactoria aquella situación.
Yo la consideraba de muy diferente modo. Ese pequeño monstruo moderno que Oliverio llamaba
«lo vulgar», que le causaba tanto horror y que le condujo ya sabe usted a dónde, lo conocía
yo tan bien como él bajo otro nombre. Habitaba tan bien en la región de las ideas como en el
mundo inferior de los hechos. Había sido el genio malhechor de todos los tiempos y era una
llaga del nuestro. Había en derredor mío una perversión de ideas con respecto a la cual nunca
me había dejado engañar. No me revolvía contra las adulaciones que, después de todo, no podían
ya hacerme cambiar de opinión en ningún caso: las acogía como inocente expresión del juicio
público en una época en que la abundancia de lo mediocre había tornado indulgente al gusto
embotando el sentido acerado de las cosas superiores. La opinión me parecía perfectamente equitativa
en cuanto a mí, aunque hiciera yo a la vez que mi proceso también el suyo.

Recuerdo que un día ensayé una prueba más convincente que todas las demás. Tomé de mi biblioteca
cierto número de libros contemporáneos y procediendo poco más o menos como la posteridad procederá
antes de acabarse el siglo, pedí a cada uno cuenta de sus títulos a la duración y sobre todo
del derecho que tenían para llamarse útiles. Advertí que llenaban muy poco la primera condición
que hace vivir una obra, eran muy poco necesarios. Muchos habían servido de pasajera diversión
a sus contemporáneos sin más resultado que agradar y caer en el olvido. Algunos tenían un falso
aspecto de necesidad que engañaba, vistos de cerca, pero que lo futuro se encargará de definir.
Un número muy pequeño--me quedé asustado--poseían ese raro, absoluto e indudable carácter,
en el cual se reconoce toda una creación divina y humana, de poder ser imitada pero no suplida
y de hacer falta a las necesidades de las gentes si se la supone ausente. Aquella especie de
juicio póstumo, ejercido por el más indigno sobre tantos espíritus elegidos, me demostró que
no sería yo nunca del número de los absueltos de culpa y pena. Aquel que tomaba en su barca
los hombres meritorios me habría dejado ciertamente en la otra orilla del río: y en ella me quedé.

Otra vez más atrajo la atención del público mi nombre o por lo menos el de mi imaginario personaje,
y fue la última. Me pregunté entonces qué era lo que me quedaba que hacer y me costó algún
tiempo resolverlo. Había para eso una dificultad de primer orden. Mi existencia desligada de
muchas vinculaciones--como usted ha visto--y desengañada de muchos errores ya no pendía más
que de un hilo, el cual aunque horriblemente estirado y más resistente que nunca, seguía sujetándome
y no imaginaba que nada pudiera quebrarlo.

Ya apenas oía a nadie hablar de Magdalena aparte Oliverio a quien veía muy poco, y Agustín
a quien ella había atraído a su casa, sobre todo después que yo desaparecí. Sabía vagamente
cuál era el empleo de su vida exterior: que había viajado y después vivido algún tiempo en
Nièvres; que luego había recobrado dos o tres veces sus costumbres en París, para abandonarlas
otra vez casi sin motivo y como bajo el imperio de un malestar que se traducía en una perpetua
inestabilidad de carácter y como una necesidad de cambiar de lugares. Algunas veces la había
visto, pero tan furtivamente y a través de tan gran turbación, que en cada una de aquellas
ocasiones me había parecido que era víctima de un ensueño penoso. De aquellas fugaces apariciones
me quedaba la impresión de una imagen extraña, de un rostro ajado como si los negros colores
de mi alma se hubieran desteñido sobre aquella radiante fisonomía.

Por aquella época tuve una gran emoción. Había una exposición de pintura moderna. Aunque muy
ignorante de una bella arte en punto a la cual tenía el instinto sin la más leve cultura, y
de la que hablaba tanto menos cuanto más la respetaba, iba algunas veces a perseguir observaciones
de otros que me enseñaban a conocer bien mi época y hacer comparaciones que no me alegraban
nada. Un día vi un grupito de personas--que debían ser conocedoras--discutiendo delante de
un cuadro. Era un retrato de medio cuerpo concebido en un estilo antiguo, con fondo oscuro:
el vestido indeciso y sin ningún accesorio, dos manos espléndidas, la cabellera medio perdida,
la cabeza presentada de frente, firme de contornos, grabada sobre el lienzo con la precisión
de un esmalte y modelada yo no sé de qué manera sobria, amplia y sin embargo velada, que daba
a la fisonomía incertidumbres extraordinarias y hacía palpitar un alma emocionada en el vigoroso
dibujo de las facciones tan firme y resuelto como el grabado de una medalla. Me quedé anonadado
delante de aquella efigie espantosa de realidad y de tristeza. La firma era la de un ilustre
pintor. Recorrí el catálogo y encontré las iniciales de la señora De Nièvres. No había yo menester
de aquel testimonio. Magdalena estaba allí, delante de mí, fija en mí la mirada; pero, ¡con
qué ojos, en qué actitud, con qué palidez y qué misteriosa expresión de espera y de amarga pena!

En poco estuvo que no lanzara un grito y no sé cómo logré contenerme lo bastante para no darle
a la gente el espectáculo de una locura. Me coloqué en primera fila apartando a todos aquellos
curiosos que nada tenían que hacer entre aquel retrato y yo. Para tener el derecho de examinarlo
desde más cerca y más largo tiempo imité el gesto, las actitudes, la manera de mirar y hasta
las pequeñas exclamaciones de aprobación de los aficionados prácticos en la materia de arte
pictórico. Fingí apasionarme por la obra del pintor cuando en realidad no apreciaba ni adoraba
otra cosa que el modelo. Volví al siguiente día y los sucesivos, me deslizaba muy temprano
a lo largo de las galerías desiertas, veía el retrato desde lejos como a través de una nube
tomando vida a cada paso que yo avanzaba hacia él. Llegaba, todo artificio apreciable desaparecía:
era Magdalena más y más triste, más y más fija en no sé qué terrible ansiedad henchida de ensueños.
Le hablaba, le refería todas las cosas fuera de razón que me torturaban el alma desde hacía
cerca de dos años, le pedía gracia para ella y para mí. Le suplicaba que me recibiera, que
me permitiese volver a ella. Le contaba mi vida entera con el más lamentable y el más legítimo
de los orgullos. Había momentos en que el fugitivo modelado de las mejillas, el brillo de los
ojos, el indefinible dibujo de la boca daban a la muda efigie movilidades que me causaban miedo.
Hubiérase dicho que me escuchaba, me comprendía, y que el implacable y sabio buril que la había
aprisionado en un rasgo tan rígido, era lo único que la impedía conmoverse y contestarme.

Algunas veces me vino a las mientes la idea de que Magdalena había previsto lo que sucedía,
es decir, que la reconocería yo y me volvería loco de dolor y de alegría en aquel fantástico
coloquio de un hombre vivo con una pintura. Y según veía yo en ese hecho malicia o compasión,
aquella idea me exasperaba la cólera o me hacía verter lágrimas de agradecimiento.

Lo que le refiero a usted duró casi dos meses; pasados que fueron, al otro día el que le di
un adiós verdaderamente fúnebre, los salones fueron clausurados y desaparecido el retrato quedé
más solo que nunca.

Pasado algún tiempo, recibí una visita de Oliverio. Estaba serio, notaba en él cierto embarazo,
algo así como si el peso de un caso de conciencia le pesara en el alma.

Apenas le vi me puse a temblar.

--Yo no sé qué sucede en Nièvres--me dijo;--pero todo parece que va mal.

--¿Magdalena?--le pregunté espantado.

--Julia está enferma, bastante enferma para causar inquietudes. Magdalena misma no está buena.
Me gustaría ir, pero la situación no sería sostenible. Mi tío me escribe cartas muy desoladas.

--¿Pero Magdalena...?--volví a preguntar temeroso de que aun sucediera otra desgracia que él
me ocultaba.

--Te repito que Magdalena está en un muy triste estado de salud. No ha empeorado de algún tiempo
a esta parte, pero continúa mal.

--Oliverio--exclamé,--vayas tú o no a Nièvres yo estaré allí mañana. Nadie me ha despedido
de la casa de Magdalena, me alejé de ella voluntariamente. Le había dicho a Magdalena que me
escribiera el día que tuviera necesidad de mí; si ella tiene motivos para callar, yo los tengo
para correr a su lado.

--Harás absolutamente lo que quieras. En semejante caso obraría como tú, dejando a salvo el
arrepentimiento si el remedio era peor que la enfermedad.

--Adiós.

--Adiós.

XVII

El día siguiente estaba yo en Nièvres. Llegué por la tarde un poco antes de cerrar la noche.
Era el mes de noviembre. Me apeé a cierta distancia de la verja, en pleno bosque. Atravesé
el patio de entrada sin ser notado. Al extremo de las habitaciones de servicio a la derecha
brillaba luz en las cocinas. Dos ventanas se destacaban luminosas sobre la fachada del castillo.
Me fui en derechura al vestíbulo cuya puerta estaba sólo entornada; alguien lo cruzaba cuando
yo entré, estaba oscuro. «¿La señora De Nièvres?» dije creyendo que hablaba con alguna doncella
de la servidumbre. La persona a quien me había dirigido se volvió bruscamente, vino hacia mí
y lanzó un grito: era Magdalena.

Se quedó petrificada por la sorpresa y yo le tomé la mano sin hallar fuerzas para articular
una sola palabra. La escasa, claridad que venía de fuera le prestaba la blancura de una estatua:
sus dedos completamente inertes y helados se desprendían insensiblemente de mi mano como si
fueran las de una muerta. La vi tambalearse, pero al movimiento que hice para sostenerla se
desprendió por un impulso de inconcebible terror, abrió desmesuradamente los ojos extraviados
y exclamó: «¡Domingo!...» como si despertara de un mal sueño que hubiese durado aquellos dos
años; luego dio algunos pasos hacia la escalera arrastrándome en pos de ella sin conciencia
de lo que hacía. Subimos juntos, el uno al lado del otro, siempre juntas nuestras manos. Al
llegar a la antesala del primer piso tuvo como una llamarada de presencia de espíritu.

--Entre usted aquí--me dijo,--voy a avisar a mi padre.

La vi que llamaba a su padre y encaminarse al cuarto de Julia.

Las primeras palabras del señor D'Orsel fueron éstas:

--Mi querido hijo, tengo mucha pena.

Aquella frase decía más que todas las recriminaciones y me penetró en el corazón como una estocada.

--He sabido que Julia estaba enferma--le dije sin hacer ningún esfuerzo para disfrazar el temblor
de mi voz que desfallecía.--Supe también que la señora De Nièvres estaba delicada y vine a
verles a ustedes. Hace tanto tiempo...

--Es verdad--repuso el señor D'Orsel,--hace mucho tiempo. La vida se pasa: cada cual tiene
sus deberes y sus preocupaciones...

Llamó, mandó encender las luces, me examinó rápidamente como si quisiera comprobar en mí un
cambio análogo a las alteraciones que los dos años transcurridos habían producido en sus hijas.

--También usted ha envejecido--continuó con cierta especie de benevolencia y de interés muy
afectuoso.--Ha trabajado usted mucho, tenemos la prueba...

Después me habló de Julia, de las vivas inquietudes que habían tenido, pero que, por fortuna,
se habían disipado desde algunos días. Julia entraba en la convalecencia; ya todo era cuestión
de cuidado, de atenciones y de algunos días de reposo. De nuevo pasó de un asunto a otro.

--He ahí que es usted todo un hombre ya célebre--continuó.--Hemos puesto atención en sus cosas
con el más sincero interés.

Se paseaba de arriba abajo, hablándome así, sin hilación. Tenía los cabellos totalmente blancos,
su alto cuerpo un poco encorvado ofrecía un aspecto singularmente noble, de vejez prematura
o de abatimiento.

Magdalena vino a interrumpirnos al cabo de cinco minutos. Iba vestida de oscuro y se parecía
mucho, con la animación de la vida además, al retrato que tanto me había impresionado. Me levanté,
le salí al paso, balbuceé dos o tres frases incoherentes que no tenían ningún sentido; ya no
sabía ni cómo explicar mi visita, ni cómo llenar de golpe el enorme vacío de dos años que ponía
entre nosotros como un abismo de secretos, de reticencias y de oscuridades. Me repuse, sin
embargo, al verla más dueña de sí misma y le hablé lo más sosegadamente que pude de la alarma
que me había dado Oliverio. Cuando pronuncié ese nombre me interrumpió.

--¿Vendrá?--dijo.

--No lo creo--repliqué.--Por lo menos en unos cuantos días.

Hizo un gesto de desanimación absoluta y los tres caímos en el más penoso silencio.

Pregunté en dónde estaba el señor De Nièvres, como si fuera posible que Oliverio no me hubiera
informado de su viaje y me mostré sorprendido al saber que estaba ausente.

--¡Oh, estamos en un gran abandono!--dijo Magdalena.--Todos estamos enfermos o poco menos.
Hay en el ambiente malas influencias, la estación es malsana y no tiene nada de alegre--añadió
dirigiendo la mirada a las altas ventanas de antiguas vidrieras de colores en las cuales se
reflejaba todavía un resto de luz del día casi del todo extinguido.

Para huir de una conversación imposible por embarazosa hablé de la deplorable situación de
algunas personas, que amenazaba aumentar en el próximo invierno, por enfermedades en unos casos
y por miseria en otros; de un niño que se moría en el pueblo y que Julia había asistido y cuidado
hasta el día en que, gravemente enferma ella misma, hubo de encomendar a otros su papel, impotente
contra la muerte, de hermana de la caridad. Parecía complacerse con aquellos relatos de lamentables
desgracias y enumerar, con no sé yo qué sombría avidez, todas las calamidades vecinas que formaban
en torno de su existencia un concurso de causas de tristeza. Luego, al igual que había hecho
el señor D'Orsel, me habló de mí, tan pronto con cierta reserva como con un abandono admirablemente
calculado para facilitar la posición de cada uno.

Mi propósito era hacerle una visita y luego ganar la posada del pueblo en la cual había comprometido
una habitación; pero Magdalena dispuso otra cosa: advertí que había dado las órdenes oportunas
para que me alojasen en el piso segundo del castillo, en un cuarto que ya había ocupado yo
la primera vez que pasé una temporada en Nièvres.

Aquella misma noche, antes de separarnos, estando yo presente, le escribió a su marido.

--Le aviso al señor de Nièvres que está usted aquí--me dijo.

Y me di cuenta de lo que semejante precaución, tomada en mi presencia, implicaba de escrúpulos
y resoluciones leales.

No había visto a Julia. Estaba débil y agitada. La noticia de mi llegada, a pesar de la prudencia
con que se le comunicó, le había causado una sacudida muy viva. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04163</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>173619</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21586</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> And perhaps the anger was what saved me. She gave me energy to react
and adopt an extreme party. That same day I wrote two or three letters saying as I left Paris. I
moved home, went to hide in a remote neighborhood, call my rescue what was left of reason,
intelligence and love of good, and I began again a new probationary period did not know, but
in any case should be the last.

XVI

This change came in the overnight and it was radical. It was not the time to falter and cool.
Had a horror of half-measures. I liked the fight. Superabundant energy me. Rejected in part,
my will was in need of turning in another sense, find a new obstacle to overcome in a few hours,
so to speak, and jump on it. The time seemed eternal to me. Apart from any question of time I
felt, if not old, to least very mature. I was not a teenager who stabs the child despite all painful,
the soft slopes of youth. It was a proud man, impatient, wounded, pricked by the desires and sorrows,
that dropped suddenly in the prime of his life - as a soldier at noon on the final day - with
hearts full of grievances, bitter soul by impotence, brain exploding
project.

I did not set foot in the world, at least in that part of society where risked notice and find me
memories that I had been tempted. I also locked too narrow because it would have drowned, but I
was confined in a circle of men activities, studies, special, lost, enemies of chimeras, which
were devoted to science, to scholarship or art as that which created Florentín naive perspective
and at night woke his wife to say, "How sweet is the perspective!" distrusted wanderings of the
imagination and put in order. As for my nerves, I had carefully so voluptuously until then,
were punished in the most rude for contempt all that is ill and the
firm intention of not more than the estimate that is robust and healthy.

The

moonlight on the Seine, the sun sweet dreams at the window, walks under the trees, discomfort
or welfare caused by a sunbeam or a raindrop, the roughness of the genius that caused me a little
air and good living thoughts that inspired the absence of wind, all that softness of heart,
that slavery the spirit, those feelings were considered exorbitant and the examination was decreed they
were unworthy of a man, and broke all those ice wrapped around me in a tissue influences and
weaknesses.

It was a very active life. He read widely. I wasted, I economized. The feeling sacrifice repellent
was combined with the attraction of a duty that had to be filled with about myself. This got
some satisfaction that it was dark joy, unless still full, but that much resembled what should
be the haughty pleasure of a monastic vow well done. There was nothing childish deemed that a reform
that was so serious because and could have a serious result. I did my reading of what he had
made thousand other things, considering them important food of my spirit, expunged. He no
longer felt the need for clarification on matters of the heart. It was not worth to recognize
gripping book when he fled from myself. I had to find better or worse, if better the election was unnecessary
and, worse, was an example that should be sought. I was, so to speak, a kind of healthy library
between human talent that has left more bracing, more pure, from the moral point of view,
more exemplary in terms of reasoning. Finally, Magdalena had promised to test my strength
and wanted to keep my promise if only to show potential in me without a job and that could While measuring
the duration and energy of an ambition that was ultimately become more than love.

After several months of this inflexible system, I came to a artificial
condition and strength of spirit that seemed appropriate to undertake
a lot.

I started to pay off my accounts with the past. You know who had the mania of the verses. Whether
for pleasure involuntary nice day and longed for, either by greed, I did not want that part
of living of my youth was entirely destroyed. I set myself the task of stirring that old code of childish
things and feelings just awakened. It was a sort of general confession Forgiving, but firm, without
any danger to a consciousness that is judged. Of those countless sins of another age I wrote two
volumes. I put a title that determined the character a little spring of the work. I led with
a preface by the ingenious to be, at least, put under cover of ridicule and posting without a signature.
Appeared and disappeared. I did not expect more of them. I did nothing to save them from total
oblivion, convinced that everything is deserves to be abandoned and that there is a real ray of
sunshine lost in the universe.

Made this scan of conscience, I cared for less frivolous tasks.

It was so much policy everywhere and particularly in the middle observer that I acted. Had in
environment at that time a multitude of ideas in a state of nebulous state problems of hope,
generosity to be moving later condense and form what now called the stormy sky of modern politics.

My
imagination almost treeless, but not entirely off, something was in that goal the seduced.
The position of a statesman was - at the time that I speak to you,
- the crowning necessary, to some extent, the advent of man the title
useful for all one who had great intellectual ability, talent or simply
genius.

I fell in love the idea of ??becoming useful after being harmful so long. And the ambition to
be I also illustrate invaded little by little - but, God knows what - I started to do a kind
stay in the same lobby of public affairs, is among a small parliament composed of young ambitious
minds of very young abnegations willing to volunteer, which were reproduced in a diminutive
part of the controversial depleting then all of Europe. Achieve success, I can say without pride
that our parliament today it is forgotten. It seemed that my path was laid out. It was deployed
through consuming activity that consumed me. I do not know what I was hoping unbeatable again
to find Madeleine. "I had said goodbye or au revoir? I would better understand transformed, with
a live brightness to ennoble my position. Everything was mixed well between stimuli that stung
me. The bitter memory of Magdalena hummed in the background of my ambitions and had moments
where I was given no distinction in my dreams premature of power, what emanated from the philanthropist
and what came from love.

All those ideas and feelings summarized in a book that appeared under an assumed name. A few
months later published another. The two had more resonance than I expected. Before long I almost
changed into a celebrity see the darkness in which it was. Savored with delight the pleasure vain,
sneaky and quite intimate, hear me praise in personality my pseudonym.

The day's success was undeniable I took my two books to Augustine. I wholeheartedly embraced, told
me that he had great talent, was amazed that he had suddenly revealed as soon as I predicted
and infallible thing, a moral position capable go mad. Magdalena I decided that he enjoyed the first
omens of my celebrity and you I sent my books to Mr de Nièvre. He begged that I did not treason gave
explanations I retired plausible: it was excusable since the time it was shown that had an object.

The
reply of Mr. de Nièvre contained only words of thanks and praise modeled on those who ran
the public. Magdalena did not add a word to those of the husband.

The slight confusion in my spirit that followed the happy beginning of my literary life vanished very
quickly. The excitement aroused by early production, drawn, almost unthinkingly, came a great calm,
that is, a moment of serenity and singularly lucid examination.

There was an old me who I very long time ago and do not talk to you, silent but surviving.
He took that moment of rest and reappear using a severe language. With the encroachments of
my heart I had completely emancipated.

He returned to take his high position as it was more controversial issues and was deliberating coldly
more positive interest in my spirit. In other words, calmly analyzed what a legitimate lay at the bottom
of my success, and precise conclusion was that considers if it was reason to cheer. I did the
balance - very definitive - of my knowledge, ie acquired resources and my gifts, or what is
the same, my driving forces, I compared the fictitious with native weighed that belonged to everyone
and how little I had my own. The result of this criticism fair, made as methodically as a liquidation
business was that I was a distinguished man and mediocre.

He had suffered cruel disappointments: this one did not cause me the slightest bitterness.
On the other hand, if it was just such disappointment. For many would have been more than satisfactory
that situation. I felt very differently. That little monster called modern Oliverio "Vulgar",
which caused much horror and led him you know where, I knew I as well as it under another name. Lived
so well in the region of ideas as in the lower world of facts. He had been the genius villain of
all time and was a wound of ours.

There were around me a perversion of ideas on which he never had me fooled. I revolted against
the flattery, after all, could not and change my mind in any case: welcomed the trial as an innocent
expression public at a time when the abundance of mediocrity had become indulgent taste blunting
the steely sense of higher things. The opinion seemed perfectly fair As for me, although I
do while my process is also yours.

I remember one day I tried a test more convincing than all the others. I took my library number
of contemporary books and proceeding more or less as posterity shall before the end of the century,
has asked each of their titles to the duration and especially the right they had to be called
useful. I noticed that very little filling the first condition a work that gives life, were
hardly necessary. Many had served as a temporary diversion his contemporaries no other result than to
please and be forgotten. Some had a false aspect of need deceived
watched closely, but it will define future.

A very small number - I was afraid - had that rare, absolute and unquestionable character, which
is recognized in all divine and human creation, it can be imitated but not supplied and be required
to the needs of the people if it is absent. That kind of posthumous trial exercised by the most
unworthy of so many spirits elected, I showed that I would not ever the number of those acquitted
of guilt and sorrow. One who took in his boat meritorious men certainly would have left me on
the other side of the river, and she stayed.

Once again attracted the attention of the public my name or at least my imaginary character
and was the last. I wondered what it was that I had to do and I took some time to resolve. Had
for that one major difficulty. Detached from my life many links - as you have seen - and disillusioned
many errors and no more hanging that the balance, which, although horribly stretched and stronger
than ever, still holding on and never imagined that nothing could break it.

And hardly heard anyone talk about other than Magdalena Oliver, whom he saw very little, and Augustine
whom she had brought home, especially after I disappeared. I knew vaguely what was the use
of outdoor life: he had traveled and lived some time after Nièvre, which had recovered after
two or three times their customs in Paris, only to abandon again almost without reason, and
as under the rule of a malaise that resulted in a perpetual instability of character and as a need to
switch places.

Sometimes there seen, but so secretly and through so much trouble, that in each of those Sometimes
I had thought he was the victim of a painful dream. In those fleeting appearances I had the
impression of a strange image of a face wrinkled as if the black color My soul had faded on
that radiant face.

At that time I had a great emotion. There was an exhibition of modern painting. Although very
ignorant of a fine art in the matter of which had not the slightest instinct culture and I
was talking about much less the more respected, would sometimes chase comments others who taught
me to know well my time and make comparisons that cheered me nothing. One day I saw a small
group of people - who should be familiar - before discussing a picture.

It was a half-length portrait in an antique style designed with a dark background: undecided
dress without accessories, two splendid hands, her hair half lost, head made from the front,
strong outlines, engraved on the canvas with precision a patterned enamel and I do not know what a
sober, comprehensive and yet evening, which gave to face extraordinary uncertainties was excited
to beat a soul in the vigorous drawing of the factions as firm and resolute as the engraving
of a medal. I was stunned effigy in front of that awful reality and sadness. The signature
was that of an illustrious painter. I scanned the list and found the initials of the lady of Nièvre.
I had no need of that testimony. Magdalene was there before me, eyes fixed on me, but with what
eyes, in what position, how pale and what mysterious expression of expectation and bitter grief!

In
just was not to launch a cry and I do not know how I managed to restrain myself for not giving enough
people the spectacle of madness. I placed in the front row away to all those curious that had nothing
to do between the portrait and me. To have the right to examine a closer and more long imitated
the gesture, attitude, and how to look up small exclamations of approval from fans practical in the
field of art painting. I feigned a passion for the painter's work when in fact they liked or
loved otherwise the model.

I returned the next day and onwards, I slipped early along the deserted galleries, saw the picture
from afar and through a cloud life taking every step that I moved toward him. Arrived, all significant
device disappeared: Magdalena was sadder and sadder, more and more fixed in who knows what terrible
anxiety bursting with dreams. He spoke, I meant all the things beyond reason I had been tortured
soul about two years, asked for her grace and me. I prayed that I received, which allow me
to return to it. I had my whole life with the most unfortunate and most legitimate The pride and
joy. There was a time when the fugitive modeling of the cheeks, the brightness of the eyes,
the indefinable mouth drawing moves gave the effigy mobilities caused me fear. It seemed as
I listened, I understood, and that the relentless and chisel he had learned imprisoned in a trait
so hard, was all that prevented moved and reply.

Sometimes I came to mind the idea that Magdalene had foreseen what happened, ie that would
recognize me and I would go mad with grief and joy at the fantastic conversation of a man living
with a painting. And as I saw in that fact malice or compassion, idea that anger or exasperate
me made me shed tears of gratitude.

What you mean you took almost two months past that were, on the other
day I gave truly a farewell funeral halls were closed and I was missing
portrait more alone than ever.

After some time, I received a visit from Oliver. He was serious, it felt somewhat embarrassed,
almost as if the weight of a case of conscience was weighing on his soul.

Just saw him I began to tremble.

- I do not know what happens in Nièvre - I said, - but everything seems to go wrong.

- Magdalena? - I asked aghast.

- Julia is sick, sick enough to cause concern.

Magdalene herself is not good. I would go, but the situation is not sustainable. My uncle would
write letters very desolate.

- Magdalena ...?-- But I asked again fearing that another disaster
happen even he I hid.

- I tell you, Magdalena is a very sad state
of health.

There has deteriorated some time this part, but still wrong.

- Oliver - I cried - you go or not I'll be there tomorrow Nièvre. Nobody has been fired Magdalena's
house, I left voluntarily. Magdalena had told me wrote the day he had need of me, if she has
reason to be quiet, I have them to run to his side.

- You will do absolutely anything you want. In such a case would act like you, deferring to
the regret if the remedy was worse than the disease.

- Bye.

- Bye.

XVII

The next day I was in Nièvre. Afternoon I arrived just before nightfall. It was the month of November.
I got out some distance from the gate in the forest. Crossed the entrance courtyard without being
noticed. At the end of the service rooms to the right shining light in the kitchen. Two bright
windows are highlighted on the front of the castle.

I went straight to the hall whose door was just ajar when someone crossed I went, it was dark.
"" Mrs. Nièvre? "I believe I talked to a girl of the easement. The person to whom I had addressed
turned suddenly came to me and screamed: it was Magdalena.

Froze in surprise and I took her hand without finding the strength to articulate a word. The poor,
came out clearly that he lent the whiteness of the statue: completely inert fingers and ice
cream fell off my hand imperceptibly as if were those of a dead woman. I saw it wobble, but
the movement I made to hold it off by an impulse of inconceivable terror, lost eyes widened
and said, "Sunday !...» as if waking from a bad dream that had lasted
those two years, then took a few steps toward the stairs, dragging
after her without conscience what he was doing.

We went up together, next to each other, always together our hands.

Al reach the threshold of the first floor was like a flash of presence
of mind.

- Come in here - I said - I will tell my father.

I saw that she called her father and move to the Fourth of July.

The first words of Mr. D'Orsel were these:

- My dear son, I have a lot of grief.

Those words spoke louder than all the recriminations and penetrated my heart like a sword.

- I heard that Julia was sick - I told him no effort to disguise the trembling My voice grew
faint .-- I also learned that Mrs. Nièvre was delicate and came to
see you.

So long ago ...

- It's true - said Mr. D'Orsel - long ago.

Life happens: everyone has their duties and their concerns ...

Called, put on the lights, I looked quickly as if to check on me a change analogous to the changes
that had occurred two years after their daughters.

- Also you have aged - continued with a sort of benevolence and very interesting .-- loving you
worked a lot, we have proof ...

Then I spoke to Julia, the serious concerns that they had, but fortunately had vanished from a few
days. Julia entered the convalescent and everything was a matter of care, attention and a
few days of rest. Again went from one subject to another.

- Behold, you're quite a man now famous - .-- We have continued to
focus on their stuff with sincere interest.

He paced up and down, talking and without hilación. His hair was completely white, their high body
slightly hunched offered a singularly noble appearance of premature
aging or depression.

Magdalena came to interrupt us after five minutes. She was dressed in dark and resembled long,
with the animation of life as well, the portrait that had impressed
me so much.

I got up, met him, mumbled incoherently two or three that had no meaning, no longer even know
how to explain my visit, and how suddenly fill the huge gap of two years put among us as a bottomless
pit of secrets, and dark misgivings. I recovered without But seeing her more in control of herself
and spoke calmly as I could alarm Oliver had given me. When I gave that name stopped me.

- Will he come? - Said.

- I do not think - I said .-- At least in a few days.

He made a gesture of absolute discouragement and the three fell into the most painful silence.

I asked where he was the lord of Nièvre, as if it were possible I would not Oliverio informed
of his trip and I was surprised to learn he was absent.

- Oh, this
is a great abandon! - Magdalena said .-- We are all sick or a little
less.

There are bad influences on the environment, the resort is unhealthy
and there is nothing cheerful - added looked up at the tall windows
of old stained glass windows in which yet at a daylight remaining
almost completely extinguished.

To escape embarrassing conversation impossible spoke of the deplorable
situation Some people, who threatened increase in the next winter,
in some cases diseases and misery in others, of a child who died in
the village and that Julia had attended and care until the day when,
gravely ill herself, had to entrust to other role, powerless against
death, a sister of charity.

Seemed pleased with those unfortunate stories misfortunes and to enumerate, I know not what sombre
greed, all the calamities that were nearby around his existence a
cause of sadness contest. Then, as he had done Mr. D'Orsel, spoke
of me with some reservation as soon as admirably abandonment calculated
to facilitate the position of each.

My purpose was to make a visit
and then win the village inn in which he had committed a room, but
decided otherwise Magdalena: I noticed that he had given the necessary
orders for me to stay on the second floor of the castle, in a room
that I had already occupied the first time that I spent some time
in Nièvre.

That night, before we part, in my presence, she wrote
to her husband.

- I notice Mr Nièvre you're here - I said.

And I
realized that such a precaution, taken in my presence, involved in
unscrupulous and fair decisions.

Julia had not seen. He was weak
and agitated. The news of my arrival, although caution that was told,
had caused a shock very much alive</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>