<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04101</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>4196</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>808</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> No nos fijemos ahora en estos cabos.

Aislada la fábula de los amores de FAUSTO y Margarita, su disposición y desenvolvimiento merecen
más elogio que censura. Fausto, con todo el ardor y el ímpetu de su renovada juventud se apasiona
de la sencilla y linda muchacha, y quiere lograrla pronto, sin que le arredren obstáculos ni
reflexione en malas consecuencias. Mefistófeles, fuera de las joyas que lleva de presente a
Margarita, apenas emplea más medios para ayudar a la seducción, que los que podría emplear
un lacayo listo de nuestras antiguas comedias de capa y espada. Así es y así debe ser. Si en
el amor que Fausto inspira interviniese algún artificio o prestigio diabólico, la belleza de
este amor, casi toda su poesía, y más aún su ulterior virtud, redentora y santificante, habrían
de desvanecerse. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07684</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>227034</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>716</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Do not we look now at these ends.

Isolated the fable of the loves of Faust and Marguerite, disposition and development deserve more
praise than censure. Faust, with all the ardor and impetuosity of his youth renewed passion
the simple and beautiful girl, and want to achieve soon, without hindrance or daunt him reflect
on bad consequences. Mephistopheles, out of the jewelry takes this to Margarita, just uses
more resources to aid seduction, which could be used a list of our old servant swashbuckling
comedy. That is how it should be. If Fausto love that inspires some artifice or prestige intervene
diabolical beauty this love, most of his poetry, and even further under, redeeming and sanctifying
would vanish</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>