<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10900</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>149900</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24539</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Después de esto, cuanto hayan trabajado nuestros Misioneros en criar y mantener estas tiernas
plantas, no se puede explicar mejor que refiriendo sinceramente, sin añadir nada de mío, algún
hecho particular y parte de carta verídica, como lo haré, donde quiera que halle coyuntura,
trasladando fielmente los originales con que esta historia quedará más fidedigna y el gusto
de los lectores más satisfecho.

Dice, pues, el hermano Juan de Avila, compañero que fué del P. Visitador de esta provincia,
Antonio Garriga y del P. Provincial Luis de la Roca, cuando como adelante diré, visitó aquellas
Doctrinas sujeto de mucho juicio y capacidad en una carta que desde allí escribió:

«Así como para fundar las Misiones del Paraguay padecieron increíbles trabajos aquellos primeros
varones apostólicos, sacando á los indios de las selvas y entablando en ellos vida cristiana
y política hasta ponerlos en el estado en que hoy día se mantienen, divididos en treinta Reducciones,
así también no han sido menores los trabajos y sudores de estos primeros que han fundado la
cristiandad de los Chiquitos. No es fácil de decir lo que al descubierto les han dado que sufrir
los enemigos y ocultamente los amigos, la carestía de todo lo necesario para la vida humana,
los profundos pantanos, inaccesibles montañas, bosques impenetrables, fieras, climas destemplados,
sed, hambre, extrema desnudez, total abandono de todas las cosas y jurada guerra de todo el
infierno. Pudiera descender á casos particulares que he visto y oído si no fueran bien sabidos
y me son materia contínua de rubor y confusión. No traer sobre sí sino un vestidillo de tela
baladí, hecho pedazos, y no pocas veces vestirse de pieles de animales; no traer otros zapatos
que un pedazo de cuero crudo atado con otro cordel de cuero por las plantas de los piés, y
en la cabeza, para reparo del sol ardientísimo que allí hace, uno como sombrero, pero también
de cuero, la cama sin ningún alivio, la vianda ordinaria, un puñado de maíz, y éste tan escaso,
que apenas era bastante para mantenerles las fuerzas, vivir gran tiempo sin el consuelo siquiera
de ver á alguno de sus compañeros, y estando afligidos de largas y penosas enfermedades, no
tener á dónde volver los ojos.»

Así el dicho hermano; y yo en prueba de todo lo que él dice, quiero apuntar algunos casos en
particular.

Díjome, no ha mucho, un Padre qué fué Superior de aquellas Reducciones, que por muchos meses
no tuvo otra cosa de qué sustentarse, sino raíces de yerbas, y faltándole éstas también, acosado
de la hambre, se vió precisado á andar en busca de frutas silvestres.

Cuando el P. Gregorio Cabral fué en nombre del P. Simón de León, Provincial de esta provincia,
á visitar aquellas Misiones, le cogió el invierno (que allí no se mide por el frío, que no
hace, sino por el romper de las lluvias) le cogió debajo de una enramada, donde con siete Misioneros
pasó largo tiempo sin otro sustento que una fruta silvestre á que llaman Motaquí, con alguna
cosa de leche; y el día de Pascua, por gran regalo, les dieron los neófitos una mazorca ó espiga
de maíz. Pero no tuvo otro tanto el mismo día el P. Zea, que presentándole por gran regalo
ciertos panecillos bien pequeños, no pudo probar bocado de ellos por ser amargos como la hiel.

No me ha parecido supérfluo contar estas menudencias, para que quien en los hombres apostólicos
no mira otra cosa que conversiones de infieles, adviertan también cuánto les cuestan y considere
si tiene necesidad de una generosísima caridad quien se emplea en buscar la gloria de Dios
y en mirar por la eterna salvación de las almas. Y ciertamente el no acobardarse con los peligros,
el no volver las espaldas á tantos trabajos, el no retirarse y no dejar una vida en que á cada
paso se encuentra con la muerte, pereciendo aquí de hambre, perdiéndose allí por los bosques,
ahora andando entre flechas y macanas, ahora enmedio de pueblos furiosos, es virtud difícil
de hallarse, y con todo eso esta virtud es necesaria siempre á quien emprende en países remotos
y entre gente bárbara el oficio de la predicación Apostólica.

Pero lo que me llena de estupor y maravilla, es que en medio de tantos trabajos é incomodidades,
no hayan hasta ahora muerto entre tantos operarios más que tres ó cuatro, siendo así que hay
quien ha trabajado veinticinco y treinta años; pero es singular providencia del Altísimo, que
quien ningún caso ha hecho de su vida por su servicio, se conserve más sano y mejor que si
hubiera vivido en las comodidades de un colegio, como yo ví, con grande estupor, en el P. Juan
Bautista de Zea, que en edad de sesenta y cinco años parecía joven de poco más de treinta en
el aliento y valor.

Verdad es que hoy día se han aligerado en gran parte tantos trabajos, porque introducida en
aquella gente, con la santa fe la vida civil y política, lo pasan un poco mejor los Misioneros,
y la piedad de muchos caballeros les provee de algunas cosas con que ocurrir á las necesidades
domésticas.

Y ahora entiendo con cuánta razón claman los Superiores de esta provincia á nuestros Padres
generales, diciendo que no es esta vocación de cualquiera, sino de hombres solamente de virtud
muy grande y bien probada. Y á la verdad, uno entre otros engaños en que vivía cuando en Europa
ardía en deseos encendidos de venir á Indias, era persuadirme que para un Misionero Apostólico
de estas partes, bastaba tener un gran celo de las almas; pero quien leyere esta relación,
hallará que son más las ocasiones de ejercitar la interna abnegación del ánimo, la paciencia,
la humildad y la mortificación en sí mismo, que el celo de las almas con los otros, cuando
yo refiero aquí poco más que trabajos corporales, que son la menor parte de los que se ofrecen
que sufrir.

Por tanto, quiero poner aquí una carta que me escribió un compañero mío, á quien lloro y reverencio
á un tiempo, el cual, con otros cuarenta y tres de la Compañía que conducía á la provincia
de Quito, su procurador general Padre Nicolás de la Puente, por impenetrables consejos de Dios,
se ahogó en el navío Caballo Marino que se fué á pique el año de 1717. Dice, pues así:

«La circunstancia de que quizás no nos volveremos á ver más en Europa, me anima á escribir
ésta á mi hermano, que espero le hallará en Cádiz, á fin de darle el último vale, y con el
corazón un humilde abrazo, alegrándome, juntamente con el más vivo de mis afectos, por su ya
próxima suerte de dejar este mundo engañoso de acá y de ir en busca de otro mejor, ó para mejorarlo.
Conozcamos, hermano mío carísimo, nuestra fortuna, la cual estoy por decir que es la mayor
de cuantas Dios puede conceder á sus escogidos. ¿Y qué? ¿Por ventura es cosa de poca monta
vivir desconocido, y si tengo de decir la verdad, despreciado de todos, ó á lo menos poco estimado?
¡Oh, afortunados nosotros, si de cosa tan grande fuéramos participantes! ¡Ánimo, hermano mío
muy amado! ¡aliento, vamos, vamos! mas ¿dónde? á las Indias, esto es, al Calvario. ¿A qué fin?
A coronarnos, sí, pero de espinas; á descansar, sí, pero sobre una cruz. Aquí acabo, porque
desde aquí deben comenzar los deseos de un Jesuita indiano. Pidamos á Dios y á su Madre Santísima
que destierre de nuestro corazón todo otro afecto y no deje en él sino el ardientísimo deseo
de padecer por amor de quien nos amó hasta dar por nosotros la vida.»

CAPÍTULO VII

Fervor y virtud de la nueva cristiandad, premiada de Dios Nuestro Señor con muchos sucesos
milagrosos.

Eran verdaderamente grandes, como hemos visto, los trabajos y fatigas de los Padres en domesticar
este inculto campo de la gentilidad; pero no obstante eso, les parecía nada, aunque hubieran
sido sin comparación mucho mayores, viendo cuán bien prendía y se lograba la semilla de la
predicación evangélica, y cuán presto se sazonaba en frutos dignos del Paraíso; mas en esto
no quiero yo poner nada de mío, sino sólo hacer hablar á los mismos sembradores de esta semilla,
que se maravillan de ello y se dan el parabién con júbilos de incomparable consolación.

«En el conocimiento de Dios (dice uno de ellos) y en la observancia de la ley divina, se puede
con toda verdad, sin rastro de encarecimiento, afirmar que esta selva de bestias y de vicios
es ahora un retrato de la primitiva Iglesia. Bendigo infinitamente las santas llagas del Redentor
(dice otro) que comparada la vida pasada y presente de esta gente, son ahora tan diferentes
de sí mismos, cuando eran idólatras, que parecen en cierta manera reengendrados en la inocencia
original.»

Añade el P. Sebastián de Samartín, Superior que fué de aquellas Reducciones:

«Todo se puede sufrir por ellos, por el afecto que tienen á la fe, á la devolución y á lo que
es Dios ó de Dios.»

Pero más por extenso habla el Padre Misionero de la Reducción de San Joseph de la piedad de
su pueblo, en la Cuaresma del año de 1705.

«No es fácil de decir el fervor que estos santos días mostraron los nuevos cristianos en las
cosas de Dios; oían la paladra de Dios con gran gusto y no con menor fruto y compunción, de
suerte que me parecía estar entre españoles muy piadosos. El acto de contricción que se usa
al fin de los sermones, le hacían con tanto sentimiento, que lloraban muchísimo. El cual mostraron
también en la disciplina larga verdaderamente no poco, pero no tanto que satisfaciese á su
fervor, por lo cual costaba mucho el hacerles cesar, pidiendo á gritos misericordia á Nuestro
Señor, y repitiendo fervorosísimos actos de contricción y propósitos de no ofender más á su
Divina Majestad, principalmente en su innato vicio de la embriaguez, del cual, con el favor
de Dios, se han olvidado totalmente, pero donde se conocía más claramente su piedad y el verdadero
dolor y arrepentimiento de sus culpas, era en el acto de la confesión sacramental á que se
llegaban llorando tan amargamente que me sacaban lágrimas á los ojos y me llenaban de increíble
consuelo, dando gracias á la Divina Misericordia que obra en gente de suyo tan bárbara y nueva
en la fe tan prodigiosos efectos.»

Así aquel Misionero que prosigue diciendo otras mil cosas de bondad y devoción de sus cristianos,
que sirven de no pequeña confusión y rubor á quien ha nacido y vivido en el gremio de la Santa
Iglesia.

Bien que por lo que toca á la pureza de su conciencia dan otros Misioneros relación más distinta,
diciendo que hacen mucho escrúpulo de retener cosa ajena por pequeña que sea, que muchas veces
apenas se les halla materia suficiente para la absolución; que luego que sienten el menor remordimiento
de cualquiera culpa, por ligera que sea, y sólo en apariencia á veces, corren volando á llorarla
delante de Dios y pedir remedio á sus ministros, aunque estén actualmente ocupados en las labores
del campo, ó de noche reposando, y singularmente se refiere de una buena mujer que pareciéndole
aún esto poca parte para mantenerse inocente, importunó tanto al cielo con sus plegarias para
que la pusiese donde estuviese más segura de manchar su alma, que al fin logró feliz despacho
de sus súplicas, porque el día solemne de la Ascensión, asaltada de un accidente casi repentino,
recibidos todos los Sacramentos, fué por la muerte á gozar la gracia que deseaba.

Ni esta inocencia es solamente de algunos á quien Dios Nuestro Señor mira con ojos más piadosos,
y cuyas almas fortalece con mayor copia de bendiciones celestiales, sino que es común en todas
las Reducciones, á lo menos en lo exterior, porque algunos de los regidores del pueblo tienen
por oficio sindicar las costumbres de los demás, y cuando tal vez alguno, por sugestiones de
la carne se rinde al vicio sensual, vistiéndole primero de penitente, le hacen confesar su
culpa y pedir perdón á Dios en medio de la iglesia, de donde llevado á la plaza, le azotan
ásperamente delante de todos.

Pero no me causa tanta maravilla la penitencia que estos culpados hacen, siendo descubiertos
por ajenas diligencias, cuanto la sincera confesión de un Cathecúmeno y de una india. Supo
aquél que un cristiano había sido castigado con el rigor que he dicho, y parecióle tan bien
esta justicia, que instantáneamente suplicó se usase con él de semejante castigo, porque yo,
dijo, soy reo del mismo pecado; y la india, habiendo caído secretísimamente en una fragilidad,
no paró hasta que con gran sentimiento manifestó su culpa á los Regidores, pidiéndoles con
muchos ruegos y súplicas se ejecutase en ella el público castigo, afirmando que le movía á
hacer esto la ofensa cometida contra Dios, y el no haber seguido los ejemplos de tantos que
habían resistido al incentivo de la carne con la consideración de la presencia de Dios que
en todas partes asiste, con la memoria de las penas eternas del infierno y con los otros medios
que les han enseñado los Padres.

Y lo que es más en unos bárbaros hechos á vivir en su libertad sin frenos de castigos y penas,
que ninguno de ellos se siente de esta severidad que se usa para corregir sus deslices. Mas
lo que parece milagro es que los Chiquitos de tal suerte han depuesto las enemistades con los
confinantes, mamadas con la leche, fomentadas del genio, defendidas con las armas y hechas
implacables con la sangre derramada, que cuando antes no podían sufrir ni aun ver á sus enemigos
en el mundo, ahora están con ellos en una misma Reducción, viven en una misma casa y comen
á una mesa, convirtiendo los odios y rencores en otro tanto amor de unos con otros, como si
no tuvieran otro padre que á Dios y todos fueran una familia de Jesucristo.

Esto pudiera parecer lo sumo de la virtud en unos cristianos nuevos si no hubieran pasado adelante
á dejarse despedazar á gusto de los gentiles, por no faltar, como á ellos les parecía en un
punto, á la santa ley de Dios. Oyeron ellos que Dios mandaba no se volviese mal por mal, y
que á los ultrajes é injurias, aun en la vida, no se respondiese sino con mansedumbre y sufrimiento.

A poco tiempo fueron algunos neófitos (como adelante diremos) á buscar infieles para reducirlos
al conocimiento de Dios, y encontrándose de improviso con una Ranchería, los paisanos dieron
sobre ellos con sus macanas y flechas; pero los cristianos, aunque muy animosos y bien pertrechados
de armas con que fácilmente se hubieran podido defender, no obstante, por no hacerles mal alguno,
se dejaron quitar las vidas.

Otros, habiendo salido á otra empresa semejante, ni aun quisieron llevar armas consigo, y entrando
en una tierra enarbolaron en ella la imagen de Nuestra Señora, exhortando á la gente la hiciese
reverencia; pero la respuesta que tuvieron fué ver caer sobre sí una tempestad de saetas, de
que muchos quedaron allí muertos. Supieron esto los Misioneros y lloraron de consuelo pareciéndoles
un prodigio de la gracia en una nación tan soberbia y vengativa.

Y á la verdad, afecto tan tierno á las cosas de Dios, horror tan grande al pecado y á todo
lo que huele á vicio, se debe atribuir á la santa vida que observan y á los contínuos ejercicios
de piedad que todos, indiferentemente, sin distinción de sexo ni condición, practican.

Tres veces al día, al romper del alba, á medio día y á la noche, juntos los niños y las niñas
cantan á coros distintos gran número de oraciones y decoran de memoria lo que el Misionero
les ha explicado del Catecismo.

Todos los días de fiesta se junta el pueblo á oir algún punto de la doctrina cristiana ó sermón,
después de haber cantado solemnemente la misa. Al levantarse y acostarse se encomiendan á Dios,
á la Reina de los Ángeles y al Santo Ángel de la Guarda, con devotas oraciones que en bautizándose
aprenden; de otras usan al entrar en la Iglesia y cuando el Sacerdote eleva la Sagrada Hostia
ó el Cáliz. Antes de sentarse á comer echan en pie la bendición, y fuera de eso no comen ninguna
vianda fuera de la mesa sin que primero la bendigan con la santa cruz. Cuando son admitidos
á la participación de los divinos misterios, no es fácil de explicar con cuánta devoción y
tiernos coloquios se llegan á comulgar y cuánto después procuran mantener su corazón puro y
limpio de toda mancha de pecado.

Pudiera traer muchos ejemplos en confirmación de esto, pero por no causar fastidio á los lectores,
me contentaré con referir uno sólo. Deseaban ciertos mozos recibir el Pan de los Ángeles; mas
el Padre les dió á entender que no se lo concedería jamás si primero no corregían y enmendaban
cierta libertad que tenía algún resabio de gentilismo; ellos, sin otra diligencia, obedecieron
luego; y aunque les costaba no poco, se enmendaron totalmente de la dicha costumbre. Preguntóles
después si habían vuelto á recaer y admirándose mucho, respondieron que cómo era posible ofender
á su Señor después de haberle dado acogida en su corazón.

Pero cuando estas Reducciones parecen un paraíso (dice un sujeto que las ha visto), es por
la noche, cuando todos cantan las cosas de nuestra Santa fe, puestas en cierto modo de música
muy llano, lo cual hacen los niños y niñas en las calles públicas al pie de las cruces, y los
hombres en sus casas y en lugar separado de las mujeres; después rezan el rosario y concluyen
esta devota función con cánticos en alabanza de Cristo Señor Nuestro, y de su Santísima Madre
Nuestra Señora la Virgen María, á quien profesan afecto tiernísimo, no llamándola con otro
título que de Madre; todos los sábados y las vísperas de las festividades consagradas á su
nombre, cantan la misa á son de instrumentos músicos, cuales se usan entre ellos, y jamás van
á trabajar al campo ó vuelven de su labor sin que primero entren en la iglesia á hacer oración
delante de su imagen.

Lo mejor de sus pobres haberes emplean en servicio de esta Señora, y quieren antes ser pobres
que faltar un punto en su culto; y una vez que un Padre quería que vendiesen la cera de las
abejas llamadas Opemús, que es blanquísima, y la mejor, le respondieron resueltamente: «No
quiera Dios que se expenda en provecho nuestro lo que hemos ofrecido á su Madre Santísima,
pues si nosotros nos privamos de esta cera por amor suyo, á ella le tocará socorrer nuestra
pobreza.»

Finalmente, para última prueba de la devoción de estos nuevos cristianos, daré noticia de ciertas
precesiones públicas suyas, las cuales, si á algunos parecieren menudencias de que no se debe
hacer caso, digo que en otros pudiera parecer así pero no en gente para quien fué necesario
un oráculo del Vaticano para creer que eran capaces de la ley de Dios: «Pues los primeros descubridores
de las Indias juzgaron falsa y temerariamente que no eran racionales sino brutos, incapaces
de razón; y fundados en este error los españoles de la isla de Santo Domingo y las demás, teniéndolos
por animales, los cargaban tres y cuatro arrobas acuestas, los sacaban y llevaban muchas leguas
y esta opinión se entendió después con harto daño de los naturales, de suerte que en Nueva
España, juzgándoles imprudentemente por bestias con forma humana, los trataban como si lo fueran,
negando, por el consiguiente, ser capaces de la Bienaventuranza y de los Santos Sacramentos,
y llegó á tanto esto, que obligó á D. Fr. Juan Garcés, primer Obispo de Haxcala, Dominico,
año 1636[V.] á escribir una carta llena de piedad y erudición, informando la verdad al Sumo
Pontífice Paulo III, quien con Breve y Bula especial, definió y declaró á los indios por hombres
racionales y capaces de la fe católica, como todas las demás naciones de la Europa y de todo
el mundo: Indos ipsos utpoté veros homines, non solúm christianæ, fidei capaces existere decernimus
et declaramus, etcétera.[VI.] Siendo, pues, tales los indios, que ha habido quien los haga
irracionales, aun á los menos bárbaros, y siendo estos Chiquitos unos de los de la clase de
los más bárbaros (P. Acosta in Prooem. ad lib. de Procur. Indor, salute, según lo que enseña
el P. Joseph Acosta, D. Juan Solorzano, Lib. de Politic. Indian. capítulo 9, pág. 41, y el
ilustrísimo señor Obispo de Quito D. Alonso de la Peña Montenegro, libro 2 del Itinerario in
Prologo, página 141 y otros muchos autores) nadie tendrá por cosa de menos monta estas señales
exteriores de devoción que ya refiero.»

La noche, pues, del Jueves Santo, después de haber oído un fervorosísimo sermón de la Pasión
de Nuestro Señor Jesucristo, se visten un hábito acomodado á la tristeza de aquel santo tiempo;
y para imitar al Redentor penando, llevan algunos á cuestas cruces muy pesadas; otros se ciñen
de agudas espinas la cabeza; quién atadas atrás la manos, va arrastrado por tierra; quién derecho
con los brazos extendidos en forma de cruz, los más se azotan ásperamente con terribles disciplinas;
cierra la procesión una tropa de niños que de dos en dos llevan los instrumentos de la Pasión
del Señor.

Después, al pie de un devoto Crucifijo puesto delante del santo sepulcro, todos por su orden,
con lágrimas de tiernísimos sentimientos en los ojos, le ofrecen los frutos de sus sementeras,
«llenándose entre tanto (dice un Misionero) de consuelo nuestros corazones al ver postradas
estas almas delante del Divino Cordero que las rescató con su sangre; las cuales poco antes
andaban como fieras descarriadas y perdidas por las selvas.»

La otra procesión hacen el día del Corpus, á la cual convidan las naciones confinantes de los
gentiles; componen, pues, las calles lo más ricamente que á su pobreza es posible, y en lugar
de tapices recamados de oro ó de colgaduras de damasco, adornan con ingenioso artificio las
fachadas de las casas de ramos de palma, hermosamente enlazados unos con otros; á las cabeceras
de las calles levantan arcos triunfales que visten de cuanto hermoso y florido hay en sus huertas
y bosques; lo mejor de los aderezos y bordaduras labradas hermosa y delicadísimamente de plumas,
lo pone cada uno delante de su casa; y á fin de que todas las criaturas, aun irracionales,
rindan homenaje y tributo de reverencia al común Señor de todas, salen días antes á caza de
pájaros y de fieras, aunque sean tigres y leones, y bien atados los ponen en el camino por
donde ha de pasar el Santísimo Sacramento, y juntamente arrojan por el suelo el maíz y las
demás semillas de que han de hacer sus sementeras para que sea bendito de Dios y las haga multiplicar
á la medida de su necesidad; pero lo mejor de esta devotísima fiesta es la tiernísima devoción
y fervor con que acompañan aquel trabajo á gloria de su Criador.

Y no piense nadie que Dios Nuestro Señor se deja (á modo de decir) vencer de la piedad de estos
sus nuevos fieles, antes bien parece, por decirlo así, que ha andado con ellos á competencia,
de suerte que, cuanto ellos más se emplean en su servicio, tanto más les retorna y recompensa
con beneficios, porque como por experiencia sabemos, suele ser sobremanera amoroso y benéfico
en la primera formación de aquellos, que escoge para cimientos de alguna nueva Iglesia entre
infieles y usa más largamente en provecho suyo de sus bendiciones, no sólo en las necesidades
espirituales, sino también en las corporales.

Perdíanse una vez los sembrados por falta de agua, y apenas la pidieron los neófitos, cuando
rompió en abundantísimas lluvias.

Hacía gran estrago en la gente del pueblo de San Rafael una pestilencia; corrió luego el pueblo
á la iglesia á pedir á Dios misericordia, y al punto cesó el contagio, de suerte que ninguno
de los tocados de él murió en adelante, ni de los sanos enfermó alguno.

Había también aquí gran carestía de víveres, por cuya causa algunas buenas mujeres representaron
á Dios su necesidad, diciéndole la una: «Señor y Dios Nuestro Jesucristo, dadnos qué comer,
porque si no nos morimos.» Y otra: «Señor ¿queréis que me muera? Mirad que me estoy cayendo
de hambre», y aquel año fueron abundantísimas las cosechas.

Habían de ir al monte los cristianos del pueblo de San Juan Bautista á hacer provisión de carne,
pero por no haberse concluído la fábrica de la iglesia se quedaron trabajando por acabarla
de fabricar con toda perfección, fiándose de Dios que los proveería como de hecho sucedió,
porque de allí á poco salieron del bosque muchos jabalíes en tropas; y para que claramente
se conociese que era cosa de Dios, se pararon junto á la Reducción, para que la gente pudiese
á su salvo matar los que eran suficientes para socorrer á su necesidad.

Pero sería nunca acabar si quisiésemos referir una por una las finezas que Dios Nuestro Señor
ha usado con ellos. Sea solamente última prueba de ellas que estiman más estos neófitos un
rosario que cualquiera otra cosa, por hermosa y preciosa que sea, y con razón, porque le sirve
de un seguro reparo y escudo en las desgracias y peligros que encuentran en sus caminos; y
los nombres santísimos de Jesús y de María, los han librado muchas veces de evidentes riesgos
de ser hechos pedazos de las fieras. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02451</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>100136</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21901</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

After this, the Missionaries have worked our breed and maintain these tender plants can not explain
better than talking honestly, without adding anything of mine, a particular fact and part of letter
true, as I will, wherever they find juncture, originals faithfully carried this story will
be more reliable and taste more satisfied readers.

He says, then, Brother Juan de Avila, P. partner was Visitor of this province Antonio Garriga
and P. Provincial Luis de la Roca, where as I shall, visited those Doctrines subject of much trial
and ability in a letter from there wrote:

"As for founding the Missions of Paraguay suffered incredible work those first apostolic men,
taking the Indians of the jungles and engaging in their Christian life and politics to put them in the
state that remain today, divided into thirty Reductions well have been less work and sweat
of those who have founded the first Christianity of the Chiquitos. It is not easy to say what they
have been exposed to suffer hidden enemies and friends, the high cost of everything needed for
human life the deep swamps, inaccessible mountains, impenetrable forests, wild animals, intemperate
climates, thirst, hunger, extreme nudity, total abandonment of all things and honor all war
hell. Could descend to particular cases I have seen and heard if they were not well known and
I are continuing matter of shame and confusion. Do not bring upon itself, but a cloth vestidillo
trivial pieces, and often dressed in animal skins, do not bring other shoes a piece of rawhide
attached to another string of leather for the soles of the feet, and head for shelter from
the sun ardientísimo there does, one as a hat, but also leather bed without any relief, the regular
lunch box, a handful of corn, and this with such low it was barely enough to keep the forces, great
time to live without the comfort even of seeing one of his companions, and being afflicted with
long and painful diseases, no nowhere to turn our eyes. "

So the brother said, and I test everything he says, want to point out some cases where particular.

He
told me not long ago, a father who was Superior of those reductions,
which for many months did not have something else to sustain, but
grass roots, and they also lacking, harassed of hunger, was compelled
to go in search of wild fruits.

When Fr Gregory Campbell was on behalf of P. Simon de Leon, Provincial
of the province, to visit those missions, he took the winter (there
is not measured by the cold, not does, but by the breaking of the
rains) took him under a bower, where seven missionaries spent a long
time without other sustenance than a wild fruit called Motaquí, with
some kinds of milk, and the day of Easter, great gift, the neophytes
were given an ear or spike corn.

But it had another on the same day as Fr Zea, which present great gift for While some small rolls,
could not eat anything from them for being bitter as gall.

Has not seemed superfluous to have these trifles, for apostolic men who in does not look anything
other than conversion of infidels, notice also how much they cost and consider if you need a very
generous charity is employed in seeking the glory of God and look for the eternal salvation
of souls.

And certainly not cower to hazards, not to turn their backs to many jobs, not to withdraw and not
leave a life in which to each pass is with death, dying of hunger here, lost there in the woods,
now walk between arrows and clubs, now in the midst of angry people, it is difficult under
of being, and all that is necessary under whom ever undertaken in remote countries and among barbarians
the office of the Apostolic preaching.

But what fills me with awe and wonder, is that amidst so many hardships and discomforts, have
not yet died among many workers more than three or four, whereas there who has worked twenty-five
and thirty years, but it is singular providence of the Almighty,
who whom no case has made his life for his service, are kept healthier
and better than if had lived in the comforts of a college, as I saw,
with great astonishment, in P. Juan Zea Baptist, that age of sixty-five
years seemed younger in just over thirty breath and courage.

Truth is that today have largely eased many labors, introduced in those people with the Holy Faith
civil and political life, pass it a little better Missionary and the piety of men provides
them with some things to happen to the needs domestic.

And now I know how right to claim the Superiors of the province to
our Fathers general, saying there is this desire for anyone, but only
men of virtue very large and well established.

And indeed, one among other deceptions in which he lived when in Europe firings was eager to
come to India, was to persuade me that for a Missionary Apostolic of these parts, enough to have
a great zeal for souls, but who shall read this regard, find that there are more occasions to
exercise the internal devotion of mind, patience, humility and self-mortification,
and zeal for souls with the other, when I refer here little more than
physical labor, which are the least of which are offered to suffer.

So I want to add a letter that I wrote a friend of mine, whom I cry and reverence at once, which,
with forty-three of the Company that led to the province Quito, the Attorney General Nicholas
de la Puente Father, by God's inscrutable counsels, drowned in the sea horse that ship was
sunk by the year 1717. Dice, thus:

"The fact that we may not see again in Europe, encouraged me to write it to my brother, I hope
you will find in Cadiz, in order to give the final okay, and the
embrace a humble heart, rejoice, along with the most vivid of my affections,
by his now next sort of misleading to leave this world of here and
go in search of a better, or to improve it.

Know, my dearest brother, our fortune, which I am about to say is the largest how many God can give
to his chosen. So what? Perchance is a small thing live unknown, and if I have to tell the
truth, despised by all, or at least some estimate? Oh, lucky us, a great thing if we were involved!
Courage, my brother beloved! Breath, go, go! but where? the Indies,
that is, to Calvary.

To what end? A crown us, yes, but with thorns, to rest, yes, but on a cross. Here just because
from here should start the wishes of a Jesuit Indian. Pray to God and his Blessed Mother to
banish from our hearts all other affections, and not leave him but the desire ardientísimo to
suffer for love of Him who loved us to make life for us. "

CHAPTER VII

Fervor and under the new Christianity, winner of our Lord God with many events miraculous.

They were truly great, as we have seen, the work and labors of the Fathers in tame this uneducated
heathen field, but nevertheless it seemed to them nothing, even if they no comparison was much higher,
seeing how well lit and could seed Gospel preaching, and how soon is seasoned by fruits worthy
of Paradise, but in this I do not want to put any of mine, but only
to speak to them sowers of the seed, to marvel at it and give Rejoice
with incomparable joys of comfort.

"In the knowledge of God (says one) and the observance of divine law
can be in all truth, without a trace of exaggeration, say that this
jungle of beasts and vice is now a portrait of the early Church.

Bendigo infinitely holy wounds of the Redeemer (Says another) that compared the past and present
life of these people, are now so different themselves, when they were idolaters, who seem somehow
born anew in innocence Original. "

Add Father Samartín Sebastian, who was Superior of those reductions:

"Everything can suffer for them, for the affection they have to faith, to return and to what God
or of God. "

But speaking at length Missionary Father St. Joseph Reduction of mercy his people, during Lent
of the year 1705.

"It is not easy to say the fervor that these holy days showed the
new Christians in things of God, heard the paladra of God with great
taste and less fruit and no compunction in I felt lucky to be among
pious Spanish.

The act of contrition that is used the end of the sermons, made him such grief, crying a lot.
Which showed discipline also not really long enough, but not so paid
upon fervor, which cost so much stop them, screaming for mercy to
our Lord and fervorosísimos repeating acts of contrition and purpose
of his no longer offend Divine Majesty, especially in their innate
vice of drunkenness, which, with the help God, have completely forgotten,
but which most clearly knew his piety and true sorrow and repentance
for their sins, was in the act of sacramental confession to that came
crying so bitterly that drew tears to my eyes and filled me with incredible
comfort, giving thanks to the Divine Mercy which is in its people
as barbaric and new faith in such prodigious effects.

"

So Missionary who went on to say that a thousand other things of kindness and devotion of Christians
that serve no little confusion and shame to those born and lived in the bosom of the Holy Church.

Rather
than by what touches to the purity of his conscience are other missionaries relationship differently
saying they do much scruple to hold another's property by small, often they are found just enough
matter for absolution, then they feel the slightest remorse of any guilt, however slight,
and sometimes only in appearance, are flying to weep before God and seek remedy to his ministers,
although they are currently engaged in the work the field, resting or night, and particularly
concerns a woman who looks good even this small part to keep innocent, touted as the heavens
with their prayers for that put an safest where staining was his soul that he finally managed to happy
office their pleas, because the feast of the Ascension, assaulted an accident almost sudden
received all the Sacraments, was for death to enjoy the grace he wanted.

Neither this innocence is only a few to whom God looks with eyes more
pious and whose souls strengthened further copy of heavenly blessings,
but is common in all Reductions, at least on the outside, because
some of the aldermen of the town have by trade syndicate the customs
of others, and when maybe one, for suggestions the flesh yields to
vice sensual, seen first as a penitent, I do confess guilt and apologize
to God in the midst of the church, which led to the plaza, they lash
sharply in front of everyone.

But it makes me wonder penance so that those guilty are being discovered
by foreign coaches, as the sincere confession of catechumens and of
India.

Knew that a Christian had been punished with the rigor that I have said, and it seemed so good this
righteousness, which instantly begged him is use of such punishment, because I said, I'm guilty
of that sin, and India, a hush had fallen fragility not stop until he said with great feeling his guilt
to the Rulers, asking them many prayers and supplications were run in her public punishment, saying
he moved to make this offense against God, and not following the examples of many that had resisted
the lure of meat with the consideration of the presence of God assists everywhere, with the memory
of the eternal punishment of hell and the other media they taught the Padres.

And what's more barbarians made to live in freedom without brakes punishments and penalties, none
of them feel this severity that is used to correct his errors.

More it seems a miracle is that in such a way Chiquitos have laid down their enemies with confining,
blowjobs with milk, fostered the genius, defended with weapons and made the relentless bloodshed,
when previously unable to suffer or even see his enemies in the world, now are with them in the
same reduction, live in the same house and eat at a table, turning hatred and resentment at
as much love for one another, as if had no other father than God and all were a family of
Jesus Christ.

This might seem the most of virtue in a new Christian if they had not passed along left to shatter
them like the Gentiles, not to miss, even as they seemed in a point to the holy law of God.
They heard that God commanded them not return evil for evil, and than to the insults and injuries,
even in life, but no replies with meekness and suffering.

A short time were some newbies (as we shall) to seek to reduce them infidels the knowledge
of God, and suddenly found a Rancheria, the peasants were upon them with clubs and arrows,
but the Christians, but very spirited and well-equipped weapons that could have been easily
defended, however, not make them evil; were allowed to take lives.

Others, having gone to another such company, or even wanted to carry
weapons with them, and entering in a land peaked in it the image of
Our Lady, exhorting the people hiciese reverence, but the response
we had was to see fall upon them a storm of arrows, of there were
many dead.

They knew that the missionaries and wept with seeming comfort a miracle of grace in a nation so
proud and vengeful.

And indeed, affection so tender to the things of God, so great horror of sin and to all what
smells of vice, should be attributed to the holy life and to observe the continuous exercises pity
that everyone, regardless, regardless of sex or condition, practice.

Three times a day, at daybreak, at noon and at night, together children
choirs to sing various prayers and many memory decorate what the Missionary
has explained the Catechism.

All holidays are meeting the people to hear a point of Christian doctrine or sermon after a
solemn sung mass. By standing up and lying are entrusted to God the
Queen of the Angels and the Holy Guardian Angel, with devout prayers
that baptized learning, of some use to enter the Church and when the
priest elevates the Sacred Host or the Chalice.

Before sitting down to dinner cast up the blessing, and besides that do not eat any lunch box off
the table without first blessed with the holy cross. When admitted to the participation of the
divine mysteries, it is difficult to explain with much devotion and tender colloquies come near to
communicate and how much then try to keep your heart pure and clean from all stain of sin.

Could bring many examples in confirmation of this, but not to cause annoyance to readers content myself
with referring one. They wanted some young men receive the Bread of Angels, but Father gave them
to understand that it never granted without first corrected and amended certain freedom that
I had some remnant of heathenism; them, without any proceeding, obeyed then, and although not cost
them little, amended completely from this custom.

He asked then if they had returned to relapse and much admired, replied that how could offend
to his Lord after he had hosted in his heart.

But when these reductions seem a paradise (say a subject that has seen), is night, when everyone
sings the things of our holy faith, put on some music mode very flat, which makes children
on public streets at the foot of the crosses, and men in their homes
and in a separate place for women, then pray the rosary and conclude
This feature devoted to songs in praise of Christ Our Lord and His
Blessed Mother Our Lady the Virgin Mary, whom profess most tender
affection, not calling another Mother's title, all on Saturdays and
the eve of the festivities devoted to his name, to sing the Mass are
musical instruments, which are used among them, and never will to
work in the field or returning from their work without first entering
the church to pray in front of his image.

The best of its poor assets used in service of this lady, and want to be poor before to miss a point
in their worship, and once a father wanted to sell on the wax Opemús calls bees, which is very
white, and the best, answered resolutely: "No God forbid that our benefit is expended on what we
have offered to his Blessed Mother, because if we deprive ourselves of this wax for his sake,
she will get to help our poverty. "

Finally, for ultimate proof of the devotion of these new Christians,
give notice of certain public precessions own, which, if it proves
to some offal should not be ignore, others say that may seem so, but
not in people for whom it was necessary an oracle of the Vatican to
believe they were capable of the law of God: "For the first discoverers
de las Indias recklessly false and judged that they were not sound
gross but, unable of reason, and based on this error the Spanish island
of Santo Domingo and the other, holding them by animals, three four
arrobas loaded go to bed, were taken out and carried many miles and
this view was understood then fed natural damage, so that in New Spain,
to be careless by beasts in human form, treated as if they were, denying
the consequent, be able to Bliss and the Holy Sacraments and reached
as this, which led to D. Br Juan Garces, the first bishop of Haxcala,
Dominico, year 1636 [V] to write a letter full of piety and scholarship,
reporting the truth to the Supreme Pope Paul III, who with Quick and
special Bull, defined and declared to the Indians for men rational
and capable of the Catholic faith, like all other nations of Europe
and all the world see you utpoté Indos ipsos homines, non solum Christianae,
fidei able existere decernimus et declaramus and so on.

[VI.] Being then such Indians who has been rendering irrational, even the less barbarous, and these
little kids being one of the class the most barbarous (P. Acosta in Prooem. ad lib. attempting.
Indor, salute, as he teaches Fr Joseph Acosta, D. Juan Solorzano, Lib. of Politic. Indian. Chapter
9, pg. 41, and illustrious Bishop of Quito D. Alonso de la Peña Montenegro, in Book 2 of Schedule
Foreword, page 141 and many other authors) one less thing shall mount these signals external devotion
and mean. "

The night, therefore, Holy Thursday, after hearing a sermon on the Passion fervorosísimo of
Our Lord Jesus Christ, to wear a habit off the sadness of this holy season; and to imitate the
Redeemer grieving, have some very heavy crosses their backs, others are restricted head with
sharp thorns, who tied behind their hands, you dragged to the ground, who right with arms outstretched
in a cross, the most harshly hit with terrible disciplines closes the procession a troop of children
in pairs bearing the instruments of the Passion the Lord.

Then, at the foot of a crucifix placed before devotee of the Holy Sepulchre, all in their order,
tiernísimos feelings with tears in his eyes, he offered the fruits of their fields, "Filling in
the meantime (say a Missionary) of comfort our hearts to see prostrate
these souls before the Divine Lamb who rescued them with his blood
which shortly before they were like beasts strayed and lost in the
jungles.

"

The other procession made the day of Corpus, to which they invite the nations bordering the
Gentiles up, then, the most richly streets that his poverty is possible, and instead embroidered
tapestries of gold or damask hangings, decorated with the ingenious artifice facades of palm
branches, linked together beautifully, to the headwaters the triumphal
arches rise streets dressed as beautifully landscaped gardens are
in their and forests, the best of dressings and delicate embroideries
and beautiful carved feather it puts everyone in front of his house,
and in order that all creatures, even irrational, homage and tribute
of reverence to the common Lord of all, leave days prior to hunting
birds and beasts, even tigers and lions, and tied tightly put them
on the road which has to pass the Blessed Sacrament, and throw together
the ground corn and other seeds that have to do their fields to be
blessed by God and then multiply to the extent of their need, but
the best of this most devout party is the most tender devotion and
fervor with which accompany this work to the glory of his Creator.

And do not think that our Lord God one is left (so he said) to overcome the mercy of these his
new faithful, but rather it seems, so to speak, who has walked with them to competition, so that, the more
they are used in their service, the more returns and reward them with benefits, because as
we know from experience, is usually extremely loving and beneficent in the first training for those who
choose to foundations of a new church between infidels and uses more length to your advantage of
your blessings, not only on the needs spiritual, but also in the body.

Perdíanse once the fields for lack of water, and just called neophytes, when broke in very abundant
rainfall.

It was great havoc on the townspeople of San Rafael a pestilence; ran then the people to the church
to ask God for mercy, and to the point it stopped spreading, so that no of headgear he died
on, or any ill healthy.

There was also great shortage of food here, because of which women made some good their need
to God, telling one: "Jesus Christ Our Lord and God, give us something to eat, because if we
do not die. "And again:" Lord do you want me to die? Look I'm falling hunger ", and this year
were very abundant crops.

Had to go to Mount Christian town of San Juan Bautista to make provision
of meat, but have not finished the fabric of the church were working
to finish to make with all perfection, trusting God to provide as
in fact happened, Shortly afterwards it emerged from the forest are
many wild boars in troops, and to clearly was known that was a thing
of God, stood by the reduction, so that people could to kill her unless
they were enough to help their needs.

But it would never end if we want to relate one by one the favors that God Our Lord used with them.
Ultimate test is only them who believe most of these newcomers a rosary anyone else, beautiful and
precious it is, and rightly so, because it serves insurance repair and shield the misfortunes and dangers
they encounter in their ways, and most holy names of Jesus and Mary, have fought many times of
obvious risks to become the pieces of the beasts.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>