<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05994</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>55705</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19894</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Luego hay fuera de nosotros un conjunto de seres sometidos á leyes fijas, tanto con respecto
á nuestras sensaciones como entre sí: luego existe el mundo externo; luego el interno que nos
le representa, no es una pura ilusion.

CAPÍTULO VII.

ANÁLISIS DE LA OBJETIVIDAD DE LAS SENSACIONES.

[36.] El mundo externo, ¿es tal como nosotros nos le figuramos? Estos seres que nos causan
las sensaciones, y que llamamos cuerpos, ¿son en realidad lo que nosotros creemos? Despues
de demostrada la existencia de dichos seres, y su necesaria sujecion á leyes constantes, ¿no
podemos dudar todavía de si hemos demostrado la existencia de los cuerpos? ¿Basta para este
objeto, el haber probado que existen seres externos, en relacion con nosotros y entre sí, por
medio de leyes fijas y necesarias, independientes de ellos y de nosotros?

[37.] Para comprender á fondo esta cuestion, será conveniente simplificarla, reduciéndola á
un solo objeto.

Tengo á mi vista y en mi mano una manzana. Por lo demostrado mas arriba, estoy cierto de que
existe un ser externo, relacionado con otros seres y con el mio por leyes necesarias; estoy
cierto que de él me vienen diferentes impresiones: veo su color, figura y tamaño; percibo su
olor, experimento su sabor; siento en la mano su magnitud, su peso, su figura, sus concavidades
y convexidades, y oigo tambien el leve ruido que despide cuando la manoteo.

La idea de cuerpo es una idea compuesta; por manera que la de la manzana será: la de una cosa
externa, extensa, colorada, olorosa y sabrosa. Siempre que se reunan estas circunstancias,
esto es, siempre que yo reciba de un objeto las mismas impresiones, diré que tengo á la vista
una manzana.

[38.] Examinemos ahora hasta qué punto corresponde el objeto á las sensaciones que nos causa.

¿Qué entendemos significar cuando decimos que es una cosa sabrosa? Nada mas sino que nos produce
en el paladar una impresion agradable: lo propio se verifica con respecto al olfato. Luego
las dos palabras olorosa y sabrosa, solo expresan la causalidad de estas sensaciones, residente
en el objeto externo. Tocante al color, se puede afirmar lo mismo; porque si bien comunmente
transferimos la sensacion al objeto y nos ponemos en cierta contradiccion con la teoría filosófica
del color y de la luz, esta contradiccion no es mas que aparente; pues en el fondo, bien examinado
el juicio, solo consiste en referir la impresion á objetos determinados; por manera que cuando
por primera vez oimos en las cátedras de física que los colores no están en el objeto, fácilmente
nos acostumbramos á conciliar la teoría filosófica con la impresion del sentido; pues al fin
esa teoría no altera la verdad de que tales ó cuales impresiones nos vienen de estos ó aquellos
puntos de los diferentes objetos.

[39.] En esta parte, no es difícil explicar los fenómenos de las sensaciones, ni la correspondencia
de ellas con los objetos externos; porque para salvar esta correspondencia basta que ellos
sean realmente la causa (ú ocasion) de las mismas. No es tan fácil la tarea en lo tocante á
la extension; pues esta propiedad es como la base de todas las otras sensibles: y prescindiendo
de si constituye ó nó la esencia de los cuerpos, lo cierto es que nosotros no concebimos cuerpo
donde no hay extension.

[40.] Se palpará la diferencia que va de la extension á las demás calidades sensibles con la
observacion siguiente. Cuando no hemos pensado jamás en la relacion de los objetos externos
con nuestras sensaciones, tenemos no sé qué confusion sobre estos puntos; y el color, el olor,
el sabor y hasta el sonido, los transferimos en cierto modo á los mismos objetos, considerando
confusamente estas cosas como calidades inherentes á ellos. Así el niño y el rústico creen
que el color verde está realmente en las hojas, que el olor está en la rosa, el sonido en la
campana, el sabor en la fruta. Pero es fácil de notar que este es un juicio confuso de que
no se dan cuenta á sí mismos con toda claridad; juicio que puede ser alterado y aun destruido,
sin destruir ni alterar el conjunto de las relaciones de nuestros sentidos con los objetos.
Así, aun en edad muy tierna, nos acostumbramos con facilidad á referir el color á la luz, y
hasta á no fijarle en esta definitivamente, sino á mirarle como una impresion producida en
nuestro sentido por la accion de este agente misterioso. El olor tampoco nos cuesta trabajo
considerarle como una sensacion dimanada de la accion de los efluvios de un cuerpo sobre el
órgano del olfato; así como el sonido dejamos de considerarle cual una cosa inherente al cuerpo
sonoro, y no vemos en él mas que la impresion causada en el sentido por la vibracion del aire,
conmovido á su vez por la vibracion del cuerpo sonoro.

Estas consideraciones filosóficas que á primera vista nos parecian estar en contradiccion con
nuestro juicio, no alteran para nosotros el mundo externo; no causan un trastorno en las ideas
que nos formamos de él; solo nos hacen fijar mas la atencion en algunas relaciones que deslindábamos
mal; y no nos permiten atribuir á los objetos, mas de lo que tienen en realidad. Nos hacen
limitar el testimonio de los sentidos á la esfera que les pertenece, rectifican en algun modo
los juicios que habíamos formado; pero el mundo continúa siendo el mismo que antes; solo que
los encantos de la naturaleza, los hemos encontrado en mas íntima relacion con nuestro ser,
notando que en ellos tienen mas parte nuestra organizacion y nuestra alma de lo que nos habíamos
imaginado.

[41.] Pero destruyamos la extension, quitemos á los objetos externos esta calidad, finjamos
que ella no es mas que una simple sensacion, sin que sepamos otra cosa sino que hay un objeto
que nos la causa, y desde entonces, el mundo corpóreo desaparece. Todo el sistema del universo
se reducirá á un conjunto de seres que nos causan diferentes impresiones; pero quitada la extension
ya no nos formamos idea del cuerpo, ya no sabemos si todo lo que hemos pensado sobre el mundo
es algo mas que una pura ilusion. Yo me resigno fácilmente á deshacerme de lo que creia en
mi infancia de que el color que veo en mi mano esté en ella, de que el ruido que hace al chocar
con la otra esté en ella; pero no puedo de ningun modo privarla de la extension; no puedo imaginar
que la distancia de la palma al extremo de los dedos no sea mas que una pura sensacion, de
que solo haya un ser que me la cause, sin saber si en la realidad esta distancia existe. A
la fruta que encuentro sabrosa, le quito sin mucho trabajo los honores del sabor; y considerándola
filosóficamente, no tengo inconveniente en admitir que en ella no hay nada semejante á este
sabor, y sí tan solo, que está compuesta de tal suerte que afecta el órgano del paladar de
la manera conveniente para que yo reciba la sensacion agradable; pero no puedo quitar á la
fruta su extension, no puedo de ningun modo considerarla como una cosa indivisible; no me es
dable mirar las distancias de uno á otro punto de ella como meras sensaciones. Cuando me esfuerzo
por contemplar como indivisible en sí el objeto sabroso, me esfuerzo en vano; y si por un momento
me parece que llego á vencer el instinto de la naturaleza, todo se me trastorna: con el mismo
derecho que hago de la fruta una cosa indivisible lo hago del universo; y el universo indivisible
no es para mí el universo; mi inteligencia se confunde, todo se aniquila al rededor de mí:
sufro algo mas que la vista del caos; el caos se me presenta al menos como alguna cosa, bien
que con horrible confusion de elementos en espantosas tinieblas; pero ahora sufro algo mas,
pues el universo corpóreo, tal como le habia concebido, vuelve á la nada.

CAPÍTULO VIII.

Sensacion de la Extension.

[42.] Dos sentidos perciben la extension; la vista y el tacto; el olor, el sabor, el sonido,
andan acompañados de la extension, pero son cosa muy diferente. La vista no percibe nada que
no sea extenso; la extension es de todo punto inseparable de dicha sensacion. Embebidos en
una deliciosa armonía de muchos instrumentos, podremos saborearnos en la percepcion de los
sonidos hasta olvidarnos de la extension de los instrumentos, del aire, y de nuestros órganos:
pero al contemplar un cuadro, aun en medio del entusiasmo mas ardiente, no puede desaparecer
la extension. Si de la transfiguracion de Rafael quitamos la extension, la maravilla desaparece;
porque en la esencia de ella, aun considerándola como simple fenómeno de nuestra alma, entran
por necesidad la continuidad y las distancias.

Lo propio se verifica con respecto al tacto, bien que nó con tanta generalidad. La dureza ó
la blandura, la aspereza ó la lisura, la angulosidad ó la rotundidad traen consigo la extension:
pero no puede negarse que hay ciertas impresiones de tacto, en las que no es tan claro que
vayan acompañadas de ella. El agudo dolor de una punzada, y otros que se sienten sin causa
exterior conocida, no se refieren con tanta claridad á la extension, y parecen tener algo de
aquella simplicidad que distingue las impresiones que nos llegan por el conducto de otros sentidos.

Como quiera, es cierto que el percibir la extension pertenece de una manera particular á la
vista y al tacto.

[43.] Para formarnos ideas claras sobre la extension en sus relaciones con la sensacion, la
analizaremos con algun detenimiento.

En primer lugar es digno de notarse que la extension envuelve multiplicidad; un ser extenso
es por necesidad un conjunto de seres: estos se hallarán mas ó menos unidos entre sí, por medio
de un vínculo que los hará formar un todo: pero esto no quita que ellos no sean muchos. Un
hermoso cuadro donde domina la unidad de pensamiento del artista, no deja de ser un compuesto
de muchas partes; el vínculo moral que las une, no las identifica; solo las enlaza, las ordena,
las hace concurrir á un fin. La firmísima adhesion que entre sí tienen las moléculas de que
está formado el diamante, no hace que estas moléculas no sean distintas: el vínculo material
las une, no las identifica.

Sin multiplicidad pues, no hay extension; donde hay extension, no hay un ser solo, en todo
el rigor de la palabra, sino muchos.

[44.] Pero la multiplicidad no constituye la extension, porque puede existir la primera sin
la segunda. La multiplicidad de sonidos no forma la extension, la multiplicidad de sabores
ni de olores tampoco: nosotros concebimos multiplicidad de seres de diferentes órdenes así
en el mundo material, como en el moral y en el intelectual, sin que se envuelva en esa multiplicidad
la idea de extension. Aun limitándonos al órden puramente matemático, encontramos multiplicidad
sin extension en las cantidades aritméticas y algebráicas. Luego la multiplicidad, si bien
es necesaria para constituir la extension, no basta ella sola para constituirla.

Reflexionando sobre la especie de multiplicidad requerida para formar la extension, notaremos
que ha de andar acompañada de la continuidad. Las sensaciones así de vista como de tacto, envuelven
la continuidad: pues ni me es posible ver ni tocar, sin que reciba la impresion de objetos
continuos, inmediatos los unos á los otros, coexistentes en su duracion y que á un mismo tiempo
se me ofrecen como continuados unos con otros en el espacio. Sin esta continuidad, la multiplicidad
no constituye la extension. Así por ejemplo, si tomo cuatro ó mas puntos en el papel en que
escribo, y por una abstraccion los considero indivisibles, esta multiplicidad no me constituye
la extension: necesito unirlos por medio de líneas, cuando menos imaginarias; y á falta de
continuidad del cuerpo en que los suponia situados, me será preciso valerme de la continuidad
del espacio: es decir, mirar este espacio como un conjunto de puntos, cuya continuacion enlaza
los primeros. Por mas esfuerzos que haga no me será posible considerar como extension un conjunto
de puntos indivisibles no continuos, ni unidos por líneas: aquel conjunto será para mí como
si fuera de otros seres, que nada tuviesen que ver con la extension. Y es digno de notarse,
que si les doy un lugar determinado en el espacio, es tambien enlazándolos por medio de líneas
imaginarias con otros puntos: pues nó de otra manera puedo concebir distancias, ni situacion
en el espacio. Que si de todo esto quisiese prescindir, entonces ó paso á la nada intelectual,
es decir aniquilo toda idea del objeto, ó me traslado á otro órden de seres que ninguna relacion
tengan ni con la extension ni con el espacio. Habré dejado la materia y las sensaciones, y
me habré remontado á la region de los espíritus.

[45.] Luego la multiplicidad y la continuidad son necesarias para constituir la extension.
¿Y bastan estas dos condiciones? creo que sí; pues donde ellas existen, existe la extension:
con ellas dos solas, enteramente solas, nos formamos la idea de la extension. El objeto de
la geometría es la extension; y en ella solo entran multiplicidad y continuidad. Las líneas,
las superficies, los volúmenes, tales como son objeto de la geometría, prescinden de todo lo
que no sea esa continuidad, mirada en su mayor abstraccion. Por esto le basta el espacio vacío;
ó mejor se diria, que por esto exige el espacio vacío; pues que cuando hace la aplicacion á
los cuerpos, no encuentra toda la exactitud que hallaba en la continuidad en abstracto.

[46.] Si la multiplicidad y la continuidad en el espacio constituyen la extension, esta existe
realmente en los objetos que nos causan las sensaciones. Ya he demostrado que á estas les corresponden
objetos externos, fundándome en la relacion misma de los fenómenos entre sí, y con las causas
que los producen: es así que esta relacion existe tambien con respecto á la multiplicidad y
á la continuidad, luego estas dos propiedades se hallan realmente en la naturaleza. Las impresiones
que recibimos por la vista y el tacto, aun limitándonos á un solo objeto, son múltiplas y por
tanto corresponden á muchos objetos; son continuas y por lo mismo corresponden á objetos continuos.

Aclararé algo mas esta razon. Mi vista fijada sobre un cuadro recibe una impresion que le viene
de muchos puntos diferentes; siendo de notar que esta impresion resulta sin interrupcion en
toda la superficie que se me ofrece. Si como llevo demostrado, la vista de un punto externo
me basta para convencerme de su existencia, la de muchos me bastará para estar seguro de la
de muchos; y la continuidad de la impresion me cerciora tambien de la continuidad de los puntos
imprimentes.

Si toco un objeto visto, el tacto me confirma el testimonio en la parte que á él le corresponde,
es decir la multiplicidad y la continuidad. Experimento la misma sucesion continuada de sensaciones,
lo que me indica la existencia y la continuidad de los objetos que las causan.

[47.] En resúmen: la extension supone la coexistencia de muchos objetos, pero de tal suerte
que estén unos á continuacion de otros; de ambas cosas nos aseguran las sensaciones: luego
el testimonio de los sentidos basta para estar ciertos de que hay objetos extensos, y pueden
producirnos varias impresiones. Estas ideas contienen cuanto encerramos en la idea de cuerpo:
luego el testimonio de los sentidos nos cerciora de la existencia de los cuerpos.

CAPÍTULO IX.

OBJETIVIDAD DE LA SENSACION DE EXTENSION.

[48.] Probado ya que el testimonio de los sentidos es suficiente para asegurarnos de la existencia
de los cuerpos, veamos hasta qué punto son exactas las ideas que de los mismos nos hace formar.
No basta saber que podemos estar seguros de la existencia de la extension, es preciso investigar
si ella es en realidad tal cual nos la presentan los sentidos; y lo que digo de la extension
puede aplicarse á las demás propiedades de los cuerpos.

En mi concepto, la única sensacion que nosotros trasladamos al exterior, y que no podemos menos
de trasladar, es la de extension; todas las otras se refieren á los objetos, solo como efectos
á causas, nó como copias á originales. El olor, el sabor, el sonido, no nos representan nada
que sea parecido á los objetos que los causan; pero la extension sí: la extension la atribuimos
á los objetos, y no podemos concebirlos sin ella. El sonido fuera de mí, no es sonido; no es
mas que una simple vibracion del aire, producida por la vibracion de un cuerpo; el sabor fuera
de mí, no es sabor; no es mas que un cuerpo aplicado á un órgano, y que le causa una modificacion,
mecánica ó química; y lo propio se verifica con el olor. Aun en la luz y los colores, fuera
de mí, no hay mas que un flúido que cae sobre una superficie, y que directa ó reflexamente,
llega ó puede llegar á los ojos; pero la extension fuera de mí, independientemente de toda
relacion con los sentidos, es verdadera extension, es algo cuya existencia y naturaleza no
necesitan de mis sentidos. Cuando yo la siento, ó cuando me la imagino, hay entre mis impresiones
y ella, algo mas que la relacion de un efecto á una causa: hay la representacion, la imágen
interior, de lo que existe en lo exterior.

[49.] Para que se comprenda perfectamente y se sienta con viveza la verdad de lo que acabo
de asentar, voy á ofrecer al lector un cuadro del cual se vayan eliminando sucesivamente determinadas
sensaciones, haciéndole notar el grado de eliminacion á que se puede llegar y del cual no se pasa.

Supongamos que todos los animales pierden de una vez el sentido del paladar, ó que todos los
cuerpos de la naturaleza son destituidos de la propiedad de causar por su contacto con un órgano,
la sensacion que llamamos sabor. A pesar de esto el mundo externo existe como antes. Los mismos
cuerpos que nos causaban las sensaciones ahora perdidas, continuarán existiendo y podrán ser
aplicados al mismo órgano que antes afectaban, causando en aquella parte las sensaciones del
tacto, como de blando ó duro, frio ó caliente, ú otras semejantes. O los cuerpos sabrosos ó
los órganos animales habrán sufrido alguna mudanza, con la que se ha cortado la relacion que
antes tenian: se nota que una causa que antes producia un efecto, es ahora impotente para producirle.
Esto puede haber acontecido por una modificacion de los cuerpos, que en nada altera su naturaleza,
en cuanto nosotros la concebimos; y tambien es posible que sin haberse mudado ellos, haya sobrevenido
esta diferencia con sola la alteracion de los órganos. Pero en todo caso, la desaparicion de
la sensacion, no ha hecho desaparecer del universo nada semejante á ella; si la alteracion
se ha verificado solo en los órganos, los cuerpos exteriores quedan intactos: y si ha tenido
lugar en los cuerpos, esta alteracion les ha hecho perder una propiedad causante de la sensacion,
mas nó una propiedad representada por la sensacion.

Ya hemos privado á los alimentos de todos sus sabores: el universo existe como antes: privémosle
de sus olores, alterando los cuerpos odoríferos, ó el órgano del olfato. ¿Qué resultará? lo
mismo que hemos notado con respecto al sabor. Los cuerpos odoríferos continuarán existiendo,
y hasta enviando á nuestro órgano los efluvios que antes producian la sensacion del olor; no
habrá mas novedad que la no existencia de esta sensacion: faltará en nuestros órganos la disposicion
para recibir la impresion necesaria, ó habrá desaparecido del universo una causalidad: mas
nó una cosa representada por la sensacion. Los jardines no serán despojados de su belleza simétrica,
los prados de su lozanía y verdor: el árbol ostentará su frondosa copa, y el hermoso fruto
continuará pendiente de las ramas mecidas por el viento.

Prosigamos en nuestra tarea destructora, ensordeciendo de repente á todos los animales. Los
músicos de los conciertos se convertirán en actores de una silenciosa pantomima; el campanero
tirando de la cuerda, hará dar vueltas al metal mudo; las conversaciones se reducirán á gestos
orales; los gritos de los brutos, no serán mas que abrir y cerrar bocas; pero el aire vibrará
como antes; sus colunas vendrán á herir el tímpano como antes; todo existirá como antes: nada
faltará en el universo sino una sensacion. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09333</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>943423</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17970</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Then there was us with a set of beings subject to fixed laws, both in terms to our feelings as
between themselves, then there's the external world, then the inner us it represents, it is a
pure illusion.

CHAPTER VII.

ANALYSIS OF THE OBJECTIVITY OF THE SENSATIONS.

[36.] The external world, is just as we figured it? These beings that cause us feelings, and
we call bodies, are in fact what we believe? After demonstrate the existence of such beings,
and its necessary subjection to constant laws, do not yet we doubt
whether we have demonstrated the existence of bodies?

Is it enough for this object, have proven that there are external beings in relationship with
us and each other, through fixed and necessary laws, independent
of them and us?

[37.] To fully understand this question, it will be convenient simplified to a single object.

I
have to my view and in my hand an apple. As shown above, I am sure that There is an external being,
related to other beings and with mine by necessary laws, I am it
true that my views are different: see its color, shape and size, feel
his smell, taste experiment, I feel in the hand of their magnitude,
their weight, figure, its concavities and convex, and also hear the
faint sound bouncing when the nudging.

The idea of ??body is a composite idea, and so the apple will be: a thing external large, colorful,
fragrant and tasty.

Whenever you meet these circumstances, that is, whenever I receive
an object the same views, I will say that I have in sight an apple.

[38.] Let us now examine the extent to which the object corresponds to the sensations it causes.

What
do we mean when we say we mean is something tasty? Nothing else but that makes us an impression
on the palate nice: the self is checked against the smell. Then the two words fragrant and tasty,
only express the causality of these feelings, resident in the external object. For the color, we can
say the same, because although commonly transfer the sensation to the object and put ourselves
in some contradiction to the philosophical theory color and light, this contradiction is only apparent,
since in the end, it examined the trial, only the printing is referred to specific objects,
for so when first we hear in the departments of natural colors are not the object easily get used
to reconcile the philosophical theory of meaning with the impression,
because in the end that theory does not alter the truth that such
and such impressions are coming from these or those points of different
objects.

[39.] In this part, it is difficult to explain the phenomena of feeling, no correspondence of
them with external objects, because this correspondence is enough to save them are really the cause
(or occasion) of them. It's not as easy task as regards the extension, as this property is as the
basis for all other sensitive, and regardless whether or not it is
the essence of bodies, the truth is that we can not conceive of body
where there is no extension.

[40.] This will feel the difference going from the extension to the other grades sensitive to following
observation. When we have not ever thought of the relation of external objects with our feelings,
we do not know what confusion on these points, and the color, smell, taste and even sound,
somehow transferred to the same objects, considering confused these as qualities inherent to
them. So the child and the rustic feel that is really green in the leaves, the smell is in
the rose, the sound in the Bell, taste the fruit. But it is easy to see that this is a confusing
trial that not realize to themselves clearly; trial that can be altered and even destroyed
without destroying or altering the overall relationship of our senses with objects. Thus, even
very young age, we got used to easily refer to the light color and up to set you on is definitely
not, but to look at him as an impression produced in our sense of the mysterious action of
this agent. The smell does not trouble us regarded as a sensation emanating from the action
of the waves of a body on organ of smell and the sound left to consider what something inherent
in the body sound, and we see it more than the impression conveyed in the direction of the vibration
of air, moved to turn the vibration of sound body.

These philosophical considerations which at first sight, it seemed to be in contradiction with
our view, do not alter the external world for us, not cause a disruption in the ideas we form of him,
only make us more secure attention in some relationships deslindábamos evil, and do not allow
us to attribute to objects, more than you actually have. We do limit the testimony of the senses
to the field they belong, in some measure rectified the judgments that had formed, but the world
remains the same as before, except that the charms of nature, found in more intimate relationship
with ourselves, noting that they have most part our organization and our soul than we imagined.

[41.]
But destroy the extension, removing foreign objects that quality,
let's pretend she is nothing more than a mere sensation, without knowing
anything except that there is an object we are the cause, and since
then, the corporeal world disappears.

The whole system of universe be reduced to a set of things that cause us different impressions,
but the extension removed no idea we form of the body, we do not know if everything we thought
about the world is more than a pure illusion. I am resigned to easily get rid of what they believed
in my childhood that the color I see in my hand is in it, that the noise it makes when hitting the
other is in it, but I can not in any way of removing the extension, I can not imagine the distance
from the palm to the tip of the fingers is not more than a mere feeling of there is only a
being that causes me, not knowing if in fact this distance exists. A I find tasty fruit, took the
honors work without much flavor, and considering philosophically, I have no problem admitting that
there is not anything like this taste, and if only, which is composed in such a way that affects
the body's palate convenient way for me to receive the pleasant sensation, but I can not get
to the fruit its extension, I can not in any way be considered as an indivisible thing, I am not possible
to look at the distances from one to another point of it as mere sensations. When I try by
itself viewed as indivisible object tasty, I strive in vain, and if for a moment I think I
come to conquer the instinct of nature, everything upsets me: with the same I do the right
fruit indivisible thing I do in the universe, and the indivisible universe not for me the universe,
my mind is confused, everything is destroyed around me: I suffer something more than the face of
the chaos, the chaos is to me something at least as well that horrible confusion of elements in appalling
darkness, but now suffer some more, as the corporeal universe, as he had conceived, come to naught.

CHAPTER
VIII.

Sense of the Extension.

[42.] Two senses perceive the extension, the sight and touch, smell,
taste, sound, walk accompanied by the extension, but are quite different.

The view that perceives nothing is not extended, the extension is
absolutely inseparable from that feeling.

Embedded a delicious harmony of many instruments, can be enjoyed
on the perception of sounds to forget the extension of the instruments,
air, and our bodies: but when looking at a picture, even in the midst
of the most ardent enthusiasm, can not disappear the extension.

If the transfiguration of Raphael remove the extension, the wonder disappears because the essence
of it, even considering it as a simple phenomenon of our soul, come continuity of necessity
and distances.

The same is checked against the touch, though not so generally. The hardness or softness, smoothness
or roughness, the angle or forcefully bring the extension: but it is undeniable that there are
some impressions of touch, which is not so clear that accompanied it. The sharp pain of a stitch,
and others who feel no cause known abroad, not so clearly relate to the extension, and seem to
have some that simplicity that distinguishes the impressions that
come to us for the conduct of other senses.

Since it is true that the extension belongs to perceive a particular way to the sight and touch.

[43.]
To form clear ideas about the extension in its relations with the sensation, the discuss in
some detail.

Firstly, it is noteworthy that the extension involves multiplicity, an extended being is necessarily
a set of beings: they will find themselves more or less linked together
through a bond that will form a whole: but this does not mean that
they are not many.

A beautiful picture which dominates the unity of thought of the artist, never ceases to be
a compound of many parts, the moral bond that unites them, not identified,
only the bonds, are ordered make them go to an end.

The very firm adherence to one another are the molecules that consists of the diamond, does
not make these molecules are different: the link material unites, not identified.

No multiplicity therefore no extension, where extension, there is a single being in any the rigor
of the word, but many.

[44.] But the multiplicity is not the extension, because there may be the first without the second.
Multiplicity of sounds is not the extension, the multiplicity of
flavors smells or not, we conceive multiplicity of beings of different
orders and in the material world, as in the moral and intellectual,
not to get involved in such multiple the idea of ??extension.

Even limiting ourselves to a purely mathematical, we found multiple no extension in arithmetic
and algebraic quantities.

Then the multiplicity, while is necessary to constitute the extension is not sufficient alone
to establish it.

Reflecting on the kind of variety required to form the extension, we note you have to walk together with
the continuity. The feelings and views as of touch, involving Continuity: because I can not see
or touch, without receiving the impression of objects continuous, immediate one to the other,
coexisting in its duration and at the same moment I offered as continuing
with each other in space.

Without this continuity, multiplicity not the extension. For example, if I take four or more
points in the paper that write, and consider them an abstraction indivisible, this multiplicity is
not me the extension: I need to connect them by lines, at least imaginary, and in default
of continuity of the supposed body located, I will need to avail myself of continuity space: that
is, watch this space as a set of points, which refers below the former. For more efforts to make me
not be possible to consider as a set extension non-continuous indivisible points, or by lines:
one set will be for me as if other beings, they had nothing to do with the extension. It is noteworthy,
that if I give a particular place in space, is also linked by lines imaginary other points:
it no other way I can conceive of distances, or situation in space. That if he wanted it all
without, then step into nothingness or intellectual ie annihilate the whole idea of ??the object,
or I move to another order of beings no relationship having either the extension or space. I have
left the area and feelings, and I'll be traced to the region of spirits.

[45.] Then the multiplicity and continuity are necessary to form the extension. What these two
conditions are sufficient? I think so, because where they exist, there is the extension: with
them two alone, entirely alone, we form the idea of ??extension. The purpose of geometry is the
extension, and it only come multiplicity and continuity. The lines, surfaces, volumes, such as the
subject of geometry, disregard everything other than that continuity, look for the most abstraction.
Therefore it is enough empty space; or rather it would seem, that
this requires the empty space, because when he makes the application
bodies, can not find all the accuracy that was in continuity in the
abstract.

[46.] If the multiplicity and continuity in space are the extension, it exists objects really
cause us feelings. I have already shown that they are entitled to these external objects, based
on the relationship of the phenomena itself together, and the causes that produce them: so that
this relationship exists also with respect to the multiplicity and to continuity, then these two
properties are actually in nature. Prints we receive by sight and touch, even limited to a
single object, are multiple and both correspond to many objects,
are continuous and therefore correspond to continuous objects.

I will clarify something else is right. My eye fixed on a table gets an impression that comes
from many different points, is worthy of note that this impression is no interruption in entire
area that I offer. If as I have shown, the view from an external point sufficient to persuade me of
its existence, many me enough to be sure the of many, and the continuity of the posters I also
ensure the continuity of the points imprimentes.

If you touch an object seen, touch me confirms the testimony in the party he belongs to, ie
the multiplicity and continuity. I experience the same continuous succession of sensations,
which tells me the existence and continuity of the objects that cause them.

[47.] In short: the extension is the coexistence of many objects,
but in such a way they are one after another, to assure us both sensations,
then the testimony of the senses enough to be certain that there are
extended objects, and can produce several prints.

These ideas contain as caught up in the idea of ??body: then the testimony of the senses we are
sure of the existence of bodies.

CHAPTER IX.

OBJECTIVITY OF THE SENSATION OF EXTENSION.

[48.] Tested and that the testimony of the senses is enough to ensure
the existence of bodies, see how far the ideas are correct that makes
us the same form.

Not enough to know that we can be sure of the existence of the extension
is necessary to investigate if she is in reality as it senses it is
presented, and what I say about the extension can be applied to other
properties of bodies.

In my opinion, the only feeling that we moved abroad, and we can not to move, is the extension,
all others refer to objects, just as effects to causes, not original copies. The smell, taste, sound,
we do not represent anything that is similar to the objects that cause them, but the extension
itself: the attribute extension to objects, and we can not conceive
without it.

The sound out of me is not sound, it is not more than just a vibration of air, produced by the
vibration of a body, the taste out me, not taste, is nothing but applied to a body organ, and
causes a modification, mechanical or chemical, and likewise takes place with the smell. Even
in the light and colors outside me, there is but one fluid falling on a surface, and direct or
reflexive reached or can reach the eyes, but the extension out of me, regardless of any relationship
with the senses, it is true extension, is something whose existence and nature need my senses.
When I am, or when I imagine, between my impressions and she, more than just the relationship of an
effect to a cause: there is representation, image interior of what exists on the outside.

[49.] In order to fully understand and feel vividly the truth of what I of seating, I am going
to give the reader a picture of which are eliminated on certain feelings, making note the
degree of elimination and can be reached which is not passed.

Suppose that all the animals once they lose the sense of taste, or
that all natural bodies are removed from the property caused by contact
with an organ the sensation we call flavor.

Despite this the external world exists as before. The same bodies that cause us feelings now
lost, continue to exist and may be applied to the same body that previously affected, causing sensations
in that part of touch, as soft or hard, cold or hot, or similar.

O tasty or bodies animal organs have undergone some change, with which it has cut the relationship
that had before: it is noted that a cause which once produced an effect, is now powerless to produce
it. This may have happened by a modification of the bodies, which in no way alters their nature,
as we see it, and also may not have moved them, has occurred this difference with only the alteration
of the organs. But in any case, the disappearance of sensation, has not removed the universe
anything like it, if the alteration has been verified only in the organs, external bodies are
intact, and if you have place in the body, this alteration has made them lose a property that
causes the sensation, but not a property represented by the sensation.

Already deprived of food for all tastes: the universe exists as before privémosle its smells, altering
the body odor, or the organ of smell. What result? what same as we have noted with taste. Odoriferous
bodies continue to exist, and even send our bodies the fumes that once produced the sensation
of smell, not there will be more novelty than the non-existence of this feeling in our bodies
lack the disposition necessary to receive the impression, or the universe will be gone causality:
more Not one thing represented by the sensation.

The gardens will be stripped of its beauty symmetrical the meadows of its freshness and greenery:
the tree will hold its lush canopy, and beautiful fruit continue to monitor the branches swaying
in the wind.

Let us continue our work of destruction, suddenly deafening to all animals. The concert musicians become
actors in a silent pantomime, the ringer pulling the rope, the metal will spin dumb conversations
are reduced to gestures oral, the cries of the gross will be nothing but open and close mouths, but
the air vibrate as before, its columns will come to hurt the ear drum as before, all exist
as before: nothing missing in the universe but a feeling.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>