<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07766</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>224701</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20057</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El país carece
de espíritu militar. Nosotros somos un pueblo de guerreros, y nos será fácil vencer á los ingleses,
debilitados por una falsa concepción de la vida.

El doctor hizo una pausa y añadió:

--Contamos además con la corrupción interna de nuestros enemigos, con su falta de unidad. Dios
nos ayudará sembrando la confusión en estos pueblos odiosos. No pasarán muchos días sin que
se vea su mano. La revolución va á estallar en Francia al mismo tiempo que la guerra. El pueblo
de París levantará barricadas en las calles: se reproducirá la anarquía de la Commune. Túnez,
Argel y otras posesiones van á sublevarse contra la metrópoli.

Argensola creyó del caso sonreir con una incredulidad agresiva.

--Repito--insistió Hartrott--que este país va á conocer revoluciones aquí é insurrecciones
en sus colonias. Sé bien lo que digo... Rusia tendrá igualmente su revolución interior, revolución
con bandera roja, que obligará al zar á pedirnos gracia de rodillas. No hay mas que leer en
los periódicos las recientes huelgas de San Petersburgo, las manifestaciones de los huelguistas
con pretexto de la visita del presidente Poincaré... Inglaterra verá rechazadas por las colonias
sus peticiones de apoyo. La India va á sublevarse contra ella y Egipto cree llegado el momento
de su emancipación.

Julio parecía impresionado por estas afirmaciones, formuladas con una seguridad doctoral. Casi
se irritó contra el incrédulo Argensola, que seguía mirando al profesor insolentemente y repetía
con los ojos: «Está loco: loco de orgullo.» Aquel hombre debía tener serios motivos para formular
tales profecías de desgracia. Su presencia en París, por lo mismo que era inexplicable para
Desnoyers, daba á sus palabras una autoridad misteriosa.

--Pero las naciones se defenderán--arguyó éste á su primo--. No será tan fácil la victoria
como crees.

--Sí, se defenderán. La lucha va á ser ruda. Parece que en los últimos años Francia se ha preocupado
de su ejército. Encontraremos cierta resistencia; el triunfo resultará más difícil, pero venceremos...
Vosotros no sabéis hasta dónde llega la potencia ofensiva de Alemania. Nadie lo sabe con certeza
más allá de sus fronteras. Si nuestros enemigos la conociesen en toda su intensidad, caerían
de rodillas, prescindiendo de sacrificios inútiles.

Hubo un largo silencio. Julius von Hartrott parecía abstraído. El recuerdo de los elementos
de fuerza acumulados por su raza le sumía en una especie de adoración mística.

--La victoria preliminar--dijo de pronto--hace tiempo que la hemos obtenido. Nuestros enemigos
nos aborrecen, y sin embargo nos imitan. Todo lo que lleva la marca de Alemania es buscado
en el mundo. Los mismos países que intentan resistir á nuestras armas copian nuestros métodos
en sus universidades y admiran nuestras teorías, aun aquellas que no alcanzaron éxito en Alemania.
Muchas veces reímos entre nosotros, como los augures romanos, al apreciar el servilismo con
que nos siguen... ¡Y luego no quieren reconocer nuestra superioridad!

Por primera vez Argensola aprobó con los ojos y el gesto las palabras de Hartrott. Exacto lo
que decía: el mundo era víctima de la «superstición alemana». Una cobardía intelectual, el
miedo al fuerte, hacía admirar todo lo de procedencia germánica, sin discernimiento alguno,
en bloque, por la intensidad del brillo: el oro revuelto con el talco. Los llamados latinos,
al entregarse á esta admiración, dudaban de las propias fuerzas con un pesimismo irracional.
Ellos eran los primeros en decretar su muerte. Y los orgullosos germanos no tenían mas que
repetir las palabras de estos pesimistas para afirmarse en la creencia de su superioridad.

Con el apasionamiento meridional, que salta sin gradación de un extremo á otro, muchos latinos
habían proclamado que en el mundo futuro no quedaba sitio para las sociedades latinas, en plena
agonía, añadiendo que sólo Alemania conservaba latentes las fuerzas civilizadoras. Los franceses,
que gritan entre ellos, incurriendo en las mayores exageraciones, sin darse cuenta de que hay
quien les escucha al otro lado de las puertas, habían repetido durante muchos años que Francia
estaba en plena descomposición y marchaba á la muerte. ¡Por qué se indignaban luego ante el
menosprecio de los enemigos!... ¡Cómo no habían de participar éstos de sus creencias!...

El profesor, interpretando erróneamente la aprobación muda de aquel joven que hasta entonces
le había escuchado con sonrisa hostil, añadió:

--Hora es ya de hacer en Francia el ensayo de la cultura alemana, implantándola como vencedores.

Aquí le interrumpió Argensola: «¿Y si la cultura alemana no existiese, como lo afirma un alemán
célebre?» Necesitaba contradecir á este pedante que los abrumaba con su orgullo. Hartrott casi
saltó de su asiento al escuchar tal duda.

--¿Qué alemán es ese?

--¡Nietzsche!

El profesor le miró con lástima. Nietzsche había dicho á los hombres: «Sed duros», afirmando
que «una buena guerra santifica toda causa». Había alabado á Bismarck; había, tomado parte
en la guerra del 70; había glorificado al alemán cuando hablaba del «león risueño» y de la
«fiera rubia». Pero Argensola le escuchó con la tranquilidad del que pisa un terreno seguro.
¡Oh tardes de plácida lectura junto á la chimenea del estudio, oyendo chocar la lluvia en los
vidrios del ventanal!...

--El filósofo ha dicho eso--contestó--y ha dicho otras cosas diferentes, como todos los que
piensan mucho. Su doctrina es de orgullo, pero de orgullo individual, no de orgullo de nación
ni de raza. El habló siempre contra «la mentirosa superchería de las razas».

Argensola recordaba palabra por palabra á su filósofo. Una cultura, según éste, era «la unidad
de estilo en todas las manifestaciones de la vida». La ciencia no supone cultura. Un gran saber
puede ir acompañado de una gran barbarie, por la ausencia de estilo ó la confusión caótica
de todos los estilos. Alemania, en opinión de Nietzsche, no tenía cultura propia por su carencia
de estilo. «Los franceses--había dicho--están á la cabeza de una cultura auténtica y fecunda,
sea cual sea su valor, y hasta el presente todos hemos tomado de ella.» Sus odios se concentraban
sobre su propio país. «No puedo soportar la vida en Alemania. El espíritu de servilismo y mezquinería
penetra por todas partes... Yo no creo mas que en la cultura francesa, y todo lo demás que
se llama Europa culta me parece una equivocación. Los raros casos de alta cultura que he encontrado
en Alemania eran de origen francés.»

--Ya sabe usted--continuó Argensola--que, al pelearse con Wágner por el exceso de germanismo
en su arte, proclamó la necesidad de mediterranizar en música. Su ideal fué una cultura para
toda Europa, pero con base latina.

Julius von Hartrott contestó desdeñosamente, repitiendo las mismas palabras del español. Los
hombres que piensan mucho dicen muchas cosas. Además, Nietzsche era un poeta que había muerto
en plena demencia, y no figuraba entre los sabios de la Universidad. Su fama la habían labrado
en el extranjero... Y no volvió á ocuparse más de aquel joven, como si se hubiese evaporado
después de sus atrevidas objeciones. Toda su atención la concentraba ahora en Desnoyers.

--Este país--continuó--lleva la muerte en sus entrañas. ¿Cómo dudar de que surgirá en él una
revolución apenas estalle la guerra?... Tú no has presenciado las agitaciones del bulevar con
motivo del proceso Cailloux. Reaccionarios y revolucionarios se han insultado hasta hace tres
días. Yo he visto cómo se desafiaban con gritos y cánticos, cómo se golpeaban en medio de la
calle. Y esta división de opiniones aún se acentuará más cuando nuestras tropas crucen las
fronteras. Será la guerra civil. Los antimilitaristas claman, creyendo que está en manos de
su gobierno el evitar el choque... ¡País degenerado por la democracia y por la inferioridad
de su celtismo triunfante, deseoso de todas las libertades!... Nosotros somos el único pueblo
libre de la tierra, porque sabemos obedecer.

La paradoja hizo sonreir á Julio. ¡Alemania único pueblo libre!...

--Así es--afirmó con energía von Hartrott--. Tenemos la libertad que conviene á un gran pueblo:
la libertad económica é intelectual.

--¿Y la libertad política?...

El profesor acogió esta pregunta con un gesto de menosprecio.

--¡La libertad política!... Únicamente los pueblos decadentes é ingobernables, las razas inferiores,
ansiosas de igualdad y confusión democrática, hablan de libertad política. Los alemanes no
la necesitamos. Somos un pueblo de amos, que reconoce las jerarquías y desea ser mandado por
los que nacieron superiores. Nosotros tenemos el genio de la organización.

Este era, según el doctor, el gran secreto alemán, y la raza germánica, al apoderarse del mundo,
haría partícipes á todos de su descubrimiento. Los pueblos quedarían organizados de modo que
el individuo diese el máximum de su rendimiento en favor de la sociedad. Los hombres regimentados
para toda clase de producciones, obedeciendo como máquinas á una dirección superior y dando
la mayor cantidad posible de trabajo: he aquí el estado perfecto. La libertad era una idea
puramente negativa si no iba acompañada de un concepto positivo que la hiciese útil.

Los dos amigos escucharon con asombro la descripción del porvenir que ofrecía al mundo la superioridad
germánica. Cada individuo sometido á una producción intensiva, lo mismo que un pedazo de huerta
del que desea sacar el dueño el mayor número de verduras... El hombre convertido en un mecanismo...
nada de operaciones inútiles que no proporcionan un resultado inmediato... ¡Y el pueblo que
proclamaba este ideal sombrío era el mismo de los filósofos y los soñadores, que habían dado
á la contemplación y la reflexión el primer lugar en su existencia!...

Hartrott volvió á insistir en la inferioridad de los enemigos de su raza. Para luchar se necesitaba
fe, una confianza inquebrantable en la superioridad de las propias fuerzas.

--A estas horas, en Berlín todos aceptan la guerra, todos creen seguro el triunfo, ¡mientras
que aquí!... No digo que los franceses sientan miedo. Tienen un pasado de bravura que los galvaniza
en ciertos momentos. Pero están tristes, se adivina que harían cualquier sacrificio por evitar
lo que se les viene encima. El pueblo gritará de entusiasmo en el primer instante, como grita
siempre que lo llevan á su perdición. Las clases superiores no tienen confianza en el porvenir;
callan ó mienten, pero en todos se adivina el presentimiento del desastre. Ayer hablé con tu
padre. Es francés y es rico. Se muestra indignado contra los gobiernos de su país porque le
comprometen en conflictos europeos por defender á pueblos lejanos y sin interés. Se queja de
los patriotas exaltados, que han mantenido abierto el abismo entre Alemania y Francia, impidiendo
una reconciliación. Dice que Alsacia y Lorena no valen lo que costará una guerra en hombres
y dinero... Reconoce nuestra grandeza: asegura que hemos progresado tan aprisa, que jamás podrán
alcanzarnos los demás pueblos... Y como tu padre piensan muchos otros: todos los que se hallan
satisfechos de su bienestar y temen perderlo. Créeme: un país que duda y teme la guerra, está
vencido antes de la primera batalla.

Julio mostró cierta inquietud, como si pretendiese cortar la conversación.

--Deja á mi padre. Hoy dice eso porque la guerra no es todavía un hecho, y él necesita contradecir,
indignarse con todo lo que se halla á su alcance. Mañana tal vez dirá lo contrario... Mi padre
es un latino.

El profesor miró su reloj. Debía marcharse: aún le quedaban muchas cosas que hacer antes de
dirigirse á la estación. Los alemanes establecidos en París habían huído en grandes bandas,
como si circulase entre ellos una orden secreta. Aquella tarde iban á partir los últimos que
aún se mantenían en la capital ostensiblemente.

--He venido á verte por afecto de familia, porque era mi deber darte un aviso. Tú eres extranjero
y nada te retiene aquí. Si deseas presenciar un gran acontecimiento histórico, quédate. Pero
mejor será que te marches. La guerra va á ser dura, muy dura, y si París intenta resistirse
como la otra vez, presenciaremos cosas terribles. Los medios ofensivos han cambiado mucho.

Desnoyers hizo un gesto de indiferencia.

--Lo mismo que tu padre--continuó el profesor--. Anoche, él y tu familia me contestaron de
igual modo. Hasta mi madre prefiere quedarse al lado de su hermana, diciendo que los alemanes
son muy buenos, muy civilizados y nada puede temerse de ellos cuando triunfen.

Al doctor parecía molestarle esta buena opinión.

--No se dan cuenta de lo que es la guerra moderna, ignoran que nuestros generales han estudiado
el arte de reducir al enemigo rápidamente y que lo emplearán con un método implacable. El terror
es el único medio, ya que perturba la inteligencia del contrario, paraliza su acción, pulveriza
su resistencia. Cuanto más feroz sea la guerra, más corta resultará: castigar con dureza es
proceder humanamente. Y Alemania va á ser cruel, con una crueldad nunca vista, para que no
se prolongue la lucha.

Había abandonado su asiento, requiriendo el bastón y el sombrero de paja. Argensola le miraba
con franca hostilidad. El profesor, al pasar junto á él, sólo hizo un rígido y desdeñoso movimiento
de cabeza.

Luego se dirigió hacia la puerta, acompañado por su primo. La despedida fué breve.

--Te repito mi consejo. Si no amas el peligro, márchate. Puede ser que me equivoque, y esta
gente, convencida de que su defensa resulta inútil, se entregue buenamente... De todos modos,
pronto nos veremos. Tendré el gusto de volver á París cuando la bandera del Imperio flote sobre
la torre Eiffel. Asunto de tres ó cuatro semanas. A principios de Septiembre, con seguridad.

Francia iba á desaparecer; para el doctor, era indudable su muerte.

--Quedará París--añadió--, quedarán los franceses, porque un pueblo no se suprime fácilmente;
pero ocuparán el lugar que les corresponde. Nosotros gobernaremos el mundo: ellos se cuidarán
de inventar modas, harán agradable la vida del extranjero que los visite, y en el terreno intelectual
les estimularemos para que eduquen actrices bonitas, produzcan novelas entretenidas y discurran
comedias graciosas... Nada más.

Desnoyers rió mientras estrechaba la mano de su primo, fingiendo tomar sus palabras como paradojas.

--Hablo en serio--continuó Hartrott--. La última hora de la República francesa como nación
importante ha sonado. La he visto de cerca, y no merece otra suerte. Desorden y falta de confianza
arriba; entusiasmo estéril abajo.

Al volver la cabeza vió otra vez la sonrisa de Argensola.

--Y nosotros entendemos un poco de esto--añadió agresivamente--. Estamos acostumbrados á examinar
los pueblos que fueron, á estudiarlos fibra por fibra, y podemos conocer con una sola ojeada
la psicología de los que aún viven.

El bohemio creyó ver á un cirujano hablando con suficiencia de los misterios de la voluntad
ante un cadáver. ¡Qué sabía de la vida este pedante interpretador de documentos muertos!...

Cuando se cerró la puerta fué al encuentro de su amigo, que volvía desalentado. Argensola ya
no tenía por loco al doctor Julius von Hartrott.

--¡Qué bruto!--exclamó levantando los brazos--. ¡Y pensar que viven sueltos estos fabricantes
de sombríos errores!... Quién diría que son de la misma tierra que produjo á Kant el pacifista,
al sereno Goethe, á Beethoven... Haber creído tantos años que formaban una nación de soñadores
y filósofos ocupados en trabajar desinteresadamente por todos los hombres...

La farsa de un geógrafo alemán revivió en su memoria como una explicación: «El germano es un
bicéfalo. Con una cabeza sueña y poetiza, mientras con la otra piensa y ejecuta.»

Desnoyers se mostraba desesperado por la certidumbre de la guerra. Este profesor le parecía
más temible que el consejero y los otros burgueses alemanes que había conocido en el buque.
Su tristeza no era únicamente por el pensamiento egoísta de que la catástrofe iba á estorbar
la realización de sus deseos y los de Margarita. Descubría de pronto, en esta hora de incertidumbre,
que amaba á Francia. Veía en ella la patria de su padre y el país de la gran Revolución...
El, aunque no se había mezclado nunca en las luchas de la política, era republicano y había
reído muchas veces de ciertos amigos suyos que adoraban á reyes y emperadores, considerando
esto como un signo de distinción.

Argensola pretendió reanimarle.

--¡Quién sabe! Este es un país de sorpresas. Al francés hay que verlo á la hora en que procura
remediar sus imprevisiones. Diga lo que diga el bárbaro de tu primo, hay entusiasmo, hay orden...
Peor que nosotros debieron verse los que vivían días antes de lo de Valmy. Todo desorganizado:
como única defensa, batallones de obreros y campesinos que por primera vez tomaban un fusil.
Y sin embargo, la Europa de las viejas monarquías no supo cómo librarse durante veinte años
de estos guerreros improvisados.

V

Donde aparecen los cuatro jinetes

Los dos amigos vivieron en los días siguientes una vida febril, considerablemente agrandada
por la rapidez con que se sucedían los acontecimientos. Cada hora engendraba una novedad--las
más de las veces falsa--, que removía la opinión con rudo vaivén. Tan pronto el peligro de
la guerra aparecía conjurado, como circulaba la voz de que la movilización iba á ordenarse
dentro de unos minutos.

Veinticuatro horas representaban las inquietudes, la ansiedad, el desgaste nervioso de un año
normal. Y lo que agravaba más esta situación era la incertidumbre, la espera del acontecimiento
temido y todavía invisible, la angustia por el peligro que nunca acaba de llegar.

La Historia se extendía desbordada fuera de sus cauces, sucediéndose los hechos como los oleajes
de una inundación. Austria declaraba la guerra á Servia, mientras los diplomáticos de las grandes
potencias seguían trabajando por evitar el conflicto. La red eléctrica tendida en torno del
planeta vibraba incesantemente en la profundidad de los océanos y sobre el relieve de los continentes,
transmitiendo esperanzas ó pesimismos. Rusia movilizaba una parte de su ejército. Alemania,
que tenía sus tropas prontas con pretexto de maniobras, decretaba el estado de «amenaza de
guerra». Los austriacos, sin aguardar las gestiones de la diplomacia, iniciaban el bombardeo
de Belgrado. Guillermo II, temiendo que la intervención de las potencias solucionase el conflicto
entre el zar y el emperador de Austria, forzaba el curso de los acontecimientos declarando
la guerra á Rusia. Luego, Alemania se aislaba, cortando las líneas férreas y las líneas telegráficas
para amasar en el misterio sus fuerzas de invasión.

Francia presenciaba esta avalancha de acontecimientos, sobria en palabras y manifestaciones
de entusiasmo. Una resolución fría y grave animaba á todos interiormente. Dos generaciones
habían venido al mundo recibiendo al abrir los ojos de la razón la imagen de una guerra que
forzosamente llegaría alguna vez. Nadie la deseaba: la imponían los adversarios... Pero todos
la aceptaban, con el firme propósito de cumplir su deber.

París callaba durante el día con el enfurruñamiento de sus preocupaciones. Sólo algunos grupos
de patriotas exaltados, siguiendo los tres colores de la bandera, pasaban por la plaza de la
Concordia para dar vivas ante la estatua de Estrasburgo. Las gentes se abordaban en las calles
amistosamente. Todos se conocían sin haberse visto nunca. Los ojos atraían á los ojos; las
sonrisas parecían engancharse mutuamente con la simpatía de una idea común. Las mujeres estaban
tristes, pero hablaban fuerte para ocultar sus emociones. En el largo crepúsculo de verano,
los bulevares se llenaban de gentío. Los barrios extremos confluían al centro de la ciudad,
como en los días ya remotos de las revoluciones. Se juntaban los grupos, formando una aglomeración
sin término, de la que surgían gritos y cánticos. Las manifestaciones pasaban por el centro,
bajo los faros eléctricos que acababan de inflamarse. El desfile se prolongaba hasta media
noche, y la bandera nacional aparecía sobre la muchedumbre andante escoltada por las banderas
de otros pueblos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09257</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>8983</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18173</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The country lacks
military spirit. We are a warrior people, and it will be easy to beat the English, weakened by a false
conception of life.

The doctor paused and added:

- We also have the internal corruption of our enemies, their lack of unity. God help us to sow confusion
in these hateful people. There will be many days without you see his hand. The revolution is
about to explode in France while the war.

The people Paris barricades in the streets, will play the anarchy
of the Commune.

Tunisia Algiers and other possessions are to revolt against France.

Argensola believed the case aggressively smiling with incredulity.

- I repeat - Hartrott insisted - that this country is going to know rpm and insurrection here in
their colonies. I know what I mean ... Russia will also be your inner revolution, revolution red
flag, forcing the tsar to ask grace to his knees.

You only have to read Recent newspaper strikes in St. Petersburg, demonstrations by strikers under
the pretext of the visit of President Poincare ... England will be rejected by the colonies requests
for support. India is to rise up against it and believes Egypt is time of empowerment.

July seemed impressed by these statements, made with a doctoral security.

Almost was angry with the unbeliever Argensola, still staring insolently and repeated Professor
eyes: "Are you crazy: crazy with pride."

The man must have serious reasons to make such prophecies of misfortune. His presence in Paris, so it
was inexplicable Desnoyers, gave his words a mysterious authority.

- But the nations will defend - he argued his cousin -. Do not be so easy victory as you think.

-
Yes, you will make. The fight is going to be tough.

It seems that in recent years France has been concerned of his army. Find some resistance,
the more difficult victory, but defeat ... You do not know how far
the offensive power of Germany.

Nobody knows for sure beyond its borders. If our enemies known in all its intensity, fall knees,
regardless of useless sacrifice.

There was a long silence. Julius von Hartrott seemed oblivious. The memory elements accumulated force
by race plunged him into a kind of mystical worship.

- The preliminary victory - he said suddenly - for some time that we have obtained. Our enemies
hate us, and yet we imitate. Everything bears the mark of Germany is sought in the world.
The same countries that try to resist our weapons to copy our methods in their universities
and admire our theories, even those who did not achieve success in Germany. Many times we laughed
with us, as the Roman augurs, in assessing the servility with we are ... And certainly do not
want to recognize our superiority!

Argensola first approved eye and gesture Hartrott words. Exactly what saying the world was a victim
of the "German superstition." Intellectual cowardice, the Fear the fort, was admiring all of Germanic
origin, without any discrimination, collectively, by the brightness, the gold mixed with the powder.
The so-called Latinos to give this admiration, they doubted their own strengths to irrational
pessimism. They were the first to order his death. And the proud Germans had no more than repeat
the words of these pessimistic to assert itself in the belief of their superiority.

With the passion southern jumping without gradation from one extreme to another, many Latinos
had proclaimed that in the future world there was no room for Latin
American societies, in full agony, adding that Germany remains latent
only the civilizing forces.

The French, they yell at each other, incurring the greatest exaggerations,
not realizing that there who listened to the other side of the doors
had been repeated for many years that France was in decay and marched
to death.

Why then are outraged at the contempt of enemies ... How they were not to participate in their
beliefs! ...

The teacher, misinterpreting the silent approval of the young man
who until then He had listened with hostile smile, added:

- The time
has come to trial in France on German culture, implanting it as victors.

Here

Argensola interrupted: "What if the German culture did not exist,
as stated by a German celebrity?

"I needed to contradict this pedantic that overwhelmed with pride. Hartrott almost jumped from
his seat to hear such a question.

- German What is this?

- Nietzsche!

The professor looked at him with pity. Nietzsche had said to the men: "Be tough," affirming that
"a good war hallows every cause."

Bismarck had praised them, had, taken part in the war of 70, had glorified the German when he
spoke of "laughing lion" and "Blond beast." But Argensola listened to the quiet of a safe ground
to tread. Oh peaceful afternoons reading by the fireplace in the study, listening to the rain
hitting the Glazed glasses! ...

- The philosopher said that - said - and says different things, like everyone think a lot. His doctrine
is pride, but of individual pride, not pride of nation or race. He spoke always against "the deceitful
trickery of the races."

Argensola remembered word for word to his philosopher.

A culture, as it was' unity style in every aspect of life. " Science is not culture. A great
learning can be accompanied by a great barbarity, the lack of style or chaotic confusion of
all styles.

Germany, according to Nietzsche, it had its own culture gap style. "The French - he said - are
at the head of an authentic culture and fruitful whatever its value, and to date all have taken
it. "His hatred was focused about their own country. "I can not bear to live in Germany. The spirit
of servility and mezquinería penetrates everywhere ... I do not think more than in French culture,
and everything else called educated Europe seems like a mistake.

The rare cases of high culture that I found in Germany were of French origin. "

- You know - continued Argensola - which, to quarrel with Wagner by excess Germanism in his art,
he proclaimed the need mediterranizar music. His ideal was a culture throughout Europe, but
Latin based.

Julius von Hartrott replied disdainfully, saying the same words in Spanish. The men who think
much say many things. Moreover, Nietzsche was a poet who had died in full dementia, and not among
the scholars of the university.

His fame had wrought abroad ... And not reoccupied most of the young,
as if he had evaporated After his daring objections.

All her attention now focused on Desnoyers.

- This country - continued - carries death in his gut.

How do I doubt that will arise in him revolution just war breaks out?

... You have not witnessed the upheavals of the boulevard Cailloux plea process. Reactionaries and revolutionaries
have been insulted for three days. I have seen how challenged with shouts and songs, how they
beat in the middle of street. And this division of opinion will be accentuated even more when
our troops crossing borders. It will be civil war.

Antimilitarists claim, believing that it is in the hands of his government to avoid the crash ...
Country degenerated democracy and inferiority its celtic triumphant, anxious of all freedoms!
... We are the only people free land, because we obey.

The paradox was smiling to July. Germany only free people! ...

- That's right - he said vigorously von Hartrott -. We have the freedom that befits a great nation: economic
and intellectual freedom.

- What political freedom? ...

The teacher greeted this question with a gesture of contempt.

- Political freedom!

... Only decadent peoples and unruly, the inferior races eager to equality and democratic confusion,
talk about political freedom. The Germans did not the need. We are a nation of masters, which recognizes
the hierarchy and want to be commanded by those born superior. We have the organizational genius.

This
was, according to the doctor, the great secret German and the Germanic race, to take over the
world, would involve all of its discovery. The villages would be organized so that give the individual
the maximum of performance for the company. Men regimented for all kinds of productions, obedient
as machines to a senior management and giving the maximum amount of work: this is the perfect
state. Freedom was an idea purely negative if it was accompanied by a positive concept were
that he should help.

The two friends listened with astonishment the description of the future that gave the world the
superiority Germanic. Each individual subject to intensive production, as well as a piece of garden
that you want to get the owner the highest number of vegetables ... The man turned into a mechanism
... no unnecessary operations that do not provide immediate results
... And the people that proclaimed this ideal was the same grim philosophers
and dreamers, who had given to contemplation and reflection first
in your life!

...

Hartrott returned to insist on the inferiority of the enemies of their race. To fight was necessary
faith, an unshakable confidence in the superiority of their own forces.

-
At this time, in Berlin all accept the war, all believe certain victory,
while here!

... I'm not saying that the French feel fear. Have a history of bravery that galvanizes at
certain times. But they are sad, they guess that would make any sacrifice to avoid what they
are coming. The people shall shout with excitement at the first moment her screaming whenever
they have to their doom.

The upper classes do not have confidence in the future; silent or lie, but they all guess the premonition
of disaster. Yesterday I spoke with your father. Is French and is rich. It shows his fury upon
the governments of his country because he engage in conflicts in Europe to defend remote villages
and uninteresting. He complains exalted patriots, who have kept open
the gap between Germany and France, preventing reconciliation.

Alsace and Lorraine says are not worth the cost in men war and money
... Acknowledges our greatness: it ensures that we have progressed
so fast, they can never reach other peoples ... And as your father
think many others: all those who are satisfied with their welfare
and are afraid to lose.

Believe me, a country that doubts and fears war is due before the first battle.

July showed some concern, as if to cut the conversation.

- Leave my father. Today he says that because the war is not yet a fact, and he needs to contradict
indignant with all that is within his reach. Tomorrow might tell you otherwise ... My father is
a Latino.

The professor looked at his watch. Should go: he still had many things to do before go to the
station.

The Germans established in Paris had fled in large flocks, circulate among them as a secret.
That evening were the last ones to depart still remained in the capital significantly.

- I came to see family affection, because it was my duty to give a
warning.

You are a foreigner and nothing holds you back here. If you want to witness a great historical
event, stay. But You'd better leave. The war is going to be hard, very hard, and if Paris tries
to resist as before, will witness terrible things. The offensive capabilities have changed dramatically.

Desnoyers
made a gesture of indifference.

- The same as your father - continued the professor -. Last night, he and I had answered your
family Similarly. Even my mother prefers to stay beside her sister, saying that the Germans are
very good, very civilized and nothing to be feared of them when they succeed.

The doctor seemed to resent this good opinion.

- They do not realize
what is modern war, know that our generals have studied the art of
reducing the enemy quickly and used it with a relentless approach.

Terror is the only means, disturbs the intelligence of the opponent,
paralyzing its action, powder resistance.

The more fierce as the war will be shorter, is heavily penalize proceed humanely. And Germany
is going to be cruel with a cruelty never seen, not to more protracted struggle.

He had left his seat, requiring a cane and straw hat.

I looked Argensola with hostility. The teacher, passing by him, only made a dismissive motion rigid
head.

Then he went to the door, accompanied by his cousin. The farewell was brief.

- I repeat my advice. If you do not love the danger, leave. I may be wrong, and this people,
convinced that his defense is useless, it delivers good ... Anyway,
soon we'll see.

I will be happy to return to Paris when the flag float over the Empire Eiffel Tower. Case of
three or four weeks. In early September, for sure.

France was about to disappear, for the doctor, was certain death.

- Left Paris - added - will the French, because a people is not easily
removed; but they take their rightful place.

We will rule the world: they will take care inventing fashion, make life pleasant abroad to
visit them, and in the intellectual field will encourage them to educate beautiful actresses,
produce entertaining novels and run funny comedy ... Nothing more.

Desnoyers laughed as he shook hands with his cousin, pretending to take his words as paradoxes.

-
I'm serious - continued Hartrott -. The last time the French Republic as a nation important
has sounded. I've seen up close, and does not deserve another chance. Disorder and lack of
confidence above; enthusiasm sterile below.

Turning his head he saw the smile again Argensola.

- And we understand a little of this - he said aggressively -. We are used to examine people
who were, to study fiber by fiber, and we can know at a glance the psychology of those still
living.

The Bohemian thought he saw a surgeon talking to sufficiency of the
mysteries of the will to a body.

What I knew of life this pedantic documents interpreter dead! ...

When the door was closed to meet his friend, who became discouraged. Argensola and was not
crazy to Dr. Julius von Hartrott.

- What a brute! - Said lifting the arms -. And to think that these producers live loose of dark
error ... Who would you say are of the same land that produced Kant, the pacifist, the serene Goethe,
Beethoven ... Many years have believed that they formed a nation
of dreamers and philosophers busy working unselfishly for all men
...

The farce of a German geographer revived in her memory as an
explanation: "The Germany is a two heads.

With a head dreams and poet, while the other thinks and running. "

Desnoyers showed desperate certainty of war. This teacher seemed more frightening than the counselor
and the other German bourgeoisie had met on the ship. His sadness was not only selfish thought that the
disaster was about to interfere carrying out their wishes and those of Margarita. Suddenly
discovered, at this time of uncertainty, I loved to France. She saw her father's homeland
and the country of the Great Revolution ... He, although there had never mixed in the struggles
of politics, a Republican and had some laughed many times to friends who adored kings and emperors,
considering this as a sign of distinction.

Argensola tried revive him.

- Who knows? This is a country of surprises. The Frenchman has to be seen at the time it seeks
remedy their lack of foresight. Whatever you say your cousin the Barbarian, no enthusiasm,
no order ... Worse than we had seen the living days ahead of Valmy. All Disorganized as the only
defense battalions of workers and peasants who first took a rifle.

And yet, the old monarchies of Europe did not know how to get out for twenty years of these warriors
improvised.

V

Which shows the four horsemen

The two friends lived in the days following a hectic life, considerably enlarged by the speed with
which events were happening. Every hour spawned a novelty - the More often false - that stirred
the harsh opinion sway. As soon as the danger of appeared averted war, and circulated the
word that the mobilization was ordered to within a few minutes.
Twenty-four hours represented the concerns, anxiety, nervous exhaustion
one year normal. And what the situation was worsened by the uncertainty,
the expected event feared and yet invisible, anxiety about the danger
never stops coming.

History overwhelmed stretched out their banks,
succeeding the facts as waves a flood. Austria declared war against
Serbia, while the diplomats of the great powers were still working
to avoid conflict. The stretched grid around the planet vibrating
incessantly in the deep ocean and on the relief of the continents,
providing hope or pessimism. Russia mobilized a portion of his army.
Germany he had his troops ready pretext of maneuvers, declared a state
of 'threat war. " The Austrians, without waiting for the efforts of
diplomacy, began the bombardment Belgrade. William II, fearing that
the intervention of the powers to resolve the conflict between the
Tsar and the Emperor of Austria, forcing the course of events by stating
war against Russia. Then, Germany was isolated by cutting the railroads
and telegraph lines dough in the mystery its invasion forces.

France
witnessed the avalanche of events, words and expressions sober enthusiasm.
A severe cold resolution encouraged all inside. Two generations had
come into the world getting to open the eyes of the reason the image
of a war inevitably would come. Nobody wanted: the imposing adversaries
... But all accepted it, with the firm intention of fulfilling their
duty.

Paris streets during the day sulking with their concerns. Only
a few groups exalted patriots, following the three colors of the flag,
passed by the square Concordia cheering before the statue of Strasbourg.
The people were addressed in the streets amicably. They all knew without
having ever seen. The eyes attracted the eyes, the smiles seemed to
catch each other on the sympathy of a common idea. Women were sad,
but spoke loud to hide his emotions. In the long twilight of summer
boulevards were filled with crowds. Converged to the outlying neighborhoods
of the city center, As the days and revolutions remote. Groups came
together to form an agglomeration without end, from which emerged
shouting and singing. The demonstrations went through the center under
the electric lights had just ignited. The parade runs through mid
night, and the national flag appeared on andante crowd escorted by
the flags of other peoples</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>