<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>72408</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>774</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Verde era su traje, que por lo fino debía de ser obra de unas arañas muy pulidas
que en los profundos senos de la tierra tejen con hebras de fuego. El séquito de Samdai era
tan vistoso y brillante que deslumbraba. Como le preguntara la Petra si no venía también Su
Majestad la Reina, quedose un momento parado el narrador, recordando, y al fin dio cuenta de
que vido también a la señora del Rey, pero con la cara muy tapada, como la luna entre nubes,
y por esta razón Mordejai no pudo distinguirla bien. La Soberana vestía de amarillo, de un
color así como nuestros pensamientos cuando estamos entre alegres y tristes. Expresaba esto
el ciego con dificultad, supliendo las torpezas de su lenguaje con el juego fisonómico de la
convicción, y los mohines y gestos elocuentes.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09815</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>263377</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>732</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Green was his costume, which was fine as being the work of a highly polished spiders
in the deep bosom of the earth woven with threads of fire. The entourage was Samdai so colorful
and bright dazzling. As I asked Petra if not also His coming Majesty the Queen, he remained
standing a moment the narrator, recalling, and finally realized which also saw Mrs. King, but
very stuffy face like the moon between clouds Mordechai and therefore could not distinguish
right. The Sovereign wore yellow, a color as well as our thoughts when we are between happy
and sad. Expressed this the blind with difficulty supplying the clumsiness of his language
with the physiognomy of the game conviction, and the grimaces and gestures speak volumes.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>