<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>265208</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22537</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Unas veces iba á ver cómo marchaban las reparaciones de su buque, excelente pretexto para descargar
en alguien su mal humor. Otras mañanas se dirigía al jardín de la ribera de Chiaia por los
mismos lugares que había pisado yendo con Freya. Esperaba verla aparecer de un momento á otro.
Todo lo que le rodeaba tenía algo de ella. Arboles y bancos, aceras y candelabros eléctricos,
la conocían perfectamente, por hallarse en su camino habitual.

Al convencerse de que esperaba en vano, una última ilusión le hacía volver los ojos hacia el
blanco palacio del Acuario.

Freya le había hablado de él. Con frecuencia se entretenía horas enteras contemplando la vida
de los seres marinos. Y Ferragut parpadeaba al pasar rápidamente del jardín caldeado por el
sol á la penumbra de unas galerías húmedas, sin otro alumbrado que el de la luz diurna descendida
al interior de los acuarios: luz que tomaba á través del agua y el cristal un tono misterioso,
el tinte verde y difuso de las profundidades submarinas.

Esta visita le hacía pasar el tiempo plácidamente. Surgían en su memoria antiguas lecturas,
afirmadas ahora por una visión directa. El no era de los marinos que navegan sin preocuparse
de lo que existe debajo de su quilla. Había querido conocer los misterios del inmenso palacio
azul por cuyo techo circulaba, dedicándose al estudio de la oceanografía, la más reciente de
las ciencias.

Al dar sus primeros pasos en el Acuario, se imaginaba inmediatamente la marina profundidad,
con las divisiones desiguales en que la ha fraccionado la exploración. Junto á las orillas
la zona llamada litoral, donde desembocan los ríos, se amontonan las substancias nutridoras
al impulso de mareas y corrientes y crecen las vegetaciones subacuáticas. Esta zona era la
de las grandes pescas, y llegaba hasta doscientos metros de fondo, profundidad en la que se
pierden los rayos del sol. Más allá cesaba la luz, desaparecían las plantas, y con ellas los
animales herbívoros.

La pendiente submarina, suave hasta este límite, se acentuaba, descendiendo rápidamente á los
abismos oceánicos, y esta parte del mar--la casi totalidad del Océano--, inmensa masa de agua
sin luz, sin olas, sin mareas, sin corrientes, sin oscilaciones de temperatura, era la llamada
zona abisal.

En el litoral, las aguas, saludablemente agitadas, cambiaban de salinidad según la cercanía
de los ríos. Las rocas y fondos se cubrían de una vegetación que era verde cerca de la superficie
y se iba ensombreciendo, hasta llegar al rojo obscuro y al amarillo bronce así como se alejaba
de la luz. En este paraíso oceánico, de aguas nutritivas y luminosas cargadas de bacterias
y alimentos microscópicos, se desarrollaba la vida con exuberancia. A pesar de los continuos
ataques del pescador, los rebaños marinos se mantenían incólumes por medio de una procreación
infinita.

La fauna de la profundidad abisal, donde la falta de luz hace imposible toda vegetación, era
forzosamente carnívora. Los habitantes débiles devoraban los residuos y los animales muertos
que descendían de la superficie. Los fuertes se nutrían á su vez con las substancias concentradas
de los pequeños carniceros.

El fondo del Océano, desierto monótono de barro ó de arena, producto de un sedimento de centenares
de siglos, ofrecía de tarde en tarde un oasis de extraña vegetación. Estos bosques surgían
como manchas de vida allí donde el encuentro de las corrientes superficiales hacía llover un
maná de diminutos cadáveres. Las plantas retorcidas y calcáreas, duras como la piedra, no eran
plantas: eran animales. Sus hojas, tentáculos inertes y traidores, se encogían de pronto. Sus
flores, bocas ávidas, se inclinaban sobre la presa, sorbiéndola por sus ventosas glotonas.

Una luz fantástica atravesaba con ráfagas multicolores este mundo de absoluta lobreguez. Era
luz animal, producida por los organismos vivientes.

En los abismos abisales resultaban muy contados los seres ciegos, contra la opinión del vulgo,
que se los imagina á casi todos faltos de ojos por su lejanía del sol. Los filamentos de los
árboles carnívoros eran guirnaldas de lámparas; los ojos de los animales cazadores, globos
eléctricos; las insignificantes bacterias, glándulas fotógenas; y todos ellos abrían ó cerraban
sus conmutadores fosforescentes según la necesidad del momento, unas veces para perseguir y
devorar, otras para mantenerse disimulados en las tinieblas.

Los animales-plantas, inmóviles como estrellas, rodeaban de un círculo de rayos sus bocas feroces,
y los seres minúsculos se sentían empujados irresistiblemente hacia ellos, lo mismo que las
mariposas vuelan hacia la lámpara y los pájaros de mar chocan con el faro.

Ninguna de las luces de la tierra podía compararse con las del mundo abisal. Todos los fuegos
de artificio palidecían ante las variedades del fulgor orgánico.

Las ramas vivientes del polípero, los ojos de las bestias, hasta el barro sembrado de puntos
brillantes, emitían chorros fosfóricos, haces de chispas cuyos resplandores se abrían y cerraban
incesantemente. Y estas luces iban pasando en su gradación por los más diversos colores: violeta,
púrpura, rojo anaranjado, azul, y, sobre todo, verde. Los pulpos gigantescos se iluminaban
al percibir la proximidad de una víctima como soles lívidos, moviendo sus brazos de mortífero
tirón.

Todos los seres abisales tenían el órgano de la vista enormemente desarrollado, para poder
captar hasta los más débiles rayos de luz. Muchos eran de ojos salientes y enormes. Otros los
tenían despegados del cuerpo, al final de dos tentáculos cilíndricos como telescopios.

Los que eran ciegos y no producían resplandor compensaban esta inferioridad con el desarrollo
de los órganos táctiles. Sus antenas y nadaderas se prolongaban desmesuradamente en la obscuridad.
Los filamentos de su cuerpo, largos pelos ricos en terminaciones nerviosas, distinguían instantáneamente
la presa apetecida ó el enemigo en acecho.

El abismo abisal tenía dos pisos ó techumbres. En lo más alto estaba la llamada zona nerítica,
la superficie oceánica, diáfana y luminosa, lejos de toda costa. A continuación venía la zona
pelágica, mucho más profunda, en la que residen los peces de incesante movimiento, capaces
de vivir sin reposarse en el fondo.

Los cadáveres de los animales neríticos y de los que nadan entre dos aguas eran el sustento
directo é indirecto de la fauna abisal. Los seres de frágil dentadura y escasa velocidad, mal
armados para la conquista de las presas vivas, se alimentaban con las gotas de esta lluvia
de materia alimenticia. Los grandes nadadores, pertrechados de mandíbulas formidables y estómagos
elásticos é inmensos, preferían las peripecias de la lucha, las persecuciones de la caza viviente,
y devoraban--como devoran en la tierra los carnívoros á los herbívoros--á todos los pequeños
comedores de residuos y de plancton.

Esta palabra, de invención científica reciente, hacía ver al capitán Ferragut el más humilde
é interesante de todos los personajes del Océano. El plancton es la vida que flota en grumos
sueltos ó formando nubes á través de la superficie nerítica, descendiendo hasta las profundidades
abisales.

Allá donde iba el plancton iba la animación viviente, agrupándose en apretadas colonias animales.
El agua salada más pura y diáfana mostraba bajo ciertos rayos luminosos una multitud de pequeños
cuerpos, inquietos como las espirales de polvo que danzan en un rayo de sol. Estos seres transparentes,
revueltos con algas microscópicas y mucosidades embrionarias, eran el plancton. En su masa
densa y poco visible para el ojo humano flotaban los sifonóforos, guirnaldas de individuos
unidos por un hilo transparente, frágiles, delicados y luminosos como cristales de Bohemia.
Otros organismos igualmente sutiles tenían la forma de pequeños torpedos de vidrio. La suma
de todas las materias albuminúricas flotantes en el mar se condensaba en estas nubes nutritivas,
añadiéndose á ellas las secreciones de los animales vivientes, los residuos de sus cadáveres,
los cuerpos arrastrados por los ríos, las briznas alimenticias de los prados de algas.

Cuando el plancton, á impulsos del azar ó siguiendo misteriosas atracciones se iba aglomerando
en un punto determinado del litoral, las aguas hervían en peces con asombrosa fecundidad. Las
poblaciones ribereñas se agrandaban, el mar se llenaba de velas, las mesas eran más opulentas,
surgían industrias, se abrían fábricas y circulaba el dinero en la costa, atraído del interior
por el comercio de pesquería y de conservas.

Si se retiraba el plancton caprichosamente, bogando hacia otro litoral, los rebaños marinos
emigraban detrás de las praderas vivientes y la llanura azul quedaba vacía como un desierto
maldito. Las flotas de barcas permanecían en seco, se cerraban los talleres, ya no humeaba
la olla, los caballos de la gendarmería cargaban contra la muchedumbre protestante y famélica,
la oposición gritaba en las Cámaras y los periódicos hacían responsable de todo al gobierno.

Este polvo animal y vegetal nutría á las especies más numerosas, para que ellas á su vez sirviesen
de pasto á los grandes nadadores armados de dientes.

La ballena, el más voluminoso de los habitantes oceánicos, cerraba este ciclo destructor en
el que se devoran unos á otros para vivir. El gigante pacífico y sin dientes mantenía su organismo
sólo con plancton, absorbiéndolo á toneladas. El maná imperceptible y cristalino alimentaba
su cuerpo de campanario tumbado, haciendo circular bajo la piel grasosa ríos purpúreos de sangre
caliente.

La transparencia de los seres planctónicos evocaba en la memoria de Ferragut las coloraciones
maravillosas de los habitantes del mar, ajustadas exactamente á las necesidades de su conservación.
Las especies que viven en la superficie tenían, por lo general, el lomo azul y el vientre plateado.
De este modo les era posible escapar á la vista de los enemigos. Su color claro, visto desde
las tinieblas de la profundidad, se confundía con la lámina blanca y luminosa de la superficie.
Las sardinas, que nadan en bancos, podían pasar inadvertidas gracias á sus lomos azules como
el agua, librándose así de los peces y los pájaros que las dan caza.

Viviendo en abismos donde la luz no penetra nunca, los animales pelágicos ignoraban la necesidad
de ser transparentes ó azules como los seres neríticos de la superficie. Unos eran opacos é
incoloros, otros bronceados y negros; los más se revestían con tintas soberbias, cuyo esplendor
desesperaba á los pinceles humanos, incapaces de imitarlas. Un rojo magnífico era la base de
esta coloración, descendiendo gradualmente al rosa pálido, al violeta, al ámbar, hasta perderse
en el lácteo iris de las perlas y la policromía temblona y vagorosa del nácar de los moluscos.
Los ojos de ciertos peces, colocados al final de varillas separadas del cuerpo, brillaban como
diamantes en los extremos de un doble alfiler. Las glándulas salientes, las verrugas, las sinuosidades
dorsales, tomaban coloraciones de joyería.

Pero las piedras preciosas de la tierra son minerales muertos que necesitan el rayo de luz
para existir con breve chisporroteo. Las alhajas animadas del Océano, peces y corales, brillaban
con colores propios que eran reflejos de su vitalidad. Su verde, su rosado, su amarillo intenso,
sus iris metálicos, tintas jugosas eternamente barnizadas por un charol húmedo, no podían subsistir
en el mundo atmosférico.

Algunos de estos seres eran capaces de un poderoso mimetismo que les hacía confundirse con
los objetos inanimados ó pasar en pocos momentos por toda la gama de colores. Unos, de nerviosa
actividad, se inmovilizaban y encogían, llenándose de rugosidades, tomando el tono obscuro
de las rocas. Otros, en momentos de irritación ó de fiebre amorosa, se cubrían de rayas y temblonas
manchas, extendiéndose por su epidermis nubes diversas con cada uno de sus estremecimientos.
Las sepias y calamares, al verse perseguidos, se hacían invisibles dentro de una nube, lo mismo
que los encantadores de los libros de caballerías, enturbiando el agua con la tinta almacenada
en sus glándulas.

Ferragut iba avanzando entre las dos filas de estanques verticales del Acuario, escaparates
de rocas con un grueso vidrio que dejaba á la vista todo su interior. Estos dos muros claros
y luminosos, que recibían el fuego del sol por su parte alta, esparcían un reflejo verde en
la penumbra de los corredores. Al circular, los visitantes tomaban una palidez lívida, como
si marchasen por un desfiladero submarino.

El agua tranquila de los estanques apenas era visible. Detrás de los vidrios sólo parecía existir
una atmósfera maravillosa, un ambiente de sueño, en el que subían y bajaban flotantes seres
de colores. Las burbujas de su respiración era lo único que delataba la presencia del líquido.
En la parte superior de estas jaulas acuáticas, la atmósfera luminosa se estremecía bajo un
chorro continuo de polvo transparente. Era agua de mar con aire inyectado, que renovaba las
condiciones de existencia de los huéspedes del Acuario.

Viendo el capitán estas mangas vivificantes, admiró la fuerza nutridora del agua azul sobre
la que había transcurrido casi toda su existencia.

La tierra perdía sus orgullos al ser comparada con la inmensidad acuática. En el Océano habían
apuntado las primeras manifestaciones de la vida, continuando luego su ciclo evolutivo sobre
las montañas, surgidas igualmente de su seno. Si la tierra era la madre del hombre, el mar
era su abuela.

El número de los animales terrestres resultaba insignificante comparado con el de los marítimos.
Sobre la tierra--mucho más pequeña que el Océano--, los seres sólo ocupan la superficie del
suelo y una capa atmosférica de unos cuantos metros. Las aves y los insectos rara vez van más
allá en sus vuelos. En el mar, los animales están dispersados en todos los niveles de su espesor,
pudiendo disponer de muchos kilómetros de profundidad, multiplicados por miles y miles de leguas
de extensión. Cantidades infinitas de seres que escapan á todo cálculo nadan incesantemente
en todos los pisos de sus aguas. La tierra es una superficie, un plano, y el mar es un volumen.

La inmensa masa acuática--tres veces más salada que al nacer el planeta, á causa de una evaporación
milenaria que había disminuido el líquido sin absorber sus componentes--guardaba, revueltos
con sus cloruros, el cobre, el níquel, el hierro, el cinc, el plomo, y hasta el oro procedente
de los filones que la ebullición planetaria aglomeró en el fondo oceánico, y de cuya masa no
son mas que insignificantes tentáculos los filones de las montañas, con sus arenas auríferas
arrastradas por los ríos.

También la plata estaba disuelta en sus aguas. Ferragut sabía por ciertos cálculos que con
la plata flotante en el Océano podían levantarse pirámides más enormes que las de Egipto.

Los hombres que habían pensado en la explotación de estas riquezas minerales desistían de su
quimera. Estaban tan diluidas, que era imposible su aprovechamiento. Los seres oceánicos sabían
reconocer mejor su presencia, filtrándolas á través de su cuerpo para la renovación y coloración
de sus órganos. El cobre lo acumulaban en su sangre; el oro y la plata se descubrían en los
tejidos de los animales-plantas; el fósforo era absorbido por las esponjas; el plomo y el cinc,
por los fucos.

Todos podían extraer del agua los residuos de unos metales disueltos en fragmentos tan imponderablemente
pequeños, que ningún procedimiento químico alcanzaba á captarlos. Los carbonatos de cal arrastrados
por los ríos ó arrancados á las costas servían á innumerables especies para la construcción
de sus caparazones, esqueletos, conchas y caracolas. Los corales, filtrando el agua á través
de sus cuerpos blanduchos y mucosos, solidificaban sus duros esqueletos, para convertirse al
final en islas habitables.

Los seres de una diversidad desconcertante que flotaban, rampaban ó coleaban en torno de Ferragut
no eran mas que agua oceánica. Los peces, agua hecha carne; los animales mucosos, agua en estado
de gelatina; los crustáceos y los políperos, agua transformada en piedra.

Contempló en uno de los estanques un paisaje que parecía de otro planeta, grandioso y reducido
al mismo tiempo, como un bosque visto en un diorama. Era un palmeral surgiendo entre rocas;
pero las rocas no pasaban de ser guijarros, y las palmeras anélidos de mar, simples gusanos
que se mantenían en vertical inmovilidad.

Guardaban su cuerpo anillado dentro de un tubo coriáceo que los protegía, y sobre este tronco
rectilíneo de color de marfil lanzaban, como un surtidor de ramas, los tentáculos movedizos
que les sirven para respirar y para comer.

Dotados de una rara sensibilidad, bastaba el paso de una nube ante el sol para que se contrajesen
en el interior de los tubos, quedando éstos sin su vistoso capitel, como palmeras desmochadas.
Luego, lenta y prudentemente, iban surgiendo otra vez los animados pinceles por la abertura
de sus vainas, flotando en el agua con ansiosa espera. Todos estos árboles y flores-animales
eran de una voracidad mecánica cuando la víctima microscópica se dejaba atraer por sus tentáculos
El suave ramaje se contraía, se cerraba, arrastrando á la esbelta torre secretada por él mismo,
digería su conquista.

Otros estanques atrajeron después la atención del marino.

Deslizándose sobre las rocas, introduciéndose en las cavernas, dormitando medio enterrada en
la arena, toda la varia y tumultuosa nación de los crustáceos movía sus herramientas cortantes
y tentaculares, hacía brillar sus armaduras japonesas, unas teñidas de rojo casi negro, como
si guardasen la sangre seca de un lejano combate, otras de fresca escarlata, lo mismo que si
reflejaran en su dureza los primeros fuegos de la aurora.

El fiero bogavante--el homard, soberano de las ricas mesas--descansaba sobre las tijeras de
sus patas anteriores, arma poderosa como una doble hacha de combate. La langosta saltaba con
agilidad por las peñas valiéndose de los ganchos de sus patas, herramientas de guerra y de
nutrición. Su próximo pariente la cigarra de mar, animal torpe y pesado, permanecía en los
rincones, cubierta de fango y de algas, en una inmovilidad que le hacía confundirse con las
piedras. Y en torno de estos gigantes, como una democracia roja acostumbrada á sufrir de vez
en cuando el ataque de los fuertes, nadaban los enjambres de langostinos y camarones. Sus movimientos
eran sueltos y graciosos, su sensibilidad tan afinada, que la menor agitación les hacía dar
saltos enormes.

Ulises pensó en la esclavitud que había impuesto la Naturaleza á estos animales dándoles su
hermosa envoltura defensiva.

Nacían acorazados, y el crecimiento les obligaba repetidas veces á cambiar de armadura. Mudaban
de piel, como los reptiles; pero éstos, al ser cilíndricos, podían ejecutar la operación con
la misma facilidad que una pierna que abandona su media. Los crustáceos habían de sacar de
su coraza, que empezaba á rajarse, el múltiple mecanismo de sus miembros y sus apéndices: las
patas, las antenas, las gruesas pinzas, operación lenta y peligrosa, en la que muchos parecían
rasgados por su propio esfuerzo. Luego, desnudos é inermes, habían de esperar á que se formase
una nueva piel que á su vez se convirtiese en armadura. Y esto en medio de un ambiente hostil,
rodeados de ávidas bestias, grandes y pequeñas, que sentían la atracción de su rica carne,
y sin otra defensa que el ocultamiento.

Entre el hormiguero de pequeños crustáceos que se movían en el fondo arenoso, cazando, comiendo
ó batiéndose con feroz enredijo de patas, buscaban los observadores á un ser bizarro y extravagante,
el paguro, apodado Bernardo el Eremita. Era una caracola que avanzaba recta como una torre
sobre unas patas de cangrejo, teniendo por corona la cabellera de una anémona de mar.

La cómica aparición estaba compuesta de tres animales distintos, uno sobre otro, ó más bien,
de dos seres vivientes llevando en medio un féretro. El paguro nacía con la parte posterior
desprovista de coraza: un excelente bocado, tierno y sabroso, para los peces hambrientos. La
necesidad de defenderse le hacía buscar una caracola para guardar la parte débil de su organismo.
Si encontraba vacía una vivienda de esta especie, se la apropiaba. De no ser así, se comía
al habitante, introduciendo después en el nacarado refugio su posterior, armado de dos patas
ganchudas.

No bastaban al débil paguro sus precauciones defensivas. Necesitaba ser ofensivo para vivir;
inspirar respeto á los monstruos devoradores, especialmente á los pulpos, que buscaban la presa
de su busto y sus patas peludas, asomadas por la locomoción fuera de la torre.

Una anémona de mar venía á fijarse en la cúspide calcárea: á veces llegaban á ser cinco ó seis.
Ninguna relación corporal existía entre el paguro y los organismos de arriba. Eran simples
socios, por un interés recíproco. Los animales-plantas picaban como ortigas; todos los monstruos
sin coraza huían del veneno de sus órganos urticantes; las briznas de su cabellera quemaban
como alfileres de fuego. De este modo, el humilde paguro inspiraba terror á las fieras gigantescas
de la profundidad, llevando sobre el dorso su torre coronada de formidables baterías. Las anémonas,
por su parte, le agradecían que las pasease incesantemente de un lado á otro, poniéndolas en
contacto con toda clase de animales. Podían comer así con más facilidad que sus hermanas fijas
en la roca. No tenían que esperar, como ellas, que el alimento viniese casualmente á sus tentáculos.
Además, siempre flotaban hasta sus alturas algunos despojos de las presas que hacía por abajo
el cangrejo socarrón en su errabunda impunidad.

Ferragut, al pasar de un estanque á otro, establecía mentalmente la gradación de los diversos
órdenes de la fauna marítima, desde el boceto primitivo al organismo perfecto.

Las esponjas del Mediterráneo nadaban en los primeros días de su nacimiento--cuando eran como
cabezas de alfiler--con movimientos vibrátiles. Luego permanecían inmóviles, filtrando el agua
por las celdas y corredores de sus tejidos, protegiendo su carne suave con un erizamiento de
espículas, agujas calcáreas y picantes, con las que ensartaban é inmovilizaban á los peces,
sirviéndolas de alimento sus residuos en putrefacción.

Desplegaban por millares las ortigas de mar sus hilos urticantes, proyectando un veneno que
aturdía á la víctima y la hacía caer en su corola, boca y ano al mismo tiempo. De una voracidad
sin límites, se apoderaban, fijas en su roca, de pescados más grandes que ellas, y al presentir
un peligro se encogían de tal modo, que era difícil verlas. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01154</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>384530</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19250</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Sometimes going to see how marching repairs to your ship, excellent excuse for download in someone's
bad mood. Other morning she went into the garden on the banks of Chiaia by same places that
had stepped up going with Freya. Expected her to appear at any moment. All around him was something
about her. Trees and benches, sidewalks and electric chandeliers, knew it perfectly well, for
being in the usual way.

To be convinced that waited in vain one last illusion made him turn
his eyes toward the Aquarium white palace.

Freya had told him. Often entertained for hours contemplating life of marine life. And Ferragut blinked
rapidly passing the heated garden sunshine to the gloom of a wet galleries, no other lights than
the lowered daylight inside the aquarium, took to light through the
glass of water and a mysterious tone, green dye and diffuse the deep
sea.

This visit made him pass the time pleasantly. Arose in his old memory readings now asserted by
direct vision. He was not sailing the sea without worrying of what exists below the keel. He
had wanted to know the mysteries of the vast palace The ceiling blue
circulated, dedicated to the study of oceanography, the most recent
science.

To take their first steps in the Aquarium, the Navy immediately imagined depth with unequal
divisions that have split the scan. Along the shores called littoral zone, where rivers flow,
crowd nurturer substances the pulse of tides and currents and underwater vegetation grow. This
area was of the great catches, and reached two hundred meters deep, depth at which lost sun.
Beyond the light stopped, the plants disappeared, and with them herbivores.

The

submarine slope, soft to this limit, stressed, descending rapidly to the ocean depths, and this
part of the sea - almost all of the ocean - vast body of water no lights, no waves, no tides,
no currents, no oscillations of temperature, was the call abyssal plain.

On the coast, water, waved, salinity changed depending on the distance rivers. The rocks and
funds were covered with green vegetation that was near the surface and would cast a shadow, until
the dark red and yellow bronze and walked away light. In this ocean paradise, nutrients and light
water bacteria-laden Food and microscopic life unfolded with exuberance. Despite continuous
attacks fisherman, marine herds remained intact through procreation infinite.

The fauna of the abyssal depths, where the lack of light makes it
impossible for all vegetation was necessarily carnivorous.

The weak people devoured the waste and dead animals descended from the surface. The strong turn
nourished with concentrated substances small butchers.

The bottom of the ocean, monotonous desert sand or clay, the product
of sediment hundreds centuries, offered from time to time an oasis
of rare vegetation.

These forests arose Life as spots where the surface currents meeting rained a mana of tiny corpses.
Twisted plants and limestone, hard as stone, were not plants: they were animals. Its leaves,
tentacles inert and traitors, suddenly shrank. Its flowers, hungry mouths, bent over the dam,
sipping their greedy suckers.

A fantastic light passing through this world with colorful bursts
of utter gloom.

Was animal light produced by living organisms.

In the abyssal depths were very few blind beings, against the opinion of the vulgar, imagines that
almost all eyes lacking their distance from the sun. The filaments of the carnivorous trees
were garlands of lamps, the eyes of hunting animals, balloons electric; the insignificant
bacteria, photogenic glands, and they all opened or closed their fluorescent switches according
to need of the hour, sometimes to pursue and eat, others to remain hidden in the darkness.

Animals,
plants, immobile as stars, surrounded by a circle of their mouths
fierce rays, and the tiny beings irresistibly felt pushed toward them,
the same as butterflies flying towards the lamp and sea birds collide
with the beacon.

None of the lights of the earth could be compared to the nether world.

All fires artifice paled before the splendor of organic varieties.

Polypary living branches of the eyes of the beasts, until the mud strewn with items bright jets
emitted phosphoric sparks beams whose splendors opened and closed incessantly. And these lights
were going in degree for many different colors: purple, purple, red, orange, blue and especially
green. The giant octopus lit to sense the proximity of a victim and soles livid, waving his
arms deadly hitch.

All deep-sea creatures were the organ of sight enormously developed in order to capture even
the weakest rays of light. Many were bulging eyes and huge. Others were detached from the body,
at the end of two tentacles cylindrical like telescopes.

Those who were blind and did not produce glare offset this inferiority development tactile organ. Their
antennae and fins, were prolonged beyond measure in the dark. The strands of her body, long hair rich in
nerve endings, instantly distinguished coveted prey or the enemy
in ambush.

The abyss abyssal had two floors or roofs. At the top was the so-called neritic the ocean surface,
clear and bright, far from any coast.

Next came the area pelagic, much deeper, in which fish reside incessant movement, capable to
live without resting in the background.

The carcasses of animals that neritic and swim between two waters were a living direct and indirect
impacts of abyssal fauna. Fragile beings teeth and slow speed, poor armed for the conquest of the
live prey, fed with drops of rain food material. The great swimmers, armed with formidable jaws
and stomachs elastic and immense, they preferred the vicissitudes
of the struggle, persecution of hunting living and devour - devour
the earth and carnivores to herbivores - to all small and waste-eating
plankton.

This word, recent scientific invention, to Captain Ferragut was the most humble and interesting of
all the characters of the ocean.

Plankton is the life that floats in clumps loose or forming clouds through the neritic area, descending
to the depths abyssal.

Wherever he went was the animation plankton living animals grouped in tight colonies. Salt
water pure and clear under certain light rays showed numerous small bodies, restless as the
spirals of dust dancing in a sunbeam. These transparent beings, microscopic algae mixed with
embryonic mucus were plankton. In its mass dense and less visible to the naked eye floating
siphonophores, garlands of individuals united by a transparent thread, fragile, delicate and bright
as Bohemian crystal. Other agencies were also subtle form of small glass torpedoes. The sum of
all the materials floating on the sea albuminurie condensed in these
clouds nutritious adding to them the living animal secretions, waste
of their bodies bodies dragged through the rivers, the blades of grass
eating algae.

When the plankton, to random impulses or following mysterious attractions crowding would at some
point along the coast, fish boiled in water with amazing fertility. The coastal populations are
growing larger, the sea was filled with candles, the tables were
more affluent industries arose, opened factories and money circulating
in the sea, drawn inside by trade in fishery and canning.

If capriciously withdrew plankton, paddling to another coastal marine herds migrated behind
the living meadows and blue plain was empty as a desert damn. Fleets of boats remained dry, closed
shops, no longer smoked the pot, the horses of the gendarmerie charged
into the crowd Protestant and starving, shouted opposition in the
Chambers and the newspapers were responsible for everything the government.

This

powder fed to animal and plant species more numerous, so they in turn served grass to the great swimmers
armed with teeth.

The whale, the most voluminous of the ocean inhabitants, closed this destructive cycle in which devour
one another to live. The peaceful and toothless giant kept his body only plankton, absorbing
tons. Imperceptible and crystal manna fed his body lay tower, circulating under the oily purple
rivers of blood hot.

The transparency of planktonic creatures evoked the memory of the colors Ferragut wonderful inhabitants
of the sea, exactly adjusted to the needs of conservation. The species living in the area were,
in general, blue back and silver belly. In this way they could escape the sight of the enemy. Its
light color, as seen from the depth of darkness, mingled with bright white sheet surface. Sardines
swimming in banks, could go unnoticed thanks to their backs and blue
water, being freed from the fish and birds that hunt.

Living at depths where light never penetrates, pelagic animals ignored the need be transparent or
blue as the surface neritic beings. Some were opaque and colorless, other tan and black, were
of the most superb die, whose splendor human brushes desperate, unable to imitate. A gorgeous red
was the basis of this coloration, gradually descending to pale pink, violet, amber, to miss in
the iris of pearl milk and polychrome vagorosa trembling and nacre of molluscs. The eyes of certain
fish, placed at the end of rods separated from the body, glowing like diamonds on the ends of a double
pin. Outgoing glands, warts, the windings dorsal coloration took
jewelry.

But precious minerals on earth are dead they need the light beam to exist at short sputtering. The
animated jewels of the ocean, fish and coral, glowed own colors that were reflections of their vitality.
Its green, its pink, its bright yellow, their iris metallic inks
forever juicy wet painted by a patent, could not survive in the atmospheric
world.

Some of these beings were capable of a powerful mimicry that made them confused with inanimate
objects, or spend a few moments for the full range of colors. Some, of nervous activity, was immobilized
and cowering, filled with rough, taking the pitch dark rocks. Others in anger or love fever,
were covered with stripes and trembling spots, spreading his clouds epidermis different with each
of their tremors. Cuttlefish and squid, to be pursued, were made invisible in a cloud, as The
charming books of chivalry, muddying the water with the ink stored
in their glands.

Ferragut was moving between the two vertical rows of tanks of the Aquarium, showcases rocks
with a thick glass that left everything in sight inside. These two clear walls and bright,
they received fire from the sun by the upper part, scattered green
mirror the shadows of the corridors.

When driving, the visitors took a livid pallor, and if they went for a submarine canyon.

The calm water of the ponds was barely visible. Behind the glass seemed to exist only a wonderful
atmosphere, a sleep environment, which beings floating up and down color. Bubbles his breath
was all that betrayed the presence of liquid. On top of these cages water, the luminous atmosphere
was shocked by a steady stream of transparent powder.

Seawater was injected air, which renewed the conditions of existence of Aquarium guests.

Viewing these sleeves exhilarating master, admired the blue water force on nurturer he had spent
most of its existence.

The land lost its pride when compared with the vast water.

In the ocean had pointed the first signs of life, then continuing on its evolutionary cycle the
mountains, also emerged from their midst. If the earth was the mother of the man, the sea was
her grandmother.

The number of land animals was negligible compared with that of the sea. On the ground - much smaller
than the ocean - beings occupy only the surface soil and atmospheric layer a few meters. Birds
and insects rarely go back in their flights.

At sea, the animals are scattered at all levels of its thickness, may have many miles deep, multiplied
by thousands and thousands of miles extension. Infinite number of beings beyond all calculation
to swim continuously on every floor of its waters. The earth is a surface, a plane, and the sea
is a volume.

The vast mass of water - three times saltier than the birth of the
planet, owing to evaporation millennial declined without absorbing
liquid components - keeping, scrambled with chlorides, copper, nickel,
iron, zinc, lead, and even the gold from of reefs to global boiling
agglomerated on the ocean floor, and mass not are more than minor
veins tentacles the mountain, with its gold-bearing sands carried
by rivers.

Silver was also dissolved in the water. Ferragut knew for certain calculations that silver floating
in the ocean could rise to the enormous pyramids of Egypt.

The men who had thought about the exploitation of these mineral riches were withdrawing their
chimera. Were so diluted that it was impossible to use. Knew ocean beings better recognize its
presence, filtering it through your body to renew and coloring their
bodies.

Copper accumulated in his blood, the gold and silver were discovered in tissues of animals, plants, the
phosphorus was absorbed by the sponges, lead and zinc, by wrack.

All were removed from the waste water of some dissolved metal fragments as imponderably small,
that no chemical process quite grasp. Washed lime carbonates torn by rivers to the coast or
to many species were used for construction of their shells, skeletons,
shells and conch.

Corals, filtering water through their flabby bodies and mucous, solidified their hard skeletons,
to convert to final habitable islands.

Beings floating bewildering diversity, ramp or around Ferragut coleaban were nothing more than
ocean water. Fish, water made flesh, and the animals mucous, water as gelatin; polyphenos crustaceans
and water, transformed into stone.

Looked at one of the ponds a landscape that seemed from another planet, great and small at the
same time, like a forest seen in a diorama. It was a palm emerging among rocks; but the rocks
were merely pebbles, and sea palm annelids, simple worms that were
kept in vertical immobility.

Her body kept ringing in a leathery tube that protected them, and this trunk rectilinear throwing
ivory color, as a supplier of arms, tentacles shifting which allow them to breathe and eat.

Gifted
with a rare sensitivity, sufficient passage of a cloud with the sun to contrajesen inside the tubes,
leaving them without their colorful capital, such as palms lopped. Then slowly and cautiously,
they arose again the brush through the opening animated its pods,
floating in the water with eager anticipation.

All these trees and flowers, animals was a voracious microscopic
mechanical when the victim was left by its tentacles to attract The
contorted branches smooth, closed, pulling the slender tower secreted
by himself, digested conquest.

Other ponds attracted attention after the seaman.

Slipping on rocks, introduced in caves, half buried in slumber sand,
all the various and tumultuous nation of crustaceans moving their
cutting tools and tentacular Japanese armor shone, a dyed red almost
black, as if you keep the dried blood from a distant combat, others
in fresh scarlet, the same as if reflected in its hardness the first
fires of dawn.

The fiery lobster - the homard, ruler of the rich tables - rested on the scissors their forelegs,
powerful weapon as a double battle-ax. The locust jump with agility on the rocks using the
hooks on their legs, tools of war and nutrition. His nearest relative sea cicada, animal clumsy
and slow, remained in corners, covered with mud and seaweed, in a stillness that made him confused
with stones. And around these giants, red as a democracy used to suffer from time then the attack of
the strong, swimming swarms of shrimp and prawns. Their movements were loose and funny, so
refined sensitivity that the slightest agitation made them give huge
jumps.

Ulysses thought slavery had imposed nature of these animals showed them beautiful defensive shell.

Battleships
were born, and growth were forced repeatedly to change armor. Moved Leather, like reptiles,
but these, being cylindrical, could perform the operation as easily as a leg that leaves the
media. Crustaceans were to draw from its shell, which was beginning to crack, the multiple mechanisms
of its members and its appendages: the legs, antennae, thick claws, slow and dangerous operation,
which many seemed torn by their own efforts. Then, naked and helpless, had expected to be formed
a new skin to turn from becoming armor. And this in the midst of a hostile environment surrounded
by hungry beasts, large and small, who felt the pull of its rich meat and no other defense
that the concealment.

Among the swarm of small crustaceans that moved in the sand, hunting, feeding or fighting with fierce
tangle of legs, looking for observers to be bizarre and extravagant the paguro, Bernardo dubbed
the Hermit. It was a shell that moved straight as a tower on some
crab legs, crown having at the hair of a sea anemone.

The comic appearance was composed of three different animals, one over another, or rather of
two living beings in the middle wearing a coffin. The paguro born with back devoid of armor: an excellent
bite, tender and tasty, for hungry fish. The need to defend a shell made him seek to save
the weak part of your body. If a house was empty for this species is appropriate. Otherwise,
ate the resident, introduced after the pearly shelter later, armed
with two legs hooked.

Not sufficient to paguro their weak defensive precautions.

Need to be offensive to live; inspire respect for eating monsters, especially the octopus, looking
for prey of your breasts and hairy legs, leaning out for locomotion outside the tower.

A sea anemone came to look at the top limestone: at times came to be five or six. No relationship
existed between the body and bodies paguro above. They were simple partners, mutual interest. Animals,
plants and stinging nettles all monsters without armor fleeing from the venom of stinging organs, the
strands of her hair burned like needles of fire. Thus, the humble paguro inspired terror to
the giant beasts depth, carrying on the back its tower crowned with formidable batteries. Anemones,
for his part, thanked the pasease incessantly from one side to another, placing them in contact with
all kinds of animals. They could eat more easily and her sisters still in the rock. They had
to wait, like them, the food came casually to their tentacles.

Also, always floated to its heights any remains of the prey was below crafty crab in his wandering
impunity.

Ferragut, moving from one pond to another, provided the gradation of the mentally diverse orders
of marine fauna, from the original sketch the perfect body.

Mediterranean sponges swam in the early days of his birth - when they
were as pinheads - vibrating movements.

Then stood motionless, straining water by the cells and corridors of their tissues, protecting
their soft flesh with a ruffling spicules, calcareous needles and spicy, with which strung and
immobilize fish serving them food waste into putrefaction.
Deployed by thousands of sea nettles stinging their strings, projecting
a poison stunned the victim and made her fall into the corolla, mouth
and anus simultaneously. A voracious without limits, seized, locked
in stone, of larger fish to them, and presenting danger shrank so,
it was difficult to see</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>