<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>48877</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>2729</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
No acaba una de ver verdades que parecen mentiras... En fin, otros son peores que este D. Carlos,
que al cabo da algo, aunque sea por cuenta y apuntación... Peores los hay, y tan peores...
que ni apuntan ni dan... El cuento es que con estos dos duros no se me arregla el día, porque
quiero devolverle a Almudena el suyo, que bueno es tener con él palabra. Vendrán días malos,
y él me servirá... Me quedan veinte reales, de los cuales habré de dar parte a la niña, que
está pereciendo, y lo demás para comer hoy, y... Tendré que decirle a la señora que su pariente
no me ha dado más que el libro de cuentas, con el cual y el lápiz pondremos un puchero que
será muy rico... caldo de números y substancia de imprenta... ¡qué risa!... En fin, para las
mentiras que he de decirla a Doña Paca, Dios me iluminará, como siempre, y vamos tirando. A
ver si encuentro a Almudena por el camino, que esta es la hora de subir él a la iglesia. Y
si no nos tropezamos en la calle, de fijo está en el café de la Cruz del Rastro».

Dirigiose allá, y en la calle de la Encomienda se encontraron: «Hijo, en tu busca iba--le dijo
la Benina cogiéndole por el brazo--. Aquí tienes tu duro. Ya ves que sé cumplir.

--Amri, no tener priesa.

--No te debo nada... Y hasta otra, Almudenilla, que días vendrán en que yo carezca y tú me
sirvas, como te serviré yo viceversa... ¿Vienes del café?

--Sí, y golvier si querer tú migo. Convidar tigo».

Asintió Benina al convite, y un rato después hallábanse los dos sentaditos en el café económico,
tomándose sendos vasos de a diez céntimos. El local era una taberna retocada, con ridículas
elegancias entre pueblo y señorío; dorados chillones; las paredes pintorreadas de marinas y
paisajes; ambiente fétido, y parroquia mixta de pobretería y vendedores del Rastro, locuaces,
indolentes, algunos agarrados a los periódicos, y otros oyendo la lectura, todos muy a gusto
en aquel vagar bullicioso, entre salivazos, humo de mal tabaco y olores de aguardiente. Solos
en una mesa Benina y el marroquí, charlaron de sus cosas: el ciego le contó las barrabasadas
de su compañera de vivienda, y ella su entrevista con D. Carlos, y el ridículo obsequio del
libro de cuentas y de los dos duros mensuales. De las riquezas que, según voz pública, atesoraba
Trujillo (treinta y cuatro casas, la mar de dinero en papelorios del Gobierno, muchismos miles
de miles en el Banco), charlaron extensamente, corriéndose luego a considerar, verbigracia,
el sinnúmero de pobres que podrían ser felices con toda aquella guita, que a D. Carlos le venía
tan ancha, pues descontando una parte para sus hijos, que de natural debían poseerlo, con lo
demás se apañarían tantos y tantos que andan por estas calles de Dios ladrando de hambre. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00246</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>11185</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>2988</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> This
is not only an opinion, it is quite accurate, that there are valuable truths that don't seem true. Sometimes
the point they make is so obscure even after much expense and explanation. The story just
becomes worse and worse, somehow pointless you could say. This sort of dilemna cannot be repaired
in a mere day's time, at least, not usually. Of the man Almudena, he is gifted with much to say
of this caliber and I love to hear him speak.

There are days of sorrow ahead and I hope to enlighten the girl who is dying during lunch today,
with some proverbial truths while they are lining the center of my head. I am also expected
to convey the stock numbers and other matters from the Book of Accounts to your relative Mrs....
, this could prove to make us all very rich, or, perhaps it will bring a laugh to our hearts.
Everything I can say has its roots in the Dona Paca.

It is always the case that God is the tool that lights our path no matter
what we are trying to do.

If you happen to see Mary along the way, this is a sign to get to
the church.

As we struggle through the lanes of life it is all fixed for us as
if it may be a fine restaurant for dining.

There are those who run away from the difficulties in life; but, you
might search instead of run away.

Knights were formed on many occasions when some brave souls stared
uncertainity in the face.

Maybe you are like them. With this idea the man took Benina by his arm. He told him not to hurry,
because the time would come that he would get to do his justice in the world.

"Are you going to be here for coffee?" asked the man of Benina. "Could you also ask Tigo to come?"
Benina nodded his head to acknowledge that he would show for the coffee. While they sat and
talked over coffee, Benina uttered many disatisfied opinions about the economic situation and also
took two glasses of coffee at ten cents a piece. The whole cafe was a refurnished tavern and
appeared as something between an old village and and elegant manor, a
little funny actually. The mixture of bright marine blue color, with
touches along with sellers, parishiners and newspaper readers created
quite a hearty group of souls, each of them slighly individual in the
midst of it all. The smell of smoke and alcohol fused with the newspaper
print but still did not disturb the comfort they all seemed to be enjoying.

Maybe
it was the great landscape in the background or the comfortable chatting
taking place between some of them that made everyone feel at ease.
Everyone seemed to be at the coffee house. Conversations about wealth
and money were popular with them all and there was even some gossip
pertaining to the locals. Talk of the bank, the government and D.
Carlos, who was making allowances for children in the latest tax bills,
were common discussions making the rounds. 

As for D. Carlos creating
advantages for the people with children, it was felt that they should
be spared the hunger that could interfere with their march with God</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>