<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05189</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>157521</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19956</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El abismo que los separaba era cada vez más profundo.
Por eso, la airada venganza cogía esta ocasión por los pelos.

Clementina le miró un instante. Luego, encogiéndose de hombros y haciendo con los labios una
leve mueca de desdén, dió la vuelta y se dispuso a salir de la estancia. Osorio avanzó unos
pasos colocándose entre ella y la puerta.

--Antes de irte quiero que sepas que el cajero tiene orden de no pagar ningún recibo que no
vaya visado por mí.

--Enterada.

--Para tus gastos tendrás una cantidad fija, que ya determinaremos cuál ha de ser. No quiero
más sorpresas en la caja.

Clementina, que iba a salir por la puerta de la antesala, retrocedió para hacerlo por la de
su boudoir. Antes de desaparecer, teniendo el portier levantado con una mano y encarándose
con su marido, le dijo con reconcentrada ira:

--Al fin resultas un puerco como tu cuñado; sólo que éste no las echa como tú de generoso.

Dejó caer el portier y dió un gran portazo.

Osorio hizo un movimiento para arrojarse detrás de ella; pero reponiéndose instantáneamente
gritó más que dijo para que le oyese bien:

--¡Es claro! soy un puerco porque no quiero mantener señoritos hambrientos. ¡Que los mantengan
las viejas que los utilizan!

Después de proferida esta ferocidad quedó satisfecho al parecer, porque en sus labios se dibujó
una sonrisa de triunfo y sarcasmo.

Cinco minutos después ambos esposos estaban en el comedor riendo y bromeando con los tres o
cuatro convidados que tenían.

IV

#Cómo alentaba a la virtud el señor duque de Requena.#

A ver, a ver, explica eso.

--Señor duque, el negocio es clarísimo. Hoy he hablado con Regnault. La mina puede producir,
cambiando los hornos, construyendo algunas vías y estableciendo maquinaria a propósito, una
mitad más de lo que actualmente rinde. Puede llegar a producir sesenta mil frascos de azogue.
El dinero necesario para lograr esto no pasa de ciento a ciento cincuenta mil duros.

--Me parece mucho.

--¿Mucho, para un resultado como ese?

--No; me parecen muchos frascos.

--Pues a mí no me cabe duda de que es verdad lo que dice Regnault. Es un ingeniero inteligente
y práctico. Seis años ha estado explotando las de California. Además, el ingeniero inglés que
ha ido con él asegura lo mismo.

Los que así hablaban eran el duque de Requena y su secretario, primer dependiente o como quiera
llamarse, pues en la casa no había apelativo designado para él. Llamábasele simplemente Llera.
Era un mozo asturiano, alto, huesudo, de rostro pálido y anguloso, brazos y piernas larguísimos,
grandes manos y pies, brusco y desgarbado de ademanes y con unos ojos grandes de mirar franco
y sincero donde brillaba la voluntad y la inteligencia. Era un trabajador infatigable, asombroso.
No se sabía a qué horas comía ni dormía. Cuando llegaba a las ocho de la mañana al escritorio,
ya traía hecha la tarea de cualquier hombre en todo el día. A las doce de la noche aún se le
podía ver muchas veces con la pluma en la mano en su despacho. Con ese don especial para conocer
a los hombres, que poseen todos los que han de lograr éxito feliz en el mundo, Salabert penetró,
al poco tiempo de tenerle por ínfimo escribiente, el carácter y la inteligencia de Llera. Y
sin darle gran consideración en apariencia, porque esto no entraba jamás en su proceder, se
la dió de hecho acumulando sobre él los trabajos de más importancia. En poco tiempo llegó a
ser el hombre de confianza del célebre especulador, el alma de la casa. Su laboriosidad humillaba
a todos los demás empleados y de ella se servía Salabert para cargarlos de trabajo en horas
excepcionales. Llera, a un mismo tiempo, era su secretario, su mayordomo general, el primer
oficial de su oficina, el inspector de las obras que tenía en construcción y el agente de casi
todos sus negocios. Por llevar a cabo este trabajo inconcebible, superior a las fuerzas de
cuatro hombres medianamente laboriosos, le daba seis mil pesetas al año. El dependiente se
creía bien retribuido, considerábase feliz pensando que hacía seis años nada más, ganaba mil
quinientas. Todos los días, antes de dar su paseo matinal y emprender sus visitas de negocios,
daba el duque una vuelta por el despacho de Llera, se enteraba de los asuntos y conversaba
con él un rato largo o corto según las circunstancias.

El duque tenía las oficinas en los altos de su palacio del paseo de Luchana, soberbio edificio
levantado en medio de un jardín que, por lo amplio, merecía el nombre de parque. En el verano,
los árboles, tupidos de follaje, apenas dejaban ver la blanca crestería de la azotea. En el
invierno, las muchas coníferas y arbustos de hoja permanente que allí crecían, le daban todavía
aspecto muy grato. Era el centro de reunión de todos los pájaros del distrito del Hospicio.
Tenía acceso por una gran escalinata de mármol. Además del piso bajo donde se hallaban los
salones de recibir y el comedor poseía otros dos. Parte del último era lo que ocupaban las
oficinas, que no eran muy considerables. A Salabert le bastaba para la dirección de sus negocios
con una docena de empleados expertos. El lujo desplegado en la casa era sorprendente: el mobiliario
valía no pocos millones. Chocaba con la avaricia, que todo el mundo atribuía a su dueño. Esta
y otras contradicciones parecidas se irán resolviendo según vayamos penetrando en su carácter,
uno de los más curiosos y más dignos de fijar la atención del lector. Las cocinas estaban en
los sótanos, que eran espaciosos y bien dispuestos. El comedor, que ocupaba la parte trasera
del piso bajo, tenía por complemento un invernadero de excepcionales dimensiones, donde crecían
gran número de arbustos y flores exóticas y donde el agua que manaba profusamente formaba estanquecillos
y cascadas muy gratos de ver; todo imitando, en lo posible, a la naturaleza. Las cuadras estaban
en edificio aparte al extremo del jardín, lo mismo que la habitación de algunos criados, no todos.

El duque, repantigado en el único sillón que había en el despacho de Llera, mientras éste se
mantenía frente a él de pie dando vueltas en la mano a unas grandes tijeras de cortar papel,
paseó tres o cuatro veces de un ángulo a otro de la boca el negro y mojado cigarro, sin contestar
a las últimas palabras de su secretario. Al fin gruñó más que dijo:

--¡Hum! El ministro está cada día más terco.

--¡Qué importa! ¿No sabe usted el secreto de hacerle ceder?... Telegrafíe usted a Liverpool
y antes de quince días el frasco de azogue baja desde sesenta a cuarenta duros.

El duque de Requena había formado por iniciativa y consejo de Llera, hacía cuatro años, una
sociedad o sindicato de azogues con el objeto de acaparar todo el mercurio que saliese al mercado.
Gracias a ello, este producto había subido extraordinariamente. La sociedad se encontraba con
un depósito inmenso en Liverpool. El plan de Llera era lanzarlo al mercado en un momento dado,
produciendo una baja enorme que asustase al Gobierno. Esto, realizado en la época misma del
pago del empréstito de cien millones de pesetas que el Gobierno había hecho hacía diez años
a una casa extranjera, le empujaría a pensar en la venta de la mina de Riosa. Si por otra parte
se ayudaba a la empresa sacrificando algunos millones, subvencionando periódicos y personajes,
podía darse por seguro el éxito. Este plan, formado por Llera y madurado por el duque, venía
desenvolviéndose con regularidad y tocaba a su término.

--Allá veremos--manifestó el opulento banquero quedándose unos instantes pensativo--. Cuando
salga a subasta--dijo al cabo--, será necesario formar otra sociedad. La de azogues no nos
sirve para el caso.

--¡Claro que se formará!

--El caso es que yo no quiero comprometer en este negocio más de ocho millones de pesetas.

--Eso ya es otra cosa--manifestó Llera poniéndose serio--. Apoderarse de un negocio de esa
entidad con tan poco dinero me parece imposible. La gerencia irá a parar a otras manos y entonces
queda reducido a un tanto por ciento mayor o menor.... ¡es decir, a nada!

--Verdad, verdad--masculló Salabert quedándose otra vez profundamente pensativo. Llera también
permaneció silencioso y meditabundo.

--Ya le he indicado a usted el único medio que hay para conseguir la dirección....

Este medio consistía en tomar una cantidad bastante crecida de acciones en la mina al ser comprada
por la sociedad; seguir comprando todas las que se pudiesen; luego comenzar a venderlas más
baratas, hasta llegar a producir el pánico en los accionistas. Comprar y vender perdiendo durante
algún tiempo éste era el medio que proponía Llera para conseguir la baja de las acciones y
poder adquirir con mucho menos dinero la mitad más una y apoderarse por completo del negocio.
Salabert no lo veía tan claro como su secretario. Era la suya una inteligencia perspicaz, minuciosa,
penetrante; pero le faltaba grandeza e iniciativa en los negocios, aunque otra cosa pensasen
los que le veían acometer empresas de excepcional importancia. El pensamiento primordial, la
que pudiéramos llamar idea madre de un negocio, casi nunca nacía en su cerebro; le venía de
afuera. Pero en él germinaba y se desarrollaba quizá como en ningún otro de España. Poco a
poco lo iba analizando, disecando mejor, penetraba hasta las últimas fibras, lo contemplaba
en sus múltiples aspectos, y una vez convencido de que le reportaría ventajas, se lanzaba sobre
él con rara y sorprendente audacia. Esto era lo que acerca de sus dotes de especulador había
producido el engaño del públíco. Estaba bien convencido de que una vez resuelto a acometer
la empresa, cualquier vacilación resultaba perjudicial. Tal audacia no procedía, pues, directamente
de su temperamento, sino de la reflexión. Era una muestra de su astucia incomparable.

Por lo demás, su fondo era tímido. Este defecto, en vez de corregirse con la felicidad casi
nunca interrumpida de sus éxitos, se aumentaba cada día. La avaricia es medrosa y suspicaz.
Salabert era cada vez más avaro. Además, con los años, el pesimismo va penetrando en el espíritu
del hombre. Acostumbrado a grandes resultados en sus especulaciones, nuestro banquero juzgaba
deplorable el negocio en que no percibía pingües ganancias. Si por acaso no obtenía ninguna
o había leve pérdida, creía el caso digno de ser lamentado largamente. Así que, sin el concurso
de Llera, sin su carácter osado y su imaginación fecunda en invenciones, el duque de Requena
haría ya tiempo que no se aventuraría en un negocio de mediana importancia. En cambio, lo que
había perdido de inventiva y audacia habíalo reemplazado por un tacto y habilidad verdaderamente
pasmosos, un conocimiento de los hombres que sólo la edad y una atención constante pueden lograr.
En tal sentido puede decirse que Llera y él se completaban a maravilla. Esta sagacidad y este
conocimiento del corazón humano llegaban en Salabert a pecar de excesivos; esto es, se pasaba
de listo en ocasiones. En su trato con los hombres, mirándoles siempre del lado de los intereses
materiales, había llegado a formarse tan triste idea de ellos, que resultaba monstruosa y le
expuso a serios percances. Quizá lo que veía en los otros no era más que el reflejo de su propia
imagen como nos sucede a todos los humanos. Para él no había hombre ni mujer incorruptibles.
Un poco más caras o un poco más baratas las conciencias, todas estaban a la venta. En los últimos
años el soborno llegó a ser en él una manía. Si tropezaba con personas que no se dejaban comprar,
nunca imaginaba que lo hacían de buena fe, sino porque se estimaban en mayor precio del que
ofrecía. Era una de las tareas más pesadas de Llera arrancarle de la cabeza los proyectos de
soborno cuando recaían en hombres que sin duda habían de rechazarlos con indignación. Si tenía
un pleito, lo primero que pensaba era cuánto dinero iban a costarle los magistrados que habían
de fallarlo. Si estaba interesado en un expediente gubernativo, separaba in mente la cantidad
que debía destinar al ministro o al subsecretario o a los consejeros de Estado. Desgraciadamente
este lápiz negro que tenía siempre en la mano para tiznar el rostro de la humanidad, se empleaba
con resultado positivo en bastantes ocasiones.

El duque de Requena ni tenía sentido moral ni nunca lo había conocido. Su vida de granuja anónimo
en Valencia, estaba señalada por una serie de travesuras y mañas chistosas, por una fecundidad
tan grande en trazas para sacar al prójimo su dinero, que lo hicieron digno émulo del Lazarillo
de Tormes, El pícaro Guzmán de Alfarache y otros héroes famosos de la novela española. Por
cierto que antes de ir adelante conviene expresar que un grupo de socios del Ateneo había puesto
a Salabert el sobrenombre de El pícaro Guzmán con que le conocían. Pero este apodo no salió
del círculo de amigos. Mejor éxito tuvo una frase del presidente del Consejo de Ministros explicando
las iniciales del duque. Decía que a estas iniciales A.S. debía ponérseles signo de admiración
para que dijeran: ¡A Ese!

Contábase con visos de verosimilitud que en Cuba, adonde había ido a buscar fortuna, compró
un tabernucho en los arrabales de la Habana, con todo su mobiliario, incluyendo en él una negra
destinada a su servicio. Esta negra, durante los años que tuvo aquel comercio, fué su criada,
su ama de gobierno, su dependiente y su concubina. De ella tuvo varios hijos. Cuando hubo ahorrado
algunos miles de duros para restituirse a España, liquidó sus cuentas vendiendo la taberna,
el mobiliario, la negra.... ¡y los hijos!

Luego comenzaron los equipos para la tropa, los negocios de tabacos, la subasta de carreteras,
cediéndolas unas veces con primas, otras construyéndolas sin las condiciones exigidas por el
contrato, los empréstitos al Gobierno, etc., etc. En todos ellos desplegó nuestro negociante
su rara sagacidad, su talento positivo y un "órgano de la adquisividad" tan poderoso, que con
razón le hicieron célebre entre los personajes de la banca.

No era antipático su trato. Al revés de casi todos los que aspiran a las riquezas o al poder,
ni era fino en los modales ni meloso en las palabras. Era más bien brusco que cortés; pero
sabía admirablemente distinguir de personas y se suavizaba cuando hacía falta. Esta misma tosquedad
nativa servíale para disfrazar lo astuto y sutil de su pensamiento. Parecía que aquel exterior
burdo, rústico, aquellos modales exageradamente libres y campechanos no podían menos de guardar
un corazón franco y leal. Era (por fuera nada más) el tipo acabado del castellano viejo, honradote,
sincero e impertinente. Hablaba poco o mucho según le convenía, se expresaba con dificultad
real o fingida (que esto nunca llegó a averiguarse), tenía de vez en cuando salidas chistosas,
aunque siempre tocadas de grosería, y solía decir en la cara algunas cosas desagradables que
le hacían temible en los salones. La preponderancia adquirida por sus riquezas había hecho
crecer este último defecto. A la mayor parte de las personas, aun a las damas, solía hablarles
con una franqueza rayana en el cinismo y la desvergüenza; signos del desprecio que en realidad
le inspiraban. No obstante, cuando tropezaba con un personaje político de los que a él le convenía
tener propicios, esta franqueza tomaba otro giro muy distinto y se transformaba en adulación
y casi casi en servilismo. Mas esta farsa, aunque admirablemente desempeñada, no engañaba a
nadie. El duque de Requena era tenido por un zorro de marca. Por milagro creía ya alguno en
sus palabras ni se dejaba cautivar por aquel aspecto rudo y bonachón. Los que le hablaban estaban
siempre en guardia, aunque fingiendo confianza y alegría. Como sucede a todos los que han conseguido
elevarse, los defectos que universalmente se le reconocían, mejor dicho, la mala fama que tenía,
no era obstáculo para que se le respetase, para que todos le hablasen con el sombrero en la
mano y la sonrisa en los labios, aunque nunca hubiesen de necesitar de él. Los hombres muchas
veces se humillan por el solo placer de humillarse. Salabert conocía esta innata tendencia
que tiene la espina dorsal del hombre a doblarse y abusaba de ella. Muchos que vivían con independencia,
no sólo le toleraban impertinencias que les hubieran parecido intolerables en algún amigo de
la infancia, sino que apetecían y buscaban su trato.

--Veremos, veremos--repitió de nuevo cuando Llera le recordó el medio de apoderarse de la gerencia--.
Tú eres muy fantástico; tienes la cabeza demasiado caliente. No sirves para los negocios. A
ver si nos pasa aquí lo que con las alhóndigas.

Por consejo de Llera, el negociante había construído alhóndigas en algunas capitales de España,
las cuales no habían tenido el éxito que esperaban. Como después de todo el negocio no era
de gran entidad, las pérdidas tampoco fueron cuantiosas. A pesar de eso, el duque, que las
había llorado como si lo fuesen y no había escaseado a su secretario frases groseras e insultantes,
le recordaba a cada instante el asunto. Servíale de arma para despreciar sus planes, aunque
después los utilizase lindamente y a ellos debiese un aumento considerable de su hacienda.
Teníale de esta suerte sumiso, ignorante de su valer y presto a cualquier trabajo por enojoso
que fuera.

Un poco avergonzado por el recuerdo, Llera insistió en afirmar que el negocio de ahora era
de éxito infalible si se le conducía por los caminos que él señalaba. Salabert cortó bruscamente
la discusión pasando a otros asuntos. Informóse rápidamente de los del día. La pérdida de una
fianza que había hecho por un pariente de Valencia, le puso fuera de sí, bufó y pateó como
un toro cuando le clavan las banderillas, se llamó animal cien veces y tuvo la desfachatez
de decir, en presencia de Llera, que su bondadoso corazón concluiría por arruinarle. La pérdida,
en total, representaba unas veintidós mil pesetas. Las fianzas que el duque hacía por sus más
íntimos amigos o parientes eran del tenor siguiente: Las hacía generalmente en papel, exigía
al afianzado un seis por ciento del capital depositado, y se encargaba además de cortar y cobrar
los cupones. De suerte que el capital, en vez de redituarle lo que a todos los tenedores de
valores del Estado, le producía un seis por ciento más. Así eran los negocios que el duque
hacía, no tanto por interés como por impulso irresistible de su corazón.

Salió furioso del despacho de su secretario, fuese a la caja y aprendiendo allí que iban a
mandar a cobrar al Banco nueve mil duros de cuenta corriente, él mismo recogió el talón después
de firmarlo. Debía pasar por allá a celebrar una Junta como consejero, y de paso ningún trabajo
le costaba hacerlo efectivo. Salió a pie como era su costumbre por las mañanas. En las hermosas
coníferas que bordaban los caminos del jardín-parque cantaban alegremente los pájaros. Se comprendía
que no habían puesto fianza alguna y la habían perdido. El señor duque maldita la gana que
tenía de cantar ni aun escuchar sus regocijados trinos. Pasó de largo con el semblante torvo,
sin responder a los saludos de los jardineros y del portero, mordiendo con más ensañamiento
que nunca su enorme cigarro. En la calle no tardó en colorearse un poco su rostro. Tuvo un
encuentro agradable y útil. El presidente del Consejo de Estado, a quien le gustaba también
madrugar, le saludó en el paseo de Recoletos. Hablaron algunos momentos y los aprovechó para
recomendarle, con la brusquedad calculada que le caracterizaba, un expediente de ciertas marismas
en que estaba interesado. Después, a paso lento, mirando con sus ojos saltones, inocentes,
a los transeuntes, deteniéndolos particularmente en las frescas domésticas que regresaban a
sus casas con la cesta de la compra llena y las mejillas más coloradas por el esfuerzo, se
dirigió al Banco de España. Era mucha la gente que le quitaba el sombrero. De vez en cuando
se detenía un instante, daba un apretón de manos, y cambiando con el conocido que tropezaba
cuatro palabras en tono familiar y desenfadado, seguía su camino.

Era temprano aún. Antes de llegar al Banco se le ocurrió subir a casa de su amigo y compariente
Calderón. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09787</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>170804</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17756</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The gulf between them was growing deeper. Therefore, the
angry vengeance this time grabbed by the hair.

Clementina looked at him a moment. Then, shrugging his lips and making a slight sneer, turned
around and started to leave the room.

Osorio took a few steps standing between her and the door.

- Before you go I want you to know that the cashier has orders not
to pay any receipt that is not be endorsed by me.

- Aware.

- For
your expenses have a fixed amount, which will determine what must be.

I do not want more surprises in the box.

Clementina, who was to walk out the door of the antechamber, drew back from doing so by the
her boudoir. Before he disappeared, having lifted the portiere with one hand and facing with
her husband, told with concentrated wrath

- The end result a pig as your brother, just check it like you do
not generous.

He dropped the portiere and gave a big bang.

Osorio made a motion to throw behind it, but instantly recovering cried more than he said to hear
it well:

- Of course!

I'm a pig because they want to keep hungry gentlemen.

That kept The use of old!

After uttering this ferocity was apparently satisfied, because his lips were drawn a triumphant
smile and sarcasm.

Five minutes later both spouses were in the room laughing and joking
with the three four guests they had.

IV

# How virtue encouraged the Duke of Requena. #

Let's see, see, explains why.

- Sir Duke, business is clear. Today I talked to Regnault. The mine can produce, changing ovens,
built some roads and establishing machinery to purpose, a more than half currently pays. Can
produce sixty thousand flasks of quicksilver. The money needed to achieve this does not happen a
hundred to one hundred fifty thousand dollars.

- I think a lot.

- A lot, for a result like that?

- No, I think many bottles.

- Well, I do not doubt that is true what he says Regnault. It's a smart engineer and practical.
Six years has been exploiting those of California. In addition, the English engineer has gone
with him says the same thing.

Those who spoke were the Duke and Requena and his secretary, chief clerk or whatever called,
since the house was designated nickname for him. Llamábasele simply Llera. He was a fellow Spaniard,
tall, skinny, pale, angular face, arms and legs very long, large hands and feet, sudden gestures
and lanky with big eyes looking at ex- where bright and sincere will and intelligence. He
was a tireless worker, amazing. It was not known what time he ate
or slept.

When I arrived at eight o'clock to the desktop, brought and made the task of any man in all day.
At twelve o'clock he was still I could see many times with the pen in his hand in his office.
With the special talent to know men, who have all to be happy succeed in the world, Salabert
penetrated shortly after having him for lowest clerk, character and intelligence Llera. Y without
giving serious consideration in appearance, because this is not ever entered into his conduct
is actually gave it accumulated on the work of more importance. In short time he be the henchman
of the famous speculator, the soul of the house. His industriousness humiliated all other
employees and she served Salabert workloads in hours exceptional. Llera, at the same time, it was
his secretary, his general foreman, the first his official office, the inspector of works was under
construction and almost Agent all its businesses. By carrying out this work inconceivable, beyond
the strength of four men fairly laborious, gave him six thousand pesetas a year. The clerk was
felt well paid, we felt happy thinking that just six years ago, won a thousand hundred. Every
day, before his morning walk and take their business visits, Duke gave a tour of the office
Llera, learned of the issues and talking with it a long or short according to circumstances.

The Duke had the highest offices of his palace Luchana ride, superb building up in the middle of
a garden, so large, deserved the name of the park. In the summer,
trees, lush foliage, leaving only see the white crests of the roof.

In the winter, many conifers and leafy shrubs that grew there permanently, still gave very pleasing
appearance. It was the gathering of all the birds of the district's Hospice. Had access to a
large marble staircase. In addition the ground floor where they were the receiving rooms and the
dining room had two. Part of the latter was what occupied the offices,
which were not very significant.

A Salabert was sufficient for the conduct of their business with
a dozen skilled employees.

The luxury displayed in the house was amazing: the furniture worth more than a few million.
Clashed with greed, everyone attributed to its owner.

This and other similar contradictions will be resolved as we go penetrating in character, one
of the most curious and most worthy of setting the reader's attention. The kitchens were in basements,
which were spacious and well arranged. The dining room, which occupied the rear the ground floor,
was to add an exceptionally large greenhouse where they grew large number of shrubs and exotic
flowers and where the water was flowing profusely estanquecillos and very pleasing to see waterfalls,
all imitating, if possible, to nature. The blocks were in separate building at the end of the
garden, as well as some servants' room, not everyone.

The Duke, lounging on the only chair that was in the office Llera, while it kept standing in
front of him spinning in the hand of a big scissors cut paper, walked
three or four times from one angle to another of her mouth and wet
black cigar unanswered the last words of his secretary.

At last he grunted more than he said

- Hum!

The minister is becoming more stubborn.

- Who cares!

Do not you know the secret of giving him?

... Liverpool telegraph you and fifteen days before the bottle of quicksilver down from sixty
to forty dollars.

The Duke of Requena had formed on the initiative and advice Llera, for four years, quicksilver
company or union in order to capture all the mercury they release
it on the market.

As a result, this product had risen dramatically. The company was
to a huge deposit in Liverpool.

Llera plan was released in a given time producing a huge low frightened the government. This, held
at the same time payment of the loan of one hundred million pesetas that the Government had
made ten years ago to a foreign company, would push him think about selling mine rivers. If on the
other hand helped the company will sacrifice a few million, subsidizing newspapers and characters
could be assured success. This plan, consisting of Llera and matured by the Duke, came unfolding
regularly and was coming to an end.

- There shall see - said the wealthy banker and was some thoughtful moments -. When go to auction
- said after - it will be necessary to form another company. Of quicksilver we do not served
for the case.

- Of course it will be!

- The fact is that I do not want to compromise in this business more than eight million pesetas.

-
That's another thing - getting serious Llera said -. Grab a business that entity with so little money
it seems impossible.

Management will go into other hands and then is reduced to a percentage higher or lower ....
Ie, nothing!

- True, true - again remaining Salabert mumbled in deep thought. Llera also remained silent and
thoughtful.

- I have already indicated to you the only way is to get the address ....

This medium was to take a fair amount of shares flood the mine to be purchased by society to keep
buying all that could be and then start selling them cheap, until you get to produce panic among
shareholders. Buying and selling lost during some time this was the means proposed for achieving
low Llera actions and to acquire a lot less money in half and take more of a business altogether.
Salabert not see it as clear as his secretary. It was his keen intelligence, thorough, penetrating,
but lacked grandeur and initiative in business, but another thing thought those who saw him
undertake enterprises of exceptional importance. The primary thought, the we might call the mother
of a business idea, almost never born in his brain, he came from outside. But it germinated
and developed perhaps as nowhere else in Spain. Little little was analyzing, dissecting better, penetrated
to every fiber, watching him in its many aspects, and once convinced it would bring benefits, was
thrown on rare and surprising him with boldness. This was what about his skills had speculator
occurrence of the deception of the public. I was quite convinced that once resolved to undertake
the company was damaging any hesitation. Such boldness was not appropriate, therefore, directly
of his temperament, but of reflection. It was a sign of his cunning incomparable.

Moreover, his background was shy. This defect, instead of happiness almost corrected never interrupted
their successes, increased every day. Greed is fearful and suspicious. Salabert was becoming greedy.
In addition, over the years, the pessimism in the spirit penetrates
man.

Used to great results in their speculations, our banker judged Business deplorable that not receiving
huge profits. If by chance did not get any or had mild loss, thought the case worthy of long lamented.
So no contest Llera, without his daring character and imagination fertile in invention, the Duke
of Requena time and would not venture into a business of medium importance. Instead, what
lost inventive and daring Tell them replaced by a truly tact and skill breathtaking, a knowledge
of men, only age and constant attention can accomplish. In this sense we can say that he Llera
and wonderfully completed. This wisdom and this knowledge of human nature came in to sin of excessive
Salabert, ie spent Ready at times. In his dealings with men, watching them always on the side
of interest materials, had come to form their idea so sad that it
was monstrous and exposed to serious mishaps.

Perhaps he saw in others was not only a reflection of their own image as it happens to all
humans. For him there was no man or woman incorruptible. A little bit more expensive or cheaper
consciences, all were sold. In recent Bribery years it became a hobby. If faced with people who
are not let buy never imagined that they did in good faith, but because they felt a greater price
than offered. It was one of the heaviest tasks Llera tore his projects bribery when accruing
to men who no doubt had to reject with indignation.

If he had a lawsuit, the first thing I thought was going to cost much money the judges who had
failure. If you were interested in a gubernatorial record, separated in mind the amount to be
directed to the Minister or the directors or secretary of state. Unfortunately This black pencil
that had always on hand to smudge the face of humanity, was used with positive results on many
occasions.

The Duke of Requena and moral sense and never had known. His life of anonymous rogue in Valencia,
was marked by a series of silly pranks and tricks for fertility so great to get the neighbor trace
their money, they did worthy rival of Lazarillo de Tormes, Guzmán de Alfarache The Rogue and other
famous heroes of the Spanish novel. For true that before going forward should say that a group
of partners had Ateneo Salabert to the nickname of The Rogue Guzman who knew him. But this nickname
did not come out circle of friends. Best success was a phrase the president of the Council
of Ministers explaining Duke initials. He said that at this early AS was brought to an exclamation
point to read: A That!

We had with a veneer of plausibility that in Cuba, where he had gone to seek his fortune, bought
a tavern on the outskirts of Havana, with all its furniture, including in it a black aimed at
your service. This black, during the years that had that trade, was her maid, his housekeeper, his
clerk and his concubine. It had several children. When he had saved some thousands of dollars
to be returned to Spain, settled their accounts by selling the tavern furniture, black ....
And children!

Then began the teams for the troops, the tobacco business, the sale of roads cediéndolas sometimes with
premiums, other building without the conditions imposed by the contract, the Government loans, etc.,
etc. Deployed in all our dealer his rare wisdom, talent and a positive "organ of acquisitiveness"
so powerful that made him famous because of the characters from the bench.

Their treatment was not unpleasant. Contrary to almost all who aspire to wealth or power nor was fine manners
and sweet in words. It was rather rude than polite, but People knew admirably distinguish and
softened as needed.

The same coarseness native ministered unto him to disguise how clever and subtle thought. It seemed that
this exterior rough, rustic, those overly free and hearty manner could not fail to save frank
and loyal heart.

It was (outside only) type finish old Castilian, honradote, sincere and impertinent. He spoke little
or much as it suited him, he expressed himself with difficulty real or fake (this was never
ascertained), was occasionally humorous outputs, but always played rudeness, and would say
on the face some unpleasant things made him formidable in the classroom. The preponderance acquired
their wealth had been increase last defect. For most people, even the ladies, used to talk
with a frankness bordering on cynicism and shamelessness; signs of contempt that actually
inspired him. However, when faced with a political character which it suited him be supportive,
took another twist this openness very differently and flattery was
transformed into and almost almost servile.

But this farce, but performed admirably, did not fool anyone. The Duke of Requena was taken
by a fox brand. For any longer believed in miracles his words or was left captivated by that tough-looking,
good-natured. Those who spoke were always on guard, though feigning confidence and joy. As all
who have achieved rise, the defects that are universally recognized him, rather, the bad reputation
it had, was not an obstacle to be respected, for everyone you speak with the hat on hand and
smile, but never had to need it. Many men sometimes humiliating for the mere pleasure of humbling.
Salabert knew this innate tendency that has the man's spine to bend and abused her. Many who
lived independently, not only tolerated him guff that they would have seemed intolerable to
a friend children, but craved and sought his treatment.

- We will see, see - repeated again when reminded Llera seize the means of management -. You
are so fantastic, your head is too hot. No good for business.

A if we see what happens here with corn exchanges.

On the advice of Llera, the trader had built corn exchanges in some cities of Spain, which had not
been as successful as expected. And after all the business was not large entity, the losses were
not substantial. Despite this, the Duke, that he cried as if they were scarce and there was his secretary
rude and insulting phrases, reminded every moment matter. Servial weapon to belittle their
plans, although then use them and they Shall nicely a significant increase in their wealth. Thus
Teníale of submissive, ignorant of their worth and work quickly to any annoying it was.

A little embarrassed by the memory, Llera state insisted that the business was now infallible
success if you are driving down the road he pointed. Salabert abruptly cut discussion going
on to other issues. Informóse quickly from the day. The loss of a bond was made by a relative of
Valencia, he was beside himself, snorted and stamped as a bull when he nailed the flags, animal
called a hundred times and had the effrontery say, in the presence of Llera, conclude that
his kind heart to ruin. The loss in total, representing about twenty thousand. The bonds that
the Duke did for his most close friends or relatives were the following lines: The paper was
generally, required the secured six percent of the amount deposited, and did well to cut and
collect coupons.

So that the capital, instead of what profitable to all holders of securities, gave him a six percent
increase. So were the Duke business did not so much by interest as
by irresistible impulse to his heart.

Stormed out of the office of
his secretary, went to the box and there they would learn send to
charge the new bank current account thousand dollars, he picked up
the heel after sign. Should drop by to hold a board as a director,
and no job step it cost him cash. Out on foot as usual in the morning.
In the beautiful conifers that lined the roads of garden-park birds
sang merrily. It is understood that had failed and the bond being
lost. The Duke damn who wins had to sing or even hear their joyful
cries. Passed over, his face grim, without responding to the greetings
of the gardeners and the goalkeeper, with more ferocity biting never
his big cigar. On the street soon his face colored slightly. Had a
pleasant and useful meeting. The chairman of the State Council, who
also liked early, greeted him at the Paseo de Recoletos. They spoke
a few moments and took the opportunity to recommend, with calculated
abruptness that characterized him, a record of some wetlands that
was interested. Then slowly, looking with their eyes bulging, innocent,
passers, particularly in stopping them returning home fresh home with
the shopping cart full and cheeks are red from the effort, led the
Bank of Spain. Were many people who took off his hat. Occasionally
paused a moment, giving a handshake, and changing the familiar encountered
four words in familiar and relaxed tone, went on his way.

It was
still early. Before arriving at the Bank came up to the house of his
friend and compariente Calderón</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>