<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07766</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>400710</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21241</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Cuando todos huían hacia París, él necesitaba marchar en dirección contraria. El
senador no pudo creer lo que escuchaba.

--¡Está usted loco!--exclamó--. Hay que salir de París, pero con dirección al Sur. A usted
se lo digo solamente, y cállelo, porque es un secreto. Nos vamos de un momento á otro; todos
nos vamos: el presidente, el gobierno, las Cámaras. Nos instalaremos en Burdeos, como en 1870.
El enemigo va á llegar: es asunto de días... de horas. Sabemos poco de lo que ocurre, pero
todas las noticias son malas. El ejército se mantiene firme, aún está intacto, pero se retira...
se retira, cediendo terreno... Créame, lo mejor es marcharse de París. Gallieni lo defenderá,
pero la defensa va á ser dura y penosa... Aunque caiga París, no por eso caerá Francia. Continuaremos
la guerra si es necesario hasta la frontera de España... Pero esto es triste, ¡muy triste!

Y ofreció á su amigo el llevarle con él en la retirada á Burdeos, que muy pocos conocían en
aquellos momentos. Desnoyers movió la cabeza. No; deseaba ir al castillo de Villeblanche. Sus
muebles... sus riquezas... su parque.

--¡Pero va usted á caer prisionero!--protestó el senador--. ¡Tal vez lo maten!

Un gesto de indiferencia fué la respuesta. Se consideraba con energías para luchar contra todos
los ejércitos de Alemania defendiendo su propiedad. Lo importante era instalarse en ella, ¡y
que se atreviese alguien á tocar lo suyo!... El senador miró con asombro á este burgués enfurecido
por el sentimiento de la posesión. Se acordó de los mercaderes árabes, humildes y pacíficos
ordinariamente, que pelean y mueren como fieras cuando los beduínos ladrones quieren apoderarse
de sus géneros. El momento no era para discusiones: cada cual debía pensar en su propia suerte.
El senador acabó por prestarse al deseo de su amigo. Si tal era su gusto, podía cumplirlo.
Y consiguió con su influencia que saliese aquella misma noche en un tren militar que iba al
encuentro del ejército.

Este viaje puso en contacto á don Marcelo con el extraordinario movimiento que la guerra había
desarrollado en las vías férreas. Su tren tardó catorce horas en salvar una distancia corrida
en dos normalmente. Se componía de vagones de carga llenos de víveres y cartuchos, con las
puertas cerradas y selladas. Un coche de tercera clase estaba ocupado por la escolta del tren:
un pelotón de territoriales. En uno de segunda se instaló Desnoyers, con el teniente que mandaba
este grupo y varios oficiales que iban á incorporarse á sus regimientos después de terminar
las operaciones de movilización en las poblaciones que guarnecían antes de la guerra. Los vagones
de cola contenían sus caballos.

Se detuvo el tren muchas veces para dejar paso á otros que se le adelantaban repletos de soldados
ó volvían hacia París con muchedumbres fugitivas. Estos últimos estaban compuestos de plataformas
de carga, y en ellas se apelotonaban mujeres, niños, ancianos, revueltos con fardos de ropas,
maletas y carretillas que les habían servido para llevar hasta la estación todo lo que restaba
de sus ajuares. Eran á modo de campamentos rodantes que se inmovilizaban muchas horas y hasta
días en los apartaderos, dejando paso libre á los convoyes impulsados por las necesidades apremiantes
de la guerra. La muchedumbre, habituada á las detenciones interminables, desbordaba fuera del
tren, instalándose ante la locomotora muerta ó esparciéndose por los campos inmediatos.

En las estaciones de alguna importancia, todas las vías estaban ocupadas por rosarios de vagones.
Las máquinas, á gran presión, silbaban, impacientes de partir. Los grupos de soldados dudaban
ante los diversos trenes, equivocándose, descendiendo de unos coches para instalarse en otros.
Los empleados, calmosos y con aire de fatiga, iban de un lado á otro guiando á los hombres,
dando explicaciones, disponiendo la carga de montañas de objetos. En el convoy que llevaba
á Desnoyers los territoriales dormitaban, acostumbrados á la monótona operación de dar escolta.
Los encargados de los caballos habían abierto las puertas corredizas de los vagones, sentándose
en el borde con las piernas colgantes. El tren marchaba lentamente en la noche, á través de
los campos de sombra, deteniéndose ante los faros rojos para avisar su presencia con largos
silbidos. En algunas estaciones se presentaban muchachas vestidas de blanco, con escarapelas
y banderitas sobre el pecho. Día y noche estaban allí, reemplazándose, para que no pasase un
tren sin recibir su visita. Ofrecían en cestas y bandejas sus obsequios á los soldados: pan,
chocolate, frutas. Muchos, por hartura, intentaban resistirse, pero habían de ceder finalmente
ante el gesto triste de las jóvenes. Hasta Desnoyers se vió asaltado por estos obsequios del
entusiasmo patriótico.

Pasó gran parte de la noche hablando con sus compañeros de viaje. Los oficiales sólo tenían
vagos indicios de dónde podrían encontrar á sus regimientos. Las operaciones de la guerra cambiaban
diariamente su situación. Pero fieles al deber, seguían adelante, con la esperanza de llegar
á tiempo para el combate decisivo. El jefe de la escolta llevaba realizados algunos viajes
y era el único que se daba cuenta exacta de la retirada. Cada vez hacía el tren un trayecto
menor. Todos parecían desorientados. ¿Por qué la retirada?... El ejército había sufrido reveses
indudablemente, pero estaba entero, y según su opinión debía buscar el desquite en los mismos
lugares. La retirada dejaba libre el avance del enemigo. ¿Hasta dónde iban á retroceder?...
¡Ellos que dos semanas antes discutían en sus guarniciones el punto de Bélgica donde recibirían
los adversarios el golpe mortal y por qué lugares invadirían á Alemania las tropas victoriosas!...

Su decepción no revelaba desaliento. Una esperanza indeterminada pero firme emergía sobre sus
vacilaciones: el generalísimo era el único que poseía el secreto de los sucesos. Y Desnoyers
aprobó, con el entusiasmo ciego que le inspiraban las personas cuando depositaba en ellas su
confianza. ¡Joffre!... El caudillo serio y tranquilo lo arreglaría todo finalmente. Nadie debía
dudar de su fortuna: era de los hombres que dicen siempre la última palabra.

Al amanecer abandonó el vagón. «Buena suerte.» Y estrechó las manos de aquellos jóvenes animosos,
que iban á morir tal vez en breve plazo. El tren pudo seguir su camino inmediatamente al encontrar
por casualidad la vía libre, y don Marcelo se vió solo en una estación. En tiempo normal salía
de ella un ferrocarril secundario que pasaba por Villeblanche; pero el servicio estaba suspendido
por falta de personal. Los empleados habían pasado á las grandes líneas, abarrotadas por los
transportes de guerra.

Inútilmente buscó, con los más generosos ofrecimientos, un caballo, un simple carretón tirado
por una bestia cualquiera, para continuar su viaje. La movilización acaparaba lo mejor, y los
demás medios de transporte habían desaparecido con la fuga de los medrosos. Había que hacer
á pie una marcha de quince kilómetros. El viejo no vaciló: ¡adelante! Y empezó á caminar por
una carretera blanca, recta, polvorienta, entre tierras llanas é iguales que se sucedían hasta
el infinito. Algunos grupos de árboles, algunos setos verdes y las techumbres de varias granjas
alteraban la monotonía del paisaje. Los campos estaban cubiertos de rastrojos de la cosecha
reciente. Los pajares abullonaban el suelo con sus conos amarillentos, que empezaban á obscurecerse
tomando un tono de oro oxidado. En las vallas aleteaban los pájaros sacudiendo el rocío del
amanecer.

Los primeros rayos del sol anunciaron un día caluroso. En torno de los pajares vió Desnoyers
una agitación de personas que se levantaban, sacudiendo sus ropas y despertando á otras todavía
dormidas. Eran fugitivos que habían acampado en las inmediaciones de la estación, esperando
un tren que les llevase lejos, sin saber con certeza adónde deseaban ir. Unos procedían de
lejanos departamentos: habían oído el cañón, habían visto aproximarse la guerra, y llevaban
varios días de marcha á la ventura. Otros, al sentir el contagio de este pánico, habían huído
igualmente, temiendo conocer los mismos horrores... Vió madres con sus pequeños en los brazos;
ancianos doloridos que sólo podían avanzar con una mano en el bastón y otra en el brazo de
alguno de su familia; viejas arrugadas é inmóviles como momias, que dormían y viajaban tendidas
en una carretilla. Al despertar el sol á este tropel miserable se buscaban unos á otros con
paso torpe, entumecidos aún por la noche, reconstituyendo los mismos grupos del día anterior.
Muchos avanzaban hacia la estación con la esperanza de un tren que nunca llegaba á formarse,
creyendo ser más dichosos en el día que acababa de nacer. Algunos seguían su camino á lo largo
de los rieles, pensando que la suerte les sería más propicia en otro lugar.

Don Marcelo anduvo toda la mañana. La cinta blanca y rectilínea del camino estaba moteada de
grupos que venían hacia él, semejantes en lontananza á un rosario de hormigas. No vió un solo
caminante que siguiese su misma dirección. Todos huían hacia el Sur; y al encontrar á este
señor de la ciudad, que marchaba bien calzado, con bastón de paseo y sombrero de paja, hacían
un gesto de extrañeza. Le creían tal vez un funcionario, un personaje, alguien del gobierno,
al verle avanzar solo hacia el país que abandonaban á impulsos del terror.

A mediodía pudo encontrar un pedazo de pan, un poco de queso y una botella de vino blanco en
una taberna inmediata al camino. El dueño estaba en la guerra, la mujer gemía en la cama. La
madre, una vieja algo sorda, rodeada de sus nietos, seguía desde la puerta este desfile de
fugitivos que duraba tres días. «¿Por qué huyen, señor?--dijo al caminante--. La guerra sólo
interesa á los soldados. Nosotros, gentes del campo, no hacemos mal á nadie y nada debemos temer.»

Cuatro horas después, al bajar una de las pendientes que forman el valle del Marne, vió á lo
lejos los tejados de Villeblanche en torno de su iglesia, y emergiendo de una arboleda las
caperuzas de pizarra que remataban los torreones de su castillo.

Las calles del pueblo estaban desiertas. Sólo en los alrededores de la plaza vió sentadas algunas
mujeres, como en las tardes plácidas de otros veranos. La mitad del vecindario había huído;
la otra mitad permanecía en sus hogares, por rutina sedentaria, engañándose con un ciego optimismo.
Si llegaban los prusianos, ¿qué podían hacerles?... Obedecerían sus órdenes sin intentar ninguna
resistencia, y á un pueblo que obedece no es posible castigarlo... Todo era preferible antes
que perder unas viviendas levantadas por sus antepasados y de las que nunca habían salido.

En la plaza vió, formando un grupo, al alcalde y los principales habitantes. Todos ellos, así
como las mujeres, miraron con asombro al dueño del castillo. Era la más inesperada de las apariciones.
Cuando tantos huían hacia París, este parisién venía á juntarse con ellos, participando de
su suerte. Una sonrisa de afecto, una mirada de simpatía, parecieron atravesar su áspera corteza
de rústicos desconfiados. Hacía mucho tiempo que Desnoyers vivía en malas relaciones con el
pueblo entero. Sostenía ásperamente sus derechos, sin admitir tolerancias en asuntos de propiedad.
Habló muchas veces de procesar al alcalde y enviar á la cárcel á la mitad del vecindario, y
sus enemigos le contestaban invadiendo traidoramente sus tierras, matando su caza, abrumándolo
con reclamaciones judiciales y pleitos incoherentes... Su odio al municipio le había aproximado
al cura, por vivir éste en franca hostilidad contra el alcalde. Pero sus relaciones con la
Iglesia fueron tan infructuosas como sus luchas con el Estado. El cura era un bonachón, al
que encontraba cierto parecido físico con Renán, y que únicamente se preocupaba de sacarle
limosnas para los pobres, llevando su atrevimiento bondadoso hasta excusar á los merodeadores
de su propiedad.

¡Cuán lejanas le parecían ahora las luchas sostenidas hasta un mes antes!... El millonario
experimentó una gran sorpresa al ver cómo el sacerdote, saliendo de su casa para entrar en
la iglesia, saludaba al pasar al alcalde con una sonrisa amistosa.

Después de largos años de mutismo hostil se habían encontrado en la tarde del 1.º de Agosto
al pie de la torre de la iglesia. La campana sonaba á rebato para anunciar la movilización
á los hombres que estaban en los campos. Y los dos enemigos, instintivamente, se habían estrechado
la mano. ¡Todos franceses! Esta unanimidad afectuosa salía también al encuentro del odiado
señor del castillo. Tuvo que saludar á un lado y á otro, apretando manos duras. Las gentes
prorrumpían á sus espaldas en cariñosas rectificaciones. «Un hombre bueno, sin más defecto
que la violencia de su carácter...» Y el señor Desnoyers conoció por unos minutos el grato
ambiente de la popularidad.

Al verse en el castillo dió por bien empleada la fatiga de la marcha, que hacía temblar sus
piernas. Nunca le había parecido tan grande y majestuoso su parque como en este atardecer de
verano; nunca tan blancos los cisnes que se deslizaban, dobles por el reflejo, sobre las aguas
muertas; nunca tan señorial el edificio, cuya imagen repetía invertida el verde espejo de los
fosos. Sintió necesidad de ver inmediatamente los establos con sus animales vacunos; luego
echó una ojeada á las cuadras vacías. La movilización se había llevado sus mejores caballos
de labor. Igualmente había desaparecido su personal. El encargado de los trabajos y varios
mozos estaban en el ejército. En todo el castillo sólo quedaba el conserje, un hombre de más
de cincuenta años, enfermo del pecho, con su familia, compuesta de su mujer y una hija. Los
tres cuidaban de llenar los pesebres de las vacas, ordeñando de tarde en tarde sus ubres olvidadas.

En el interior del edificio volvió á congratularse de la resolución que le había arrastrado
hasta allí. ¡Cómo abandonar tales riquezas!... Contempló los cuadros, las vitrinas, los muebles,
los cortinajes, todo bañado en oro por el resplandor moribundo del día, y sintió el orgullo
de la posesión. Este orgullo le infundió un valor absurdo, inverosímil, como si fuese un ser
gigantesco procedente de otro planeta y toda la humanidad que le rodeaba un simple hormiguero
que podía borrar con los pies. ¡Que viniesen los enemigos! Se consideraba con fuerzas para
defenderse de todos ellos... Luego, al arrancarle la razón de su delirio heroico, intentó tranquilizarse
con un optimismo falto igualmente de solidez. No vendrían. El no sabía por qué, pero le anunciaba
el corazón que los enemigos no llegarían hasta allí.

La mañana siguiente la pasó recorriendo los prados artificiales que había formado detrás del
parque, lamentando el abandono en que estaban por la marcha de sus hombres, intentando abrir
las compuertas para dar un riego al pasto, que empezaba á secarse. Las viñas alineaban sus
masas de pámpanos á lo largo de los alambrados que las servían de sostén. Los racimos repletos,
próximos á la madurez, asomaban entre las hojas sus triángulos granulados. ¡Ay, quién recogería
esta riqueza!...

Por la tarde notó un movimiento extraordinario en el pueblo. Georgette, la hija del conserje,
trajo la noticia de que empezaban á pasar por la calle principal automóviles enormes, muchos
automóviles, y soldados franceses, muchos soldados. Al poco rato se inició el desfile por una
carretera inmediata al castillo, que conducía al puente sobre el Marne. Eran camiones cerrados
ó abiertos que aún conservaban sus antiguos rótulos comerciales bajo la capa de polvo endurecido
y las salpicaduras de barro. Muchos de ellos ostentaban títulos de empresas de París; otros
el nombre social de establecimientos de provincias. Y juntos con estos vehículos industriales
requisados por la movilización pasaron otros procedentes del servicio público, que causaban
en Desnoyers el mismo efecto que unos rostros amigos entrevistos en una muchedumbre desconocida.
Eran ómnibus de París que aún mantenían en su parte alta los nombres indicadores de sus antiguos
trayectos: Madeleine-Bastille, Passy-Bourse, etc. Tal vez había viajado él muchas veces en
estos mismos vehículos, despintados, aviejados por veinte días de actividad intensa, con las
planchas abolladas, los hierros torcidos, sonando á desvencijamiento y perforados como cribas.

Unos carruajes ostentaban redondeles blancos con el centro cortado por la cruz roja; otros
tenían como marca letras y cifras que sólo podían entender los iniciados en los secretos de
la administración militar. Y en todos estos vehículos, que únicamente conservaban nuevos y
vigorosos sus motores, vió soldados, muchos soldados, pero todos heridos, con la cabeza y las
piernas entrapajadas, rostros pálidos que una barba crecida hacía aún más trágicos, ojos de
fiebre que miraban fijamente, bocas dilatadas como si se hubiese solidificado en ellas el gemido
del dolor. Médicos y enfermeros ocupaban varios carruajes de este convoy. Algunos pelotones
de jinetes lo escoltaban. Y entre la lenta marcha de monturas y automóviles pasaban grupos
de soldados á pie, con el capote desabrochado ó pendiente de las espaldas lo mismo que una
capa; heridos que podían caminar y bromeaban y cantaban, unos con un brazo fajado sobre el
pecho, otros con la cabeza vendada, transparentándose á través de la tela el rezumamiento interior
de la sangre.

El millonario quiso hacer algo por ellos; pero apenas intentó distribuir unas botellas de vino,
unos panes, lo primero que encontró á mano, se interpuso un médico, apostrofándole como si
cometiese un delito. Sus regalos podían resultar fatales. Y tuvo que permanecer al borde del
camino, impotente y triste, siguiendo con ojos sombríos el convoy doloroso... Al cerrar la
noche ya no fueron vehículos cargados de hombres enfermos los que desfilaban. Vió centenares
de camiones, unos cerrados herméticamente, con la prudencia que imponen las materias explosivas;
otros con fardos y cajas que esparcían un olor mohoso de víveres. Luego avanzaron grandes manadas
de bueyes, que se arremolinaban en las angosturas del camino, siguiendo adelante bajo el palo
y los gritos de los pastores con kepis.

Pasó la noche desvelado por sus pensamientos. Era la retirada de que hablaban las gentes en
París, pero que muchos no querían creer; la retirada llegando hasta allí y continuando su retroceso
indefinido, pues nadie sabía cual iba á ser su límite. El optimismo le sugirió una esperanza
inverosímil. Tal vez esta retirada comprendía únicamente los hospitales, los almacenes, todo
lo que se estaciona á espaldas de un ejército. Las tropas querían estar libres de impedimenta,
para moverse con más agilidad, y la enviaban lejos por ferrocarriles y carreteras. Así debía
ser. Y en los ruidos que persistieron durante toda la noche sólo quiso adivinar el paso de
vehículos llenos de heridos, de municiones, de víveres, iguales á los que habían desfilado
por la tarde.

Cerca del amanecer, el cansancio le hizo dormirse, y despertó bien entrado el día. Su primera
mirada fué para el camino. Lo vió lleno de hombres y de caballos que tiraban de objetos rodantes.
Pero los hombres llevaban fusiles y formaban batallones, regimientos. Las bestias arrastraban
piezas de artillería. Era un ejército... era la retirada.

Desnoyers corrió al borde del camino para convencerse mejor de la verdad.

¡Ay! Eran regimientos como los que él había visto partir de las estaciones de París... pero
con aspecto muy distinto. Los capotes azules se habían convertido en vestiduras andrajosas
y amarillentas; los pantalones rojos blanqueaban con un color de ladrillo mal cocido; los zapatos
eran bolas de barro. Los rostros tenían una expresión feroz, con regueros de polvo y sudor
en todas sus grietas y oquedades, con barbas recién crecidas, agudas como púas, con un gesto
de cansancio que revelaba el deseo de hacer alto, de quedarse allí mismo para siempre, matando
ó muriendo, pero sin dar un paso más. Caminaban... caminaban... caminaban. Algunas marchas
habían durado treinta horas. El enemigo iba sobre sus huellas, y la orden era de andar y no
combatir, librándose por ligereza de pies de los movimientos envolventes intentados por el
invasor. Los jefes adivinaban el estado de ánimo de sus hombres. Podían exigir el sacrificio
de su vida, ¡pero ordenarles que marchasen día y noche, siempre huyendo del enemigo, cuando
no se consideraban derrotados, cuando sentían gruñir en su interior la cólera feroz, madre
del heroísmo!... Las miradas de desesperación buscaban al oficial inmediato, á los jefes, al
mismo coronel. ¡No podían más! Una marcha enorme, anonadadora, en tan pocos días, ¿y para qué?...
Los superiores, que sabían lo mismo que ellos, parecían contestar con los ojos, como si poseyesen
un secreto: «¡Animo! Otro esfuerzo... Esto va á terminar muy pronto.»

Las bestias, vigorosas, pero desprovistas de imaginación, resistían menos que los hombres.
Su aspecto era deplorable. ¿Cómo podían ser los mismos caballos fuertes y de pelo lustroso
que él había visto en los desfiles de París á principios del mes anterior? Una campaña de veinte
días los había envejecido y agotado. Su mirada opaca parecía implorar piedad. Estaban flacos,
con una delgadez que hacía sobresalir las aristas de su osamenta y aumentaba el abultamiento
de sus ojos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09257</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>299051</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18449</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> When all fled to Paris, he needed to go in the opposite direction. The Senator could
not believe my ears.

- Are you crazy! - He said -. You have to leave Paris, but toward the south. You I say only,
Calella, because it is a secret. We leave at any moment, all we go: the president, the government,
"Chambers. We settle in Bordeaux, as in 1870. The enemy is going to get there: it is a matter
of days ... of hours. We know little of what happens, but all news is bad. The military remains
firm, remains intact, but is removed ... removed, giving way ... Believe me, it's best to leave
Paris. Gallieni will defend, but the defense is going to be hard and painful ... Although falling Paris,
why not drop France. Continue war if necessary to the border of Spain
... But this is sad, very sad!

And he offered to his friend take him in the retreat of Bordeaux,
that few knew in that time.

Desnoyers shook his head. No, he wanted to go to the castle of Villeblanche.

Its furniture ... their wealth ... park.

- But are you going to fall prisoner! - Protested the senator -. Maybe kill him!

A shrug was the answer. Energies are considered to combat all German armies defending their property.
The important thing was installed in it, and anyone who dared to touch yours! ... The senator looked
in amazement to this bourgeois rage by the sense of possession. He remembered the Arab merchants,
humble and peaceful ordinarily, who fight and die like beasts when they're taking over the
Bedouin thieves of their gender.

The moment was not for discussion, everyone should think about their own fate. The senator finally
given the desire of his friend. If such was his pleasure, could accomplish. And got to his influence
that come out that night on a military train that went to meet the army.

This trip was contacted Don Marcelo with extraordinary movement that the war had developed on the
railway. His train took fourteen hours to save a run away two normally. It consisted of boxcars
full of food and ammunition, with doors closed and sealed. A third car was occupied by the escort
of the train: territorial firing.

In a second-Desnoyers was installed, with the lieutenant who commanded this group and several officers
who were to join their regiments after completing mobilization operations manned populations before
the war. Wagons tail containing their horses.

The train stopped many times to give way to others who are full of soldiers put through or returned
to Paris with crowds fugitive. The latter consisted of platforms load, and they huddle together women,
children, seniors, mixed with bundles of clothes, bags and trucks that had served to bring to
the station all that remained their outfits.

Camps were like trailers that are immobile for many hours and even days in the sidings, allowing
free passage to convoys driven by the pressing needs of war. The crowd, accustomed to endless
detentions, overflowed outside train locomotive facilities with dead or scattered by the immediate
field.

At stations of any importance, all avenues were occupied by strings of wagons. The machines, high
pressure to, whistled, eager to leave. Groups of soldiers doubted to the various trains, mistakenly
went down a few cars to be installed in others. Employees, calmly and with an air of fatigue,
going from one side to the other leading to men, giving explanations, having the burden of
mountains of objects. In the convoy carrying Desnoyers to the territorial dozing, accustomed
to the monotonous operation to escort. The charge of the horses had opened the sliding doors
of the cars, sitting on the edge with his legs dangling. The train was going slowly at night,
through shadow fields, stopping at the red lights to warn its presence long whistles. In some
stations had girls dressed in white with ribbons and flags on the chest. Day and night were
there, replaced, not to pass a train without receiving your check.

In baskets and trays offered their gifts to the soldiers, bread, chocolate, fruit. Many, for
fill, tried to resist, but finally had to cede before the frown of the youngsters. To Desnoyers found
himself assaulted by these gifts of patriotic enthusiasm.

He spent much of the night talking with your fellow travelers. The officers were only vague
indications of where they could find their regiments. The operations of the war changed daily situation.
But faithful to duty, went forward, hoping to reach time for the decisive battle. The head of
the convoy had made several trips and was the only one who realized exact withdrawal. Every
time the train was a trip lower. Everyone seemed disoriented. Why withdrawal? ... The army had
suffered setbacks sure, but it was whole, and in his opinion should
seek revenge in the same places.

The retreat left open the enemy's advance. How far would he go back? ... They discussed two weeks
earlier point in their garrisons in Belgium where they would receive adversaries the fatal blow
and why more troops would invade Germany victorious! ...

His disappointment showed no discouragement.

An undetermined but firm hope emerged on their hesitation: Generalissimo was the only one who possessed
the secret of the events. And Desnoyers approved, with the blind enthusiasm which inspired the people
when deposited in them their confidence. Joffre! ... The leader serious and calm it all out eventually.
Nobody should doubt his fortune was of men who say the last word.

At dawn he left the car.

"Good luck." And shook the hands of those young, enthusiastic that maybe they were going to die
soon. The train could be on their way immediately to find free road accident, and Don Marcelo
was seen only in one season. In normal time left it a secondary rail Villeblanche passing by,
but the service was suspended because of staff shortages. The employees had gone to the great
lines, crowded by transport of war.

Vain sought, with the most generous offers, a horse, a cart pulled simple either by a beast,
to continue his journey. The mobilization was monopolizing the best, and other means of transport had
disappeared with the flight of the cowards. Had to do to walk a march of ten miles. The old
man did not hesitate: go!

And he began to walk a white road, straight, dusty plains and equal between that lined up infinity.
Some groups of trees, some green hedges and the roofs of several farms alter the monotony of the
landscape. The fields were covered with crop stubble recent. Haystacks puffed the ground with
their yellow cones, which were beginning to darken taking an oxidized gold tone. At the billboard
shaking birds fluttering spray dawn.

The first rays of the sun announced a hot day. Around the barns saw Desnoyers a flurry of people
who stood up, shaking his clothes and waking up to yet other asleep. Were fugitives who had
camped near the station, waiting a train to take them away, not knowing for sure where they wanted
to go. Some came from distant departments had heard the cannon, had been approaching war, and
carried several days of walking at random. Others, feeling the contagion of this panic, had fled
also, fearing know the horrors ... He saw mothers with small arms; old sore that could only
move with one hand on the stick and another in the arm any of his family crones and motionless
as mummies, lying asleep and traveled in a wheelbarrow.

On waking the sun to this wretched throng looked at each other with stiff gait, stiff even at
night, retracing the same groups the day before. Many advanced towards the station with the hope
of a train that never came to be formed, believed to be more happy on the day was born. Some
continued their way along the tracks, thinking that it would be more conducive luck elsewhere.

Don
Marcelo walked all morning. The white ribbon of road was straight and mottled groups that came
to him in the distance like a string of ants. No one saw Walker to
continue the same direction.

All were fleeing to the South, and to find this lord of the city, which was fine footwear, walking
stick and a straw hat, made a gesture of surprise. I thought maybe an officer, a character,
someone from the government, to see him go it alone to the country they left to impulses of
terror.

At noon he could find a piece of bread, some cheese and a bottle of white wine a tavern on the
road immediately. The owner was in the war, she was moaning in bed. The mother, a rather deaf
old, surrounded by her grandchildren, was at the door this parade
fugitives lasted three days.

"Why run away, sir?" - Said the traveler -. The war only interest to the soldiers. We country people
do not do evil to no one and nothing to fear. "

Four hours later, dropping one of the slopes that form the valley of the Marne, he saw what Villeblanche
away roofs around his church, and emerging from a grove of shale caps finished off the turrets
of the castle.

The village streets were deserted. Just around the square sit saw some women, as in other summers placid
evenings. Half the neighborhood had fled; the other half remained in their homes, sedentary
routine, fooling with blind optimism. If the Prussians arrived, what could they do to them? ...
Obey his orders without attempting any resistance, due to a people who can not punish him ...
Everything was better before to lose some houses built by their ancestors and who had never left.

In
the square he saw, forming a group, the mayor and the principal inhabitants. These, and and
women, watched with amazement the owner of the castle. It was the most unexpected occurrences.
When so many fled to Paris, the Parisian came to join them, sharing their fate. A smile of affection,
a look of sympathy, appeared through its rough bark of rustic suspicious. Desnoyers had long
lived on bad terms with entire people. Roughly maintained their rights, make allowance in
property matters. He spoke many times to process the mayor and send to prison half the neighborhood,
and answered his enemies treacherously invaded their lands, killing their game, overwhelming
legal claims and lawsuits with incoherent ... His hatred of the town
had approximately the priest, to live it in open hostility against
the mayor.

But his relations with the Church were as unsuccessful as their struggles with the state.
The priest was a good-natured, the they found some resemblance to Renan, who only get worried
alms for the poor, bringing its kind to excuse daring marauders of
your property.

How far now the struggle seemed held up to a month before! ... Millionaire experienced a great surprise
to see how the priest, leaving his house to enter the church, passing the mayor greeted with
a friendly smile.

After long years of hostile silence had been found on the afternoon of January. St August at
the foot of the tower of the church.

The bell sounded the alarm to announce mobilization the men who were in the fields. And the
two enemies, instinctively, had narrowed hand. All French! It also unanimously find out loving
the hated lord of the castle. Had to say hello to one side to another, shaking hands hard. People
broke out behind him in loving corrections. "A good man, with no default the violence of his
character ... "And Mr. Desnoyers met for a few minutes the pleasant popularity environment.

Finding
himself in the castle as well spent given the fatigue of travel, that shook their legs. She
had never seemed so big and majestic as the park this evening of summer, never as white swans
glided, double by the reflection on water dead, never so stately building, whose image repeated
inverted mirror of the green pits. Felt the need to immediately see the cattle barns with their
animals, then He glanced at the empty blocks. The mobilization had
taken their best horses of work.

Staff also had disappeared. The charge of the work and several boys were in the military. Throughout
the castle there was only the caretaker, a man over fifty years, sick of the chest, with his family,
consisting of his wife and daughter. The three tended to fill the stalls of cows, milking now
and then forgotten their udders.

Inside the building again to welcome the resolution that had dragged there. How to give up
such riches! ... Looked at the tables, cabinets, furniture, the curtains, all bathed in gold by the glow
dying day, and felt proud possession. This value instilled pride absurd, improbable, as if it were
a being giant from another planet and all mankind around him a simple
anthill I could clear with his feet.

That should come enemies! It was considered strong enough defend all of them ... Then, to snatch
the reason for his heroic frenzy, tried to calm also lacks a solid optimism. Do not come. He
did not know why, but he announced the heart that the enemy would not reach there.

The next morning was spent touring the artificial grass that had formed behind Park, lamenting the
neglect that were by the departure of his men, trying to open gates
to give a watering grass, which was beginning to dry.

The vines align their mass of branches along the fences that served as support. Packed clusters,
coming to maturity, the leaves sticking out their triangles granules. Oh, who collect this wealth!
...

In the afternoon he noticed an extraordinary movement in the village. Georgette, the daughter of
the concierge, brought the news that began to go through the huge main street cars, many automobiles,
and French soldiers, many soldiers. Soon the parade was initiated by a immediate road to the
castle, leading to the bridge over the Marne. Trucks were closed open or still retained their
old commercial signs in the dust layer hardened and splashes of mud. Many of them hold diplomas
of the Paris business, others the corporate name of establishments in the provinces. And together
with these vehicles requisitioned by the mobilization took another from the public service,
causing Desnoyers in the same effect as some friendly faces in a crowd glimpsed unknown. Paris
buses were still kept in top names of his former indicators paths:
Madeleine-Bastille, Passy-Bourse, etc. Perhaps he had traveled many
times these vehicles, faded, aviejados twenty days of intense activity,
with plates dented, twisted irons, sounding as ramshackle and perforated
screens.

Some coaches sported white roundels with the center cut by the Red Cross, others had as a mark
letters and numbers that only the initiated could understand the secrets of military administration.
And in all these vehicles, new and retained only vigorous engines, saw soldiers, many soldiers,
but all injured, with head and bandaged legs, pale faces a beard made it even more tragic eyes Stare
fever, dilated mouths as if they have been frozen in the groan pain. Doctors and nurses occupied
several carriages of the train. Some platoons riders escorting him. Among the slow pace of
automobile frames and groups spent of soldiers on foot, with unbuttoned coat the back slope
or the same as a layer; wounded who could walk and joke and sing, some with an arm swaddled
on chest, another with his head bandaged, transparent through the oozing interior fabric of blood.

The
billionaire wanted to do something for them, but just tried to distribute
some bottles of wine, about bread, the first thing that came handy,
interposed a doctor, apostrophes as if committed a crime.

Your gifts could be fatal. And he had to stay on the edge of way, helpless, sad, dark eyes following
the convoy painful ... Closing the night and no vehicles were loaded with sick men who marched.
He saw hundreds truck, a sealed, with prudence imposed by explosives; some with bundles and
boxes scattered musty smell of food. Then moved large herds of oxen, which swirled in the
narrows of the road, moving forward on the stick and the cries of the shepherds to his vest.

He
spent the night awake by your thoughts. It was the withdrawal of people speaking in Paris, but many
refused to believe, the withdrawal coming up there and continuing to decline indefinite, because
nobody knew what was going to be your limit. The optimism suggested a hope unlikely. Maybe this
retreat included only hospitals, warehouses, all that is parked in
the rear of an army.

The troops wanted to be free of baggage, to move with more agility, and sent away by rail and
road. This was to be. And noise that persisted throughout the night just wanted to guess the pass carloads
of wounded, ammunition, food, equal to those who had marched afternoon.

Near dawn, fatigue made him fall asleep, and woke up late in the day. His first was looking for
the road. He saw it full of men and horses pulling trailers objects. But the men were carrying
guns and battalions, regiments. The beasts dragged artillery. It was an army ... was removed.

Desnoyers
ran to the edge of the road for better convinced of the truth.

Ay! Regiments were like those he had seen from stations in Paris ... but look very different.
The blue coats had become tattered clothes and yellowish red pants with a whitewashed brick color
undercooked; shoes were balls of clay. The face was fierce, with trails of dust and sweat in
all its cracks and crevices, with newly grown beard, sharp as pins,
with a gesture fatigue that revealed a desire to stop, to stay right
there forever, killing or dying, but go a step further.

Walking ... walking ... walked. Some marches had lasted thirty hours.

The enemy was on his tracks, and the order was walking and not battle, waged by the lightness
of feet outflanking attempted by the invader. The heads guessed the mood of his men. Could
require the sacrifice of his life, but marching orders day and night, always fleeing from the enemy
when not considered to be defeated, when they felt inside growl fierce anger, mother heroism!
... The looks of despair looking for the officer immediately to the chiefs, the Colonel himself.
They could not anymore! A huge place, stunned, in a few days, and for what? ... Superiors, who
knew the same thing they seemed to answer with his eyes, as if possessed a secret: "Courage!
Another effort ... This is going to end very soon. "

The beasts, vigorous, but devoid of imagination, resisted less than men. His appearance was deplorable.
How could they be the same horses strong and lustrous hair he had seen in parades in Paris
at the beginning of the month? A twenty year days had aged and exhausted. His eyes seemed
to implore mercy opaque. Were weak, with a thin edges that made their stand and increased bone
bulging their eyes.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>