<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07122</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>66115</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19255</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Todo lo que la había dicho
en contrario, era un embuste para explotar su candorosa ignorancia. Se le podía haber cogido
en una de sus emboscadas, como a un zorro en el cepo, como se le cogería de seguro si aún andaba
por allí...

A esto se estremeció de espanto la angustiada mujer y volvió a caer de rodillas delante de
mí, para pedirme por Dios crucificado que no se hiciera tal cosa. También a ella se la había
ocurrido alguna vez que podía no ser verdad todo lo que él la decía «al auto de aquellos particulares»;
pero ¿y qué?... Si lo que la acongojaba no era eso, sino el temor al ruido y al escándalo;
a que el lugar se enterara del caso, y después don Celso y, sobre todo, su hija, ¡Oh, esto
nunca!... ¡Tapar, tapar y no más que tapar!... Por ello, la vida suya y cien vidas y mil vidas;
el suplicio en cruz, en la lumbre de un horno; descuartizada viva... enterrada en salud, entre
sapos y serpientes.

--¿Y el robo también?--la interrumpí con mal disimulada dureza.

--¡Señor!--me respondió como aterrada por el sonido de la pregunta--. Aunque capaz fuera de
eyu, ¿qué sé yo ónde guarda las riquezas el mi amo, ni si las tiene en casa tan siquiera?

Aquí me refirió, espiritada y convulsa, después de sentarse otra vez, por mis reiterados mandatos,
cómo, no teniendo valor para hacer lo que el infame la proponía, ni resolución bastante para
negarse a ello, había ido entreteniéndole las impaciencias con aquel reparo y con el de la
continua presencia mía y de otras gentes en la casa con motivo de la recaída de su amo (porque
esto ocurrió en los días que siguieron a la nevada); pero, aunque de todo estaba enterado él,
a nada de ello daba la menor importancia: al contrario, sostenía que al amparo de aquellos
quehaceres y preocupaciones, era como mejor podía ella lograr sus intentos, si los ponía por
obra. Esto, por las buenas; porque si aún la parecía mucho, acudiría a las malas, pues, por
las malas o por las buenas, ello había de hacerse, y en el aire.

La infeliz no sabía qué partido tomar dentro de aquel estrecho círculo de hierro candente,
abrasador; y como las impaciencias del pícaro no daban la menor tregua, un día, la víspera
del en que Facia me lo contaba, la había dicho él: «Puesto que no te resuelves a cogerlo con
tus manos, «hemos» resuelto «nosotros» robarlo con las nuestras. Hacia la media noche de mañana,
cuando ya no quede señal de hombre en la cocina ni chispa de rescoldo en el hogar y duerman
todos en la casa, llegaremos al portón de la calleja. Entonces oirás un silbido de este aire
(y silbó por lo bajo de cierto modo). Sin más que oírle, te llegas callandito al estragal y
me abres la puerta, con tal finura y cuidado, que ni las mismas bisagras se enteren de ello.
Lo demás corre de nuestra cuenta. Ya daremos con el gato, por escondido que esté. Si hay alguno
demasiado ligero de sueño, boca abajo para in saecula en cuanto se despierte, y el primero
tu amo, si es que no ha habido que empezar por su sobrino... o no se dejan amarrar todos con
la docilidad que pide el caso. Conque ya estás advertida, y bien te consta cómo las gasto.
Sabiendo que me juego la vida en el trance, figúrate lo que se me importará de la tuya si hay
que ponerla en pleito porque se te haya ido un poco la lengua en todo el día, y por razón de
ello no encontramos la casa por la noche en el sosiego y la tranquilidad que siempre tuvo a
tales horas.»

Dicho todo esto con un cinismo feroz, marchóse, dejando a Facia más muerta que viva. Y así
estaban las cosas; y estando así, ¿cómo gozar hora de sueño ni minuto de tranquilidad, ni cómo
dejar de confesarlo al fin y al postre, ni a quién, sino a mí?

Interesóme de veras el caso, porque vistos los antecedentes del «caballero» aquél y de sus
fidalgos camaradas, no era para tomarlo a risa; y después de meditar un poco mientras Facia
gemía y se retorcía las manos cadavéricas, la dije:

--¿De manera que eso ha de suceder esta misma noche?

--Así fue la amenaza--respondióme, casi sin voz para ello.

Notaba yo que la pobre mujer estaba en aquellos instantes bajo la doble tortura de los sucesos
mismos declarados, y del temor a lo que pudiera alcanzarla del mal juicio que yo hubiera formado
de todo ello; inspirábame honda compasión, y con el fin de aliviarla un poco de ambos tormentos,
la hablé así:

--En primer lugar, del dicho al hecho siempre hay gran trecho, y mucho más si los hechos son
de la magnitud de éste que a usted la espanta; de manera que las amenazas de venir esta noche
esos bandoleros a desvalijar a mi tío, se cumplirán... o no se cumplirán; y bien pesado y medido
todo, quizás fuera preferible que vinieran, particularmente para usted, por aquello de que
«muerto el perro, se acabó la rabia». En segundo lugar, con la confesión que usted me ha hecho,
y ¡ojalá se le hubiera ocurrido hacérmela la primera vez que topó con su marido en la fuente!
si no viene por aquí esta noche a liquidar todas sus deudas en una sola partida, tengo todo
lo que necesito saber para obligarle, por la cuenta que le trae, a que abandone esta comarca
callandito la boca y a buen andar por donde nadie le vea, y la deje a usted en santa paz por
todos los días de su vida. De manera que no hay para qué gemir ni angustiarse, como usted gime
y se angustia. Déjelo, pues, todo a mi cargo; obedézcame en cuanto yo disponga; comience por
arreglarse el tocado y el vestido, después de alegrar un poco los sombríos celajes de la cara;
vuelva a ocuparse desde ahora en sus ordinarios quehaceres con el remango que solía; atienda
a mi tío como siempre, y cuide mucho de que Tona no empiece a poner en duda las disculpas con
que, en éstos y otros días de tormenta, ha estado usted engañando su candidez. Conque ya está
usted absuelta de todo pecado por lo que a mí toca; y ánimo, y a cumplir la penitencia que
la acabo de imponer.

Con esto la di dos palmaditas en la espalda; logré que las angustias desesperadas de antes
se trocaran en copioso y sosegado llanto; incorporóse al fin con cierto brío; intentó, y no
se lo consentí, besarme las manos; y después de prometerme que emplearía todos los alientos
que la quedaban de los suyos y los que yo la había prestado, en obedecer mis mandatos, se dirigió
a la puerta. Pero yo no sé qué vio de pronto en la luz del aposento, que se lanzó, con aquella
fuerza que siempre la arrastraba, un tiempo hacía, a leer los fenómenos meteorológicos en la
bóveda celeste, a uno de los cuarterones de la puerta de la solana. Allí se estuvo unos instantes
devorando el espacio con los ojos. Acerquéme yo al otro cuarterón, y exclamó ella entonces:

--¡Ay, señor don Marcelo!... Si las señales no mintieran, ¡qué suerte la nuestra!... ¡Miri,
miri esas nieblas que abajan por ayí... y por ayí, y por toas partes; miri esi cielu encenizau
y escuru; miri aqueyas motas negras de ayá arriba, que son butres que pasan cara acá!... Pos
lo unu y lo otru y too eyu en juntu, y ese frío que ahora noto que se sienti, too es nieve,
nieve pura que se cuez y está pa caer de una hora a otra. ¡Si el Señor y mi Padre de los cielos
fuera tan misericordiosu que tampocu esta vez fallaran los barruntus!...

Y con esto abandonó el observatorio sin esperar mi respuesta, y salió del gabinete casi batiendo
las palmas y con una agilidad desconocida en ella mucho tiempo hacía.

Yo me quedé ¿a qué negarlo? haciendo votos porque los barruntos no fallaran; después medité
un rato sobre los sucesos que podrían ocurrir aquella noche; y con el esbozo de un plan en
la cabeza, dejé mi cuarto y pasé al de mi tío.

XXVI

En aquel momento entraba Neluco. Yo no había visto al enfermo más que un instante después de
saltar de la cama; nada había respondido a mis preguntas porque dormitaba, y a la escasa luz
que entonces aclaraba un poco las tinieblas del dormitorio, nada tampoco me había chocado en
su aspecto; pero al observarle nuevamente y a mejor luz, ya me pareció cosa muy distinta. Estaba
mucho más anheloso que por la noche, más azulado de color, más vidrioso de mirada, y, sobre
todo, muy atormentado por la tos y muy inquieto en la cama. Miré a Neluco, que le estaba pulsando,
y leí en su cara sombría la confirmación de mi diagnóstico. De pronto, nos dijo él con voz
tenue y silabeando casi las palabras por no alcanzar a más sus alientos:

--Hoy no me gusto pizca, muchachos.

Nos miramos el médico y yo, y le preguntó éste:

--¿Por qué lo dice usted?

--Porque me encuentro peor que el día en que más malo me he visto.

--Aprensiones de usted,--dije yo, por decir algo que le animase.

--Eso ha de verse pronto--respondió el enfermo.

Neluco, entre tanto, continuaba pulsándole, ora en una muñeca, ora en la otra; arrimó el oído
a su pecho, encima del corazón, y le descubrió y palpó las piernas hasta la rodilla; hízole
varias preguntas luego, y, por último, se quedó un buen rato arrimado a la cama y mirándole
fijamente, con la cabeza algo caída, como si no supiera qué decirle o lo estuviera discurriendo
en vista de los fenómenos que observaba. Yo estaba enfrente de Neluco, arrimado a la cama también;
y a la puerta de la alcoba, con los brazos cruzados y en pie, como dos estatuas de la melancolía
y de la curiosidad, Facia y su hija esperando órdenes. Las primeras fueron de mi tío para pedir
«otra almohada», y eso que pasaban de tres las que le servían de apoyo para sus espaldas y cabeza.

Mientras las dos mujeres cumplían el mandato y mullían y arreglaban el montón resultante para
menor incomodidad del enfermo, salió Neluco del dormitorio y yo tras él, por una seña que me hizo.

--Esto va por la posta--me dijo, de modo que no lo oyera el enfermo.

--¿Tan grave le halla usted?--preguntéle.

--Gravísimo--me respondió--. Cuestión de horas más o menos. Así es que si apunta el menor deseo
de confesarse, no se le contraríen por ningún miramiento; y si no le apunta... procuren ustedes
apuntársele. No le dispongo nada nuevo, porque todo sería inútil, incluso la mortificación
de una cantárida. La hinchazón de las piernas, como usted habrá visto, ha tomado esta noche
un gran incremento... el propio y natural del avance repentino que ha dado la enfermedad, quizás
por el rápido descenso que ha habido en la temperatura esta madrugada... porque no sé si habrá
usted notado que hace un frío desde el amanecer, que corta un pelo.

Esto del frío produjo en mi imaginación un trastrueque súbito de ideas; y olvidando al enfermo,
no me acordé más que de la intentona dispuesta por los tres forajidos para aquella noche; y
así es que pregunté a Neluco con la misma avidez que pudo hacerlo Facia en sus «mejores días»
de espantos y congojas:

--¿Cree usted que nevará?

--Y de firme--me respondió Neluco--. Todos los síntomas son de una nevada de las más copiosas
y duraderas que se descuelgan por acá.

--¿Y cree usted también--insistí--, que empezará hoy mismo?

--Como que ya empezaba cuando yo he venido--me contestó--. ¡Vea usted!

Y me condujo a la puerta de la solana, desde cuyos cuarterones vimos pasar, llevados por el
airecillo glacial que soplaba afuera, algunos copos, idénticos a los que yo había visto al
empezar la otra novela. Sin embargo, el cielo no estaba tan «encenizado» ni sombrío como entonces.
Así se lo advertí al médico, y él me replicó:

--Pero todo se andará, y pronto, no lo dude usted. Por lo mismo--añadió--, hay que tener mucho
cuidado con el abrigo de estas habitaciones. Que no falte de aquí el brasero bien quemado,
de modo que se conserve inalterable la temperatura que ahora hay en el cuarto del enfermo.
No ha de sanarle la precaución, ni de mejorarle siquiera, por supuesto; pero hay que poner
de nuestra parte, en bien de él, todo cuanto sea posible... Otra cosa: en vista de lo que ocurre,
y, particularmente, de lo que pueda ocurrir, hace aquí falta más gente que ustedes, por razones
que en otra ocasión análoga le di, y pienso avisar a Mari Pepa para que venga enseguida con
su hija... Es posible que le diga también algo a don Sabas, para que esté prevenido siquiera.

Con poco más que esto y unas advertencias que me hizo concernientes al enfermo después de pasar
otra ratito a su lado, se fue Neluco y quedéme yo sumido en las más endiabladas cavilaciones.
El mismo Satanás, puesto a discurrir un conflicto para la casona, no le hubiera hilado tan
bien como lo estaba el que yo temía para aquella noche, si las amenazas del baratijero se realizaban,
o no venía a impedirlo y arreglarlo todo el deus ex machina de la nieve, en la dosis en que
me la había pronosticado Neluco. Porque de otro modo, «¡Virgen la mi Madre celeste!», como
habría dicho en igual caso la mujer gris. Don Celso, agonizante quizás a aquellas horas, o
tal vez cadáver ya; Lita y su madre a su lado, asistiéndole o rezando por él; Facia en los
paroxismos de su reproducida tribulación; tres bandoleros asaltando la casa, y yo, con Chisco
y Pito Salces, a tiro limpio con ellos, acabando de matar con el susto a mi tío, si aún vivía,
y poniendo a punto de morir de congoja a las mujeres, a dos de las cuales, por lo menos, estaba
yo obligado a defender de todo riesgo mientras me quedaran un soplo de vida, un cartucho que
quemar o un asador que esgrimir. Recién oída por mí la confesión de Facia, me había imaginado
este cuadro mucho más sencillo. Chisco, Pito Salces y yo, armados hasta los dientes y bien
apercibidos, en acecho y sin respirar, en las tinieblas del portalón; uno de nosotros abriendo
la puerta con las precauciones convenidas en cuanto se dejara oír afuera el silbido del baratijero,
y luego los tres, según iban entrando los bandidos... ¡fuego a quemarropa sobre ellos! Ni el
primer peldaño de la escalera habían de profanar con su pie los infames. Para que no se sobrecogiera
mi tío con el estruendo, le habría engañado yo antes con un embuste cualquiera: le habría dicho,
por ejemplo, que se había visto la noche antes el lobo rondando la casa por aquel lado, y que
pensábamos matarle en las altas horas de la inmediata si volvía. Las agallas de Chisco y de
Pito Salces me eran bien conocidas, y no había para qué avisar más gente ni dar cuarto al pregonero.
Nos bastábamos los tres para aquella empresa por de pronto: lo demás, es decir, el recoger
los despojos de la batalla, los cadáveres achicharrados y hechos jigote, ya lo haría la justicia
oportunamente avisada. Y a esto se reduciría todo. Pero con el nuevo aspecto de las cosas,
ignorado por los bandidos; con la casa llena de mujeres, y la muerte, con su cortejo de lágrimas
y de ceremonias y accesorios patéticos, enseñoreada de ella, ¡qué perturbaciones y qué escándalos
y qué profanaciones y sacrilegios no produciría una batalla en el estragal, a tiro seco, con
sus correspondientes blasfemias y alaridos, y cadáveres ensangrentados y palpitantes! En fin,
que si no arreglaba el conflicto la nevada, había para volverme tarumba y tener por cuerda
y resignada a la mujer gris en sus recientes apuros. Por lo pronto, y esto me calmaba algo
las inquietudes, había muchas horas por delante; se vería qué rumbos iba tomando y cómo se
portaba el temporal insinuado, y qué marcha seguía durante la mañana la agravación de mi tío.
Yo bien provisto estaba de armas y municiones; Chisco también, y a mi lado vivía en casa; y
a Chorcos, ya cuidaría yo de avisarle a tiempo para que se quedara a velar con el pretexto
del grave estado de don Celso. No dejó de ocurrírseme que, en lugar de esperar a los salteadores
en el portalón de la casa, se les podía armar una emboscada en los peñascos inmediatos a ella,
y fusilarlos a mansalva en cuanto se arrimaran a la puerta los tres. Pero este plan era menos
«concluyente» que el otro, y estaba expuesto a quiebras que podían salirnos caras a los acometedores,
por más que nos asistiera la justicia, según todas las leyes divinas y humanas. Así y con todo,
se pesarían y medirían ambos planes si llegaba el caso y en su hora, y se optaría por el mejor.

Esto y mucho más lo meditaba yo voltejeando maquinalmente por el interior de la casona después
de haber despedido al médico. Dando, de repente, por bien examinado el punto por entonces,
resolví volver a ver cómo andaba mi tío de sus angustias mortales. Pero no entré en su cuarto
sin asomarme antes a uno de los vidrios de la puerta que daba a la solana por el comedor. El
cielo continuaba obscureciéndose y el chispear de la nieve espesando. Me gustó el síntoma.
Mi tío, aunque entre amagos continuos de la tos, parecía más sosegado, y dormitaba. Facia,
sentada lejos de él y atenta a cuanto pudiera ocurrirle, después que yo hube contemplado al
enfermo acercándome de puntillas a su cama, me dijo con la mirada:

--Bien va eso, ¿eh?

A lo que yo respondí con otra mirada y un gesto:

--De lo mejor.

Pero bien sabe Dios que ni la pregunta ni la respuesta se referían al estado del enfermo, sino
al aspecto del temporal.

Pasaron dos horas sin que dentro ni fuera de la casona ocurriera novedad digna de ser notada,
y llegaron, pero sin el estrépito de costumbre, Lita y su madre y hasta el propio don Pedro
Nolasco. Esta peripecia, relativamente alegre, en el sombrío drama que se desenvolvía, y a
todo andar, en aquellos envejecidos ámbitos, me levantó mucho el espíritu. Venían los tres
personajes hondamente impresionados por las noticias que les había dado Neluco. El gigante,
por todo saludo, me estrechó la mano en silencio, con dos tremendas sacudidas que a poco me
desarticulan el brazo por el hombro; su nieta y su hija, con los ojos empañados, me pidieron,
mientras comenzaban a desliarse los abrigos, y en voz muy baja algo temblorosa, las noticias
de cajón sobre el estado actual de mi tío. Díselas, no tan malas como las que esperaban ellas,
y esto las animó a acercarse muy quedito hasta la puerta de la alcoba. Desde allí estuvieron
contemplando el batallar que no cesaba dentro de las ruinas de don Celso, entre el sueño que
le amodorraba y la tos que se lo prohibía, hasta que se revolvió en la cama por uno de aquellos
choques, del que salió medio sofocado, con la boca y los ojos muy abiertos y acopiando el aire
para respirar, hasta con las manos. Entonces se ocultaron rápidamente, casi de un salto, en
la salona, y se volvieron ambas hacia mí, que no las perdía de vista, con la pena y la conmiseración
pintadas en la cara. A todo esto, don Pedro Nolasco, de pie, rígido, inmóvil y silencioso,
en el mismo sitio en que se había plantado al entrar. Pasó en breve el acceso, y volvió el
enfermo a caer en el marasmo de antes... Pero ¿qué diablos veía yo en Lituca que me cautivaba
más la atención en aquellos momentos que el pasmo de su abuelo y la angustiosa situación de
mi tío? ¿Qué había en ella de nuevo y de extraño para mí? Pues, lisa y llanamente, las lágrimas
de sus ojos y la expresión dolorida de su cara infantil; y yo me preguntaba en cuanto salí
de mis dudas: «Pero ¿cuándo está más mona esta chica? ¿cuando ríe y gorjea como los pajaritos
del monte, sin penas ni cuidados, o cuando siente, como ahora, a falta de dolores propios,
la compasión que le inspiran los ajenos?» Y no sabiendo por cuál de estos extremos optar, quedéme
con los dos, porque es lo cierto que, riendo o llorando, estaba monísima aquella criatura.

Temiendo que la impresionara con exceso la contemplación frecuente de aquel cuadro aflictivo
de la miseria humana, tan nuevo para ella, la aconsejé que se abstuviese de entrar en el cuarto
del enfermo. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02019</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>74936</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17279</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Everything that was said in
contrast, was an innocent lie to exploit their ignorance. You could have picked in one of their
ambushes, like a fox in the trap, as it would take insurance if you have walked there ...

This is thrilled with horror the distraught woman and fell back on his knees before me to ask
me crucified by God not to do such a thing. She also had ever happened that could not be true
all that he said "the order of those individuals'; but so what? ... If that was not grieved that, but the
noise and fear of scandal to the place found out the case, then Don Celso and, above all,
his daughter, Oh, this ever! ... Cover, cover, and no more than cover! ... Therefore, your
life and a hundred lives and a thousand lives; the agony on the cross, in the glow of a furnace,
dismembered alive ... Buried in health, frogs and snakes.

- What about the theft too? - With ill-concealed interrupted harshly.

-
Lord - I responded as terrified by the sound of the question -.

Although capable off EYU, what do I know HERE saves on my master's wealth, or whether it is
even home?

Here I mentioned, spirit and troubled, after sitting down again, by my repeated mandates how,
not having the courage to do what was proposed by the infamous, or resolution enough to refuse,
had been entertaining him impatience with that objection and that of the continued presence of
myself and other people in the house because of the recurrence of his love (because this happened
in the days that followed the snow) but, although all knew about him to none of this was of
no importance: on the contrary, argued that under those chores and concerns, it was like she
could best achieve their attempts, whether placed by work. This, for good, because if he still
looked very much, would come to bad, then, for bad or good, it had
to be done, and in the air.

The poor do not know what course to take in this circle of hot iron, burning, and as the impatience
of the rogue did not give the slightest respite, one day, the day before Facia of which had me,
had told him: "Since we do not take it with you to solve your hands, "we" decided "we" steal
with ours. By midnight tomorrow, when there is no sign of man in the kitchen or embers spark
at home and sleep everyone in the house, get to the gate of the lane. Then you will hear a
hiss of the air (And whistled softly in a way). Needless to hear you and you come creeping to
astragalus I open the door with such finesse and care that neither of them know about it hinges.
The rest is on us. We'll come to the cat, which is hidden. If any too light to sleep, tummy
to in saecula as soon as you wake up, and the first your master, if it has not been started
by his nephew ... and not left to tie all submissiveness to order the case. So you're forewarned,
and how it has cost you. Knowing that life I play trance, imagine what I care for yours if to
put it in a lawsuit because you have gone a little tongue all day, and because of it does not
find the house at night in the calm and tranquility that always had those hours. "

Having said all this with a fierce cynicism, he departed, leaving more dead than alive Facia.
And so things were, and remain so, how to enjoy hours of sleep or quiet minute, or how fail to
confess at last and dessert, or who, but me?

Interesóme really the case, because in view of the history of the "gentleman" and that their
fidalgos comrades, was not to take it to laugh, and after thinking
for a little while Facia moaned and wrung her hands corpses, said:

-
"So this has to happen tonight?

- That was the threat - he replied,
almost inaudibly for it.

I noticed that the poor woman was in those moments under the double torture of events they declared,
and the fear of what might reach the wrong opinion I had formed of it; inspirábame deep compassion
and to relieve a little of both torments I spoke with:

- First, from words to action there is always some distance, and more if the facts are the magnitude
of it that scares you, so that threats come tonight these bandits to rob my uncle, he met ...
or not be met, and well weighed and measured However, it may be preferable to come, particularly
for you, by that which "Dead dog, no more anger." Second, with the confession that you made
me, and I wish I would have thought I have one the first time I met her husband at the source!
if not come here tonight to pay off all your debts into a single game, I have everything I need
to know to force, by the fact that it brings, to abandon this region callandito mouth and good
walking where no one will see, and leave you in peace santa every day of your life. So I must
not whine or fret, as you groan and anxiety. Let, then, all at my expense, obey me as I have,
starting with arranged the headdress and clothing, after a little brighter for the dark colored
clouds of face; now should return to their regular chores that used to Remango; attend my uncle
as always, and take good care of Tona no doubt start with an apology that in these and other storm
days, you were deceiving his candor. So now is you are absolved of all sin as far as I'm concerned,
and encouragement, and to fulfill the penance the just impose.

This gave two slaps on the back, I got that desperate anguish before cut them into copious
tears and calm, sat up at last with some panache, tried, and not
consented to it, kiss my hands, and after promising that he would
use all breaths to the left of yours and that I had borrowed, to obey
my commands, addressed at the door.

But I do not know why he suddenly saw the light of the room, which was launched, with that
drag force always a time did, to read the weather in sky, one of the paneled door utility.
There was a moment space devouring eyes. I approached me the other paneled, and then she cried:

-
Oh, Don Marcelo! ... If the signals do not lie, how lucky it was! ... Miri miri those mists that
down by ayi ... and Ayi, and toas parties; miri cielu encenizau esi and escuru; miri aqueyas above
of aya black specks, which are spent face Boutros here! ... Pos so unu and otru and EYU in juntu
too, and that cold sienti now I notice that, too is snow pure snow is cooked through and fall pa
hour to hour. If the Lord and my Father in heaven that was so misericordiosu
tampocu the barruntus fail this time!

...

And with that he left the observatory without waiting for my answer, and almost beating out of
cabinet palms and with a grace unknown in a long time she did.

I stayed why deny? vowing not fail because the intimations, then pondered
a while about the events that could occur that night, and the outline
of a plan head, I left my room and went to my uncle.

XXVI

At that moment came Neluco.

I had not seen the patient more than a minute after jump out of bed,
nothing had answered my questions because he dozed, and the low light
then cleared a little the darkness of the bedroom, I had hit anything
either in appearance, but look again and better light, and I found
something very different.

Was much more anxious than in the evening, more bluish color, the glassy-eyed, and, However,
very troubled by coughing and restless in bed. Neluco looked, that he was pressing, and read
in his face grim confirmation of my diagnosis. Suddenly, he said, his voice soft words and syllables
almost not reach more than their breath:

- Today I did not like pinch, guys.

We looked at the doctor and me, and said this:

- Why did you say?

- Because I feel worse than the worst day I have seen.

- Apprehensions of you, - said I, say he is encouraged.

- That has
to be soon - replied the patient.

Neluco, meanwhile, continue to press, sometimes in a doll, now on the other, pulled the ear
to his chest above the heart, and he discovered and felt his legs below the knee caused him Several
questions later, and finally, it was a long time leaning against the bed and looking intently, his
head something fall, as if not knowing what to say or what was flowing in view of the phenomena
he observed. I was in front of Neluco, leaning against the bed as well; and the bedroom door, arms
crossed and feet, and two statues of Melancholy and curiosity, Facia
and daughter waiting for orders.

The first was from my uncle to ask "Another pillow," and that they spent three of which served
as support for his back and head.

As the two women met the mandate and Mullian and arranging the resulting
heap for less discomfort for the patient left the bedroom and I Neluco
behind him, a sign that I did.

- This is for the post - I said, so
they would not hear the patient.

- So serious is it you? - Ask.

-
Very serious - he replied -.

Matter of hours or so. So if you point the slightest desire to confess, he was not bound by any
regard, and if not points ... you seek apuntársele. Do not I own anything new, because everything
would be useless, even mortification a blister beetle. The swelling of the legs, as you have
seen, has taken tonight a big increase ... Natural own and sudden advancement has given the
disease, perhaps by the rapid decline that has occurred in the temperature this morning ... because
they do not know if there you noticed that it is cold since dawn, cutting hair.

It was cold in my imagination a sudden scrambling of ideas, and forgetting the sick, I remembered
more than the attempt by the three outlaws ready for that night, and so I asked the same avidity
Neluco he could do Facia in their "best days" of ghosts and sorrow:

- Do you think it will snow?

- And the sign - I said Neluco -.

All the symptoms are of the heaviest snowfall and durable that hang around here.

- What do you too - insisted - that begins today?

- As already beginning when I came - I said -. See you!

And led me to the door of the laundry, from whose paneled we pass, carried by the icy breeze blowing
outside, some flakes were identical to those I had seen start another
novel.

However, the sky was not so "encenizado" or dark as ever. So I warned the doctor, and he replied:

-
But everything will come, and soon, no doubt you. For the same reason - he said - must be
very shelter care of these rooms. Do not miss it here on the hearth burned so as to keep unchanged
the temperature now is in the sick room. No precaution is to heal, or even improve it, of
course, but we must put on our part, for the sake of it, everything is possible ... Another thing:
given what is happening and, particularly, of what might happen in here that you need more people,
for reasons On another occasion gave similar, and I tell Mari Pepa to come immediately with
his daughter ... You may also say something to Don Sabas, to make it even prevented.

With little more than this and I did some warnings regarding the patient after passing another
little while at his side, he went and I remained Neluco I plunged into the most devilish thoughts.
Satan himself, as a discourse to a conflict to the house, so I had not spun well as it was the one I
feared for the night, if baratijero threats were made, or did not come to stop and fix all
the deus ex machina of the snow, in the dose that Neluco I had predicted. Because otherwise,
"Virgin my heavenly Mother!" As have said in similar cases the gray woman. Don Celso, dying
perhaps those hours, or perhaps already dead, Lita and her mother at his side, assisting him
or praying for him in Facia reproduced paroxysms of distress, three bandits raiding the house,
and I, Chisco and Salces Pito, a clean shot with them, ending with the shock of killing my uncle,
if still alive, and setting about to die of grief for women, two of which, at least, was I have
to defend any risk as I remain a breath of life, a cartridge burn or a grill to wield. I recently
heard by the confession of Facia, I had imagined this picture much easier. Chisco, Salces Pete
and I, armed to the teeth and well perceive, and not breathing lurking in the shadows of the
gate, one of us opening the door as agreed precautions were left outside to hear the whistle of
baratijero, and then the three, as the robbers were entering ... Point-blank fire on them! Neither
first rung of the ladder had to profane with his foot the infamous. Lest it be overwhelmed my
uncle in the crash, would have fooled me before with a lie either: I would have said, for example, who
had seen the night before the wolf around the house on that side, and thought to kill him in the
wee hours of the immediate if returned. Chisco galls and Pito Salces me were well known, and
there was no warning what most people do not give room to the preacher. We bastábamos the three
for that company for the time: the rest, ie collecting the spoils of battle, the charred bodies and
jigote facts, and justice would duly notified. And this will reduce everything. But with the
new look of things, ignored by the bandits, with a house full of women, and death, with their train
of tears and ceremonies and accessories pathetic rule over them, what shocks and what scandals
and desecration and sacrilege which would not produce a battle in the astragalus, a shot dry, their
respective oaths and screams and bloodied bodies and throbbing! Finally, if not managed the conflict
of snow, had to make me and have the rope Tarumba and gray woman resigned to his recent troubles.
For one thing, and this calmed me something concerns, there were many hours ahead, it would be
what was taking courses and how carried the suggested time, and what was up in the morning
the aggravation of my uncle. I was well supplied with arms and ammunition; Chisco too, and
me living at home, and to Chorcos, and take care to tell me in time for him to stay to ensure
the pretext the serious condition of Mr. Celso. No longer fancy that, instead of waiting for
the robbers in the doorway of the house, they could put together an ambush in the immediate
rocks it and shoot at close range as the door is placed along the three. But this plan was
less "Conclusive" than the other, and was exposed to bankruptcy that they could get out faces of
the assailants, much as we attend to justice, by all divine and human laws. Still yet will weigh
and would measure both plans if the case came in due time, and opt for the better.

This and more I pondered mechanically by tacking inside the house after have fired the doctor. Dando,
suddenly, well, the point then, I decided to see how he was my uncle
of his mortal anguish.

But I went in his room without a trace before one of the glass in the door into the sunshine through
the dining room. The continued darkening sky and the sparkling snow thickens. I liked the
symptom. My uncle, though between continuous feigned coughing, seemed calmer, and slept. Facia,
sitting away from him and attentive to whatever might happen, after I had I referred to sick
tiptoed to the bed, his eyes told me:

- Well it going, eh?

To which I responded with another look and a gesture

- From the best.

But God knows that neither the question nor the answer referred to the condition of the patient,
but the temporal aspect.

They spent two hours with no inside or outside the house occurred novelty worthy of being noticed,
and came, but without the usual noise, Lita and her mother and even the Don Pedro Nolasco.
The ups and downs, relatively happy, in a dark drama that unfolded, and walk around in those
aged area, much the spirit lifted me. Came three characters deeply impressed by the news that
had given them Neluco. The giant Greeting all, I shook hands in silence, with two tremendous
shock that soon I dismantle the arm at the shoulder, his granddaughter and his daughter, his
eyes misted over, I asked, loosened as they began to shelters, and in a low voice a little shaky,
news drawer on the current state of my uncle. Tell him, not as bad as they expected them and
this encouraged them to come very quietly to the door of the bedroom. Since there were watching
the battle that did not stop within the ruins of Don Celso, between the dream you drowsy and coughing
he insisted, until it rolled over in bed in one of those clashes, which left half suffocated,
mouth and eyes wide open and collecting air breathing, even with their hands. Then he hid quickly,
almost jumping in the Hall, and did both to me, not lost sight of the grief and sympathy painted on
the face. To all this, Don Pedro Nolasco, standing, rigid, motionless and silent, in the same
place that had been planted at the door. Access soon passed, and turned fall ill in the morass
of before ... But what the hell I saw that I was captivated Lituca more attention at that time
that the shock of his grandfather and the plight of my uncle? What was in it again and strange
to me? Well, quite simply, tears their eyes and pained expression on his boyish face, and I wondered
as I left my doubts: "But when this girl is cuter? "When he laughs and gurgles as the birds
the mountain, without sorrow or care, or feel, as now, in the absence of pain themselves, compassion
that will inspire others? "And not knowing which of these two extremes to choose, I remained
with the two, because it's true that laughing or crying, I was really cute creature.

Fearing that too much impressed with frequent contemplation of that distressing picture human
misery, so new to her, advised her to refrain from entering the room the patient.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>