<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05565</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>55426</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>17067</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Era esta poblacion de Genoveses, dividida por un estrecho cerco del mar de la Ciudad de Constantinopla,
llamado de los antiguos Cuerno de Bisancio, y hoy de los Turcos y Griegos Galata. Retirados
y sosegados los nuestros, les mandó el Emperador en agradecimiento de su puntual obediencia
librar una paga. Quedaron muertos de los Genoveses en la Ciudad cerca de tres mil, y aunque
lo peor llevaron ellos entónces, fué causa de mayores daños en lo venidero para los nuestros,
porque con esto quedó irritada una nacion émula y poderosa, que importaba su amistad para conservar
nuestras armas en aquel Imperio; porque en estos tiempos era grande y temido su poder en todo
el Oriente, arbitros de la paz y la guerra. Tenian ilustres Colonias y Presidios en Grecia,
en Ponto, en Palestina, armadas poderosas, poseian muchas riquezas adquiridas con su industria
y valor, y absolutamente eran dueños del trato universal de Europa, con que mantenian fuerzas
iguales á las de los mayores Reyes, y Repúblicas. Con esto llegaron á ser casi dueños del Imperio
Griego. En este tiempo cuando los Catalanes llegaron á Constantinopla, y reconociendo las fuerzas
que traian, les pareció á los Genoveses peligrosa la vecindad de sus armas; y así siempre se
mantuvo entre estas dos naciones aborrecimiento y enemistad implacable que duró muchas edades,
hasta que el valor de entre ambos se fué perdiendo, juntamente con el Imperio del mar, y cesó
la emulacion por cuya causa muchas veces con varia fortuna se combatió.

CAPITULO IX.

Pasa la armada á la Natolia, y hecha la gente en el cabo de Artacio.

Con el peligro de la pendencia entre Catalanes y Genoveses, advirtió Andronico los que pudieran
suceder, por tener dentro de la Ciudad diferentes y varias naciones armadas, y ofendidas, que
con ménos ocasion que la vez pasada vinieran sin duda á rompimiento. Llamó á nuestros Capitanes,
y les explicó brevemente el fusto que tendría de ver sus armas en el Asia, amparando su miserables
y Cristianos pueblos, oprimidos de los Turcos, y quitada la ocasion de nuevas pendencia y desórdenes.
Roger con sus Capitanes ofreció que embarcaría su gente luego. Pero para que su partida fuese
con más gusto, y el ejército quedase satisfecho, y seguro de tener en la armada ciertos los
socorros y retiradas, le suplicaron nombrase por General de ella algun Caballero, ó Capitan
que fuese de su nacion, para que dependiesen de ellos, temiendo que Andronico diese este cargo
á Griegos ó Genoveses; y fuera cosa peligrosa para su seguridad tener el socorro en poder de
gente extraña, con quien siempre hay emulacion y competencias; ocasion de graves pendencias
y daños, y más en los socorros de mar, tan sujetos á las mudanzas del tiempo, que puede la
ruindad y malicia de un General retardar el socorro, y hallar razon que disculpe y apruebe
lo mal hecho, atribuyendo al tiempo y á peligros imaginados su tardanza. Andronico cumplidamente
satisfizo á la demanda, dando el cargo de General de la armada con título de Almirante á Fernando
de Aones Caballero de conocida sangre, y gallardo por su persona, y juntamente quiso que se
casase con una parienta suya, para que el nuevo parentesco diese más autoridad á su cargo.
El título de Almirante en aquel Imperio no era tan supremo como lo fué entre nosotros, por
que estaba sujeto al Megaduque, y de él recibia las órdenes. Mando el Emperador, que un insigne
Capitan de Romeos que se llamaba Marulli, hombre de sangre y estado, fuese siguiendo las banderas
de Roger con su gente, y Gregorio con la mayor parte de los Alanos hiciese lo mismo. Embarcose
el ejército en los navíos y galeras de su armada, y atravesando el mar de Propontide, dicho
hoy de Marmora, tomaron tierra en el cabo de Artacio, poco mas de cien millas lejos de Constantinopla,
lugar acomodado para la desembarcacion de la caballería. A este cabo llama Montaner Artaqui,
y los antiguos Artacio, no lejos de las ruinas de la famosa ciudad de Cizico.

Llegó Roger con la armada, y supo que los Turcos aquel mismo dia habian querido ganar una muralla,
ó defensa de media milla de largo, puesta en la parte que el cabo se continua con la tierra
firme, y que dejaron el combate, mas por la fortaleza del sitio, que por el valor de los que
la defendían. Estiéndese este cabo, desde esta defensa, ó muralla algunas leguas dentro del
mar, y en él hay muchas poblaciones, y abundantes valles, fértiles colinas. Era en los tiempos
antiguos Isla, pero después se vino á cerrar con las arenas.

Con el aviso cierto que Roger tuvo, de que los Turcos habian acometido el reparo y defensa
del cabo, y que no podian estar muy lejos, dióse prisa á desembarcar la gente, y envió luego
á reconocer el campo de los enemigos, y dentro de pocas horas se supo como estaban alojados
seis millas lejos entre dos arroyos, con sus mugeres, hijos y haciendas. En aquel tiempo los
Turcos, no olvidados aún de las costumbres de los Scitas, de quíen se precian suceder, vivian
la mayor parte, y la más belicosa en la campaña, debajo de tiendas y barracas, mudándose según
la variedad del tiempo, y comodidades de la tierra. Tenian puesta su mayor fuerza en la caballería,
gobernada por Capitanes y Príncipes de valor, no de sangre, á quien obedecían más por gusto
que por obligacion. Tenian perpetua guerra con los vecinos, sin órden militar, á imitacion
de los Alarabes, que hoy poseen el Africa. Esta forma de vivir tuvieron, desde que dejaron
las riveras del rio Volga, y entraron en la Asia menor, hasta que la vileza de las naciones
de la Asia, y Grecia les dió crédito y reputacion. A las Monarquias y naciones, sucede lo mismo
que á los hombres que nacen, crecen y mueren. Nació Grecia cuando se defendió de Jerjes, y
cuando su valor deshizo el poder de tan numerosos ejércitos, y forzó al bárbaro Monarca, que
se retirase vencido, y pasase el estrecho de mar del Helesponto en una pequeña barca, que poco
antes soberbio y desvanecido humilló con puente. Tuvo su aumento, cuando las armas de Alejandro
pasaron más allá del Ganges, y los límites y fines inmensos de la misma naturaleza no lo fueron
de su ambicion. Fué su muerte, cuando las armas de los Bárbaros, por flojedad de sus Príncipes,
y poca fidelidad de sus Capitanes, le pusieron en dura servidumbre.

En este tiempo que Andronico ocupaba el Imperio de Oriente, los Turcos se dividieron, y hubo
entre ellos algunas guerras civiles, pero por el consejo y autoridad de Orthogules se sosegaron,
remitiendo á la suerte sus pretensiones, que como reviere Gregoras, y Chalchondilas, se dividieron
por suerte las Provincias entre siete Capitanes, pretensores todos al gobierno universal. Dio
la suerte á Caramano la parte mediterranéa de la Provincia de Frigia hasta Cilicia, y Philadelphia,
aunque algun autor quiere, que este no fuese de los siete Capitanes, y que solo reinó en Caria:
á Carcano la parte Frigia, que se estiende hasta Esmirna: á Calami y á su hijo Carasi, la Lidia
hasta Misia Bitinia, y las demás Provincias junto al monte Olimpo, cayeron en la suerte de
Otomano, que en aquella edad comenzó á ser temido, y á levantar poco después su Monarquía,
venciendo y sujetando los demás Tiranos de las Provincias que vamos nombrando; con que quedó
absoluto señor y Príncipe de todas ellas. La Patagonia, y las demás tierras que caen á la parte
del Ponto Euino, las ocuparon los hijos de Amurat. En esta forma hallaron los nuestros repartida
el Asia, y á los Turcos señores de ella: que fué grande ayuda para nuestras victorias el estar
sus fuerzas divididas.

CAPITULO X.

Vencen los Catalanes y Aragoneses á los turcos.

Por el aviso que Roger tuvo de como los Turcos estaban cerca, temiendo perder tan buena ocasion
si advertidos de la llegada de los nuestros se previnieran, ó retiraran, juntó el campo, y
en una breve platica les dijo, como el siguiente dia queria da sobre los alojamientos de los
enemigos, fáciles de romper por estar descuidados. Propusoles la gloria que alcanzarian con
vencer, y que de los primeros sucesos nacía el miedo, ó la confianza, y que la buena ó mala
reputacion pendia de ellos. Mandó que no se personase la vida sino á los niños, porque esto
causase más temor en los Bárbaros, y nuestros soldados peleasen sin alguna esperanza d que
vencidos pudiesen quedar con vida. Dispuesto el órden con que se habia de marchar, dió fin
á la platica. Oyéronle con mucho gusto, y aquella misma noche partieron de sus alojamientos
á tiempo que al amanecer pudiesen acometer á los Turcos. Guiaba Roger con Marulli la vanguardia
con la caballería, y llevaba solos dos estandartes, en el uno las armas del Emperador Andronico,
y en el otro las suyas. Seguia la infantería hecho un solo escuadron de toda ella, donde gobernaba
Corbarán de Alet Senescal del ejército. Llevaba en la frente solas dos banderas, contra el
uso comun de nuestros tiempos, que suelen ponerse en medio del escuadron como lugar más fuerte
y defendido. La una bandera llevaba las armas del Rey de Aragon Don Jaime, y la otra las del
Rey de Sicilia Don Fadrique; porque entre las condiciones que por parte de los Catalanes se
propusieron al Emperador, fué de las primeras, que siempre les fuese lícito llevar por guia
el nombre y blason de sus Príncipes, porque querian que adonde llegasen sus armas, llegase
la memoria y autoridad de sus Reyes, y porque las armas de Aragon lastenian por invencibles.
De donde se puede conocer el grande amor y veneracion que los Catalanes y Aragoneses tenian
á sus reyes, pues aún sirviendo á Príncipes extraños, y en Provincias tan apartadas, conservaron
su memoria, y militaron debajo de ella: fidelidad notable, no solo conocida en este caso, pero
en todos los tiempos. Porque no se vió de nosotros Príncipe desamparado por malo y cruel que
fuese, y quisimos más sufrir su vigor y aspereza, que entregarnos á nuevo señor. No fué preferido
el segundo al primogénito. Siempre seguimos el órden que el cielo, y naturaleza dispuso, ni
se alteró por particular aborrecimiento ó aficion, con no haber apenas Reino donde no se hayan
visto estos trueques y mudanzas.

Pasaron los nuestros á media noche la muralla, ó reparo que divide el cabo de tierra firme,
y al amanecer se hallaron sobre los Turcos, que como en parte segura, y á su parecer lejos
de enemigos, estaban sin centinelas, reposando dentro de sus tiendas con descuido y sueño.
Cerró Roger y Marulli con la caballería, metiéndose por las tiendas y flacos reparos que tenian
con grande ánimo. Siguiéronle los Almugavares con el mismo, dando un sangriento y dichoso principio
á la nueva guerra. Los Turcos á quien la furia y rigor de nuestras espadas no pudo oprimir
en el sueño, al ruido de las armas y voces despertaron, y con la turbacion y miedo que semejantes
asaltos suelen causar en los acometidos, tomaron las armas para su defensa, pero fueron pocos,
divididos y desarmados, con que su resistencia fué inútil y sin provecho contra el esfuerzo
y gallardia de nuestra gente, que ya lo ocupaba todo. Pelearon los Turcos con desesperacion,
viendo á sus ojos despedazar y degollar á sus más caras prendas, de gente que ni aún por el
nombre conocían. Alcanzose cumplidísima victoria, dejando en el campo muertos de los Turcos
tres mil caballo, y diez mil infantes. Los que quedaron vivos fueron los que reconociendo con
tiempo el desorden y pérdida, y que los Catalanes eran impenetrables á los golpes de sus dardos,
se pusieron en seguro con la huida, y el que querer muchos hacer lo mismo después les causó
mas presto la muerte, por que ocupados en retirar sus hijos y mujeres, dejaban la batalla,
y luego perecian. La presa fué grande, y los niños cautivos muchos. Refiere Nicéforo, Griego
de nacion, y enemigo declarado de la nuestra, el espanto y terror que causó en los Turcos este
primer acometimiento con estas mismas palabras: «Como los Turcos vieron el ímpetu feroz de
los Latinos, (que así llama á los Catalanes) su valor, su disciplina militar, y sus lucidas
y fuertes armas, atónitos y espantados huyeron, no solo lejos de la ciudad de Constantinopla,
pero más adentro de los antiguos límites de su Imperio.» Nuestra gente siguió el alcance poco
rato, por no tener la tierra conocida, y volvieron aquella misma noche al cabo, por tener el
alojamiento reconocido y seguro.

CAPITULO XI.

Retirase el ejército par invernar en el cabo de Artacio sus alojamientos.

Dieron aviso al Emperador del buen suceso de su victoria, enviando cuatro galeras con riquísimos
presentes para entre ambos Príncipes, Andronico y Miguel, y en nombre de los soldados se envió
á María muger del Megaduque Roger lo más precioso y rico de la presa. Causó notable admiracion
entre los Griegos la brevedad con que se alcanzó tan señalada victoria, y el pueblo la celebró
con alabanzas, libre del temor de los Turcos, que insolentes con las victorias alcanzadas de
los Griegos de la otra parte del estrecho amenazaban la Ciudad, con los alfanges desnudos;
pero casi toda la nobleza, que como fuera justo debiera mostrarse más agradecida á tan grande
beneficio, manifestó el veneno de sus ánimos, que la envidia de la agena felicidad no dió lugar
á que se pudiese mas encubrir. Los privados de Andronico, y las personas de mayor estimacion
de su nacion, comenzaron á temer nuestras fuerzas, juzgándolas por superiores á las que ellos
tenian, y que dentro de casa tanto poder en manos de extranjeros era cosa peligrosa. Estas
platicas y discursos las alentaba el Emperador Miguel, incitado de un oculto sentimiento que
causó en su ánimo la victoria, porque algunos meses antes habia pasado el estrecho con un ejército
poderosísimo, y por miedo de los Turcos ó poca seguridad de los suyos, se retiró con gran pérdida
de su reputacion, sin travar ni aún una pequeña escaramuza con el enemigo; y como los Catalanes
siendo tan pocos vencieron á los que él no se atrevió acometer con tan excesivo número de gente,
de esto nació su corrimiento, y de él un grande aborrecimiento y deseo de nuestra perdicion.
Los Príncipes sienten mucho que haya quien se les iguale en valor, y aún en la dicha aborrecen
á quien se les aventaja, porque el poder no sufre virtud y partes aventajadas en ageno sujeto,
y más cuando en su competencia sucede el aventajarse. Si una baja y vil emulacion de un Príncipe
en hacer versos causó la muerte á Lucano, ¿Cuánto mayor fuera si de valor y fortuna se compitiera?
Y así no se debe tener por Captan cuerdo el que intenta una empresa errada por su Príncipe,
si ya n quiere competir con el del Imperio.

Con el buen suceso que tuvieron no trataron de pasar adelante, ni seguir la victoria: cosa
que les hizo perder reputacion, y fué ocasion de hacer muchos excesos en aquella comarca, que
irritaron gravemente el ánimo de los naturales y Griegos. Cuando quisieron entrar la tierra
á dentro, comenzó el primer dia de Noviembre á entrar con tanto rigor el invierno, con vientos
frios y agua que les detuvo. Los rios por sus crecientes sin poderse vadear, la campaña esteril
llena de enemigos, los caminos difíciles por donde se habia de marchar para socorrer á Philadelphia,
eran causas bastantes para diferir cualquier empresa. Roger con el parecer y consejo de sus
Capitanes se resolvió de invernar en Cizico, lugar acomodado por la fortaleza del sitio, y
abundancia de las vituallas, y porque el año siguiente fuese menos embarazosa la salida que
si hubieran de partir de Grecia, y embarcar y desembarcar la caballería tantas veces, cosa
de suyo tan molesta. Dieron luego aviso al Emperador de esta resolucion y aprobóla con mucho
gusto, porque era lo que más le convenia, por tener el ejército alojado en la frente del enemigo,
y apartado de Constantinopla y de los demás pueblos Griegos, donde no faltáran quejas y pesadumbre,
aunque cerca de tres meses anduvieron alojados por Asia sin efecto, trabajando la tierra con
insoportables contribuciones. Mandó Andronico que con mucha diligencia se llevasen por mar
las vituallas que no se hallaban en el cabo, con que pasaron los nuestros un invierno muy apacible.
El Megaduque Roger envió con cuatro galeras por su mujer María. El órden que se tuvo en los
cuarteles para escusar pendencias entre los soldados y sus huéspedes, fué el siguiente. Los
soldados nombraron seis de su parte, y los de la tierra otros tantos, para que de comun parecer
y acuerdo se pusiese precio á las vituallas: porque encareciéndose más de lo justo fuera gran
descomodidad para los soldados, y dándose á un precio muy bajo no resultase en notable daño
de los huéspedes, á más que faltára el comercio y provision ordinaria que acudia de todas partes
con abundancia. Ordenose á Fernando Aones Almirante, que con la armada fuese á invernar á la
isla de Jio, puerto seguro y vecino de las Costas enemigas. Es el Jio isla de las más señaladas
del mar Egeo, por nacer en ella sola el Almaste, cosa que negó naturaleza á las demás partes
de la tierra.

CAPITULO XII.

Ferran Jimenez de Arenós se aparta de los suyos.

Las cosas de mar y tierra, concertadas en la forma dicha, se pasaba el invierno con sosiego
y mucha conformidad, pero luego nuestras fuerzas se fueron enflaqueciendo con algunas divisiones
y discordias civiles. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07318</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>13129</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15387</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

It was this population of Genoese, divided by a narrow sea siege of the city of Constantinople call of the
ancient Horn of Byzantium, and now of the Turks and Greeks Galata. Retired and sedate us, the
Emperor ordered them in appreciation of your prompt obedience wage pay. The Genoese were killed
in the City about three thousand, and although They then took the worst, was the cause of more
damage in coming to ours, irritated because this was a rival and powerful nation, that mattered
to keep their friendship our weapons in the empire, for in these times was great and feared their power
around East, arbiters of peace and war. Colonies and Prisons had distinguished in Greece Pontus,
in Palestine, powerful armed, possessed great wealth acquired in its industry and value, and
absolutely owned the universal treatment in Europe with forces that kept equal to those of the
greatest kings, and republics. This came to be almost owners of the Empire Greek. At this time
when the Catalans came to Constantinople, and recognizing the forces who brought them to the Genoese
seemed dangerous vicinity of their weapons, and so always maintained between these two nations implacable
hatred and enmity that lasted many ages, until the value of the two went missing, along with
the Empire of the sea, and ceased emulation, for whom often fought with varying fortune.

CHAPTER IX.

Navy passes to the Natoli, and made people in Cape Artacio.

With the danger of dependence between Catalans and Genoese, Andronico said that could happen,
within the City have different and various armed nations, and offended, which with less chance than
last time came, doubtless, to break. Call our Captains and briefly explained the shaft would have
to see their weapons in Asia, protecting their miserable and Christian peoples, oppressed by the Turks,
and removed the opportunity of new independence and disorders. Captains Roger with his people
offered to embark later. But his departure was more tasteful, and the army is satisfied, and
be sure the Navy certain relief and retired, begged General appoint for it a gentleman, or
Captain it was of his nation, that depend on them, fearing that Andronico give this position to
Greeks or Genoese, and was dangerous thing for their safety have the power relief strange people,
who always emulation and skills; occasion of serious quarrels and damage, and more on the relief
of the sea, as subject to the changes of time, can the meanness and malice of a general delay
relief, and find reason to excuse and approval evil deeds, giving the time and imagined dangers
to his lateness. Andronico dutifully to satisfy demand, and thus the position of General of the
Army with the title of Admiral Ferdinand Knight Aones known of blood, and graceful in his person,
and wanted to be together marry a relative of hers, so that the new relationship would give
more authority to his office. The title of Admiral in the empire was not as supreme as it
was between us, that was subject to the Grand Duke, and he received the orders. Command the
Emperor, a famous Romeos Captain Marulli named man of blood and state flags were following Roger
with his people, and Gregory with most of the Alans do the same. Embarked the army in the ships and
galleys of his fleet, and crossing the sea of ??Propontis, the Marmora today, they landed at Cape
Artacio, little more than a hundred miles away from Constantinople, accommodated for the landing-place
of the cavalry. In this place called Artaqui Montaner, Artacio and old, not far from the ruins of the
famous city of Cyzicus.

Roger arrived with the army, and knew that the Turks that same day had wanted to make a wall defense
or half a mile long, placed on the party that the corporal continued to land firm, and left
the fight, but by the strength of the site, the value of which defended it. Estiéndese this
out, since this defense, or wall within a few leagues sea, and in it there are many populations,
and abundant valleys, fertile hills. Was at the time ancient island, but later came to close to
the sands.

With the announcement that Roger was true, that the Turks had undertaken the repair and defense
Cape, which could not be far away, she hasted people to disembark and then sent to recognize
the field of enemies, and within hours they were staying was known as six miles away between
two rivers, with their wives, children and property. At that time Turks have not forgotten the
customs of the SCIT, who is proud to happen, vivian most, and the most warlike in the campaign,
in tents and barracks, moving as the variety of the time, and amenities of the land. He had his greatest
strength in the cavalry ruled by princes and value, not of blood, whom they obeyed more for
pleasure that obligation. Had perpetual war with the neighbors, no military order, in imitation
of Alarab, they now possess Africa. This way of life had, since leaving the banks of the Volga
river, and entered the Asia Minor until the vileness of nations of Asia, and Greece gave them
credit and reputation. Monarchies and nations, so does than men are born, grow and die. Born defended
Greece when Xerxes and when its value broke the power of so many armies, and forced the barbarian
monarch, who withdraw up, and pass the strait of the Hellespont in a small boat, which soon
proud and humbled before vanished bridged. Had its rise, when weapons of Alexander went beyond
the Ganges, and the limits and purposes of the immense nature were not of his ambition. It was
his death, when the arms of the Barbarians, for looseness of their Princes, and little loyalty
to their captains, they put in hard labor.

At this time Andronico occupied the Eastern Empire, the Turks were divided, and there including
some civil wars, but by the advice and authority of Orthogules be quieted, referring to the fate
their claims, which as Reviere Gregoras and Chalchondilas, divided Fortunately the Provinces of seven
Masters, pretensioners all universal government. Dio Caramanico luck to the Mediterranean part
of the province of Phrygia to Cilicia, and Philadelphia, but any author wants, that this was not the
seven captains, and only reigned in Caria: Carcano to the Phrygian, which extends to Smyrna to
Calami and his son Carasi, Lydia to Mysia Bithynia, and other provinces next to Mount Olympus,
fell into the fate of Ottoman, at that age began to be feared, and to raise shortly after
its monarchy conquering and holding the other tyrants of the provinces that we appoint, that
was absolute lord and prince of them all. Patagonia, and other lands that fall to the Euino
Pontus, the children occupied Amurath. In this way they found the our distributed Asia, and the
Turks masters of it, that was great help for our victories being divided forces.

CHAPTER X.

Catalans and Aragonese due to the Turks.

By Roger took notice of how the Turks were close, afraid of losing such a good opportunity
if advised of the arrival of our people were prevented, or withdrawn, along the field, and in
a brief talk he said, as the next day wanted to give on accommodation of enemies, easy to break
by being careless. Propusoles the glory that reached with overcome, and that of the first event
was born of fear, or trust, and that good or bad reputation hung from them. He ordered that
no person's life but to children, because this causes fear among the barbarians, and our soldiers
peleasen without any hope d that losers could be alive. Provisions of the order with which
they had to march, gave order to the talks. Heard him gladly, and that night started from their
seats While he could attack at dawn the Turks. Roger led the vanguard with Marulli with the cavalry,
and had only two banners, in the arms of the Emperor an Andronico, and the other his. I kept the
infantry made a single squadron of it all, ruled Alet CORBA Steward of the military. He had been in
the face alone two flags, against common use of our time, who sit in the middle of the squad
as the strongest place and defended. The flag bore the arms of Don Jaime King of Aragon and the
other those of Fadrique Don King of Sicily, for among the conditions that are part of the Catalans
proposed to the Emperor, was the first, which was always driven by legal guide the name and
coat of arms of Princes, where they arrived because they wanted their weapons, arrived memory
and authority of their kings, and for the weapons of Aragon Lastenia considered invincible.
From where you can meet the great love and reverence that the Catalans and Aragonese had their
kings, they still serve foreign princes, and in such remote provinces, retained memory, and
militated below it: remarkable fidelity, not only known in this case, but at all times. Because
they saw us not forsaken evil Prince and cruel was, and wanted more suffering its force and harshness,
which will supply new master. It was not preferred the second to the eldest. Always follow the
order to the sky, and ordered nature or particular altered by hatred or love, with no little kingdom
where there are no seen these trade-offs and relocations.

Passed at midnight our wall, or repair after dividing the land, and
at dawn were found on the Turks, who as partly safe, and his apparently
far enemies, were without guards, resting in their tents and sleeping
carelessly.

Roger and Marulli closed with the cavalry, getting around the shops and repairs that had weak
with great spirit. Next came the Almugavares with it, giving a bloody and happy principle
to the new war. The Turks, whom the fury and precision of our weapons could not push in sleep,
the clash of arms and voices awoke, and the agitation and fear that such assaults often result
in the attacked, took up arms for their defense, but few, divided and disarmed, that their resistance
was futile and useless against the effort and gallantry of our people, who already occupied
it. The Turks fought with desperation, watching his eyes tear and slay their most expensive clothes,
people who even by the known name. Cumplidísima Alcanzose victory, leaving the field dead Turks
three thousand horse and ten thousand infantry. Those left alive were those acknowledging time
disorder and loss, and that the Catalans were impervious to the blows of his arrows, were put
in safe flight, and that many want to do so afterwards caused them death more quickly, because
they engaged in removing their children and women, left the battle and then perished. The dam
was great, and many captive children. Nicephorus relates, Greek the nation and declared enemy
of ours, the fear and terror caused in the Turks this first pursued with the same words: "As the
Turks were fierce momentum Latinos (so called to the Catalans) its value, its military discipline,
and its lucid and strong arms, amazed and terrified they fled, not only far from the city
of Constantinople, but inside the old limits of his empire. "Our people followed the little
scope time, not having the known world and returned that night after all, for having the recognized
and secure accommodation.

CHAPTER XI.

Withdraw the army in the winter even after Artacio their seats.

They told the Emperor of the success of his victory, sending four
galleys with delicious present to the two Princes, and Michael Andronico,
and on behalf of the soldiers sent Grand Duke to Mary wife of Roger
the most precious and rich prey.

Caused considerable admiration among the Greeks as soon as that signal
victory was achieved, and the people held with praise, free from fear
of the Turks, who insolent with the victories achieved by Greeks on
the other side of the strait threatened the City with the naked cutlass;
but almost all the nobility, which was fair as it should be more grateful
to so great benefit, said the poison of their hearts, to the envy
of the happiness agena gave rise that could be more to conceal.

Andronico's private, and those with higher estimation of his nation, began to fear our might, judging
them by superiors to which they had, and indoors as much power in foreign hands was something
dangerous. These talks and speeches encouraged them Emperor Michael, prompted by a hidden feeling
caused in his mind the victory because he had passed some months before the close with an army
powerful, and fear of the Turks or little security of their own, retired with great loss your
reputation, not through or even a small skirmish with the enemy, and as the Catalans being
so few beat them that he dared not rush through as too many people, this was your shift, and
it a great hatred and desire for our ruin. The Princes feel much that anyone will be equal in value,
and even in such hate whom are ahead, because power and virtue suffers advantaged parties in
Agen subject especially when competition happens in your advantage. If a low and vile emulation
of a Prince to make verses killed Lucan, how much worse off if competing value and fortune?
And no sane Captan must have a company that tries wrong by Prince n if you want to compete with
the Empire.

With the good fortune which had not tried to move on, or following the victory thing that caused
them to lose reputation, and was the occasion to make many excesses in that region, which seriously
angry mood of the natives and Greeks. When they tried to enter the land inwards, began the first
day of November to come so severely winter winds and cold water stopped them. The rivers and their
growing without being able to wade through the barren season full of enemies, the difficult road
which was to march to succor Philadelphia, causes were enough to postpone any business. Roger with
the advice and counsel of Captains decided to winter in Cyzicus, instead accommodated by the strength
of the site, and abundance of victuals, and that next year the output was less embarrassing
than if they had to leave Greece, and embarking and disembarking
of chivalry so often, something of his so upset.

Emperor then gave notice of this resolution and far approvedthe taste, it was what suited
him, having stayed in the army against the enemy, and away from Constantinople and other Greek
towns, with enough complaints and grief, but walked about three months without effect hosted
by Asia, working the land contributions unbearable. Andronico sent diligently to be carried by
sea the food they were not in place, that passed our very mild winter. Roger sent the Grand Duke
with four galleys for his wife Mary. The order which was held in quarters to excuse quarrels between
the soldiers and their guests, was as follows. The Soldiers named six of his hand and land
as many, so that seems common and put an agreement price to the victuals: for more costly
out more than just great descomodidad for soldiers, and giving them a very low price does not
result in significant damage reviews, to more missing trade and regular provision that came
from everywhere abundance. Ordenose Aones Admiral Ferdinand, who were armed to the winter to
the Jio island, safe harbor and neighboring enemy coasts. Jio is the island of the most marked Aegean
Sea, have been born in the Almaste herself, which nature denied to other parties land.

CHAPTER XII.

Ferran Jimenez of sand away from theirs.

The things of land and sea, arranged in the form that, he spent the winter with calm and a lot of
conformity, but then our forces were emaciated with some divisions and civil strife.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>