<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>200908</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20562</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Desde lejos le miró Benina, inmóvil,
la cabeza caída. Pasado un rato, se dejó caer en el suelo, y allí le vieron toda la tarde los
transeúntes, sentado, mudo, la negra mano extendida.

No encontró la Nina en su casa grandes novedades, como por tal no se tuviera el contento de
Doña Paca, que no cesaba de alabar la finura de su huésped, y la gracia con que a la conversación
traía los recuerdos de Algeciras y Ronda. Sentíase la buena señora transportada a sus verdes
años; casi olvidaba su pobreza, y movida del generoso instinto que en aquella edad primera
había sido fundamento de su carácter imprevisor y de sus desgracias, propuso a Nina que se
trajeran para Frasquito dos botellas de Jerez, pavo en galantina, huevo hilado, y cabeza de jabalí.

«Sí, señora--replicó la criada--: todo eso traeremos, y luego nos vamos a la cárcel, para ahorrar
a los tenderos el trabajo de llevarnos. ¿Pero usted se ha vuelto loca? Para esta noche haré
unas sopas de ajo con huevos, y san sacabó. Crea usted que a ese caballero le sabrán a gloria,
acostumbrado como está a comistrajos indecentes.

--Bueno, mujer. Se hará lo que tú quieras.

--En vez de cabeza de jabalí, pondremos cabeza de ajo.

--Creo, con tu permiso, que en todas las circunstancias, aunque sea sacrificándose, debe una
portarse como quien es. En fin, ¿cuánto dinero tenemos?

--Eso a usted no le importa. Déjeme a mí, que ya sabré arreglarme. Cuando se acabe, no es usted
quien ha de ir a buscarlo.

--Ya, ya sé que irás tú y lo buscarás. Yo no sirvo para nada.

--Sí sirve usted; y ahora, ayúdeme a pelar estas patatitas.

--Lo que quieras. ¡Ah!... se me olvidaba. Frasquito toma té... y como está tan delicadillo,
hay que traerlo bueno.

--Del mejor. Iré por él a la China.

--No te burles. Vas a la tienda, y pides del que llaman mandarín. Y de paso te traes un quesito
bueno para postre...

--Sí, sí... eche usted y no se derrame.

--Ya ves que está acostumbrado a comer en casas grandes.

--Justamente: como la taberna de Boto, en la calle del Ave María... ración de guisado, a real;
con pan y vino, treinta y cinco céntimos.

--Estás hoy... que no se te puede aguantar. Pero a todo me avengo, Nina. Tú mandas.

--¡Ay, si yo no mandara, bonitas andaríamos! Ya nos habrían llevado a San Bernardino o al mismísimo
Pardo».

Bromeando así llegó la noche, y cenando frugalmente, alegres los tres y resignados con la pobreza,
mal tolerable y llevadero cuando no falta un pedazo de pan con que matar el hambre. Y el historiador
debe hacer constar asimismo que el buen temple en que estaba Doña Paca se torció un poco al
recogerse las dos en la alcoba, la señora en su cama, Benina en el suelo, por haber cedido
su lecho a Frasquito. Como la viuda de Zapata era tan voluble de genio, en un instante, sin
que se supiera el motivo, pasaba de la bondad apacible a la ira insana, de la credulidad infantil
a la desconfianza marrullera, de las palabras razonables a los disparates más absurdos. Conocía
muy bien la criada este fácil girar de los pensamientos y la voluntad de su señora, a quien
comparaba con una veleta; y sin tomar a pecho sus displicencias y raptos de ira, esperaba que
cambiase el viento. En efecto, este variaba de improviso, rolando al cuadrante bueno; y si
en un momento la malva se había convertido en cardo, en otro momento tornaba a su primera condición.

El mal humor de Doña Paca en la noche a que me refiero, debe atribuirse, según datos fehacientes,
a que Frasquito, en sus conversaciones de la tarde, y en los ratos de la cena y sobremesa de
esta, mostró por Benina unas preferencias que lastimaron profundamente el amor propio de la
viuda infeliz. A Benina manifestaba el buen señor casi exclusivamente su gratitud, reservando
para la señora una cortés deferencia; para Benina eran todas sus sonrisas, sus frases más ingeniosas,
la ternura de sus ojos lánguidos, como de carnero a medio morir; y a tantas indiscreciones
unió Ponte la de llamarla ángel como unas doscientas veces en el curso de la frugal cena.

Y dicho esto, oigamos a Doña Paca, entre sábanas metida, mientras la otra se acostaba en el
suelo: «Pues, hija, nadie me quita de la cabeza que le has dado un bebedizo a este pobre señor.
¡Vaya cómo te quiere! Si no fueras una vieja feísima y sin ninguna gracia, creería que le habías
hecho tilín... Cierto que eres buena, caritativa, que sabes ganar la simpatía por lo bien que
atiendes a todo, y por tu dulzura y ese modito suave... que bien podría engañar a los que no
te conocen... Pero con todas esas prendas, imposible que un hombre tan corrido se prende de
ti... Si te lo crees y por ello estás inflada de orgullo, mi parecer es que no te compongas,
pobre Nina. Siempre serás lo que fuistes... y no temas que yo le quite a D. Frasquito la ilusión,
contándole tus malas mañas, lo sisona que eras, y otras cosillas, otras cosillas que tú sabes,
y yo también...».

Callaba Benina, tapándose la boca con la sábana, y esta humildad y moderación encendieron más
el rencorcillo de la viuda de Zapata, que prosiguió molestando a su compañera: «Nadie reconoce
como yo tus buenas cualidades, porque las tienes; pero hay que ponerte siempre a distancia,
no dejarte salir de tu baja condición, para que no te desmandes, para que no te subas a las
barbas de los superiores. Acuérdate de las dos veces que tuve que echarte de mi casa por sisona...
¡A tal extremo llegó tu descaro, ¿qué digo descaro? tu cinismo en aquel vicio feo, que... vamos,
yo, que jamás he hecho una cuenta, ni me gusta, veía mi dinero pasando de mi bolsillo al tuyo...
en chorro continuo!... Pero ¿qué? ¿No dices nada?... ¿No contestas? ¿Te has vuelto muda?

--Sí, señora, me he vuelto muda--fue la única respuesta de la buena mujer--. Puede que cuando
la señora se canse y cierre el pico, lo abra yo para decirle... en fin, no digo nada».

XXVI

«Ja, ja... Di lo que quieras...--prosiguió Doña Paca--. ¿Te atreverías a decir algo ofensivo
de mí? ¡Que no he sabido llevar el Cargo y Data! ¿Y qué? ¿Quién te ha dicho a ti que las señoras
son tenedoras de libros? El no llevar cuentas ni apuntar nada, no era más que la forma natural
de mi generosidad sin límites. Yo dejaba que todo el mundo me robase; veía la mano del ladrón
metiéndose en mi bolsillo, y me hacía la tonta... Yo he sido siempre así. ¿Es esto pecado?
El Señor me lo perdonará. Lo que Dios no perdona, Benina, es la hipocresía, los procederes
solapados, y el estudio con que algunas personas componen sus actos para parecer mejores de
lo que son. Yo siempre he llevado el alma en mi rostro, y me he presentado a los ojos de todo
el mundo como soy, como era, con mis defectos y cualidades, tal como Dios me hizo... ¿Pero
tú no tienes nada que contestarme?... ¿O es que no se te ocurre nada para defenderte?

--Señora, callo, porque estoy dormida.

--No, tú no duermes, es mentira: la conciencia no te deja dormir. Reconoces que tengo razón,
y que eres de las que se componen para disimular y esconder sus maldades... No diré que sean
precisamente maldades, tanto no. Soy generosa en esto como en todo, y diré flaquezas... pero
¡qué flaquezas! Somos frágiles: verdaderamente tú puedes decir: «No me llamo Benina, sino Fragilidad...».
Pero no te apures, pues ya sabes que no he de ir con cuentos al Sr. de Ponte para desprestigiarte,
y deshojar la flor de sus ilusiones... ¡Qué risa!... No viendo en ti, como no puede verlo,
una figura elegante, ni un rostro fresco y sonrosado, ni modales finos, ni educación de señora,
ni nada de eso, que es por lo que se enamoran los hombres, habrá visto... ¿qué? Por Dios que
no acierto. Si tú fueras franca, que no lo eres, ni lo serás nunca... ¿Oyes lo que digo?

--Sí, señora, oigo.

--Si tú fueras franca, me dirías que el Sr. de Ponte te llama ángel por lo bien que haces las
sopas de ajo, acartonaditas... Y ¿te parece a ti que esto es suficiente motivo para que a una
mujer la llamen ángel con todas sus letras?

--¿Pero a usted qué le importa?... Deje al Sr. de Ponte Delgado que me ponga los motes que quiera.

--Tienes razón, sí, sí... Puede que te lo diga irónicamente, que estos señorones, muy curtidos
en sociedad, emplean a menudo la ironía, y cuando parece que nos alaban, lo que hacen es tomarnos
el pelo, como suele decirse... Por si el hombre va por derecho, y se ha prendado de ti con
buen fin... que todo podría ser, Benina... se ven cosas muy raras... tú debes proceder con
lealtad, y confesarle tus máculas, no vaya a creer Frasquito que la pureza de los ángeles del
cielo es cualquier cosa comparada con tu pureza. Si así no lo haces, eres una mala mujer...
La verdad, Nina, en estos casos, la verdad. El hombre se ha creído que eres un prodigio de
conservación, ja, ja... que has hecho un milagro, pues milagro sería, en plena vida de Madrid
y en la clase de servicio doméstico, una virginidad de sesenta años... Puedes plantarte en
los cincuenta y cinco, si así te conviene... Pero si le engañas en la edad, que esta es superchería
muy corriente en nuestro sexo, no andes con bromas en lo que es de ley moral, Nina; eso no.
Mira, hija, yo te quiero mucho, y como señora tuya y amiga te aconsejo que le hables clarito,
que le cuentes tus faltas y caídas. Así el buen señor no se llamará a engaño, si andando el
tiempo descubre lo que tú ahora le ocultaras. No, Nina, no; hija mía, dile todo, aunque se
te ponga la cara muy colorada, y se te congestione la verruga que llevas en la frente. Confiesa
tu grave falta de aquellos tiempos, cuando contabas treinta y cinco años... y ten valor para
decirle: «Sr. D. Frasquito, yo quise a un guardia civil que se llamaba Romero, el cual me tuvo
trastornada más de dos años, y al fin se negó a casarse conmigo...». Vamos, mujer, no es para
que te pongas como la grana. Después de todo, ¿qué ha sido ello? Querer a un hombre. Pues para
eso han venido las mujeres al mundo: para querer a los hombres. Tuviste la desgracia de tropezar
con uno, que te salió malo. Cuestión de suerte, hija. Ello es que estuviste loca por él...
Bien me acuerdo. No se te podía aguantar; no hacías nada al derecho. Sisabas de lo lindo, y
mientras tú no tenías un traje decente, a él no le faltaban buenos puros... A mí, que veía
tus padecimientos y tu ceguera, pues atormentada y sin un día de tranquilidad, en vez de huir
del suplicio, ibas a él; a mí, que vi todo esto, nadie tiene que contármelo, Nina. Conozco
la historia, aunque no la sé toda entera, porque algo me has ocultado siempre... y a mí me
refirieron cosas que no sé si son ciertas o no... Dijéronme que de tus amores tuviste...

--Eso no es verdad.

--Y que lo echaste a la Inclusa...

--Eso no es verdad--repitió Benina con acento firme y sonora voz, incorporándose en el lecho.
Al oírla, calló súbitamente Doña Paca, como el ratoncillo nocturno que cesa de roer al sentir
los pasos o la voz del hombre. Oyose tan sólo, durante largo rato, alguno que otro suspiro
hondísimo de la señora, que después empezó a quejarse y a gruñir por lo bajo. La otra no chistaba.
Había hecho rápida crisis el genio de la infeliz señora, determinándose un brusco giro de la
veleta. La ira y displicencia trocáronse al punto en blandura y mimo. No tardó en presentarse
el síntoma más claro de la sedación, que era un vivo arrepentimiento de todo lo que había dicho
y la vergüenza de recordarlo, pues no significaban otra cosa los gruñidos, y el quejarse de
imaginarios dolores. Como Benina no respondiera a estas demostraciones, Doña Paca, ya cerca
de media noche, se arrancó a llamarla: «Nina, Nina, ¡si vieras qué mala estoy! ¡Vaya una nochecita
que estoy pasando! Parece que me aplican un hierro caliente al costado, y que me arrancan a
tirones los huesos de las piernas. Tengo la cabeza como si me hubieran sacado los sesos, poniéndome
en su lugar miga de pan y perejil muy picadito... Por no molestarte, no te he dicho que me
hagas una tacita de tila, que me refriegues la espalda, y que me des una papeleta de salicilato,
de bromuro, o de sulfonal... Esto es horrible. Estás dormida como un cesto. Bien, mujer, descansa,
engorda un poquito... No quiero molestarte».

Sin despegar los labios, abandonaba Nina el jergón, y, echándose una falda, hacía la taza de
tila en la cocinilla económica, y antes o después daba la medicina a la enferma, y luego las
friegas, y por fin acostábase con ella para arrullarla como a un niño, hasta que conseguía
dormirla. Anhelando olvidar la señora su anterior desvarío, creía que el mejor medio era borrar
con expresiones cariñosas las malévolas ideas de antes, y así, mientras su compañera la arrullaba,
decíale: «Si yo no te tuviera, no sé qué sería de mí. Y luego me quejo de Dios, y le digo cosas,
y hasta le insulto, como si fuera un cualquiera. Verdad que me priva de muchos bienes; pero
me ha dado tu compañía y amistad, que vale más que el oro y la plata y los brillantes... Y
ahora que me acuerdo, ¿qué me aconsejas tú que debo hacer para el caso de que vuelvan D. Francisco
Morquecho y D. José María Porcell con aquella embajada de la herencia?...

--Pero, señora, si eso lo ha soñado usted... y los tales caballeros hace mil años que están
muy achantaditos debajo de la tierra.

--Dices bien: yo lo soñé... Pero si no aquellos, otros puede que vengan con la misma música
el mejor día.

--¿Quién dice que no? ¿Ha soñado usted con cajas vacías? Porque eso es señal de herencia segura.

--¿Y tú, qué has soñado?

--¿Yo? Anoche, que nos encontrábamos con un toro negro.

--Pues eso quiere decir que descubriremos un tesoro escondido... Mira tú, ¿quién nos dice que
en esta casa antigua, que habitaron en otro tiempo comerciantes ricos, no hay dentro de tal
pared o tabique alguna olla bien repleta de peluconas?

--Yo he oído contar que en el siglo pasado vivieron aquí unos almacenistas de paños, poderosos,
y cuando se murieron... no se encontró dinero ninguno. Bien pudiera ser que lo emparedaran.
Se han dado casos, muchos casos.

--Yo tengo por cierto que dinero hay en esta finca... Pero a saber dónde demontres lo escondieron
esos indinos. ¿No habría manera de averiguarlo?

--¡No sé... no sé!--murmuró Benina, dejando volar su mente vagarosa hacia los orientales conjuros
propuestos por Almudena.

--Y si en las paredes no, debajo de los baldosines de la cocina o de la despensa puede estar
lo que aquellos señores escondieron, creyendo que lo iban a disfrutar en el otro mundo.

--Podrá ser... Pero es más probable que sea en las paredes, o, un suponer, en los techos, entre
las vigas...

--Me parece que tienes razón. Lo mismo puede ser arriba que abajo. Yo te aseguro que cuando
piso fuerte en los pasillos y en el comedor, y se estremece todo el caserón como si quisiera
derrumbarse, me parece que siento un ruidillo... así como de metales que suenan y hacen tilín...
¿No lo has sentido tú?

--Sí, señora.

--Y si no, haz la prueba ahora mismo. Date unos paseos por la alcoba, pisando fuerte, y oiremos...».

Hízolo Benina como su señora mandaba, con no menos convicción y fe que ella, y en efecto...
oyeron un retintín metálico, que no podía provenir más que de las enormes cantidades de plata
y oro (más oro que plata seguramente) empotradas en la vetusta fábrica. Con esta ilusión se
durmieron ambas, y en sueños seguían oyendo el tin, tin...

La casa era como un inmenso cuerpo, y sudaba, y por cada uno de sus infinitos poros soltaba
una onza, o centén, o monedita de veintiuno y cuartillo.

XXVII

A la mañanita del siguiente día iba Benina camino de las Cambroneras, con su cesta al brazo,
pensando, no sin inquietud, en las exaltaciones del buen Almudena, que le llevarían de pronto
a la locura, si ella, con su buena maña, no lograba contenerle en la razón. Más abajo de la
Puerta de Toledo encontró a la Burlada y a otra pobre que pedía con un niño cabezudo. Díjole
su compañera de parroquia que había trasladado su domicilio al Puente, por no poderse arreglar
en el riñón de Madrid con la carestía de los alquileres y la mezquindad del fruto de la limosna.
En una casucha junto al río le daban hospedaje por poco más de nada, y a esta ventaja unía
la de ventilarse bien en los paseos que se daba mañana y tarde, del río al punto y del punto
al río. Interrogada por Benina acerca del ciego moro y de su vivienda, respondió que le había
visto junto a la fuentecilla, pasado el Puente, pidiendo; pero que no sabía dónde moraba. «Vaya,
con Dios, señora--dijo la Burlada despidiéndose--. ¿No va usted hoy al punto? Yo sí... porque
aunque poco se gana, allí tiene una su arreglo. Ahora me dan todas las tardes un buen platao
de comida en ca el señor banquero, que vive mismamente de cara a la entrada por la calle de
las Huertas, y vivo como una canóniga, gozando de ver cómo se le afila la jeta a la Caporala
cuando la muchacha del señor banquero me lleva mi gran cazolón de comestible... En fin: con
esto y algo que cae, vivimos, Doña Benina, y puede una chincharse en las ricas. Adiós, que
lo pase bien, y que encuentre a su moro con salud... Vaya, conservarse».

Siguió cada cual su rumbo, y a la entrada del Puente, dirigiose Benina por la calzada en declive
que a mano derecha conduce al arrabal llamado de las Cambroneras, a la margen izquierda del
Manzanares, en terreno bajo. Encontrose en una como plazoleta, limitada en el lado de Poniente
por un vulgar edificio, al Sur por el pretil del contrafuerte del puente, y a los otros dos
lados por desiguales taludes y terraplenes arenosos, donde nacen silvestres espinos, cardos
y raquíticas yerbas. El sitio es pintoresco, ventilado, y casi puede decirse alegre, porque
desde él se dominan las verdes márgenes del río, los lavaderos y sus tenderijos de trapos de
mil colores. Hacia Poniente se distingue la sierra, y a la margen opuesta del río los cementerios
de San Isidro y San Justo, que ofrecen una vista grandiosa con tanto copete de panteones y
tanto verdor obscuro de cipreses... La melancolía inherente a los camposantos no les priva,
en aquel panorama, de su carácter decorativo, como un buen telón agregado por el hombre a los
de la Naturaleza.

Al descender pausadamente hacia la explanada, vio la mendiga dos burros... ¿qué digo dos? ocho,
diez o más burros, con sus collarines de encarnado rabioso, y junto a ellos grupos de gitanos
tomando el sol, que ya inundaba el barrio con su luz esplendorosa, dando risueño brillo a los
colorines con que se decoraban brutos y personas. En los animados corrillos todo era risas,
chacota, correr de aquí para allá. Las muchachas saltaban; los mozos corrían en su persecución;
los chiquillos, vestidos de harapos, daban volteretas, y sólo los asnos se mantenían graves
y reflexivos en medio de tanta inquietud y algarabía. Las gitanas viejas, algunas de tez curtida
y negra, comadreaban en corrillo aparte, arrimaditas al edificio grandón, que es una casa de
corredor de regular aspecto. Dos o tres niñas lavaban trapos en el charco que hacia la mitad
de la explanada se forma con las escurriduras y desperdicios de la fuente vecinal. Algunas
de estas niñas eran de tez muy obscura, casi negra, que hacía resaltar las filigranas colgadas
de sus orejas; otras de color de barro, todas ágiles, graciosas, esbeltísimas de talle y sueltas
de lengua. Buscó la anciana entre aquella gente caras conocidas; y mira por aquí y por allá,
creyó reconocer a un gitano que en cierta ocasión había visto en el Hospital, yendo a recoger
a una amiga suya. No quiso acercarse al grupo en que el tal con otros disputaba sobre un burro,
cuyas mataduras eran objeto de vivas discusiones, y aguardó ocasión favorable. Esta no tardó
en venir, porque se enredaron a trompada limpia dos churumbeles, el uno con las perneras abiertas
de arriba abajo, mostrando las negras canillas; el otro con una especie de turbante en la cabeza,
y por todo vestido un chaleco de hombre: acudió el gitano a separarlos; ayudole Benina, y a
renglón seguido le embocó en esta forma:

«Dígame, buen amigo: ¿ha visto por aquí ayer y hoy a un ciego moro que le llaman Almudena?

--Sí, señora: halo visto... jablao con él--replicó el gitano, mostrando dos carreras de dientes
ideales por su blancura, igualdad y perfecta conservación, que se destacaban dentro del estuche
de dos labios enormes y carnosos, de un violado retinto--. Le vide en la puente... díjome que
moraba dende anoche en las casas de Ulpiano... y que... no sé qué más... Desapártese, buena
mujer, que esta bestia es mu desconsiderá, y cocea...».

Huyó Benina de un brinco, viendo cerca de sí las patas traseras de un grandísimo burro, que
dos gandules apaleaban, como para conocerle las mañas y proveer a su educación asnal y gitanesca,
y se fue hacia las casas que le indicó con un gesto el de la perfecta dentadura.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10379</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>112372</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18869</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> From afar it looked Benina motionless
drooping head. After a while, he fell on the floor, and there I saw all afternoon bystanders
sitting mute, black outstretched hand.

Nina did not find the big news at home, as such, does not have the happy Doña Paca, who never ceased
to praise the fineness of his guest, and the grace with which the conversation brought memories
of Algeciras and Ronda. He felt the good woman transported to its green years, almost forget
their poverty, and moved the generous instinct in that first age had been improvident foundation
of his character and his misfortunes, which proposed to Nina for
Frasquito bring two bottles of sherry, turkey in aspic, egg yolk,
and boar's head.

"Yes, ma'am -" said the maid -: all this will bring, and then we go to jail, to save shopkeepers
to take the job. But have you gone mad?

For tonight I will a garlic soup with eggs, and St. Sacabo.

Believe me, you know that gentleman to glory comistrajos used as
is indecent.

- Well, woman.

Do whatever you want.

- Instead of boar's head, will head of garlic.

- I think, with your permission, that in all circumstances, even sacrificing,
should a act like he is.

In short, how much money we have?

- That you do not mind.

Leave it all to me, and I know dress.

When finished, you are not who has to go get it.

- Yeah, I know you and go look for it.

I'm no good.

- If you serve, and now, help me peel these potatoes.

- Whatever
you want.

Ah ... I forgot. Bottle drink tea ... and as is so delicadillo, must bring good.

- The best.

I'll get him to China.

- Do not laugh. Go to the store and ask the called Mandarin. And while you bring a quesito good
for dessert ...

- Yes, yes ... take you and does not spill.

- You see that you are accustomed to eating in big houses.

- Just: as Boto's Tavern, across the street from Ave Maria ... ration of stew, a real; with
bread and wine, thirty-five cents.

- You are today ... I can not endure. But every avenge me, Nina. You command.

- Oh, if I did not send, would run pretty! Already we have taken to San Bernardino or very Pardo.
"

Joking and it was evening, and dine frugally, happy three and resigned
to poverty, bad tolerable and bearable when not needed a piece of
bread and to kill hunger.

And the historian should be noted also that the good climate in Doña Paca was a little twisted
collected both in the bedroom, the lady in your bed, Benin on the floor, having given Frasquito
his bed. Zapata's widow was so mercurial genius, in an instant, without to know the reason, the
goodness went from calm to insane rage, of childish credulity a crafty distrust of reasonable
words the most absurd nonsense. Knew very well bred this easy turning of the mind and the will
of his wife, whom compared with a weathervane, and without taking to heart their displeasure
and a fit of rage, he hoped that the wind changed. Indeed, this varied from suddenly veering
to the quadrant good, and if in a moment had become purple thistle, later returns to his first condition.

The
Dona Paca cranky at night I mean it must be attributed, according to reliable, to Frasquito, in
his talks in the afternoon, and the times for dinner and desktop
This showed a preference for Benina that deeply hurt the pride of
the widow unhappy.

A good Mr. Benina expressed his gratitude almost exclusively, reserving for lady a polite deference,
for Benina were all smiles, his most ingenious the tenderness of his languid eyes, and medium
ram die and many indiscretions Ponte joined to call the angel as a hundred times in the course
of the frugal meal.

And with that, listen to Doña Paca, tucked between the sheets, while the other was sleeping in floor:
"Well, daughter, no one out of my head that you have given a potion to this poor guy. Go how you
want!

If you were not an old ugly and without any grace, believe that you had ding made ... True that
you are good, charitable, you know to gain sympathy by how well attend
to everything, and for your sweetness and that modito soft ... that
it could mislead those who do not you know ... But with all those
clothes, impossible for a man so corrido garment you ... If you believe
and why you are inflated with pride, my view is that you do not compose,
Poor Nina.

You'll always be what you were ... and I fear not that quite a D.
Bottle illusion, telling your bad habits, what you were ssion, and
other stuff, other stuff that you know, and I ...».

Benina silent, covering her mouth with a sheet, and this humility and moderation lit more the rencorcillo
Zapata's widow, who continued molesting her companion: "No one recognizes like me your good qualities,
because you have, but we must always put away do not let you out of your low status, so you
do not lawless, so you will not upload to the higher beard. Remember the two times I had to
kick you out of my house ... ssion To that end comes your impudence, what do I say chutzpah?
your cynicism at the ugly vice, which ... go, I've never made an account, I like seeing my money
going out of my pocket to yours ... continuous jet! ... But what? Do not say anything? ...
Have you no answer? Have you gone mute?

- Yes, ma'am, I have become mute - was the only response from the good woman -. Maybe when the
lady is tired and shut up, open it to tell me ... In short, do not say anything. "

XXVI

"Ja, ja ... Say what you went Doña Paca ...-- -. Would you dare to say something offensive
Me? Do not have known how to take Charge and Data! So what? Who ever told you that the ladies are
a bookkeeper? Failure to keep accounts or target anything, it was just the natural way my boundless
generosity. I let everyone I stole, I saw the thief's hand getting
into my pocket, and I was the fool ... I have always been so.

Is this sin?

The Lord forgive me. What God does not forgive, Benin, is the hypocrisy, the procedures with
overlapping, and study with some people make up their acts to look better what they are. I've
always been the soul of my face, and I presented to the eyes of the
world as I am, as it was, with my faults and qualities, just as God
made me ... But You have nothing to answer to me ... Or do you not
think of anything to defend?

- Madam, scallops, because I'm asleep.

-
No, you do not sleep, is a lie: the conscience will not let you sleep.

Acknowledge that I have reason and that you are of which are made
to disguise and hide their evil ... I will not say they are very evil,
so no. I am generous in this as in everything, and say weaknesses
... but What weakness!

We are fragile, you can truly say, "Do not call me Benina but ...». Fragility But do not worry,
because you know that I have to go with Mr. de Ponte stories to desprestigiarte, and pluck the flower
of his dreams ... What a laugh! ... Not seeing you, as you can not see, an elegant figure,
not a fresh, rosy face, and fine manners, no education for women, or anything like that, which
is why men fall in love, you've seen ... What? By God I fail. If you were honest, you're not,
nor ever will be ... Do you hear what I say?

- Yes, madam, I hear.

- If you were honest, I would say that Mr. de Ponte angel calls you by how well you do the garlic soup,
acartonaditas ... And do you think to yourself that this is sufficient reason for a angel woman
called out in full?

- But you do not care? ... Let Mr. de Ponte Delgado put the nicknames I want.

- You're right, yeah, yeah ... Can I say it ironically, that these big shots, very tanned in
society, often employ irony, and when we seem to worship, what they do is to take hair, as they
say ... For if man is on the right, and has smitten you with good order ... that everything could
be Benina ... things are very rare ... you must proceed with loyalty, and confess your macules,
Frasquito will not believe that the purity of the angels Heaven is anything compared to your purity.
If you do not, you're a bad woman ... The truth, Nina, in these cases the truth. The man believed
that you are a prodigy conservation, ha, ha ... you've done a miracle, because miracles would,
in the midst of life in Madrid and the kind of domestic service, a virginity of sixty years
... You plantarte in fifty-five, if you should ... But if you cheat on age, this is fraud very
common in our sex, jokes do not go with what is moral law, Nina, why not. Look, daughter,
I love you very much, and as a lady friend of yours and I advise that you speak clearly, tell
you your faults and falls. So the good Lord will not call hoax, they
walk the time you discover what her to hide.

No, Nina, no, my dear, tell all, although I get my face very red,
and congested the wart you carry in your face.

Confess your severe lack of those times, when thirty-five years ...
and have value for say, "Mr. D. Bottle, I wanted a civilian guard
was called Romero, who took me disordered over two years, and finally
refused to marry me ...».

We, women, not for you wear scarlet. After all, what was it? Love a man. As for women that have
come into the world to love men. You had the misfortune to stumble with one, you went wrong.
Matter of luck, my dear. This is you were crazy about him ... I remember well. I could not
stand, did not do anything right. Sisabas a great time, and while you did not have a decent suit,
he did not lack good cigars ... To me, he saw your sufferings and your blindness, as tormented
and without a quiet day, instead of fleeing of punishment, going to him for me, I saw all this,
nobody has to tell me, Nina. I know history, but not know the whole entire thing because I've always
hidden ... and I reported things I do not know if they are true or not ... They told me that
you had your love ...

- That's not true.

- And you threw it to the Foundling ...

- That's not true - he repeated with emphasis Benina firm and sonorous voice, sitting up in bed. To
hear, suddenly stopped Doña Paca, as the little mouse that night,
feeling constantly gnaw steps or the man's voice.

Was heard only, for a long time, the occasional sigh very profound for the lady, who then began
to complain and grumble under his breath. The other is not complaining. Quick crisis had made
the genius of the unhappy lady, determining a sharp turn of vane. Trocáronse anger and displeasure
to the point tenderness and affection. Occur soon the clearest symptom of sedation, he was a keen
remorse of what he had said and shame to remember, did not mean anything because the grunts, and complain
imaginary pain. As Benina not respond to these demonstrations, Doña Paca, and about midnight, it
started to call her "Nina, Nina, if you only knew how bad I am! What a nochecita I'm going!
Looks like I applied a hot iron on the side, and tear me to pulling the leg bones. I have
the head as if I had got the brains, putting in place of bread crumbs and parsley finely chopped ...
Not bothered, I have not told me make a cup of lime, rub me back
and give me a ballot salicylate bromide, or sulphonal ... This is
horrible.

You sleep like a basket. Well, woman, rest, a little fat ... I do not want to bother. "

Without a word, Nina left the pallet, and throwing a skirt, made the cup tila in economic stove,
and before or after giving medicine to the sick, and then rubs, and
finally went to bed with her to coo like a child, until getting sleep
it off.

Mrs. Longing forget his previous rant, I thought the best way was
clear loving the evil expressions of ideas before, and so, while his
companion cooed, he would say: "If I did not have you I do not know
what would happen to me.

And then I complain to God, and say things and to insult him as if
he were a nobody.

I really deprived of many goods, but I have given your company and
friendship, which is worth more than gold and silver and shiny ...
Y I remember now, what do you advise I should do in case of renewed
D. Francisco Morquecho and D. José María Porcell embassy with that
inheritance?

...

- But, Madam, if thats what you dreamed ... and such men are a thousand
years achantaditos very underground.

- You are right: I dreamed ...
But if not those, others might come to the same music the best day.

-
Who says no? Have you ever dreamed you with empty boxes?

Because this is a sign of inheritance safe.

- And you, what you dream?

- Me? Last night we were with a black bull.

- So that means that we will discover a hidden treasure ... Look you,
who tells us that this old house, once inhabited the rich merchants,
there is within such partition wall or a pot full of pelucones well?

-
I have heard tell that in the last century lived here a few stockists
of cloth, powerful and when he died ... no money was not found.

It may be that the paninis. There have been cases, many cases.

- I have certainly money is on this farm ... But you know where they hid démontrer these indinos.
Is not there a way to find out?

- I do not know ... I do not know!
- Benina murmured, letting fly his mind wander to the eastern spells
proposed by Almudena.

- And if the walls do not, under the tiles
of the kitchen or pantry can be what these gentlemen hid, thinking
that they would enjoy in the afterlife.

- May be ... But it is more
likely to be in the walls, or a guess, on roofs, including beams ...

-
I think you're right.

The same can be up than down. I assure you that when strong floor in hallways and dining room,
and swept through the mansion as if to collapse, I think I feel a ruidillo ... metal and they
sound and they ding ... Have not you felt?

- Yes, ma'am.

- And if not, try it now.

Date walks around the room, stomping, and hear ...».

Benin and his wife obeyed his command, with no less conviction and faith that she, in effect ...
heard a metallic clang, which could not only come from the huge amounts of silver and gold
(probably more gold than silver) embedded in the ancient factory.

This illusion both asleep, and dreams were still hearing the ting, ting ...

The house was like a huge body, sweating, and each of its infinite
pores let go one ounce, or center, or twenty-one and a quarter penny.

XXVII

In the early morning the next day was Cambroneras Benina way, with his basket on his arm thinking,
not without concern, in the exaltation of the good Almudena, which would lead to early madness,
if she, with her very quick, he could not restrain the right. Below the Puerta de Toledo and
found the other poor Burlada calling a stubborn child. Said to her fellow parishioners who had
moved his home to the Bridge, not being able to fix in the kidney of Madrid with the high cost
of rent and the meanness of the fruit of charity. In a shack by the river gave accommodation for
little more than nothing, and this advantage united to ventilate the field trips that gave morning
and afternoon, the river and point to point river. Asked by Benin on the Moor and his blind
housing, replied that it had seen near the fountain, past the bridge, asking, but did not know
where he dwelt. "Well, with God, madam - said goodbye Burlada -. Are not you going to the point
now? I do ... because although little is gained, there is a settlement. Now I have every evening
a good Platão ca food on Mr. Banker, who lives very entrance facing the street las Huertas,
and live as a canon, enjoying to see how he sharpens the snout to
the Caporal when the girl Mr. banker takes me my big cazolón of edible
... In short: with this and something goes down, live, Dona Benin,
and can be a bug in the rich.

Goodbye, which have fun, and find your health Moor ... Well, preserved. "

Followed each his due, and the entrance of the bridge on the road and ran Benina declining that
to the right leads to the suburb called Cambroneras, to the left bank Manzanares, at low land.
As he found a small square, bordered on the west side by a common building, the south by the
railing of the bridge abutment, and the other two unequal sides sandy slopes and embankments,
are born wild thorns, thistles and stunted grass. The site is colorful, airy, and might almost
say happy, because since it is dominated by the green banks of the river, washing and dish clothes
tenderijos thousand colors. To the west stands the mountains, and the opposite bank of the
river cemeteries San Isidro, San Justo, offering a spectacular view to both tuft of cemeteries
and both dark green cypress ... The melancholy inherent in the cemeteries not deprive them in
that picture, its decorative nature, as a good backdrop added by
man to Nature.

To descend slowly toward the square, he saw the beggar two donkeys ... What do I say two? eight
ten or more donkeys, with their angry red collars, and with them groups of Gypsies sunbathing,
which flooded the neighborhood with its radiant light, cheerful giving shine to were adorned with
colorful gross and people. In the animated huddles all was laughter, chacota, running to and
fro. The girls jumped, the boys ran in pursuit; the children, dressed in rags, tumbled, and donkeys
were kept only serious and reflective in the midst of unrest and commotion. Old gypsy women,
some tanned complexion and black circle gossiping in separate Grandón arrimaditas the building,
a house regular racer look. Two or three girls wash cloths in the middle puddle of the square
is formed with escurriduras and waste from the local source. Some of these girls were very dark
skinned, almost black, which highlighted the filigree hanging their ears, others color of mud, all
agile, graceful, and drop-waisted esbeltísimas language. He sought the old familiar faces among
those people, and look around here and there, thought he recognized a gypsy who had once been
in the hospital, going to pick up a friend of hers. He would not approach the group in which such
other disputed on a donkey whose sores were the subject of lively discussion, and waited a favorable
opportunity. This was soon come, because entangled two churumbeles clean punch, the one with legs
open from top to bottom, showing the black cops, the other with a sort of turban on his head, and
all dressed in a man's sweater: the gypsy came to separate; ayudole Benin, and Immediately
afterwards he holed in this way:

"Tell me, good friend, have you seen around here yesterday and today to a blind man they call Almudena
moro?

- Yes, ma'am: halo seen ... jablao with him - said the gypsy, showing two teeth racing ideal
because of their whiteness, equality and perfect preservation, which
highlighted within the case two large, fleshy lips, a violation retinto
-.

We saw in the bridge ... she said she dende dwelling houses last night Ulpiano ... and ...
I do not know what else ... Desapártese, good woman, this beast is many inconsiderate, and kicks
...».

Benina fled from the chair, looking around him the great hind
legs of a donkey, two peas beaten, and to know the tricks and his
education asses and gitanesca, and went to the houses that he motioned
that of perfect teeth</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>