<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09773</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>18780</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24756</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Pero, ¡caso estupendo! en medio de todo este entusiasmo, doña Luz no tenía ni había tenido
novio: no hablaba ni había hablado con nadie por la reja. Lo que sí había tenido era multitud
de pretendientes, sin que ella hubiese dado esperanzas a ninguno. Los jóvenes más ricos de
algunas leguas en contorno la consideraban ya como inexpugnable fortaleza. La esperanza, con
todo, no se pierde jamás. Los hombres, en esto de conquistas amorosas, nos las prometemos,
a menudo, felices. Así es que, si los del lugar estaban ya sosegados y desengañados, no faltaban
aún forasteros, con tal de que fuesen sujetos de cierto fuste, que se alborotasen al ver a
doña Luz, y propusiesen, allá en sus adentros, conseguir lo que otros no habían conseguido;
pero pronto también se desengañaban.

Con esta adoración resuelta, con este prurito de ser correspondidos, se habían hallado muchos,
o simultánea o sucesivamente. Ninguno había llegado a explicaciones. Doña Luz se supo componer
de suerte que no se había visto nunca en la dura necesidad de dar formales calabazas, ni de
excitar el resentimiento que esto trae consigo. Era difícil hablar a solas con ella. Era difícil
hacer llegar a sus manos carta o billete amoroso. Y si bien, merced a algunas viejas audaces,
que donde quiera las hay de sobra, doña Luz había recibido papelitos en prosa y hasta en verso,
constantemente los había devuelto sin abrir. En vista de estos y de otros desdenes, todos los
enamorados desistían al fin de sus propósitos, sin motivo y hasta sin pretexto de queja.

Y no podía haberla, porque doña Luz callaba toda razón ofensiva. No se sentía inclinada al
matrimonio. No amaba. Nadie manda en su corazón. Tales eran sus razones.

Alguien podría sospechar pero no probar su invencible repugnancia a todo lo vulgar y plebeyo,
y el horror que de ella se apoderaba a la sola idea de poder un día tener un hijo que llevase
su ilustre apellido en pos de otro apellido oscuro y rústico de algún ricacho villano.

En suma: doña Luz, si no tenía esperanzas de casarse a su gusto, tampoco tenía o dejaba traslucir
el menor deseo. Todo era en ella frialdad tranquila y contentamiento suave. En balde, el peor
pensado de los hombres se atrevería a buscar en sus actos, en sus palabras, en sus ademanes
y gesto, la más leve señal de que estuviese despechada.

Doña Luz no lo estaba en realidad. Había tomado enérgicamente su partido y había trazado de
antemano la senda de su vivir. Las frases burlonas de quedarse para tía o para vestir imágenes
no hacían mella en su firme y acerado corazón, ni podían violentarla ni inclinarla a aceptar
marido con el solo fin de no llegar a solterona.

Varias parientas ricas, que tenía doña Luz en Sevilla y en Madrid, la habían invitado a que
se fuera a vivir con ellas: pero, o bien porque así fuese en verdad, o porque doña Luz lo sospechaba,
las invitaciones habían sido más que de corazón por cumplimiento. Además, doña Luz se consideraba
muy pobre para su clase, y no quería ser gravosa, ni vivir a expensas de otros y en una especie
de dependencia próxima a la servidumbre. Había, pues, rehusado todas las invitaciones. Su plan
era vivir y morir oscuramente en Villafría.

La misma impureza de su origen, el vicio de su nacimiento, la humilde condición de su desconocida
madre, obraban por reacción en su ánimo y casi convertían su orgullo en fiereza. Para limpiar
aquella mancha original, quería ser doña Luz mucho más limpia y mucho más pura.

No quería pordiosear ni deber nada a nadie.

Conservaba sin vender su casa solariega del lugar con sus antiguos muebles y dos criados. Si
no vivía en ella, pensaba vivir más tarde, o bien porque don Acisclo podría faltar, o bien
porque ya, entrada ella en años, nadie podría extrañar que viviese sola.

Entretanto, vivía doña Luz en el caserón de don Acisclo, donde tenía holgada e independiente
habitación, y donde había traído, para adornarla, sus más bonitos y preciosos muebles y sus
libros mejores.

En pago de esta hospitalidad, hacía aceptar a don Acisclo, por más que éste se había resistido,
más de la mitad de sus rentas, o sea 8.000 reales al año. Con lo restante, como era económica
y arreglada, tenía lo suficiente para vestirse, comprar algunos libros nuevos y hacer limosnas.

El único lujo, el único regalo de doña Luz, era un magnífico caballo negro, en el cual solía
ella salir a paseo con D. Acisclo o con un criado llamado Tomás, que había envejecido en el
servicio de su padre.

Don Acisclo estaba viudo hacía muchísimo tiempo. Tenía dos hijos y tres hijas, todos casados
y con casa aparte, de modo que, en la soledad anchurosa de aquel inmenso caserón, doña Luz
y D. Acisclo se daban mutua compañía.

Rayaba ya D. Acisclo en los setenta años; pero estaba recio y bien de salud. Iba derecho como
un huso; era hombre ágil y enjuto de carnes; y, si no sabía más que leer y escribir medianamente
y las cuatro reglas, y si jamás había leído un libro, tenía gran despejo natural, aunque burdo.
Jamás había turbado su conciencia con sutilezas morales. Así es que no le remordía, como hemos
dicho, de haber contribuido a la ruina del marqués. Si se había aprovechado de ella mejor le
parecía que hubiese sido él que no otro. Mucho le hubiera dolido ver en manos extrañas el caudal
de su amo. Poseíale, por lo tanto, de buena fe, con justo título, y hasta con y por cierto
sentimiento de veneración a la memoria del difunto ilustre poseedor.

Esta veneración se extendía, o mejor dicho, se extremaba y llegaba a su colmo, sin afectación
ni servilismo, cuando se trataba de la señorita doña Luz, en quien, fascinado el viejo, creía
descubrir a un ser cuyos arcanos pensamientos, móviles y resortes de acción, apenas entreveía;
a una criatura rara e inusitada, de otra casta muy diferente de la suya, y con la cual, sin
embargo, comía de diario y tenía la honra de compartir la vivienda.

-III-

De otras menudencias que la escrupulosidad del narrador no permite que pasen en silencio

Constaba esta vivienda, como la de muchos otros ricos hacendados de Andalucía, de dos casas
contiguas, en comunicación: la de los amos y la que se llama siempre casa de campo, aunque
esté en el centro de la población.

La casa de los amos no tenía más habitantes que D. Acisclo en un extremo, y doña Luz en otro,
con su vieja criada Juana, que dormía en un cuarto al lado del de su señora.

Había un gran comedor, otro comedor pequeño para diario y varios salones de respeto, que no
se abrían sino en las ocasiones solemnes, y donde, entre otras preciosidades, D. Acisclo, sus
hijos, hijas, yernos y nueras, todos resplandecían retratados al óleo, de tamaño más que natural,
y casi de cuerpo entero, por un pintor ambulante que acertó a pasar por Villafría, y que llevó
una onza de oro por cada retrato. Verdad es que D. Acisclo le agasajó y trató a cuerpo de rey,
sentándole a su mesa todo el tiempo que tardó en pintarlos, lo cual fue obra de cinco meses,
y luego, al partir, le hizo presente de mil chucherías, como, por ejemplo, de un pipotillo
con aguardiente de doble anís, de orejones secos y de alfajores y piñonate. Los retratos lo
merecían por lo parecidos. No les faltaba más que hablar. Las blondas que figuraban en los
de las damas, estaban algo confusas al principio; pero, cediendo a las quejas de las damas
susodichas, el pintor lo arregló con ingenioso artificio. Untó en albayalde un pedazo de tul,
le aplicó al sitio del cuadro, ya seco, donde la blonda estaba representada, y resultó un efecto
maravilloso, porque hasta los agujeritos de la blonda se veían y aun podían contarse.

Todo esto era en el piso principal, donde había dos chimeneas, que allí llaman francesas, y
que no se encendieron sino cuando vino el obispo, en pleno invierno, y por poco se ahoga S.
S. I. con el humo que se armó. Pero en cambio había una magnífica cocina de señores, con chimenea
de campana, de muchísimo tiro, donde ardía siempre, durante la estación fría, abundante leña
de olivo y de encina y rica pasta de orujo; donde rara vez se guisaba; y donde los señores
se calentaban muy a su sabor. En esta cocina adornaban las paredes varias jaulas de perdices,
puestas sobre repisas, escopetas y otras armas, y algunas cabezas de ciervos, lobos, zorros,
tejones y garduñas, muertos por D. Acisclo.

En el piso bajo había casi tanta habitación como en el principal; y, si se contaba con el patio
con toldo, había más. Allí se vivía durante el verano. En toda estación estaba allí el despacho
de D. Acisclo, donde este activo labrador y ganadero trataba con chalanes, corredores, rabadanes,
aperadores, capataces y caseros: entendiéndose por caseros, no el terror de los inquilinos
morosos, como en Madrid, sino los que cuidan y guardan las caserías o viviendas de cada finca
rústica.

En el piso bajo, en la sala de más aparato y autoridad, que se llamaba la cuadra, porque era
cuadrada, había también algo que daba lustre a aquella casa. Es de saber que en no pocos pueblos
de Andalucía hay multitud de imágenes benditas, que se sacan en procesión en las grandes festividades,
y singularmente en Semana Santa. El número de estas imágenes suele hacer que no quepan bien
en los templos, por lo cual muchas están depositadas en casas particulares hasta el único día
del año en que han de salir en procesión. D. Acisclo tenía en la cuadra baja una de estas imágenes,
de cuya cofradía era hermano mayor; pero no era una imagen de tres al cuarto, sino la más complicada
que se conocía y la de mayor empeño y coste, ya que en realidad no rezaba con ella aquel decir
proverbial de:

Santirulitos bonitos, baratos, Ni comen, ni beben, ni gastan zapatos.

Aquella imagen o representación comía y bebía, o mejor dicho, cenaba: era nada menos que la Cena.

Cristo y los doce apóstoles de bulto estaban sentados a la mesa; Cristo echaba la bendición,
San Juan se dormía sobre el hombro de su Divino Maestro, y el feísimo y traicionero Judas,
con enmarañado pelo rojo, metía la mano en el plato del centro, porque es sabido que no tenía
pizca de educación.

El Jueves Santo salía en procesión la Cena, y el Miércoles Santo por la noche estaba expuesta
en la cuadra a la veneración de los fieles, quienes con tal motivo tenían entrada franca en
la casa, lo cual se llamaba y se llama aún visitar las insignias, y apenas quedaba en el lugar
quien no las visitase en la víspera de la respectiva procesión. Y esto si contar con los forasteros.

La mesa en que Cristo y los apóstoles estaban sentados, era bastante capaz, y, en tan solemnes
días, se cubría con preciosos manteles alemaniscos y se adornaba con mil lindezas, flores,
viandas, dulces y frutas. Aunque no había en la mesa de cuanto Dios crió, como afirmaba la
gente del pueblo con encarecimiento desmedido, era innegable que había objetos raros y costosos:
uvas de corazón de cabrito como acabadas de coger y que por milagro se habían conservado, claveles
y tempranas rosas de olor en grandes piñas, ramos de violetas y camelias, etc., etc. Las paredes
de la sala donde estaba la Cena se tapizaban de damasco carmesí; sobre el damasco se colgaban
lindas y antiguas cornucopias con muchas velas de cera ardiendo, y también en la sala había
verdes plantas, y canarios en jaulas, y una enorme cruz negra de madera, con adornos y remates
de plata fina, asida a la pared por fuertes alcayatas. Era la cruz que D. Acisclo, cuando mozo,
había llevado al hombro en las procesiones durante muchos años, porque había sido y era aún
hermano de cruz, aunque jubilado, y aún se vestía de nazareno, para ir en la procesión como
hermano mayor delante de la Cena, con una túnica de rica seda morada que había costado un dineral;
pero entonces no llevaba la cruz, sino una pértiga reluciente, signo de autoridad y mando.
Su hijo primogénito iba delante con el estandarte de la cofradía.

El gasto de la fiesta era grande, porque D. Acisclo costeaba toda la cera que llevaban ardiendo
los que con sendas velas seguían su insignia, y en la noche del Jueves Santo, terminada ya
la procesión, daba de cenar a todos los cofrades, que eran muchos, agasajándolos y hartándolos
con potaje de habas, cornetillas picantes, cazón en ajo de pollo, bacalao con tomates o en
albóndigas, a veces hasta serafines fritos, pues, aunque parezca extraño, serafines se llaman
en aquel país los boquerones, y de postres deliciosos pestiños y vino añejo. Pagaba además
con rumbo generoso a los cuarenta o cincuenta ganapanes que habían llevado en hombros las andas,
y en las andas la mesa, con Cristo, Apóstoles y cuanto Dios crió; empresa titánica, de la cual
no pocos quedaban derrengados y con feroces ampollas, a pesar de las almohadillas.

Aquella noche echaba D. Acisclo el bodegón por la ventana.

La gente menuda fumaba a su costa los mejores coraceros que había en el estanco, y el señorío
tomaba chocolate con hojaldres, empanadas, hornazos, tortas de varias clases, como por ejemplo,
de polvorón y de aceite, y roscos de vino y de huevo.

En cualquier día y a cualquier hora se mostraba en todo que D. Acisclo era espléndido y acaudalado.

El patio de la casa era anchuroso y enlosado de mármol. En su centro lucía una taza de mármol
también, donde caía el agua clara de un copioso y alto surtidor. En torno de la fuente se veían
muchas macetas con flores y hierbas olorosas, y alrededor arriates con bojes, que formaban
bolas y pirámides, y rosales de enredadera, jazmines y naranjos, que revestían el muro y trepaban
por cima de los balcones del piso principal, tejiendo una capa o manto de flores, frutos y
verdura, y embalsamando el ambiente, ya con el olor del azahar, ya con el más leve aroma de
jazmines y de mosquetas.

De este patio, así como de un jardín más extenso, con honores de huerta, que había a espaldas
de la casa, cuidaba doña Luz con esmero. Hasta hacía venir flores y plantas, que jamás se habían
conocido en Villafría, y solía aclimatarlas.

De nada más cuidaba doña Luz, no por desidia, sino porque, según decía D. Acisclo, se obstinaba
en sostener que estaba como de huésped, y no quería meterse en camisón de once varas.

Quien lo gobernaba todo, la verdadera directora y ama de llaves, era la Sra. Petra, de edad
de cincuenta años muy cumplidos. Ella entendía en el gasto diario, vigilaba la cocina y tenía
las llaves de la despensa, de la repostería, de la candiotera, de las cuatro bodegas de vino,
aceite, aguardiente y vinagre, y de los desvanes o graneros, donde siempre había trigo, cebada,
arvejones, yeros, matalahúga y otras semillas.

A las inmediatas órdenes de la Sra. Petra había cuatro criadas: dos, zagalonas aún, duras en
el trabajo, de apretadas carnes y músculos de acero, las cuales eran de las que llaman por
allá de cuerpo de casa, esto es, que servían para fregar, aljofifar, enjalbegar y tenerlo todo
saltandito de limpio; otra, ya más granada, aunque moza también, que cosía, zurcía y planchaba
la ropa, y otra que guisaba los más castizos y sabrosos guisotes de la tierra, y que sabía
hacer almíbares, cuajados, pastelillos, arrope y gachas de mosto.

Toda esta tropa femenina habitaba y dormía en el piso principal de la casa de campo, donde
también tenían habitación el aperador, su mujer y sus cuatro chiquillos; pero éstos, tan apartados,
que no se veían ni se entendían sino cuando el amo llamaba.

Había, por último un mozo, que dormía junto a la caballeriza y cuidaba de ella, de los patios
y corrales.

Tal era la servidumbre doméstica, por decirlo así. Pero ya se entiende que los jornaleros,
el mulero, los caseros, los viñadores, los pisadores, los del molino y la demás gente que se
empleaba en las faenas agrícolas, iban y venían y hacía estancia en la casa de campo, donde
había anchura sobrada, y alambique, lagar, alfarje y prensas para la aceituna y la uva.

Resultaba, pues, como ya queda apuntado, que en la casa de los amos sólo vivían D. Acisclo,
doña Luz y su criada Juana.

Tomás, el antiguo criado del marqués, vivía en la casa solariega con un mozuelo que le ayudaba
a cuidarla y a cuidar también el hermoso caballo negro de la señorita.

En la casa había dos mesas: una a la que se sentaban D. Acisclo y doña Luz y algún convidado
si le había; otra para la familia (en los pueblos andaluces se sigue llamando familia a los
criados), y en dicha mesa se sentaban la señora Petra presidiendo, las dos mozas de cuerpo
de casa, la costurera y planchadora, la cocinera, el mozo de la caballeriza, Tomás y su ayudante,
y la Juana, doncella de la señorita doña Luz.

El aperador y los suyos hacían rancho aparte y tenían una cocinilla moruna donde guisaba la
aperadora.

Esto no impedía que ella, o alguno de sus hijos, o todos, incluso el aperador, aunque no hijo,
sino padre, estuviesen convidados con frecuencia a la mesa de la familia, a la cual se sentaban
asimismo el mulero y otros cuando estaban en el lugar, y a la cual la señora Petra y la Juana
se atribuían el derecho, y no se descuidaban en ejercerle, de hacer las invitaciones que se
les antojaban.

Tal era la casa en que durante doce años había vivido doña Luz, y tal la gente de que estaba
rodeada en mayo de 1860.

-IV-

Los amigos íntimos de doña Luz

Doña Luz, dadas las circunstancias en que se hallaba y las condiciones de su carácter, no podía
menos de vivir como vivía.

El orgullo es malo sin duda.

¿Cuánto mejor y más cristiana no es la humildad? En el orgullo hay mucho de egoísmo, mientras
que la humildad es toda devoción y abandono. Y sin embargo, ¿cómo negar que un orgullo bien
dirigido es causa a veces de altas virtudes y de honrada conducta?

Sea como sea, no debemos ocultar que nuestra heroína era muy orgullosa.

Quien esto escribe no tiene manías o predilecciones aristocráticas. Al contrario, siempre se
ha obstinado en creer que no vale menos la gente de los lugares que la más encopetada de la
corte. Mutatis mutandis, todo le parece lo mismo: la mujer del alcalde es igual a una emperatriz
o reina, la del escribano equivale a la duquesa más en moda en Madrid, y el majo Fulanito se
le antoja más brioso, y gallardo, buen jinete, seductor, afable y ameno, que el más perfecto
dandy de cuantos ha conocido.

Pero, mirándolo bien, esto no es espíritu democrático discreto, sino negro y desconsolador
pesimismo. La democracia optimista y sana consiste, sin duda, en creer que la mejor educación
desde la primera infancia, el buen ejemplo y nombre de padres y abuelos, la obligación de no
deshonrar ni deslustrar este buen nombre y el vivir en medio más urbano y culto, deben ser
escuela e incentivo eficaz para ser virtuosos o discretos, o seductores, o dignos o todo a
la vez. En igualdad de índole y de luces intelectuales debe, por consiguiente, valer mucho
más quien posee los dichos exteriores requisitos que aquel que no los posee: en igualdad de
condiciones internas, la hija de un marqués, por ejemplo, aun cuando sea bastarda, debe conducirse
mejor que la hija de un pelafustán. De entender lo contrario por espíritu democrático, se seguiría
que lo que debemos desear es la igualdad bajando y no subiendo: la nivelación en la ignorancia,
la abyección y la miseria, y no la nivelación y elevación posibles, en todos aquellos medios,
en toda aquella acumulación de recursos hecha por las pasadas generaciones, a fin de que con
su auxilio sigamos ascendiendo hacia el bien, hacia la luz y hacia la belleza.

Yo comprendo como veneranda y punto menos que santa, aunque vaya por caminos extraviados, la
intención del demagogo, demócrata y hasta socialista, que pugne por dar a todos los hombres
educación liberal, recursos y cuantos elementos gozan los llamados aristócratas, si es que
estos elementos valen, no sólo para gozar, sino para ser mejores; pero si sólo valen para gozar
y ser más débiles, corrompidos y ruines, no me explico la democracia progresista, sino la democracia
de Rousseau, que procura retrotraer a la humanidad al estado salvaje.

De cualquier modo que sea, conste que yo no defiendo aquí esta o aquella opinión. No es lo
que escribo un tratado de filosofía política. No intento tampoco presentar a doña Luz como
un dechado de excelencias, sino presentarla tal como ella fue.

Doña Luz sentía profundamente la dignidad humana, pero suponía que lo claro y distinto de este
sentimiento, que había en ella más que en otras personas, no dependía sólo de un don natural
y gratuito, sino de una educación superior a la de la generalidad, y mucho más esmerada. Esto,
más bien que orgullo, parece modestia. Ella creía tener un ideal de sí propia que había ido
realizando y como trayendo fuera, merced sin duda a su misma energía, pero auxiliada de circunstancias
dichosas e iniciales que debía a la Providencia, y en que no todos, sino pocos, se hallan.
Se juzgaba, pues, como favorecida por Dios, y por lo mismo con más obligaciones que cumplir.
Por cada favor divino, una obligación sagrada. Tenía talento, estaba obligada a cultivarle;
era bella y fuerte, necesitaba conservar su fuerza y su hermosura; había recibido un nombre
ilustre, y, ya que no acertase a ilustrarle más, no debía mancharle.

Aunque ella se considerara igual por naturaleza a los demás seres humanos, los juzgaba a todos
marchando en busca de mayor bien y de superior altura más luminosa y serena. Si ella, aun cuando
fuese por un capricho de la suerte, iba delante y se hallaba más cerca de la cumbre, su filantropía
no podía extenderse a más que a dar la mano a los que estuviesen en condiciones de trepar hasta
donde estaba ella, y no a aquellos que estaban tan bajos o tan hundidos en el lodo, que en
vez de alzarlos, se dejaría ella arrastrar cayendo en el lodo también.

Ya hemos indicado que el orgullo de doña Luz se velaba y envolvía en el más discreto disimulo;
y esto no sólo por prudencia y por interés propio, sino por vivo sentimiento de caridad. Nada
le dolía tanto como humillar al prójimo. Si tal vez se complacía en lucir alguna habilidad,
alguna buena prenda de su espíritu, algún primor o elegancia de su persona, era con los capaces
de sentir el estímulo de imitarla o alzarse hasta ella; no por el prurito de excitar estéril
admiración o envidia dolorosa.

Doña Luz, por lo mismo que tenía tanto orgullo, no tenía chispa de vanidad. Gustaba en todo
de pagar con usura lo que recibía. No anhelaba que la amasen más de lo que podía amar ella.
La coquetería era, pues, para doña Luz un vicio ignorado y casi incomprensible. Su fallo, la
propia sentencia que ella dictaba acerca de cualquiera calidad, acto o virtud de su persona,
la lisonjeaba y complacía mil veces más que todo el aplauso de cuantos la rodeaban. Así es
que sólo quería agradar de puro bondadosa: por donde resultaban en ella una naturalidad, una
modestia y un olvido aparente de su propio mérito, que encantaban y pasmaban.

Otras mujeres están anhelando siempre inspirar pasiones; doña Luz huía de inspirarlas; y, aplicando
un pronto desengaño, las mataba en todo corazón antes de que naciesen. ¿Para qué ser amada
si no había de amar a quien la amase? En amor, lo mismo que en amistad, doña Luz deseaba dar
el doble. Y no pudiendo amar en Villafría, había poco a poco apartado de sí a todos los mozos
del lugar, y había elegido sus amigos íntimos entre los viejos.

Si era dulce en su trato con todos, usaba tan estudiada cortesía, que sin que la tildasen de
soberbia, evitaba la intimidad con todos, menos con cuatro sujetos.

El primero era D. Miguel, cura de la parroquia, anciano excelente aunque de cortísimos alcances,
con quien se confesaba todos los meses, a quien daba sus ahorrillos para que los repartiese
en limosnas a los necesitados, y con quien a menudo jugaba al tute. El corazón y la mente de
doña Luz eran para el pobre cura el libro de los siete sellos. En esta oscuridad, y siendo
además D. Miguel poco entusiasta, quería con moderación a doña Luz; pero la quería con toda
la fuerza de alma de que él podía disponer para el cariño, que era poquísima. Doña Luz, en
cambio, idolatraba al cura de cierta manera. Se complacía en aquella transparencia, en aquella
nitidez, en aquella bendita vaciedad de su espíritu, y le mimaba y agasajaba como a un niño
pequeñuelo. Por medio de un contrabandista que iba y venía con telas de algodón, hacía traer
de Lisboa para D. Miguel el rapé más selecto; y, procurando que no le hiciesen mal, le enviaba
confites, bizcochos y otras golosinas, a que el cura era muy aficionado.

Otro íntimo de más importancia, era el médico D. Anselmo. Y digo de más importancia, por lo
que él valía, no porque doña Luz le necesitase. La salud de doña Luz era insolente de buena.
Ni un dolor de cabeza nunca.

D. Anselmo era un hombre despejadísimo, y no sólo hábil e instruido en su profesión, sino de
variada lectura y de singular facilidad de palabra. No se extrañe que con tales dotes fuese
médico en un lugar. O la fortuna no le había sonreído, o su genio indómito y arisco se había
opuesto a que se encumbrase. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1028765</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22532</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

But if great! amid all this enthusiasm, Dona Luz had had no Boyfriend: Do not talk about or
talked to anyone on the fence. What she did was crowd had suitors, though she had given hope
to none. The richest young Some leagues around the already considered impregnable fortress.
The hope, all, it is ever lost. The men in this matter of sexual conquests, promise to us, often
happy. So, if the place had already been refreshed and disillusioned, not missing even strangers,
as long as they were subjects of a stem, that is stirred to see Dona Luz, and proposed himself back
in, get what others had failed; but soon also disappointed.

With this worship resolved with this itching to be matched, had found
many or simultaneously or successively.

None had come to explain. He composed Dona Luz so that had not ever seen the need for formal hard
squash, or excite the resentment that this entails. It was difficult to talk to her alone. It
was difficult to get their hands letter or billet-doux. And while, thanks to some old bold
that wherever there are plenty of Dona Luz had received little notes in prose and even in verse,
had consistently returned unopened. In view of these and other slights, all lovers finally desist
from their purpose, no reason and no excuse to complain.

And I could not any, because Dona Luz rightly offensive silent. He
did not feel inclined to marriage.

Not love. No one sends in his heart. Such were his reasons.

Someone might suspect but not prove invincible repugnance to everything vulgar and plebeian and
the horror that gripped her at the thought of being able to one day have a son who carry his
illustrious family name after another dark and rustic name of some rich guy villain.

In short: Dona Luz, if he could not expect to marry at will, or had not betrayed no desire. Everything
was quiet and contentment she coolly smooth. In vain, the worst thought of the men would dare
to look at their actions, their words, their gestures and gesture,
the slightest sign that was spurned.

Luz was not true. He had taken his party had strongly path advance the path of his life. The
derisive phrase to stay for Aunt or dress pictures made no dent in
your firm and steely heart, nor could violate it, nor inclined to
accept husband with the sole purpose of not reaching spinster.

Several wealthy relatives, who had Dona Luz in Seville and Madrid, had been invited to went to live
with them: but, or because they really were, or because he suspected Dona Luz, the invitations
had been more than heart for compliance. In addition, Mrs. Light was considered very poor for
its class, and would not be burdensome, nor live at the expense of
others and in a kind dependence close to servitude.

There was, therefore, refused all invitations. His plan was to live and die obscurely in Villafría.

The
same impurity of his origin, birth defect, the humble condition of unknown mother, worked for
reaction in his mind and almost turned his fierce pride.

To clean original spot that I wanted to be Dona Luz much cleaner
and more pure.

I did not want pordiosear not owe anything to anyone.

Retained without selling his ancestral home the place with its antique furniture and two servants.
If did not live there, thinking later life, or because they don Acisclo
could be missing or because, entered her in years, one might wonder
that he lived alone.

Meanwhile, Dona Luz lived in the mansion of Don Acisclo, where he
had ample independent room, where he had brought to adorn her most
beautiful and precious furniture and better books.

In return for this hospitality, gift Acisclo did accept, though it
had resisted, more than half their income, or 8,000 reais a year.

With the rest, as economic era and arranged, was enough to dress, buy some new books and do
charity.

The only luxury, the unique gift of Dona Luz was a magnificent black horse, which used her out
to walk with D. Acisclo or a servant named Thomas, who had grown old in for her father.

Don Acisclo was a widower so long. He had two sons and three daughters, all married and a separate
house, so that in the wide expanse of that vast solitude mansion, Dona Luz and D. Acisclo gave
each other's company.

Verged and D. Acisclo in seventy years, but he was strong and in good
health.

He was right as a spindle, was a man agile and lean meat, and if he knew no more than read and
write fairly and the four rules, and if he had never read a book, had great natural clearing,
even crude. I had never troubled his conscience with moral subtleties. So, not to his heart, as
we said, had contributed to the ruin of the Marquis. If she had taken advantage of her best
He seemed to have been no other.

Much would have hurt to see the flow into foreign hands of his master.

Poseíale, therefore, in good faith with just title, and up to and
indeed feeling of reverence for the memory of the illustrious deceased
owner.

Such worship is extended, or rather, are extreme and reached its height,
without affecting or servility, when it was Miss Dona Luz, who, fascinated
by the old man, believed discover a being whose arcane thoughts, mobile,
and springs of action, barely glimpsed; a rare and unusual creatures
from another caste very different from yours, and which, without But
I ate every day and had the honor of sharing the house.

-III-

In
other trifles that conscientiousness of the narrator does not allow
to pass in silence

It included this house, like many other wealthy
landowners in Andalucía, of two houses contiguous communication: the
masters and always called cottage, although is in the center of town.

The house masters inhabitants had no D. Acisclo at one end, and Dona Luz in another Juana with
her old servant, who slept in a room next to his wife.

There was a large dining room, another small room for newspapers and several rooms of respect,
not opened only on great occasions, and where, among other treasures, D. Acisclo, their sons,
daughters, sons and daughters, all glowing oil portraits, more than natural size, and almost
the entire body, an itinerant painter who happened to pass by Villafría, and led an ounce
of gold for each portrait. True, D. Acisclo you entertained and treated like royalty, him at
his desk all the time it took to paint, which was the work of five months and then, when he
departed, he did this a thousand sweets, for example, a pipotillo with double brandy anise,
dried apricots and alfajores and Piñonate. The portraits it like it deserved. Lacked not only
talk. The lace contained in of the ladies were a little confusing at first, but, bowing to complaints
from the ladies aforesaid, the painter managed to ingenious artifice.

Smeared on a piece of tulle white lead, was applied to the picture site, and dry, where the
lace was represented, and it was a fact wonderful, because even the lace holes looked and still
could be counted.

All this was on the main floor, where two fireplaces, French call there, and not lit, but when
the bishop came in mid-winter, and nearly drowns S. SI with the smoke that was put together.
But instead there was a great gentlemen kitchen with fireplace Bell, of much shot, which always
burned during the cold season, plenty of firewood oak and olive-pomace
rich pasta, where it is rarely cooked, and where the lords warmed
very much to his taste.

In this kitchen adorned the walls several cages for partridges, placed on shelves, shotguns and
other weapons, and some heads of deer, wolves, foxes, badgers and martens, killed by D. Acisclo.

On
the ground floor was almost as much room as in the main, and, if the court had with awning, was more.
Lived there during the summer. In all seasons he was there at the office D. Acisclo, where
the cattle farmer and was active with barges, brokers, rabadanes, overseer, foreman and home:
understanding by landlords, not tenants' terror delinquent, as in
Madrid, but those who care and keep those houses or dwellings in each
farm paperback.

On the ground floor in the living room and authority over device, called the block, because it was square,
there was something that gave luster to the house. It should be known that in many villages
Andalusia is blessed multitude of images that are taken in procession on the great festivals,
and particularly at Easter. The number of these images often do not fit well in temples, so many are
held in private houses until one day the year in which they leave in procession. D. Acisclo was in the
barn down one of these images brotherhood whose older brother was, but it was a picture of three
fourth, but the more complicated was known and the most effort and
cost, and it does not really say that she prayed proverbial:

Santirulitos
nice, cheap, neither eat nor drink, nor wear shoes.

Image or representation that eating and drinking, or rather supped, was nothing less than the
dinner.

Christ and the twelve apostles of the package sat at the table, threw
the blessing Christ, San Juan is asleep on the shoulder of his Divine
Master, and the ugly and treacherous Judas, with tangled red hair,
put his hand on the center plate, because it is known not pinch of
education.

Holy Thursday procession left the Supper, and Holy Wednesday evening was exposed on the block to
the veneration of the faithful, who on that occasion had free entry
into the house, which was called and is called the badges still visit,
and just left in place who no visits on the eve of the respective
procession.

And this if you have outsiders.

The table at which Christ and the apostles were sitting, was quite capable, and in so solemn
days, was covered with precious cloths and adorned alemaniscos niceties of a thousand flowers, meats,
sweets and fruits. Although not on the table of what God created, as claimed by the villagers with
excessive price increases, it was undeniable that there were rare and expensive: grape goat heart
as just that miracle catch and had been preserved, carnations and early roses smell in large
cones, bunches of violets and camellias, etc.., etc. The walls of the room where the dinner
was carpeted with crimson damask is, on the damask hung beautiful and ancient cornucopias with
many burning candles, and also in the room was green plants, and canaries in cages, and a huge
black cross, wooden ornaments and finials fine silver, clutching to the wall by sharp spikes.
It was the cross D. Acisclo, when young, shoulder had taken in processions for many years because
it had been and was still Cross brother, though retired, still dressed in Nazareth, to go in the procession
as older brother before the dinner, with a rich purple silk gown that had cost a fortune;
but then did not carry the cross, but a shiny pole, a sign of authority
and command.

His eldest son went ahead with the banner of the brotherhood.

The expense of the party was great, because D. Acisclo expenses all carrying burning wax the paths
that still sails his flagship, and on the night of Holy Thursday, and finished the procession,
dinner was all the brothers, who were many, entertained and fed with bean stew, cornetillas spicy
garlic chicken dogfish, cod with tomatoes or meatballs, sometimes fried seraphim, because,
oddly enough, are called seraphim in that country, anchovies, and delectable desserts and vintage
wine bores. Also paid generous due to the forty or fifty porters who had carried on the shoulders
of the litter and the litter the table, with Christ, Apostles, and
as God created him mammoth undertaking, which not a few were broken-backed
and blisters fierce, despite the pads.

That night threw D. Acisclo still life out the window.

The little people smoked at their expense cuirassiers best that was
in the tobacco and dominion took chocolate with pastries, pies, hornazos,
cakes of various kinds, such as polvorón and oil, wine and donuts
and egg.

On any day, any time all that was shown in D. Acisclo was beautiful and wealthy.

The backyard was broad and paved with marble. In the center wearing a marble basin also, where
clear water falling a hearty, high spout. Around the source were many pots of flowers and fragrant
herbs, and some beds with bogies, which were balls and pyramids,
and climbing roses, jasmine and orange trees that lined the wall and
climbing on top of the balconies on the main floor, weaving a cloak
or mantle of flowers, fruits and vegetables, and embalming the environment,
and with the smell of orange blossoms, and with the slightest scent
jasmine and musk.

In this courtyard, and a larger garden, with garden honors, he had
to back of the house, looked carefully Dona Luz.

So did come flowers and plants, which had never Villafría known and used to acclimatise.

De Dona Luz cared nothing, not laziness, but because he said D. Acisclo persisted to argue that
he was as a guest, and did not want to get into nightgown chew.

Who ruled all, the real director and a housekeeper was Mrs. Petra, age very accomplished fifty years.
She understood in daily expenditures, and had watched the kitchen
the keys to the pantry, pastry, the winery, the four wineries, oil,
spirits and vinegar, and attics or barns, where there were always
wheat, barley, arvejones, yeros, anise and other seeds.

In the immediate orders of Mrs. Petra had four servants, two, zagalonas even hard? Work, tight
meat and muscles of steel, which were called by the Beyond body home, that is, they served to
scrub, mop, whitewash and have it all saltandito of clean, another and more grains, but also
girl, who sewed, mended and ironed clothing, and one that cooked
the most authentic and tasty stews of the earth, and knew make syrup,
clotted, pastries, syrup and juice porridge.

All these female soldiers lived and slept on the main floor of the
cottage where room were also the overseer, his wife and four kids,
but these, so far apart, not seen or understood but when the master
called.

There was finally a boy, who was sleeping next to the barn and took care of it, patios and
pens.

Such was the domestic servitude, as it were.

But it is understood that the hired the mule, landlords, the tenants, the plungers, the mill
and the other people who employed in agricultural work, came and
went and had stayed in the cottage where width was more than enough,
and still, press, paneled ceiling and presses for olives and grapes.

It was, therefore, as we have already noted, that the house owners only lived D. Acisclo Dona
Juana Luz and her maid.

Thomas, the former servant of the Marquis, lived in the manor house with a lad that helped to care
and also care for the beautiful black horse of the lady.

In the house were two tables: one that would sit D. Acisclo and Dona Luz and some invited if he
had, one for the family (in the Andalusian village is still called the family servants), and on
that table sat Mrs. Petra presiding, the two women's body home, seamstress and laundress, cook,
the groom of the stables, Thomas and his assistant and Jane, maiden Miss Dona Luz.

The overseer and his ranch were separate and had a small kitchen where she cooked the Moorish
overseer.

This did not prevent him or any of their children, or all, even the
overseer, but not child but father, were often guests at the family
table, which sat mule and others also when they were in place, and
which Mrs. Petra and Jane assumed the right, not neglecting to exercise
it, to make the invitations that they wanted.

Such was the house he had lived for twelve years Dona Luz, and such
people that was surrounded in May 1860.

-IV-

Close friends Dona
Luz

Luz, the circumstances in which it was and the conditions of
his character, could not less to live as he lived.

Pride is certainly wrong.

How much better and is not Christian humility? In much of selfish pride, while humility is all
devotion and abandonment. Yet how can we deny that a good pride led sometimes causes high virtues
and honest behavior?

Anyway, we should not hide the fact that our heroine was very proud.

This writer has no hobbies or aristocratic predilections. On the contrary, always has persisted
in believing that people are not worth less the more swanky places that the court. Mutatis mutandis,
everything looks the same: the mayor's wife is equal to an empress or queen, the clerk's equivalent
to the Duchess more in vogue in Madrid, and is nice Fulanito he seems more lively, and graceful,
a good horseman, charming, affable and friendly, the most perfect dandy he has known.

But, on balance, this is not democratic spirit discreet, but black and dismal pessimism. Optimistic
and healthy democracy is no doubt in believing that the best education from early childhood, good
example and name of parents and grandparents, the obligation not disgrace or tarnish the good name
and a half living in urban and educated, should be school and effective incentive to be virtuous
and discreet, or alluring or worthy or particularly time. On an equal intellectual light nature
and should therefore be worth much else who has the external requirements such that it does
not possess: equal internal conditions, the daughter of a marquis,
for example, even if it is spurious and should be conducted better
than the daughter of a ragamuffin.

Otherwise understand the democratic spirit, it follows that what we want is equality and not
climbing down: Levelling in ignorance abjection and misery, not leveling and elevation possible
in all media, in all this accumulation of resources made by past generations, so that their
help continue climbing towards good, towards the light and the beauty.

I understand how venerable and all but holy paths even if you lost,
the intention of the demagogue, Democrat and even socialist, which
strives to give all men liberal education, resources and few elements
have so-called aristocratic, if these items are worth, not only to
enjoy, but to be better, but if you only apply for benefit and be
more weak, corrupt and vile, I can not explain the progressive democracy,
but democracy Rousseau, who seeks to roll back humanity to the savage
state.

Either way it is, it appears that I am not advocating this or that
opinion here.

Is not I write a treatise on political philosophy. Do not attempt to present either as Dona Luz
a paragon of excellence, but as she was present.

Luz deeply felt human dignity, but assumed that this clear and distinct sentiment, which had
in it more than other people, not just reliance on a natural gift and free, but a higher education to
the generality, and more careful. This rather than pride, seems modest. She believed he had
an ideal of himself that had been made and as we bring out, thanks no doubt to his own power,
but assisted in circumstances blissful and initials should be to Providence, and that not all
but few are. Be judged, then, as favored by God, and therefore more obligations to fulfill.
For every divine favor, a sacred obligation.

He had talent, he was obliged to cultivate; was beautiful and strong, needed to retain its strength
and beauty, had been named illustrious, and, if not more successful to enlighten, it should not
stain.

Although she was considered equal in nature to other humans, he judged all going in search
of greater height than good and more luminous and serene.

If she does, even if was by a quirk of fate, went ahead and was closer to the summit, his philanthropy
could not extend more than shake hands with those who were able to climb up where she was, and
not those who were so low and so deep in the mud, which Instead of lifting, it would drag it
falling in the mud too.

We have already indicated that the pride of Dona Luz was veiled and
shrouded in the most discreet concealment; and this not only out of
prudence and self-interest, but by the lively sense of charity.

Nothing hurt as much as to humiliate others. If you may be pleased to show off a skill, a good
piece of his mind, a delicacy and elegance of his person, was able to feel the stimulus to
imitate or rise to it, not with a desire to excite sterile painful admiration or envy.

Doña Luz, therefore he had so proudly, had no spark of vanity. Liked all to repay with interest
what he received. No longed to love her more than I could love her. The flirtation was, then,
for a vice Dona Luz ignored and almost incomprehensible.

The decision, the own statement she dictated about any quality or act under him, the flattered and
pleased thousand times more than all the applause of those around her. So I just wanted to
please the pure kind, where there were a naturalness, a modesty and apparent neglect of his
own merit, which charmed and amazed.

Other women are longing to always inspire passions inspire Dona Luz fleeing, and, applying an
early disappointment, the killing in my heart before they were born.

Why be loved if there was to love who loved her? In love as in friendship, wished to Dona Luz twice.
And not being able to love in Villafría, had little by little out of himself to all the boys
the place, and had chosen his close friends among the old.

If it was fresh in his dealings with everyone, as studied using courtesy, without the branded
pride, avoiding intimacy with all but four subjects.

The first was D. Michael, parish priest, Father excellent although very short ranges, whom he
confessed every month, who gave his nest egg for the dole in alms to the needy, and who often
played the tute. The heart and mind Dona Luz was for the poor priest's book of seven seals. In
this darkness, and being also D. Miguel unenthusiastic, I wanted
in moderation Dona Luz, but loved her with all the strength of soul
that he could have for the baby, which was very little.

Doña Luz, Instead, he idolized the priest in some way. He was pleased that transparency, in
that sharpness, in that blessed emptiness of his spirit, and pampered and entertained him as
a child little boy.

By means of a smuggler who came and went with cotton cloth, was brought D. Lisbon Miguel choicest
snuff, and making sure that did not make him wrong, he sent candies, cookies and other goodies,
that the priest was very fond.
Another intimate of more importance, was the doctor D. Anselmo. I
say more importance, he was worth, not because you need him Dona Luz.
The health of Dona Luz was insolent good. Not a headache ever.

D.
Despejadísimo Anselmo was a man, not only skilled and educated in
his profession, but reading varied and unique way with words. Do not
be surprised that such gifts were doctor in one place. O fortune had
not smiled, and his genius was wild and vicious lifted himself opposed.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>