<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01338</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>172080</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23591</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Al espanto de aquella noche, recién llegado
yo a Tablanca, habían sucedido otros dos por el estilo; pero como huía de mí en cuanto me acercaba
a ella con propósitos de interrogarla sobre tan extraño particular, después de pedirme con
las manos juntas y por el amor de Dios que no le dijera a mi tío una palabra de lo que estaba
notando, limitábame, por complacerla, a observarla desde lejos y a no perderla de vista mientras
me fuera posible. ¿Qué diablos podía haber allí? ¿Eran fantasmas, alucinaciones histéricas
de la pobre mujer tan castigada por la desgracia a lo mejor de su vida, o estaba bajo el peso
insoportable de alguna nueva desdicha? Neluco Celis: continuaba pareciéndome lo mismo que me
pareció cuando le hablé por vez primera: discreto, simpático, de clarísima inteligencia y noble
corazón, y un arca cerrada para guardar lo que a mí se me antojaba que debía estar al alcance
de mi vista: verbigracia, su inclinación amorosa a la nieta de don Pedro Nolasco. Porque yo
no podía concebir que Lita y Neluco no se amaran, como no lo concebía tampoco la matrona locuaz
de Robacío, ni lo concebiría nadie que tuviera entrañas de humanidad y vislumbres de buen gusto,
y reparara un poco en aquella parejita, «única», que parecía puesta por Dios en aquel rinconcito
de la tierra para eso sólo, para amarse y para unirse. Lita y su madre habían estado dos veces
en mi casa después que yo estuve en la suya. Una de ellas, según me declararon, para pagarme
la visita y saludar, de paso, a mi tío; y la otra, por mi tío solamente, cuya salud les interesaba
mucho; además de que, como no podía salir de casa, iban a hacerle un rato de compañía, como
siempre que lo permitían el tiempo y sus ocupaciones. Todo esto me lo afirmaba Lituca descubriendo
las esmaltadas filas de sus blanquísimos dientes, en su lenguaje vehemente, retozón y admirativo,
a la puerta del estragal y mientras sacaba sus pies, calzados con menudas zapatillas de abrigo
sobre medias de color, de un par de almadreñas que parecían dos cáscaras de nuez. En aquella
visita, lo mismo que en la anterior, yo, terco y emperrado en mi tema, le eché cincuenta veces
al campo de la conversación disfrazado de mil modos, con el piadoso fin de observar qué cara
le ponía Lita... y nada: ni un gesto, ni un punto arrebolado en las mejillas, ni la más insignificante
señal en la nieta de don Pedro Nolasco de que había oído su corazón las llamadas que yo le
hacía con el nombre de Neluco y los elogios de sus méritos: hablaba de él con el descuido y
la serenidad con que podía hablar de su madre o de su abuelo. Lo cual me impacientaba a mí,
como si fuera asunto de mi propia pertenencia, y en más de una ocasión me acometieron serias
tentaciones de preguntarla derechamente y sin ambages ni rodeos: «¿se quieren o no se quieren
ustedes? ¿Ama usted o no ama a Neluco?». Pero señor, ¿por qué tenía yo tanto empeño en que
se amaran? O mejor dicho, ¿por qué le tenía tan grande en que quedara enseguida aquel punto
bien esclarecido y deslindado?

Después, mi tío Celso, el alma y el centro de todo cuanto le rodeaba, con su energía indomable,
sus cuchufletas singularísimas, su atención siempre fija en el modo de hacerme, ya que no divertida,
llevadera la vida en su casa, y los cuidados a que me obligaban el parentesco y la gratitud
para velar por él con especial esmero durante el tiempo de las humedades y de los grandes fríos,
en el cual, según dictamen del médico, corría su vida los mayores peligros, por la índole de
la enfermedad que padecía.

Y por último, su tertulia y mis libros, mis periódicos y mi correspondencia. Lo restante de
ambos montones, algo de ello por su insignificancia, y otro poco por lejano, sólo podía considerarse
como personajes decorativos y accesorios escénicos.

Cierto que con todas estas reservas de tan escasa importancia en relación con las necesidades
de mi espíritu, se podía llegar hasta lo épico, consideradas como elementos de creación en
la fantasía de un novelista ingenioso; pero tomadas en lo que eran y valían, como casos y cosas
de la vida real y prosaica en un medio tan remoto, tan obscuro y tan aislado como aquél, ¿qué
había de prometerme yo de ellas para en adelante? ¿Qué auxiliares contra mi enemigo temible
podía esperar de aquel lado? ¿Qué podía venir de allí de lo que más necesario me era?

--¡Quién sabe!--me dije en conclusión de mis cavilaciones--. Por puntos más obscuros ha amanecido
otras veces; si está de Dios que ha de venir algo, ello vendrá. Todo es cuestión de paciencia
y de saber conformarse. Conque un poco de filosofía, y a esperar lo que viniere.

XVII

Y comenzó a venir sin tardar mucho; pero ¡ay! lo que vino fue, primeramente, una niebla gris
que bajó de los montes, envolvió todo el pueblo y se coló hasta en los hogares; tras de aquella
niebla vino un «gallego» frío con otra niebla parda que fue mezclándose con la primera, tiznándola
de su color y haciéndola más húmeda y pegajosa; llegó también un ruido sordo y continuo, como
lejano cañoneo, que a mí me parecía de la mar batiendo furibunda hacia el Norte los peñascos
de la costa; pero según dictamen de la gente de mi casa, era el «rebombe» del «pozón de Peña
Sagra», un lago o pozo muy grande, que se da por existente, aunque no sé de nadie que le haya
visto, en las entrañas de aquel coloso de la cordillera; y sin cesar este ruido bronco, dejáronse
oír en el espacio y sobre el valle unos como quejidos siniestros y antipáticos, que eran, según
informes de Chisco, el graznar de los «butres» (buitres) y las grullas, que pasaban «cararriba»;
señal ésta, como la del «rebombar» del pozo y la de las nieblas bajas con el «gallego» detrás,
de que se nos echaba encima una invernada de las gordas.

Y se cumplieron las profecías: las nieblas se convirtieron en negras nubes henchidas de aguaceros,
que el viento, embravecido poco a poco, estrellaba, con mugidos tremebundos, contra casas,
ribazos y bardales, cerrándose boquetes y horizontes por donde quiera que se miraba; sintieron
los más ardientes de sangre los primeros estremecimientos de frío, y nos declaramos todos en
la casona seria y formalmente bloqueados por el invierno.

Las primeras consecuencias de este bloqueo fueron en ella, como era fácil de presumirse, la
reducción de la tertulia a media docena escasa de valientes, entre ellos Pito Salces, a quien
no atajaban en los impulsos de la querencia que le atraía, ni los más fieros vendavales, y
(lo que fue para mí harto más desagradable y no esperado tan pronto) una crisis de mal género
en el estado de mi tío. Como por encargo del médico se le vedaba hasta el asomar las narices
al cuarterón abierto de una ventana, se consumía de impaciencia en los páramos entenebrecidos
de su cárcel; y cuando llegaba la noche y, después de rezar el Rosario en la cocina, veía entrar
en ella dispersos, acobardados, ateridos de frío y calados de agua a unos pocos tertulianos
de los de aquella apretada falange de las primeras noches, y notaba la causa de la deserción
de los demás en el furioso batir de las celliscas contra puertas y ventanas y en el cañón de
la chimenea, quedábase pensativo y mustio, con la cerviz humillada y la vista fija en el flamear
de la lumbre, cuyo calor buscaba por instinto. Y así un día y otro y otro, sin que la dureza
de su fibra alcanzara a disfrazar siquiera los desalientos de su espíritu, llegó a un grado
tal de abatimiento, que me alarmó, porque en un estado moral como el suyo, cualquier aletazo
de su enfermedad era muy temible.

Hablando con él una mañana de aquellos días tan crudos, y solos los dos en la cocina, que era
su ordinario paradero entonces, yo animándole como podía y él conociendo la endeble calidad
de mis estimulantes, acabó por decirme:

--No te canses, Marcelo: este ujano que me roe es más fuerte que tú y yo juntos, por grandes
que sean tus cuidados y por dura que haya sido mi correa. Mira, hombre: todavía no jaz un año
que me tenía yo por tan duro de caer como las hayas de esos montes. ¡Trastajo con la vanidá
de la guapeza humana! A lo mejor del pensar que solamente un rayo de la voluntá de Dios podía
acaldarme en el suelo, un soplo que no apagaría una luz, me puso a las puertas de la muerte
cuando menos lo esperaba y más descuidado dormía. Desde entonces acá, ¡pispajo!, yo que nunca
me espanté de nada ni me encogí por cosa alguna, miro y remito con desconfianza hasta el suelo
en que pongo los pies, porque siempre y a todas horas y en todas partes estoy temiendo el último
golpe que falta para que el roble acabe de caer. Esta es la verdad, ¡cascajo!, y hasta creo
que te apunté algo de ella en alguna de las cartas que te escribí. Pero entonces eran los días
más largos y las noches más cortas; alumbraba el sol a la tierra y calentaba la sangre de los
viejos, y, sobre todo, volvía de su viaje muy temprano; madrugaba mucho para espantar las ideas
tristes de las cabezas en que apenas entra la caridad del sueño por la noche. Por eso me jallaste
tan campante a la venida y me has visto ir tirando así hasta ayer, como quien dice... hasta
que vino lo que yo había visto venir otras veces sin apurarme por ello, y no sé si te diga
que con gusto... ¡con gusto, trastajo! porque cuando hay buena salud, la tierra no tiene salsa
si nos está cantando siempre una misma solfa... y sin cambiar de ropajes... Digo que fui tirando
tal cuál hasta que llegó la primer cellerisca, ésta que todavía está pasando, mientras llega,
por las señales, otra más dura de pelar que ella; y se apagó el sol de día, y se cerraron puertas
y ventanas, y empezó a faltar de noche la gente de la cocina, y a no haber fin para las horas
de la cama ni punto de sosiego para el mal pensar de la cabeza. Yo nunca había visto pasar
por ella las negruras que ahora pasan. Hasta estos días y desde que tengo uso de razón, siempre
el interés de los demás jizo que me olvidara de mí propio; pues ahora ¡ya te quiero un cuento,
pispajo!... y esto es lo que me descuajaringa: no tengo ojos más que para ver cómo va la carcoma
rejundiendo y ajondando en este tronco podrido que se cae por sí mesmo de día en día, de hora
en hora. Paez que el viento, al rebombar en el cañón de la chimenea, me dice algo que nunca
había oído yo antes; pero algo muy temeroso y muy triste... vamos, que ajuyera de ello de buena
gana, si el temporal de afuera no me cerrara todos los caminos de escape, y el frío no me encadenara
los remos y no me cortara la poca respiración que me queda en el gaznate... Otra cosa nunca
vista: te puedo jurar que no me asusta la muerte porque soy viejo y cristiano y sé que ha de
venir sin tardar mucho y que me toca esperarla confiado en la misericordia de Dios, como la
espero; y con ello y con todo, me espanta la enfermedad que me va quitando la vida. ¿Cómo se
explica este potaje? ¿Qué te parece a ti que será esto, Marcelo?

Faltábanme a mí los sofismas científicos con que Neluco, por ejemplo, hubiera podido aclarar
aparentemente aquellas complejas oscuridades que me consultaba mi pobre tío, y despaché la
consulta con cuatro vaguedades muy recalcadas y encarecidas sobre el influjo que ejercen en
la máquina de los pensamientos los largos insomnios, la soledad de la noche, los fríos estacionales...

--Bien podrán tener algo de culpa esos ingredientes--me replicó mi tío con muy escasas señales
de creerlo--; pero a veces se me figura a mí que hay también otros motivos de por medio...
y harto será, ¡trastajo!, que no venga de esa banda toda la podredumbre. Mira, hombre... (porque
puesto en tela de juicio el punto, debe ventilarse en regla; y yo le he visto por muchas caras
en tantas y tantas noches de no pensar en otra cosa): si a mí me viviera no más que uno solo
de los hijos que Dios me fue dando, la muerte de su padre no sería propiamente muerte; porque
en casos como éste, y bien lo sabes tú, la vida de los que se van retoña en los que se quedan
para algo más que llorarlos y rezar por ellos: es un eslabón trabado en otro eslabón... vamos,
una cadena que nunca se rompe ni se acaba. Pero tal como han resultado aquí las cosas y puesto
yo a considerar que estoy a dos dedos de morirme... ¡ay, Marcelo, qué pinturas se me ponen
delante de los ojos! Con las últimas boqueadas, la cadena rota para siempre, el hogar sin lumbre,
los establos vacíos, la casa en silencio y (lo que es peor, si no metisteis la llave entre
las cuatro tablas que fueron a pudrirse con mis huesos al campo santo) en manos de hombres
que no verán en ella más que el ochavo roñoso con que pagarán el derecho de maltratarla. Pues
échate a pensar después en todas estas gentes que viven de su calor, porque son todos ellos,
lo mismo que fueron sus padres y debieran serlo sus hijos, como sangre de la nuestra sangre
y carne del nuestro propio cuerpo, mirándola de reojo al principio para acabar por no acordarse
de ella y por irse desparramando, como pollucos sin la madre, robados al fin, uno a uno por
el milano que no duerme... ¡Ay, trastajo! Esto es muy doloroso, hasta para soñado en pesadilla...
¿Qué no será, hijo mío, visto y palpado en la misma realidad? Créeme, Marcelo: importa mucho
más que la vida de tu tío, lo que ha de irse con ella al otro mundo, si Dios no lo remedia...
¿No te parece a ti que pudiera ser ésta la «consistidura» de las cosas raras que me quitan
el sueño y tanto me acobardan últimamente?

Conociendo como conocía yo la entereza de carácter y los sentimientos de mi tío, evidente era
que andaba en lo cierto en aquella suposición, y que por cierto lo tenía él aunque aparentaba
lo contrario; pero yo no podía declarárselo así, porque declarándolo, o me manifestaba a sus
ojos descariñado e inclemente, o aceptaba un compromiso que no podía aceptar, porque era otro
muy distinto del suyo mi modo de ver aquellas cosas. Me hubiera sido fácil engañarle aventurando
una promesa que quizás andaba él buscando desde la primera carta que me escribió; pero me repugnaba
esa mentira dicha a un hombre tan honrado y tan sagaz como aquél, exponiéndome, además, a que
no me la creyera. Por eso adopté un temperamento anodino que ni alcanzó a levantar sus abatidos
ánimos, ni siquiera a disfrazarle los aprietos en que me puso con su pregunta.

--Todo ello--repuso el buen señor, tratando de hacer un pinito de cháchara que no le salía
bien--, es decir por decir. Marcelo, y ya que echamos la conversación hacia ese lado... ¡Pues
tendría que ver, ¡pispajo!, que diera yo ahora en la gracia de agobiarte con pesadumbres nuevas,
cuando más falta te hace algo alegre con que espantar las negruras de este temporal que se
nos ha echado encima! Mira, hombre, créasme o no me creas: las únicas agallas que me quedan...
vamos, lo único para que me siento animoso a la hora presente, es para ayudar a que no se te
amurrien a ti también las alegraderas. ¿Oístelo? Pues bueno. Algo más y de más importancia
que tengo que decirte, ya te lo diré en su hora y lugar correspondientes, y sin tardar mucho.
Dicho debiera estar ya y por si acaso, días hace; pero... basta de conversación, y no te espante
la amenaza, que aunque el punto es pariente cercano del tratado aquí, no tiene la cara tan
fea. Si las tuvieran iguales los dos me libraría yo mucho de darte a conocer la que no has
visto todavía.

Entró en la cocina Tona, algo tocada también de la murria inverniza, a trajinar en el fogón
donde hablábamos mi tío y yo al calorcillo de la lumbre, y ya no pude preguntarle lo que tenía
a la punta de la lengua, como exploración siquiera alrededor de la casta de aquel nuevo «punto»
que me había puesto en gran curiosidad.

Pero más que curioso por aclararle, quedé preocupado y triste con la pintura hecha por don
Celso del estado de su espíritu. Para llegar a tales extremos de franqueza un hombre de su
temple, ¿cuál no sería el peso de su tribulación? Y ¿cuál la magnitud de mi disgusto y de mi
pena al considerar que yo poseía el remedio de la más grande de las suyas, y, sin embargo,
me resistía a ofrecérsele? ¿Era honrada esta conducta mía? ¿Estaba obligado yo a aceptar compromisos
imposibles de cumplir? ¿Estaba bien demostrada esta imposibilidad? ¿Cabía, en la duda, el recurso
de prometer, a reserva de cumplir hasta donde se pudiera?...

Puesta la cuestión en estos últimos términos ya me pareció más racional y soportable; y si
hubiéramos continuado los dos solos en la cocina, es posible que allí mismo hubiera intentado
yo introducir por este resquicio el primer sostén para sus desfallecimientos.

Pero Tona llevaba tarea para rato (como que se andaba en las proximidades del mediodía), y
por si era poco este estorbo, entró Facia a dirigir la faena. ¡Cosa extraña! La mujer gris
era el único ser de los que habitábamos la casona, en quien no había estampado alguna roncha
el azote del temporal reinante. Hasta el mismo Chisco andaba un tanto espelurciado y encogido
por establos y corraladas, y entraba en la cocina algunas veces con el humor avinagrado; al
revés que Facia, la cual, desde que se habían desencadenado las primeras celleriscas, parecía
otra. Cuanto más azotaban los granizos los paredones de la casa, y más «runflaban» los vendavales
en el cañón de la chimenea, más alegre se le ponía la cara y más diligente se volvía para el
trabajo.

Viéndola tan boyante y en tan ventajosas disposiciones, trabé conversación con ella aquel mismo
día, al llevarme no sé qué cachivaches a mi cuarto.

--Parece--la dije para empezar--, que marchan bien los asuntos, ¿eh?

Entendióme la pregunta; y después de sobrecogerse un poco con ella, me respondió sin titubear:

--Así me los conserve Dios muchu tiempu.

--Me alegro en el alma--la dije entonces--; porque por no verla a usted con los espantos de
estos días...

--¡Ni me los miente, señor, por obra de caridá!--me replicó volviendo a compungirse--. Paez
que los males, como si oyeran, se ponen de pie en cuanto se les menta en boca...

--De todas suertes, resulta que los negocios de usted andan al revés del tiempo.

--¿Por qué lo diz, cristianu?

--Porque a la vez que él se embravece y se emperra, ellos van mejorando.

--Siempre lo que Dios jaz está bien jechu... ¡Ah, si esto durara muchu!...

--¿El temporal?

--Y lo otru.

--¿Cuál es lo otro?

--Lo que reza con lo que usté quiere saber.

--Y sin llegar a conseguirlo, por más señas... Vamos a ver, Facia: ahora que está usted un
poco más tranquila, ¿por qué no me lo cuenta? ¿Por qué está llevando usted sola tan pesada
carga?... porque yo creo que ni siquiera Tona tiene la menor noticia de ella...

--¡Hija de mi alma!... La lengua me partiera en dos con los mesmus dientes mius si la viera
en tentaciones de parláselu... ¡igual que al probe señor y mi amu! ¡Santa Virgen de las Nieves!...
Y, por caridá de Dios, no me pregunte más de esu por ahora... ni nunca jamás, señor don Marcelu;
que yo, por la cuenta que me trae, buscaré el amparu de usté cuando la carga me rinda y las
angustias me ajueguen... porque la peste ha de golver, y sin mucha tardanza, señor don Marcelu.
¡Ay, desdichada de mí!... ¡Y el amu... y Tona!... ¡Santa Virgen la mi Madre!

Púsose lívida de repente, se le pintaron en la cara las angustias de otros días, y llevó hasta
ella sus manos cruzadas y convulsas. Me movió a compasión la pobre mujer, y sentí remordimientos
de haber sido yo el causante de aquella crisis amarga. Tomé con empeño el trabajo de calmarla,
y lo conseguí; pero con la ayuda de una «zurriascada» feroz que se estrelló de repente contra
las puertas del balcón. Cuando esto ocurría, se enjugaba Facia los ojos y respondía malamente
a mis últimas observaciones. Al oír el estrépito de afuera, suspendió hasta las lágrimas y
se lanzó a uno de los cuarterones abiertos, y allí se estuvo mirando, con la avidez de un sediento,
aquella mar de lluvia cernida, revuelta y zarandeada en el espacio por la furia del vendaval.

--¡Oh!--exclamó al fin, retirándose de su observatorio con la cara radiante de alegría y andando
presurosa hacia la puerta de salida--, por misericordia de Dios, hay pa ratu.

¿No era bien singular y extraño todo aquello?

Entre tanto, yo no cesaba de meditar sobre el grave tema, y punto de suma trascendencia para
mí, surgido aquella misma mañana de la conversación que tuve con mi tío; y cuanto más vueltas
le daba en mi cabeza, más obligado me creía, hasta por obra de caridad, a ofrecerle lo único
que honradamente le podía ofrecer yo. Si con este ofrecimiento se curaba de sus angustias mortales,
¿qué mayor satisfacción para mí? Si andando el tiempo resultaba que no llegaban mis fuerzas
tan allá como mis buenos propósitos, ¿qué culpa tendría yo de ello?

No vacilé más: busqué a mi tío, le hallé en su cuarto cerca de un brasero, hojeando unos papeles,
tosiendo mucho y moviéndose mal debajo de la espesa ropa que le abrumaba, a la tétrica luz
de la media tarde y al ruido ingrato de las celliscas y de los truenos que no cesaban afuera.

XVIII

Me anuncié preguntándole desde la puerta si podía hablar con él cuatro palabras sin molestarle.

Volvió hacia mí la cara con la viveza ratonil que le era propia, y me contestó, enderezando
cuanto pudo el cuerpecillo descarnado:

--¡Mira, hombre, qué casualidad!... Apuradamente estaba yo pensando en ir enseguida a preguntarte
lo mismo para cumplirte después la promesa que te hice esta mañana por remate de nuestra conversación.

--Pues a cumplir otra promesa--añadí--, que no pude hacerle a usted entonces por falta de oportunidad,
pero que quedó hecha en mis adentros, vengo yo ahora.

--Ya estás sentándote y hablando--me dijo a esto, arrojando sobre la cómoda los papeles que
hojeaba, sentándose después en una silla junto a la caja del brasero e indicándome que hiciera
yo lo propio en otra que estaba enfrente de ella.

--En lo de sentarme--le dije, haciéndolo--, le obedezco a usted desde luego; pero en lo de
hablar... no tanto.

--¡Esta es buena, trastajo! ¿Por qué, hombre?

--Porque quiero darle a usted la preferencia, como debo, en lo que mutuamente tenemos que decirnos,
según parece.

--Vaya, vaya, déjate de cumplimientos, y empecemos por el caso tuyo, que para el mío siempre
hay lugar. Conque ¿qué es lo que se te ocurre, hijo mío?

--Pues lo que se me ocurre--dije yo comenzando a tocar las dificultades de acometer de frente
un asunto de tan delicada naturaleza como aquél, cuyo punto de partida era nada menos que la
muerte de mi venerable interlocutor--, se me ocurre, mi querido tío, algo que se relaciona
con otro algo que le oí a usted esta mañana y me produjo muy honda y muy amarga impresión...

--A ver, a ver--interrumpió el pobre hombre acercando más su silla a la mía, mientras se pintaba
en sus ojuelos chispeantes la curiosidad que le devoraba.

--No crea usted que se trata de una cosa del otro jueves--añadí sonriéndome.

--Sea del otro jueves o del otro sábado, ¡venga esa cosa por derecho y sin envoltorios, hombre!--me
respondió con un brío inconcebible en su extenuación cadavérica.

--Corriente--le dije yo, no sabiendo cómo armonizar mis escrúpulos con sus impaciencias--;
pero después de declarar, para la debida inteligencia, que yo tomo el caso en el punto mismo
en que usted le puso y le dejó esta mañana.

--Declarado y entendido... ¡Adelante ahora!

--Me dijo usted entonces, metido en la injustificada aprensión de que iba a morirse pronto...
y Dios no lo confirme.

--Ésa es cuenta de Él y mía... ¡Adelante, Marcelo!

--Me dijo usted, repito, confesándome además que esa... aprensión...

--Aprensión, ¿eh?

--Que esa... cavilación, si lo prefiere así, era la que le estaba matando; que a usted no le
espantaba la muerte, sino el morirse, el cesar de vivir, el irse del mundo para siempre, porque
hace mucha falta en él y no deja quien le reemplace en su labor de toda la vida. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01115</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>242402</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20981</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The horror of that night, newcomer I to Tablanca
had happened two like that, but as he fled from me as I approached purposes it strange questioning
about particular, after asking me to hands together and the love of God that my uncle told
a word of what was noting, limitábame, to please her, to watch from afar and while not losing
sight I could. What the hell could there be? Were ghosts, hallucinations, hysterical the poor woman
so punished by misfortune to the best of your life, or was under the weight unbearable for
some new misfortune? Neluco Celis, still looks the same as me thought when he first spoke: discreet,
friendly, and noble understanding of very clear heart and a closed ark to save me what seemed
to me that should be available My view: verbigracia, their inclination loving granddaughter of
Don Pedro Nolasco. Because I Lita could not conceive and Neluco not loved, and neither conceived
nor garrulous midwife of Robacio, nor anyone with guts conceive of humanity and glimpses of
good taste and repair a bit at that couple, "single", which seemed to put God in that corner land
for that alone, to love and to join. Lita and her mother had been twice in my house after I was
in hers. One of them, as I said, to pay me welcome the visit and, incidentally, my uncle and the
other only by my uncle, whose health they were interested much, besides that, how could you leave
home, they would make a bit of company as whenever the weather permitted and occupations. All
this I said discovering Lituca the rows of glazed white teeth, in vehement language, frisky and admiring
astragalus to the door and as he pulled his feet, shod in sneakers petite coat on colored stockings,
a pair of clogs that looked like two nutshells. At that visit, as in the above, I, stubborn and dogged
in my theme, I took fifty times the field of conversation disguised in a thousand ways, with the
pious to observe which side Lita made him ... and nothing, not a frown, or a point on her cheeks
flushed, nor the most insignificant signal the granddaughter of Don Pedro Nolasco had heard
his heart calls me to made with the name of Neluco and praise of its merits: he spoke of him with
neglect and the serenity with which he could speak to his mother or his grandfather. That made
me impatient to me as if it were a matter of my own membership, and more than one occasion, I undertook
serious tempted to ask the right questions and unambiguous and clearly: "do you want or not
want you? Do you love or not love Neluco?. " But sir, why was I so hard that to love? Or rather,
why it was so great you got that point right away well understood and demarcated?

Then my Uncle Celso, the soul and center of everything around him, with his indomitable energy,
their jokes most singular, his attention always fixed on me how, since no fun life bearable
at home and care for forcing me kinship and gratitude to ensure it with special care during
the time of damp and very cold, in which, according to medical opinion,
his life was in greater danger, by the nature of her illness.

And finally, its gatherings and my books, my papers and my correspondence. The remaining both
lots, some of it for its insignificance, and partly because of distance, could only be as decorative
characters and scenery.

True that all these reservations so little relevance to the needs My spirit could reach epic,
considered as elements of creation the fantasy of a witty writer, but they were taken and worth, as
cases and things real life and prosaic in half so remote, so dark
and so isolated like that, what I had to promise them for later?

What are my enemy against formidable auxiliary could expect from that side? What could come from
there of what I was most needed?

- Who knows - I said in conclusion of my musings -. For light in the darkest points other times,
if God has something coming, it will come. It's all about patience and learn to comply. So
a bit of philosophy, and await what may come.

XVII

And he began to come before long, but alas! what came was, first,
a gray mist that came down from the mountains, wrapped around the
village and slipped up at home, after that fog came a "gallego" cool
with another brown fog, which was mixed with the first, sooty their
color and making it more moist and sticky, was also a continuous rumble,
like distant gunfire, which seemed to me the raging sea beating the
rocks north the coast, but as the opinion of the people in my house,
it was the "Rebombo" of the "Peña Pozón Sagra ", a large lake or well,
that is for existing, I do not know of anyone who has seen, in the
bowels of this giant of the Andes, and this noise constantly bronco,
dejáronse heard in the area and the valley as a sinister and nasty
moans, which were, according to Chisco reports, the cawing of the
"Boutros"

(vultures) and cranes, which spend "cararriba '; this signal, as the "Rebombo" the well and
the low fog with the "Galician" behind that we are pouncing on a wintering of fat.

And the prophecies were fulfilled: the clouds became dark clouds swollen with rain, the wind,
raging slowly crashed with frightful bellowing, into homes, slopes and Bardales, closing gaps
and horizons everywhere you looked, felt the most ardent of blood the first shivers of cold,
and we declare all in the house seriously and formally blocked by winter.

The first consequences of this blockade were in it, as it was easy to be presumed, the reduction
of half a dozen small gathering of brave, including Salces Pito, who no saves in the impulses of
the fondness that attracted him, and the fiercest winds and (What was for me far more unpleasant
and unexpected so soon) a crisis of gender wrong in the state of
my uncle.

As commissioned by the doctor forbade him to poke their noses the paneled open a window, was consumed
with impatience in darkened moors of his prison, and when night came, and after praying the
rosary in the kitchen, looked into it scattered, unmanned, shivering with cold and water drafts
of a few commentators those of that tight phalanx of the first night, and I noticed the cause
of desertion of others in the furious beating of the sleet against
doors and windows and gun fireplace, stayed thoughtful and gloomy,
with the humbled neck and staring at the flame the fire, whose heat
instinctively sought.

And so one day and another and another, without that toughness of its fiber reach to disguise
even the disappointments of his mind, reached a degree such abatement, which alarmed me, because
in a moral status as yours, any gives flight of his illness was very scary.

Talking with him one morning in those days so raw, and just the two in the kitchen, which was
his whereabouts regular time, I encouraged him as he could and he knows the weak quality my stimulants,
finally say:

- Do not get tired, Marcelo: This ujano that eats me is stronger than you and I together, by
large who are your care and hard it has been my belt. Look, man, not yet one year jaz I was
so hard for me to fall as the beeches of those mountains. Piece of junk with Vanida of human handsomeness!
Maybe the thought that only a glimmer of the will of God could mayor in the soil, a breath that
light extinguished, put me to death's door when least expected and most neglected sleep. Since
then here, pispajo!, I never nothing I am astonished by anything I shrugged, and looked suspiciously
refer to the ground where I put my feet, because they always and
at all times and everywhere I am afraid the last remaining to beat
the falling oak finish.

This is the truth, gravel!, And to think you signed up some of it in one of the letters that
I wrote. But then those were the days longer and the nights are shorter, the sun shone and
warmed the earth's blood old, and, above all, returning from his
trip early, much to scare up early ideas sad heads that charity comes
just sleep at night.

So I Jallas happy ever to have seen me coming and get along well until yesterday, as they say
... to came what I had seen it coming sometimes not rush for it, and do not know if I tell you
that taste ... Tasteful piece of junk! because when you have good health, the earth has no
sauce if we are always singing the same solfa ... and no change of clothes ... I say that I was
pulling so what until he reached the first cellerisca, it is still going on, while waiting,
by signs, yet another tough one to her, and went out the sun by day, and closed doors and windows
and night began to miss the people in the kitchen, and no end to the hours of bed or point of
rest for evil to think of the head. I had never seen it happen the blackness for her go now. To
this day and since I have use of reason, always the interests of other Jizo me forget my own,
for now and I love a story pispajo! ... and this is what me and hastily: I have eyes only to see
how it goes woodworm rejundiendo and ajondando in this rotten log that falls with himself day
by day, hour hour. Paez to the wind, Rebombo in the chimney, I said something I never I had heard
before, but something very afraid and very sad ... come on, it's good ajuyera win, if I temporarily
shut off all avenues of escape, and the cold chained me oars and I cut the little breath left
in my gullet ... Another thing never view: I can swear I'm not afraid of death because I am
old and I know Christian has come before long and I have to wait for trusting in the mercy of
God as I hope, and with it and yet the disease that scares me is me taking life. How explains this
soup? How about you that is it, Marcelo?

Faltábanme to me the scientific fallacies that Neluco, for example, could clarify apparently those
complex darkness that I consulted my poor uncle, and dispatched the consultation with four
heavily underlined and encourages vague about the influence they exert on thoughts machine the
long sleepless nights, the solitude of the night, the seasonal cold ...

- Well may be some blame those ingredients - "my uncle me with very little sign to believe - but
sometimes it seems to me to me that there are other reasons for using ... and be fed, piece
of junk!, that come from that band all the rot. Look, man ... (Because put into question the point,
should be ventilated in order, and I have seen many faces in so many nights of not thinking about anything
else) if I would live no more than one of the children that God was giving me the death of
his father's death would not be proper, because in cases like this, and you well know, the life
of the sprouts to be on those who stay for more than weep and pray for them: a link locked
in another link ... go, a chain that never breaks or ends. But as things have turned out here
and put I consider that I am within an inch of dying ... Ay, Marcelo,
what makes my paintings before your eyes!

With the last gasp, the string broken forever home without fire, empty barns, the house in silence
and (even worse, if not the key metisteis between the four tables that were to rot my bones
to the cemetery) in the hands of men you will not see in it only the rusty farthing to be paid
by the right to abuse.

Well lie down to think after all these people who live by their heat because they all are, same
as were their parents and their children should be, as our blood blood and flesh of our own
body, looking askance at the beginning to end for not remembering leave it and spreading, as POLLUCE
without mother, stolen at last, one by one the kite that never sleeps ... Oh, piece of junk! This
is very painful, even to dream into a nightmare ... What is not my son, seen and felt in the
same reality? Believe me, Marcelo: matter much more than the life of your uncle, what is to go
with her to another world, if God does not intervene ... Do not you think to yourself that it
could be the "consistidura" of the strange things that I removed both sleep and I cringe lately?

Knowing
as I knew the strength of character and feelings of my uncle, was evident who was right in that
assumption, and certainly it was he even appeared otherwise, but I could not so state, he
declared, or expressed to me descariñado eyes and harsh, or accept a compromise that could not accept,
because it was another very different from yours I see those things. I would have been easy
to deceive venturing a promise that he was walking perhaps looking for from the first letter
to me, but I hated the lie that a man so honest and so smart like that, also states that I do
not believe her. So I took a bland temper that neither reached to lift his shot encouragement,
even in disguise that I got trouble with your question.

- All this - said the good man, trying to make small talk pinito that did not come out well
- that is to say. Marcelo, and since we take the conversation to that side ... Well would have to
see, pispajo!, which I now give the grace of burden you with grief new when you most need to
do something cheerful to chase the darkness of this time is caught up with us! Look, man, Creasman
or not believe me: the only remaining guts than me ... come on, the only thing that I feel
when this game is to help you not Amurrio alegraderas you also.

"Oístelo? For good. Something more and more important I have to say, and I'll tell you in time
and place concerned, and before long. This should be now and in case, days ago, but ... Enough
talk, and do not scare the threat, but the point is a close relative of the treaty here, has
no face so ugly. If the two were equal I would get rid a lot of letting you know that you have
not seen yet.

Tona came into the kitchen, something touched also on the wintry blues, a bustle at the stove
where my uncle and I talked about the warmth of the fire, and I could not ask him what he had to
the tip of the tongue, even as exploration around this new breed
of 'point' I had a great curiosity.

But more than curious to clarify, I was worried and sad about the painting by Don Celso state of
his mind. To reach such extreme frankness of a man temple, what would be the weight of his
trouble? And what the extent of my disgust and my worth considering that I had the choice of the
largest of theirs, and yet, I refused to be offered? Was honored this conduct mine? "I was forced
to compromise impossible to fulfill? Was well demonstrated this impossibility? "It was to
be, in doubt, resort promising, subject to where you could meet? ...

Putting the issue in recent terms and seemed more rational and tolerable, and if we had continued
the two alone in the kitchen, you may have tried spot I enter this loophole the first support
for their faintness.

But Tona had time task (as they are walking in the vicinity of noon), and if this was little hindrance,
came to lead the task Facia. Strange!

The gray woman was the only one of which we inhabited the house, in whom there was a bump
pattern the scourge of the storm which prevailed. Even the walking Chisco espelurciado and
shrunk somewhat through the stables and corrals, and went into the kitchen sometimes with sour
mood, the Facia setback, which, since they had triggered the first celleriscas seemed another.
The more the hail lashed the walls of the house, and more "Runfla" gales in the chimney, put it more
cheerful and more diligent face turned to the work.

Seeing so buoyant and so advantageous provisions, I struck up a conversation with her that
same day, to take not know what junk to my room.

- It seems - I said it to begin - that matters are going well, eh?

Entendióme the question, and after a bit overwhelm her, she replied without hesitation:

- It's kept me God Muchu tiempu.

- I'm glad in my soul - I said it then - it, because it does not see you with the horror of these
days ...

- Not lying to me, sir, Carida work! - I replied back to compunction -. Paez that the evils, as
if heard, stand up as soon as they mint on the palate ...

- At any
rate, it's business you go in reverse time.

- Why do diz, cristianu?

-
Because while he is raging and dogged, they are improving.

- God
always is good Jechu jaz ... Ah, if this lasts Muchu!

...

- Is the time?

- And otru.

- What is that?

- The states with what YOU WANT to know.

- And without actually achieve
more by token ... Let's see, Facia: Now that you're a little quieter,
why do not you tell me?

Why are you being so heavy single load?

... because I think even Tona has any news of her ...

- Daughter of my soul ... My tongue split in two with mesmus Mius
if I saw her teeth temptations of parláselu ... The probe as my lord
and amu!

Santa Virgen de las Nieves!

... And Carida of God, do not ask me over for now ... esu and will
never, Don Marcelu; I, for the account that brings me, Nah, you look
for the amparu of when load and render me ajueguen troubles me ...
because the plague has golves, and without much delay, Don Marcelu.

Oh, miserable me! ... And the amu ... and Tona! ... My Mother the Blessed Virgin!

Stood suddenly pale, he painted in the face the anxieties of other
days, and led to her hands crossed and convulsed.

I moved to pity the poor woman, and felt remorse I have been the cause of that crisis, bitter.
Took hard work to calm, and I got it, but with the help of a "zurriascada" fierce suddenly crashed
against balcony doors. When this happened, he wiped his eyes and responded Facia badly to my last
comment. Hearing the noise outside, and stopped to tears launched into one of the open paneled,
and there was watching, with the eagerness of a thirsty that sea of ??rain sifted, stirred and
tossed into space by the fury of the gale.

- Oh! - He cried at length, retiring from his observatory with beaming face and walking hurried toward
the exit door - by God's mercy, there Ratu pa.

"It was very singular and strange all this?

Meanwhile, I never stopped to reflect on the serious subject and point of paramount importance for me,
born that very morning of the conversation I had with my uncle, and
the more laps I was in my head, I felt more bound up by charity, to
offer all who honestly could offer me.

If this offer is healed of his mortal anguish, What greater satisfaction for me? If the passage
of time was not my strength came so there like my good intentions,
what would I blame it?

I did not hesitate more, I looked for my uncle found him in his room near a brazier, browsing
some papers bad cough a lot and moving under the thick clothing that overwhelmed him at the
gloomy light mid-afternoon and unpleasant noise of sleet and thunder did not stop outside.

XVIII

I announced at the door asking if he could speak four words without disturbing you.

Face turned to me with the vividness that it was very mousy, and he
said, straightening the scrawny little body as he could:

- Look,
man, what a coincidence!

... I was busily thinking of going soon to ask the same for cumplirte
then I promise you this morning by finishing our conversation.

-
Well, to fulfill another promise - I added - I could not ask you then
for lack of opportunity, but that was made in myself, I come now.

-
You're sitting and talking - I told this comfortable throwing on the
roles browsing, then sat in a chair beside the hearth box and telling
me to do I own into one that was in front of her.

- As I sat down
- I said, making it - you will obey of course, but as of talk ...
not so much.

- This is good piece of junk!

Why, man?

- Because I want to give you the preference, as I must, as each have to say, it seems.

- Well, well, let's compliments, and start with the case of yours, which for me always there is room. So
what is it that you think, my son?

- For what it occurs to me - I said I began playing tackle difficulties facing so delicate a matter
of nature like this, whose starting point was nothing less than death
of my venerable partner - it occurs to me, my dear uncle, something
that relates another thing that I heard you this morning and I was
very deep and very bitter impression ...

- So, to see - the poor
man interrupted her chair closer to mine, while painting the bright
eyes, the curiosity which devoured.

- Do not think that it is a thing
of another Friday - added smiling.

- Let the other Thursday or next
Saturday, come the right thing and without wrappers, man! - Me responded
with a vigor mortis inconceivable in its exhaustion.

- Current -
I said, not knowing how to reconcile my qualms with his impatience
-; but after declaring for the proper intelligence, I took the case
at the very point when you put him and left him this morning.

- Declared
and understood ... Go now!

- I told you then, stuck in the unjustified
fear that he would die soon ... and God does not confirm it.

- That
's account of him and me ... Next, Marcelo!

- I told you, I repeat,
also confessed that ... apprehension ...

- Apprehension, eh?

- That
this ... cavil, if you prefer so, was what was killing him, that you
do not frightened of death, but dying, ceasing to live, leaving the
world forever, because badly need it and who does not leave his place
in your work life.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>