<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document06247</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>7639</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22078</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Hace no mucho tiempo
bajaron de su pueblo a pedirme «algo», a tales horas y en tales términos, que tuve que darles
el «Dios vos ampare» con la escopeta echada a la cara. Primera y única vez que los he visto.

»Pues bueno, y para fin y remate del camino que traigo y ya me cansa: creo que si tú te animaras
y me dieras el regalo de tu compañía en esta casona, el vocear de la tierra me sería más llevadero.
No hay cosa mayor con qué tentarte entre estos solitarios despeñaderos, a ti que estás avezado
a las pompas y regalos de la corte; pero a todo se hacen los hombres cuando se empeñan en ello,
sin contar con que también aquí hay su sol correspondiente; y aunque es cierto que tarda un
poco por la mañana en trasponer los picachos que rodean el lugar, una vez arriba alumbra y
calienta y regocija el ánimo como el sol más majo de cualquiera parte. Además, tu destierro
no podría durar mucho por razones que yo me sé; y por último y finiquito, con salir de él en
cuanto no pudieras resistirle, estaba el cuento acabado para ti.

»Ítem más: tengo ciertos planes en el magín, que me dan mucho que hacer. ¿Qué hombre anda sin
ellos en mi caso? No tengo herederos forzosos, y no deja de haber en casa algo que echar a
perder de mi propia pertenencia; algo que irá a parar Dios sabe adónde, si en mis últimas y
postreras no topo al alcance de la vista con un ser que me haga un poco de cosquilleo en las
entretelas del corazón.

»Por supuesto, que no trato de encender tu codicia con estas indirectas. ¡A buena parte iría!
Pero es bien que todo se estipule y se tenga presente en horas como las que han empezado a
correr para mí.

»En fin, hombre, anímate a venir por acá; y si no puedes hacerlo por gusto, hazlo por caridad
de Dios.»

Menos lo del «bajón» y sus consecuencias, todo lo que mi tío me contaba en esta carta me lo
tenía yo bien sabido; y sabía también, por lo que se deducía fácilmente de su anterior y escasa
correspondencia con nosotros y lo poco que me había dicho mi padre, que su hermano Celso era
un hombre campechano, de escasas letras y excelente corazón, agudo de magín y un tanto marrullero,
como buen montañés, y más cuidadoso del cultivo y prosperidad de sus tierras y ganados, que
del fomento de su cariño a la familia que le quedaba; dejadez que a ratos tocaba en una indiferencia
que parecía rayana del absoluto olvido. Menos que de mi tío sabía yo de su tierra nativa y
de nuestra casa solar, no tanto por culpa de mi poca curiosidad sobre estos particulares, como
por obra de una de las flaquezas más salientes de mi padre. Le llamaban más la atención los
apellidos que las condiciones personales de «los nuestros»: así es que al preguntarle por la
vida y milagros de cualquiera de ellos, en lugar de responder derechamente a la pregunta, se
encaramaba en la copa del árbol genealógico de la familia, y gateando de rama en rama hacia
abajo, no paraba hasta dar, lo que menos, con la pata del Cid, si es que se conformaba con
eso. De sus padres sólo pude sacar en limpio, en las diferentes veces que le pedí noticias
sobre ellos, que habían sido el entronque de la casa «única» de los Ruiz de Bejos, de Tablanca,
con la de los Gómez de Pomar, la más ilustre de las de Promisiones. Pocos caudales, eso sí,
por parte de estos últimos principalmente, es decir, por la de mi abuela paterna, que sólo
aportó al matrimonio unas gargantillas y unas arracadas de coral, dos relicarios de plata con
una astilla de la Vera-Cruz, y un hueso de Santa Felícitas, respectivamente; tres mudas de
ropa blanca, dos mantelerías de hilo casero, una cadena de oro cordobés, el vestido de gala
con que se casó, y otro a medio uso para todos los días. Por parte de mi abuelo ya fue cosa
muy diferente. Nuestra casa de Tablanca ejercía en todo el valle, por virtud de su condición
benéfica amén de ilustre, cierto señorío indiscutible y patriarcal, y era el paradero obligado
de todas las personas notables que pasaban por allí, incluso los obispos. Solamente en lo que
recordaba mi padre, se habían hospedado dos en ella: el de Santander y el de León. Para estos
y otros parecidos menesteres había en arcas y alacenas buena provisión de sábanas y mantelerías
superiores, maciza y abundante plata de mesa y hasta dos colchas de damasco y un crucifijo
de marfil y ébano. Nada faltaba allí de lo que no debía de faltar en la casa de una familia
como la nuestra. Pero de su situación, de su forma, de su amplitud, de sus comodidades, ni
una palabra: a lo sumo, que era grande, con solanas, escudo nobiliario y accesorias. Del terreno
en que estaba enclavada y sus aledaños, de las condiciones y aspecto del paisaje, de su clima,
de sus recursos para la vida algo más que animal, de las costumbres de sus habitadores, era
ocioso inquirir cosa alguna por informes de aquel buen señor, que con estar tan pagado de su
estirpe y poner en los cuernos de la luna los blasones de su casa y la tierra en que había
nacido, sólo una vez y muy de prisa volvió a ella después de haberla abandonado, aunque por
imperio de la necesidad, siendo muchacho todavía. Se remontaba a lo más alto de cuanto había
oído y leído sobre aquella empingorotada región de la cordillera cantábrica, y era de ver cómo
se las había, primeramente, con los celtas, nuestros supuestos progenitores, y se descolgaba
enseguida de allí para enzarzarse mano a mano y como quien ventila y justiprecia ordinarios
y corrientes asuntos de familia, con aquellas tribus montaraces, con aquel cántabro feroz que
pasó los Alpes y luchó con Aníbal contra Roma y derrotó a Escipión en el Tesino. Después hablaba
de Augusto y sus legiones, venidos a Cantabria expresamente para someternos al yugo romano;
de que tal era nuestro empuje, tal «nuestro» valor y tal «nuestro» apego a la independencia,
que el César había necesitado seis años para triunfar en un empeño que le había parecido obra
de pocos días; de los horrores de esta guerra bárbara entre inaccesibles peñascales y profundos
y sombríos barrancos, donde rugían las aguas tintas en la sangre de «los nuestros» y de los
aguerridos legionarios. No faltaba lo de las madres que durante la guerra mataban a sus pequeñuelos
para no verlos esclavos de los triunfadores extranjeros, ni lo de la muerte en cruz de tantos
mártires entonando himnos de libertad entre maldiciones al conquistador, y con todo esto, un
sinnúmero de pormenores sobre el tipo y las costumbres de sus héroes, pormenores que yo hubiera
querido sobre la tierra que habitaron, tal y como era en mis días. Lejos de ello, sólo dejaba
los cántabros para mezclar a sus sucesores en la epopeya de Covadonga o en los líos de los
«Bandos» de Castilla; y ya puesto aquí con los ditirambos a sus ínclitos «antepasados», recorría
con ellos las cinco partes del mundo, hasta no saber por dónde se andaba, ni yo tampoco. Porque
sobre estas materias tenía mi padre una erudición abundante, pero un tanto sospechosa, obra
de una voracidad que entraba con lo cierto lo mismo que con lo fantástico, por apego tenaz,
aunque meramente platónico, a las cosas de su tierra.

De esta manera sabía yo de ella, al recibir la carta de mi tío, poco más de lo que se sabe,
por conjeturas o por comparación, de otras semejantes que se han visto «al pasar», y muy de prisa.

Entre tanto, yo había cumplido ya los treinta y dos años; hacía seis que era doctor en ambos
derechos, aunque sin saber, por desuso de ellas, para qué servían esas cosas; más de siete
que campaba por mis respetos, y me daba la gran vida con el caudal que había heredado de mi
padre. Porque de mi madre no heredé un maravedí. Fue una granadina muy guapa, hija de un magistrado
de aquella Audiencia territorial. La conoció mi padre andando por allá una temporada, ocupado
en negocios de minas, y se casó con ella de la noche a la mañana. El magistrado era viudo y
pobre, y se murió dos años después de la boda de su hija.

Debo a Dios, entre otras muchas mercedes, la de un temperamento singularmente equilibrado de
humores, que me ha permitido atravesar por las más peligrosas asperezas de la vida, sin dejar
entre ellas la menor tira del pellejo. Muy pocas cosas me han llegado al alma, y rara vez me
he apasionado por la mejor de ellas. Esta ha sido mi mayor fortuna en medio de la libertad
y de la abundancia en que viví, siendo niño mimado y consentido, mientras fui «hijo de familia»,
y rico y desligado de toda traba en cuanto quedé huérfano de padre y madre y me declaré «mozo
de casa abierta». En estas condiciones y con un temperamento más apasionado, sabe Dios lo que
hubiera sido de mí y de mi dinero. Así y todo, no acrecenté el heredado de mi padre, y hasta
le mermé en una buena tajada, porque no todos los tiempos corrían iguales para el vil ochavo;
y yo, aunque sin perder de vista lo útil que es este ingrediente para vivir a gusto entre los
hombres, no había nacido para esclavo de él y tenía muy arraigadas aficiones que no eran baratas.
Me gustaba viajar, y viajaba mucho dentro y fuera de España; me gustaba el llamado «gran mundo»
o «alta sociedad», y la frecuentaba en sus salones, en los teatros, en los paseos y hasta en
los balnearios de moda, y en el deporte; me gustaban las Bellas Artes, aunque consideradas
principalmente como artículo de lujo, y compraba cuadros y esculturas en las exposiciones;
me gustaban ciertos hombres de la política y de la literatura, no por políticos ni por literatos
precisamente, sino por la resonancia de sus nombres y el atractivo de sus conversaciones, y
frecuentaba su trato y los acompañaba en sus círculos y en sus banquetes y en sus tertulias
y francachelas... hasta me gustaban los toreros a cierta distancia, y a cierta distancia cultivaba
la amistad de algunos de ellos.

Todo esto, y otro tanto más que de ello se sigue por ley forzosa, al fin y a la postre resultaba
caro y producía hondos desgastes, si no del pellejo, cuando menos de la sensibilidad moral,
aun tratándose de un mozo como yo, que en ningún cuadro aspiró a ser figura de primer término,
ni a levantar media pulgada sobre la talla común de la masa de espectadores; y esto, no por
virtud, sino por exigencias de mi temperamento.

Es muy de notarse que en la afición más acentuada de todas las mías, la de los viajes, me seducía
mucho más el artificio de los hombres que la obra de la Naturaleza. Como buen madrileño, amaba
a Madrid sobre todas las cosas de la tierra, y después de Madrid, a sus similares de España
y del extranjero: las más grandes y más alegres capitales del mundo civilizado. Lo que quedaba
entre unas y otras, me tenía sin cuidado, y pasaba sobre ello, para ir adonde fuera, como insensible
proyectil que lleva el paradero determinado desde su punto de origen. Hijo y habitante de tierra
llana, los montes me entristecían y los cielos borrosos me acoquinaban. Una vez sola había
estado en la capital montañesa, disfrazando con el deseo de pisar «la tierra de mis mayores»,
como diría mi padre, la tentación de veranear en aquel puerto que comenzaba a ser «elegante».
Atravesando en ferrocarril la cordillera cantábrica casi por encima de las fuentes del Ebro,
recordé que «por allí», no sabía si a la derecha o a la izquierda, debía de andar mi casa solariega,
en algún repliegue de aquellos montes encapuchados de neblinas y ceñidos de negros robledales.
Y no tuvo entonces mayor resonancia que ésta en mi corazón el tan cacareado «grito de la sangre».
Días después, y desde una de las alturas que dominan la ciudad, un santanderino, práctico en
ello, me nombraba, señalándolos con el dedo, cada picacho y cada monte de la grandiosa cordillera
que empieza al Oriente en Cabo Quintres y Galizano (la cola del enorme reptil), y acaba al
Occidente metiendo entre las nubes los Picos de Europa (su cabeza).

Después, al trazar en el aire con el mismo dedo el curso de cada río de los que en ella nacen
y por el fondo de sus negras barrancas se despeñan, llegó a encararse al Oeste; y marcando
tres rayas casi verticales, me nombró el Saja, el Nansa y el Deva; y allí le atajé yo con el
pensamiento, diciéndome a mí propio: «Junto a uno de esos tres ríos (creo que el Nansa), más
arriba o más abajo, debe de andar el solar de mis mayores.» Y a esto solo se redujo, por segunda
vez, «el grito de la sangre» que llevaba en las venas. Como decoración, me enamoraba aquel
rosario de escalonadas montañas que de Este a Oeste por el Sur sirven de marco grandioso a
la admirable bahía; ¡pero como tierras habitables!...

Tales eran, pico más, pico menos, mis antecedentes personales cuando recibí la carta en que
mi tío Celso me llamaba a su lado, y por tiempo indefinido, desde lo más recóndito y montaraz
de la región cantábrica; y, sin embargo, no me causó la embajada impresión tan desagradable
como pudiera presumirse tomando al pie de la letra lo dicho sobre mi modo de ser y de sentir.

Aparte de lo que me interesó el estado físico y moral de mi tío, no estaba yo tan enamorado
de mi sistema de vida, que me espantaran los riesgos de trastornarle radicalmente por algún
tiempo. Sin sentirme «cansado» de vivir como vivía, porque no cabía el cansancio en un andar
tan reposado y, relativamente, metódico como el que había usado yo hasta llegar adonde había
llegado por tantos y tan peligrosos caminos, comenzaba a notar a la sazón cierta languidez
de espíritu, cierta inapetencia moral que no estaban reñidas seguramente con un paréntesis
de reposo, y mucho menos con un cambio de impresiones y de «alimentos». Por este lado, la carta
de mi tío no podía llegar más a tiempo de lo que llegó a mis manos. Lo grave, lo inesperado,
lo terrible para mí estaba por otro lado: la calidad de lo que se me pedía en ella. Resuelto
a cambiar de vida por algún tiempo, Dios sabe qué derroteros hubiera adoptado yo; pero es indudable
para mí que jamás habría elegido el que mi tío deseaba y me proponía. Llegarme allá para hacerle
una visita; pasar por allí de largo, siquiera por conocer de vista el solar de mis abuelos,
menos mal; pero establecerme en él; hacer la vida de las fieras entre riscos y breñales; aclimatarme
a ella de repente en la estación que corría (más que mediado el otoño), la antesala del invierno,
¡qué tendría que ver en Tablanca! recién llegado yo de Aguas-Buenas y de París y de medio mundo
«distinguido», con las maletas atestadas de «novedades», lo mismo en ropas que en libros; reinstalado
en mi «confortable» casita de soltero... Vamos, era el colmo de lo imposible soñar siquiera
en trocar todo eso y de repente por lo que se me ofrecía desde Tablanca.

Pero yo no podía decir a mi tío estas cosas que le hubieran lastimado mucho en la situación
de ánimo en que se hallaba; y le entretenía despachando sus apremiantes instancias con evasivas
corteses, pretextando negocios que no tenía, y apuntando «veremos» sin el menor propósito de
cumplirlos.

Ente tanto, la visión, a mi modo, de la casa de Tablanca, con sus montes y sus fieras y sus
gentes y su desolación inverniza, no se apartaba un instante de mis ojos, porque las súplicas
de mi tío, cada vez más vivas, llegaron a tocarme muy adentro; y por lo que pudiera suceder,
sentía la necesidad de poner el caso en tela de juicio, que vale tanto, según las reglas de
la experiencia, como empezar a transigir.

Lo cierto es que un día, el en que recibí la anteúltima carta de mi tío, que me comovió muy
hondamente, di en el tema de buscar dentro de mí el porqué de ser yo tan poco sensible a los
convenidos encantos de la Naturaleza. ¿Faltaba esa cuerda en mi organismo, o la tenía y no
la había puesto en ocasión de que vibrara? Pues había que averiguarlo, porque comenzaba a mortificarme
el temor de carecer de ella. Además, o es uno hombre, o no lo es; o tiene o no tiene entrañas
de humanidad, agallas para ir por donde vayan y hacer lo que hagan otros; o sirve o no sirve
para algo más útil y de mayor jugo y provecho que pisar alfombras de salones; engordar el riñón
a fondistas judíos, sastres y zapateros de moda; concurrir a los espectáculos; devorar distancias
embutidas en muelles jaulas de ferrocarril, y gastar, en fin, el tiempo y el dinero en futilidades
de mujerzuela presumida y casquivana.

Encarrilado el discurso en este sendero, llegué a sentir un vigor de espíritu, una virilidad
desconocida en mí; soliviantóse mi amor propio de mozo bien saneado de alma y cuerpo; y aprovechando
la fiebre, por temor de que, si era pasajera, se llevara consigo mi ardimiento al desaparecer,
escribí a mi tío diciéndole «allá voy» y hasta fijándole la fecha de mi salida de Madrid. Entre
tanto haría yo mis preparativos de viaje, y me contestaría él dándome las necesarias instrucciones
para llegar a su casa desde la última estación del ferrocarril.

Mientras anduve ocupado en hacer abundante provisión de ropas de abrigo, calzado recio, armas
ofensivas y defensivas, libros de Aimard, de Topffer y de cuantos, incluso Chateaubriand, han
escrito cosas amenas a propósito de montañas, de selvas y de salvajes, lo mismo que si proyectara
una excursión por el centro de un remoto continente inexplorado, puedo responder de que no
me faltó la fiebre. Menos seguridad tuve de ello cuando intenté «levantar» mi casa. Me parecía
que esto equivalía a quemar mis naves, o, por lo menos, a darme ya por consentido en que había
de ser muy larga mi permanencia entre los osos de Cantabria; y el temor de este riesgo me inclinó
a dejar esas cosas como estaban, sobrándome buenos amigos en Madrid que mirarían por ellas.
De todas suertes, nada más fácil que resolver lo contrario desde allá, si así lo pidieran las
circunstancias.

En fin, temiendo que por este resquicio de mis flaquezas se me fueran colando otros aires aún
más fríos y enervadores, cerré las puertas del discurso a toda reflexión contraria a lo convenido,
y Alea jacta est, me dije, como César, resuelto a pasar a todo trance mi correspondiente Rubicón.

II

Y acometí la empresa en la fecha convenida, un día de los últimos de octubre, frío y nebuloso
en las alturas de la romana «Juliobriga». En la clásica villa inmediata, termino de mi jornada
primera, y única posible en ferrocarril, hice un alto de media hora escasa: lo puramente indispensable
para desentumecer los miembros y confortar el estómago; porque no había tiempo que perder,
según dictamen del espolique que me aguardaba en aquel punto desde la víspera con dos caballejos
de la tierra, espelurciados y chaparretes, uno para conducirme a mí y otro para cargar con
mis equipajes.

Puestos en marcha todos, bien corrida ya la media mañana, delante el espolique llevando del
ramal la cabalgadura que apenas se veía debajo de la balumba de mis maletas y envoltorios,
sin salir del casco de la villa atravesamos por un puente viejo el Ebro recién nacido; y a
bien corto trecho de allí y después de bajar un breve recuesto, que era por aquel lado como
el suburbio de la población que dejábamos a la espalda, vímonos en campo libre, si libre puede
llamarse lo que está circuido de barreras. De las cumbres de las más elevadas se desprendían
jirones de la niebla que las envolvía, y remedaban húmedos vellones puestos a secar en las
puntas de las rocas y sobre la espesura de aquellas seculares y casi inaccesibles arboledas,
con el aire serrano que soplaba sin cesar, y tan fresco, que me obligaba a levantar hasta las
orejas el cuello de mi recio impermeable.

Siguiendo nuestro camino encarados al Oeste, llevábamos continuamente a la izquierda, aguas
arriba, el cauce del río, con sus frescas y verdes orillas y rozagantes bóvedas y doseles de
mimbreras, alisos y zarzamora, y topábamos de tarde en cuando con un pueblecillo que, aunque
no muy alegre de color, animaba un poco la monotonía del paisaje.

A la vera del último de los de esta serie de ellos, en el centro de un reducido anfiteatro
de cerros pelados en sus cimas, se veían surgir reborbollando los copiosos manantiales del
famoso río que, después de formar breve remanso como para orientarse en el terreno y adquirir
alientos entre los taludes de su propia cuna, escapa de allí, a todo correr, a escondidas de
la luz siempre que puede, como todo el que obra mal, para salir pronto de su tierra nativa,
llevar el beneficio de sus aguas a extraños campos y desconocidas gentes, y pagar al fin de
su desatentado curso el tributo de todo su caudal a quien no se le debe en buen derecho. Y
a fe que, o mis ojos me engañaron mucho, o sería obra bien fácil y barata atajar al fugitivo
a muy poca distancia de sus fuentes, y en castigo de su deslealtad, despeñarle monte abajo
sin darle punto de reposo hasta entregarle, macerado y en espumas, a las iras de su dueño y
natural señor, el anchuroso y fiero mar Cantábrico.

Debí pasar demasiado tiempo en meditar sobre éstas y otras puerilidades, y en paladear los
recuerdos que despertaba en mí la contemplación de aquellas cristalinas aguas que tanto han
dado que hacer a la Historia y a la fantasía de los poetas, porque el espolique, salvando todos
los respetos de costumbre en su ruda cortesía, me apuntó la conveniencia de que continuáramos
andando.

--Da grima--le dije obedeciéndole--, pensar en la conducta de este renegado montañés.

Tuve que descifrar la metáfora para que el espolique me entendiera lo que yo quería decirle;
y en cuanto me hubo entendido, me respondió:

--Déjeli, déjeli que se vaya en gracia y antes con antes aonde jaz más falta que aquí. Pa meter
buya y causar malis a lo mejor, ríus como ésti nos sobran por la banda de acá.

Explicóse a su vez el espolique para que yo le entendiera, y llegué a convencerme, con ejemplos
que me puso de ríos montañeses desbordados a lo mejor sin qué ni para qué, arrollando casas,
puentes y molinos en las alturas, y comiéndose en los valles las tierras que debieran de regar,
de que bien pudiera ser obra meritoria lo que me había parecido en el Ebro falta imperdonable.

Por cierto que no se explicaba mal ni dejaba de tener su lado interesante mi rudo interlocutor,
en quien apenas me había fijado hasta entonces. Era un mocetón fornido, ancho y algo cuadrado
de hombros; vestía pantalón azul con media remonta negra, sujeto a la cintura por un ceñidor
morado; y sobre la camisa de escaso cuello, un «lástico» o chaquetón de bayeta roja. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08065</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>47450</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19734</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Not long ago down from
his people asking me "something", at this hour and in such terms that I had to give the "God
you for protection" with the shotgun lying in the face. First and only time I've seen.

"For good and for a finishing touch to the way that I bring and I'm tired: I think if we encourage you
and give me the gift of your company in this house, the cry of the earth, I would be more bearable.
There is nothing more to do tempt among these solitary crags, you who are seasoned the buttocks
and gifts of the court, but to everything men do when they insist on it, without also relevant
here is its sun, and although it is true that it takes a little in the morning in transposing
the peaks that surround the place, and lights up once warms and gladdens the soul like the
sun more friendly of any party. In addition, your exile could not last long for reasons that
I know, and last settlement, to leave it in could not resist as he
was finishing the story for you.

'Item more: I have certain plans in the Magin, they give me much to do. What man walks free
them for me? I have no heirs and no longer have at home something to throw losing my own membership,
something that will go God knows where, if my last and rearward no
mole at sight with a being that makes me a little tingling in interlinings
of the heart.

"Of course, I do not try to turn on your lust with these hints.

A large part go! But all is well and have stipulated this in hours that have begun run to me.

"Well,
man, come on come over here, and if you can not do it for fun, do
it for charity of God.

"

Least the 'slump' and its consequences, all that my uncle told me this letter to me I was well
known, and knew also, what is easily deduced from its earlier low correspondence with us and how little
I had told my father, who was his brother Celso a folksy man of few lyrics and excellent heart,
acute and somewhat cunning Magin, as a good mountaineer, and more careful cultivation and prosperity
of their land and livestock, which the promotion of their affection for the family she had
left; sloppiness that sometimes played in an indifference seemed bordering the absolute oblivion.
Unless I knew my uncle in his native land and of our solar house, not so much because of my
lack of curiosity about such matters as by the work of one of the most salient weakness of my
father. He further called attention surnames personal conditions of "our", and thus to ask for
life and times of any of them, rather than straight answer to the question, perched at the
top of the family tree, and crawled from branch to branch to down, not stop to give the least,
with the leg of the Cid, if it is satisfied with that. Their parents could only take in clean,
at different times asked news on them, which had been the junction of the house "only" of the Ruiz
de Bejos of Tablanca, with those of Gómez de Pomar, the most illustrious of the promise. Few
flow, yes, by mainly the latter, that is, by my paternal grandmother, who only brought into
the marriage a few necklaces and earrings of coral, two silver reliquaries a splinter of the
True Cross, and a bone of St. Felicitas, respectively, three sets of linen, linen tablecloths
home two, a gold chain from Cordoba, the prom dress with his marriage, and another half for
everyday use. On my grandfather was a thing very different. Our house Tablanca exercised throughout
the valley, by virtue of their status amen of noble charity, certain undeniable and patriarchal
dominion, and was forced whereabouts of all the notable people who passed by, even bishops. Just
as remember my father had stayed two in it: the de Santander and Leon. For these and other necessities
like chests and cabinets were in good supply of linens and table linens higher abundant solid
silver table and up to two damask bedspreads and a crucifix ivory and ebony. Nothing was there
that must not be missing from the house of a family like ours. But its situation, its form,
its extent, its comforts, or short, at most, which was great, with sunny, coat of arms and
ancillary. Ground it was located and its outskirts, the conditions and appearance of landscape,
climate, of its resources for life more than animal, the customs of its inhabitants, was idle inquire
anything by reports that good sir, that be so paid out of race and put on the horns of the moon
the arms of his house and the land they had born only once and very quickly returned to it
after having left it, though rule of necessity, as a boy yet. Went back to the top of all that
had heard and read about this empingorotada region of the Cantabrian Mountains, and was to
see how they are there, primarily with the Celts, our putative progenitors, and took down then
from there to become embroiled hand in hand and as one fan and regular fair price and current
family issues, with those tribes untamed, with that fierce Spaniard passed the Alps with Hannibal
against Rome fought and defeated Scipio in Ticino. After talking Augustus and his legions who
have come to Cantabria expressly to subject the Roman yoke; that that was our thrust, that
"our" value and that "our" attachment to independence, that Caesar had six years to succeed in
an endeavor that had seemed to work a few days of the horrors of this barbarous war between inaccessible
crags and deep and dark ravines where the water roared inks in the blood of "our" and hardened
legionnaires. No missing as of mothers during the war killed their little ones to not see them
slaves to foreign winners, nor the death of so many cross martyrs singing hymns of freedom from
curses to the conqueror, and with all this, a number of details about the type and the mores of
his heroes, details that I had wanted on the land they inhabit, as it was in my days. Far from
it, leaving only Cantabrians to mix his successors in the epic of Covadonga or the trouble of "Bands"
of Castile, and you put here with dithyrambs their illustrious "ancestors", ran with them the
five parts of the world to not know where he was, nor I either. Because on these matters my
father was a generous scholarship, but somewhat suspicious, work a greed that came with the truth
as with the fantastic, by clinging tenaciously, but purely platonic, things of earth.

In this way I knew it, upon receiving the letter from my uncle, little more is known, by guesswork
or by comparison, other fellows who have been "passing" and very quickly.

Meanwhile I had already served thirty-two years for six who was a doctor in both rights, albeit
unknowingly, by disuse of them, what they were for those things more
than seven that field for my respect, and gave me the high life with
the flow that I inherited from my father.

Because my mother did not inherit a penny. Granada was a very pretty daughter of a judge Hearing
of that land. He met my father walked over there a while, busy mining
business, and married her in the overnight.

The judge was a widower and poor, and died two years after the wedding of his daughter.

I owe to God, among other grants, the temperament of a uniquely balanced moods, which allowed
me to go through the most dangerous hardships of life, while including the lower strip of skin. Very
few things have touched my soul, and I seldom I have a passion for the best of them. This has
been my greatest fortune in the midst of freedom and abundance in which I lived, being pampered
and spoiled child, while I was' son of the family " rich and detached
from all constraints when it has no father and mother and declared
myself "boy open house.

" Under these conditions and a passionate temperament, God knows what had been of me and my
money. Still, not increase the legacy of my father, and even drop him a good chop, because not
all the time ran the same for the vile farthing; and I, though without losing sight of how useful
it is this ingredient to live at home with the men, there was born to a slave to him and had
entrenched interests that were not cheap. I liked traveling, and traveled extensively in and outside
Spain, I liked the so-called "big world" or 'high society', and frequented its halls, theaters,
field trips and even fashionable resorts, and sports, I like the Fine Arts, although considered
mainly as a luxury item, and buy paintings and sculptures in the exhibition; I liked certain
men of politics and literature, not by politicians or by literati precisely, but the resonance
of their names and the attractiveness of their conversations and frequented his treatment and
accompanied him in his circle and their feasts and gatherings in and revelry ... I even liked the
bullfighters at a distance, and distance grew the friendship of some of them.

All this, and as much more than it follows the law enforced at the end of the day was wear
expensive and produce deep, if not hide, at least moral sensitivity, even though it is a boy
like me, who aspired to be no box set of the first term, or half-inch lift on the common size of
the mass of spectators, and this, not virtue, but by the exigencies of my temperament.

It is very noteworthy that in the hobby more pronounced of all mine, the travel, seduced me much artifice
of men that the work of Nature.

As good Madrid, loved to Madrid over all earthly things, and after Madrid, similar to Spain and
abroad, the largest and liveliest capitals of the civilized world. What remained among those,
I did not care, and passed on it, to go wherever he went, as insensitive projectile that has given
whereabouts from their point of origin. Son and resident of land plain, mountains and sky saddened
me fuzzy fearfulness me.

Once one had been in the mountain capital, masking a desire to tread "the land of my ancestors" my
father would say, the temptation to spend the summer at the port began to be "elegant." Rail crossing
near the Cantabrian Mountains above the sources of the Ebro, recalled that "there" did not
know whether the right or left, had to walk my ancestral home, in a withdrawal of those mountains
mists and tight hooded black oak. And then had more resonance in my heart this much-vaunted "cry blood."
Days later, and from one of the heights overlooking the city, Santander, practical So I named, pointing
with his finger, every peak and every mountain of the great mountain range that begins at
the East Cape and Galizano Quintres (the tail of the huge reptile), and ends at West poking through
the clouds the Picos de Europa (his head).

Then, by drawing in the air with the same finger during each river of her birth in and the bottom of
his black cliffs tumble, arrived addressed to the West, and marking three stripes almost vertical,
I named the Sakha, the Nansa and Deva, and there I stopped him with thought, telling me himself,
"Along with one of the three rivers (I think the Nansa) plus above or below, must walk the site
of my elders. "And this just fell for the second time, "the cry of blood" who had in his veins. As
decoration, that I fell in love string of jagged mountains from east to west on the south
serve as grandiose setting the wonderful bay, but as habitable land!

...

Such were, peak, peak less, my personal background when I got the letter in which Celso my uncle
called me to his side, indefinitely, from the depths and Mountaineer of the Cantabrian region,
and yet, no embassy gave me unpleasant impression as might be assumed to take exactly what was said
about my way of being and feeling.

Apart from what interested me the physical and moral of my uncle,
I was not so in love My way of life, scares me the risks of radical
upheaval for some time.

Without feeling "tired" of living as he lived, because there was no drop at ride so calm and
relatively orderly as he had used me to get where he come by so many dangerous roads, began to
notice at the time certain languor spirit, inappetence certain moral certainly were not at
odds with a break homes, and much less an exchange of views and "food".

On this side, the letter My uncle could not be more timely than it was in my hands. The serious,
unexpected terrible thing for me was on the other hand, the quality of what I called it. Resolved
to change their lives for some time, God knows what paths I had taken, but certainly to me that
never would have chosen that my uncle wanted and I intended. Get there to make a visit, stop
by long, even to know view the site of my grandparents, thank goodness, but to settle it;
make the lives of the beasts among crags and brambles; acclimated she suddenly ran into the
station (rather than mid autumn), the threshold of winter Why should he see Tablanca! Water newcomer
I-Hi Paris and halfway around the world "Distinguished", with suitcases packed with 'new', both
in carrying clothes; reinstated in my "comfortable" single house ... Come on, was the height
of the impossible dream even trocar in all that and so suddenly I was offered from Tablanca.

But I could not tell my uncle these things that would hurt a lot in the situation of mind in
which he found himself, he entertained his urgent request dispatching evasive polite, claiming that
he had business, and targeting "see" without the slightest intention of comply.

Ente Thus, the vision, my way, Tablanca's house, with its mountains and wild animals and their people
and their wintry desolation, not a moment away from my eyes, because the pleadings my uncle,
more alive, came to touch me deep inside, and what might happen,
felt the need to put the case in question, which is as good as the
rules experience, as you start to compromise.

The truth is that one day, I received the second to last letter from my uncle, I very comovió
deeply, say in the matter of looking within myself why I be so insensitive
to agreed charms of nature.

Are you missing that string in my body had either not had put in hand to vibrate? For there
to find out, because it began to mortify the fear of not having it. Additionally, or is one man,
or it is not, or has or does not have guts humanity, guts to go where you go and do what others
do, or serves or served for something more useful and more juice and enjoyment to tread rugs
salons, kidney fat a Jewish innkeepers, tailors and shoemakers in
fashion shows to attend, devouring distances crammed into cages rail
docks, and spending, in short, time and money on trifles in vain and
frivolous slut.

On track the discourse on this path, I feel a force of spirit, a virility unknown to me my
love soliviantóse own good healthy boy of soul and body, and taking advantage fever, fearing that if it
was temporary, it will take my ardor to disappear I wrote to my uncle saying "here I come" and
even by attaching the date of my departure from Madrid. Among I would therefore my travel arrangements,
and I answer he gave me the necessary instructions to get home from the last railroad station.

As
I walked busy making abundant supply of warm clothing, sturdy footwear, weapons offensive and defensive
Aimard books of Töpffer and few, including Chateaubriand, have pleasant things written about mountains,
forests and wild, as if projected a tour of the center of a remote
unexplored continent, I can not answer that Missed me fever.

Less secure it when I tried to "lift" my house. Seemed that this amounted to burn my ships,
or at least to me and had consented to by to be very long my stay among the bears of Cantabria, and
the fear of this risk I leaned to leave these things as they were on good friends in Madrid that
they would look for them. At any rate, nothing is easier than solving the contrary from there,
if you ask the circumstances.

Finally, fearing that this remnant of my weaknesses is I would still brewing other air cooler
and enervating, closed the doors of all reflection speech contrary to the agreement, and boasts
Alea est, I thought, like Caesar, resolved to pass all costs for my Rubicon.

II

And the company rushed on the agreed date, one day in late October, cold and misty in the heights
of the Roman "Juliobriga." In the classic villa immediate end of my journey first and only
possible by train, I stopped half an hour away: the purely essential members to stretch and comfort
the stomach, because there was no time to lose according to the opinion
of the footman who was waiting for me at that point from the previous
day with two nag land, and chaparretes espelurciados, one to drive
me and one for bear my luggage.

Launched all well run and mid-morning, before the footman carrying
the spur the horse that was barely visible beneath the heap of my
bags and wrappers, without leaving the center of the town by a bridge
crossed the Ebro old newborn and rather short stretch down there and
after a short lie down, it was on that side as suburban population
we left back, Vimon free field, if free can which is encircled called
barriers.

From the summits of the highest fell off wisps of fog that enveloped
them, and mimicked left to dry wet fleeces in tips of the rocks and
the thickness of those secular and almost inaccessible trees, with
the mountain air blowing constantly, and so fresh, that forced me
to lift up the ears, the neck of my new raincoat.

Continuing our journey faced west, we had continually to the left, water above the river, with its fresh,
green and pompous bank vaults and canopies willow, alder and blackberry, and topábamos from
time to time with a small town, although not very happy color, spice up the monotony of the landscape.

At
the edge of the last of this series of them in the center of a small amphitheater of bare
hills in their tops, were reborbollando the copious springs emerge
from famous river, after briefly haven to orientate in the field and
gain breaths from the slopes of their own crib, escapes from there,
running around, hiding from light whenever possible, as everyone who
does evil to leave soon for his native land, bring the benefits of
their waters to foreign fields and unknown people, and pay to inattentive
during his tribute to all his wealth to whom you should not be in
a good law.

Y to faith, or my eyes deceived me much, or would work very easy and cheap to tackle the runaway
a short distance from their sources, and as punishment for his disloyalty, cast him down headlong
downhill without giving rest to give point, macerated and in foams, the wrath of its owner
and natural lord, the broad and fiery Bay of Biscay.

I should spend too much time meditating on these and other childish things, and taste the memories
awoke in me the contemplation of those crystal clear waters that have so as do history and
the imagination of poets, because the footman, saving all the usual compliments on his rude
courtesy, I noted the desirability of us to continue walk.

- Da Grim - obeying said - think of the behavior of this renegade mountain.

I had to decipher the metaphor for the footman to understand me what I wanted to say; and as
I had understood, he replied:

- Déjeli, déjeli to go in grace and, earlier, before jaz Aonda needed more than here. Pa meter
Malis buya and cause maybe, people have many Rius as estimated by the band here.

Explicóse turn the footman for me to understand, and I became convinced, with examples I became
overwhelmed mountain rivers perhaps without why or wherefore, sweeping houses bridges and mills
in the highest, and eating in the valleys the land should be watering, that may well be meritorious
what had seemed in the Ebro unpardonable.

Certainly not bad, nor explained his side have kept my harsh interesting interlocutor, in whom
only I had noticed before.

It was a fine fellow burly, broad and somewhat square shoulders, and wore blue pants with
black back half, subject to the waist by a girdle purple, and the low neck shirt, a "lastic"
or red flannel jacket.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>