<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07122</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>81147</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23975</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Yo bien provisto estaba de armas y municiones; Chisco también, y a mi lado vivía en casa; y
a Chorcos, ya cuidaría yo de avisarle a tiempo para que se quedara a velar con el pretexto
del grave estado de don Celso. No dejó de ocurrírseme que, en lugar de esperar a los salteadores
en el portalón de la casa, se les podía armar una emboscada en los peñascos inmediatos a ella,
y fusilarlos a mansalva en cuanto se arrimaran a la puerta los tres. Pero este plan era menos
«concluyente» que el otro, y estaba expuesto a quiebras que podían salirnos caras a los acometedores,
por más que nos asistiera la justicia, según todas las leyes divinas y humanas. Así y con todo,
se pesarían y medirían ambos planes si llegaba el caso y en su hora, y se optaría por el mejor.

Esto y mucho más lo meditaba yo voltejeando maquinalmente por el interior de la casona después
de haber despedido al médico. Dando, de repente, por bien examinado el punto por entonces,
resolví volver a ver cómo andaba mi tío de sus angustias mortales. Pero no entré en su cuarto
sin asomarme antes a uno de los vidrios de la puerta que daba a la solana por el comedor. El
cielo continuaba obscureciéndose y el chispear de la nieve espesando. Me gustó el síntoma.
Mi tío, aunque entre amagos continuos de la tos, parecía más sosegado, y dormitaba. Facia,
sentada lejos de él y atenta a cuanto pudiera ocurrirle, después que yo hube contemplado al
enfermo acercándome de puntillas a su cama, me dijo con la mirada:

--Bien va eso, ¿eh?

A lo que yo respondí con otra mirada y un gesto:

--De lo mejor.

Pero bien sabe Dios que ni la pregunta ni la respuesta se referían al estado del enfermo, sino
al aspecto del temporal.

Pasaron dos horas sin que dentro ni fuera de la casona ocurriera novedad digna de ser notada,
y llegaron, pero sin el estrépito de costumbre, Lita y su madre y hasta el propio don Pedro
Nolasco. Esta peripecia, relativamente alegre, en el sombrío drama que se desenvolvía, y a
todo andar, en aquellos envejecidos ámbitos, me levantó mucho el espíritu. Venían los tres
personajes hondamente impresionados por las noticias que les había dado Neluco. El gigante,
por todo saludo, me estrechó la mano en silencio, con dos tremendas sacudidas que a poco me
desarticulan el brazo por el hombro; su nieta y su hija, con los ojos empañados, me pidieron,
mientras comenzaban a desliarse los abrigos, y en voz muy baja algo temblorosa, las noticias
de cajón sobre el estado actual de mi tío. Díselas, no tan malas como las que esperaban ellas,
y esto las animó a acercarse muy quedito hasta la puerta de la alcoba. Desde allí estuvieron
contemplando el batallar que no cesaba dentro de las ruinas de don Celso, entre el sueño que
le amodorraba y la tos que se lo prohibía, hasta que se revolvió en la cama por uno de aquellos
choques, del que salió medio sofocado, con la boca y los ojos muy abiertos y acopiando el aire
para respirar, hasta con las manos. Entonces se ocultaron rápidamente, casi de un salto, en
la salona, y se volvieron ambas hacia mí, que no las perdía de vista, con la pena y la conmiseración
pintadas en la cara. A todo esto, don Pedro Nolasco, de pie, rígido, inmóvil y silencioso,
en el mismo sitio en que se había plantado al entrar. Pasó en breve el acceso, y volvió el
enfermo a caer en el marasmo de antes... Pero ¿qué diablos veía yo en Lituca que me cautivaba
más la atención en aquellos momentos que el pasmo de su abuelo y la angustiosa situación de
mi tío? ¿Qué había en ella de nuevo y de extraño para mí? Pues, lisa y llanamente, las lágrimas
de sus ojos y la expresión dolorida de su cara infantil; y yo me preguntaba en cuanto salí
de mis dudas: «Pero ¿cuándo está más mona esta chica? ¿cuando ríe y gorjea como los pajaritos
del monte, sin penas ni cuidados, o cuando siente, como ahora, a falta de dolores propios,
la compasión que le inspiran los ajenos?» Y no sabiendo por cuál de estos extremos optar, quedéme
con los dos, porque es lo cierto que, riendo o llorando, estaba monísima aquella criatura.

Temiendo que la impresionara con exceso la contemplación frecuente de aquel cuadro aflictivo
de la miseria humana, tan nuevo para ella, la aconsejé que se abstuviese de entrar en el cuarto
del enfermo. A lo que me respondió con una fuerza de resolución que se imponía:

--¡Pues mire que tendría que ver, señor don Marcelo!... ¡Vaya! ¡vaya!... ¿Piensa que soy yo
de melindres, por si acaso? No diré que al principio no me encoja un poco; pero después...
¡vaya! ¡vaya! Y, por último, para las ocasiones son las valentías; y ahora o nunca. ¡El mi
pobre señor don Celso!...

--Déjela, déjela--me decía casi al mismo tiempo la rozagante Mari Pepa, arrojando el último
de sus abrigos flotantes sobre una silla, encima de los que acababa de arrojar Lituca--; déjela
que entre y salga cuando quiera, que es bueno jacerse a todo, como ella se irá jiciendo, porque
la conozco bien. Al que hay que tener a raya sobre ese punto, es al mi padre. Cayóle la noticia
como una peña en la nuca, y aturdióse como usté le ve. Yo no sabía si dejarle en casa o traerle;
pero vile roncero de quedarse solo y muy arrimao a venirse, y jícele su gusto, que era también
el nuestro; porque puestas aquí, podemos tardar más o menos en volver a casa, y mejor que en
parte alguna estará el venturao con nosotras donde quiera que ello sea. Lo que está él es aterecío
de frialdá, ¿no es cierto, padre? Y mire, en la cocina habrá buena lumbre, ¿no es verdá, don
Marcelo? y estará usté más apartao de estas cosas que le amurrian y acobardan, sin dejar de
estar bien acompañao con los que entran y salen... y de paso, mire, que añada Tona buen por
qué al ollón grande, que somos tres bocas más... ¡Hija, qué bobás se le ocurren a una cuando
no sabe lo que diz, ni tomar los tiempos como vienen! Conque ¿entendióme, padre?... Y a usté,
don Marcelo, ¿qué le paez de este disponer mío, como si estuviera en la mi casa?

Todo me pareció bien, hasta el estilo, y las precauciones que tomaba Mari Pepa para no ser
oída del enfermo, y la decisión de Lituca, y, en particular, la cara que ponía para declarármela.
Yo mismo conduje a la cocina a don Pedro Nolasco, que se dejaba traer y llevar como un niño
atolondrado, y le senté en el sillón de mi tío, dejándole al cuidado de Tona y de Chisco, que
andaba por allí entonces, con encargo de que le entretuvieran y animaran... y le dieran de
comer cuanto pidiera, si lo pedía. Yo volvería por allí muy a menudo, y las señoras lo harían
también de vez en cuando. En el ínterin, mucha leña a mano y buena lumbre sin cesar.

Antes de salir de la cocina, miré por los cristalejos de la puerta que da al balconazo de aquella
fachada, y vi que continuaban ennegreciéndose los celajes y que ya blanqueaban un poco los
picachos de enfrente y hasta las praderas del valle por algunos sitios.

Cuando llegué al cuarto de mi tío, ya se habían apoderado de él y de sus aledaños Lituca y
su madre, y enviado a Facia a sus ordinarios quehaceres, por no ser necesaria allí su presencia
por entonces. Ordenaban adentro muebles, ropas y frascos y botellas de potingues; enderezaban
felpudos y alfombrillas, que abundaban en el suelo; graduaban y dirigían la luz de los cuarterones
de la ventana y la que entraba por la puerta, de modo que no diera de lleno en la cara del
enfermo, y hasta le limpiaban el sudor viscoso y frío que relucía en su frente, y le arreglaban
las coberturas y las almohadas; pero todo ello, lo mismo que cuando trabajaban afuera, sin
hacer ruido ni levantar polvo ni causar la más leve mortificación al paciente. Me daba gusto
contemplar aquel trabajo de hadas bienhechoras. Mi tío, sofocado por la tos, despertaba algunas
veces de su letargo, abría los ojos, clavaba en nosotros su mirada entorpecida y voraz, y volvía
a cerrarlos enseguida para caer de nuevo en su modorra. Cuando se aprovechaba una de estas
coyunturas para darle unos sorbos de caldo o la «cucharada» medicinal que «le correspondía»,
tomábalo entre quejidos y balbucía protestas iracundas.

Cerca del mediodía se despejó un poco y nos ponderó mucho lo mal que se encontraba. Llegó en
esto Neluco, y ni por cortesía intentó convencerle de lo contrario. Pero le exhortó a que llevara
con paciencia sus trabajos, pues no estaba obligado a menos un hombre de su fe y de su correa.
A lo que contestó el enfermo, con toda la iracundia que pudo hallar entre el montón de sus
propias ruinas:

--¿Todavía te paez cosa de ná la mi paciencia, condenao? Con la mitá de lo que tengo te quisiera
yo ver, mediquín, matasanos de los demonios, a ver qué cara ponías... ¡Pues hombre!...

Intervinimos todos, Neluco inclusive, para calmarle, y se calmó pronto; pero no apuntó la menor
idea de prepararse a bien morir. Sobre este punto venía muy contrariado el médico. Me dijo,
al despedirse, que don Sabas estaba ausente del lugar, auxiliando a un moribundo de otro pueblo,
cuyo párroco se hallaba enfermo. Al saberlo le había mandado un propio; pero como hasta el
pueblo había muchas varas de camino que medir y la nevada iba espesando por instantes, aunque
don Sabas procuraría no perder uno solo en cuanto se enterase de lo que ocurría en la casona,
¡fuera usted a saber a qué hora de la tarde llegaría, y si llegaría a tiempo ya!

Por no acercar demasiado al gigantón de la Castañalera al cuadro que tan tristemente le impresionaba,
comimos todos con él en la perezosa de la cocina, servidos por Tona, mientras su madre cuidaba
del enfermo. No fue aquella comida tan sabrosa para mí como otra que yo no olvidaba, más que
por lo reciente de su fecha, por lo regocijada que la hicieron aquellas dos comensalas que
en la última, algo por respeto a la tristeza «oficial» de la casa, y algo más por la pena que
los motivos de esta tristeza les daban, comieron muy poco y hablaron menos. Menos habló todavía
que ellas, don Pedro Nolasco, que no habló palabra; pero, en cambio, ¡qué engullir el suyo
tan formidable!

Antes de que acabáramos de comer, supimos por Facia que el enfermo había vuelto a dormirse
y que «el trapeu de la nieve iba tan a más, que daba gustu». Yo me acordé de la ausencia de
don Sabas y de la falta que hacía al lado de mi tío, y no recibí la noticia con tanto placer
como el que sentía la madre de Tona al dármela.

Según corrían las horas de la tarde, apretaba el temporal y también las ansias del enfermo,
que seguía luchando con ellas a ojos cerrados y sin conciencia, al parecer, de lo que estaba
pasando. Bien sabe Dios lo que nos inquietaban estos síntomas y que ardíamos en deseos de insinuarle
lo que Neluco deseaba, ya que no se anticipaba él a insinuarlo; pero ¿de qué serviría la insinuación
mientras no tuviéramos a mano al Cura? Entre estas dudas y las consiguientes inquietudes, llegó
la noche cerrada, a poco más de las cuatro, con una tercia de nieve sobre el valle y un nevar
espeso y continuo que ya me iba alarmando mucho, porque suponía a don Sabas en camino y pensaba
en los peligros que podía correr. Entre tanto la cocina se llenaba poco a poco de gente que
acudía a saber de don Celso y a ofrecerse para toda clase de menesteres en la casa en aquellas
horas de prueba, y a mí no me disgustaba verme tan bien acompañado en ocasión de tantos apuros.
A don Pedro Nolasco le sucedía lo propio, y hasta rompió a hablar con los contertulios y se
permitió ciertos vaticinios risueños acerca de la enfermedad del viejo amigo y casi pedazo
de su alma... precisamente en el instante en que mi tío saliendo de su modorra pertinaz y después
de recorrer la estancia con los ojos azorados, dijo entre angustias de la respiración, como
si no le cupiera ya en el pecho una burbuja de aire sin haberle desocupado de otra igual:

--Ahora... ahora es la de irse de veras, hijos míos, y la de prepararme al viaje en toda regla.
Hacedme la caridad de decirle al Cura que le llamo yo para lo que él sabe... si no es alguno
de los bultos que yo distingo malamente desde aquí, no sé si por culpa de la poca luz del cuarto,
o porque ha empezado a apagarse ya la de mis ojos... ¡Sabas!... ¡Sabas!...

Todos los allí presentes oíamos y callábamos, y nos mirábamos unos a otros sin saber qué contestar.
¿Cómo decirle que el Cura no estaba en la casona ni en el pueblo?... Pero ¡qué ofuscación tan
absurda la nuestra! ¿Qué inconveniente había en entretenerle las impaciencias, respondiendo
que habían ido a avisarle y que estaba a punto de llegar? Esto iba a responderle yo al mismo
tiempo que me acercaba a su cama con Lita y Mari-Pepa, hechas un mar de lágrimas, mientras
quedaba Facia arrimada a la pared del fondo con los brazos cruzados, la cabeza inclinada sobre
el pecho y los ojos, secos, entristecidos e inmóviles, clavados en la faz cadavérica de su
amo, cuando éste volvió a exclamar, pero con un brío inconcebible en su estado miserable:

--¡Sabas! ¡Sabas!...

En esto oí un rudo golpeteo, como al desembocar del carrejo en la salona, y al mismo tiempo
una voz que respondía a estas llamadas enérgicas:

--¡Allá va, jinojo!...

Conocí la voz, retrocedí de un salto hasta la puerta, y vi que por la del salón avanzaba un
bulto que lo mismo podía ser un jaral de la montaña, tal y como debían estar todos en aquellos
instantes, que un hombrazo del calibre y los talares de don Sabas, porque venía nevado por
la cabeza y por los hombros y por donde quiera que asomaba un relieve, por mínimo que fuera,
en sus luengas y espidas vestiduras; y al andar y sacudirse de propio intento, arrojaba en
el suelo la nieve en cascadas polvorosas, como cae de los matorros cuando los sacude y zarandea
el cierzo enfurecido. Salí a su encuentro para ayudarle a sacudirse y a enjugarse... y a nada,
porque de dos bativoleos se desprendió de todo lo flotante que goteaba sobre él. Así quedó,
en un periquete, liso y mondo de pies a cabeza, es decir, de chaqueta corta y en pelo. Mientras
se iba despojando de aquellas envolturas y accesorios, me decía:

--¡Ah! pues gracias a que el tordillo tiene más agallas de lo que paez, y pudo con el espolique
que a medio camino le cargué a las ancas, que si no... ¡jinojo! dígote que no llegamos vivos
ninguno de los tres; porque nevadas he visto en lo que llevo de vivir; pero como ésta, ¡vaya,
vaya!... ¿Y qué le pasa al pobre don Celso, hombre? Cuando allá me lo fueron a decir, no me
cogió de susto, porque me lo venía yo temiendo de día en día. Lo peor del caso fue que aquel
infeliz agonizante no acababa, y no era cosa de abandonarle en trance tal... Pues ¡cuidado
si le da por no acabar en toda la tarde de Dios!... A todo esto, la nieve espesando y cerrándose
los caminos. ¡Mira tú qué ocasión para ponerse este otro en la agonía!... ¡Si lo que hace Satanás
para jincar el diente a las almas, es mucho cuento! A bien que no ha sido ello por falta de
advertencias mías; pero este Celso, con ser tan hombre de fe, es de suyo tan...

Todo eso lo decía ya, y casi lo gritaba, el bueno del Cura a la puerta del dormitorio de su
amigo, donde le interrumpió el descosido razonamiento otra llamada como la de antes.

--¡Sabas! ¡Sabas!

--¡Aquí estoy, hombre!--respondió el Cura--. ¡Cuidado que es tema!... Pues mira, con esas prisas
en mejor salú, no las tuvieras ahora...

--¡Eso es!--refunfuñó mi tío--. Para consuelo de mis ajogos, tíñeme y vociférame, ¡pispajo!

--¡Qué te he de reñir, hombre, qué te he de reñir!--díjole entonces don Sabas, que enfrente
de aquellas ruinas miserables del amigo y camarada de toda su vida, no acertaba a contener
los lagrimones que le brotaban en los ojos--, ¡ni cómo te he de vociferar!... ¡Pues bueno estaría
ello, jinojo!... sino que, como he venido, pude no venir, por causa de fuerza mayor. ¡Y figúrate
tú entonces! ¡figúratelo, Celso!... Vaya--añadió interrumpiendo de pronto su discurso y pasando
la mirada por el cuarto y acentuándola con un movimiento de sus brazos, muy significativo--:
aquí sobran todos menos el enfermo y yo; porque lo que va a pasar entre nosotros, no admite
más testigo que uno, que es el Señor y juez de vidas y almas.

Salimos los que sobrábamos y cerró don Sabas la puerta por dentro. Yo no sé lo que pasó por
mí entonces; pero declaro que me sentí muy conmovido y que hasta lloré, disimulándolo mucho,
como si fuera una debilidad indigna de los hombres fuertes.

¿Procedían aquellas lágrimas vergonzantes del contagio de otras más francas? ¿Eran arrancadas
de mi corazón por la pena de ver a aquél, mi pariente en estado tan mísero y compasible? ¿Me
las producía aquella rara escena que acababa de presenciar entre el Cura y el enfermo, a través
de cuya tosca urdimbre se dejaban ver fondos y lejanías admirables? Quizás hubiera en ellas
algo de todos y cada uno de estos ingredientes; pero el hecho es que yo lloraba, aunque no
tanto como las mujeres que se agrupaban junto a mí, mientras iban entrando de puntillas en
el salón en que estábamos muchos de los tertulianos de la cocina que se habían amontonado en
el carrejo después de la llegada del Cura, transidos de pesadumbre... y de curiosidad.

La luz que Facia había encendido en la lamparilla del dormitorio al salir de él, y que aún
conservaba en la mano, iluminaba un poco aquellas fauces entenebrecidas; y así pude entreverlas
atascadas, materialmente, de figuras apiñadas y oscilantes que miraban hacia nosotros con impaciencias
voraces; y aun hubiera jurado yo que allá en el fondo, detrás de toda la masa, pero alzándose
un codo sobre la cabeza del más talludo, relucían, como dos linternas en un túnel, los ojazos
verdes y saltones del gigantón de la Castañalera.

XXVII

Al cabo de un buen rato me pidió Mari Pepa muchas cosas que, a su juicio, iban a ser necesarias
allí muy pronto. Yo, delegando en ella y en su hija cuantas atribuciones tenía en la casa,
las entregué las pocas llaves que guardaba, y mandé a Facia que se pusiera a sus órdenes con
las restantes. Para despachar bien y pronto lo que proyectaban, era indispensable que se volvieran
a la cocina los tertulianos que, dispersos por aquí o en rebaños por allá, todo lo obstruían...
y apestaban, y no había manera de revolverse entre ellos. Hízose así al punto por mi mandato,
y empezaron las dos mujeres a saquear alacenas, armarios y cajones. Facia guiaba, y yo seguía
como un autómata a las tres.

Mientras desvalijaban el último cajón de la cómoda de mi cuarto, se abrió la puerta de mi tío,
y apareció don Sabas en el hueco. Noté que salía lloriqueando, y corrí hacia él temiendo que
ya hubiera concluido todo allí; pero desde medio camino oí toser al enfermo, y esto me tranquilizó.
Salióme al encuentro el Cura, y me dijo, mientras se secaba los ojos con un pañuelo de yerbas:

--No se puede remediar, ¡qué jinojo!... por más avezado que uno esté a contemplar miserias
y acabaciones humanas... Porque hay casos y casos, señor don Marcelo, y éste es uno de los
más duros de pelar para el pobre Cura. Sesenta años de vivir, más que como amigos, como hermanos,
y cada cual en su ministerio... ¡y cuidado si ha sido de altura el suyo!... algo rejunde en
la entraña... me parece a mí... De pronto diz el otro al uno de ellos: «vaya, pues yo me marcho...
y para no volver: conque ajústame tú estas cuentas que tengo que dar a Dios, por tu mediación
mesma de lo mucho que le debo y de lo poco y mal que le he pagado... y ahí te quedas, viejo
y solo, hasta que te llegue la tuya, que no puede tardar porque de viejo nadie pasa; y ya verás
lo que es jallarte un día y otro sin el amigo de siempre, que parecía ya carne de tus carnes
y llenaba todo el lugar, aunque en él no se le viera...» Y vaya usté, por otra parte, a saber
si al llegar la de uno, le cogerá así o le cogerá asao, porque la carne es flaca y Satanás
no duerme, y si, por tomas o por dacas, tampoco volvemos a encontrarnos en el otro mundo. Porque
él va bien de equipajes... ¡eso sí, jinojo! y derecha como un juso ha de subir la su alma.
En lo humano no puede presumirse otra cosa, con la preparación que él ha hecho, después de
una vida de caridad, que yo me sé de memoria... En fin, que de ésta se va, y que no hay que
dormirse para disponerle todo lo que le falta en el trance en que se ve... Hay que viaticarle
enseguida, y para ello me voy a la iglesia ahora mismo. Adviértase aquí para que se espere
a Dios con la pompa que se le debe.

Se habían llevado sus talares a la cocina para secarlos a la lumbre; y al ir el Cura a recogerlos,
hizo a la gente congregada en ella la misma advertencia que a mí, y la arrastró luego consigo,
menos a Chisco y a Pito Salces, a quienes ordené yo que se quedaran «vigilando la casa, por
lo que pudiera ocurrir». Ocioso lujo de precauciones a aquellas horas (cerca de las siete),
con una noche oscura como boca de lobo, cayendo la nieve a puñados, y con unos rugidos del
vendaval hacia la montaña, que daban miedo.

Sin preocuparme gran cosa del pobre Marmitón, que se quedaba solo otra vez, repantigado, mudo
y atónito en el sillón de madera y muy arrimado al fuego, volvíme al cuarto de mi tío para
ver lo que pasaba en él después de la salida de don Sabas. Ya estaba desconocido todo aquel
interior, y aún continuaban transformándole por momentos las dos hadas de la casona. En la
cama del enfermo, la colcha de damasco rojo de los grandes días, y vuelto sobre ella, el amplio
y bordado embozo de una sábana de lujo; las almohadas, con fundas de grandes guarniciones muy
tiesas y escaroladas, y el enfermo mismo, con camisola limpia, calentada poco antes al brasero
y sahumada con tomillo, sobre el espeso chaquetón elástico que le abrigaba el tronco; junto
a la cama, una alfombra en lugar del felpudo de siempre; encima de la cómoda, cayendo en airosos
pabellones por los lados, otra colcha de las buenas de la casa, y sobre ella, esperando mejor
destino, el crucifijo de marfil, seis candeleros de plata, un vaso con agua bendita y un ramito
de laurel.

Cuando yo llegué, se ocupaban las dos mujeres, que parecían tener diablillos en las manos,
en sustituir, ayudadas de Facia, el trasto viejo que siempre estuvo a la cabecera de la cama,
con una mesita cuadrangular sacada de mi gabinete, donde la usaba yo para leer y despachar
mi correspondencia. Ofrecíles mi ayuda para aquella faena; pero la desdeñó Lita con un gestecillo
muy intencionado y dos frases de cortesía para templarle. Mientras Facia se llevaba el achacoso
artefacto, tendieron ellas sobre la mesa otra colcha de damasco rojo, y sobre la colcha una
muy blanca sabanilla con randas de muchos calados; luego trasladaron de la cómoda a la mesa
el crucifijo de marfil, cuatro candeleros y el vaso con agua bendita y el ramito de laurel;
enseguida otra alfombra delante de la mesita; después todas las tiras y ruedos que se encontraron
para formar una senda tan larga como se pudo; cuatro vapuleos a las sillas antes de ponerlas
en orden; unos toquecitos más a las ropas de la cama; una mirada desde lejos al conjunto de
tantas y tan diversas cosas... y ya estaba aquello despachado.

Mi tío, entre tanto, jadeando y tosiendo y pasando entre los dedos sarmentosos de su diestra
cuentas y más cuentas del rosario, y reza que reza entre dientes, sin darse por enterado de
lo que ocurría en su derredor, ni contestar más que con un gesto avinagrado a la menor pregunta
que se le hiciera. Antes de morir con el cuerpo, estaba ya en el otro mundo con el espíritu.
De Dios era, a Dios iba y sólo de Dios esperaba.

Terminado lo del cuarto, se emprendió afuera otra labor más peliaguda, para la que no bastaron
las mujeres solas. Mari Pepa esparcía en el suelo las colchas y pañolones que habían acopiado
en el saqueo y andaban en confuso montón sobre las sillas; Lita escogía y combinaba colores
y tamaños, y Pito Salces y yo, encaramados en muebles de la necesaria altura, clavábamos en
las paredes, y tan arriba como nos era posible, con tachuelas, con puntas... hasta con clavos
«trabaderos» y cuanto habíamos podido haber a las manos en una mechinal de la bodega en que
acumulaba Chisco las reservas de esta especie, lo que la diligente y afanada nieta del gigantón
de la Castañalera nos iba alargando con sus manitas primorosas, de lo desparramado por el suelo.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05983</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>80138</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21662</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I
was well supplied with arms and ammunition; Chisco too, and me living at home, and to Chorcos,
and take care to tell me in time for him to stay to ensure the pretext the serious condition
of Mr. Celso. No longer fancy that, instead of waiting for the robbers in the doorway of the house,
they could put together an ambush in the immediate rocks it and shoot at close range as the door
is placed along the three. But this plan was less "Conclusive" than the other, and was exposed
to bankruptcy that they could get out faces of the assailants, much as we attend to justice, by all divine
and human laws. Still yet will weigh and would measure both plans if the case came in due time,
and opt for the better.

This and more I pondered mechanically by tacking inside the house after have fired the doctor.
Dando, suddenly, well, the point then, I decided to see how he was my uncle of his mortal anguish.
But I went in his room without a trace before one of the glass in the door into the sunshine
through the dining room. The continued darkening sky and the sparkling snow thickens. I liked
the symptom. My uncle, though between continuous feigned coughing, seemed calmer, and slept.
Facia, sitting away from him and attentive to whatever might happen, after I had I referred
to sick tiptoed to the bed, his eyes told me:

- Well it going, eh?

To which I responded with another look and a gesture

- From the best.

But God knows that neither the question nor the answer referred to the condition of the patient,
but the temporal aspect.

They spent two hours with no inside or outside the house occurred novelty worthy of being noticed,
and came, but without the usual noise, Lita and her mother and even the Don Pedro Nolasco. The
ups and downs, relatively happy, in a dark drama that unfolded, and walk around in those aged
area, much the spirit lifted me. Came three characters deeply impressed by the news that had given
them Neluco. The giant Greeting all, I shook hands in silence, with two tremendous shock that
soon I dismantle the arm at the shoulder, his granddaughter and his daughter, his eyes misted
over, I asked, loosened as they began to shelters, and in a low voice a little shaky, news drawer
on the current state of my uncle. Tell him, not as bad as they expected them and this encouraged
them to come very quietly to the door of the bedroom. Since there were watching the battle
that did not stop within the ruins of Don Celso, between the dream you drowsy and coughing he insisted,
until it rolled over in bed in one of those clashes, which left half suffocated, mouth and
eyes wide open and collecting air breathing, even with their hands. Then he hid quickly, almost
jumping in the Hall, and did both to me, not lost sight of the grief and sympathy painted on
the face. To all this, Don Pedro Nolasco, standing, rigid, motionless and silent, in the same
place that had been planted at the door. Access soon passed, and turned fall ill in the morass
of before ... But what the hell I saw that I was captivated Lituca more attention at that
time that the shock of his grandfather and the plight of my uncle? What was in it again and strange
to me? Well, quite simply, tears their eyes and pained expression on his boyish face, and
I wondered as I left my doubts: "But when this girl is cuter? "When he laughs and gurgles as the
birds the mountain, without sorrow or care, or feel, as now, in the
absence of pain themselves, compassion that will inspire others?

" And not knowing which of these two extremes to choose, I remained with the two, because it's
true that laughing or crying, I was really cute creature.

Fearing that too much impressed with frequent contemplation of that distressing picture human
misery, so new to her, advised her to refrain from entering the room the patient. To which
I replied with a force resolution to be imposed:

- Well, now you have to do, Don Marcelo! ... Go! Go! ... Do you think I am of fuss, just in
case? I will not say that at first I shrink a little, but then ... Go! Go! And finally, for the
chances are the mighty, and now or never. On my Poor Mr. Don Celso! ...

- Leave it, leave it - I said almost the same time the rosy Mari Pepa, throwing the last their coats
on a chair floating on top of which had just shed Lituca -, let in and out whenever you want,
which is good jacerse all, as she will jiciendo because I know it well. When you have to hold
off on that point, is to my father. Cayouette the news as a rock in the neck, and aturdióse as Nah,
you see him. I did not know if leaving home or bring; but vile Roncero of being alone and very
arrimao to cum, and jícele your taste, it was also ours, because it placed here, it may take
more or less to return home, and better than nowhere will the venturao with us wherever it
is. What is it's aterecío coldness, is not it, father? And look in the kitchen there is good
light, do not you, don Marcelo? Nah, you depart and be more of these things that Amurrio and
intimidate, while acompañao be fine with going in and out ... and
by the way, look that adds good for Tona what the ollon great that
we are three more mouths ... Daughter, what silly occur to one when
do not know what he says or take the times as they come!

Entendióme "So, Father? ... And Nah, you, Don Marcelo, what you have paez of this mine, as
if you were in my house?

Everything seemed fine, until the style, and taking precautions to avoid being Mari Pepa patient's
hearing and decision of Lituca, and in particular, face to put to declarármela. I drove myself
to the kitchen at Don Pedro Nolasco, who was left fetch and carry like a child confused, and
I sat on the couch in my uncle, leaving the care of Tona and Chisco,
which was around then, with orders to entertain him and encouraged
... and gave him the eat as much as requested, if asked.

I would return there often, and the ladies they would also from time to time. In the meantime, lots
of wood by hand and constantly good fire.

Before leaving the kitchen, I looked out the door cristalejos giving the balconazo of that
facade, and saw the colored clouds still blackening and whitening and a little peaks in front and
to the prairies of the valley by some sites.

When I go into my uncle, and had seized him and his surrounding Lituca and his mother, and
sent to their regular chores Facia, not being necessary their presence there then. In ordering
furniture, clothes and bottles and bottles of potions, straightened rugs and mats, which were
plentiful in the soil, graduated and headed in light of the paneled window and coming in the
door so not to give in full in the face of sick, and he even cleaned the cold, clammy sweat that
glistened on his forehead, and he arranged covers and pillows, but this, as well as when working
out, without make noise or raising dust or cause the slightest mortification to the patient.
I was glad contemplate that beneficent fairy work. My uncle, choking cough, awakening some sometimes
from their slumber, opened his eyes, his gaze fell upon us hampered
and voracious, and again then closed them to fall back into slumber.

When taking advantage of these joints to give a few sips of broth or "scoop" medicinal "he corresponded"
Tomabal between groans and angry protests stammered.

About noon it cleared a bit and we pondered much how bad it was. Came in Neluco this, and not
by courtesy tried to convince them otherwise.

But he urged to carry with patience her work, since he was not required unless a man of his faith
and his belt.

To which I replied the patient, with all the ire he could find in the pile of own ruins:

- Do you still get something of NA paez my patience, condenao? With the mita of what I have loved
you I see mediquín, quacks of demons, to see which side Put them ... Well man! ...

Intervened all inclusive Neluco to calm him down, and calmed down soon, but not the least said
idea of ??preparing for death. On this point the doctor had been
very upset.

He said, bid farewell to Don Sabas was absent from the place, helping the dying of another people whose
pastor was ill. Upon hearing he had sent a self, but as to the people had many sticks on the way
to measure and the snow was thickening by the minute, although Don Sabas would try not to lose
one when he heard what was happening in the house, Were you to know what time the evening
was coming, and if you arrive on time and!

Not to get too close to the giant of the table Castañalera impressed him so sadly, ate with
him at all lazy in the kitchen, served by Tona, while his mother
kept the patient.

That was not so tasty food for me and I did not forget other, rather than so recent date,
so elated that made those two diners in the latter, somewhat out of respect for the sadness
'official' of the house, and more for the pain the reasons for the sadness that I gave, ate
little and spoke less.

Less talked about yet they, don Pedro Nolasco, who never said a word, but, instead, what engulf
his so great!

Before we finished eating, we learned from Facia the patient had fallen asleep again and that "the snow
was trapeu so again, that was gustu." I remembered the absence of Don Sabas and the need to made
by my uncle, and I received the news with much pleasure as felt by the mother to give me Tona.

According
ran the afternoon, clutching the storm and the anxieties of the patient, was still struggling with
them eyes closed and unaware, apparently, of what was happening. God knows what we are worried
that these symptoms and was eager to insinuate what Neluco wanted, since it is not anticipated
to hint at, but what good would Overture while we did not hand the Priest? These questions and
subsequent questions, was the dark, a little after four, with a trio of snow on the valley
and snow thick and continuous and was alarmed me much, because supposed to Don Sabas on the
way and thought the dangers that could run. Meanwhile, the kitchen is filled little by little people
came to hear of Don Celso and volunteer for all sorts of chores around the house in those test
hours, and I do not dislike me so well together on the occasion of
so much trouble.

A Don Pedro Nolasco was happening the same, and even began to talk with fellow members and Laughing
allowed certain predictions about the disease and almost bit old friend your soul ... precisely
at the moment my uncle out of his stupor and after persistent to tour the room with dazed eyes, said
to distress of breathing, as if you could fit in the chest and an
air bubble to another without having vacated the same:

- Now ...
now is to really leave, my children, and prepare to travel to every
rule.

Charity make me tell the priest that I call for what he knows ... if there is any of packages that
I distinguish badly from here, because I do not know if the little light in the room, or because
it has started to fade and my eyes ... Sabas! ... Sabas! ...

All those present heard and callábamos, and we looked at each other not knowing what to say.
How to tell the priest was not in the house or in town? ... But so what obfuscation absurd it
was! What problem was to entertain the impatience, responding who had come to tell and that
was about to arrive?

This was going to answer me the same time I approached his bed with
Lita and Mari-Pepa, made a sea of ??tears as Facia was leaning against
the back wall with his arms folded, head bent over chest and eyes,
dry, saddened and still, stuck in the face of his corpse master, when
he returned to exclaim, but with a verve inconceivable in its miserable
state:

- Sabas!

Sabas! ...

By this I heard a harsh beating, as the result of Carrejo in the Hall,
and at the same time a voice that would respond to strong calls:

-
There he goes, jinojo!

...

I knew the voice, jumped back to the door, and saw that the lounge was up package that the
same could be a mountain jaral as should be all those moments, a gauge and hombrazo talares
Don Sabas, for he was snowed head and shoulders and everywhere I looked out a relief, however
little, Espido in their long and garments, and go and shake the very attempt, threw in soil dusty
snow falls, as falls from Matos shakes and shakes when the raging gale. I went to meet him and
shake to help wipe ... nothing, because of two detached bativoleos floating everything dripped
on him. This was, in a jiffy, smooth and mondo from head to toe, that is, short jacket and hair.
While it was stripped of those wraps and accessories, he said:

- Ah! because thanks to the gray horse has more guts than Paez, and was able to footman that
I carried him halfway to the legs, if not ... Jinojo! I tell thee that we do not live none of
the three, because I have seen snow as I live, but like this, go, go! ... What happens to poor
Don Celso, man? When I went there I say, not me took fright, because I was afraid I was coming
every day. The worst part was that he dying person, not just unhappy, and it was not to abandon
him in such a trance ... Well Care if you get for not finishing in the afternoon of God ... To all
this, the snow thick and closed roads. Look you what time to put this one in the agony! ... If what
Satan JINCEN the tooth for the souls, is much story! A well that it was not for lack of mine
warnings, but this Celsus, to be as a man of faith, is inherently so ...

All that we said already, and I almost cried, the better the cure
to his bedroom door friend, where he interrupted a call disjointed
reasoning as before.

- Sabas!

Sabas!

- Here I am, man! "- Replied the priest -.

Care is the subject! ... Look, with the rush better Sallu not you have them now ...

- That's it - my uncle grumbled -. For comfort of my ajogos, tíñeme and vociférame, pispajo!

-
Do you have to fight, man, do you have to fight! - Don Sabas said to him then that face of those
miserable ruins of his friend and comrade of his life, failed to contain the tears that flowed in
his eyes - or how I will scream! ... Well then would Thus, jinojo! ... but as I came, I could not
come, because of force majeure. And just think you then! Figúratelo, Celso! ... Go - added suddenly
interrupting his speech and passing look around the room and accented with a movement of his
arms, very significant -: here on all but the patient and me, because
what will happen between us, not support one other witness, who is
Lord and Judge of lives and souls.

We leave those who don Sabas sobrábamos and closed the door from inside.

I do not know what went through me then, but I declare that I was very touched and even cried,
hiding much like a weakness unworthy of strong men.

They came the tears shameful "the spread of other more free? Were torn my heart with grief to
see that, my relative in a state so miserable and compassionate? Am the produce that strange
scene he had just witnessed between the priest and the sick, through whose coarse warp distances
left to seek grants and admirable? Might have on them some of each and every one of these ingredients,
but the fact is that I cried, but not as well as women who gathered
with me, as they were entering on tiptoe the room where we were many
of the pundits in the kitchen that had been amassed in Carrejo after
the arrival of the priest, transfixed with grief ... and curiosity.

Facia The light bulb had lit in the bedroom to get out of it, and still kept in hand, lit up a little darkened
those jaws, and so I could glimpse of clogged, materially, huddled figures and oscillating looked
at us with impatience greedy, and even I could have sworn that back in the background, behind
all the mass, but rising one elbow on the head of more Tallud glistened
like two lanterns in a tunnel, big eyes giant green and bulging of
the Castañalera.

XXVII

After a while I asked Mari Pepa many things which, in its view, would be necessary there very soon.
I, delegating to her and her daughter had many responsibilities at home delivered them to the few
keys which he kept, and sent to Facia to put on your orders the rest. To send well and soon they
planned, it was necessary to return commentators to the kitchen, scattered herds here or there,
all choked ... and stank, and there was no way to squirm between
them.

They did so to point at my command, and the two women began to raid cupboards, wardrobes and drawers.
Facia guided, and I was like an automaton at three.

While ransacked the bottom drawer of the dresser in my room, opened
the door to my uncle Don Sabas and appeared in the hole.

I noticed that out crying and ran to him fearing that already completed all there, but since
I heard coughing halfway to the sick, and this was reassuring. Salióme to meet the priest,
and he said, wiping her eyes with a handkerchief of grass:

- Can not help it, what jinojo! ... more than one is accustomed to contemplate miseries and human finishers
... Because there are cases and cases, Don Marcelo, and this is one of the peel harder for the
poor priest. Sixty years of living, more than friends, like brothers, and each in his ministry
... And care if it was his height! ... something rejunde in the bowels ... it seems to me ... Suddenly
he says to the other one: "I go, because I'm leaving ... and never to return: so you ajústame
these accounts that I have to give to God, through you Mesmer how much I owe and how little and
bad that I have paid ... and you stay here, man and alone, until you get yours, you can not
take because no one is old, and you'll see what is jallarte day after day without longtime friend,
who looked and flesh of your flesh and filled the whole place, although he did not see him
... " Nah, you go and, moreover, namely if getting one's own, and catch him or catch him Asao,
because the flesh is weak, and Satan not sleeping, and if, for shots or TATS, we find ourselves
not in the other world. Because it goes well for luggage ... Yes, jinojo! and right as a juso
has to raise the soul. At the human level can not be assumed otherwise, to the preparation
he has done, after a life of charity, that I know by heart ... In
short, that it is going, and that we should not sleep to make all
the missing in the trance you see ... You have to viatical immediately,
and for that I go to church now.

Note here that is expected God with the pomp that is owed.

They had taken their talares to the kitchen to dry by the fire, and the priest go to pick them
up made people gathered in her the same advice as I am, and then dragged him, Chisco and Pito
least Salces, who ordered me to stay "watching the house, what might happen. " Precautions
idle luxury at that hour (around seven), with a dark as pitch, dropping
handfuls of snow, and with a roaring gale up the mountain, which were
scary.

Without worrying much about the poor Marmitón, who was left alone again, lounging, dumb and
amazed at the wooden chair and very leaning to fire, and returned to the apartment of my uncle
see what was going on it after the departure of Don Sabas. It was already known anyone interior,
and even now continue to be transformed by the two tales of the house. In the bedside, the red
damask quilt of the great days, and back on it, the broad and embroidery fold of a sheet of luxury
pillows, with pockets of very large garrisons stiff and escarole, and the patient himself,
with camisole clean, heated just before the brazier and perfumed with thyme, on the elastic thick
coat that harbored the trunk, along to bed, a carpet mat instead of forever on the dresser, falling
in graceful flags on the sides, another quilt of good house, and on it, expecting better destination,
the ivory crucifix, six silver candlesticks, a glass of holy water
and a sprig bay.

When I arrived, they occupied the two women who appeared to be little devils in your hands,
to replace, helped to Facia, the junk that was always at the bedside, with a square table taken from
my closet, where I used to read and send my correspondence. Ofrecíles my help for that task, but
the disdain with gestecillo Lita very deliberate and two annealed complimentary phrases. While
it took the ailing Facia artifact, tended them on the table another red damask quilt and the
quilt on a very white piece of cloth with lace of many drafts, then moved to the comfortable
at the table the crucifix of ivory, four glass candlesticks and holy water and the sprig of laurel;
then another rug in front of the table, then all strips and arenas that were found to form a
path so long as he could, four beatings on chairs before them in order, a pat over the bed
clothes, a look from afar to the whole so many different things ...
and what was already shipped.

My uncle, meanwhile, gasping and coughing and passing among the gnarled fingers of his right hand
beads and more beads of the rosary, and pray that says through clenched teeth, not take notice
what was happening around him, or answer more than a gesture to the
smaller question vinegary that he did.

Before he died his body was already in another world with the spirit. God was, God was God's only
expected.

I finished fourth, another work was undertaken outside nastier, for which not enough single
women. Mari Pepa scattered on the floor quilts and shawls that had gathered looting and walked
in a mass on the chairs, Lita chose and combined colors and sizes, Salces Pete and I, perched
on tall furniture needed, clavábamos in walls, and as high as we could, studded with spikes ...
up with nails "Trabaderos" and how we could have at hand in the cellar
weep holes that Chisco accumulated stocks of this species, which the
diligent and poring granddaughter of giant Castañalera of us was exquisite
lengthening with his hands, as scattered on the floor</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>