<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10900</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>531658</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23676</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Llegaron los mensajeros y fueron recibidos con grande amor y cortesía, y fueron sentados á
la mesa del cacique, cuyas viandas se reducían á raíces de cardos silvestres, que era todo
su mantenimiento, y por gran regalo les ofrecieron un vaso de agua, porque había allí tal carestía,
que cada uno estaba esperando la suerte de poder coger tanta cuanta cabía en la palma de mano,
de un pequeño manantial que salía de un peñasco.

Dos días después se partieron los cristianos, acompañados del cacique principal, con otros
de los suyos, y encontrándose en el bosque con el P. Miguel, dieron la vuelta, y á 5 de Octubre
llegaron á donde el P. Zea el año antecedente había levantado la cruz.

Increíble fué el júbilo y la fiesta que hizo aquella buena gente, manifestando el gusto que
tenían de ver en sus países á nuestros Misioneros, diciendo en nombre de todos el cacique principal,
indio, por cierto digno de estimación, que no obstante sus grandes necesidades, hambres y pobreza
no se había apartado de su pueblo ni permitido que los suyos se alejasen por estar en continua
esperanza de que habían de ir los nuestros, habiendo enviado varias veces, y él mismo ido en
persona, á registrar los caminos para ver si parecían.

Igual fué también la alegría del P. Miguel que veía ya logrados los sudores del P. Zea, que
con tantos trabajos había empezado á plantar aquella viña, y para su fecundidad le llovía del
cielo copiosas bendiciones.

Trató luego con aquel cacique y con todos los demás principales, del fin de su ida á aquellos
pueblos, que era el fundar Reducción en sus tierras y quedarse con ellos; á cuyo fin les pidió
le diesen paso franco y guías para todos los demás pueblos, para escoger en ellos el que fuese
más acomodado para la fundación, y en particular hacia los que estaban al Poniente cercanos
á las salinas, donde habían informado al Padre había parajes muy buenos para pueblos, aguadas,
montañas y palmeras para estancias de ganados, interesándose en esto también el irse acercando
á los demás pueblos de los Chiquitos, con camino más derecho y más breve.

«Oyéndome el cacique (son palabras del Padre Miguel, en la carta para el P. Juan Patricio Fernández).
Oyéndome el cacique éstas y otras conveniencias, dió un grito y suspiró, diciendo:

»--Me tuviera por ingrato y vil, después de tantas finezas y estimación que habéis hecho de
mí, si en alguna cosa os mintiera y engañara, y negando lo que me pedís os desazonara; y aunque
no me queráis creer, os desengaño, Padre, de que en todas nuestras tierras no hallaréis parajes,
ni las comodidades que decís para fundar, pues lo mismo que véis y reconocéis en este mi pueblo,
sucede en todos los demás; y aunque en tiempo de lluvias, por causa de las avenidas, corren
algunas cañadas con abundancia de agua, mas pasados algunos meses no quedan más que las madres
secas, y sin agua, por lo cual luego nos desparramamos con nuestras chusmas á buscar qué comer
y qué beber.

»No obstante esta respuesta, le volví á instar con otras razones más eficaces que Nuestro Señor
me inspiró, que me dejase pasar siquiera á visitar al cacique de los pueblos del Poniente,
dándome guías y quien me abriese alguna senda para poder pasar á la ligera.

»Respondióme á esta petición el cacique:

»--Te aseguro, Padre, por el amor que te tengo, que si vas, tú y todos tus compañeros, pereceréis
de sed.»

Hasta aquí el P. Miguel, que oyendo esto se retiró aparte para encomendar á Nuestro Señor aquel
negocio.

Entonces el cacique juntó á todo el pueblo en la plaza y le reprendió con palabras muy sentidas
el que hubiese alguno de ellos mentido y engañado al P. Misionero con decirle que había en
sus tierras los parajes y comodidades ya dichas para fundación; y les añadió que quedaba muy
avergonzado de que hubiesen dado ocasión para que el Padre juzgase que él le engañaba, negándole
lo que ellos mismos tanto deseaban; y por fin mandó á todos que obedeciesen en todo á la voluntad
del P. Miguel. Estaba éste retirado en su Rancho, rogando á Nuestro Señor que no se frustrase
esta fundación y Reducción de todo el gentío cercano y encomendando á Su Majestad la resolución
que tomaría en este caso.

Luego supo por medio del intérprete, que había estado oyendo de secreto al cacique, todo el
razonamiento que éste había hecho á los suyos en la plaza.

«Con lo cual (prosigue el Padre en su relación) me determiné á proponerles si gustarían de
fundar y juntarse para este efecto fuera de sus montañas y al remate de las campañas de las
Japeras de los Cucarates, por ser tierras muy cabales para una fundación, aunque sólo de paso
vistas y registradas con ánimo (si viniesen en ello) de registrarlo mejor á la vuelta, trayendo
alguno de ellos conmigo para ver los parajes.

»Llamé de allí á un rato al cacique y le propuse todo esto; á que sin dejarme pasar adelante,
con grande algazara respondió que era grande elección, y que ya había estado y visto todas
aquellas campañas, y que le parecieron muy buenas y á propósito para el fin, y que me siguiera
luego con toda su gente y todos los demás pueblos vecinos, á no tener todos sus zapallares
ya en flor y muchos que ya comenzaban á dar, y que no sembrarían otra cosa, sino que en acabando
los juntaría y convocaría toda aquella gente, y se vendría luego al sitio que yo dejase señalado
para el pueblo, y enviaría conmigo alguno de los principales para que registrasen y viesen
el puesto para dicho pueblo; y en volviendo á darles cuenta de lo visto, tomaría luego el camino
para aquel paraje.

»Con esto resolví volverme después de dos días, porque no había agua que beber; y en estos
dos días que estuve allí, fué forzoso beber de unos charquitos que se habían juntado en una
cañada, una legua del pueblo, de un aguacero que cayó, que más era barro que agua; y de una
poca que ellos tenían recogida, llovediza, en unos calabazos, nos dieron uno, por gran fineza,
y vendido por un poco de maíz.

»Poco después que se sosegaron los del pueblo, cerrada ya la noche, vino el cacique, acompañado
con algunos viejos, á pedirme audiencia junto á mi toldo; y dándoles asiento por señal de alegría
y albricias, me dijo el cacique:

»--Padre, no te aflijas, que después del año en que se haya poblado el sitio que nos señalares,
iré con la gente de este mi pueblo hacia el Sur, en tres días de camino de montaña, á traer
y convidar á otra provincia de Zamucos (con quienes antiguamente estábamos amigos y quebramos
con ellos) que son diez pueblos de tanto número como nosotros; y de ahí á un día de camino,
en que remata la montaña y comienzan las campañas, está innumerable gentío que llega hasta
á los pueblos que llamamos nosotros de los españoles. Estos guerrean siempre con esta otra
provincia de Zamucos, que se llaman Ugaroñós (de los cuales hay uno en este pueblo de San Juan,
que antiguamente vino con sus padres á esta otra provincia, y de ahí á los Morotocos; y cuando
andaba con los Padres, llegó á ver todo ese gentío, que es el Chaco, y á un lado algunos pueblos
de Guarayos.) Agradecíle sumamente las noticias al cacique, quien volvió á añadir estaban contentísimos
con el paraje que les había insinuado, muy á propósito para poder desde ahí con más facilidad
y brevedad penetrar hasta las naciones dichas, pues desde más lejos había venido yo á sus tierras
y pueblos; y dándome otras noticias de otros gentíos por diversos rumbos, se despidió para
irse á descansar.»

Así el P. Miguel; el cual, queriendo al otro día despedirse de ellos, se levantó una gritería
y llanto de toda la gente, á quien el deseo del santo bautismo no daba aliento para ver partir
al Padre Misionero; mas dándoles palabra de que cuanto antes los volvería á ver, se quietaron;
y levantadas al cielo las manos, pedían á Dios les diese feliz viaje y que volviese presto.

Partióse, finalmente, echando mil bendiciones á aquel pueblo, tan deseoso de recibir la santa
fe, trayéndose en su compañía aquellos Zamucos enviados de su cacique; y reconocido el país
de los Cucarates, pasó á San Juan Bautista, donde los neófitos recibieron y acogieron á los
dos cathecúmenos con extraordinario afecto, tratándolos con aquellas cortesías que el celo
del bien de sus almas y el amor á Dios dictan á los que son nuevos en la santa fe.

Llegó, pues, de vuelta de los Zamucos al pueblo de San Juan á 26 de Octubre de aquel mismo
año de 1718 y luego participó las noticias de todo lo referido en este capítulo al Padre Visitador
de aquellas Misiones, Juan Patricio Fernández, quien atribuyendo á singular misericordia de
Dios y á los méritos y sudores del apostólico P. Zea que aquellos bárbaros estuviesen tan deseosos
del santo bautismo y tan contentos y prontos á dejar sus tierras hizo luego despachar los dos
Zamucos que trajo el P. Miguel de Yegros, con aviso al cacique de que se fuese con todos sus
vasallos á las tierras de los Cucarates, porque en breve se partiría allá el P. Miguel con
el hermano Alberto Romero.

¡Quién creyera que una obra, encaminada con tantos trabajos y sudores y con tanta felicidad,
de donde resultaría á Dios grande gloria y á la iglesia mucho número de fieles, se destruyese
en un momento, y de tal manera, que hasta ahora no se les ha podido reducir, bien que siempre
se intenta!

La causa de esta novedad la atribuyen todos á la natural inconstancia é inestabilidad de los
indios; mas si yo á este común sentir pudiese añadir el mío particular, diría que ha tenido
más alta causa este infeliz suceso; porque siendo la conversión de las almas obra principalmente
de Dios, deja Su Majestad muchas veces que las industrias humanas, y la virtud de los medios
que ponemos, no surtan efecto, para que desconfiados nosotros de ellos, atribuyamos á sola
la virtud de su gracia aquellos sucesos que efectuándose prósperamente, sería fácil cosa nos
los atribuyésemos á nosotros mismos.

Mas sea lo que fuere de esto, salieron por Agosto de 1719 el P. Miguel de Yegros y el hermano
Alberto, llevando todo recado para celebrar la Misa y lo demás necesario para fundar la iglesia
de la nueva Reducción de San Ignacio Nuestro padre, llegando á la campaña que los Zamucos habían
escogido para fundarla, no hallaron persona alguna; y enviando algunos por todas partes para
tomar noticia de esta gente, hallaron su pueblo quemado, y supieron que se había retirado algunas
jornadas lejos de allí, junto á una laguna abundante de pesca, cerrando los pasos por donde
se les podía seguir.

Resolvió ir en persona el hermano Alberto en su seguimiento á buscarlos, como lo hizo, y habiéndolos
encontrado, los reconvino con la palabra que habían dado á Dios y á los Padres de querer ser
cristianos y vivir juntos en un pueblo, en el lugar que ellos mismos habían escogido y señalado.

Hiciéronle al principio buen semblante los bárbaros y con muestras de alegría fingieron querer
estar á lo prometido; y en señal de eso, se encaminaron con él hacia el sitio señalado, encubriendo
entre tanto en el corazón su premeditada alevosía, y por muchos días fueron entreteniendo con
buenas palabras al hermano que procuraba, con todas las finezas de su gran caridad, ganarles
las voluntades con beneficios. Al fin se quitaron la máscara el día 1.º de Octubre, y muertos
á traición doce cristianos, un infame cacique asió de la garganta al santo hermano y con el
filo de una pesada macana le partió la cabeza, despojóle después bárbaramente, y de miedo de
que no viniesen sobre ellos á vengar aquella muerte los Chiquitos, se huyeron todos juntos,
sin saberse dónde.

El P. Miguel, avisado de este suceso por dos cristianos que por gran ventura se pudieron escapar
del estrago, se volvió con increíble dolor de su corazón por no poder hacer más; y divulgada
por todos los pueblos la nueva de la muerte del santo hermano, le lloraron inconsolablemente
los indios, los cuales, en recompensa de las buenas obras que de él habían recibido, le celebraron
solemnes exequias en todos sus pueblos, cuanto cupo, y fué posible en su pobreza; y yo, para
acabar este capítulo, daré aquí una breve noticia de su vida y virtudes, por serle muy debida
esta memoria.

Fué el hermano Alberto Romero de nación español y natural de Segovia, hijo de padres honrados
y de profesión mercader, bien acomodado; mas deseoso de ver tierras y hacer mayor fortuna,
pasó con otros mercaderes Perú, esperando hallar aquí fortuna igual á sus deseos.

No le salieron fallidas sus esperanzas, porque adquirió buen caudal y fué de todos muy estimado;
y así la Real Audiencia como el arzobispo de Chuquisaca, le cometieron negocios de mucha monta
para bien público; mas como sea tan ordinario en las cosas humanas el hacerse y deshacerse
en un punto, mudando semblante á cada paso la fortuna, sin durar mucho en un estado, ya sea
próspera, ya adversa, siendo sólo semejante á sí misma, en ser siempre inconstante, habiendo
estado siempre para nuestro Alberto risueña y propicia, experimentó en sí estas mudanzas; porque
de repente, no sé por qué causa, si ya no fuese para que levantase sus deseos á las cosas del
cielo, cayó desplomada á tierra la gran máquina de su prosperidad.

En poco tiempo perdió todo lo que en muchos años, y á costa de grandes fatigas había adquirido,
con que quedó reducido á mucha pobreza, mas no sin ganancia, porque con este golpe volvió en
sí, y viéndose ya anciano, sin tener en la tierra riquezas ni méritos para el cielo, se dolió
mucho de lo mal que había empleado su corazón en ganar y adquirir bienes caducos, sin quedarle
de tanto tiempo perdido más que un perpetuo remordimiento del mal logro de sus años.

Por tanto, resolvió darse todo á Dios, al cuidado de su alma y á las cosas de la eternidad,
gastando, como más próvido mercader, el resto de su vida en el tráfico de bienes no sujetos
á mudanzas y reveses de la fortuna, en lo cual tuvo mejor logro que cuando en el mundo navegaba
su prosperidad viento en popa.

Y Dios, que muchas veces se agrada más de los que vienen á trabajar en su viña á la última
hora, que los que desde la primera hora del día echan mano á la labor, se agradó sobremanera
de su determinación, y le dió luego de contado una plenitud de consuelo en su servicio, por
prenda de galardón que sobre todos sus méritos le tenía preparado aquí en la tierra, y después
eternamente en el cielo.

Por aquel tiempo, algunos piadosos españoles, recogiendo de los vecinos de Tarija algunas limosnas,
enviaban todos los años un copioso socorro á la cristiandad de los Chiquitos y á los Misioneros
lo necesario para celebrar el santo sacrificio de la misa, y hacer con toda la devoción posible
las funciones sagradas.

Con esta provisión le enviaron una vez nuestros Padres del colegio de Tarija, con quienes él
trataba familiarmente, y luego le pagó Dios aquella caridad muy largamente.

Porque considerando el fervor y santa vida de los nuevos cristianos y las apostólicas fatigas
de los obreros evangélicos, que con vivir en semejantes trabajos, á los que de sí escribe el
Apóstol San Pablo, estaban siempre alegres y con una boca de risa, se mudó en otro hombre y
se le inflamó el corazón en vivísimos deseos de unirse más estrechamente con Dios, y gastar
su vida en servicio de aquella nueva cristiandad, y de hecho dió luego muestras de cuán de
veras lo decía.

Púsose luego á enseñar á los indios todos los oficios mecánicos, á desmontar los bosques, á
labrar la tierra y á manejar los arados para cultivarla; con los enfermos, viejos y estropeados,
tenía entrañas y ternura de madre; no había cosa que por ellos no hiciese; con los bárbaros
que se convertían de nuevo, se deshacía en afectos de caridad, no sabía apartarse de su lado,
parecía que se los quería meter dentro del corazón; y por bárbaros que fuesen, no dejaba de
hacer con ellos semejantes demostraciones, no mirando en ellos lo que parecían en el exterior,
sino el valor de sus almas, compradas por el Redentor con el precio de toda su sangre.

Ni por trabajar tanto por las almas de sus prójimos se descuidaba de la suya propia; recogíase
muchas veces á tener oración, en el cual tiempo las copiosas lágrimas que derramaba, eran indicios
de los consuelos con que Dios confortaba su espíritu.

Y á la verdad era bien necesario este consorte celestial para darle ánimo y aliento en la dura
y continuada batalla con el enemigo infernal, que dolorido fuertemente de que un viejo idiota
y sin letras corriese por el camino de la más alta perfección y se burlase de él quitándole
tantas almas de sus manos, no le dejaba de perseguir de día ni de noche, ya apareciéndole en
forma de feísimos animales, ya espantándosele con otras visiones abominables.

Duró esta terrible persecución más de tres años; mas nuestro Alberto, asistido siempre de Dios
y del ángel de su guarda, que si no estaba á su lado en forma visible, á lo menos lo estaba
con la invisible operación en su corazón, jamás se dió por vencido, ni omitió las acostumbradas
obras de caridad, ni dió un paso atrás en el modo de vivir que había emprendido.

Y por ventura, en premio de esta generosa constancia, se le encendió el corazón en vivos deseos
de entrar en la Compañía, que amaba tiernísimamente; mas atendida su mucha edad, era necesaria
la licencia de nuestro Padre General, la que no se podía tan presto alcanzar; por lo cual,
para consolar en parte sus plegarias y sus lágrimas, el P. Vice Provincial Luis de la Roca,
cuando visitó aquellas Misiones, le admitió por Donado hasta que viniese de Roma la licencia
de recibirle por hermano Coadjutor de la Compañía; pero el cielo le firmó más presto esta licencia,
y la Compañía triunfante le contó en el número de aquellos campeones que bordaron la librea
de Cristo con su propia sangre, antes que acá en la tierra le contase la militante en el número
de aquéllos, que con los ministerios humildes de su estado la ayudan á la conversión de las almas.

CAPÍTULO XX

Progresos y aumentos de otras REDUCCIONES en los años de 1717 y 1718.

Aunque lo que he escrito en estos dos capítulos últimos, ha sucedido en muchos años y en este
tiempo se han convertido á la fe y ganado para el cielo muchos centenares de infieles, todavía,
por no confundir los sucesos y Misiones de las Reducciones, los quise separar con ánimo de
referir ahora y dar noticia del fervor y mérito de los neófitos de las otras tierras, dignándose
Dios Nuestro Señor de premiar sus sudores con abundante cosecha de infieles para animarlos
á trabajar con mayor aliento y fervor en servicio de la iglesia.

Los cristianos, pues, de la Reducción de San Francisco Xavier, hicieron Misión por dos partes
diversas.

Algunos Zamalos salieron en busca de unos infieles, que habían hallado los años pasados y los
habían dejado de recoger por falta Guarayos, donde fueron bien recibidos; y aunque no se entendían,
les hablaron por señas y movieron á algunos á seguirlos y á recibir el santo bautismo.

Otros, de nación Piñocas, quisieron ir á los Puyzocas, que mataron al P. Lucas Caballero mas
apenas lo pudieron conseguir, porque en el camino entraron en una Ranchería de los Cozocas,
tan de improviso, que sentidos de los paisanos, que estaban trabajando en sus sementeras, y
creyendo ser gente enemiga, se dieron á huir á toda furia por librar la vida; los nuestros
alcanzaron á algunos, y entrando en la Ranchería la hallaron desierta, sin persona viviente.

Vieron en los Ranchos muchos escudos, tejidos de plumas de bellísimos colores con mucho arte
é industria; con éstos estaban adornadas las cámaras donde estaban amontonados muchos huesos
de difuntos y pedazos de carne fresca, indicios de que eran comedores de carne humana.

Andan todos bien vestidos y tienen las mismas costumbres que los Baures y Cosiricas, bien que
usan de diferente lengua. Entre grandes y pequeños recogieron 36.

Los cristianos del pueblo de la Concepción fueron á predicar la ley de Cristo á los Cosiricas,
mas no sacaron más logro que los trabajos.

Dos años antes habían ido á su Ranchería y habían traído cuatro para que viesen las Reducciones,
en donde fueron recibidos con grande amor y cortesía.

Estos dos fueron con los neófitos para llevarlos á sus paisanos, de quienes no fueron admitidos
con mucho afecto, porque el demonio les puso en sospecha de que eran Mamalucos ú otros enemigos
que habían venido á hacerlos esclavos. No obstante, los sentaron á la mesa y les presentaron
algunos regalos del país; mas concurriendo allí indios de otras tierras, los cercaron en forma
de media luna, disparándoles una tempestad de flechas para hacerlos huir; los neófitos, sin
hacer más que reparar los golpes, se retiraron con buen orden, y en medio de que muchos hacían
instancia á los capitanes para responderles con las armas, venció la parte de los mejores,
que, á imitación del Redentor, no quisieron volverles mal por mal; tres quedaron muertos; los
otros, maltratados, se volvieron á la Reducción.

De San Rafael salieron por dos partes en busca de almas; una tropa de Taus ganó á la fe cuatrocientos
y ochenta infieles, de nación Bacusones.

La otra, de Tabicas, fué á las riberas del río Paraguay en busca de Curucanes.

Apenas llegaron á orillas del río, cuando un Chiquito con algunos otros, se adelantó, y descubriendo
una canoa que venía hacia ellos, se escondieron detrás de algunos matorrales, creyendo ser
los infieles que buscaban; mas observando que era un negro con dos indios, que andaban pescando,
gritaron los compañeros del Chiquito: ¡Mamalucos! ¡Mamalucos! y se pusieron en fuga precipitada.

Apenas el negro vió sólo al Chiquito, cuando le apuntó con el arcabuz; mas se detuvo en dispararle,
porque el indio le gritó en voz alta: No me mates, que soy cristiano como tú y no te hago daño;
y para que lo conociese más claramente, le mostró una imagen de Nuestra Señora con el Niño
en los brazos, la cual, el negro, dejando el arcabuz, adoró de rodillas.

Juntáronse luego allí nuestros neófitos en número de ciento y cincuenta, extendidos en buen
orden sobre la ribera.

En este ínterin vino el Capitán de los Mamalucos, y llamando á un Chiquito que entendía la
lengua Guaraní, le preguntó quiénes eran y á qué fin andaban por aquellas costas.

Respondió que eran hijos de nuestros Misioneros (esta es la frase que usan ellos con los que
les han reducido á la fe) y cristianos del pueblo de San Rafael, que andaban en busca de infieles
para conducirlos al gremio de la santa madre iglesia.

--Para el mismo fin los buscamos nosotros,--respondió el capitán Mamaluco; y añadió en ademán
de enojado:

--¿Y por qué venís aquí si nosotros hemos llevado ya todos los infieles?

Preguntóle después qué Padre le instruía y enseñaba la fe y quién venía con ellos.

Dijo que el P. Felipe Suárez, era cura de su pueblo, mas que ellos iban solos.

--Y, pues,--replicó el Mamaluco--¿qué capitanes y conductores os gobiernan?

Aquellos, con astucia más que de indios, les respondieron que sus capitanes eran sesenta. Entonces,
vuelto á los suyos, les dijo el Mamaluco:

--Mucha gente tienen éstos alistada; y sin hablar más, haciendo tocar á retirada, se embarcó
con todos los suyos en las canoas, huyendo á todo vogar, por no venir á las manos con tanta
gente; y quiera el cielo que así como los cristianos Guaranís, de mucho tiempo á esta parte
son el terror de estos crueles enemigos, así lo sean también los Chiquitos reducidos á la fe
y al gobierno civil. Los neófitos, alegres con el buen logro de su astucia, anduvieron mucho
trecho por aquella ribera, hasta que finalmente dieron con la Ranchería de los Curucanes, donde
siendo bien recibidos, se pusieron todos en la plaza, de rodillas, á rezar el Rosario de Nuestra
Señora para que Su Majestad diese á aquellos gentiles juicio (frase con que se explican cuando
hacen oración por sí ó por otros á Nuestro Señor y á la Santísima Virgen) para que todos abrazasen
la santa ley de Dios.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06600</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>99628</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21549</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Messengers arrived and were received with great love and courtesy, and were seated at the table
of the chief, whose tubers were reduced to wild thistle roots, which was all maintenance,
and great gift offered them a glass of water, because there was such a shortage, everyone was waiting
for the lucky to get so much fit in the palm of hand a small spring coming out of a cliff.

Two days later, the Christian left, accompanied by the principal chief, with other of their
own, and being in the forest with P. Miguel, turned, and to October 5 arrived at where Fr Zea had
raised the year before the cross.

Was incredible joy and celebration that made those good people, expressing the pleasure they see in their
countries for our missionaries, saying on behalf of all the principal chief, Indian, certainly worthy
of esteem, that despite their greater need, hunger and poverty section had not allowed his people
or his people moved away from being in continuous hope that our people had to go, having sent
several times, and he went on person to record the paths to see if
they looked.

Same was also the joy of P. I saw Miguel and sweats made of P. Zea,
which with so many jobs that had begun to plant a vineyard, and it
rained for fertility of sky abundant blessings.

Then treated with one boss and all the other major, the end of his going to those peoples, which
was the reduction in their land base and keep them asked for which purpose give him free passage
and guidelines for all other peoples, to pick at them which was wealthier for the foundation,
and in particular to those who were closest to the West to the salt flats, where they had informed
the Father had very good places for people, gouache, mountains and
palm trees for stays of cattle, being interested in this also go closer
to the other peoples of the Chiquitos, with the right path and shorter.

"The

chief hearing me (words of the Father Miguel, in the letter to Father Juan Patricio Fernández). Listening
to me the chief of these and other conveniences, gave a cry and sighed, saying:

"- I had to ungrateful and mean, after so many subtleties and estimate that you have made me, if
something you lie and deceive, and deny what you're asking me annoy you, and although ye believe
not me, you the truth, Father, that in all our lands will not find places, and the amenities you
say to found, as the same as you see and recognize in this my people happens in all others,
and even in the rainy season, because of the floods, are some canyons with plenty of water, but
after a few months there are more than mothers dry, without water, so then we spread with our
mob to find what to eat and drink.

"Despite this response, I again urged other reasons more effective
than our Lord inspired me to let me pass even to visit the cacique
of the peoples of the West, giving me guidance and who opened a path
for me to go to the light.

"He replied to this request the chief:

"- I assure you, Father, for
the love I have for you, if you go, you and all your colleagues, perish
of thirst.

"

So much for the P. Michael, who heard this and went aside to commend to our Lord that business.

Then
the chief all the people gathered in the square and heartfelt words rebuked which one of them
had lied and deceived the P. Mission to say he had in their land and such places and facilities
for the foundation, and they said that was very ashamed that had given occasion for the Father judges
that he was deceiving him, denying what they both wanted, and finally sent to all who obey in all
things will Fr Miguel. While he was retired to his ranch, praying to Our Lord who is not frustrated
Reducing this foundation and all the crowd close and committed to his Majesty's resolution which
would in this case.

Later learned through the interpreter, who had been hearing from the
chief secret, the whole reasoning that he had done to his people in
the square.

"With which (continuing the Father in their relationship), I determined to propose if would like
to establish and join for this purpose out of the mountains and the auction of the campaigns of
Japeras of Cucarates, being very sane land for a foundation, but
only in passing registered views and mind (if they came at it) to
register it better to return, bringing some of them with me to see
the sites.

"I called from there to the chief a while and I suggested all this, to go ahead without me, responded
with great jubilation that was great choice, and he'd been and seen all those campaigns, and
that seemed very good and calculated to the end and follow me then with his people and all other
neighboring villages, to not have all zapallares already in bloom and many had already begun to
give, and not sow anything but that ending would put together and convened the all those people,
and would then leave the site I mentioned for the people, and send me one of the main register and
they saw the place for such people, and give them back what has been,
then the road would to that place.

"With that he decided to return after two days because there was no water to drink, and in these
two days I was there, was forced to drink a few puddles that had gathered in a Glen, a league
from the village, a rain that fell, which was more mud than water,
and a they had little collection, rainwater, in a few pumpkins, we
got one, very fine, and sold some corn.

"Shortly after the people were quieted, it was quite dark, came the
chief, accompanied with some old, to ask me sitting next to my tent,
and seat giving a sign of joy and reward, "said the chief:

"- Father,
do not worry, that after the year that has populated the site to point
out to us, go with the people of this my village to the south in three
days of mountain road, to bring and invite Zamucos to another province
(with whom formerly were friends and we broke with them) that are
ten villages in both number and us, and from there back to a day's
journey, that crowns the mountain and begin campaigns is reaches innumerable
crowd to the people who call us from the Spanish.

These wars always with this other Zamucos province, called Ugaroñós (of which there is one in this
town of San Juan, that once came with his parents to the other province, and from there to
the Morotocos, and when was with the Padres, came to see all the crowd, which is the Chaco, and
some towns on one side Guarayos.) Agradecíle very news the chief, who again were thrilled to
add with the place that they had suggested, well adapted to power more easily from there and
soon penetrate to those nations, as the farthest I had come to their land and villages, and
giving me more news in other crowds in different directions, said goodbye to go to rest. "

Thus P. Miguel, who, loving the other day saying goodbye to them, there arose a clamor and tears
of all people, to whom the desire of the holy baptism was not encouraging to see from Missionary Father,
but by giving them word that as soon see them again, it still; and hands raised to heaven, asking
God to give them safe journey and return quickly.

Departed, finally, casting a thousand thanks to those people, so willing
to receive Holy faith, and brought in his company who Zamucos sent
their chief, and recognized the country of Cucarates, went to San
Juan Bautista, where the neophytes received and welcomed to the two
catechumens with extraordinary affection, those treating them with
courtesy and zeal the good of their souls and the love of God dictate
to those who are new to the holy faith.

, Then, arrived back from
the Zamucos the people of San Juan to October 26 of that same year
1718 and then took the news of everything mentioned in this chapter
to the Father Visitor of those missions, Juan Patricio Fernandez,
who attributed to singular mercy God and the merits and sweats to
the Apostolic P. Zea barbarians were so eager of holy baptism, and
so happy and ready to leave their land was then dispatched two Zamucos
brought Fr Miguel de Yegros, with notice to the chief of which was
with all vassals to the lands of Cucarates, because there soon would
break Fr Miguel, brother Alberto Romero.

Who would believe that a work, directed with much work and sweat and with so much happiness, where
it would be great glory to God and the church lot number of the faithful,
is destroyed at a time, and so, so far not been able to reduce, rather
than always you try!

The cause of this new attribute it all to the natural fickleness and instability of Indians,
but if I am against this common sense could add my own particular, I would say it has had
highest cause this unfortunate event, for being the conversion of
souls mainly work God, let Your Majesty many times the human industries,
and the power of the media that we do not take effect for us suspicious
of them attributed to single virtue of his grace those events to be
made prosperous, it would be an easy thing we those to be attributed
to ourselves.

But whatever it is that, left in August 1719 by Fr Miguel de Yegros and brother Alberto, bringing
all message to celebrate Mass and everything else necessary to support the church Reduction of the
new San Ignacio Our father, coming to the campaign that had Zamucos chosen to base it did not
find anyone, and sending some to everywhere take notice of these people, they found his burned
village, and knew that he had withdrawn some days away, beside a lagoon abundant fishing,
closing steps where they could follow.

Decided to go in person in his brother Albert to look up, as he did, and having encountered, remonstrated
with the word they had given to God and want to be Padres Christians
and live together in a village in the place they had chosen and marked.

They

put a good face at first the barbarians and feigned wanting signs of joy be to the promise, and
that signal, they walked with him to the designated site, covering up between both the heart
and its premeditated treachery, and many days were entertained with good words to the brother who
tried, with all the subtleties of his great charity beat wills with benefits. Finally the mask
is removed on day 1. First of October, and dead treacherously twelve Christians, an infamous
chief grabbed the throat to the holy brother and the edge of a heavy baton split his head, then
stripped him savagely, and fear of not to come upon them to avenge
this death the Chiquitos, fled together, without knowing where.

Fr Miguel, warned of this event by two Christians who by good fortune was able to escape the havoc,
he turned with great pain in his heart for not being able to do more, and disclosed by all peoples
the news of the death of the holy brother, he wept inconsolably Indians, who, as a reward for good
deeds that he had received, he held solemn funeral in all its peoples, the quota, and was possible
in their poverty, and I, for finish this chapter, give here a brief
account of his life and virtues, because it is very appropriate herein.

Alberto

Romero was the brother of the Spanish nation and native of Segovia, the son of honest parents and occupation
merchant, well settled, but eager to see land and make more fortune Peru went with other merchants,
hoping to find this fortune equal to his wishes.

Not left their hopes failed because acquired great wealth and was highly esteemed by all; and so the
Royal Court as the Archbishop of Chuquisaca, he rides a lot of businesses committed for public
good, but as is so common in the human things done and get rid at one point, changing face at
every turn of fortune, not last long in a state either prosperous and adverse, being just like
himself, to be always unstable, having Alberto always been our cheerful and supportive, experienced
themselves these moves, because suddenly, I do not know for what reason, if it was not to raise
their desires to the things of heaven, earth sank down to the great machine of its prosperity.

Soon
he lost all that many years, and at the expense of great difficulty
had acquired that was reduced to great poverty, but not without profit,
because this blow turned yes, and seeing an old man, without wealth
or merit earth to heaven, is hurt much of the wrong he had used his
heart to win and buy goods obsolete, without being this time lost
more than a perpetual remorse achieve their bad years.

Therefore decided to give everything to God, the care of his soul and to the things of eternity,
spending, most provident merchant, the rest of his life in the smuggling of goods not subject to removals
and reversals of fortune, which had better achievement when the sailing world booming prosperity.

And
God, which is often more like those who come to work in the vineyard to the final hour than the
first hour of the day to dig into the work, is extremely pleased
their determination, and gave him cash after a fulness of comfort
in his service, garment award for all his merits he was prepared on
earth, and then eternally in heaven.

At that time, some pious Spanish, collected from the residents of
Tarija some alms, sent every year a generous relief to the Christianity
of the Chiquitos and the Missionaries you need to celebrate the Holy
Sacrifice of the Mass and devotion to do with all possible sacred
functions.

With this provision once sent him our Fathers of the College of Tarija, with whom he was familiar,
and then paid that love God very long.

Because considering the fervor and holy life of the new Christian and apostolic labors the evangelical
workers, that live in such work, to them that writes itself St. Paul, were always cheerful and
a mouth with laughter, moved to another man and is vivid inflamed
heart desires to be more intimately with God, and spend his life in
service of this new Christianity, and indeed gave then sampling of
how really said it.

Then stood to teach the Indians all mechanical trades, to clear forests, to work the land and
to manage the plows to cultivate, with the sick, old and disabled, had guts and tenderness of
a mother, there was nothing that they would not do, with the barbarians
who became again, fell apart in the affections of charity, did not
know leave her side, appeared that one wanted to get into the heart,
and barbarians they were, kept Similar demonstrations to do with them,
not looking at them what appeared abroad but the value of their souls,
the Redeemer bought with the price of all his blood.

Not for work both for the souls of their neighbors was neglected in his own, collected many times
to have prayer, at which time the copious tears shed were indications
the consolations with which God comforted his spirit.

And indeed it was very necessary this celestial consort to give courage and encouragement in
the tough and continuing battle with the infernal enemy, which strongly aching like an old fool
and no letters running down the road to the highest perfection and
mocked by removing so many souls in their hands, would not allow him
to pursue the day or night, is already in feis form of animals, and
other visions espantándosele abominable.

This terrible persecution lasted more than three years, but our Alberto, God always attended and
her guardian angel, that if his side was not visibly, at least it
was the invisible operation on his heart, never gave up, nor missed
the usual charities, and took a step backwards in the way of life
he had undertaken.

And perhaps, in this generous award from the record, he lit the living heart desires joining the
Company, he loved very tender, but in view of its great age, it was necessary License our Father
General, which could not be reached so quickly, therefore, partly to console her prayers and
tears, Fr Provincial Vice Luis de la Roca, when he visited those missions, he admitted for
the Donated until the license came from Rome to welcome a brother Coadjutor of the Company,
but the sky more quickly signed him this license, and the Company
triumphantly told the number of those champions who boarded the livery
of Christ with his own blood, rather than here on earth he would tell
the militant in the number of those, who with humble ministries of
state aid for the conversion of souls.

CHAPTER XX

Developments and other reductions increases in the years 1717 and 1718.

Although I have written in these two last chapters, it has happened
in many years and in this time have turned to faith and livestock
to the sky many hundreds of infidels, yet not to confuse the events
and missions of the reductions, I wanted to separate with the intention
of and now turn would report the fervor and merit of the neophytes
of the other lands, deigning Lord God reward your sweats with abundant
harvest of unbelievers to encourage to work more encouragement and
enthusiasm in service of the church.

Christians, therefore, the reduction of San Francisco Xavier Mission
made up of two parts different.

Some ZAMALA went looking for some infidels, who had found the past years and had stopped collecting
for lack Guarayos, where they were welcomed, and although not understood, they made signs to
them and moved some to follow and to receive the holy baptism.

Others Piñocas nation, wanted to go to the Puyzocas, killing at P. Lucas Knight more barely
could get, because the way they entered a village of Cozocas, so suddenly, that sense of the peasants,
who were working in their fields, and People believed to be enemy
to flee were furiously to rid the life of us amounted to some, and
entering the Ranching found it empty, and no living person.

Seen in the Ranchos many shields, feathers woven beautiful colors with lots of art and industry,
they were adorned with cameras where they were piled many bones the dead and pieces of fresh
meat, evidence they were man-eaters.

Walk all dressed up and have the same customs as the Baures and Cosiricas, though use a different
language. Between large and small gathered 36.

Christians in the town of Concepcion was to preach the law of Christ
to the Cosiricas, but no more I took the job.

Two years earlier had gone to their village and brought four for them to see the reductions, where
they were received with great love and kindness.

These two were with the neophytes to bring to his countrymen, who were not admitted With great
affection, because the devil put them in suspicion that they were
Mamalucos or other enemies who had come to make them slaves.

However, sat at the table and presented them some gifts in the country, but there exist for other
Indian lands, encompassed in a half-moon, shooting a storm of arrows
to make them flee, the newborns without do more to repair the shock,
retreated in good order, and half that many were instance the captains
to respond with weapons, beat the part of the best, that imitation
of the Redeemer, unwilling to return evil for evil, three were dead,
the others, abused, returned to the reduction.

San Rafael came by two parties in search of souls, a troop of Taus
won to the faith four and eighty infidels Bacusones nation.

The other, risers, went to the banks of the Paraguay River in search of Curucanes.

When they arrived on the banks of the river when a little boy with
some others, came forward, and discovering a canoe coming toward them,
they hid behind some bushes, thinking he seeking the infidels, but
noting that it was a black man with two Indians, who were fishing,
Chiquito mates shouted: Mamalucos!

Mamalucos! and drove them headlong.

Just saw black Chiquito only when he pointed his musket, but stopped
shooting, because the Indian shouted out loud: Do not kill me, I am
a Christian like you and do not do any harm; and knew that more clearly
showed an image of Our Lady and Child in the arms, which, black, leaving
the musket, adored knees.

Then our neophytes were assembled there in number one hundred and fifty, issued in good order on
the bank.

In the interim came the Captain of the Mamalucos, and calling to one
who understood Chiquito Guarani language, asked who they were and
to what end they went for those costs.

Replied that they were children of our missionaries (this is the phrase that they use with which
reduced them to the faith) and Christians from the village of San Rafael, who were looking for
infidels to lead the guild of the holy mother church.

- For the same reason we look for us, - said the captain Mamaluco, and added in a gesture of
anger:

- Why come here if we have taken and all infidels?

Father asked him then what you instructed and taught the faith and
who came with them.

Said Fr Felipe Suarez, was a priest of his people, but they were alone.

- And, then, - said the Mamaluco - what captains and drivers govern you?

Those with cunning rather than Indians, they responded that their captains were sixty. So returned
to their own, they said Mamaluco:

- Many people have enrolled them, and without speaking again, by playing
to retirement, he embarked with all his men in the canoes, running
to every Vogar, for not coming to blows with such people, and heaven
forbid that Christians and Guarani, a long time now are the terror
of these cruel enemies, they are also reduced to the faith Chiquitos
and civil government.

The newcomers, happy with the good achievement of his cunning, proceeded far some way to that
shore, until they finally found the Curucanes Rancheria, where being
well received, They were all square, kneeling to pray the Rosary of
Our Lady to His Majesty to give those nations trial (sentence explaining
when They pray for themselves or for others to our Lord and the Blessed
Virgin) so that all will embrace God's holy law.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>