<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08331</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>295805</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22966</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

  Cruzamos la ria de Southampton, el golfo de Gascuña, Finisterre;
  pasamos por enfrente de Burdeos, y al cuarto dia de viaje
  llegamos á Lisboa.

  El Great Western, vapor que me condujo, es una colosal
  embarcacion de 2,500 toneladas, con un puente de una extension
  prodigiosa y unos anchos y soberbios salones.

  Salimos de Inglaterra doscientos pasajeros, y cada uno tenia
  cómodamente su puesto en la mesa, pues el comedor es un
  magnífico salon. Los camarotes, de dos camas en su mayor parte,
  son estrechos y poco confortables.

  El trato que reciben los viajeros es bueno: á las nueve de la
  mañana se sirve el almuerzo, á medio dia el indispensable
  lunch ingles, que equivale á tomar las once, á las cuatro una
  abundante comida, inglesa por de contado, á las siete el té con
  pan y manteca.

  De Southampton á Lisboa, todos los viajeros estuvimos en cama
  veinticuatro horas. El mar de Inglaterra y el golfo de Gascuña,
  constantemente agitados, dan al buque un movimiento continuo que
  no hay viajero que soporte sin incomodidad.

  En Lisboa nos detuvimos doce horas, continuando despues nuestra
  marcha por un mar sosegado y tranquilo, llegando á las treinta y
  seis horas á Madera.

  Esta bellísima isla que goza de un saludable clima y produce el
  celebrado vino que en todas las buenas mesas se sirve, merece un
  viaje. Ocho horas solamente descansamos en Madera, en cuyo
  tiempo visitamos parte de la isla, corriendo sobre los esbeltos
  y ligeros caballos que aguardan dispuestos y enjaezados á la
  orilla del mar siempre que llegan viajeros. Los alquilan por un
  moderado precio, y con su ayuda se goza del encanto que producen
  los pintorescos paisajes que por todas partes se ofrecen.

  Las calles de Madera, en cuesta en su mayor parte, están á
  derecha é izquierda sembradas de jardines frescos y lucidos, que
  con sus flores embalsaman el purísimo y fresco aire que allí
  se respira.

  La poblacion es pequeña y de corta importancia: hay dos ó tres
  hoteles, entre ellos uno ingles que está regularmente
  servido[34].

  De Madera salimos para Santa Cruz de Tenerife empleando cuarenta
  y ocho horas.

  Yo venia de recorrer paises extranjeros todos; hacía bastante
  tiempo que faltaba de España y tenia necesidad de hablar nuestra
  espléndida lengua y recordar á mi querida patria.

  Mis deseos se frustraron en parte: llegamos á Santa Cruz á las
  ocho de la noche, y habiendo dicho el capitan que solo nos
  detendríamos el tiempo necesario para dejar y recojer la
  correspondencia, ningun viajero saltó á tierra. Yo me desquité,
  hablando, hasta que el buque marchó, con los españoles que
  vinieron á bordo en sus pequeñas lanchas cargadas de naranjas,
  manzanas, ciruelas y otros deliciosos frutos.

  Entre las sombras de la noche, mi ávida mirada distinguia,
  aunque confusamente, la ciudad de Santa Cruz, que simbolizaba á
  mis ojos toda España, y saludándola con júbilo y emocion, la
  perdí de vista en el momento en que continuamos nuestro
  largo viaje.

  De Santa Cruz de Tenerife á San Vicente, en el Cabo Verde, se
  emplean cuatro dias.

  San Vicente, notable para mí, por ser el primer sitio del mundo
  donde ví lo que llaman esclavos, seres desgraciados tan dignos
  como el primer hombre libre, es un miserable lugar que cuenta
  solo una docena de casas: allí tiene la Empresa de los vapores
  depósito de carbon de piedra: esta es la causa de detenerse en
  semejante sitio, de otro modo nadie se pararia.

  Grupos de africanos, hombres, mujeres, niños, todos desnudos
  casi completamente, componen la corta poblacion de San Vicente.
  El alma se duele y el corazon se comprime al aspecto de
  semejante sitio: el clima de allí, casi abrasador, como tocando
  con el Africa que está, hace imposible toda vegetacion: falta
  tierra, aire, vida, seres humanos, todo falta allí.

  El número de esclavos africanos que allí habita, no tiene por
  alimento mas que el maiz, y no todos. No hay viajero que al
  desembarcar en San Vicente no se sienta mal á la vista de
  semejante cuadro: inmediatamente que nuestro vapor se proveyó
  del carbon necesario, dejamos las islas del Cabo Verde con
  general contentamiento.

  Al salir de San Vicente dió principio el verdadero viaje: nos
  engolfamos en pleno Océano, solos, en medio del poderoso
  Atlántico, sin mas testigos que Dios, sin otro horizonte que un
  círculo siempre el mismo, cerrado por todas partes por la
  inmensidad.

  Al salir de San Vicente, se despide el viajero de la tierra que
  no vuelve á ver en ocho dias; el mar y el cielo son su única
  perspectiva en todo ese tiempo.

  Hay algo de solemne y magnífico en un viaje por mar, por ese
  prepotente elemento que nos habla del infinito con la tremebunda
  voz de su cólera.

  El mar, cuyos secretos permanecen en el misterio, que nuestra
  curiosidad no acierta á comprender, que la ciencia no explica,
  que nos habla con su eterno movimiento sin que podamos saber qué
  es lo que nos dice; el mar, digo, es soberbiamente majestuoso
  y grande.

  El hombre, que á pesar de su pequeña talla ha obrado prodigios
  de gigante, ora recojiendo el rayo en su mano, ora barrenando
  las montañas, ya descendiendo á las entrañas de la tierra para
  robarla sus guardados secretos, ya escalando el cielo para ver
  de cerca esas lumbreras que le cubren y cuya marcha ha
  averiguado; el hombre, que por todas partes imprime la huella de
  su paso, no ha conseguido nada del mar.

  El arrojo de los navegantes, á los que la industria humana ha
  prestado casas flotantes para cruzar las soledades del Océano;
  la ciencia, que una tras otra le ha suministrado al marino
  nuevas conquistas, con las cuales sabe donde va y por qué
  sitios, cuanto anda y adonde se encuentra; el vapor, que le ha
  facilitado marchar velozmente y en todas las épocas del año, sin
  tener que someterse como ántes á la poderosa ayuda de los
  vientos; todo en una palabra, solo ha servido para que los
  hombres se comuniquen, para estudiar y conocer el mundo, para
  grandes y poderosas conquistas, es verdad, pero no para imprimir
  la huella del hombre, pero no para marcarle con el sello del
  genio como el hombre hace con todas sus obras.

  El mar, el poderoso mar, quizá demasiado soberbio, no quiere que
  el hombre le señale.

  El hombre ha cambiado mil veces la faz de la tierra sembrando
  ciudades, cortando montañas, haciendo excavaciones inmensas,
  barrenando istmos: pues bien, la superficie del mar está hoy
  como al dia siguiente de haber brotado del soplo de Dios, y así
  estará hasta el último y postrero instante del mundo. Pasa una
  magnífica nave por las ondas del océano, abre un sulco,
  inmediatamente se avanzan nuevas olas y borran la huella; por
  eso gritan eternamente al rededor de un buque, se impacientan al
  sentirle, pero inmediatamente que pasa se lanzan á borrar
  sus trazas.

  El océano es la imágen de la inmensidad, el espejo de Dios, la
  brillante prueba de su existencia.

  Ocho dias estuve solo en pleno océano, sin otra cúpula que el
  firmamento, sin otro apoyo que el abismo.

  Es arrogantemente temerario el valor del hombre que se ha
  lanzado á ciegas en medio de los precipicios y las tempestades.

  No hablo en manera alguna de hoy; hoy no tiene ningun mérito un
  viaje al rededor del mundo, hoy todo se conoce, hoy hay medios.

  Me refiero á Colon, atalaya inmensa de las modernas edades que
  no tiene rival.

  Es necesario hacer un viaje á América para llegar á comprender
  el heroismo de Colon; de otro modo no se entiende; y mas que el
  heroismo de Colon, el de nuestros valientes compatriotas que
  componian la tripulacion de sus tres pequeñas embarcaciones.

  Sí, ellos son mas heróicos; Colon tenia el genio, el rayo de la
  inspiracion, la perspectiva de la gloria que le ha
  inmortalizado, por guia: él sabia adonde iba: los sencillos
  marineros que le acompañaban no, no conocian mas playas que las
  de España, no podian ni soñar con la existencia de otro mundo,
  se veian arrojados en una empresa que acobardaba á todos, que la
  Europa toda calificaba de locura, se vieron solos en medio de
  mares que nadie mas que el ojo de Dios habia visto, sin saber
  adonde iban ni por qué ruta: creyendo que la vuelta seria
  imposible y creyéndolo con razon é ignorando al propio tiempo si
  habria llegada, porque ellos nada sabian, porque entónces se
  ignoraba todo, porque no se sabia qué habia detras del mar. Es
  necesario hacer un viaje marítimo para comprender esto.

  Desde San Vicente hasta Pernambuco, primera poblacion del
  Brasil, que del otro lado de la línea se encuentra, empleó
  nuestro vapor ocho dias.

  La distancia que separa ámbas poblaciones es de 1,620 millas
  marítimas.

  Nada mas grande que la salida y puesta del sol vista desde un
  buque en pleno océano. Semeja el astro del mundo un inmenso
  globo de fuego resplandeciente: no parece sino que se levanta
  del seno de los mares, la ilusion es completa.

  El horizonte está cerrado por todas partes por un círculo de
  agua; allí, á bordo, en mitad del Atlántico, figúrase la
  imaginacion que la tierra toda está cubierta por el Océano,
  único elemento que se ve; de aquí el que parezca, con todas las
  apariencias de verdad, que el sol se levanta por la mañana del
  seno de las aguas, y que allí vuelve á acostarse cuando la
  tierra girando en el vacío ha hecho su movimiento diario al
  rededor de él.

  En el mar no se comprende el ateismo: tampoco tiene explicacion
  en la tierra, no, pero el Océano, con su voz inmortal, ora hable
  con la soberbia cólera de la tormenta, ora con la apacible
  majestad de su tranquilo y eterno flujo y reflujo, siempre
  publica la existencia de Dios, siempre pregona su poder, siempre
  canta su omnipotencia, siempre habla de la eternidad, siempre
  explica el infinito, siempre convence de la otra vida.

  Esos inmensos buques que cruzan hoy los mares, á pesar de sus
  gigantescas proporciones, están en el mar, en la relacion que un
  átomo en la materia, que un punto en el espacio. Una sola de las
  tremendas ondas que arrullan el Océano despedaza y convierte en
  astillas las mas pujantes escuadras.

  Esto habla muy alto en favor del hombre, que á pesar de su
  pequeñez, que en el Océano se palpa mejor que en parte alguna,
  se lanza atrevido á sulcar sus piélagos y abismos, marchando
  entre tempestades y truenos, solo, en una miserable lancha,
  porque eso es en el Océano el mas colosal navío, una lancha;
  allí va el hombre, solo, pero con Dios encima de su cabeza.

  Un viaje marítimo de ocho á diez dias es magnífico,
  sorprendente, admirable: es necesario hacerle para ver y oir á
  Dios, para comprender el mundo, para adivinar la inmensidad.

  Pero un viaje largo no siendo marino por vocacion es monótono,
  fatiga, cansa.

  En ocho dias pueden admirarse las bellezas de un cielo azul y
  transparente, visto desde el mar; el portentoso descenso del sol
  que sumerge su brillante cabellera en el seno de las aguas: la
  espantosa y dramática grandeza del mar poderosamente irritado:
  en una palabra, en ocho dias puede verse lo que en treinta, que
  fueron los que yo empleé en mi viaje, á pesar de que el vapor
  era el agente de nuestra marcha.

  Un tiempo tan largo en el puente de un buque fatiga. Al fin de
  los diez ó doce primeros dias las escenas se repiten, son las
  mismas, las emociones ningunas, y allí donde no hay emocion,
  alimento mio, no hay nada, hay el prosáico fastidio.

  Desde Pernambuco á Bahia empleamos cuarenta y ocho horas, y
  desde Bahia á Rio Janeiro cuatro dias.

  La distancia que acababa de recorrer, desde Southampton á la
  capital del Brasil, mi primer viaje marítimo, fué de 5,155
  millas, distribuidas del siguiente modo: de Rio Janeiro á Bahia,
  685 millas; de Bahia á Pernambuco, 380; de Pernambuco á San
  Vicente, 1,620; de San Vicente á Canarias, 850; de Canarias á
  Madera, 265; de Madera á Lisboa, 525; y de Lisboa á
  Southampton, 830.

  El ensayo fué bueno, tuve la suerte de no sufrir el mareo
  haciendo todo el viaje perfectamente bien.

  #BRASIL.#

  Rio Janeiro, capital del imperio del Brasil, es una ciudad de
  300,000 almas; magníficamente situada y con una soberbia y
  pintoresca bahía, una de las mayores del mundo.

  Sus calles principales son la Rua Dereta y la Rua d'Ouvidor:
  la primera de estas es ancha y despejada; en el centro está el
  edificio de la Bolsa: es calle muy concurrida y de bastante
  animacion; tiene buenos comercios y cafés, empieza en la plaza
  de Palacio y termina cerca de una iglesia cuyo nombre
  he olvidado.

  La Rua d'Ouvidor es la principal calle de Rio Janeiro, por la
  importancia de los elegantes comercios que la adornan: es recta
  y desemboca en la rua Dereta, que, como ya he indicado, es de
  las mejores de la ciudad. Tiene un grande número de elegantes
  tiendas, de franceses en su mayor parte, vestidas con el lujo de
  los comercios de las ciudades europeas: el empedrado es de lo
  mas detestable que puede imaginarse, y como las lluvias son muy
  frecuentes, apénas puede transitarse por la citada calle.

  El resto de las calles de Rio Janeiro, en general, está en un
  lamentable atraso, sin empedrar, descuidada su limpieza, y en
  estado de perfecto abandono.

  Hay un gran número de plazas, entre las que descuella, por su
  inmensa extension, la del Teatro Provisorio. Como carezca de
  grandes edificios, y no tenga proporciones, ni árboles, ni
  cultivo, ni adornos, solo ofrece á la vista del viajero una
  grande extension de terreno, que podria ser una magnífica plaza.

  En uno de sus lienzos están los palacios del Senado y la Cámara
  de los Diputados. En el centro de otro de los frentes está el
  Ministerio de Negocios Extranjeros, en una modesta casa que no
  me atrevo á llamar palacio. Enfrente se levanta el teatro
  Provisorio, destinado á la ópera italiana.

  El nombre del Teatro indica bastantemente lo que es,
  provisional; se construyó en un corto plazo de tiempo: ni tiene
  arquitectura, ni estilo, ni formas, ni pensamiento; es una obra
  ejecutada sin mas objeto que el de hacerla servir por poco
  tiempo para teatro, ínterin se construia otro, que aun no se
  ha empezado.

  De todos modos allí se canta la ópera italiana, y es en verdad
  un gran recurso para Rio Janeiro: en general hay buenas
  compañías; el gobierno contribuye al sostenimiento del Teatro
  con una subvencion de ocho mil duros anuales. La compañía que
  cantaba en 1856 era bastante buena: las dos primas donnas,
  mademoiselle la Grua y madame Charton, interpretaban muy bien
  sus papeles, como en cualquier teatro de Europa. Despues cantó
  la Steffenone, que últimamente ha brillado en los Italianos de
  Paris cantando con grande éxito el Trovador.

  Cuando yo salí de Rio Janeiro para regresar á Europa, estaban
  escriturados Tamberlik y la Dejean.

  Otra de las plazas que merecen mencionarse es la del Rosario,
  espaciosa, regular, y con mas proporciones que la del
  Provisorio. Tiene cuatro fachadas de casas regulares, y en el
  centro han plantado algunas docenas de árboles que la completan
  y hermosean. En uno de sus ángulos está el Teatro de San Pedro,
  consagrado á la comedia: se representan en portugues, piezas
  traducidas del frances y del español. Estando yo en Rio Janeiro
  un voraz incendio consumió por la segunda vez el coliseo.

  En otra plaza grande tambien, hay un jardin público, adonde
  acuden músicas militares los dias festivos: hay profusion de
  árboles y plantas tropicales, y está regularmente dispuesto,
  aunque falta gusto y órden.

  El jardin botánico, llamado así poco modestamente, está fuera de
  la ciudad y á una distancia de tres cuartos de legua. El
  descuido mas completo y la negligencia mas desdeñosa, convencen
  al que le visita del poco interes que sin duda inspira á los
  brasileños.

  Y en verdad que es una lástima, pues aparte de las dos
  magníficas colecciones de soberbios plátanos que le adornan,
  contiene una gran riqueza de plantas escojidas y muy estimadas,
  que brotan espontáneamente, quizá á despecho de los que cuidan
  el jardin. Tiene ademas una decoracion natural admirable; le
  circuyen como un precioso marco lienzos de pintorescas montañas,
  de muchos y graciosos contornos, de variedad de formas
  y colores.

  Los paseos de Rio Janeiro, completamente innecesarios, pues los
  habitantes del pais no acostumbran pasear, son regulares,
  distinguiéndose entre todos el de Botafogo, situado á la
  orilla del mar, con árboles, fuentes, y paseo de carruajes. Es
  bastante bueno y muy poco concurrido. El emperador pasea todos
  los domingos en carruaje cruzando siempre el de Botafogo en toda
  su extension.

  Los paseos del Acueducto, y del Corcovado, son muy
  pintorescos, en especial el último, que termina en la cresta de
  una alta montaña inclinada, de donde toma el nombre. Puede
  subirse á caballo hasta la misma cima, desde la que se alcanza
  un asombroso golpe de vista: el mar inmenso, las pintorescas
  montañas y la ciudad, se ofrecen en majestuoso conjunto al
  observador. Otro promontorio que embellece la Bahia es el
  llamado Pan de azúcar, designado así por su forma.

  Una de las mejoras de que disfruta Rio Janeiro hace ya bastantes
  años, es la del alumbrado de gas, con el cual están profusamente
  iluminadas sus principales calles y plazas. Tambien los
  carruajes de plaza son muy buenos y existen en grande número;
  los alquilan á precios fabulosamente caros. Cuéntanse diferentes
  líneas de ómnibus que hacen el servicio entre la ciudad y los
  arrabales: yo me detengo á hacer mencion de esto, porque es un
  adelanto en una ciudad tan alejada del movimiento europeo.

  Los hoteles son regulares en general, contándose dos buenos. Los
  tres mejores que hay dentro de la ciudad son el de Pfaroux, el
  de las cuatro Naciones, y el de Europa. Fuera de la ciudad, y en
  el camino de Botafogo, hay dos ingleses y uno frances: el
  mejor de todos, tanto de los de la ciudad, como de los de
  fuera, es el Hôtel des Étrangers en la plaza de Catette.

  Es una gran casa, de moderna y elegante construccion, sólida,
  con anchas y magníficas habitaciones: un gran jardin al pié del
  mar, vistas admirables, comodidades muchas. El hotel todo está
  alumbrado por el gas: tiene baños, billares, y grande capacidad:
  en el Hotel de los Extranjeros, viven la mayor parte de los
  individuos del Cuerpo Diplomático extranjero.

  Hay otros diferentes hoteles en el interior de la ciudad, poco
  apetecibles ciertamente, pero buenos para las gentes del pais.
  Hay tambien en Rio Janeiro dos ó tres cafés donde sirven helados
  todo el año; la nieve la reciben de los Estados Unidos: y ahora
  hablarémos un poco de los elementos del pais.

  La riqueza del Brasil la constituyen el azúcar y el café: el
  café sobre todo es su principal ramo de riqueza.

  Buques de todos los paises cargan constantemente en sus puertos
  el citado artículo: el año de 1855, la provincia de Rio Janeiro
  sola exportó diez millones de arrobas de café: esta fabulosa
  cantidad la recoje con una regular cosecha sola la provincia de
  Rio: los diez millones de arrobas de café importaron treinta
  millones de duros, pues cada arroba se vende á 50 reales.

  El mercado principal que tiene el Brasil para dar salida á su
  café, es el de los Estados-Unidos de América, donde se vende mas
  de la mitad de lo que se recolecta.

  Los ferrocarriles que están en construccion acrecerán
  inmensamente tan luego como estén terminados la riqueza pública
  del Brasil, pues entónces será fácil y barato el trasporte del
  café desde las provincias del interior á los puertos del Brasil,
  trasporte que hoy se hace por medio de caballerías, con grandes
  dispendios y con el empleo necesario de mucho tiempo, porque
  ademas de ser grandes las distancias, faltan caminos.

  El azúcar es otro ramo de riqueza, pero no promete grande
  porvenir, pues su condicion, inferior en mucho á la de la isla
  de Cuba y otros puntos de América, la mantiene en un estado de
  depreciacion continua.

  Lo que constituye y forma la riqueza de un pueblo, lo que dota á
  un pais de porvenir, ademas de los elementos naturales, es su
  poblacion, y esto es lo que principalmente falta al imperio de
  Don Pedro II.

  Sus viciosas leyes de colonizacion, su clima, los pocos
  atractivos que ofrece al europeo, la falta de garantías con que
  asegurar el cumplimiento de las promesas que se hacen por medio
  de sus agentes á los europeos que desean emigrar, son causas
  poderosas que retraen al europeo que desea emigrar al Brasil,
  cuyo pais, con un territorio inmenso, mayor que el de la Europa
  entera, cuenta hoy dia siete millones no completos de
  habitantes, de los cuales dos son de negros.

  Terminadas sus vias férreas, y aumentada su poblacion, el Brasil
  tendrá un riquísimo porvenir.

  Hay en el Brasil el partido constitucional partidario del
  Imperio, y el bando republicano.

  Como es un pueblo nuevo, que acaba de entrar en la vida pública
  de las naciones, tiene alguna sinceridad política que sirve para
  que se practiquen en parte las formas representativas de su vida
  constitucional, único modo de que el Imperio subsista. La
  política que sigue en el exterior no tiene nada de
  constitucional; pretende imitar al mal llamado gobierno libre de
  los Estados-Unidos, y siguiendo sus huellas, hace, en la América
  del sur, lo que la república de Washington en el Norte;
  predomina en los estados vecinos, influye en su política y
  tiende al engrandecimiento continuo, aunque para ello sea
  preciso quebrantar leyes y atacar la independencia de
  los pueblos.

  Esta es la política del Brasil con los gobiernos de Montevideo,
  Buenos-Aires y el Paraguay: aduladores torpes han hecho creer á
  los gobiernos de Don Pedro II que el Brasil podia y debia seguir
  la conducta de los Estados-Unidos; que debia hacer en el Sur lo
  que ellos práctican en el Norte, y que siendo los dos pueblos
  mas fuertes de la América nada mas natural que marchar por el
  mismo camino.

  ¡Error! ¡error grosero! la raza anglo-sajona que puebla el Norte
  de América, no tiene analogía ni remota con la indefinible y
  degenerada latino-portuguesa que habita el Brasil.

  Los dos pueblos son diferentes en todo: en energía, en orígen,
  en religion, en leyes, en costumbres: la actividad de los
  norte-americanos solo puede compararse, en lo grande, con la
  característica pereza de los brasileños: se diferencian en todo,
  absolutamente en todo: hasta los climas son opuestos.

  El Brasil no ensanchará nunca sus fronteras, nunca; si hasta hoy
  han podido sus diplomáticos ejercer alguna influencia en las
  repúblicas de la Plata, débelo exclusivamente al lamentable
  estado de constante perturbacion de sus gobiernos, á la anarquía
  completa que allí ha reinado hasta hoy.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10612</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>47123</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21011</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

  We crossed the ria of Southampton, the Bay of Biscay, Finisterre;
  we passed in front of Bordeaux, and the fourth day of travel
  we arrived at Lisbon.

  
  
  The Great Western steam led me, is a colossal vessel of 2.500 tons,
with an extension bridge and a prodigious wide and magnificent halls.

  
  
  We left England two hundred passengers, and each had comfortably
  his place in the table because the dining room is a Gorgeous salon.

  Cabins, double beds for the most part, are narrow and uncomfortable.

The
  treatment of travelers is good: at nine o'clock in the Breakfast
  is served lunch at noon the indispensable English lunch, which
  is equivalent to take the eleven, at four a abundant food, English
  for cash, at seven o'clock tea with bread and butter.

  
  
  From Southampton to Lisbon, all passengers were in bed clock. The
  sea of ??England and the Bay of Biscay, constantly agitated, give
the ship a continuous movement no traveler support without discomfort.

  
  
  In Lisbon, we stopped twelve hours, then continuing our up by a sea
calm and quiet, go to the thirty six hours to Madera.

  
  
  This beautiful island enjoys a healthy climate and produces
  wine held in all the good tables are served, deserves trip. Only
  eight hours rest in Madera, in which time we visited part of
  the island, running on the slim and light horses and harnessed
  willing to await the seashore where travelers arrive. The rent for
  a moderate price, and with their help you enjoy the charm that produce
the picturesque landscapes that are offered everywhere.

  
  
  Wood Streets in costs for the most part, are to right and left
  gardens planted with fresh and lucid, which with flowers perfume
the air pure and fresh there breathing.

  
  
  The population is small and short-importance: there are two or three
hotels, including one that is regularly English served [34].

  
  

  Wood went out to Santa Cruz de Tenerife using forty and eight
  hours.
  

  I was coming from foreign countries go all, it was quite time remaining
  in Spain and had need to speak our splendid language and remember
  my beloved homeland.
  
  My desires were thwarted in part, we came to Santa Cruz to
  the eight p.m., and the captain had said that we only would stop
  long enough to drop off and pick up the correspondence, any traveler
jumped to the ground.

  I got even, speaking, until the ship left, with the Spanish
  who came on board in their small boats laden with oranges, apples,
  plums and other delicious fruits.
  
  In the shadows of the night, my eager look distinguished, but confusingly,
the city of Santa Cruz, symbolizing my eyes all over Spain, and greeting
with joy and excitement, the I lost sight of at the moment we continue
our long journey.

  
  

  Santa Cruz de Tenerife to San Vicente, Cape Verde, employ four days.

San
  Vicente, notable for me, being the first site in the world where
  I saw what they call slaves, wretched beings as worthy as the
  first free man, is a miserable place that has only a dozen houses,
  there is the Enterprise from the vapors deposit of coal: this
  is the cause of stopping at such a place, otherwise no one would
stop.

  
  
  Groups of African men, women, children, all naked almost
  completely, cut up the population of San Vicente. Hurts the soul
  and the heart compresses the appearance of such a place: the
  climate there, almost burning, and playing in Africa it is, makes
impossible any vegetation: missing earth, air, life, human beings,
everything is missing there.

  
  
  The number of African slaves who live there, is not more food
  than corn, and not all. No traveler to land in San Vicente do
  not feel bad at the sight of such a picture: that our steam
  immediately provided coal necessary, we left the Cape Verde islands
general contentment.

  
  
  Leaving San Vicente gave the first real trip, we engulfed in the
  ocean, alone, in the midst of the powerful Atlantic, with
  no more witnesses to God, no other horizon than a always the same
circle, closed on all sides by immensity.

  
  
  Leaving San Vicente, the traveler takes leave of the earth I never
see in eight days, the sea and sky are the only perspective in all
that time.

  
  
  There is something solemn and gorgeous in a sea voyage, by the arrogant
element tells of the dreadful infinity voice their anger.

  
  
  The sea, whose secrets remain a mystery, that our curiosity can not
  understand that science does not explain who speaks with his
  eternal motion before we can know what is what he tells us, the sea,
I say, is superbly majestic and large.

  
  
  The man, in spite of its small size has worked wonders giant, now
  pick up the lightning in his hand, now scuttling mountains, and
  descend into the bowels of the earth saved to steal their
  secrets, and climbing the sky to see monitor these ports that you
  are covered and whose progress has learned, the man who prints everywhere
footprint its passage, has not achieved anything from the sea.

  
  
  The courage of the sailors, to which human industry has houseboats
  paid to cross the solitudes of ocean; science, one after
  another has been supplied to the ocean new conquests, with which
  knows where it goes and why sites, the walks and where it is, the
  vapor, which has go fast and facilitated in all seasons,
  no as before having to submit to the powerful assistance of
  the winds in a word, has only served for men to communicate,
  to study and understand the world, great and mighty conquests, it
  is true, but not for printing the human footprint, but not stamped
  with the seal of genius as a man does with all his works.

  
  

  The sea, the mighty sea, perhaps too proud, does not want the
  point man.
  
  The man has changed a thousand times the earth planting cities,
  mountains cutting, excavating immense collaring isthmus: Well,
  the sea surface is now the next day as having sprung from
  the breath of God, and so will be up to the last and final moments
  of the world. Spend a magnificent ship by ocean waves, opening a
  sulcus, new waves move immediately and delete the trace,
  for That scream eternally around a ship, are impatient to to feel,
but once that passes are thrown to erase their traces.

  
  

  The ocean is the image of the vastness, the mirror of God, brilliant
  proof of their existence.

  
  Eight days I was alone in the ocean, with no other dome that sky,
with no other support than the abyss.

  
  

  It arrogantly reckless man's value has been released to blind in
  the middle of the cliffs and storms.

  
  
  I do not speak in any way today, today has no merit a trip around
  the world today everything is known, there are now media.

  
  I refer to Colon, great vantage of modern ages has
  no rival.
  
  It is necessary to make a trip to America to gain insight the heroism
  of Columbus, otherwise it is not understood, and most of the Colon
  heroism, of our brave compatriots composed the crew of her three
  small boats.
  
  Yes, they are more heroic, Colon had the genius, the ray inspiration,
  the prospect of the glory that has immortalized by a guide:
  he knew where he was going: the simple sailors who accompanied
  him, no, no beaches that were more familiar of Spain, could not even
dream of the existence of another world were seen thrown at a company
that unnerving to all, that Europe all described as madness, were
alone in the seas that no one but God's eye had seen, without knowing
where they went or why route: believing that the return would impossible,
believing with reason and ignoring at the same time if would have
arrived, because they knew nothing, because then know everything,
because no one knew what was behind the sea.

  Is necessary to make a sea voyage to understand this.
  
  From San Vicente to Pernambuco, the first population of Brazil, on
the other side of the line is, employed our steam eight days.

  
  

  The distance between two populations is 1.620 miles sea.
  
  Nothing bigger than the rising and setting sun seen from a ship
  in the ocean.

  The world looks like a huge star glowing ball of fire: there
  seems but rises the bosom of the seas, the illusion is complete.

The
  horizon is closed on all sides by a circle of water there,
  on board in the middle of the Atlantic, the figures imagination
  that the whole earth is covered by the ocean, only element which
  is, hence the it may seem, with all appearance of truth, that
  the sun rises in the morning bosom of the waters, and that
  she returns to bed when earth spinning in a vacuum has made his move
to newspaper around it.

  
  
  At sea one does not understand atheism: it is not explanation
  on earth, no, but the ocean, with their immortal voice, sometimes
  talking with pride wrath of the storm, now with the peaceful quiet
  majesty of his eternal ebb and flow, always publishes the existence
  of God, always touts its power, always sings his omnipotence, he
always speaks of eternity, forever explains the infinite, always convinced
the afterlife.

  
  
  These huge ships crossing the seas today, notwithstanding their gigantic
  proportions, are at sea, in relation to a atom in the art, that
  a point in space.

  One of the tremendous Ocean waves lull apart and becomes chips
  the most vibrant squares.
  
  This speaks volumes for the man, notwithstanding his smallness
  in the ocean that can be felt anywhere, Sulca dared launches
  its Piélagos and chasms, marching between storms and thunder, alone
in a miserable boat because that is the most colossal Ocean vessel,
a boat; there goes the man alone, but with God over his head.

  
  
  A sea voyage of eight to ten days is great, surprising, admirable:
it is necessary to ask to see and hear God, to understand the world,
to divine immensity.

  
  

  But do not be a long journey by vocation ocean is monotonous,
  fatigue, tired.
  
  In eight days you can admire the beauty of a blue sky transparent,
  seen from the sea, the sun's descent portentous his bright hair
  dipping into the bosom of the waters: the frightening and dramatic
  grandeur of the sea mightily irritated: in short, eight days may
be so in thirty, that were those that I employed in my journey, in
spite of the steam was the agent of our march.

  
  
  Such a long time on the bridge of a ship fatigue. At the end
  of first ten or twelve days the scenes are repeated, are same, no
emotions, and where there is no emotion, my food, nothing, there is
the mundane boredom.

  
  

  From Pernambuco to Bahia employ forty-eight hours, and from Bahia
  to Rio de Janeiro four days.
  
  The distance that had to travel from Southampton to the Brazil's
  capital, my first voyage, was of 5.155 miles, distributed as
  follows: Rio de Janeiro to Bahia, 685 miles, from Bahia
  to Pernambuco, 380; of Pernambuco to St. Vicente, 1.620, of San Vicente
to the Canary Islands, 850; the Canary Islands to Wood, 265; for Wooden
to Lisbon, 525, and from Lisbon to Southampton, 830.

  
  

  The test was good, I was lucky not to suffer dizziness making the
trip just fine.

  
  
  # BRASIL. #

  
  Rio de Janeiro, capital of the empire of Brazil, is a city 300.000
  souls, superbly located and with a superb and picturesque bay,
  one of the largest in the world.
  
  Its main streets are Rua and Rua Deret d'Ouvidor: The first of these
is wide and open, in the center is Exchange building, is busy street
and quite animation, has good shops and cafes on the square start
Palace and ends near a church whose name I have forgotten.

  
  
  La Rua d'Ouvidor is the main street of Rio de Janeiro, for the
  importance of exclusive shops that adorn it: it is straight and
  empties into the rua Deret, which, as I indicated, is the best in
  town. It has a large number of elegant shops, mostly French,
  dressed in luxury shops of European cities: the pavement is what
  more detestable than you can imagine, as rainfall is Frequently,
you can barely passable by that street.

  
  
  The rest of the streets of Rio de Janeiro, in general, is in a unfortunate
delay, unpaved, careless cleaning, and perfect state of neglect.

  
  
  There are a number of places, among which stands out for its
  great extension, that of the Provisional Theater. As lacking
  large buildings, and has no proportion, no trees, no culture, or
ornaments, only provides the traveler a view large tracts of land,
which could be a great place.

  
  
  In one of his paintings are the palaces of the Senate and House
  of Deputies. In the center of one of the fronts is the Ministry
  of Foreign Affairs, in a modest house not I dare to call the palace.

  Opposite stands the theater Temporary, for the Italian
  opera.
  
  The Theatre name sufficiently indicates what it is, provisional
  built in a short period of time, neither has architecture, no
  style, no forms, no thought, is a work executed without any other
object than it used almost time for theater, built meantime another
was not yet has begun.

  
  
  Anyway there is singing Italian opera, and is indeed a great resource
  for Rio de Janeiro: in general there is good companies, the government
  contributes to the maintenance of Theatre With a grant of
  eight thousand dollars annually. The company sang in 1856 was
  pretty good: the two prima donnas, Crane Mademoiselle and Madame
  Charton, very well interpreted their roles, as in any theater
  in Europe.

  After singing the Steffenone, which has recently excelled in
  the Italian Paris singing with great success the Troubadour.

  
  
  When I left Rio de Janeiro to return to Europe, were Tamberlik
  notarized and Dejean.
  
  Another of the places worth mentioning is that of Rosario, spacious,
  regular, and with a higher proportion than the Provisional. It
  has four regular exterior walls, and center have planted several
dozen trees that complete and beautiful.

  In one corner is the Theater of San Pedro, devoted to the play:
  they are represented in Portuguese, parts translated from French
  and Spanish. When I was in Rio de Janeiro a raging fire burned
  for the second time the coliseum.

  
  
  Another great place too, there is a public garden, where military
  bands come the holidays: There are a profusion of tropical trees
  and plants, and is regularly provided, but lack taste and order.

  
  
  The botanical garden, named after some modestly, is outside the
  city and at a distance of three quarters of a league. The more
  complete carelessness and neglect more contemptuous, convinced
  when you visit the little interest that will undoubtedly inspire
  Brazilians.
  

  And indeed it is a pity, because apart from the two superb superb
  collections of bananas that adorn contains a wealth of plants
  you choose and highly appreciated, that arise spontaneously,
  perhaps in spite of those who care the garden. It also has a wonderful
  natural furnishings, you circular and with a lovely canvas of
  picturesque mountains, many and graceful contours, variety of forms
  and colors.

  
  The tours of Rio de Janeiro, completely unnecessary, since inhabitants
  of the country do not usually walk, are regular, distinguishing
  between all the de Botafogo, located at the coast, with trees,
  fountains, and carriage ride. Is pretty good and very thinly
  attended. The Emperor walks all Sundays always crossing the
  carriage across Botafogo extension.
  

  Aqueduct rides, and Corcovado, are picturesque, especially the last,
  which ends on the crest of a high mountain angled, hence the name.
  Can horseback ride to the summit, from which this is achieved
  an astonishing glance: the calm sea, the picturesque mountains
  and city, are offered in all the majestic observer. Another Bay
  headland is embellished called Sugar Loaf, named for its shape.

One
  of the best Rio de Janeiro enjoyed enough ago , is the lighting
  of gas, which are lavishly lighted main streets and squares.

  Also the Square carriages are very good and there are big numbers;
  Prices to rent them fabulously expensive. Different Cuéntanse
  bus lines that make the service between the city and suburbs: I
  stop to make mention of this, because it is a advancement
  in a city so far from the European movement.
  

  The hotels are scheduled at large, two good. The three best that
  is within the city are of Pfaroux, the of the four nations, and
  Europe. Outside the city, and the path of Botafogo, two British
  and one French, the Best of all, both in the city, as those of out,
  is the Hôtel des Etrangers in Catette Square.
  

  It's a great house, modern and elegant construction, solid with
  wide and beautiful rooms, a large garden at the foot of sea, wonderful
  views, many amenities. The whole hotel is lighting by gas, have
  bathrooms, pool, and large capacity: in the Hotel for Aliens live
  most of individuals of foreign diplomatic corps.

  
  

  There are other different hotels within the city, shortly certainly
  desirable, but good for the people of the country. There is also
  in Rio de Janeiro two or three cafes where they serve ice cream
  throughout the year, the snow is received from the United States:
  and now talk a little about the elements of the country.
  

  The richness of Brazil are sugar and coffee: the especially coffee
  is the main branch of wealth.
  

  Ships of all countries constantly loaded in their ports
  by this Article: 1855, the province of Rio Janeiro single exported
  ten million pounds of coffee: this cool number of picks with a
  single crop regular province Rio: the ten million pounds of coffee
  imported thirty millions of dollars, for each arroba is sold to
  50 reais.
  

  The main market is Brazil to vent his coffee, is that of the
  United States of America, selling more half of what is collected.

The
  railways are under construction accrue immensely as soon as they
  are completed public wealth Brazil, for then it will be easy and
cheap transportation of coffee from the inland provinces to the ports
of Brazil, transport is now done by horses, with large extravagance
and the jobs needed for a long time, because besides being great distances,
lack of roads.

  
  
  Sugar is another class of wealth, but no big promises future, for
  their condition, much less than that of the island to Cuba and other
parts of America, maintains a state of continuous depreciation.

  
  
  What is and how the wealth of a people, which gives a country's
  future, in addition to the natural elements is their population,
  and this is what I mainly need to rule Don Pedro II.
  
  His vicious laws of colonization, its climate, few attractions
  offered by the European, the lack of guarantees that ensure compliance
with the promises made by their agents to Europeans who want to emigrate,
are causes powerful European retract want to emigrate to Brazil whose
country, with a vast territory, larger than Europe whole day today
has not complete seven million inhabitants, of whom two are blacks.

  
  

  Completed its railroads, and increased its population, Brazil
  have a rich future.

  
  Brazil is in favor of the constitutional party Empire and the Republican
  side.
  
  As a new town, which has just entered public life of
  nations, has a policy that serves sincerity which are carried out
  on representative forms part of his life constitutional only way
  that the Empire exists. The policy that is outside has
  nothing constitutional aims to emulate the so-called free
  government the United States, following in his footsteps,
  made in America South, which the Republic of Washington
  in the North; predominates in neighboring states, influences policy
and tends to the continuous enlargement, although this is must break
laws and attack the independence of peoples.

  
  
  This is the policy of the governments of Brazil and Montevideo, Buenos-Aires
  and Paraguay: awkward sycophants have been led to believe Governments
  of Don Pedro II that Brazil could and should continue the conduct
  of the United States, I had to do in the South as they practice
  in the North, and that being the two peoples stronger of America
nothing more natural than go through the same way.

  
  
  Error! Gross error!

  Anglo-Saxon race that inhabit the North America has no analogy
  or remotely with the indefinable Latin degenerate Portuguese
  living in Brazil.
  
  The two towns are different in everything: energy, origin, in religion,
in laws, customs: the activity North Americans can only be compared
in a big way, with feature of the Brazilian sloth: they differ in
all absolutely everything, even the weather are opposites.

  
  
  Brazil does not widen its borders never, never, if today diplomats
  have been able to exert some influence on Plate republics, only
  the sad Debelo constant state of disturbance of their governments,
anarchy has full reign there today</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>