<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04696</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>274095</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23501</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Lo mismo pasaba con los vegetales.
Para que uno se lograse a fuerza de cuidados y desvelos, perecían treinta o cuarenta. La vigilancia
constante de los jardineros no bastaba a impedir esta considerable mortandad.

La casa, tampoco era de estilo nacional, ni siquiera europeo. Estaba construída según los preceptos
de la arquitectura chinesca, llena de torrecillas festonadas por todos lados. Qué conexión
tenían estas diminutas torres de ladrillo con la famosa de Babel, donde los idiomas se confundieron,
nosotros no lo sabemos; pero debemos manifestar que a esta fábrica así guarnecida, la llamaban
en el país la Babilonia de don Rosendo. Estaba suntuosamente amueblada. No faltaba dentro de
ella ninguna de las comodidades y refinamientos que la moderna civilización proporciona a los
ricos. Tenía una famosa habitación decorada al estilo persa, cuarto de baño, un espacioso comedor
medianamente pintado y algunos lindos gabinetes pequeños y tibios, donde la luz entraba cernida
por cristales de colores.

A este nido vinieron a parar Gonzalo y Ventura dos horas después de hallarse unidos para siempre.
En el camino se habían hablado con desembarazo de cosas indiferentes. El joven había aplicado
algunos besos en las mejillas de la niña, lo mismo que cuando novios. Mas al llegar a la babilonia,
y encontrarse solos en la cámara persa, sintióse extrañamente confuso y acortado. Buscaba asuntos
de conversación, y en todos se perdía. Venturita apenas le contestaba mirándole de reojo, con
una expresión entre burlona y apasionada.

--Mira, ¡calla, calla! Estás diciendo muchas tonterías... Calla, y dame un beso--concluyó por
decirle riendo, y tapándole la boca con su primorosa mano.

Gonzalo se puso colorado, y la abrazó con frenesí.

Su embriaguez en los primeros días rayó en locura. Venturita era, por su belleza singular,
por la expresión lánguida y voluptuosa de sus ojos, por la tendencia invencible al descanso,
una verdadera odalisca. Pero no como éstas solamente un animal hermoso, sino animada por ingenio
chispeante, que desbordaba a cada momento en graciosos equívocos y felices ocurrencias. Gonzalo
se desternillaba de risa, sin comprender que es peligroso que los maridos rían demasiado los
chistes de sus mujeres.

La vida que hacían era harto sedentaria. A Ventura no le gustaba salir de casa. El sol le producía
dolor de cabeza; el fresco de la tarde le irritaba la garganta. Cuidaba del aliño de su persona,
y variaba de trajes lo mismo que si se hallase en Madrid. En su tocador pasaba una gran parte
del día. Esto no disgustaba a Gonzalo. Al contrario, cuando la veía salir tan linda y gallarda,
exhalando, como las flores tropicales, un perfume penetrante, sentíase poseído de entusiasmo.
Un estremecimiento voluptuoso agitaba todo su ser, pensando que aquella obra exquisita de la
Naturaleza era suya, enteramente suya.

Sin embargo, no lo era tanto como él se figuraba. Algunas veces la joven esposa, medio en serio,
medio en broma, se encerraba en su cuarto. Allí pasaba tres o cuatro horas sin consentir que
entrase, a pesar de los ruegos cariñosos que le dirigía por el agujero de la llave.

--Te privo de mi vista por algún tiempo--decía después riendo,--para que desees más el tenerme
junto a ti.

Y, en efecto, por medio de estas coqueterías, el apetito del joven crecía extremadamente, y
se convertía en delirio.

A las horas que bien le placía a la hermosa, salían a pasear por los jardines, sin alejarse
mucho. Al llegar a algún sitio umbrío y fresco, de los pocos que la mano reformista de don
Rosendo había dejado, la niña quería sentarse; pero no sobre la hierba ni sobre un banco rústico.
Era menester que Gonzalo corriese a casa y trajese una butaca.

--Ahora, siéntate aquí a mis pies.

El mancebo se postraba y besaba con entusiasmo los manos que la gentil esposa le tendía.

--¡Sansón y Dalila!--exclamaba ella riendo y hundiendo sus manos como copos de nieve en la
rubia y rizada barba de su marido.

--Tienes razón--respondía él dando un suspiro.--Un Sansón sin cabellos.

--¡Qué no tienes cabellos!... ¿Y esto qué es?--replicaba levantando su pelo, y poniéndolo erizado
como una escoba.

--Hablo de mis fuerzas.

--¿No tienes fuerzas, eh? A ver: saque usted esos brazos.

El, riendo, se despojaba de la americana, y remangándose la camisa mostraba sus brazos enormes
de gladiador, donde la musculatura tomaba brioso relieve como un espeso tejido de cuerdas.

--¡Qué barbaridad!--exclamaba la niña cogiendo uno con ambas manos, sin lograr ni con mucho
abarcarlo. Y poseída de repentino entusiasmo y admiración, añadía:

--¡Qué fuerte, qué hermoso eres, Gonzalo! Déjame morderte esos brazos.

Y se inclinaba para hincar sus dientes menudísimos en ellos. Pero el mancebo tendía sus férreos
músculos, y los dientes resbalaban por la piel sin penetrarla.

Entonces ella se enfadaba, insistía, quería a todo trance coger carne. Al cabo, él aflojaba
los músculos diciendo:

--Te dejo morder; pero a condición de que me hagas sangre.

--No, eso no--respondía ella, expresando en la sonrisa anhelante el deseo de hacerlo.

-Sí, quiero que me hagas sangre; si no, no te dejo.

La niña empezaba apretando poco a poco la carne de su marido.

--¡Más!--decía éste.

Y apretaba más.

--¡Más!--volvía a decir.

Seguía apretando mientras en sus ojos chispeaba una sonrisa maliciosa.

--¡Más! ¡más!

--Basta--decía ella levantándose.--¿Lo ves? ¡ya te hice sangre! ¡Qué atrocidad, ni que fuese
un perro!

E inclinándose de nuevo, chupaba con afán voluptuoso la gotita de sangre que saltaba en el
brazo. Ambos sonreían con pasión reprimida. Después miraban al pequeño círculo cárdeno que
los dientes de la niña habían dejado impreso.

--¿Lo ves?--volvía a decir ella avergonzada.--¡Vaya unos caprichos extraños los que tienes!

--Gracias. Quisiera que esta marca quedase, ahí eternamente. Pero no; ¡bien pronto se borrará,
por desgracia!

--Puedo renovarla a diario--replicó maliciosamente.

--Me alegraría mucho.

--Vamos, tú quieres convertir a tu mujer en perrita. Dilo francamente.

Y abrazándole repentinamente, y besándole con frenesí en los ojos, en las mejillas, en la boca,
en la barba, le repetía sin cesar:

--¡Dilo francamente! ¡Dilo francamente, pedazo de oso!... Esta boca es mía, y la beso. Esta
barba es mía, y también la beso. Este cuello es mío, y lo beso. Estos brazos son míos, ¡míos!
y los beso.

--Tómame todo: mi vida es tuya--decía él ebrio de dicha.

--Te quiero, te quiero, Gonzalo, por lo hermoso, por lo fuerte... A ver, déjame poner una mano
sobre la tuya... Qué disparate, ¡parece una hormiga!

--Una hormiga blanca--replicaba él ahogando aquella diminuta mano entre las suyas grandes y
fibrosas.

--Te quiero, te quiero, Gonzalo. Tómame en brazos. ¿Serás capaz de pasear conmigo así?

--¡Oh! ¿no he de ser?

La levantó como una pluma, y poniéndola sobre un brazo como a los niños, comenzó a dar brincos
por el jardín.

--¡No tanto! Llévame suavemente. Vamos de paseo.

La paseó sin fatigarse por todo el parque. Y desde aquel día aquella forma de paseo le agradó
tanto a la niña, que en cuanto salían de casa se colgaba al cuello de su marido para que la
subiese. Los criados al verlos movían la cabeza sonriendo.

Pero muy pronto descubrió otro medio de pasarlo aún mejor. Había cerca de casa un columpio
que el tiempo, más que el uso, había deteriorado. Hizo que se arreglase, y en cuanto lo tuvo
presto se pasaba las horas mecida por Gonzalo.

--Si vieras cómo gozo. Da un poco más fuerte.

Y al empuje vigoroso del joven, el columpio volaba, y la niña cerraba los ojos dilatando la
nariz con un sentimiento de intenso placer.

Gonzalo gozaba en verla así arrobada.

Transcurrieron veinte días de esta suerte. Durante ellos recibieron dos visitas de Pablito
y Piscis, una vez en tílburi y otra a caballo. En esta última su principal objeto era dar picadero
a una jaca que Pablo había cambiado por otra más vieja. Y ¡cosa extraña! a pesar del enajenamiento
amoroso en que nuestro mancebo se hallaba, recibió la visita de los équites con inexplicable
alegría, les ayudó afanosamente en su tarea. Al marcharse sintió una impresión de vacío en
su vida. Porque era ésta tan reposada y pacífica, que su sangre y sus músculos padecían. Un
día le habló a su esposa de ir de caza, pues era famoso e incansable cazador. Venturita no
se opuso, con tal que la llevase consigo. Así se convino. Salieron una mañana en busca de un
bando de perdices, de cuya existencia sabía Gonzalo desde el día en que había llegado a Tejada.
Pero antes de alejarse dos kilómetros de la casa, Venturita se manifestó enteramente rendida.
Le era imposible dar un paso más. Se vió precisado a traerla en brazos y a renunciar a su favorito
recreo.

Doña Paula, que había mirado con hostilidad aquel matrimonio, no habló de ir a ver a los novios
hasta después de pasados muchos días. Quiso que Pablito la acompañase, porque temía que a Cecilia
le causase algún dolor el hacerlo; mas, enterada ésta, expresó su decisión de ir también a
Tejada. Y una tarde madre e hija emprendieron en carretela descubierta el camino que llevaba
a la posesión. Pero al acercarse a ella y columbrar las famosas torrecillas de ladrillo, Cecilia
comenzó a empalidecer, sintió el pecho oprimido y la vista turbada. Doña Paula, que advirtió
su indisposición, ordenó al cochero dar la vuelta.

--¡Pobre hija!--la dijo besándola.--¿Ves cómo no puedes venir?

--Ya podré, mamá, ya podré--respondió tapándose los ojos con una mano.

Al día siguiente, fué doña Paula acompañada de Pablo. Halló a los esposos muy propicios a dejar
aquel nido escondido y trasladarse a la villa; como se efectuó en la misma semana.

Cecilia salió a recibirlos a la puerta de la calle y abrazó y besó a su hermana con efusión.
A Gonzalo, le tendió la mano, que por un esfuerzo soberano de la voluntad, no tembló. El joven
la estrechó con fraternal afecto, creyéndose perdonado.

Los novios ocuparon las habitaciones que doña Paula había destinado a su hija primogénita.
La vida comenzó a deslizarse serena en apariencia. Gonzalo advertía, no obstante, con pesar,
que no les envolvía esa atmósfera tibia y afectuosa que hace tan grato el hogar doméstico.
Desde don Rosendo hasta el último criado, se mostraban con ellos atentos, deferentes, no cariñosos.
Ventura no lo advertía, y si lo advertía le importaba poco.

Volvamos ahora la vista a los asuntos más interesantes de la vida pública de Sarrió.

Ganada aquella noble victoria de los clérigos, las cosas del Faro de Sarrió, procedían bien
y prósperamente. El brioso y denodado ayudante de marina, pudo continuar su campaña civilizadora
sin peligro de nuevas celadas. Sinforoso no se retiraba, sin embargo, a su casa sin ir acompañado
de él o de otro amigo, perfectamente armados ambos.

Pero Gabino Maza, el eterno disidente, supo aprovechar maliciosamente aquella ruptura con la
Iglesia, para sobresaltar las conciencias de algunos vecinos. No que él fuese católico ferviente,
ni le diese una higa por que se pusiera a los curas como hoja de perejil. Al contrario, toda
la vida había profesado ideas bastante heterodoxas y había maldecido de los beatos. Mas ahora
se mostraba escandalizado: «Al fin y al cabo, habíamos sido educados en el respeto de la religión,
la cual es el único freno para el pueblo. No se pueden ofender tan descaradamente las sagradas
creencias de nuestras esposas, etc., etc.» Algunos con estas pérfidas insinuaciones, dejaron
la suscripción del periódico.

Los redactores y su director, que adivinaban de dónde venía el golpe, estaban grandemente indignados.
Gabino Maza, secundado por el no menos díscolo Delaunay, no cejaba en su campaña de murmuración.
Mientras alguno de los del Faro estaba delante, nada; pero en cuanto se iba, esgrimían las
lenguas con singular encarnizamiento. Unas veces hablando en serio, otras apelando a la burla,
se trituraba a todos los que intervenían en el periódico, y muy particularmente, como es lógico,
al que mejor y más altamente lo personificaba, el eximio don Rosendo. Decían ¡oh, mengua! que
sólo el afán «de verse en letras de molde» había impulsado a aquellos beneméritos ciudadanos
a encender la antorcha del progreso en Sarrió; que don Rufo, el médico, era un farsante; Sinforoso,
un pobrete a quien arrojaban un mendrugo; Alvaro Peña (aquí bajaban la voz y miraban a todos
lados), un botarate sin pizca de juicio; don Feliciano Gómez, un pobre diablo a quien más importaba
ocuparse en sus negocios no muy florecientes; don Rudesindo, un gran cazurro, que trataba de
alquilar su almacén y anunciar su sidra. En cuanto al fundador y promovedor de aquella empresa,
don Rosendo, decían que toda la vida había sido un badulaque, un necio que se creía escritor,
sin entender de otra cosa que del alza y baja del bacalao...

Sólo el deber imperioso de aparecer como cronistas fieles e imparciales, nos obliga a dar cuenta
de tales habladurías. Bien sabe Dios que ha sido con harto trabajo y disgusto. Porque la misma
pluma se estremece en nuestras manos y se niega a estampar semejantes abominaciones.

De don Pedro Miranda, absteníanse de murmurar los murmuradores, no por otra razón sino por
tenerle solicitado para que dejase la participación en el periódico, a lo cual le veían inclinarse
desde la refriega de los clérigos; pues era don Pedro cristiano viejo y muy grande amigo del
capellán de las Agustinas. Con sus malévolos discursos, habían logrado desatar contra el periódico
a algunas damas influyentes de la villa, entre ellas doña Brígida. Con esto tuvieron por suyo
dentro del Saloncillo al sandio y degradado Marín. También atrajeron a su bando, poco después,
al borracho del alcalde. Por una parte el espíritu de compañerismo con los tertulios de la
tienda de la Morana, y por otra la molestia que sentía con las constantes excitaciones de la
prensa, a las que no estaba acostumbrado, le hicieron renegar pronto de aquel gran adelanto.
Lo que acabó de ponerle mal con El Faro y sus redactores, fué cierta gacetilla en que se censuraba
al ayuntamiento y al alcalde con alguna dureza, por el lamentable abandono en que tenían los
servicios de policía urbana, y lo poco que trabajaban por hacer agradable la temporada de verano
«a los distinguidos escrofulosos que acudían a la playa de Sarrió en busca de salud».

Aunque aparentemente se trataban como amigos, existía, pues, entre los socios principales del
Saloncillo sorda y disimulada enemiga. Iba ésta aumentando de día en día merced a los correveidiles
que, en ocasiones análogas, no cesan de sembrar envidias y rencores. Temíanse ya las disputas
y se rehuían, porque los desaforados gritos y los baldones que antes se lanzaban sin resultado
alguno, gracias a la cordial avenencia que existía entre todos, eran, al presente, de mucho
peligro. Reinaba, por tanto, en aquel recinto, más silencio, más cortesía, pero muchísima menos
franqueza y cordialidad.

Aquella tirantez no podía durar mucho tiempo. Entre personas que todos los días se ven y se
hablan, y no se quieren bien, es imposible que en breve plazo no deje de estallar la discordia.
La ocasión fué ésta. Llegó al Saloncillo (¡noramala fué!), sin saber quién lo trajera, un ejemplar
de cierta Ilustración catalana, donde, entre otros grabados, se veía uno representando las
orillas de un río americano, y en ellas solazándose hasta una docena de cocodrilos de diversos
tamaños. Tenía el ejemplar en la mano Maza, cuando acercándose don Rufo por detrás, exclamó
en tono jocoso:

--¡Vaya unos cocodrilos escuálidos!

--No son cocodrilos--manifestó Maza en tono seco y desdeñoso, sin levantar la cabeza.

--¿Y por qué no han de ser?--preguntó el médico herido por aquel tono.

--Porque no.

--¡Valiente razón!

--Si no te convence, estudia, que yo no estoy aquí para hacer obras de misericordia.

--¡Uf! ¡El sabio de la Grecia! ¡Apartarse a un lado, señores!

--No soy un sabio, pero no digo que estos animales son cocodrilos, cuando en el río Marañón
no se crían cocodrilos.

--¿Qué son entonces?

--Caimanes.

--¡Llámalo hache! Caimanes y cocodrilos vienen a ser lo mismo.

--¡Otra barbaridad! ¿Dónde has aprendido eso?

--Hombre, es de clavo pasado. El caimán y el cocodrilo no se diferencian más que en el nombre.
Aquí está don Lorenzo que ha viajado, y puede decir si no es verdad.

--El caimán es algo más pequeño--expresó don Lorenzo con sonrisa conciliadora.

--El tamaño es de poca importancia. La cuestión es saber si tiene o no la misma figura.

Don Lorenzo se inclinó en señal de asentimiento. Maza saltó, hecho una furia:

--Pero, señores. ¡Pero, señores! ¿Estamos entre personas ilustradas o entre aldeanos? ¿De dónde
sacan ustedes que caimán es lo mismo que cocodrilo? El cocodrilo es un animal del Mundo Viejo
y el caimán es del Nuevo Mundo.

--Dispénseme usted, amigo Maza; yo he visto cocodrilos en Filipinas--manifestó don Rudesindo.

--¿Y qué quiere usted decir con eso?

--Como usted decía que los cocodrilos no se crían en el Nuevo Mundo...

--¡Otra que tal! ¿Las Filipinas son del Nuevo Mundo? Señores, ¡señores! hay que abrir los paraguas.
Hoy llueven aquí burradas.

--Pues qué, ¿Filipinas querrá usted decirme que no es Ultramar?--preguntó don Rudesindo con
la faz descompuesta.

--¡Nada, nada, siga el chaparrón!

--La diferencia principal, señores, que existe entre el cocodrilo y el caimán--dijo a esta
sazón con autoridad don Lorenzo--es que el cocodrilo tiene tres carreras de dientes y el caimán
sólo tiene dos.

--¡No es eso, hombre, no es eso! Los cocodrilos tienen las mismas carreras de dientes que los
caimanes.

Don Lorenzo sostuvo con brío su aserto. Le ayudó en la defensa don Rudesindo. Maza le atacó
con no menos fuego, apoyado por Delaunay. Pronto entraron en liza otros cuantos socios generalizándose
el combate, que fué haciéndose cada vez más vivo. Las voces eran horrendas. Si hubieran poseído
tres carreras de dientes como los cocodrilos, o aunque fuesen dos, no dudo que se devorarían,
dada la rabia y el coraje con que se enseñaban la única con que la Naturaleza les había dotado.
Maza estuvo tan procaz, tan insolente, que al fin don Rudesindo, sin ser dueño de sí, le descargó
un paraguazo en la cabeza. Siguióse a éste una granizada de ellos entre los contendientes,
con un pavoroso estruendo de ballenas y varillas de alambre que daba escalofríos al varón más
arriscado. Muchos, que no se habían acordado siquiera de emitir su opinión sobre la dentadura
de los reptiles citados, recibieron su parte alícuota de paraguazos, lo mismo que los que más
habían esclarecido la cuestión con sus discursos. Subieron del café el amo con algunas otras
personas; suspendieron los indianos del billar su juego; terció don Melchor de las Cuevas,
de quien así en guerra como en paz se hacía mucho caso. Al cabo se logró apaciguar el alboroto
ya que no concertar las voluntades, hacía algunos meses resfriadas.

El resultado fué que desde aquel día Gabino Maza, Delaunay, don Roque, Marín y otros tres o
cuatro socios más, se retiraron del Saloncillo. Don Pedro Miranda siguió asistiendo con largos
intervalos de ausencia. Esto hacía presumir a los tertulios restantes y a los redactores del
Faro que no podía contarse con él, y que no tardaría mucho en caer del lado contrario. Como
sucedió en efecto. Los disidentes empezaron a reunirse en el café de Londres situado en la
calle de Caborana. Pero no muchos meses después corrió por la villa la noticia de que alquilaban
un almacén en la calle de San Florencio para establecer sus reuniones. Y así fué. Lo entarimaron,
lo alfombraron, después pintaron sus paredes y su techo, amuebláronlo con algunas sillas y
butacas, pusieron mesas de tresillo y comenzaron a asistir tarde y noche a aquel sitio tan
asiduamente como antes al Saloncillo. Por ser bajo de techo y tener embutida en la pared una
litera que sirvió para dormir la siesta Marín, empezó a llamarse a aquel sitio en la población
el Camarote, y este nombre le quedó. Los del Faro, que habían desdeñado a los desertores mientras
no tenían techo donde guarecerse, entraron en cuidado. El primer síntoma de temor fué una gacetilla
o novela a la mano en verso-prosa describiendo aquella nueva tertulia y pintando a cada uno
de sus socios con nombres de animales; Maza la víbora, Delaunay un gallo belga, Marín el jumento,
don Roque el cerdo, etcétera, etc. Esta gacetilla exasperó a los del Camarote de un modo indecible.

Don Rosendo continuaba cada vez más pujante y empeñado en su campaña periodística. Introducía
en el Faro todas aquellas formas y maneras que observaba en la prensa nacional y extranjera,
particularmente en la francesa. Había comisionado a un escritor de Madrid para que los miércoles
le remitiese un telegrama de veinte palabras, y le escribiese además cartas políticas y literarias;
traducía él todas las noticias curiosas que hallaba en los periódicos; hacía revistas de modas,
de tribunales, de teatros (cuando había compañía). Pero donde más se distinguía era en las
de mercados. No es fácil representarse la destreza con que manejaba, traía y llevaba los cereales,
los aceites, los caldos y los arroces. Para que se vea con qué amenidad y galanura sabía tratar
un asunto tan prosaico, diremos que en una ocasión escribía: «Las mieles, sensibles a estas
alteraciones, se pronunciaron en baja y no alcanzaron estabilidad y firmeza en sus precios
hasta que los cafés, los cacaos y demás géneros ultramarinos lograron reprimir sus vivas oscilaciones.»
Era, en suma, el alma del periódico.

No bastaba, sin embargo, lo que había hecho para ponerlo a la altura de su ideal. Belinchón
siempre había seguido con vivísimo interés en los periódicos de París aquellas polémicas personales
que rara vez dejaban de terminar con un duelo. Y las peripecias de éste, contadas minuciosamente
por algún testigo, le placían tan extremadamente, que ninguna comida había para él tan sabrosa,
ni más grato recreo. Cuando pasaban muchos días sin desafío, don Rosendo languidecía. Las descripciones
de los asaltos de armas entre los célebres tiradores de la capital de Francia, excitaban también
grandemente su curiosidad. Y aunque un poco se le enredaban en el magín aquellas frases técnicas
engagement de sixte, battement en quarte, contre-riposte, feinte, etc., allá las traducía a
su modo y se daba por enterado. Decía él que en ningún signo se conocía mejor el grado de cultura
de un país que en la afición a las armas. El manejo de ellas despertaba o avivaba la idea del
honor y la dignidad humana. Su abandono arrastraba consigo la cobardía y la degradación. Conocía
mejor que sus parientes la biografía de los grandes duelistas y gens des armes de París. Podía
describir con pelos y señales los desafíos que habían tenido y la gravedad de las heridas.
En cuanto se anunciaba un asalto entre dos maestros, por ejemplo Jacob y Grisier, ya estaba
nuestro caballero excitado. Abría con precipitación todos los días el Fígaro y apostaba en
su interior por uno o por otro.

Un día se le ocurrió en la cama (donde le asaltaban siempre las grandes ideas) que ser periodista
sin conocer las armas o manejarlas, era lo mismo que ser bailarín y no tocar las castañuelas.
El día menos pensado se suscitaba un lance, había que acudir al terreno, y él no sabía siquiera
ponerse en guardia. Verdad que en todo Sarrió no había quien supiese más. Pero nadie tenía
tanta obligación de conocer la esgrima como él. Además, el altercado podía ser con un periodista
de Lancia o de Madrid, y entonces era preciso dejarse asesinar. Estas imaginaciones le llevaron
a adoptar una resolución; la de aprender a toda costa a tirar el florete. ¿Cómo? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02576</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>54578</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21008</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> So were the vegetables. For one to be
achieved by dint of care and vigilance, thirty or forty perished. Surveillance constant gardener was
not enough to prevent the considerable mortality.

The house style was not a national or even European. Was built according to the precepts chinoiserie
architecture, full of towers festooned everywhere. What connection had these tiny brick towers with
the famous Babel, where languages ??were confused, we do not know, but we must say that this works
well trimmed, they called Babylon in the country of Don Rosendo. It was lavishly furnished.
No missing within it none of the comforts and refinements of modern civilization provides rich.
He was a famous Persian-style decorated room, bathroom, a spacious dining moderately cabinets painted
and some nice small and warm, where the light came sifted colored crystals.

In this nest came to stop and Ventura Gonzalo two hours of being together forever. On the way he had
spoken to disengage from things indifferent. The young man had applied some kisses on the cheeks
of the girl, the same as when lovers. But to get to the Babylonian and finding themselves alone in
the Persian camera, felt strangely confused and shortened. Search Subject conversation, and all was
lost. Venturita barely looked at him askance replied with expression between mocking and passionate.

-
Look, shut up, shut up!

You're saying a lot of nonsense ... Shut up and kiss me - concluded by say laughing and covering
her mouth with her delicate hand.

Gonzalo blushed, and hugged her frenzy.

His drunkenness in the early days bordered on madness. Venturita was, by its singular beauty the
languid, sensual expression of their eyes, the invincible tendency to break, true odalisque. But
not like these only a beautiful animal, but animated by wit sparkling, overflowing all the time
in funny misunderstandings and happy occurrences.

Gonzalo is roaring with laughter, not realizing that it is dangerous to husbands laugh too much jokes
about their wives.

The life you did was quite sedentary. A Ventura did not like leaving home. The sun produces headache;
the cool of the evening was irritated throat. Dressing took care of him, and varied costumes
same as if he were in Madrid. In her dressing spent a large part the day. This is not disliked
Gonzalo.

On the contrary, when I saw so beautiful and graceful exit, breathing, such as tropical flowers,
a penetrating perfume, felt himself possessed of enthusiasm. A voluptuous shudder shook her
whole being, thinking that this exquisite work of Nature was his, all its own.

However, it was not as much as he imagined.

Sometimes the young wife, half in earnest, half in jest, was locked in his room. They spent
three or four hours without allowing enter, despite the loving prayers
that reverberate in the keyhole.

- I deprive myself of my sight for
some time - said after laughing, - for having me want more with you.

And indeed, through these flirtations, the appetite grew extremely young, and became delirious.

In the hours that it pleased him to beautiful, went for a walk through
the gardens, without departing much.

To get somewhere shady and cool, of the few reformist hand gift Rosendo
had left, she wanted to sit, but not on the grass or on a rustic bench.

Gonzalo was a need to run home and bring a chair.

- Now, sit here at my feet.

The youth prostrated himself and kissed her hands enthusiastically
handed him the gentle wife.

- Samson and Delilah! - She exclaimed,
laughing and thrusting his hands like snowflakes in the curly blond
beard of her husband.

- You're right - he responded with a sigh .--
A bald Samson.

- Do not have hair!

... So what is this? - Replied by raising his hair, and putting bristling
as a broom.

- I speak of my strength.

- Do not have forces, eh?

Let's see: you take those arms.

The laughing, is stripped of his jacket, rolled up his sleeves and
showed his huge arms Gladiator, which took vigorous muscle relief
as a thick web of ropes.

- Good lord! - Taking one girl exclaimed
with both hands, unable to even come embrace.

And suddenly possessed of enthusiasm and admiration, he added:

- How strong, how beautiful you are, Gonzalo! Let me bite those arms.

And she bent to sink their teeth menudísimos them.

But the youth spread their ferrous muscles, and teeth slipped through the skin without penetrating.

Then
she got angry, he insisted, wanted by all means take meat.

After all, he loosened muscles saying

- I leave bite, but on condition that make me blood.

- No, that's
not - she answered, smiling eagerly expressing the desire to do so.

"Yes, I want to do blood and if not, do not leave.

The girl started slowly pressing the flesh of her husband.

- More!
- He said.

And tighter.

- More! - Again say.

While still squeezing his eyes sparkled with a mischievous smile.

- More! More!

- Basta - she said .-- rising See it? And made you blood!

What atrocity, and it was a dog!

I bent down and sucked eagerly voluptuous droplet of blood that leaped in the arm. Both smiled
with repressed passion. After looking at the small circle of blue that teeth of the girl had
stopped printing.

- You see? - Say it again .-- Go embarrassed about
the strange quirks of yours!

- Thanks.

I want this mark stay, there forever.

But no soon be deleted, alas!

- I can renew it every day - he replied mischievously.

- I would be delighted.

- Come on, you want to turn your woman on dog. Say frankly.

And suddenly hugging and kissing him wildly in his eyes, cheeks, mouth,
on the chin, he kept repeating:

- Say it honestly!

Say frankly, a piece of bear! ... This mouth is mine, and kiss. This beard is mine, and kissed
her. This neck is mine, and kissed him. These arms are mine, mine! and kiss.

- Take me everything: my life is yours - he said that drunk.

- I love you I love you, Gonzalo, so beautiful, so strong ... Let's
see, let me put a hand on yours ... What nonsense, seems an ant!

-
A white ant - he replied that drowning tiny hand in his large fibrous.

-
I love you I love you, Gonzalo.

Take me in your arms.

Can you walk with me as well?

- Oh! I not be?

Lifted like a feather, and put on one arm and children, began jumping up in the garden.

- Not so much! Take me gently. Let's ride.

The fatigue-walked around the park. And from that day for a walk that way liked both the girl,
who left the house as it hung around the neck of her husband to the go up. The servants shook
their heads at them smiling.

But she soon found other means even more fun. There was a swing close to home that time, rather
than use, had deteriorated. He had arranged, and as it was spent hours soon rocked by Gonzalo.

- If you saw how joy. It's a little stronger.

And the vigorous drive of the young, flying swing, and she closed her eyes dilating nose with
a feeling of intense pleasure.

Gonzalo enjoyed seeing her so enraptured.

Passed twenty days of this sort.

During that received two visits Pablito and Pisces, once in tilbury
and another horse.

In the latter into its main purpose was to riding a pony that Paul had changed to another older.
And strange! despite the alienation love that our boy was, he was
visited by Equitable with inexplicable joy, eagerly helped in his
task.

When he left he felt a sense of emptiness in his life. Because it was so calm and peaceful,
their blood and muscles suffering. A day he told his wife to go hunting, he was famous and tireless
hunter. Venturita not opposed, provided it with you.

This was agreed. They went out one morning to find a flock of partridges, whose existence
Gonzalo knew from the day he had come to Tejada. But before two kilometers away from the house,
rendered entirely Venturita said. He could not go a step further. Was obliged to bring in
arms and give up your favorite recreation.

Dona Paula, who had looked with hostility the marriage, it talked
about going to see the bride and groom until after many days past.

Pablito wanted to accompany her, fearing that Cecilia will cause some pain to do so, but, aware
it said his decision to go also Tejada. One afternoon mother and daughter in a carriage undertaken
discovered the path leading possession. But as he approached her and descry the famous brick turrets,
Cecilia began to fade, she felt her breast and troubled eye.

Dona Paula, who warned his illness, ordered the driver to turn around.

- Poor child! - The kissing said .-- See how you can not come?

- Because I can, Mom, I'll be able - said covering his eyes with one hand.

The next day, was accompanied by Paul Dona Paula. Found a very enabling spouses to leave hiding
the nest and move into the villa, as was done in the same week.

Cecilia left her at the front door and hugged and kissed his sister with effusion. A Gonzalo,
held out his hand, which for a sovereign effort of will, not shaken. The young pressed with brotherly
affection, believing forgiven.

The couple occupied the rooms that Dona Paula had gone into their first child. Life began to
slide serene appearance. Gonzalo warned, however, with regret, they do not wrap the warm and loving
atmosphere that makes it so pleasing the domestic hearth. From Don Rosendo to the last servant,
showed them attentive, deferential, not loving. Ventura not warned, and warned if he cared little.

Let
us now view the most interesting issues of public life Sarrió.

That noble victory won clerics, things Sarrió Lighthouse, came well and prosper. The spirited
and intrepid naval aide was able to continue its civilizing campaign
without danger of new traps.

Sinforoso not withdraw, however, to his home unless accompanied him or another friend, both well
armed.

But Gabino Maza, the eternal dissident maliciously took advantage of this break with Church,
to shock the consciences of some neighbors. Not that he was a fervent Catholic, nor give a damn that
you put the priests and parsley leaf. On the contrary, all life had professed quite unorthodox
ideas and had cursed the blessed. But now showed shocked: "At last, after all, had been raised in
respect of religion, which is the only check on the people. You can not blatantly offend the
sacred beliefs of our wives, etc., etc. "Some of these perfidious insinuations, left newspaper
subscription.

The writers and director, who guessed where it came from the coup, were greatly incensed. Gabino
Maza, supported by no less wayward Delaunay, not give up its campaign of slander. While some of the
Lighthouse was before, nothing, but as he went, brandishing the languages ??with singular ferocity.
Sometimes serious, others appeal to ridicule, was ground to all those involved in the newspaper,
and particularly, of course, the best and most highly personified
as the virtuoso Don Rosendo.

They said oh, wanes! that only the desire "to be in print" had led to those deserving citizens
to light the torch of progress in Sarrió, Don Rufo, the doctor was a fraud; Sinforoso, a pauper who
threw a crust; Alvaro Peña (here the voice and looked down at all sides), a trial without a hint
of smarty, Don Feliciano Gómez, a poor devil who mattered most not engage in a thriving business,
Don Rudesindo, a large taciturn, which was rent a store and announce their cider. As the founder
and promoter of that company, Don Rosendo, said that all life had been a Badulaque, a fool who
believed writer without understanding anything other than the rise
and fall of cod ...

Only imperative duty to appear as faithful and
impartial chroniclers, forces us to realize of such talk.

God knows who has been with hard work and disgust. Because the same pen trembles in our hands
and refuse to print such abominations.

Don Pedro Miranda, absteníanse of the whisperers whisper, for no other reason but have you
applied for leave to participate in the newspaper, which saw him bow from the fray of the clergy,
as was Don Pedro and very large old Christian friend chaplain of the Augustinians. With their
malicious speeches had been made against the newspaper unleashing
some influential ladies of the town, including Dona Brigida.

This had at his of the Club within the madman and degraded Marín.

Also attracted to his side, soon after the drunk mayor.

On the one hand the spirit of fellowship with the circles of Morana
shop, and other discomfort I felt with the constant excitations press,
which was not used, will soon deny he made enormous progress.

What I ended up putting wrong with The Lighthouse and its editors,
was some press release that are censored City Hall and the mayor with
some hardness on the sad neglect that had the urban police services,
and how little work to do enjoyable summer "The distinguished scrofulous
attending Sarrió beach in search of health."

Although apparently were treated as friends, there was, therefore,
between the main partners Saloncillo deaf and hidden enemy.

It was increasing day by day thanks to the go-between that in similar cases, do not cease to
sow envy and resentment.

Temíanse and disputes and shunned because the monstrous cries and
hurled insults previously without success any thanks to the compromise
that was friendly to all, were, at present, much danger.

There was, therefore, in that place, more silence, more courtesy,
but far less frankness and cordiality.

That tension could not last long. Among people who are daily and speak, and do not want it is impossible
that in the near future be sure to burst contention. The occasion
was this.

Reached Saloncillo (was poor chance!), Without knowing who bring
a copy Illustration of some Catalan, where, among other prints, looked
one representing the American banks of a river, and amuse them up
to a dozen crocodiles of various sizes.

Had in hand exemplary Maza, when Don Rufo approaching from behind, said jokingly:

- Look at those skinny crocodiles!

- There are crocodiles - Maza said dryly contemptuous, without looking
up.

- Why not to be? - Said the doctor injured by that tone.

- Why
not.

- Valiente right!

- If you're not convinced, considering that
I'm not here to do works of mercy.

- Ugh!

The sage of Greece! To one side, gentlemen!

- I am not a scientist, but do not say that these animals are crocodiles,
when the Marañón River not bred crocodiles.

- What are they?

- Cayman.

-
Call hache!

Alligators and crocodiles come to be the same.

- Another awful! Where did you learn that?

- Man, is last nail.

The alligator and the crocodile did not differ only in name. Here is Don Lorenzo has traveled,
and can tell if it is not true.

- The alligator is somewhat smaller - said Don Lorenzo with conciliatory smile.

- The size is of little importance. The question is whether or not the same figure.

Don Lorenzo bowed in assent. Maza jumped, in a rage:

- But, gentlemen. But, gentlemen! Are we among enlightened people or among villagers? Where you
take that alligator is like crocodile? The crocodile is an animal of the Old World and the alligator
is the New World.

- Excuse me, friend Maza, I have seen crocodiles in the Philippines - said Don Rudesindo.

- What do you mean by that?

- As you said that crocodiles are not reared in the New World ...

- Other than this! "The Philippines is the New World? Gentlemen, gentlemen! have to open their
umbrellas. Nonsense raining here today.

- Why, do you want to say that the Philippines is not overseas? - Asked Don Rudesindo with the
face was broken.

- Nothing, nothing, follow the shower!

- The main difference, gentlemen, between the crocodile and the alligator - "here Don Lorenzo
seasoning authority - is that the crocodile has three races and the alligator teeth only two.

-
Not that, man, is not it! Crocodiles have the same teeth as racing alligators.

Don Lorenzo said briskly his assertion. We helped in the defense don Rudesindo. Maza attacked him no
less fire, supported by Delaunay. Soon entered the fray a few other partners generalized combat,
which was becoming more alive. The voices were horrendous. If they had possessed three races of teeth
such as crocodiles, or even if they were two, no doubt would devour,
Given the anger and the courage with which they taught the only with
which Nature had endowed them.

Maza was so impudent, insolent, who finally Rudesindo gift, without being master of himself,
he downloaded an umbrella on his head. Ensued him a hail of them among the contenders, with
an awful sound of whales and wire rods that the man was shivering more Arriscado. Many who had not
even agreed to give its opinion on the teeth the reptiles mentioned, received its share of umbrella,
as well as the most had clarified the matter with their speeches. Coffee rose the master with some
other people, the Indians stopped their game of pool, broke in Don Melchor de las Cuevas from
whom and in war and peace is a long case. Finally he managed to defuse the uproar and conclude that
the will, for some months cold.

The result was that from that day Gabino Maza, Delaunay, Don Roque Marín and three or four
members were removed from the Club. Don Pedro Miranda continued to assist with long intervals of absence.
This was presumed to social gatherings and other editors Faro could
not count on him, and did not take long to fall on the opposite side.

As came into effect. Dissidents began meeting in the coffee house located in the Caborana street.
But not many months after the town ran the news that rented a warehouse across the street from San
Florencio to establish their meetings. And so it was. The parquet, carpeted it, then painted the
walls and ceiling, with some chairs and amuebláronlo armchairs, set up tables of triplets and began
attending evening and night to that site as assiduously as before the Club. As low ceiling and be embedded
in a wall litter was used to nap Marin, began calling the place in the population the cabin, and
the name stuck. The Lighthouse, which had spurned the deserters while had no roof to shelter, went
into care. The first sign of fear was a press hand or novel in verse, prose describing this
new gathering and painting each of its members with animal names, Maza the snake, a rooster Delaunay
Belgian Marín ass Roque pork, etc., etc. This press exasperated the cabin of an unspeakable way.

Don
Rosendo still growing strong and committed to his campaign journalism. Introduced Faro in all those
ways that have looked at the national and foreign press, particularly in French. Had commissioned
a writer in Madrid for Wednesday send her a message of twenty words, and I also write political
letters and literary; translated all the news he was curious in the newspapers made fashion
magazines, courts, theater (when there was company.) But where was most distinguished in the
markets.

It is not easy skill with which he drove, and had brought cereal, oils, broth and rice. In order
to see how amenity and gallantry knew how to treat a matter so commonplace, say he once wrote:
"The honey, sensitive to these alterations, spoke in low and did not reach stability and firmness
in prices until coffees, cocoas and other genera living overseas were able to suppress their
swings. " Was, in short, the soul of the newspaper.

It was not enough, however, what he had done to bring it up to your
ideal. Belinchón always followed with lively interest in the Paris
newspapers these personal controversies rarely left to end a duel.
And the adventures of this, carefully counted by a witness, it pleased
him so extremely, that no food was so delicious to him, no more pleasant
recreation. When many days passed without challenge, Don Rosendo languished.
Descriptions of assault weapons among shooters famous capital of France,
also excited greatly curious. And if a little is entangled in those
technical phrases Magin Sixt engagement, battement in quarte, contre-riposte,
feint, etc., back to the translated his way and was aware of it. He
said that no sign was better known the extent of culture of a country
in the hobby to arms. The handling of them woke up and fanned the
idea of honor and dignity. His retirement drew him of cowardice and
degradation. Knew better than their relatives the biography of the
greatest duelists and armes des gens de Paris. Could and verse describe
the challenges they had and the severity of injuries. As announced
an assault between two masters, for example Grisier Jacob was already
our knight excited. Hastily opened the Figaro daily and bet on Inside
one or the other.

One day it occurred in the bed (where he always
attacked the big ideas) to be journalist without knowing or handle
weapons, was the same as a dancer and not playing the castanets. When
you least expect it raised a set, you had to go to ground, and he
did not even know be on guard. Sarrió true that all who knew there
was more. But nobody had obligation to know as much fencing as he.
Moreover, the argument could be a journalist Lancia or Madrid, and
then had to be left murder. These imaginings led him to adopt a resolution,
that of learning at all costs to pull the foil. How</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>