<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05089</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>344530</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24961</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

El día anterior había regresado muy tarde á la ciudad, después de verse festejado y admirado
durante varias horas por más de cien mil mujeres. Su discurso en las gradas del templo de los
rayos negros lo había escuchado esta enorme multitud, interrumpiéndolo con aplausos. Su éxito
resultó tan ruidoso como el del joven poeta rival de Golbasto. Nunca había llegado á soñar
con una gloria semejante, ni aun en los tiempos de la adolescencia, cuando, recién entrado
en la vida estudiosa, su entusiasmo le hacía aceptar la posibilidad de las más inauditas elevaciones.

Durmió mal, pues el saboreo de su triunfo parecía repeler al sueño. Pero cuando descendió de
su habitación universitaria, apreciando de antemano las felicitaciones de unos profesores y
la envidia de otros, todo su orgullo triunfante se deshizo ante la realidad. Oyó aterrado lo
que había hecho el gigante en la tarde anterior. Muchos de los que le hablaron habían asistido
á la tertulia de Momaren y se mostraban congestionados aún por la indignación al recordar los
proyectiles del gigante, algunas de cuyas salpicaduras habían llegado á ellos ó á personas
de sus familias.

El Padre de los Maestros estaba en cama después de este suceso, aunque sin enfermedad conocida.
Golbasto, el gran poeta nacional, se había retirado jurando vengarse del bárbaro intruso. Los
concurrentes le vieron con un vendaje debajo de su corona de laurel, pues se había descalabrado
al caer al suelo con Momaren bajo el disparo del gigante.

--¿Qué ha hecho usted?--volvió á repetir el profesor.

Muchos de los que presenciaron el suceso habían olvidado la insolencia del Hombre-Montaña para
preocuparse únicamente de la finalidad de otra acción suya que les parecía misteriosa. Después
que el gigante hubo limpiado de gentío los salones de Momaren, haciendo huir á todos al fondo
de la casa para librarse de su bombardeo líquido, irguió su estatura y fué á un determinado
lugar de la fachada de la Universidad, lanzando varios silbidos con la estridencia de un huracán.

Los doctores estudiosos que permanecían en sus habitaciones intentaron ocultarse, creyendo
que el Hombre-Montaña se había vuelto loco y deseaba aplastarlos. Pero antes de cerrar las
ventanas de sus viviendas pudieron ver cómo corría por los tejados un hombre envuelto en velos,
cómo el gigante lo tomaba con una de sus manos, introduciéndolo en un bolsillo de su traje,
y cómo emprendía una marcha veloz, guiado por este varón desconocido, hacia la Galería de la
Industria, sin esperar á que sonasen otra vez las trompetas y se reuniera el escuadrón que
le había escoltado en su paseo.

--¿Qué va á pasar ahora?--continuó diciendo el asustado profesor.

Los murmuradores le habían dado á entender que el Padre de los Maestros sospechaba si este
intruso ayudado por el gigante sería Ra-Ra.

--Yo temo, gentleman, que á estas horas la policía esté enterada de que, efectivamente, el
tal hombre era Ra-Ra y que, protegido por usted, entró en nuestro palacio para ver á Popito....
¡Usted, gentleman, mezclándose en cosas políticas de nuestro país y apoyando de una manera
tan descarada á un propagandista del «varonismo», enemigo de la tranquilidad del Estado! Tiemblo
por usted y tiemblo por mí.

Gillespie no necesitaba oir al profesor para darse cuenta de la gravedad de su acto. Pero renacía
su cólera al acordarse de los pinchazos de aquellos pigmeos, y creía sentir aún el dolor en
sus piernas. ¿Por qué no lo habían dejado dormir en paz?...

Sin embargo, los gestos desesperados del profesor sirvieron para hacerle pensar que estaba
á merced de aquella humanidad pigmea, despreciable para él, pero sin la cual no podía alimentarse
ni atender á otros cuidados que necesitaba su persona.

Flimnap, creyendo ver en su rostro un reflejo de intensa cólera, le recomendó la calma.

--No se exalte, gentleman; al contrario, debe usted mostrarse prudente y conciliador. Creo
que esto se arreglará finalmente. Puede usted presentar sus excusas al Padre de los Maestros.
Yo explicaré que todo se debe á su desconocimiento de nuestra lengua y nuestras costumbres.
Lo que me preocupa más es lo de Ra-Ra; pero si no hay otro remedio, lo abandonaremos y que
siga su destino. El amor es egoísta, gentleman. Antes de venir usted á esta tierra yo hubiese
hecho los mayores sacrificios por ese joven. Pero ahora no es lo mismo; ahora está usted aquí,
y más allá de su persona nada me interesa.

Parecía haber olvidado el catedrático todas las inquietudes que le entristecían momentos antes,
al saltar del plato-ascensor. Se había puesto ante un ojo su lente de disminución para contemplar
el rostro del Gentleman-Montaña, y esto le hacía sonreir dulcemente.

--Creo llegado el momento--dijo con voz insinuante--de mostrarle mi alma. Mientras usted vivía
á cubierto de peligros, yo no me atreví á decirle lo que siento. Me dominaba la timidez de
todo el que ha pasado su existencia entre libros, viendo de lejos á las personas. Pero después
de la locura de usted, la situación es otra. Tal vez el conflicto con nuestro Padre de los
Maestros acabe por arreglarse, pero en este momento la situación es mala. Corre usted grandes
riesgos, y por lo mismo considero oportuno manifestarle lo que no me hubiera atrevido á decir
en una ocasión mejor. Óigame bien, gentleman, y no se ría de mí.... Yo le quiero un poco y
me intereso por su felicidad.... ¿Por qué no hablar más claramente?... Yo le amo, gentleman,
y deseo pasar el resto de mi vida junto á usted, dedicándome en absoluto á su servicio.

A pesar de su mal humor por la aventura en la Universidad y por las persecuciones que le podían
hacer sufrir estos pigmeos, de los que era esclavo, Gillespie no pudo contener una carcajada.
Después sofocó su risa para excusarse cortésmente:

--No crea, profesor, que me río de usted. Le estoy muy agradecido para atreverme á tal insolencia.
Mi risa es de sorpresa.... En mi país, rara vez una mujer declara su amor al hombre.

--Pues aquí no es extraordinario--contestó Flimnap--. Acuérdese que todo lo dirigimos las mujeres,
y por lo mismo nos corresponde la iniciativa en los asuntos de amor.

--Además--dijo Edwin--, usted olvida el obstáculo insuperable que la Naturaleza ha establecido
entre los dos al crearnos con tamaños tan distintos. Me mira usted á través de su lente de
reducción y se ilusiona creyéndome de su talla. Contémpleme tal como soy, y se convencerá de
que por mucho que yo la amase nunca pasaría usted de ser una esposa de bolsillo.

--¡Oh, gentleman!--interrumpió ella quejumbrosamente--. No sea usted materialista en sus apreciaciones,
no se muestre grosero en sus sentimientos juzgando á las personas por su tamaño. ¿Por qué no
pueden amarse dos almas á través de sus envolturas completamente diferentes?... Ahora que le
conozco, gentleman, me doy cuenta de que toda mi vida he estado esperando su llegada. Siempre
mi alma sintió la atracción de las alturas; siempre soñé con algo inmensamente grande. Mi espíritu
veía con indiferencia las pequeñeces de nuestra vida corriente. Yo sólo podía amar á un gigante,
y el gigante ha venido. ¿No le parece que un poder superior nos ha hecho el uno para el otro?...

El Gentleman-Montaña sólo contestó á esta pregunta con un gesto ambiguo. Pero el ardoroso profesor
siguió hablando:

--Yo no le exijo que me responda inmediatamente. Confieso que esta manifestación de mis sentimientos
es un poco violenta y que usted no la esperaba. A no ser por el peligro que le amenaza, me
hubiese abstenido de hablarle de esto en mucho tiempo. Pero, en fin, lo que yo debía decir
ya está dicho. Reflexione usted, consulte su corazón; esperaré su respuesta. Lo que necesitaba
hacerle saber cuanto antes es que no soy para usted un simple traductor y que ansío participar
de su suerte, correr sus mismos peligros, si es que la situación se empeora.

Gillespie, conteniendo la risa que otra vez volvía á agitar su pecho, contestó vagamente á
la apasionada universitaria. Obedecería sus indicaciones, estudiaría con detenimiento las preferencias
de su alma. Pero por el momento, lo más urgente era resolver su situación, que, según ella,
parecía angustiosa.

--Voy á dejarle, gentleman--contestó Flimnap--. Nada consigo permaneciendo á su lado para sostener
una conversación grata, pero que resulta estéril. Necesito saber noticias. Momaren tiene poderosos
amigos y debe haber hecho algo á estas horas contra Ra-Ra. Además, hay que temer á Golbasto.
Adivino desde aquí que su cochecito tirado por los tres hombres-caballos debe estar rodando
á través de la capital desde el principio de la mañana. ¡A saber lo que habrá tramado el temible
poeta!...

Antes de desaparecer por uno de los escotillones, todavía retrocedió Flimnap hacia el gigante
para decirle en voz baja:

--Si vienen á buscar á Ra-Ra, no se empeñe en defenderlo; sería peor para él y para usted.
Déjelo abandonado á su suerte. Nosotros sólo debemos pensar en nuestro porvenir. Yo siempre
he creído que un amor que no es egoísta no merece el nombre de amor.

Y entornando los párpados con expresión acariciante detrás de los vidrios de sus gafas, el
profesor desapareció rampa abajo.

Sólo entonces el Hombre-Montaña bajó los ojos para mirarse á sí mismo, fijándolos en su pecho.
Por la abertura entreabierta de su bolsillo superior veía la cabecita de Ra-Ra, encogido en
el fondo de este refugio.

--¡Buena la hiciste ayer!--dijo el gigante en voz queda, como si hablase con él mismo--. En
realidad tú eres el culpable de todo lo ocurrido, por tu maldita idea de dejarme solo para
ir á ver á Popito.... Pero no te abandonaré por eso, como me pide la loca de Flimnap.... ¡Qué
diablo será esto del amor, que á todos nos hace cometer enormes tonterías, y hasta da un aspecto
grotesco á esa pobre mujer tan inocente y bondadosa!...

Vieron los ojos del gigante apoyada en un lado de la mesa la cachiporra que se había fabricado
durante su excursión á la selva de los emperadores. La presencia de esta arma primitiva le
hizo sonreir de un modo inquietante para los pigmeos.

--Yo te aseguro, Ra-Ra--continuó--, que los primeros que vengan en tu busca y nos molesten
corren peligro de morir aplastados.

Pero aunque esta promesa bárbara fuese muy del gusto de Ra-Ra, éste protestó, sacando la cabeza
imprudentemente por el borde del bolsillo.

--Lo creo oportuno--dijo el pigmeo--, pero dentro de algún tiempo. Ahora es inútil. Hay que
esperar nuestra Revolución, cada vez más próxima.

Mientras tanto, Flimnap corría las calles de la capital, enterándose de una serie de noticias
muy inquietantes para él. Un profesor le anunció que Momaren, por ciertos detalles que le habían
comunicado algunos subordinados, estaba ya convencido de que era Ra-Ra el que acompañaba al
gigante. El Padre de los Maestros, aceptando las sugestiones de su vanidad, creía que este
varonista, enemigo del orden, había sugerido al Hombre-Montaña la idea de interrumpir su tertulia
en el momento preciso que el gran Golbasto recitaba sus versos, para quitarle así un gran triunfo
literario. A primeras horas de la mañana había tenido una conversación violenta con Popito,
la cual negó haber visto á Ra-Ra en la parte alta del palacio universitario. Luego el influyente
personaje abandonó su cama, y estaba ahora en la presidencia del Consejo Ejecutivo, recomendando
sin duda la persecución del revolucionario masculista.

Poco después Flimnap se encontró con un grupo de noticieros de los grandes diarios, que le
iban buscando desde horas antes. Querían conocer su opinión sobre lo ocurrido en la tertulia
del Padre de los Maestros, pero él se expresó de un modo ambiguo. De buena gana hubiese contestado
rudamente á estos curiosos insaciables que le perseguían á todas horas; pero la gratitud le
obligaba á ser cortés. Todos los diarios hablaban con elogios de su discurso en el templo de
los rayos negros, lamentándose de haber desconocido durante tantos años á un orador tan eminente.

Los periodistas le dieron una noticia que resultó la peor de todas. Gurdilo había anunciado
su deseo de pronunciar un discurso en el Senado á propósito del Hombre-Montaña apenas se abriese
la sesión. Tal vez el temible orador estaba ya hablando á estas horas.

Flimnap corrió al palacio del gobierno, entrando en el ala ocupada por el Senado. Su amor por
Gillespie le sugería las más atrevidas resoluciones. El tímido profesor, que pocos días antes
era incapaz de la más pequeña iniciativa, se asombraba ahora de su audacia. Pensó hablar á
Gurdilo, si es que aún no había empezado su interpelación al gobierno. No se conocían, pero
él desde unos días antes era un personaje célebre, del que se ocupaban mucho los periódicos,
y bien podía permitirse la libertad de hacer una visita á un compañero suyo de gloria. Dentro
del Senado, al preguntar por el famoso orador, se convenció de que había llegado tarde. Gurdilo
estaba ya en el salón de sesiones, y no admitía visitas que le distrajesen cuando preparaba
mentalmente sus terribles discursos.

El catedrático subió á una de las tribunas destinadas al público, viendo abajo, entre las matronas
que formaban el Senado, al temible Gurdilo, hacia el que convergían todas las miradas.

Nunca sufrió el pobre Flimnap una tortura igual á la de escuchar á este personaje confundido
entre el público y sin poder contestarle. Después de su triunfo en el templo de los rayos negros,
se consideraba tan tribuno como el célebre sanador; pero aquí no era mas que un simple oyente
que podía ser encarcelado si osaba alterar con sus interrupciones la calma de la majestuosa
asamblea.

La oradora senatorial, con la faz más amarilla que nunca, la mirada torva, la nariz encorvada
y una voz silbante, atacó á Gillespie durante mucho tiempo, procurando que sus golpes al coloso
cayesen de rebote sobre los altos señores del Consejo Ejecutivo.

Hizo la historia de todos los Hombres-Montañas que habían llegado al país en el curso de los
siglos. El primero, según el testimonio de viejos cronistas, acabó siendo un traidor al Imperio
de Liliput que le había dado hospitalidad, pues se fué con los de Blefuscú, que eran entonces
enemigos. Además, al regresar á su monstruosa patria, publicó, según vagas noticias traídas
por Eulame, un libro en el que ponía en ridículo á todos los liliputienses.

Los colosos que habían llegado después eran gentes bárbaras y viciosas, sin educación universitaria
y de una capacidad estomacal que acababa causando grandes escaseces y hambres en la nación.
Cometían tales desafueros, que finalmente había que suprimirlos.

Y cuando se había aceptado como medida prudente el matar á estos intrusos, que se presentaban
de tarde en tarde, con la regularidad de una epidemia, llegaba el último Hombre-Montaña, y
el Consejo Ejecutivo, faltando á la tradición, le concedía la vida.

Aquí Gurdilo empezó á hablar irónicamente de la enorme influencia que unos cuantos profesores
y fabricantes de versos ejercían sobre el gobierno actual.

--Ha bastado--dijo el orador--que un pobre pedante que enseña en nuestra Universidad la inútil
lengua de los Hombres-Montañas, la cual de nada puede servirnos; ha bastado, repito, que descubriese
en un bolsillo del tal gigante un libro del tamaño de cualquiera de nosotros, con unos versos
disparatados, propios de su enorme animalidad, para que todos los falsos intelectuales que
dominan nuestra organización universitaria, y son retribuidos exageradamente por el gobierno,
viesen una ocasión de afirmar su influencia protegiendo á este colosal intruso como un compañero
de letras. Y los altos señores del gobierno, que antes de ocupar sus cargos no conocían otra
lectura que la del diario todas las mañanas, han aprovechado la ocasión para darse una falsa
importancia de intelectuales, obedeciendo las indicaciones de sus protegidos que monopolizan
la Universidad.

»No quiero hablar al ilustre Senado de los gastos que ha originado el Hombre-Montaña desde
que vive entre nosotros. Esto será objeto de un discurso que pronunciaré otro día, cuando tenga
completos los datos estadísticos que estoy reuniendo. Necesito saber con certeza cuántos bueyes
come cada día, cuántas docenas de gallinas, así como las toneladas de pescado y de pan que
lleva devoradas. No insisto en esto; pronto apreciará el Senado de qué manera el Consejo Ejecutivo
derrocha el dinero de la nación, á pesar de que el gobierno de nuestro sexo ostenta el espíritu
de economía como la mayor de las ventajas sobre todos los gobiernos anteriores.

»Hoy necesito hablar de otra cosa que considero de gran urgencia, pues equivale á un escándalo
intolerable que pone en peligro el orden del Estado y los fundamentos de nuestra sociedad,
haciendo completamente inútiles la sabiduría de aquella gran mujer que inventó los rayos libertadores
y el heroísmo de las valerosas jóvenes que combatieron en la tierra y en el aire por el triunfo
de la Verdadera Revolución.

»Yo mismo no comprendo cómo el ilustre Senado, la Cámara de diputados y los demás organismos
nacionales no fijaron su atención en el aspecto subversivo que nos ofrece ese gigante desde
que llegó. Tampoco puedo explicarme cómo los periódicos, que atisban el menor de nuestros defectos
para publicarlo inmediatamente permanecen ciegos para el Hombre-Montaña.... Debo confesar,
sin embargo, que yo también he vivido en esta ceguera inexplicable, y sólo anoche vi la realidad,
gracias á la sugestión de un poeta eminente, el más grande de todos los poetas que hoy existen,
y después de esto casi resulta inútil que os diga su nombre. Todos habéis adivinado que es
Golbasto.... Con razón llaman á los poetas videntes. Golbasto ha visto lo que ninguno de nosotros
había logrado ver.

Se hizo un silencio profundo en toda la asamblea. Lo mismo los senadores que el público de
las tribunas, esperaban anhelantes la revelación del gran descubrimiento del poeta, transmitido
por el más temible de los oradores. Más de mil pechos jadeaban oprimidos por la emoción; el
interés hacía respirar á todos con dificultad. Nadie apartaba sus ojos del tribuno, que parecía
haber crecido repentinamente. Al fin, después de una larga pausa dramática, su voz resonó en
el majestuoso silencio.

--Fíjese bien el honorable Senado en lo que representa el espectáculo antisocial y subversivo
que presenció ayer el vecindario de nuestra ciudad. El Hombre-Montaña es un hombre, como lo
indica su título.... ¡y, sin embargo, usa pantalones!

Una exclamación ahogada de todos los oyentes saludó este descubrimiento.

--¡Es verdad!... ¡Es verdad!--murmuraron los senadores y el público con asombro, como si pasase
ante sus ojos un relámpago deslumbrante.

--Imagínese el ilustre Senado--continuó Gurdilo--qué efecto tan desastroso habrá producido
ayer en el pueblo, y sobre todo en la juventud estudiosa de los colegios, ver á un hombre vestido
de un modo que parece desafiar á la moral y á las conveniencias. Hace muchos años que en nuestras
calles no se ha visto nada tan indecente.

»Bien sabido es que en el seno de nuestra sociedad algunos jóvenes insensatos y mal aconsejados
pretenden trastornar el orden social con la utopía ridícula de que los hombres puedan sustituir
á las mujeres en la dirección de los negocios públicos. Estos locos, enemigos de lo existente,
deben haber gozado mucho ayer viendo á un hombre con pantalones, y los hombres prudentes y
virtuosos de nuestras familias se habrán escandalizado con harto motivo al contemplar á uno
de su sexo sin la túnica y sin los velos que corresponden á una matrona virtuosa. El traje
de ese Hombre-Montaña significa el «varonismo» en acción, que desafía á todas nuestras leyes
y costumbres, á todo nuestro glorioso pasado, á todas las hazañas y sacrificios de nuestros
antecesores.

»Si se deja continuar este espectáculo subversivo, si no se le pone remedio, el llamado «partido
masculista», insignificante y ridículo en el presente, crecerá hasta convertirse en una gran
fuerza; los hombres querrán llevar pantalones, y nosotros, las mujeres que somos senadores,
guerreros, funcionarios, en una palabra, todos los que desempeñamos un cargo público ó contribuímos
á la buena marcha del Estado, todos los que somos cabeza de una familia, tendremos que vestirnos
con faldas.

La suposición de que las mujeres pudieran alguna vez llevar faldas resultaba tan extravagante
é inaudita, que todo el respetable Senado empezó á reir, y, animados por su hilaridad, los
ocupantes de las tribunas lanzaron igualmente grandes carcajadas.

Hasta algunas señoras masculinas que, envueltas pudorosamente en sus velos, ocupaban la tribuna
destinada á las esposas de los senadores encontraron muy original la paradoja de Gurdilo, celebrándola
con discretas risas.

El orador continuó su discurso con arrogancia, seguro ya de que la asamblea en masa iba á apoyarle
con sus votos.

Por el momento, no pedía nada contra el Consejo Ejecutivo. Su responsabilidad sería objeto
de otro discurso. Lo que él solicitaba, como patriota, era que cesase cuanto antes el escándalo
y el peligro para las buenas costumbres que significaba el modo de vestir del gigante. Los
pantalones correspondían á las mujeres, y era un atentado contra las conquistas heredadas de
la Verdadera Revolución que este intruso, siendo un hombre, se empeñase en vestir de modo diferente
á todos los de su especie.

--Pido al Senado--terminó diciendo el orador--que le quiten al Hombre-Montaña lo que no le
corresponde usar y que se envíe al Consejo Ejecutivo una ley para que mañana mismo lo vista
con el recato y la decencia que exige su sexo.

La ovación al tribuno fué larga. El presidente tuvo que hacer sonar varias veces la sirena
eléctrica de su mesa para conseguir que se restableciese el silencio.

--¿Acuerda el Senado--preguntó--que el Hombre-Montaña sea vestido como corresponde á su sexo
inferior?

Algunos senadores rutinarios que veneraban el reglamento hablaron de votación, pero los más
se opusieron, considerando que era inútil cuando todas las opiniones se mostraban unánimes.
Y levantando una mano, votaron todos por aclamación la urgencia de quitarle los pantalones
al Hombre-Montaña.

Flimnap abandonó la tribuna con el ánimo desorientado, no sabiendo ciertamente si debía entristecerse
ó alegrarse por lo que acababa de oir. La intervención de Gurdilo le había hecho sospechar
en el primer momento que tenía por objeto pedir la muerta de Gillespie. Pero al convencerse
de que el senador sólo deseaba cambiar su vestidura, sin hablar para nada de hacerle perder
la existencia, casi sintió gratitud hacia él. Le importaba poco que Gurdilo le hubiera llamado
pedante y le aludiese con otras frases despectivas, sin hacerle el honor de citar su nombre.
Los enamorados son capaces de los más grandes sacrificios á cambio de que la persona amada
no sufra. Para él lo interesante era saber que el gentleman no iba á morir. Hasta pensó que
ofrecería un aspecto más gracioso vestido con arreglo á las indicaciones del tribuno. Siempre
le había causado un malestar indefinible verlo con pantalones, lo mismo que una mujer, contra
todas las conveniencias establecidas por las costumbres y la gloriosa historia del país.

Al caer la tarde se dirigió á la vivienda del Gentleman Montaña. Después de salir del Senado
había pretendido sin éxito alguno hablar con el presidente del Consejo Ejecutivo. Su personalidad
gloriosa parecía disolverse así como iba decreciendo la curiosidad simpática por el gigante.
Las gentes volvían á no conocerle. Varios periodistas pasaron junto á él sin pedirle su opinión.
Los que antes le detenían en la calle haciéndole preguntas sobre el Hombre-Montaña casi lo
atropellaban ahora con sus máquinas terrestres. La mujer de negocios que le había propuesto
un viaje triunfal por toda la República dando conferencias en compañía del coloso volvió la
cabeza al cruzarse con él.

En los salones de espera del jefe del Consejo aguardó inútilmente unas dos horas. Los empleados
le ignoraban voluntariamente. Vió á Momaren que salía del despacho del presidente. Al cruzarse
con el profesor, que le saludó con una profunda reverencia, el Padre de los Maestros sólo tuvo
para él una mirada fría y un murmullo ininteligible. Al fin, Flimnap, convencido de que había
pasado su período de gloria y de influencia, salió del palacio del gobierno.

Cerca de la altura en cuya cumbre estaba la Galería de la Industria, notó un movimiento extraordinario.
Llegaban por diversas avenidas batallones de mujeres armadas con arcos y lanzas. Vió presentarse
además un escuadrón de la Guardia gubernamental y numerosos destacamentos de la policía masculina
y barbuda, que abandonaban la vigilancia de las calles para acudir á esta concentración guerrera.

Su corazón se oprimió con el presentimiento de que todo este aparato bélico era á causa de
alguna otra inconveniencia cometida por el gigante. Sobre la cumbre de la colina flotaban varias
máquinas voladoras. Otras iban aproximándose á toda fuerza de sus motores, viniendo de distintos
puntos del horizonte. Una alarma reciente había puesto, sin duda, sobre las armas á todas las
tropas que guarnecían la capital.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09306</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>27147</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22232</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

The day before he returned to the city late, after being feted and admired for several hours
over a hundred thousand women. His speech on the steps of the temple black lightning had heard
this huge crowd, interrupting him with applause. Its success was as loud as the young poet's
rival Golbasto. Had never dreamed with such glory, even in times of adolescence, when newly
entered the studious life, his enthusiasm made him accept the possibility of the most unprecedented
elevations.

Slept badly, as the taste of his success seemed to repel the dream. But when dropped from his
university room, enjoying in advance the congratulations of some teachers and the envy of all
his pride broke triumphantly to reality. He heard the terrified The giant had done the previous
afternoon. Many of those who spoke had attended Momar to the talk show and they were still crowded
with indignation to remember giant shells, some of which had come to splash them or to persons
their families.

The Father of the Masters was in bed after this event, but without known disease. Golbasto, the
great national poet, had retreated vowing revenge on the barbaric
intruder.

The concurrent saw him with a bandage under his crown of laurel,
for he had broken pate falling to the ground under the trip Momar
giant.

- What have you done? - Repeated the professor.

Many who witnessed the incident had forgotten the insolence of the man-mountain for concerned
only with the purpose of other action of his that seemed mysterious. After the giant crowd
was cleared from the halls of Momar, doing all the background to
flee the house to escape the bombardment liquid, raised his stature
and went to a certain instead of the facade of the University, releasing
several shrill whistles with a hurricane.

Doctors scholars who stayed in their rooms trying to hide, believe man-mountain that had gone mad
and wanted to crush them. But before closing windows of their homes could see how it ran on
the roof a man wrapped in veils, how the giant took one of his hands, putting it in a pocket
of his suit, and how fast undertook a march, led by this man unknown to the Gallery Industry,
without waiting for the trumpets sounded again and to meet the squad
escorted him on his walk.

- What will happen now? - Continued the
frightened teacher.

The gossips had been given to understand that the Father of the teachers
suspected if intruder would be helped by the giant Ra-Ra.

- I am
afraid, gentleman, who by this time the police are aware that in fact
the this man was Ra-Ra and protected by you, came into our house to
see her .... Popito You, gentleman, mixing in political affairs of
our country and support in a way so brazen he a propagandist of the
"male" enemy of peace of the state!

Shiver I tremble for you and me.

Gillespie did not need to hear the teacher to realize the gravity of his act. But reborn their
anger to remember the sting of those pygmies, and believed still feel pain her legs. Why not sleep
had left him alone? ...

However, the teacher's desperate gestures served to make him think he was humanity at the mercy
of that pygmy, despicable for him, but which could not feed or attend
to other care she needed him.

Flimnap, thinking she saw in his face a reflection of intense anger,
recommended calm.

- Do not be exalted, gentleman, on the contrary,
you should be prudent and conciliatory.

I this will be fixed eventually. Can you to apologize to the Father
of the Masters.

I explain that everything is due to their ignorance of our language and our customs. What
worries me most is what Ra-Ra, but if no other remedy, and abandon the follow your destiny. Love
is selfish, gentleman. Before you come to this land I had made the greatest sacrifices for
the young. But now is not the same, now you are here, and beyond anything I'm interested in
him.

Professor seemed to have forgotten all the concerns that saddened
him moments before, the jump-lift plate.

He had put his eye to a reduction lens to see Gentleman's face-Mountain, and this made him smile
sweetly.

- I think when the time - said insinuating voice - to show you my soul. While you were living sheltered
from dangers, I did not dare to say what I feel. Shyness possessed me anyone who has spent
his life among books, watching from afar to the people. But after the madness of you, the situation
is different. Perhaps the conflict with our Father in Teachers will finally be fixed, but
right now the situation is bad. You at large risks, and therefore consider it appropriate to
express what I had not dared to say a better chance. Listen well, gentleman, and do not laugh
at me .... I love him a little and I am interested in your happiness .... Why not speak more
clearly? ... I love you, gentleman, and want to spend the rest of my life with you, dedicating
his service at all.

Despite his bad mood for adventure in the University and by the persecution that could to experience
these Pygmies, of whom was a slave, Gillespie could not help but
laugh.

After stifled her laughter to apologize politely

- Do not think, Professor, that I laugh at you. I am very grateful for daring to such insolence. My
laugh is a surprise .... In my country, rarely a woman declares her
love for man.

- Well here is extraordinary - said Flimnap -.

Remember that all women go, and therefore for us to the initiative in matters of love.

- Also - Edwin said - you forget the insurmountable obstacle that nature has established between
the two to create us with such different sizes.

I see you through your lens reduction and thinking I was excited for her size. Contémpleme as I am, and
be convinced that much I loved you would never be a wife of pocket.

- Oh, gentleman! - She interrupted plaintively -. Do not be materialistic in their views, not
display their feelings rude to judge people by their size. Why not can love two souls through their
containers completely different? ... Now that you I know, gentleman, I realize that my whole life
I've been waiting for his arrival. Always My soul felt the pull of
the heights, always dreamed of something vastly larger.

My spirit viewed with indifference the pettiness of our everyday life. I could only love a giant and
the giant has come.

Do not you think that a higher power has given us to each other? ...

The Gentleman-Mountain just answered this question with an ambiguous gesture. But the hot teacher
continued:

- I do not demand that I respond immediately.

I confess that this expression of my feelings is a little violent and you did not expect.
Except for the danger that threatens him, I had refrained from talking about this for a long time. But
in the end, what I should say already said. Think you check your heart, wait for an answer.
What I needed let you know as soon as possible is that I am for you
just a translator and I look forward to participating of his fate,
running their own dangers, if the situation worsens.

Gillespie, holding back laughter again to shake his chest, he replied vaguely the passionate
college. Obey his instructions, study carefully preferences of his soul. But for now, the top
priority was to resolve the situation, which it claims seemed anxious.

- I shall leave you, gentleman - said Flimnap -. Anything with his remaining hand to hold pleasant
conversation, but that is sterile.

I need to know news. Momar has powerful friends and must have done something by this time
against Ra-Ra. In addition, we must fear the Golbasto. Guess from here that his buggy pulled
by three men, horses must be rolling Through the capital since early
morning.

A screening will know what the dreaded poet! ...

Before disappearing for one of the hatches, still fell into the giant Flimnap to say quietly:

- If you come to seek the Ra-Ra, not to strive to defend it, would
be worse for him and for you.

Let abandoned to their fate. We must only think of our future. I always I believed that love
is not selfish not deserve the name of love.

And squinting eyelids caressing expression behind the glass of his spectacles, the teacher disappeared
down the ramp.

Only then will the man-mountain lowered his eyes to look to himself, setting them on his chest.
For the opening of his top pocket ajar saw head Ra-Ra, shrunk the
substance of the shelter.

- Good you did it yesterday! - Giant said
quietly, as if speaking to himself -.

In Actually you're to blame for everything that happened, in your damn idea to leave me alone
go see .... Popito But why not leave you, like me crazy Flimnap calls
.... What the devil is this love that makes us all make great nonsense,
and even gives a grotesque to that poor woman so innocent and kind!

...

Giant eyes were resting on one side of the table club who had made during his trip to the jungle
of the emperors.

The presence of this primitive weapon you he smiled in a way disturbing to the Pygmies.

- I assure you, Ra-Ra - continued - the first people who come looking for you and annoy us at
risk of being killed.

But although this promise was barbaric, very much in Ra-Ra, it protested, poking his head recklessly
over the edge of the pocket.

- I believe it appropriate - said the pygmy - but in some time. Now it is useless. Must expect our
revolution ever closer.

Meanwhile, Flimnap ran the streets of the capital, learning of a series of news very disturbing
to him. A teacher told him that Momar, for certain details that had reported some subordinates, was
already convinced that Ra-Ra was accompanying the giant. The Father of the Masters, accepting
the suggestions of his vanity, thought that men, the enemy of order, had suggested to the man-mountain
discontinue the idea of ??gathering at the precise moment that the
great Golbasto recite his verses, to take away and a big win literature.

In the early hours of the morning had had a conversation with Popito violent, which he denied
having seen Ra-Ra in the top of the palace university. Then the influential characters left his
bed, and was now in the presidency of the Executive Board, recommending
without doubt the persecution of the revolutionary mascula.

Flimnap Shortly after he met a group of news from major newspapers, which were seeking from
hours earlier. They wanted to know your opinion on what happened in the party Father of the
Masters, but he said in an ambiguous way. I would fain have answered roughly to those insatiable
curiosity chasing him at all hours, but the gratitude we forced to be polite. All the newspapers
spoke with praise of his speech at the temple black rays, complaining of having unknown for many
years to so eminent a speaker.

Gave reporters a story that was the worst. Gurdilo announced his desire to make a speech in the Senate
to order the man-mountain barely opened the session. Perhaps he was
already talking scary at this hour.

Flimnap ran the government palace, entering in the wing occupied by the Senate. His love for Gillespie
suggested the boldest decisions. The shy professor, who just days before was incapable of the
slightest initiative, now in its audacity astonished.

Thought to speak to Gurdilo, if it had not yet begun his questioning the government. Not known,
but few days before he was a celebrity, which dealt a lot of newspapers, could well afford the
freedom to make a visit to a colleague of glory.

Within the Senate, to ask for the famous orator, he was convinced that he had arrived late.
Gurdilo was already in the chamber and did not allow visits distracting him while preparing mentally
its awful speeches.

The professor went to one of the grandstands for the public, looking
down between midwives forming the Senate, the fearsome Gurdilo, towards
which all eyes converged.

Flimnap poor never suffered torture equal to that of listening to
this person confusion between the public and unable to answer.

After his victory in the temple of lightning black considered as tribune like the famous healer,
but here was nothing more than a mere listener that could be jailed if he dared to alter his
breaks the stillness of the majestic assembly.

She Senate, with the face yellower than ever, the grim look, bent
nose and a hissing voice, attacked Gillespie for a long time, trying
to match their shots colossus rebound should fall on the high lords
of the Executive Council.

He made the history of all man-mountain who had come to the country in the course of centuries.
The first, according to the testimony of ancient writers, ended up being a traitor to the
Empire Liliput given him hospitality, as it was with those of Blefuscu, which were then enemies.
In addition, returning to his monstrous home, posted as news brought vague by Eulame, a book in
which he ridiculed all Lilliputians.

Giants who arrived later were barbaric and vicious people without college education and a stomach
capacity that had caused great shortages and famines in the nation.

Committed such excesses, which finally had to delete.

And when it was accepted as a prudent measure to kill these intruders, which were presented from
time to time, with the regularity of an epidemic, came the last man-mountain, and Executive
Council, taking off from tradition, he gave life.

Here Gurdilo began to speak ironically of the enormous influence that
few teachers lines and manufacturers had over the current government.

-
Was enough - he said - a poor pedant who teaches at the University
on the useless language of the man-mountain, which can serve anything,
has been sufficient, I repeat, they discovered such a giant pocket-sized
book any of us, with some lines crazy, typical of large animals, so
that all false intellectuals dominate our university organization,
and are paid excessively by the government, they saw a chance to assert
their influence to protect this huge intruder as a partner letters.

And the high lords of the government, before taking office had known nothing reading the journal
every morning, have taken the opportunity to be a false importance of intellectual, obeying
the instructions of his proteges who monopolize University.

"I do not want to talk to the illustrious Senate of expenditure from
which the man-mountain from living among us.

This will be a speech utter another day, when you comprehensive statistical data that I gathered.
I need to know for sure how many cattle eat each day, how many dozens of chickens, and tons
of fish and bread has devoured. Do not insist on this, and soon the Senate will appreciate how the
Executive Council squandered the money of the nation, notwithstanding that the government
holds our sex spirit economy as the greatest advantage over all previous governments.

"Today I need to talk about something else that I consider of great urgency, equivalent to
a scandal intolerable that jeopardizes the state order and the foundations of our society, completely
useless by the wisdom of this great woman who invented the lightning
liberators and the heroism of the brave young men who fought on land
and in the air for victory the True Revolution.

"I myself do not see how the illustrious Senate, the Chamber of Deputies and other bodies not
set national attention on the subversive side that offers this giant from reached. I can not explain
how the newspapers that the slightest peek of our wrongs to publish immediately are blind to
the man-mountain .... I must confess, however, I too have lived in
this inexplicable blindness, and only last night I saw the reality,
thanks to the suggestion of an eminent poet, the greatest of all poets
that exist today, and after it almost useless to tell you his name.

All you guessed it Golbasto .... No wonder they call the blind poets. Golbasto has seen what
none of us had managed to see.

There was a deep silence in the assembly.

The same senators that the public the stands, waiting for the revelation of longing great discovery
of the poet, transmitted by the most fearsome of the speakers.

More than a thousand breasts panted oppressed by emotion, the interest to all was breathing
with difficulty. Nobody take his eyes of the Tribune, which appeared Having grown up suddenly. Finally,
after a long dramatic pause, his voice echoing in the majestic silence.

- Pay special attention to the honorable Senate representing antisocial and subversive show that
witnessed yesterday the neighborhood in our city. The man-mountain is a man, as title suggests
.... And yet, wear pants!

A gasp of all listeners greeted this discovery.

- It's true! ... It's true! - Murmured the senators and the public in awe, as if pass before
his eyes a dazzling lightning.

- Imagine the illustrious Senate - continued Gurdilo - what effect it will have produced such disastrous
yesterday in the village, and especially in the studious youth in schools, see a man dress in
a way that seems to defy morality and to the conveniences. For many years our Street has not
seen anything so indecent.

"It is well known that within our society, some young foolish and
misguided intended to disrupt the social order with the ridiculous
utopia that men can replace to women in the conduct of public affairs.

These fools, enemies of the existing must have enjoyed a lot yesterday when she saw a man with
pants and prudent men virtuosos of our families will have been shocked with much reason to
look to one of sex without the robe and without the veils that correspond
to a virtuous matron.

The suit that man-mountain means "men" in action, which challenges all our laws and customs, to
all our glorious past, to all the deeds and sacrifices of our predecessors.

"If allowed to continue this show subversive, if not remedied, the 'party mascula "insignificant and
ridiculous in the present, will grow into a large force, the men
want to wear pants, and we, women are senators warriors, officials,
in short, all who hold public office or contribute to the smooth running
of the state, all who are head of a family, we have to dress skirts.

The assumption that women could wear skirts once was so bizarre and unheard, that all the respectable
Senate began to laugh, and, encouraged by their hilarity, the occupants of the stands also launched
big laughs.

Even some masculine women, modestly wrapped in their veils, occupied the rostrum destined to
the wives of the senators found it very original Gurdilo paradox, celebrating with subtle laughter.

He
continued his speech with arrogance, secure and that the assembly
would support mass their votes.

For the moment, asked for nothing against the Executive Council. Your responsibility would be
subject another speech.

What he sought, as a patriot, was to cease as soon as possible scandal and danger to morality
meant the giant's mode of dress. The pants was found in women, and it was an attack on the
legacy of conquest True Revolution that this intruder, being a man, they insist on dressing
differently to all of your kind.

- I ask the Senate - he ended up
saying - that take away from the man-mountain that does not appropriate
use and forwarded to the Executive Council a bill for the hearing
tomorrow with modesty and decency required by their sex.

The ovation was long the chief. The president had to blow the horn several times its power table
for silence was restored.

- Agree the Senate - said - that the man-mountain is dressed as befits their sex inferior?

Some senators routinely speak to venerate the voting rules, but the most opposed, considering
it was useless when the opinions were unanimous. He raised a hand, all voted by acclamation to
the urgency of removing pants Man-Mountain.

Flimnap left the platform with the aim disoriented, not knowing whether to be sad indeed or rejoice
over what had just heard. The intervention had made him suspect Gurdilo the first time was to ask
the dead Gillespie. But to convince that the senator only wanted to change his clothes, let
alone for anything to lose existence, almost felt gratitude toward him. It mattered little that
he had called Gurdilo pedantic and will allude to other derogatory phrases, without making
the honor to mention his name. The lovers are capable of the greatest sacrifices in exchange
for your loved one not suffer. For him it was interesting to know that the gentleman was not
going to die.

Even thought provide a more graceful dress according to the directions of the Tribune. Always had
caused him discomfort indefinable pants, just like a woman, against all the conveniences provided
by the customs and glorious history.

By late afternoon he went to the home of Mountain Gentleman.

After leaving the Senate had tried unsuccessfully to talk with President of the Executive Board. His personality
glorious seemed to dissolve and sympathetic curiosity was decreasing by the giant. The people went
back to not knowing. Several journalists went by him without asking his opinion. Those who previously
stopped in the street asking questions about the Man-Mountain almost
trampling ground now with their machines.

The businesswoman who had proposed a triumphal tour throughout the Republic to lecture in
the company of giants turned head to the cross with him.

In the waiting rooms of the head of the Council waited two hours in vain. Employees willfully
ignored him. Momar he saw coming out of the office of president.
To cross with the teacher, who greeted him with a deep bow, the Father
of the Masters had only for him a cold stare and a whisper unintelligible.
Finally, Flimnap, convinced that he had passed its period of glory
and influence, left the government palace.

Near the summit of which
was high in the Gallery of Industry, noted an extraordinary movement.
They came from different avenues battalions of women armed with bows
and spears. Appear saw also a government Guard squad and police detachments
numerous male and bearded, who left the surveillance of streets to
go to this concentration warrior.

His heart is oppressed with the
feeling that this whole war machine was on account of committed by
another giant inconvenience. On the top of the hill floated several
flying machines. Others were closer to full force of their engines,
coming from different points of the compass. A recent alarm had no
doubt about the weapons to all troops garrisoned in the capital</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>