<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09022</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>123945</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23301</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Y si te icen que si las seviyanas, que
si las malagueñas, di que es pamplina. En Jerez está la llave der cante. Eso lo declaran toos
los sabios del mundo.

Cuando Rafael se sintió fuerte tuvo que dar por terminado este período de dulce intimidad.
Una tarde habló a solas con el señor Fermín. Él no podía seguir allí; pronto llegarían los
viñadores, y la casa de Marchamalo recobraría su animación de pequeño pueblo. Además, don Pablo
anunciaba su propósito de echar abajo el caserón, para construir aquel castillo con el que
soñaba como una glorificación de su familia. ¿Cómo explicar Rafael su presencia en la viña?
Era una vergüenza que un hombre de sus energías permaneciese allí, sin ocupación, viviendo
al amparo de su padrino.

El asunto de aquella noche parecía olvidado. No temía que le persiguiesen, pero estaba resuelto
a no volver a su antigua vida.

--Con una basta, padrino; tenía su mercé razón. Ni esta es manera de ganarse honradamente el
pan, ni hay jembra que apechugue con un mozo que por más dinero que traiga a casa puede morir
de mala muerte.

Él no sentía miedo, ¡eso nunca!, pero tenía sus planes para el porvenir. Quería formarse una
familia, como su padre, como su padrino, y no pasar la vida echándolas de jaque en la montaña.
Buscaría una ocupación más honrada y tranquila, aunque conociese el hambre.

Y entonces fue cuando el señor Fermín, valiéndose de su influencia con los Dupont, hizo a Rafael
aperador del cortijo de Matanzuela, propiedad del sobrino del difunto don Pablo.

El tal Luis había vuelto a Jerez hecho un hombre, después de una continua peregrinación por
todas las universidades de España, buscando catedráticos de manga ancha que no tuviesen empeño
en malograr futuros abogados. Su tío le había impuesto la obligación de seguir una carrera,
y mientras aquél vivió, se había resignado a llevar la vida de estudiante, ajustándose a los
estrechos envíos de dinero y ampliándolos con préstamos feroces, por los que firmaba a ojos
cerrados cuantos papeles querían presentarle los usureros. Pero al ver al frente de la familia
a su primo Pablo y próxima su mayor edad, se había negado a continuar por más tiempo la comedia
de sus estudios. Era rico, no quería perder el tiempo en cosas que en nada le interesaban.
Y tomando posesión de sus bienes, comenzó la libre existencia de placeres con la que había
soñado en su estrecha vida de estudiante.

Viajaba por toda España, pero ya no era para aprobar una asignatura aquí y otra más allá: aspiraba
a ser una autoridad en el arte taurino, un grande hombre de la afición, e iba de plaza en plaza
al lado de su matador favorito, presenciando todas sus corridas. En invierno, cuando descansaban
sus ídolos, vivía en Jerez al cuidado de sus haciendas, y este cuidado consistía en pasarse
las noches en el Círculo Caballista, discutiendo acaloradamente los méritos de su matador y
la inferioridad de sus rivales, pero con tal vehemencia, que por si una estocada recibida años
antes por un toro, del que no quedaban ni los huesos, había sido caída o en su sitio, tentábase
por encima de la ropa el revólver, la navaja, todo el arsenal que llevaba sobre su persona,
como garantía del valor y la arrogancia con que resolvía sus asuntos.

No salía caballo hermoso y de precio de las yeguadas jerezanas, que no lo comprase, entablando
pujas con su primo, que era más rico que él. Por la noche, los montañeses de los colmados le
veían entrar como un presagio de borrasca, seguros de que acabaría rompiendo botellas y platos
y echando las sillas por el aire, para demostrar que era muy hombre y podía después pagarlo
todo a triple precio. Su ambición estribaba en ser el continuador del glorioso marqués de San
Dionisio, pero en el Círculo Caballista decían de él que no era más que su caricatura.

--Le farta el señorío, el aquel del bendito marqué--decía el señor Fermín al enterarse de las
hazañas de Luis, al que conocía desde niño.

Las mujeres y los valientes eran las dos pasiones del señorito. Con ellas no se mostraba muy
generoso; deseaba ser adorado por sus méritos de jinete arrogante, creyendo de buena fe que
todos los balcones de Jerez se estremecían con la palpitación de corazones ocultos cuando pasaba
él montando el último caballo que acababa de adquirir. Con la corte que le acompañaba de parásitos
y matones era más espléndido. No había en todo el término de Jerez un valentón de fama triste
que no acudiese a él atraído por su liberalidad. Los que salían de presidio no tenían que preocuparse
de su suerte; don Luis era un buen amigo y además de darles dinero, les admiraba. Cuando a
altas horas de la noche, al final de las francachelas en los colmados, sentíase borracho, despreciaba
a sus queridas para fijar toda su admiración en los hombres de bronce que le acompañaban. Hacía
que le mostrasen las cicatrices de sus heridas, que le relatasen sus heroicas peleas. Muchas
veces, en el Círculo Caballista señalaba a los amigos algún hombre malcarado que le aguardaba
en la puerta.

--Ese es el Chivo--decía con el orgullo de un príncipe que habla de sus grandes generales.--Un
hombre a quien le arrastran las borlas por el suelo. Entre tiros y cuchilladas tiene más de
cincuenta cicatrices en el pellejo.

Miraba a todos con insolente superioridad, como si las cicatrices del amigote fuesen una declaración
de su propio valor, y vivía feliz creyendo que en todo Jerez no había quien le disputase su
guapeza con los hombres y su buena fortuna con las mujeres.

Cuando el capataz de Marchamalo le habló en favor de Rafael, el señorito lo admitió inmediatamente.
Había oído hablar del muchacho; era de los suyos (y al decir esto tomaba el aire protector
de un maestro), recordaba ciertos tiros en la sierra y el miedo que le tenían los del resguardo.
Nada: que se quedaba con él; así le gustaban los hombres.

--Te colocaré en mi cortijo de Matanzuela--dijo acariciando con amistosas palmadas a Rafael,
como si fuese un nuevo discípulo.--El aperador que tengo es un viejo medio cegato, del que
se ríen los gañanes. Y ya sabemos lo que son los trabajadores: ¡mala gente! Con ellos, el pan
en una mano, y el garrote en la otra. Necesito un hombre como tú, que los meta en cintura y
cuide mis intereses.

Y Rafael se fue al cortijo, no volviendo a la viña más que una vez por semana, cuando iba a
Jerez para hablar al amo de los asuntos de la labranza. Muchas veces tenía que buscarlo en
la casa de alguna de sus protegidas. Le recibía en la cama, incorporándose sobre el almohadón,
en el que descansaba otra cabeza. El nuevo aperador reía a solas las fanfarronadas de su amo,
más atento a recomendarle la dureza y que «metiese en cintura» a los holgazanes que trabajaban
sus campos, que a enterarse de las operaciones agrícolas, echando la culpa de las malas cosechas
a los gañanes, una canalla que no quería trabajar y deseaba que los amos se convirtiesen en
criados, como si el mundo pudiera volverse del revés.

Don Luis llegaba a olvidarse de sus aficiones matonescas y sus hazañas amorosas, cuando hablaba
de la gente zafia de los campos que, movida por falsos apóstoles, quería repartírselo todo.
Él había estudiado (lo declaraba pomposamente en el Círculo Caballista, sin reparar en las
sonrisas de los que le escuchaban), él sabía que lo que deseaban los trabajadores eran utopias,
eso es; utopias (y repetía con delectación la palabra), y que todo lo que ocurría era por culpa
de los gobiernos que no «meten en cintura» a los gañanes, y también por falta de religión.
Si señor; la religión: este era el freno del pobre, y como cada vez había menos, los de abajo,
con el pretexto del hambre, querían comerse a los de arriba.

Estas palabras ya no hacían sonreír a los socios del Caballista, sino que las aprobaban con
fervorosos gestos, con toda su fe de ricos labradores, que encogían los hombros cuando algún
iluso proponía pantanos y canales, y todos los años costeaban grandes fiestas a la Virgen de
la Merced, sacándola en rogativa apenas faltaba el agua a sus campos.

A pesar de estas ideas que propalaba Luis en sus momentos de seriedad, afirmando que mejor
andarían las cosas si él gobernase, don Pablo Dupont abominaba de su primo, considerándolo
una vergüenza de la familia.

Este pariente, que renovaba los escándalos del de San Dionisio, agravados, según doña Elvira,
por su origen plebeyo, era una calamidad en una casa que siempre había infundido respeto por
su nobleza y santas costumbres. Para mayor desgracia estaban las niñas del marqués, Lola y
Mercedes. ¡Las veces que su tía se sofocó de indignación, sorprendiéndolas por la noche en
una reja baja de su hotel, hablando con los novios, que se renovaban casi semanalmente! Tan
pronto eran tenientes de la remonta, como señoritos del Caballista, o ingleses jóvenes, empleados
en los escritorios, que se entusiasmaban pelando la pava al estilo del país y hacían reír a
las niñas con su andaluz chapurreado británicamente. No había muchacho en Jerez que no tuviese
su rato de conversación con las desenvueltas marquesitas. Ellas hacían frente a todos: bastaba
pararse ante sus rejas para entablar diálogo, y los que pasaban sin detenerse eran perseguidos
por las risas y los siseos irónicos que sonaban a sus espaldas. La viuda de Dupont no podía
dominar a sus sobrinas, y éstas, por su parte, así como iban creciendo, mostrábanse más insolentes
con la devota señora. Era en vano que su primo las prohibiese salir a las rejas. Burlábanse
de él y su madre, añadiendo que ellas no habían nacido para monjas. Escuchaban con gesto hipócrita
las pláticas del confesor de doña Elvira recomendándolas la sumisión, y hacían uso de toda
clase de astucias para comunicarse con los galanes de a pie y de a caballo que rondaban la calle.

Un señorito del Caballista, hijo de un cosechero, gran amigo de la casa Dupont, se enamoró
de Lola, pidiéndola en matrimonio apresuradamente, como si temiera que se le escapase.

Doña Elvira y su hijo aceptaron la demanda: en el Círculo causó asombro el valor de aquel muchacho
casándose con una de las hijas del marqués de San Dionisio.

Este matrimonio fue para las dos hermanas una liberación. La soltera se marchó con la otra,
gozosa de emanciparse por fin de la tía huraña y devota, y a los pocos meses volvieron a reanudar
en casa del marido las costumbres que observaban cerca de los Dupont. Mercedes pasaba la noche
en la reja en apretada intimidad con los novios: su hermana acompañábala con cierto aire de
señora mayor, y hablaba con otros para no perder el tiempo. El marido protestaba, intentando
rebelarse. Pero las dos se indignaban contra él porque osaba interpretar estas diversiones
inocentes de un modo ofensivo para su pudor.

¡Qué de disgustos proporcionaron las dos Marquesitas, como las llamaban en la ciudad, a la
austera doña Elvira!... Mercedes, la soltera, se fugó con un inglés rico. De tarde en tarde
llegaban vagas noticias que hacían palidecer de rabia a la noble señora. Unas veces la veían
en París, otras en Madrid, llevando una vida de cocotte elegante. Cambiaba con frecuencia de
protectores, pues los atraía a docenas con su gracia picaresca. Además, en ciertas vanidades
producía gran impresión el título de marquesa de San Dionisio, que había unido a su nombre,
y la corona nobiliaria con que adornaba sus camisas de noche y las sábanas de una cama tan
frecuentada como la acera de una gran calle.

La viuda de Dupont creyó morir al saber tales cosas. ¡Señor, y para esto habían nacido los
preclaros varones de su familia, virreyes, arzobispos y capitanes, dándoles los monarcas títulos
y señoríos! ¡Para que tanta gloria sirviese de prospecto a una mala mujer!... Y aun ésta resultaba
la mejor de las dos. Al fin había huido por no afrentar de cerca a su familia, y si vivía en
el pecado, era entre hombres de cierto linaje, siempre con personas decentes, como si influyesen
en ella los respetos al rango de su familia.

Pero quedaba la otra, la mayor, la casada, y ésta quería acabar con todos los parientes matándolos
de vergüenza. Su vida conyugal, después de la fuga de Mercedes, fue un infierno. El marido
vivía en perpetuo recelo, marchando a ciegas en sus sospechas, no sabiendo en quién fijarse,
pues su mujer miraba del mismo modo a todos los hombres, como si se ofreciera con los ojos,
hablándoles con una libertad que incitaba a toda clase de audacias. Sintió celos de Fermín
Montenegro, que acababa de llegar de Londres, y reanudando su intimidad infantil con Lola,
la visitaba con frecuencia, atraído por su picaresco lenguaje.

Las escenas domésticas acababan a golpes. El marido, aconsejado por los amigos, acudía a la
bofetada y al palo, para domar a «la mala bestia», pero la tal bestiecilla justificaba el apodo,
pues al revolverse con el vigor y la acometividad de una infancia bravía digna de su ilustre
padre, devolvía los golpes de tal modo, que siempre era el cónyuge el que resultaba peor librado.

Muchas veces se presentaba en el Círculo Caballista con arañazos en la cara o amoratadas señales.

--Con esa no puedes tú--le decían los amigos en un tono de compasión cómica.--Es mucha mujer
para ti.

Y celebraban la energía de Lola, la admiraban, con la secreta esperanza de ser algún día de
los favorecidos.

El escándalo fue tan grande, que el marido se retiró a la casa de sus padres y la Marquesita
pudo por fin vivir a sus anchas.

--Márchate--la dijo un día su primo Dupont.--Tú y tu hermana sois nuestra deshonra. Huye lejos,
y donde estés yo te enviaré lo necesario para que vivas.

Pero Lola contestó con un ademán impúdico, gozándose en escandalizar a su devoto pariente.
No le daba la gana de irse, y no se iba. Ella era muy flamenca; le gustaba la tierra y su gente.
Marcharse sería poco menos que morir.

Anduvo algún tiempo por Madrid con su hermana, pero sus viajes fueron de corta duración. Era
una cañí, una hija legítima del marqués de San Dionisio. ¡Que no le quitasen a ella sus juerguecitas
hasta el amanecer, tocando palmas y taconeando sentada, con las faldas en las rodillas! ¡Que
no la privasen del vino de la tierra, que era su sangre y su felicidad! Si rabiaba la familia,
que rabiase. Ella quería ser gitana como su padre. Aborrecía a los señoritos; le gustaban los
hombres con sombrero pavero, y si llevaban zajones, mejor; pero muy hombres, oliendo a cuadra
y a macho sudoroso. Y paseaba su belleza de rubia fina con carnes de porcelana por los colmados
y ventorrillos, tratando con una fraternidad exagerada a los cantaoras y rameras que intervenían
en las juergas, exigiendo que la tuteasen, y riendo con nerviosa alegría de borracha cuando
los hombres, embrutecidos por el vino, sacaban las navajas y las hembras se apelotonaban asustadas
en un rincón.

Esta vida de embriaguez, estrépito, pelea y caricias alcohólicas que había entrevisto de niña
en lo casa paterna, atraíala con fuerza ancestral, entregándose a ella sin remordimiento, como
si continuase una tradición de familia. En sus excursiones nocturnas, cogida del brazo del
galán rústico que disfrutaba de su momentáneo apasionamiento, se encontraba con Luis Dupont
y su cortejo de gente alegre. Llamábanse primos por su lejano parentesco, se embriagaban juntos,
y Luis afirmaba su resolución de ir a tiros con todo el que no confesase que la Marquesita
era «la mujer más barbiana de la tierra». Pero a pesar de los abandonos de Lola, que permitían
al calavera apreciar sus secretos físicos, y de que más de una vez la acompañó hasta su casa
por las desiertas calles, haciendo esfuerzos por contener sus arrebatos de histérica que la
impulsaban al escándalo, nunca sus relaciones pasaron de una intimidad amistosa. Luis sentía
ciertos entorpecimientos en el deseo y dejaba para más adelante la fácil empresa, como si le
cohibiese el recuerdo del período de la infancia que habían pasado juntos.

Toda la ciudad comentaba los escándalos de la Marquesita a la que regocijaba mucho el asombro
de las gentes tranquilas.

Lo mismo la veían en las principales calles elegantemente vestida o en el Campo de la Feria
en un lujoso carruaje, como se presentaba despeinada y envuelta en un mantón copiando el andar
de las mozas bravas y contestando a los requiebros de los hombres con palabras que ruborizaban
a muchos. Gustaba de sonreír con gestos de misteriosa complicidad a los pacíficos señores que
pasaban junto a ella con sus familias. Después reía como una loca pensando en las querellas
conyugales que estallaban al volver a casa aquellos matrimonios honrados y solemnes que ella
había tratado cuando vivía con su esposo. En una acera de la calle Larga, ante las mesas de
los principales casinos, había besado a un amigo con exagerados transportes de pasión, entre
el griterío de la gente que salía a las puertas.

Su último amor era un mozo tratante en cerdos, un atleta chato y cejudo con el que vivía en
el arrabal. Un secreto poder de este macho fuerte la enloquecía. Hablaba de él con orgullo,
gozándose en el contraste entre su nacimiento y la profesión de su amante. De vez en cuando
sufría arrebatos de veleidad y se ausentaba de la casucha del arrabal por algunos días. El
zafio amante no la buscaba, dando su vuelta por segura; y al regresar el pájaro caprichoso,
todo el barrio poníase en alarma con los golpes y los gritos, saliendo la Marquesita al balcón
con el pelo suelto, pidiendo socorro, hasta que una zarpa la arrancaba de los hierros y la
metía dentro para continuar el vapuleo.

Si algún amigo le hablaba con tono de zumba de las amorosas palizas, contestaba con orgullo:

--Me pega porque me aprecia, y yo le quiero porque es el único que me entiende. Mi porquero
es todo un hombre.

Los escándalos de la Marquesita indignaban a muchos y regocijaban a los más. La gente popular
la miraba con cierta simpatía, como si con sus envilecimientos halagase el instinto igualitario
de los de abajo. Las familias ricas y devotas que no podían negar su parentesco con los de
San Dionisio, buscado antes como un título de orgullo, decían con resignación: «Debe de estar
loca; Dios tocará su alma para que se arrepienta».

Los que no se resignaban eran los Dupont: don Pablo y su madre, que volvían a su hotel malhumorados
y confusos cada vez que veían en las calles el rubio moño y la sonrisa insolente de Lola. Les
parecía que la gente era menos respetuosa con ellos por culpa de la mala hembra, deshonra de
la familia. Hasta creían ver en los criados cierta sonrisa, como si les alegrase la afrenta
que aquella loca infería a sus parientes. Los señores de Dupont comenzaron a frecuentar menos
las calles de la ciudad, pasando muchos días en su finca de Marchamalo, para evitar todo encuentro
con la Marquesita y con las gentes que comentaban sus excentricidades.

Este alejamiento de Jerez permitió a Dupont realizar sus ensueños sobre Marchamalo. Echó abajo
el antiguo caserón y construyó lagares nuevos, una hermosa casa para su familia, una capilla
espaciosa y rica como un templo, y un torreón cuadrado, con puntiagudas almenas, dominando
el oleaje de colinas cubiertas de cepas, que formaban el gran dominio de Marchamalo. Todo era
nuevo y sólido, construido con gran derroche de dinero. Únicamente dejó Dupont en pie la casa
de los viñadores, para que la finca no perdiese por completo su carácter tradicional, conservando
la cocina ennegrecida por el humo de muchos años, en la que dormían los jornaleros en torno
del fogaril, sobre una esterilla de enea, única cama que les proporcionaba el señor.

Fermín Montenegro, al ir en los días de fiesta a visitar a su familia, se encontraba siempre
con los amos. Así fue aumentando insensiblemente su trato con don Pablo. En medio de la campiña,
bajo el cielo de intenso azul, parecía dulcificarse el carácter imperioso de Dupont, haciéndole
tratar a su subordinado con más afecto que en el escritorio.

Contemplando el oleaje de cepas que cubría las pendientes blanquecinas, el rico cosechero admiraba
la fertilidad de su finca, atribuyéndola modestamente a la protección de Dios. Algunas manchas
yermas extendían su trágica desolación entre el follaje de los pámpanos. Eran los rastros de
la filoxera que había arruinado a medio Jerez. Los cosecheros, quebrantados por la baja de
los vinos, no tenían medios para replantar sus viñas. Era aquella una tierra aristocrática
y cara, que sólo los ricos podían cultivar. Poner de nuevo en explotación una aranzada costaba
tanto como el mantenimiento de una familia decente durante un año. Pero la casa Dupont era
opulenta y podía hacer frente a la plaga.

--Mira, Ferminillo--decía don Pablo;--todos esos claros los voy a plantar de vid americana.
Con esto, y, sobre todo, con el auxilio de Dios, ya verás como la cosa marcha bien. El Señor
está con los que le aman.

Doña Elvira, por su parte, no descendía a hacer confidente de sus pensamientos a la familia
de Montenegro, pero se dignaba hablarla con cierta llaneza, lo que producía asombro en sus
domésticos de la ciudad. La noble señora sentía ablandarse su orgullo viviendo en el campo.
Hablaba con el señor Fermín queriendo averiguar a qué iglesia de Jerez iba los domingos con
María de la Luz, para oír misa... Al ver a la hija del capataz abstraerse, poniendo su pensamiento
lejos, muy lejos, en el cortijo donde vivía Rafael, la buena señora interpretaba esta tristeza
como un anhelo de recogimiento, y la ofrecía su protección.

--No, señora--decía sonriendo la muchacha;--no quiero ser monja. A mí me tira la vida.

Para Fermín Montenegro no eran un secreto los disgustos de carácter espiritual, las grandes
contrariedades que sufría la viuda de Dupont por culpa de los negocios. Su hijo tenía que tratar
gentes de todas clases, herejes y hombres sin religión; extranjeros que consumían los vinos
de la casa, y al pasar por Jerez habían de ser recibidos con el agasajo que merecen los buenos
clientes. ¡Ser buenos servidores del Señor y tener que tratar a sus enemigos como si fuesen
iguales! En vano los Padres de la iglesia de San Ignacio disipaban sus escrúpulos recordándola
la importancia de los negocios y la influencia que una casa tan poderosa ejercía sobre la religiosidad
de Jerez. Doña Elvira sólo se reconciliaba con sus famosas bodegas cuando una vez por año salía
con destino a Roma una barrica de vino, dulce y espeso como jarabe, destinado a la misa del
Pontífice por recomendación de varios obispos, amigos de la casa. Este honor la servía de lenitivo.
Pero aun así, ¡qué angustias no la hacían sufrir aquellos extranjeros rubios y antipáticos
que tenían la audacia de leer la Biblia a su modo y en su lengua, sin creer en Su Santidad,
ni ir a misa!...

Montenegro conocía uno de los últimos disgustos de la piadosa señora, que le habían relatado
los criados de la casa.

Los Dupont tenían un viajante sueco, el mejor agente de su negocio. Colocaba miles y miles
de botellas del vino de fuego que producía Marchamalo, en aquellos países septentrionales de
noches casi eternas y días de pleno sol, que duran meses. El viajante, después de muchos años
de servicios a la casa, había venido a España, pasando por Jerez, para conocer personalmente
a los Dupont. Don Pablo había creído indispensable el invitarlo a comer con su familia.

Horrible tormento el que sufrió su madre ante aquel desconocido, enorme de cuerpo, rojo y hablador,
con esa alegría infantil de los hombres del Norte cuando se ponen en contacto con el sol y
los vinos de los países cálidos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09333</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>150276</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21119</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> And if you seviyanas hey say that if that
if Malaga, say that is chickweed. Jerez is the key in der cante. I declare that toos the sages
of the world.

When Rafael was felt strongly he had to terminate this period of sweet intimacy. One evening
he spoke alone with Mr. Fermin. He could not stay there, and soon reach the tenants, and home entertainment
Marchamalo regain her small town. In addition, Don Pablo announced plans to tear down the
mansion, to build that castle with which dreamed as a glorification of his family. Rafael explain
how their presence in the vineyard? It was a shame that a man of his energies to remain there,
without occupation, living under his godfather.

The matter seemed forgotten that night. He was not afraid to be persecuted, but he was determined
not to return to her old life.

- With vast, godfather had your honor right. Neither this is an honest way to make bread, nor
is there jembra to put up with a waiter how much money you bring home may die crummy.

He felt no fear, never!, But had his plans for the future. Wanted to obtain a family, like his father,
as his godfather, and not spend her life by throwing them in check
on the mountain.

Seek a more honest and peaceful occupation, but knew hunger.

And that's when Mr. Fermín, using his influence with Dupont, Rafael made Matanzuela overseer
of the farmhouse, owned by the nephew of the late Don Pablo.

The so Luis Jerez had again become a man, after a continuous pilgrimage all universities in Spain,
looking for professors who did not have leeway effort to frustrate future lawyers. His uncle had
an obligation to pursue a career, and while it lived, had resigned to lead the life of a student,
adjusting to close remittances and augment them with fierce loans, for which he signed in
the eyes how many papers they wanted to introduce closed loan sharks.

But to see the front of the family his cousin Paul and his next oldest, had refused to continue longer
comedy of their studies. He was rich, did not want to waste time on things that nothing interested
him. He took possession of his property, started the free existence of pleasure with which he had
dreamed of his close student life.

He traveled throughout Spain, but it was not to pass a subject here and beyond: aspired to be an
authority on the art of bullfighting, a great man of the fans, and went from place to place next
to your favorite matador, witnessing all of their runs. In winter, when resting their idols,
lived in Jerez in the care of their estates, and this care was passed
night at the Circle Caballista, heatedly discussing the merits of
his killer and the inferiority of their rivals, but with such vehemence,
that if a wound received years before a bull, of which there were
no bones or had been dropped or in place tentábase clothing over the
gun, the knife, the whole arsenal carrying on his person, as a guarantee
of value and the arrogance with which solved their issues.

No horse came out beautiful and Jerez stud price, not to buy it, engaging Bid with her cousin,
who was richer than him. At night, the mountaineers of the grocery stores will were entered
as a harbinger of storm, confident they would end up breaking bottles and plates and throwing
chairs through the air, to prove it was a real man and could then
afford all at triple price.

His ambition lay in being the continuation of the glorious San Marquis Dionisio, but in the Circle
Caballista said of him that was just a caricature.

- Le Farta the
estate, the one of the blessed scored - Mr. Fermin said after learning
of feats of Louis, whom he knew since childhood.

Women and the brave were the two passions of Master. With them was not very generous, wanted to be
adored by his merits rider arrogant, believing in good faith Jerez balconies all shook with the pounding
of hearts hidden when passing riding the last horse he had just purchased. With the court with
him, pests and bullies were more splendid. There was around the end of a bully famous Jerez sad not been
there he attracted by his liberality. Those who went to prison did not have to worry about
their fate, Don Luis was a good friend and also to give them money, they admired. When late-night carousing
at the end of the convenience stores, he felt drunk, scorned their loved ones to fix all his admiration
bronze in men who accompanied him. Was to show him the scars of his wounds, which described
his heroic fights. Many Sometimes, in the Circle Caballista pointed to a man Malcarado friends
waiting for him at the door.

- That's the Goat - said with the pride
of a prince who speaks of his great generals .-- A man who was dragged
along the ground tassels.

Between shooting and stabbing is over fifty scars on the skin.

I looked at all with insolent superiority, as if the scars were a
statement buddy of self-worth, and lived happily believing that everything
Jerez no one would dispute his guapeza with men and their good fortune
with women.

When the foreman Marchamalo spoke in favor of Rafael, the gentleman
admitted immediately.

I had heard the boy, was his own (and he said this took the air guard a teacher), I remembered certain
shots in the mountains and the fear that had the the shelter. Nothing, that stayed with him
and liked men.

- I will place in my farmhouse Matanzuela - said stroking Rafael friendly slap, like a new disciple
.-- The overseer I have is a short-sighted old media, which laugh the farmhands. And we know
what are the workers, poor people! With them, bread in one hand, and stick in the other. I need
a man like you, who put them in waist look after my interests.

And Rafael went to the farmhouse, not returning to the vineyard more than once a week, when
I was Jerez to talk to the master of the affairs of the farm. I often had to look at the house
of one of its protected. I got in bed, sitting on the cushion, resting in another head. The new
overseer laughed alone the bluster of his master, more attentive to recommend the hardness and
"metiese waist" to the lazy who worked their fields, to learn about agricultural operations, blaming
the poor harvests the farmhands, a scoundrel who would not work and wished that the masters were
to become servants, as if the world could turn upside down.

Don Luis came to forget about their hobbies and their amorous exploits bullying when he spoke boorish
people of the fields, driven by false apostles wanted to divide it all. He had studied (as
declared pompously at the Circle Caballista, regardless of the smiles of those who heard him),
he knew what he wanted the workers were utopias, that is, utopias (and repeated with pleasure the
word), and that all that happened was because governments do not "put into shape" for the laborers,
and also by lack of religion. Yes sir, religion: it was the brake of the poor, and as there
was less, the underdog, under the pretext of hunger, they wanted to eat the above.

These words were no longer smile Caballista partners, but those approved earnest gestures, with
all their faith in rich farmers, who shrugged his shoulders when a proposed deluded swamps and
canals, and every year large parties coasting to the Virgin of Merced, pulling it in supplication
just missing the water to their fields.

Despite these ideas that spread Luis in his moments of seriousness, saying that better went
about things if the governor, Don Pablo Dupont abhorred his cousin,
considering a shame to the family.

This relative, who renewed the scandals of San Dionisio, aggravated, according to Dona Elvira
plebeian in origin, was a calamity in a house that had always instilled respect for its noble
and holy customs. To make matters worse were the Marquis girls, Lola and Mercedes. The times
when his aunt choked with indignation, surprised by the night a grid floor of their hotel, talking
with the couple, which were renewed almost weekly! Tan lieutenants were soon back, as gentlemen's
horses, or young Englishmen, employees on desks, which were excited by stripping the country-style
turkey and made laugh Andalusian girls with British broken. There was no boy in Jerez had not
its time to talk with marquesitas unwrapped. Faced them all: just stand at their gates to enter
into dialogue, and without stopping passersby were persecuted the laughter and hisses sounded
ironic that behind him. Dupont's widow could not dominate his nieces, and they, in turn, and grew
up, showed themselves more insolent the devout lady. It was in vain that his cousin banned
from the bars. Burlábanse him and his mother, adding that they were not born to nuns. Listened hypocritical
gesture talks of the confessor of Dona Elvira recommending submission, and made use of all
kind of easy ways to communicate with the leading men on foot and
on horseback roamed the streets.

A Master of the Horse, son of a farmer, a great friend of the house Dupont, fell in love Lola, asking
her to marry in haste, as if afraid that he escaped.

Dona Elvira and her son accepted the application: The Circle raised eyebrows the value of that boy
marrying a daughter of the Marquis of San Dionisio.

This marriage was to release the two sisters. The single went to the other emancipate joyous
end of the sullen and devoted aunt, and a few months back to resume husband at home watching
habits near Dupont.

Mercedes spent the night in the privacy fence in tight with the couple, his sister with an
air of acompañábala lady, and talked with others to not waste time. The husband protested,
trying to rebel. But the two were indignant against him because he dared to interpret these
diversions innocent in a way offensive to her modesty.

Which of the two provided dislikes Marquis, as they were called in the city, the Dona Elvira
austere! ... Mercedes, the single, escaped with a rich Englishman. From time to time vague
news came that made pale with anger to the noble lady.

Sometimes they saw in Paris, others in Madrid, leading a life of elegant courtesan. Frequently
changed protectors, as attracted by his grace dozens picaresque. Further, in certain vanities produced
a great impression the title of Marchioness of San Dionisio, who had joined his name, nobility and
the crown that adorned their shirts at night and the sheets of a bed so popular as a main street
sidewalk.

Dupont's widow thought he would die to know such things. Lord, and for this were born the illustrious
men of his family, viceroys, archbishops and captains, giving the monarch titles and domains!
To serve as a prospect so much glory to a bad woman! ... And yet it was the best of both worlds.
At last he had fled for not insult about his family, and if she lived in sin, was among men
of a certain lineage, always decent, as is influenced in her respects to the rank of his family.

But
there was another, the eldest, married woman, and she wanted to end all killing relatives
shame. Married life after the escape of Mercedes, was hell.

The husband lived in perpetual suspicion, going blind in his suspicions, not knowing who to
be fixed because his wife looked equally to all men, as if it were offered to the eyes, talking
with a freedom that encouraged all kinds of daring. Fermin was jealous of Montenegro, which
had just arrived from London, and resumed his child intimacy Lola
frequent visitors, attracted by its picaresque language.

The domestic scenes ended with blows.

The husband, on the advice of friends, went to the slap and stick to tame the "wild beast",
but the little animals that justified the nickname, because when
stirred with vigor and aggressiveness of a feral child worthy of his
illustrious father, returned the blows so that was always the spouse
who was spared worse.

Often presented in the Circle Caballista with scratches on his face and bruised signals.

- With this you can not - he said friends in a tone of compassion .-- It is very funny woman
for you.

And celebrating the energy of Lola, the admired, with the secret hope of some day the disadvantaged.

The
scandal was so great that the husband retired to his parents and Marcasite was finally able to live
at home.

- Go away - the day her cousin said Dupont .-- You and your sister are our shame. Flee away and
where I will send you the necessary to live.

But Lola said with a lewd gesture, delighting in shock to his devoted family member. He pleased not
to go, and did not leave. She was very Flemish liked the land and its people. Would leave little
more than death.

Madrid walked some time with her sister, but his travels were short lived. Was a cañí, legitimate
daughter of the Marquis of San Dionisio. Not to take from it its juerguecitas until dawn, touching
palms and heels sitting with their skirts at the knees! That do not deprive the local wine,
it was his blood and happiness! If the family was raging, raging. She wanted to be a gypsy
like his father. Hated the gentlemen, he liked Pavero men in hats, and if they had zajones the better,
but real men, smelling block male and sweaty. And walking the fine blonde beauty with porcelain
meat grocery stores and inns, dealing with a fraternity exaggerated to the singers and prostitutes
that involved in binges, requiring that tuteasen, and laughing with nervous joy of drunk when
men, stupefied by wine, pull out the knives and females huddle frightened in a corner.

This life of drunkenness, noise, fights and alcohol that had seen fondling girl in the parental
home, atraíala ancestral hard, giving it without remorse, as whether
to continue a family tradition.

In their nocturnal outings, catching arm rustic lover enjoyed his momentary infatuation, was
with Louis Dupont and his entourage of happy people.

Cousins ??called themselves by their distant relative, got drunk together, and Luis said his
decision to go to death with anyone who does not confess that Marquesita was "the woman Barbiana
of the earth." But despite the retirements of Lola, which allowed the skull appreciate their physical
secrets, and that more than once accompanied her to her house through the deserted streets, struggling
to contain their outbursts of hysterical that drove the scandal their relationship never became
a friendly intimacy. Luis felt certain hindrances in the desire and later left for the easy
business, as if Cohiba memory of the period of childhood they had spent together.

Commented citywide Marquesita scandals of the exhilarating much amazement
of the people quiet.

The same thing they saw in the main streets or in the elegantly dressed Country Fair in a luxurious
carriage, as it appeared disheveled, wrapped in a shawl walking copying of the girls wild
and answering the blandishments of the men with words blush many. He liked to smile with mysterious
gestures of complicity in the peaceful gentlemen she passed by with their families. After laughing
like crazy thinking complaints exploding the marital home and solemn marriages that honored
her had tried when she lived with her husband.

In one long side of the street, with tables the major casinos, had
kissed a friend exaggerated passion transport between the shouting
of the people who came to the door.

His last love was a young dealer in pigs, an athlete and warbler flat with living in the suburb.
One secret to this strong male's crazy. Spoke of him with pride, delighting in the contrast between
his birth and occupation of her lover. Occasionally suffered fits of levity and was absent
from the hut of the suburbs for a few days. The uncouth lover not wanted, making his return for
safe, and to return the wayward bird, whole neighborhood put on alert
with the blows and screams out the balcony Marquesita with her hair
down, asking for help, until a paw the started of the iron and got
inside to continue the thrashing.

If a friend spoke with buzzing tone of loving beatings, he answered with pride:

- He hits me because I can see, and I love him because he is the only one who understands me.
My swineherd is a man.

The scandals of the Marquesita outraged many, and rejoiced at the most. Popular people looked at
with some sympathy, as if their debasement flattered egalitarian instinct from below. Wealthy
families and devotees who could not deny their relationship to those of San Dionisio, looked
before as a title of pride, said with resignation: "It must be crazy, God will touch your soul
to repent. "

Those who resigned were not Dupont: Don Pablo and his mother, who returned to his hotel moody
and confused every time they saw on the streets the blond bun and
Lola insolent smile.

Les seemed that people were less respectful to them because of poor female dishonor family.
Even thought they saw in the raised certain smile, as if the insult them joy inferred that this
crazy relatives. Dupont lords began to frequent less the streets of the city, passing many days
on his farm in Marchamalo to avoid meeting the Marquesa and the people
who commented on his eccentricities.

This move away from Jerez allowed Dupont make their dreams on Marchamalo. Broke down the old
house and built new wineries, a beautiful house for his family, a chapel spacious and rich
as a temple, and a square tower with pointed battlements overlooking the waves of hills covered
with vines, which formed the great Marchamalo domain. Everything was new and solid, built with
great waste of money. Only left the house standing Dupont of the tenants, so that the farm
does not completely lose its traditional character, retaining The
smoky kitchen many years, in which laborers were sleeping around of
fogaril on a rush mat, only bed that gave them the Lord.

Fermín Montenegro, to go on holidays to visit his family, was always
with their owners.

Thus grew insensibly his dealings with Don Pablo. In the middle of the countryside, under the
bright blue sky, seemed to soften the imperious character of Dupont, making treat their subject
with more affection than on the desktop.

Watching the waves of strains that covered the slopes white, rich admired grower the fertility of his
farm, modestly attributing God's protection. Some spots extended their tragic barren desolation
among the foliage of the branches.

Traces were phylloxera that had ruined half Jerez.

Growers, crushed by falling wines, could not afford to replant their vineyards. It was a land
that aristocratic and expensive that only the rich could cultivate. Put back into operation a cost
aranzadas well as maintaining a decent family for a year. But the house was Dupont affluent
and could deal with the plague.

- Look, Ferminillo - said Don Paul, - all these clearly going to plant the American vine. With
this, and, above all, with God's help, you'll see how the thing goes well. The Lord is with those who
love Him.

Dona Elvira, meanwhile, did not descend to make confident of his thoughts to the family of Montenegro,
but deigned to speak with some frankness, which caused astonishment in their household in
the city. The noble lady was softened his pride living in the countryside. He spoke with Mr.
Fermin trying to figure out what was going Jerez church on Sundays
with Maria de la Luz, for mass ... To see the daughter of the foreman
abstract, putting his thoughts far, far away in the farmhouse where
he lived Rafael, the good lady played this sadness as a desire to
retreat, and offered his protection.

- No, ma'am - the girl said
smiling, - I do not want to be a nun.

A strip me of life.

Fermín Montenegro was not a secret for spiritual troubles, large setbacks suffered by the widow
of Dupont because of business. His son had to deal people of all classes, heretics and men without
religion, foreigners who drank wine of the house, and going through Jerez were to be greeted
with the treat they deserve good customers. Be good servants of the Lord and have to treat their
enemies as if they were Same!

In vain the Fathers of the Church of San Ignacio dissipated his scruples remembering the importance
of business and the influence exerted so powerful a house on the religiosity Jerez. Dona Elvira
only reconciled with its famous wine cellars where once a year out
for Rome a cask of wine, sweet and syrupy, for the Mass Pope on the
recommendation of several bishops, friends of the house. The honor
of serving as soothing. Still, what troubles did not suffer those
nasty blond foreign who had the audacity to read the Bible in their
own way and in their language, without believing in His Holiness or
go to Mass! ...

Montenegro knew one of the recent troubles of the
pious lady, who had reported the servants of the house.

The Dupont
had a Swedish traveler, the best agent for your business. Put thousands
and thousands bottles of wine produced Marchamalo fire in northern
countries almost endless nights and sunny days, which last month.
The salesman, after many years service to the house, had come to Spain,
to Jerez, to personally meet to Dupont. Don Pablo had thought indispensable
to dinner with his family.

Horrible torment that her mother suffered
at the stranger, huge body, red and talkative, with the childlike
joy of the Northmen when they come into contact with the sun and wines
from warmer countries</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>