<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04603</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>298574</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24214</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Si yo tuviera que guardar mi fama, aviada estaba con un amigo como usted. ¡Qué cosas
suponen por ahí!

Y reía con una expresión de superioridad, considerándose muy por encima de cuanto pudieran
decir las gentes de su amistad con Rafael.

--En el mercado me hablan de usted todas las vendedoras como si esto fuese para mí el más irresistible
de los halagos; aseguran que formamos una soberbia pareja. Mi hortelana aprovecha todas las
ocasiones para decirme que es usted muy guapo. Dele usted las gracias... ¿Qué más? Hasta mi
tía, mi pobre tía que vive en el Limbo, ha salido de él para decirme el otro día: «¿Sabes que
Rafaelito viene mucho por aquí? ¿si querrá casarse contigo?» Ya ve usted; casarse ¡já! ¡já!
¡já! ¡casarse! La pobre señora no ve más que esto en el mundo.

Y seguía arrojando a la cara de Rafael, sombrío por sus malos pensamientos, aquella risa franca
y burlona que parecía el parloteo de un pájaro travieso satisfecho de su libertad.

--¡Pero qué mala cara tiene usted hoy! ¿Está usted enfermo?... ¿Qué le pasa?

Rafael aprovechó el momento. Estaba enfermo, sí; enfermo de amor. Comprendía que toda la ciudad
hablase de ellos; él no podía ocultar sus sentimientos. ¡Si supiera lo que le costaba aquella
adoración muda! Quería arrancar de su pensamiento la devoción por ella, y no podía. Necesitaba
verla, oírla; sólo vivía para ella. ¿Leer? imposible. ¿Hablar con sus amigos? Todos le repugnaban.
Su casa era una cueva en la que entraba con gran esfuerzo para comer y dormir. Salía de ella
tan pronto como despertaba y abandonaba la ciudad, que le parecía una cárcel. Al campo; y en
el campo la casa azul donde ella vivía. ¡Con qué impaciencia esperaba la llegada de la tarde,
la hora en que por una tácita costumbre, que ninguno de los dos marcó, podía él entrar en el
huerto y encontrarla en su banco bajo las palmeras!... No podía vivir así. La pobre gente le
envidiaba al verle poderoso, diputado tan joven; y él quería ser... ¿a qué no lo adivinaba?
¡qué cosas tan absurdas! ¡que no se burlara Leonora! El daría cuanto era por ser aquel banco
del jardín, abrumado dulcemente por su peso las tardes enteras; por convertirse en la labor
que giraba entre sus dedos delicados; por transfigurarse en una de las personas que la rodeaban
a todas horas, de aquella Beppa, por ejemplo, que la despertaba por las mañanas, inclinándose
sobre su cabeza dormida, moviendo con su aliento la cabellera deshecha, esparcida como una
ola de oro sobre la almohada y que secaba sus carnes de marfil a la salida del baño, deslizando
sus manos por las curvas entrantes y salientes de su suave cuerpo. Siervo, animal, objeto inanimado,
algo que estuviera en perpetuo contacto con su persona, eso ansiaba él: no verse obligado con
la llegada de la noche a alejarse tras una interminable despedida prolongada con infantiles
pretextos, al volver a la irritante vulgaridad de su vida, a la soledad de su cuarto, en cuyos
rincones obscuros, como maléfica tentación, creía ver fijos en él unos ojos verdes.

Leonora no reía. Abríanse desmesuradamente sus ojos moteados de oro; palpitaban de emoción
las alillas de su nariz, y parecía conmovida por la sinceridad elocuente del joven.

--¡Pobre Rafael! ¡Pobrecito mío!... ¿Y qué vamos a hacer?

En el huerto, Rafael jamás se había atrevido a hablar con tanta franqueza. Le cohibía la proximidad
de los allegados de Leonora; le intimidaba el aire superficial y burlón con que ella recibía
sus visitas; la ironía con que le desconcertaba apenas apuntaba él una frase de amor. Pero
allí, en medio del camino, era otra cosa; se sentía libre, quería vaciar su corazón. ¡Qué tormentos!
Todos los días iba hacia la casa azul trémulo de esperanza, agitado por la ilusión. «Tal vez
sea hoy», se decía. Y le temblaban las piernas, y la saliva parecía solidificarse en su garganta,
ahogándole. Y horas más tarde, al anochecer, la vuelta desesperada al hogar, marchando desalentado
a la luz de las estrellas, haciendo eses en el camino como si estuviera ebrio, sintiendo que
las lágrimas le escarabajeaban en los párpados, queriendo morir, como el que necesita pasar
adelante y se rompe los puños contra un muro inmenso de bloques de hielo. ¿No se fijaba en
él? ¿no veía los inmensos esfuerzos que hacía para agradarla?... Ignorante, humilde, reconociendo
la inmensa diferencia que separaba a ambos por su distinta vida, ¡qué de esfuerzos para llegar
a su altura; por colocarse al nivel de aquellos hombres que la habían poseído por unos días
o por años enteros! Ella debía haberlo notado. Si le hablaba del conde ruso, modelo de elegancia,
al día siguiente Rafael, con gran asombro de los de su casa, sacaba su mejor ropa, y sudando
bajo el sol, oprimido por el alto cuello, emprendía aquel camino que era su calle de Amargura,
andando como una señorita para que el polvo no amortiguase el brillo de sus botas. Si el músico
alemán cruzaba por el recuerdo de Leonora, él repasaba sus libros, y afectando el exterior
descuidado de aquellos artistas vistos en las novelas, llegaba allá con el propósito de hablar
del inmortal maestro, de Wagner, al que apenas conocía, pero al que adoraba como a una persona
de su familia... ¡Dios mío! Todo esto resultaba ridículo, bien lo sabía él; mejor era presentarse
sin disfraz, con toda su pequeñez. Reconocía que era imposible aquella lucha para igualarse
con los mil fantasmas que llenaban la memoria de Leonora; ¡pero qué no haría él por despertar
aquel corazón por ser amado un momento, un día nada más, y después morir!

Y había tal sinceridad en esta confesión de amor, que Leonora, cada vez más conmovida, se aproximaba
a él, caminaba pegada a su cuerpo sin darse cuenta y sonreía levemente, repitiendo su frase,
mezcla de afecto maternal y de lástima.

--¡Pobre Rafael!... ¡Pobrecito mío!

Habían llegado a la verja que daba entrada al huerto. La avenida estaba desierta. En la plazoleta,
frente a la cerrada casa, correteaban las gallinas.

Rafael, abrumado por el esfuerzo de aquella confesión, en la que daba curso a las angustias
y ensueños de muchos meses, se apoyó en el tronco de un viejo naranjo. Leonora estaba frente
a él escuchándole con la cabeza baja, rayando el suelo con la contera de su roja sombrilla.

Morir, sí; él había leído esto muchas veces en las novelas sin poder contener una sonrisa.
Ahora ya no reía. Había pensado algunas noches, en la turbación del delirio, terminar aquel
amor de un modo trágico. La sangre de su padre, violenta y avasalladora, hervía en él. Si llegaba
a convencerse de que nunca sería suya, ¡matarla para que no fuese de nadie, y matarse él después!
Caer los dos sobre la tierra empapada de sangre, como sobre un lecho de damasco rojo; besarla
él, en los labios fríos, sin miedo a que nadie le estorbara; besarla y besarla hasta que el
último soplo de vida fuese a perderse en la lívida boca de ella.

Lo decía con convicción, vibrando todos los músculos de su cara varonil, ardiendo como brasas
sus ojos de moro veteados por la pasión con venillas de sangre. Y Leonora le miraba ahora con
apasionamiento, como si viese un hombre nuevo. Estremecíase con una emoción nueva al oír los
bárbaros ensueños, las amenazas de muerte. Aquel no se mataba melancólicamente como el poeta
italiano viendo perdido su amor: moría matando, destrozaba el ídolo, ya que no atendía sus
súplicas.

Y dulcemente conmovida por la expresión trágica de Rafael, se dejaba llevar por éste, que la
había cogido un brazo y la atraía lejos de la avenida entre las copas bajas de los naranjos.

Permanecieron los dos en silencio mucho rato. Leonora parecía embriagada por el perfume viril
de aquellas amenazas de pasión salvaje.

Rafael, al ver cabizbaja y silenciosa a la artista, creyó que la habían ofendido sus palabras,
y se arrepintió de ellas.

Debía perdonarle, estaba loco. Se exasperaba ante su resistencia inexplicable. ¡Leonora! ¡Leonora!
¿A qué empeñarse en estorbar la obra del amor? El no era indiferente para ella, no le inspiraba
antipatía ni odio; de lo contrario, no serían amigos ni le permitiría las continuas visitas.
¿Amor?... Estaba seguro de que no lo sentía por él, pobre infeliz, incapaz de inspirar una
pasión a una mujer como ella. Pero que no se resistiera; ya le amaría con el tiempo; él lograría
conquistarla en fuerza de cariño y de adoración. ¡Ay! con sólo su amor, había para los dos
y para todos los amantes famosos en la historia. Sería su esclavo, la alfombra en que pondría
sus pies; el perro, siempre tendido ante ella, con la mirada ardiente de la eterna fidelidad,
acabaría por quererle, si no por amor, por gratitud y por lástima.

Y al hablar así, acercaba su rostro al de Leonora, buscando su imagen en el fondo de los ojos
verdes; oprimía su brazo con la fiebre de la pasión.

--Cuidado, Rafael... me hace usted daño, suélteme usted.

Y como si despertara en pleno peligro después de un dulce sueño, se estremeció, desasiéndose
con nervioso impulso.

Después comenzó a hablar con calma, repuesta ya de la embriaguez con que le habían turbado
las apasionadas palabras de Rafael.

No, lo que él deseaba era imposible. La suerte estaba echada, no quería amor... La amistad
les había llevado algo lejos. Ella tenía la culpa, pero sabría remediarlo. Era ya un barco
viejo que no podía cargar con el peso de una nueva pasión. Si le hubiera conocido años antes,
tal vez. Reconocía que hubiese llegado a quererle; le creía más digno de su amor que otros
hombres a los que había amado. Pero llegaba tarde; ahora sólo quería vivir. ¡Qué horror! ¡las
emociones de la pasión en un ambiente mezquino, en aquel mundo pequeño de curiosidades y maledicencias!
¡Ocultarse como criminales para quererse! ¡Ella, que gustaba del amor al aire libre, con el
sublime impudor de la estatua que escandaliza a los imbéciles con su desnuda hermosura! ¡Verse
roída a todas horas por la murmuración de los tontos, después de haber dado su cuerpo y su
alma a un hombre! ¡Sentir en torno el desprecio y la indignación de todo un pueblo que la acusaría
de haber corrompido una juventud, separándola de su camino, alejándola para siempre de los
suyos! No, Rafael, mil veces no; ella tenía conciencia, ya no era la loca de otros tiempos.

--Pero ¿y yo?--suspiraba el joven agarrando de nuevo su brazo con ansiedad infantil--usted
piensa en sí misma y en todos, olvidándome a mi. ¿Qué voy a hacer yo a solas con mi pasión?

--Usted olvidará--dijo gravemente Leonora.--Hoy he visto que es imposible mi estancia aquí.
Los dos necesitamos alejarnos. Huiré antes que termine la primavera; iré no sé dónde, volveré
al mundo, a cantar, donde no encuentre hombres como usted, y el tiempo y la ausencia se encargarán
de curarle.

Leonora se estremeció al ver la llamarada de salvaje pasión que pasó por los ojos de Rafael.
Sintió junto a los labios el ardoroso resuello de aquella boca que buscaba la suya, murmurando
con apagado rugido:

--No, no te irás; quiero que no te vayas.

Y se sintió enlazada, conmovida de cabeza a pies por unos brazos nerviosos a los que la pasión
daba nueva fuerza. Sus pies se despegaron del suelo, se sintió elevada; un impulso brutal la
hizo caer de costado al pie de un naranjo, al mismo tiempo que en sus ropas se agitaban unas
manos convulsas, estremecidas, que herían las carnes con caricias de fiera.

Fue una lucha brutal, innoble que duró unos instantes. La walkyria reapareció en la mujer vencida.
Su cuerpo robusto vibró con un supremo esfuerzo, incorporose sofocando con su peso a Rafael,
y al fin Leonora se irguió, poniendo su pie brutalmente, sin misericordia, sobre el pecho del
joven, apretando como si quisiera hacer crujir la osamenta de su pecho.

Su aspecto era terrible. Parecía loca, con su rubia cabellera deshecha y sucia de tierra. Sus
verdes ojos brillaban con reflejos metálicos como agudos puñales, y su boca, descolorida por
la emoción, contraíase, lanzando, por la fuerza de la costumbre, por el instinto del esfuerzo,
su grito de guerra, un ¡hojotoho! desgarrado, salvaje, que conmovió la calma del huerto, estremeciendo
a las aves de corral, que corrieron asustadas por los senderos.

Blandía con furor la sombrilla cual si fuese la lanza de las hijas de Wotan, y varias veces
apuntó con ella a los ojos de Rafael como si quisiera sacárselos.

El joven parecía abatido por su esfuerzo, avergonzado de su brutalidad, inerte en el suelo,
sin protesta, como si deseara no levantarse jamás; morir bajo aquel pie que le asfixiaba iracundo.

Leonora se serenó, y lentamente fue retrocediendo algunos pasos, mientras Rafael se incorporaba,
recogiendo su sombrero.

Fue una escena penosa. Los dos sentían frío, no veían luz, como si el sol se hubiera apagado
y sobre el huerto soplase un viento glacial.

Rafael miraba avergonzado al suelo; tenía miedo de verla, miedo de contemplarse con las ropas
en desorden, sucio de tierra, batido y golpeado como un ladrón al que sorprende un amo fuerte.

Oyó la voz de Leonora, hablándole con la despreciativa familiaridad que se usa con los miserables.

--¡Vete!

Levantó los ojos y vio los de Leonora irritados y altivos, fijos en él.

--A mí no se me toma--dijo con frialdad;--me entrego, si es que quiero.

Y en el gesto de desprecio y rabia con que despedía a Rafael, parecía marcarse el recuerdo
odioso de Boldini, aquel viejo repugnante, el único en el mundo que la había tomado por la fuerza.

Rafael quiso excusarse, pedir perdón, pero aquel recuerdo de la adolescencia evocado por la
escena brutal, la hacía implacable.

--¡Vete, vete, o te abofeteo!... Jamás vuelvas aquí.

Y para dar más fuerza a estas palabras cuando Rafael, humillado y sucio, salió del huerto,
Leonora cerró tras él la verja de madera con tan brutal ímpetu, que casi hizo saltar los barrotes.

IV

Doña Bernarda mostrábase contenta de su Rafael. Se acabaron las miradas feroces, los gestos
severos, las mudas escenas entre madre e hijo, que presenciaban con temor los íntimos de la casa.

Ya no iba a la casa azul; lo sabía con gran certeza, gracias al espionaje gratuito con que
la servían las gentes afectas a la familia. Apenas salía de casa; un rato al casino por las
tardes, y el resto del día en el comedor con ella y los amigos, o encerrado en su cuarto, a
vueltas sin duda con sus libros, que la austera señora miraba con el respeto supersticioso
de su ignorancia.

Don Andrés, el consejero, se mostraba triunfante al comentar aquel cambio. ¿Qué había dicho
él, siempre que doña Bernarda, en las íntimas confidencias de aquella amistad que casi tomaba
el carácter de una pasión senil, tranquila y respetuosa, se quejaba de la rebeldía del muchacho?
Aquello pasaría: era un capricho de la edad; había que dar a la juventud lo suyo. Rafael no
había estudiado para cartujo. ¡Otros a su edad y aun con más años eran peores!... Y el viejo
señor pensaba sonriendo en sus fáciles conquistas de los almacenes, entre el rebaño despeinado,
miserable y de sucios zagalejos que empapela la naranja. La buena doña Bernarda, después de
sufrir tanto de su marido era demasiado exigente con su hijo. ¡Que se divirtiera! ¡que gozara!
Ya se cansaría de la artista con ser tan hermosa, y entonces sería fácil volverle a la buena senda.

Doña Bernarda admiraba una vez más el talento del consejero, viendo cumplidas sus predicciones,
hechas con un cinismo que enrojecía a la devota señora.

Ella también lo creía acabado todo. Su hijo era menos ciego que el padre. Se había cansado
del amor de una mujer perdida como aquella; no quería reñir con su madre por tan poca cosa,
ni que los enemigos le desacreditasen y volvía a su deber con gran alegría de la buena señora
que le rodeaba de solícitas atenciones.

--¿Y de aquello?--le preguntaban misteriosamente sus amigas.

--Nada--respondía con una sonrisa de orgullo.--Han pasado tres semanas, y ni asomos de querer
volver allá. Mi Rafael es bueno. Lo ocurrido no fue más que una distracción de muchacho. ¡Si
le vierais por las tardes haciéndome compañía en la sala! Un ángel, un verdadero ángel. Se
pasa las horas hablando conmigo y con la hija de Matías.

Y añadía, extremando su sonrisa y con ojos maliciosos:

--Creo que hay algo.

Algo había, sí; o por lo menos apariencia de haberlo. Rafael, cansado de vagar por la casa
fatigado de los libros ante los cuales pasaba horas enteras volviendo hojas, sin darse cuenta
de lo que decían, refugiábase en el salón donde cosía su madre, vigilando un complicado bordado
de la hija de don Matías.

Rafael gustaba de la mansa sencillez de aquella muchacha. Su simplicidad producía en él una
impresión de frescura y descanso. La veía como una cuevecita angosta y oculta en la cual dormitaba
tranquilo después de una tempestad. La sonrisa satisfecha de su madre le animaba a permanecer
allí. Jamás la había visto tan bondadosa y comunicativa. El goce de tenerle otra vez seguro
y sumiso modificaba su carácter austero hasta la rudeza.

Remedios, con la cabeza inclinada sobre su bordado, enrojecía intensamente cada vez que Rafael
alababa su obra o la decía que era la muchacha más bonita de Alcira. La ayudaba a enhebrar
las agujas; con las manos extendidas servía de devanadera a las madejas que ovillaba la joven,
y más de una vez la pellizcaba por debajo del bastidor, con la confianza de haberla conocido
niña, lo que no evitaba sus gritos escandalizados.

--Rafael, no seas loco--decía la madre amenazándole bondadosamente con sus secas manos.--Deja
trabajar a Remedios; si te portas tan mal no te permitiré entrar en la sala.

Y por la noche, a solas en el comedor con don Andrés, cuando llegaba la hora de las confidencias,
doña Bernarda olvidaba los asuntos de la casa y del partido para decir con satisfacción:

--Eso marcha.

--¿Se enamora Rafaelito?...

--Cada día más. La cosa va a todo vapor. Ese chico es en esto el vivo retrato de su padre.
Crea usted que conviene que no les pierda de vista. Si no estuviera yo aquí, ese diablillo
sería capaz de una locura que desacreditase la casa.

Y la buena señora, estaba segura de que para Rafael no existía ya la hija del doctor Moreno,
criatura abominable, cuya belleza había sido su pesadilla durante algunos meses.

Sabía por sus espías que una mañana de mercado se habían encontrado los dos en las calles de
Alcira. Rafael volvió la mirada como si buscase un sitio por donde huir; ella palideció y siguió
adelante fingiendo no verle. ¿Qué significaba esto?... La ruptura para siempre. Ella, la buena
pieza, palidecía de rabia, tal vez porque no podía atrapar de nuevo a su Rafael, porque éste,
cansado de inmundicia, la abandonaba para siempre. ¡Ah, la perdida! ¡la ramera!

¿Pues qué no había más que educar un hijo en las más sanas y virtuosas creencias y hacer de
él un personaje, para que después llegase una correntona peor mil veces que las que por dinero
hacen porquerías en un callejón para llevársele con sus manos sucias? ¿Qué había creído la
hija del descamisado?... ¡Rabia! ¡Palidece de pena, al ver que se te va para siempre!

En la alegría de su triunfo, comenzaba a pensar en la boda de su hijo con Remedios, y levantando
una punta de su reserva de gran señora, trataba a don Matías como de la familia, ensalzando
el afecto cada vez más vivo que unía a los chicos.

--Pues si se quieren--decía el burdo ricachón,--por mí que sea la boda cuanto antes. Remedios
hace mucho papel a mi lado: una mujercita como hay pocas para el gobierno de la casa; pero
esto que no sea obstáculo para el casorio. Muy satisfecho, doña Bernarda, de que seamos parientes.
Sólo siento que don Ramón no pueda ver estas cosas.

Y era verdad que lo único que empañaba la alegría del rústico millonario, era que no viviese
el alto e imponente señor para darse el gusto de tratarle como un igual, coronando así el éxito
de su asombrosa fortuna.

Doña Bernarda también veía en aquella unión la cúspide de sus ensueños; el dinero unido al
poder; los millones de un comercio cuyos éxitos maravillosos parecían golpes de juego, viniendo
a vivificar con savia de oro el árbol de los Brulls, algo resquebrajado y viejo por largos
años de lucha.

Comenzaba la primavera. Algunas tardes doña Bernarda llevaba los chicos a sus huertos o a las
ricas fincas del padre de Remedios. Había que ver con qué aire de bondad vigilaba a la joven
pareja, gritando alarmada si en sus correrías permanecían algunos minutos ocultos tras los
naranjos.

--¡Este Rafael!--decía a su consejero con aquella confianza que le había hecho relatar más
de una vez las tristezas de la intimidad con su esposo.--¡Qué pillo es! ¡De seguro que la estará
besando!

--Déjelos usted, doña Bernarda. Cuanto más se meta en harina, menos peligro de que vuelva a
la otra.

¿Volver?... No había cuidado. Bastaba contemplar a Rafael cómo cogía las flores y las colocaba
riendo en la cabeza o el pecho de Remedios, que se resistía débilmente, con un rubor de colegiala,
conmovida por tales homenajes.

--Quieto, Rafaelito--murmuraba con una voz que parecía un balido suplicante.--No me toques;
no seas atrevido.

Y su emoción la traicionaba de tal modo, que parecía estar pidiendo que el joven volviese a
poner en su cuerpo aquellas manos que la trastornaba desde los pies a la raíz de los cabellos.
Se replegaba por educación, huía de él porque este es el deber de una joven cristiana y bien
educada; escapaba como una cabrita con graciosos saltos por entre las filas de naranjos, y
el señor diputado salía detrás a todo galope con las narices palpitantes y los ojos ardorosos.

--¡Que te coge, Remedios!--gritaba la mamá, riendo.--¡Corre; que te coge!

Don Andrés contraía su cara arrugada con una sonrisa de viejo fauno. Aquellos juegos le rejuvenecían.

--¡Hum, señora! Sí que va la cosa a todo vapor. Está que arde. Cáselos usted pronto; mire que
si no, podemos dar mucho que reír a Alcira.

Y todos se engañaban. Ni la madre ni el amigo veían la expresión de desaliento y tristeza de
Rafael cuando quedaba solo, encerrado en un cuarto en cuyos obscuros rincones seguía viendo
aquellos ojos verdes y misteriosos de que había hablado a Leonora.

¿Volver a ella? Nunca. Duraba en él la vergüenza y el anonadamiento por lo de aquella mañana.
Se veía en toda su trágica ridiculez, apelotonado en el suelo, oprimido por el pie de la viril
amazona, manchado de tierra, humilde y confuso como un delincuente que no acierta a disculparse.
Y después la palabra terrible como un latigazo: «¡Vete!»; como a un lacayo que osa atreverse
a su señora, y la verja, cerrándose a sus espaldas con estrépito cayendo como una losa de tumba
entre él y la artista.

No volvería: le faltaba valor para arrostrar su mirada. La mañana en que la encontró casualmente
cerca del mercado, creyó morir de vergüenza; le temblaron las piernas, vio que la calle se
obscurecía como si repentinamente llegase la noche. Había desaparecido ella, y todavía le zumbaban
los oídos y buscaba apoyarse en algo, como si el suelo se balanceara bajo sus pies.

Necesitaba olvidar su vergonzosa torpeza aquel recuerdo tenaz como un remordimiento, y, se
aturdía cerca de la protegida de su madre. Era una mujer, y sus manos, que parecían desatadas
desde aquella mañana dolorosa, iban a ella; su lengua libre, después de la vehemente confesión
de amor a la puerta del huerto, hablaba ahora con ligereza, expresando una adoración que parecía
resbalar sin huella alguna por la cara inexpresiva de Remedios, yendo lejos, muy lejos, donde
permanecía oculta y ofendida la otra.

Se aturdía cerca de Remedios para caer en una estúpida tristeza apenas se veía sólo. Era una
embriaguez de espuma que se evaporaba en la soledad. Remedios le parecía uno de esos frutos
sin sazonar, sanos, con la película de la virginidad, limpios de picaduras y manchas, pero
sin el sabor que deleita ni el perfume que embriaga.

En su extraña situación, viviendo durante el día de jugueteos infantiles con una muchacha que
no despertaba en él más que el regocijo de la camaradería fraternal y durante la noche de tristes
recuerdos, lo único que le placía era la confianza de su madre, la tranquilidad de la casa,
el poder ir y venir sin sentir fijos en él unos ojos irritados y escuchar palabras de indignación
ahogadas entre dientes.

Don Andrés y los amigos del casino le preguntaban cuándo sería la boda; su madre hablaba en
presencia de los chicos de las grandes trasformaciones que se tendrían que hacer en la casa.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08065</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>167431</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22013</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> If I had to save my reputation, aviada was with a friend like you. What things pose there!

And
smile with an expression of superiority, considering well above what
they could that the people of his friendship with Rafael.

- In the
market you tell me about all the vendors as if this was for me the
most irresistible of flattery; ensure that we are a proud partner.

My gardener takes all occasions to tell me you're very handsome. You give thanks ... What
else?

Even my aunt, my poor aunt who lives in limbo, has left it to me the other day: "You know Rafaelito here
so much? If you want to marry you? "You see, married ha! Ha! Ha! Married! The poor lady did
not see more than this in the world.

And he kept throwing in the face of Rafael, dark and evil thoughts, that hearty laughter and
mocking chatter seemed a mischievous bird satisfied with his freedom.

-
But what do you frown today!

Are you sick? ... What happens?

Rafael seized the moment. I was sick, yes, sick of love.

He understood that the entire city speak of them, he could not hide his feelings. If I knew what
it cost that silent worship! I wanted to start thinking of devotion to her, and could not. Needed
see, hear, and only lived for her. "Read? impossible. Talk to your friends? All repugnant to him.
Their home was a cave that went to great effort to eat and sleep. She left as soon as you wake up
and leave town, it looked like a prison. The field, and the field the blue house where she lived.
Which eagerly awaiting the arrival of the afternoon, the time by an unspoken custom, neither
scored, he could enter the garden and find it in your bank under the palms! ... I could not live
like this. Poor People powerful envied him, so young deputy, and he wanted to be ... You'll
never guess what? What absurd things! Leonora is not mocked! The terms would be that the bank
was for the garden, gently crushed by the weight of your entire afternoons, to become the work
revolving in his delicate fingers, by transforming themselves into one of the people around
her at all times, of that Beppa, for example, that the wake in the morning, leaning asleep
on his head, moving with her breath her hair undone, scattered as a wave of gold on the pillow
and wiped her ivory flesh out the bathroom, sliding your hands for incoming and outgoing curves
of her soft body. Servant, animal, inanimate object something that was in constant contact
with him, that he craved: not to be compelled to the arrival of the night away after a prolonged
farewell ending child pretexts, to return to the irritating banality of his life, the solitude of her
room, in which dark corners, as evil temptation, he thought he saw eyes fixed on green.

Leonora was not laughing. Abríanse inordinately gold flecked eyes, quivering with excitement the
alillas of his nose, and seemed sincerely moved by the eloquent young.

- Poor Rafael! Poor me! ... What do we do?

In the garden, Rafael had never dared to speak so frankly. Le proximity self-conscious of relatives
of Leonora, intimidated him and mocking the surface air with which she received visits, the
irony with which he aimed it a little disconcerting words of love. But there in the middle
of the road, was another thing was free, I wanted to empty his heart. What torment! Every day he went
to the blue house trembling hope, troubled by the illusion. "Perhaps is today, "they said. And
his legs trembled, and saliva in his throat seemed to solidify, drowning. And hours later in the
evening, desperate to return home, marching discouraged in light of the stars, zigzagging on the road
as if he were drunk, feeling beetles tears on the eyelids, wanting to die, as it needs to pass
breaks forward and fists against a huge wall of ice blocks. Did not noticed him? Do not see
the huge efforts made to please? ... Ignorant, humble, recognizing the vast difference that
separates them both for their different life, what's efforts to reach his height, for those placed
at the level of men who had owned for a few days or whole years! She must have noticed. If the
Count was speaking Russian model of elegance, Rafael next day, to the astonishment of his home,
took out his best clothes, and sweating under the sun, oppressed by the high collar, undertook that
journey it was her Street of Bitterness, walk like a lady so that dust does not dampen the shine
of their boots. If the musician German crossed the memory of Leonora, he revisited his books,
and affecting the outside neglect of those artists seen in the novels, arrived there with the purpose
of discussing the immortal master of Wagner, whom he hardly knew, but she adored as a person
family ... My God! All this was ridiculous, he knew him best was presented without disguise, with
all its smallness. Acknowledged that it was impossible that struggle to match with the thousand
ghosts that filled the memory of Leonora, but do not do it for wake that heart to be loved for a
moment, a day any more, and then die!

And there was such sincerity in this confession of love, Leonora,
increasingly agitated, approached to him, taped to his body walked
unwittingly and smiled slightly, repeating his phrase, mixture of
maternal affection and pity.

- Poor Rafael!

... Poor me!

They had reached the gate leading into the garden.

The avenue was deserted.

In the square, shut off the house, ran around the chickens.

Rafael, overwhelmed by the effort of that confession, which took account of anguish and dreams
of many months, he leaned against the trunk of an old orange. Leonora was facing listening to
him with bowed head, scratching the soil with the tip of his red umbrella.

Dying, yes, he had read this many times in novels could not suppress a smile. Now you do not
laugh. I had thought a few nights in the confusion of delirium, end that love tragically. The blood
of his father, violent and domineering, boiled in it. If she convinced that it would never be his,
was not to kill anyone, and kill him later! Drop the two on the ground soaked with blood, as
on a bed of red damask, kiss him in the cold lips, without fear that no one bothered him, kiss
her and kiss her until the last breath of life was lost in the pale
face of it.

She said with conviction, vibrating all the muscles of his face manly, burning like coals Moor
her eyes streaked for the passion of blood veins. And Leonora was looking at him now passion,
as if he saw a new man. Trembled with emotion on hearing the new barbarians dreams, death
threats.

That is not gloomily as the poet killed Italian looking lost love died killing, destroyed the
idol, if not attended to his pleas.

And sweetly moved by the tragic expression of Rafael, was carried
away by it, that had taken an arm and drew her away from the avenue
between the tops of the orange low.

Both remained silent for long. Leonora seemed intoxicated by the virile perfume of those threats of
wild passion.

Rafael, the head down and quietly watch the artist, thought he had offended his words and repented
of them.

Should forgive him, he was crazy. Exasperated at his strength is inexplicable. Lenore Lenore Why
strive to hinder the work of love? He was not indifferent to her, not inspired dislike or hate,
otherwise they would not be friends and would allow continued visits.

Love? ... I was sure that was not sorry for him, poor man, unable to inspire passion for a woman
like her.

But do not resist, and eventually love him, he achieved conquer by
force of love and of worship.

Ay! with only his love, was for the two and all the famous lovers in history. It would be his
slave, the carpet that would his feet, the dog always tended to her,
his eyes burning of eternal fidelity, would end up loving him, if
not for love, gratitude and pity.

And as he spoke, brought his face close to Leonora, seeking his image at the bottom of the
eyes green, pressed his arm with the fever of passion.

- Careful, Rafael ... do you hurt me, Let me go you.

And as if awakened in the middle of danger after a sweet dream, she shuddered, detachment with a nervous
impulse.

Then he began to speak calmly, and record of drunkenness that had troubled the passionate words
of Raphael.

No, what he wanted was impossible. The die was cast, I did not love
... Friendship I had taken something away.

She was to blame, but know about it. It was already a boat old who could not bear the weight
of a new passion. If I had known years before, maybe.

He acknowledged that he had come to love him, he thought more worthy of your love others men
she had loved. But it was late, now I just wanted to live. What horror! The emotions of passion
in a mean, in that small world of trivia and gossip! Hiding like criminals for wanting to! She, like
the love of the outdoors, with sublime immodesty of the statue shocked
the fools with their naked beauty!

Verse eaten away at all hours by the murmuring of fools, after giving his body and soul man!
Feel around the scorn and indignation of all the people that accuse having corrupt a youth, separated
from his path, away forever from the Yours!

No, Rafael, a thousand times no, she was conscious, was not the crazy
times.

- But what about me? - Sighed the young man clutching his
arm again with childhood anxiety - you thinks of itself and all, forgetting
me.

What can I do alone with my passion?

- You forget - he said gravely Leonora .-- Today I saw that it is impossible for me to stay here.
The two need to get away.

I flee before the end of the spring, I will not know where, again the world to sing, where there are
men like you, and the time and absence will be responsible of cure.

Leonora winced when he saw the blaze of wild passion that went through
the eyes of Rafael.

He felt her lips with the hot breath of those who sought his mouth, muttering to roar off:

- No, you will not go, I do not go away.

And he was linked, moved from head to foot by jittery arms that passion
gave new strength.

Her feet left the ground, he was raised, a brutal drive the he fell on his side at the foot
of an orange, while their clothes were moving about convulsive hands,
trembling, that wounded the beast flesh with caresses.

It was a brutal fight, which lasted a few moments ignoble. The Valkyrie reappeared in women up. Its
robust body vibrated with a supreme effort, she sat with her weight
smothering Raphael, Leonora and finally sat up, putting your foot
brutally, without mercy, on his chest Young, squeezing as if trying
to crack the bones of his chest.

His appearance was terrible. It seemed crazy, with dirty blond hair and ground broken. Its green
eyes glowed as sharp metal knives, and his mouth, discolored emotion,
contracting, releasing, by force of habit, the instinct of effort
his battle cry, a hojotoho! torn, savage, which shook the calm of
the garden, shaking to poultry, they ran scared from the trails.

Umbrella brandished in anger as if it were the lance of Wotan's daughters,
and several times pointed it at Rafael's eyes as if to remove them.

The girl seemed crushed by his effort, ashamed of his brutality, lifeless
on the ground, without protest, as if he wished never to rise again,
to die under that foot suffocated him angry.

Leonora calmed down, and slowly came back a few steps, while Rafael
was incorporated, picking up his hat.

It was a painful scene.

The two felt cold, did not see the light, as if the sun had gone out and the garden blowing
an icy wind.

Rafael looked embarrassed when soil was afraid of her, afraid to be seen in the clothes disheveled,
dirty ground, beaten and beaten as a thief who surprised a strong master.

Leonora's voice, speaking with contemptuous familiarity that is used
with the miserable.

- Go!

He looked up and saw the angry and arrogant Leonora, fixed on him.

- Me not take me - he said coldly, - give me if I want.

And in a gesture of contempt and rage with which dismissed Rafael, seemed to mark the memory
Boldini odious, disgusting old man, alone in the world that had taken by force.

Rafael wanted to apologize, ask forgiveness, but that memory of adolescence evoked brutal scene,
made her relentless.

- Go, go, or get slapped! ... Never come back here.

And to give more power to these words as Rafael, humiliated, dirty,
out of the garden, Leonora closed behind him the wooden fence so brutal
momentum, which nearly blew up the bars.

IV

Doña Bernarda Rafael showed himself pleased with her.

No more glaring, gestures severe, the mute scenes between mother
and son, who witnessed with awe the intimate of the house.

He did not go to the blue house, I knew with great certainty, thanks to free intelligence that
the affected people serving the family. Just left the house, a casino by the time the afternoon,
and the rest of the day in the dining room with her and friends,
or locked in his room, no doubt turn his books, which the austere
lady looked with superstitious awe of their ignorance.

Don Andres, the director, commenting triumphantly showed that change. What had him, provided that
Dona Bernarda, in the intimate secrets of their friendship that almost took the character of
a senile passion, quiet and respectful, complained of the rebellion
of youth?

That would happen: it was a quirk of age, had to give youth its own. Rafael no had studied to
Carthusian. Others of his age and even more years were worse! ... And the old Mr. thought
smiling at his easy conquest of the stores, between the unruly flock, miserable and dirty petticoats
papering orange. Good Dona Bernarda, after suffer so much from her husband was very demanding
with his son. Have fun! Enjoyed that!

Already tired of the artist to be so beautiful, and then it would be easy to get back on track.

Doña
Bernarda admired once again the talent of the director, seeing fulfilled
their predictions, made with a cynicism that the devout lady blushed.

She also believed it all over.

His son was less blind than the father.

Was tired the lost love of a woman like that, not wanting to quarrel with his mother for so
little, nor enemies discredit him and returned to duty with great joy of the good lady around
him to seek care.

- How about that? - Her friends asked her mysteriously.

- Nothing - responded with a proud smile .-- It has been three weeks and no hints of wanting back
there. My Rafael is good. What happened was just a distraction boy. If you only saw him in the
evenings to keep me company in the room! An angel, an angel. It spends hours talking to me and
the daughter of Matthias.

He added, exaggerating his smile and mischievous eyes:

- I think there's something.

Something, yes, or at least the appearance of any. Rafael, tired of wandering around the house
tired of books to which he spent hours turning leaves, unaware of
what they said, took refuge in the room where his mother sewed, watching
a complicated embroidery the daughter of Don Matias.

Rafael liked the simplicity of this gentle girl. Its simplicity produced in him a impression of freshness
and relaxation.

Cuevecitas saw it as a narrow and hidden in which slumbered calm after a storm. The satisfied
smile of his mother encouraged him to stay there. I had never been so kind and communicative. The
enjoyment of having him back safe and modified its austere submissive
to the roughness.

Remedios, head bent over her embroidery, heavily reddened whenever Rafael praised their work
or said it was the prettiest girl in Alcira.

The thread helped needles, with outstretched hands acted as the skein winder that curled the
girl and more than once pinched her under the frame, with the confidence to have met child,
which did not prevent her screams shocked.

- Rafael, do not be mad - said the mother kindly threatening their hands .-- Let dry Remedies
work, if you behave so badly will not let you enter the room.

And at night, alone in the room with Mr. Andrew, when it was time for confidences, Dona Bernarda
forgot the affairs of the house and the party to say with satisfaction:

-
That way.

- Do you love Rafaelito?

...

- Every day. The thing is in full swing.

That boy is this the image of his father. Believe me, they should not lose sight. If I were
not here, that little devil would be able to discredit the crazy
house.

And the good lady, she was sure that there was Rafael and daughter of Dr. Moreno, abominable
creature, whose beauty had been her nightmare for some months.

He knew from his spies that morning market were found both in the
streets of Alcira.

Rafael turned her gaze as if looking for a place through which to
escape, she went pale and pretending not to see him later.

What did that mean? ... The break forever. She, good piece, pale with rage, perhaps because he
could not catch her Rafael again, for he, Tired of filth, abandoned
forever.

Ah, the lost! The whore!

What then there was more to educate a child in the most wholesome
and virtuous beliefs and make him a character, so that later came
a correntona thousand times worse than those for money make junk in
an alley to take him away with his hands dirty?

What was believed the daughter of shirtless? ... Rage! Penalty pales, seeing that you will forever!

In
the joy of victory, began to think about the wedding of his son with Remedios, and lifting Reservation
tip of a great lady, Don Matías was like family, praising affection live increasingly linked to
the boys.

- Well if you want - said the rich man's crude - for me that the wedding
is soon.

Remedies makes a lot of paper in my hand: a young woman as there is little for housekeeping, but
This is no obstacle to the wedding. Very satisfied, Dona Bernarda, that we are relatives.
I just feel that Don Ramón can not see these things.

And it was true that the only thing that marred the joy of rustic millionaire, was that it
lived the high and mighty Lord for the pleasure of treating him like an equal, thus crowning
success its amazing fortune.

Doña Bernarda also saw in this union the height of his dreams: money joined power, the millions
of a business whose success seemed wonderful shots of the game, coming
to quicken with sap from the tree of gold Brülls, something cracked
and old for long years of struggle.

Beginning of spring. Dona Bernarda had some afternoons the boys to their gardens or rich estates
of the father of Remedios.

Had to do with what kindness air watching the young couples, screaming alarmed if in his travels
a few minutes remained hidden behind the orange.

- This Raphael - told his counselor that he had confidence that relate more once the sadness of intimacy
with her husband's .-- What a rascal!

Surely that will kissing!
- Let you, Dona Bernarda. The more you get into flour, less risk
of recurrence the other.

Go back? ... There was no care. Rafael enough
to contemplate how picked flowers and placed them laughing in the
head or chest of Remedios, who resisted weakly, with a blushing schoolgirl
moved by such tributes.

- Quiet, Rafaelito - whispered with a voice
like a bleat supplicant .-- Do not touch me; do not be bold.

And
his emotion betrayed in such a way that seemed to be asking the girls
to return to put in your body that upset those hands from the feet
to the root of the hair. Retreated by education, he was fleeing because
this is the duty of a Christian girl and well educated, escaped as
a goat with graceful leaps between the rows of orange trees, and Mr
deputy left behind at a gallop with quivering nostrils and eyes burning.

-
That you take, Remedios! - Mom cried, laughing .-- Run, which takes
you!

Don Andrés contorted his face wrinkled with a smile of old faun.
Those games will rejuvenated.

- Um, ma'am! Yes, things are going
full steam. Is hot. Cassettes you soon, take heed if not, we can give
a lot to laugh Alcira.

And they were all deceived. Neither mother
nor his friend saw the expression of dismay and sadness Rafael when
left alone, locked in a room whose dark corners still saw and mysterious
green eyes that he had spoken to Leonora.

Go back to it? Never. It
lasted shame and self-abasement as of this morning. Was seen in all
its tragic absurdity, matted on the ground, pressed by the foot of
the virile Amazon, stained earth, humble and confused as an offender
fails to apologize. And then the terrible word like a whip: "Go!",
As a lackey who dares venture his lady, and the gate closed behind
him noisily dropping like a stone tomb between him and the artist.

Not
again: he lacked the courage to face his eyes. The morning I found
it by chance near the market, thought he would die of shame legs trembled,
he saw that the street suddenly darkened as if nightfall. She was
gone, and he still buzzing ears and wanted to lean on something, as
if the ground beneath your feet dangle.

I needed to forget their
embarrassing blunder that memory tenacious as remorse, and is near
the protected stunned his mother. She was a woman, and her hands,
which seemed unbound since that painful morning, went to her, her
tongue was, after vehement confession love for the garden gate, now
spoke lightly, expressing an adoration that seemed without a trace
slide down his face expressionless Remedios, going far, far away,
where remained hidden and injured another. 

Remedios was stunned
about to fall into a sad stupid just barely visible. Was a drunkenness
foam evaporated in the desert. Remedios seemed one of those fruits
unseasoned, healthy, with the flick of virginity, free of pitting
and staining, but without the flavor and perfume delight that intoxicates.

In
his strange situation, living for the day of frolicking with a girl
child aroused in him no more than the joy of fraternal camaraderie
and during the night of sad memories, all he pleased was the confidence
of his mother, the quiet of the house, power come and go without feeling
eyes fixed on him angry and to hear words of indignation choked breath.

Don
Andrés and friends of the casino was asked when would the wedding,
her mother spoke presence of the children of the great transformations
that have to do at home</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>