<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04637</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>57863</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>15762</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Véase pues, que ventajas tan grandes resultaban á la provincia,
y aun á todo el reyno el reconocimiento y seguridad de estos pasos.

Las inmensas indiadas que por ellos bajan á proveerse de caballos y ganados, es una langosta,
ó plaga de su destruccion: que á no ser unos campos tan dilatados y fértiles, no dejarian casta.
El no acabar de apurarles, dan una segura idea de su abundancia y propagacion; cesando esta
causa será un aumento ventajosísimo para el comercio de la corambre, que, como fruto de la
tierra, merece la primera atencion por ser permanente y no precario. Las poblaciones de los
campos de Buenos Aires irian tomando otro incremento y extension, particularmente si se reuniesen
á ellas los vecinos, que en despoblados dispersos habitan en chácras, como está mandado por
repetidas reales cédulas: pues este disimulo es perjudicialísimo al bien espiritual de aquellas
almas, y legislacion real, porque carecen de instruccion cristiana en nuestros sagrados dogmas;
rara vez frecuentan los santos sacramentos de la penitencia, y eucaristía, y casi no tienen,
ó reconocen á quien obedecer y temer: de modo que poco se diferencian de los indios salvages.

Este método de gobierno es la destruccion de si mismos, porque la mucha extension, que media
de una chácra á otra, dá márgen á los indios para robar los ganados, cautivar y matar á sus
habitadores, á cuyas desgracias coadyuvan en mayor parte los que frecuentemente se pasan á
estos infieles, comunicándoles las noticias y caminos seguros á sus invasiones, de tal modo
que ninguna malogran.

Enterado yo en el Rio Negro por los mismos indios, y viages que hicieron los dos expresados
peones Godoy y Gonzales, de esta maldad en los nuestros, han sido repetidas las instancias
que he hecho al Señor Virey, para que se les castigue con egemplar rigor al que se aprenda
haber incurrido en tan horroroso delito, y juntamente dí cuenta á S. E. de uno de estos impios
que los dirigia: el que llegó á tal extremo su crueldad, que no estuvieron exentos de ella
sus propios padres, á quien él mismo mató en una de las entradas que hizo con los indios.

Reducidos á poblaciones los vecinos de estas chacras, tendrán diferente instruccion y gobierno,
y por medio de padrones donde se anoten, habrá conocimiento de los sugetos que falten en el
pueblo, y podrá saberse con otra facilidad su paradero.

No puedo omitir, por el mucho conocimiento adquirido en los cinco años que he estado tratando
estos salvages en el Rio Negro, cuan útil nos es el método que observan los franceses en sus
Indias con semejantes bárbaros, y con cuanta razon nos lo recomienda el Señor Ward en su proyecto
económico. Sin tener yo las mas leves noticias de estas reglas, las he seguido; y notoria es
la buena armonia que he conservado con ellos, y lo útil que han sido al fomento del establecimiento:
y no puede decirse que son de mejor índole aquellos que los de estos campos, porque allí han
concurrido los que aquí nos dañan. Todos me han conservado una verdadera amistad y buena fé,
á excepcion de algun robo de caballos, de que aun entre nosotros mismos no estamos libres.

Esta experiencia demuestra la importancia de poner en las guardias, ó pueblos que se establezcan,
sugetos de afabilidad, talento y juicio para tratar con los indios y que á cambio de abalorios
y otros efectos que no nos perjudiquen, se introduzca con ellos comercio de sus propios frutos;
como son pieles de liebre, zorrillo, guanaco, y guaracha, riendas, plumeros, ponchos y otros
efectos de que abundan: por estos medios con utilidad propia vamos conciliando y adquiriendo
su amistad como lo hacen y logran los franceses.

Tengo demostrado el método y esperanzas de las muchas utilidades que podemos sacar del establecimiento
del Rio Negro, lo vasto é importante de ellas manifiesta la creacion ó formacion de un nuevo
reyno. Todas acrescentan el comercio, aumentan, ó forman un cuerpo de marina mercantil, que
es el mayor nérvio de la felicidad de una monarquía, y por consiguiente atraen el aumento de
las poblaciones. Todo ello no puede emprenderse en la presente época, es menester poco á poco
ir adelantando, y dándose la mano uno con otro, á proporcion de sus prosperidades y ventajas.
Un prudente, sábio y celoso Gobierno, inflamado con el espirítu de patriotismo, sin intermision
de otros entusiasmos, bajo de una proteccion real, cual logramos en el dia, dedicada toda al
aumento y felicidad de los vastos dominios que rige, serán las principales basas y columnas
donde se apoyen, y sostengan el feliz éxito de estas demostradas utilidades.

                         PARTE TERCERA.

Los cortos principios del establecimiento del Rio Negro, y sus obstinadas oposiciones, causa
de tantos desperdicios y gastos,[C] le tienen tan en el aire, que al menor huracan, todo él
dá en tierra. Para su conservacion y aumento, se necesita mucho tino y pulso, porque la real
hacienda no se halla en estado de gastos, y la multitud de informes y papeles remitidos á la
Corte, han entibiado aquel primer fervor con que se promovió, borrando en el real ánimo sus
fundamentos y causas, y si ahora no se procura sostener, todo es perdido.

Estas reflexiones me hicieron, ó por mejor decir, obligaron á dar el informe de 16 de Febrero
de este año, que por órden de 14 del mismo me pidió el Señor Virey D. Juan José de Vertiz,
para arreglar el establecimiento en la forma que manda Su Magestad por la real órden de 1.º
de Agosto. La ciega obediencia y estado deplorable de estos asuntos no me dieron otro arbitrio,
que manifestar el modo y forma de su reduccion, dejando campo para que tan corta raiz fomentase,
y produjese las grandes esperanzas que anteriormente tengo expresadas; pues de haber manifestado
yo, que en aquel estado no podia subsistir, preparaba el huracan á su entera ruina.

Allí reformo el establecimiento al solo número de 12 familias; propongo los medios de su conservacion
y subsistencia, y abro campo con el fomento de la pesca de la ballena, y abasto de la sal para
que se sostenga y prospere sin gasto de la real hacienda; y estos medios son los únicos que
le han de sostener y fomentar, y los que deben merecer toda la atencion del presente Gobierno.

Aunque el primero es de mas importancia que el segundo, este es mas pronto y fácil, porque
el gasto de la Provincia no cesa; y impetrando órden de Su Magestad, para que no se permita
en España embarque y conduccion de este género á los puertos del Rio de la Plata, y se prohiba
el que las carretas salgan para las Salinas como hasta aquí se ha practicado, se queda este
provecho á beneficio de aquella poblacion, y sus vecinos, ocupados en las tareas de sus acopios
y en el despacho de sus frutos, logran la provechosa utilidad de esta industria y comercio;
que con la pesca de la ballena establecida en el puerto de San José será mas importante.

Si el estado en que se hallan los indios, y expediciones nuestras en su alcance, obligaren
á reforzar aquel puerto con mas tropa, es otro fomento y utilidad de los vecinos: pues el dinero
de su prest lo mas queda á su beneficio; procurando ellos hacer fructíferos aquellos terrenos
con la industria y trabajo de sus labores, tomando distinto método que el que han llevado,
pues ya por su natural desidia y haraganeria, y ya por las seducciones con que los desanimaban
y entibiaban para que se aplicasen á la agricultura, asegurándoles que pronto los habian de
sacar de aquel destino, y mudarlos á los amenísimos campos de Montevideo, que abundan de tanto
ganado, que sin molestarse en poco tiempo lograrian enriquecerse, eran los que por todos medios
procuraban hacer inútil la poblacion. Y estas influencias les alentaban para dedicar sus clamores
al Sr. Vertiz, ponderando la esterilidad de los terrenos, los peligros á que estaban expuestos
los indios, y el rigor del Super-intendente: porque su fervor, eficacia y fatiga no los dejaba
dormir en el ocio de su haraganeria, y les obligaba á trabajar en la agricultura, por cuyos
medios con las producciones de sus frutos ha verificado sus informes.

La conclusion de las obras del fuerte es otro medio que ha de coadyuvar en beneficio de los
pobladores, porque el dinero que causen estos gastos, redunda como el prest de la tropa en
su provecho, todo ello coadyuba á un mismo fin; pero es menester pobladores activos é industriosos;
y este es uno de los puntos mas esenciales que debe tener presente el Superior Gobierno, porque
ó poco ó nada servirá se les proporcione trabajo y salida á sus frutos, si dan con hombres
que no los aprovechan, antes sí los desprecian.

El gasto que debe reformarse es el que causan á la real hacienda los bergantines destinados
á los establecimientos de cuenta del Rey, porque este es el de mayor consideracion, y solo
es útil á sus respectivos patrones ó capitanes. Por medio del comercio de sal y pesquería de
la ballena se proporciona modo de abastecer el establecimiento de cuanto caresca y necesite,
y facilitar el transporte de los destacamentos de operarios y tropa que se mude: para lo primero
coadyuva su propio interes, porque estos géneros los venden en el establecimiento, y con sus
utilidades sacan el costo del transporte de sal, y á cuenta de ellos pagarán los jornales de
saca y conduccion al muelle á los vecinos. Para lo segundo podrá estipularse por regalia de
estas licencias; y cuando no, menos costo le ha de tener al Rey pagar el flete cuando se le
ofresca, que mantener unas embarcaciones, que le han de importar el todo de cada una al año
seis mil pesos, y el flete por mucho que suba no ha de llegar á quinientos.

Si tiene efecto el refuerzo de tropa en el Rio Negro, talvez se proporcionará ocasion que contenga
á los indios, y libres de recelos los pobladores, puedan extenderse en el egercicio de la argricultura,
y cria de ganado; pues uno y otro han de ser los mas sólidos cimientos en que estribe, y se
asegure la poblacion, atrayendo mayor número de vecinos, que por sí mismos formen cuerpos para
resistirles, y escarmentarles en todo tiempo. Los terrenos, en la proporcion que ofrece el
rio, valiendose del arte, á poca costa se pueden beneficiar con el riego, como tengo demostrado
al Señor Virey en oficio de 26 de Marzo del año próximo anterior, número 26; y aun sin los
medios que allí propongo, si los vecinos son aplicados, con norias que meuvan caballos pueden
adelantar mucho; mayormente cuando allí no tienen costo, y es muy poco lo que cuesta este ganado.

Todo lo cual parece haber persuadido que los conatos y desvelos de nuestros católicos monarcas
en proyectar y promover estos establecimientos, han sido efectos de un profundo conocimiento
y estudio sobre la religion y la política; que estas dos bases de todo Gobierno ilustrado y
cristiano, fueron el fundamento de las expediciones de Sarmiento. Las de los dos hermanos Nodales,
la del capitan Olivares, con los Padres Cardiel, Quiroga y Strobl; la del capital de fragata
D. Francisco Pando; la de D. Domingo Perlier, y ultimamente las que han salido de Montevideo
y Buenos Aires, para las comisiones que se nos han confiado á los dos hermanos; que á pesar
de todos los émulos que las quieren contradecir, siempre serán útiles estos establecimientos,
por el fomento del comercio que proporcionan en la pesca de la ballena, en la conduccion de
sal á Buenas Aires, y salida de las carnes de los ganados que crian sus inmensas campañas;
por facilitar puerto para hacer mas suave la navegacion y comercio á la mar del sur, por cerrar
y defender la puerta á nuestros enemigos, asegurando lo interior del reyno; por los progresos
de la extension de sus poblaciones, porque ellas serán la mejor trinchera que contendrá á los
indios salvajes, que á manera de un torrente impetuoso cada dia inundan estos campos, llevándose
tras sí innumerable ganado caballar y vacuno, asolando las tristes habitaciones de los vecinos
fronterizos á esta capital, haciendo que los caminos no sean seguros, y víctima de su furor
á muchos desgraciados, que perecen inhumanamente cada dia á sus manos, de un modo horrible
y espantoso. Y finalmente podrá conseguirse la mayor de las utilidades, que consiste en hacer
hombres, y hombres cristianos á este gran número de salvajes. Utilidades que pueden conciliarse
sin el dispendio del real erario, y que son las que me propuse describir en las tres partes
de esta memoria, en la cual si hubiese alguna expresion menos digna, debe ser atribuida al
ardiente celo con que miro estos establecimientos, pues mi ánimo jamas ha sido zaherir con
mis expresiones á persona alguna. Todas ellas las sugeto á la superior correccion de V. E.;
lisonjeándome, que atendiendo al buen fin con que estan dictadas, ha de disimular cualquier
defecto que se encuentre. Sí, Señor Exmo., ¿como podré yo dudar que en el ánimo V. E., tengan
benigna acogida unos pensamientos dirigidos á la prosperidad del Estado, y al aumento de la
religion? V. E., que pesa todas las cosas en la balanza del saber, alcanza mejor que yo, qué
materia se le propone para emplear toda la actividad de su celo hácia el real servicio. Ella
puede hacer una gloriosa época en los tiempos felices del mando de V. E., quien como siempre
hará lo mejor.--Buenos Aires, 1.º de Mayo de 1784.

                    FRANCISCO DE VIEDMA.

       *       *       *       *       *

        INDICE DE LAS OBRAS CONTENIDAS EN EL TOMO PRIMERO.

                               I.

Historia Argentina del descubrimiento, poblacion y conquista de las provincias del Rio de la
Plata, por Rui Diaz de Guzman.

Discurso preliminar del editor de dicha obra.

Epocas de algunos acontecimientos importantes, segun las apunta el autor de la Historia Argentina.

Tabla de los grados de latitud de algunas ciudades y parages, segun se hallan determinados
en el curso de dicha historia.

                              II.

Viage de D. Luis de la Cruz desde el fuerte del Ballenar hasta la ciudad de Buenos Aires.

Discurso preliminar del editor de dicha viage.

Tasacion de lo que puede importar un camino desde el fuerte de Antuco hasta Buenos Aires.

Tablas de distancias, relativas á dicho viage.

                             III.

Descripcion de la naturaleza de los terrenos; y costumbres de los Peguenches, por D. Luis de
la Cruz.

                              IV.

Descripcion de Patagonia, por el Padre Tomas Falkner.

Discurso preliminar del editor de dicha obra.

                               V.

Derroteros y viages á la Ciudad Encantada, ó de los Césares.

Discurso preliminar del editor sobre los siguientes documentos.

----Derrotero por el Tandil y el Volcan, por Rojas.

----Carta del Padre Cardiel sobre el descubrimiento de los Césares.

----Carta del Padre Lozano sobre los Césares.

----Derrotero desde Buenos Aires hasta los Césares, por Falkner.

----Relacion de las noticias adquiridas sobre los Césares, por Pinuer.

----Carta al Virey del Perú sobre los Césares, por Jauregui.

----Nuevo descubrimiento preparado por el Gobernador de Valdivia.

----Declaracion sobre la ciudad de los Césares, por Villagra.

----Informe y dictámen del Fiscal de Chile, sobre los Césares.

                              VI.

Diario de un viage á la Costa Magallánica, desde Buenos Aires hasta el Estrecho, formado sobre
las observaciones de los PP. Cardiel y Quiroga, por el Padre Pedro Lozano.

Advertencia del editor.

                             VII.

Representacion sobre la translacion de las fronteras de Buenos Aires al Rio Negro y Colorado,
por Undiano y Gastelu.

Itinerario de un camino desde Buenos Aires á la ciudad de Talca, por Cerro y Zamudio.

Advertencia del editor.

                            VIII.

Memoria sobre los obstàculos que han encontrado, y las ventajas que prometen los establecimientos
de la costa Patagónica, por Viedma.

Discurso preliminar del editor.

</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10629</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>42176</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14531</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> See then that were so big advantages to the province, and even to
the entire kingdom and safety recognition of these steps.

The huge Indian they fall to provide themselves with horses and cattle, is a lobster, pest or its
destruction, that had it not been a very long and very fertile fields, I would not breed. The
end does not hurry, give an idea of ??his wealth safe and propagation; ceasing this cause
will be most advantageous for increased trade corambre that, as a result of earth, deserves
attention for being the first permanent and non-poor. The populations of Buenos Aires fields would
go take another increase and extension, particularly if they were met them to neighbors, who
live on farms scattered uninhabited, as is mandated by repeated royal decrees: for this concealment
is perjudicialísimo the spiritual good of those souls, and real legislation, for lack of instruction
in our holy Christian dogmas; rarely frequent the sacraments of Penance and Eucharist, and have
almost no, recognize or obey and whom to fear: so that differ little
from the savage Indians.

This method of government is the destruction of themselves, because the lot extension, which
mediates one farm to another, leaves room for the Indians to steal cattle, engage and kill
their inhabitants, whose misfortunes contribute to a greater part
of which often go to these infidels, communicating news and safe routes
to their invasions, so any spoil.

I heard on the Black River by the Indians, and that made voyages both expressed Godoy and Gonzales
pawns in this evil in our time have been repeated instances I made the Viceroy Lord to punish
them with rigor egemplar is learned have committed such horrific crime, and realized together
to know one of these ungodly who led them: that was so extreme cruelty,
which were not exempt from it their own parents, whom he killed in
one of the entries made with the Indians.

Populations reduced to the neighbors of these farms will have different
instructions and government and through standards which are scored,
there sugetos knowledge of the missing at people, and may be known
for another facility of his whereabouts.

I can not ignore, for a lot of knowledge acquired in the five years I've been trying these savages
in the Black River, how useful is the method we observe the French in their Indies with such
barbarians, and with what reason we are recommended by Lord Ward in its draft economic. Without me the
news milder these rules, I followed, and is notorious good harmony that I have kept with them,
and how useful it has been the promotion of the establishment: and can not be said to be the
best to are those that these fields, because there have busy on here
hurt us.

All I have maintained a true friendship and good faith except for some stolen horses, that even among
ourselves we are not free.

This experience demonstrates the importance of putting in the wards, or people who are established
sugetos of kindness, talent and opinion to deal with the Indians and that in exchange for beads
and other effects that do not harm us, they enter with them their
own fruit trade; such as rabbit fur, skunk, guanaco, and guaracha,
reins, dusters, ponchos and other effect that abound in these means
we reconcile its own merits and acquiring their friendship as they
do and achieve the French.

I have shown the method and hopes of the many utilities that can make the establishment Black
River, the vast and important of them shows the creation or formation of a new kingdom. All
acrescentan trade, increase, or form a Marine Corps commercial, which is the largest nerve in
the happiness of a monarchy, and thus attract increasing populations. This can not be undertaken
in the present time, little by little it is necessary go ahead, and shaking hands with each other,
in proportion to their prosperity and benefits. A cautious, wise and zealous government, inflamed
with the spirit of patriotism, without intermission other enthusiasms, under a real protection,
which we in the day, taking all the growth and happiness of the vast
domains governing will be the main bases and columns which support
and sustain the successful outcome of these prove useful.

                         

PART THREE.

The short early establishment of the Black River, and his stubborn opposition, because of so
much waste and costs, [C] you have so much in the air, that the minor storm, everything he
gives ground.

For their preservation and increase, it takes much skill and pulse, because real estate is not
in state spending and the multitude of reports and papers submitted to the Court, have warmed
to that first fervor that was promoted by deleting in its real spirit foundations and causes,
and if not now seeks to hold, all is lost.

These reflections made me, or rather, forced to give the report of February 16 This year, by order
of 14 of the Viceroy Lord asked me D. Juan Jose de Vertiz, to fix
the setting in the manner commanded by His Majesty, the royal order
of 1. º August.

The blind obedience and the deplorable state of these issues gave me no other measure, to express the
manner and form of their reduction, leaving room for so short that promoted root, and produjese
the high expectations I have expressed previously, as having said I do that in that state could
not survive, was preparing his whole hurricane debris.

They reformed to establish the single number of 12 families propose the means of its conservation
and subsistence, and open field with the promotion of whaling, and supply of salt for to hold
and flourish without spending real estate, and these are the only means have to sustain and
encourage, and should deserve all the attention of this Government.

While the former is of more importance than the second, this is soon
and easily, because spending in the province does not cease, and beseeching
order of His Majesty, to not allow in Spain loading and driving of
this kind to the ports of Rio de la Plata, and is prohibited where
the carts go to Salinas as has hitherto been practiced, it is this
advantage to the benefit of that population, and its neighbors engaged
in the work of its stocks and the release of its fruits, achieve profitable
use of the industry and trade; with the whaling established in the
port of San Jose will be more important.

If the state who are Indians and our expeditions in scope, forces that to strengthen that port
with more troops, is another building and utility of the neighbors because the money your
loan is as much to his benefit, they were seeking to make successful those lands Working with
industry and its work, taking different approach than they have been, and because its natural
indolence and laziness, and now by the seductions with which discouraged and warm so that they
apply to agriculture, assuring them that soon they were to out of that fate, and move them to the
fields amenísimos Montevideo, which abound in both livestock, without bothering to get rich quickly
we could bring, were those who by all means sought to make useless the population. And these influences
are encouraged to devote their cries Mr. Vertiz, considering the barrenness of the land, the dangers
to which they were exposed Indians, and the rigor of the Super-intendant, because his zeal,
efficiency and fatigue would not let sleep on their laziness leisure,
and forced them to work in agriculture, which media productions have
checked off their reports.

The conclusion of the works of the fort is another medium that has to contribute for the benefit of
residents, because the money that cause these expenses, such as that provided leads the troops
in their benefit, all coadyuba to the same end, but we need active and industrious people;
and this is one of the most essential points to keep in mind the
superior government, because or little or nothing will work and give
them out to their fruits, if given to men not the advantage, before
they despise themselves.

The expenditure should be reformed is the cause to the exchequer for the launches establishments
to King's account, because this is the highest consideration, and only is useful to their employers
or masters. Through trade with salt and fishery Whale provides supply mode setting as caresca and
needs, and facilitate the transport of detachments of workers and troops to move out: for the
former contributes its own interest, because these genres are sold on the premises, and their
utilities take the cost of transportation of salt, and to realize they will pay the wages of
and driving out to the dock to the neighbors. For the second may be stipulated by regalia of
these licenses, and when not, unless you have cost him the King to pay the freight when Offer,
to keep a boat, you have to import the whole of each year six thousand
dollars, and much freight will not be pushed up to five hundred.

If you have a strengthening effect on the Rio Black troops, perhaps opportunity will be provided
containing the Indians, and free from fears the people, can be extended in the argricultura egercicio,
and raising cattle, they either have to be the most solid foundation on which rests, and secure
the population, attracting more neighbors, which themselves form bodies for resist, and chastened
at all times. The land, in the proportion provided by the river, using art, at little cost
can benefit from irrigation, as I have shown Viceroy Lord in office March 26 next year earlier,
number 26, and even without means that there suggest, if neighbors
are applied, with wells that horses can meuvan advance much, mostly
when there is no charge, and very little about the cost these animals.

All of which seems to have persuaded the near misses and worries of our Catholic monarchs to
project and promote these establishments have been effects of a deep knowledge and study on religion
and politics that these two bases of any government illustrated Christian, were the foundation
of the expeditions of Sarmiento. The two brothers of Nodal, the captain of Olivares, the Padres
Cardiel, Quiroga and Strobl, the capital of frigate D. Francisco Pando, that of D. Perlier
Sunday, and lately they have left Montevideo and Buenos Aires, to the commissions have been entrusted
to the two brothers, who, notwithstanding of all the rivals that want to contradict these establishments
always be useful, by the trade promotion provided in whaling, in the conduct of salt to Buenas
Aires, and output of meat of cattle that he raises large campaigns; to facilitate smoother port
for navigation and commerce to the South Sea, to close and defend the door to our enemies, ensuring
the interior of the kingdom, for progress the extension of their populations, because they are
the best trench to contain the wild Indians, who after the manner of a raging torrent flooded the
fields every day, taking behind him innumerable cattle, horses and cattle, sad ravage the neighboring
rooms border to the capital, making the roads unsafe, and victim of his wrath to many unfortunate
people, who die inhumanely each day to his hands, horribly and frightening. And finally be
achieved most of the profits, which consists of men and Christian men to this great number of
savages. Utilities that can be reconciled without the extravagance of the royal treasury and are
as I set out to describe the three parts of this report, in which if there was any less worthy
expression should be attributed to zeal with which I look at these establishments, it has
never been my intention to censure my words to anyone. Sugeto all the above correction to
the VE; flattered that taking the proper purpose for which they are issued, has to conceal
any defects found. Yes, Lord Exmo., How can I doubt that in the spirit VE, have benign host
some thoughts directed to the prosperity of the state and the increased religion? VE, weighing
all things in the balance of knowledge, achieves better than me, what matter is proposed to
employ all the activity of their zeal towards the royal service. She can make a glorious time
in the happy days of the VE command, who as always will do its best .-- Buenos Aires, 1. First
of May, 1784.

                    Francisco de Viedma.

       

        

                               * * * * *

CONTENTS OF WORK CONTAINED IN THE FIRST VOLUME.

I.

Argentina History of discovery and conquest population of the provinces of the River Silver,
Rui Diaz de Guzman.

                              

Preliminary Discourse editor of that work.

Times of some major events, according to the points the author of
the Historia Argentina.

                             

Table of degrees of latitude in some cities and Parag, as are certain in the course of that history.

II.

D.
journey Luis de la Cruz from the fort of whales to the city of Buenos
Aires.

                              

Editor's introductory speech of the journey.

                               

Appraisal of what can import a path from the strong Antuco to Buenos
Aires.

Distance tables relating to the voyage.

III.

Description of the nature of the land, and customs of the Peguenches,
by D. Louis Cross.

IV.

                              

Description of Patagonia, by Father Thomas Falkner.

Preliminary Discourse editor of that work.

                             

V.

Paths and journeys to the Enchanted City, or of the Caesars.

                            

Editor's introductory speech on the following documents.

---- Derrotero by Tandil and the Volcano, by Rojas.

---- Letter
from Father Cardiel on the discovery of the Caesars.

---- Letter
from Father Lozano on the Caesars.

---- Derrotero from Buenos Aires
to the Caesars, by Falkner. 

Related news ---- acquired on the Caesars,
by Pinuer.

---- Letter to the Viceroy of Peru on the Caesars, for
Jauregui.

---- New Discovery prepared by the Governor of Valdivia.

----
Statement on the city of the Caesars, by Villagra.

---- Report and
opinion of the Attorney Chile, on the Caesars.

VI.

Diary of a journey
to the Costa Magellan from Buenos Aires to the Strait, formed on observations
of the PP. Cardiel and Quiroga, by Father Pedro Lozano.

Editor's
Note.

VII.

Translational representation on the borders of Buenos
Aires to Rio Black and Colorado by Undiano and Gastelu.

Itinerary
of a journey from Buenos Aires to the city of Talca, by Hill and Zamudio.

Editor's
Note.

VIII.

Report on the obstacles encountered, and the benefits
they promise establishments Patagonian coast, from Viedma.

Editor's
introductory speech</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>