<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07650</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>6317</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19636</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Si contraemos estos principios á nuestro estado y poblacion, para observar la marcha de estas
máximas, nos asombrará nuestra perezosa inaccion y nuestro abandono punible; mucho mas remarcable
de un siglo á esta parte, por no haber echado una simple ojeada sobre la conducta de las naciones
cultas en este mismo hemisferio. Es verdad que en todos los estados, en todos los pueblos y
edades, ha habido declamadores contra tales vicios, pero por degracia han sido los menos, y
los mas abandonados, y talvez perseguidos; y mucho mas si las medidas de una sana moral y máximas
filantrópicas, estaban en razon inversa de los intereses de unos, de la ambicion de gloria
en otros, y de la grosera y estupida ignorancia, especialmente de aquellos que creen estar
negado á nuestra era todo lo que no alcanzaron sus mayores.

Es igualmente cierto, que las grandes empresas de ordinario han sido atacadas por la ambicion
de inexpertos, y la envidia de codiciosos, destruyendo á los emprendedores por medios capciosos,
y esparciendo opiniones erroneas, sin apoyo que las sostengan. Pero, sin embargo de abundar
estos agentes comunes, que enervan, paralizan y retardan semejantes obras, es ciertamente de
notar, como en el espacio de casi un siglo de controversias, no ha podido desenrollarse la
de nuestro adelantamiento de fronteras, instado viva y tenazmente por el Exmo. Cabildo, Gefes
y corporaciones todas de esta capital, en que ninguna ha dejado de tomar parte.

Nada prueba mas nuestro menguado interes en el adelanto de la patria, nada nuestra escasez
é ignorancia vergonzosa, y nada en fin nuestra indolencia hácia nuestro verdadero interes y
subsistencia, que la apatia que acaba de referirse. Cualquiera que, interesado en el bien general,
quiera imponerse de la verdad con que se nos pueden apropiar todos aquellos degradantes atributos,
se convencerá con solo desenvolver las actas capitulares, representaciones, informes, cèdulas
expedidas con franqueza del erario, reconocimientos científicos, manifiestos, detalles, fondos
aprestados y cuanto se crea necesario: hallará en fin un cúmulo de documentos, que dando principio
en el año de 1741 del siglo anterior, continúan el 45, 52, 53, 60, 68, 72, 74, 77, 84, 94,
96, 804, 810, y sin interrupcion. Hoy nos hallamos sin duda con menos proporcion que nunca
para su ejecucion, pero al parecer en mas disposicion de ánimo, segun las benéficas miras del
Gobierno. Sin embargo, hasta ahora nuestros comerciantes han tenido la calidad de arraigados,
y no podian desentenderse de que tanto crecen sus raices cuanto progresa la provincia en sus
establecimientos, y no podian mirar con indiferencia su existencia, especialmente desde el
año de 1777, en que se amplió á esta parte de América el comercio, y se cortaron las embarazosas
ataduras que le tenian ligado á expediciones eventuales de la Península, y en que ya se desplegaron
mas proporciones para la regeneracion de poblaciones, agricultura è industria.

Parece en verdad, que un génio maligno, y destructor de nuestra comun felicidad, precede siempre
á obstruir los caminos que con tanto ahinco se procura allanar, á fin de no ser precarios de
las demas provincias continentales y reinos extraños en toda clase de frutos, y demas riquezas
que tenemos en nuestro suelo, y finalmente á privarnos de las que, por medio de las poblaciones
que deben hacerse, nos son peculiares; porque la naturaleza así lo dispuso, agraciando al punto
de nuestra posicion con privilegio á todas las demas del globo conocido.

Es tanto mas notable la apatia en el adelantamiento de fronteras, en cuanto no ocupamos hoy
mas terrenos que aquellos que poseyeron y concertaron con los indios, el Adelantado Vera y
D. Juan de Garay con 60 soldados y 30 familias, al tiempo que restableció esta ciudad de Buenos
Aires en el año de 1580, á saber: 35 leguas N S, y en parte menos, que se enumeran del rio
Paraná al Salado, y 120 E O, hasta entrar en la jurisdiccion de Córdoba.

En razon directa de la progresion de aquellos pobladores, manifestó bien presto el tiempo la
necesidad de sus ensanches; pero desgraciadamente han sido desatendidos los clamores de hacendados
y labradores, que estrechados de la necesidad, se han visto precisados á establecerse entre
las mismas tribus de indios, á la parte austral del Salado, para vivir á merced de ellos, muy
á su riesgo, y donde á cada momento se ven atacados y robados.

Nuestra subsistencia y abasto de carnes, servicio de bueyes, caballos y mulas, y en fin nuestras
labranzas y sementeras, son ramos que en su mayor parte están pendientes de la arbitrariedad
de aquellos enemigos, y nuestra defensa á sus devastadoras y continuas incursiones, se hace
tan urgente como necesaria, y pone á aquellos enemigos en un respeto imponente.

Cualquiera que por experiencia en el servicio, ó porque con ojo observador en las ocurrencias
de este suelo, haya visto ó tenido noticia, aunque superficial, de las escenas lastimosas que
han teñido en sangre estas campañas de víctimas indefensas, sacrificadas por la ferocidad de
este enemigo, asi en el tiempo llamado de paz como en el de guerra abierta, execrará la indolencia
con que nuestros mayores han dejado correr los siglos, sin aplicar remedios oportunos á tan
graves males, contentándose con indicarlos solamente, cuando las sangrientas incursiones se
repetian; sin que estas indicaciones causasen otros efectos que los cáusticos aplicados al
enfermo, que removiendo algun tanto al moribundo aletargado, al fin muere sacrificado del mal
y de los cáusticos mismos, por su ineficacia.

El Supremo Gobierno desea hoy poner término á estas desgracias, para no dejar á las futuras
generaciones una tan triste memoria, como la que ahora hacemos de los que le han precedido.
Busca cuidadoso los medios que puedan hacer efectivas tan interesantes obras; incita á los
ciudadanos á que puedan prestar ideas proporcionadas segun sus conocimientos; y á la verdad,
que estos, á quienes no menos que al Señor Gobernador interesa la felicidad de la provincia,
no pueden sin injusticia negarse á la cooperacion de tan benéficas miras. Y por esta razon
creo hallarme en el caso de apuntar mis cortos conocimientos, que una contraccion asidua á
este punto de mas de seis años, encargado por el mismo Señor Gobernador, ha podido ministrarme.

No recordaré las escenas antes referidas, ni épocas de tan crueles invasiones en que vimos
enterrar los cadáveres á centenares, por no afligir con su memoria á las viudas y huérfanos,
que aun lloran sus miserias por aquellas desgraciadas ocurrencias; y porque creo mejor echar
un velo sobre todas, y convencernos por ellas solo de la necesidad en que estamos de reparar
las que de nuevo nos amenazan, y de acudir á ponerles un respeto amistoso á los indios, y fin
seguro á su animosidad, graduando las operaciones, segun surtieren los medios que para ello
se tomen, en falta de una fuerza imponente y disponible con que se pudiesen fijar nuestras
líneas de un modo inaccesible al enemigo.

Dos extremos (á mi juicio inconciliables), he visto adoptar generalmente al logro de esta empresa.
El primero, el de la fuerza imponente, que destruya y aniquile hasta su exterminio á estos
indios, que no es fácil en mucho tiempo: y el segundo, el de una amistad conciliadora de la
oposicion de animos, por el trato recíproco que les suavice, con el interes de algunos de nuestros
artículos de comercio que anhelan demasiado.

El primer medio convengo en que los escarmienta, y contiene por algun tiempo, hasta que se
rehacen para acometer con mas acaloramiento, asechando las ocasiones mas ventajosas de hacerlo.
Su carácter feroz y vengativo, hace que jamas perdonen el agravio, y para no olvidarlo, en
todas sus concurrencias y parlamentos se refieren aquellos acontecimientos con llantos y renovados
duelos, y pasan á sus hijos y descendientes el mas serio encargo de sus venganzas, que duran
tanto como las familias de agresores agraviados.

El segundo, que es de la amistad, los habilita para que á su retirada á los toldos roben impunemente,
como lo hacen con cuanto pueden abarcar sus fuerzas, y sin estrepito nos arrasan diariamente
los campos, reduciendo á nuestros ganados y chacras del Salado á una miseria espantosa: sin
que por esto dejen de reunirse en diferentes épocas del año varias tribus, para hacer cuantiosos
robos, ojeando antes los rodeos que han de asaltar, asociados, ó talvez conducidos de nuestros
transfugas gauchos desertores. De este modo no solo han arruinado nuestras estancias, sino
que tienen miras de hacer desaparecer de entre nosotros toda especie de ganados, sin que para
comprobar estos hechos sea necesaria otra observacion, que las que presentan las recolecciones
de diezmos, ya sea por un quinquenio, ó cotejando el último año por el anterior.

Es cosa bien dolorosa ver á muchos de nuestros hacendados desvelarse tres y cuatro años, impendiendo
ingentes caudales para establecer un rodeo de 10, 15 ó 20 mil cabezas de ganado, y que cuando
en la noche de su descanso meditaban recompensar sus fatigas, disponiendo la venta de su hacienda,
amanecieron sin una sola res, por habérsela robado los indios. D. Pedro Perez, D. Mariano Veliera,
D. Agustin Garcia y otros, con casi todos los fronterizos en la línea, pueden testificar de
la verdad de estos hechos.

No será exceso asegurar, que en lo que ocupa la línea de frontera exceden los robos anuales
de 40,000 cabezas de ganado vacuno, y acaso igual ó mayor número de caballos, yeguas y mulas,
sin que basten á contenerlos las reconvenciones del Gobierno, y sus reiteradas ofertas de buena
amistad; porque siendo sus campos tan dilatados, como sus poblaciones en pequeñas tribus, eluden
fácilmente el cargo, asegurando los del S que son los del O, y estos que aquellos. Y á la verdad
que guardan una perfecta alternativa en los robos, haciendo de ellos un comercio activo estacional,
vendiéndolos y permutándolos en sus importes á los indios Araucanos limítrofes por los Andes,
cuya codicia arrasadora apresura nuestra ruina, si no se repara activamente.

Aquellos nuestros compatriotas, familiarizados con ellos por huir del castigo de sus delitos,
sirven de guia unas veces, y otras de verdaderos conductores; á los cuales no solo protejen
los indios, sino que á viva fuerza defienden sus personas, si algunas veces perseguidos se
acojen á sus toldos, como repetidamente se ha visto y yo lo he experimentado.

Seis años de no interrumpido trato con estos infieles, habiendo antes cuidadosamente viajado
por sus mas interiores terrenos, hasta el centro de su mayor número de tolderias, y aun con
este motivo podido atraer á partido y consiguiente amistad a los caciques principales, me han
señalado sus localidades, y hecho conocer con menos equivocacion lo falaces que son en sus
ofertas, el doble y capcioso trato con que se presentan, suponiendo siempre representaciones
que no tienen, y ofertas que jamas pueden ni tienen miras de cumplir.

Es pues necesario tener presente, que cada familia forma un patriarcado, y se mira independiente
de los demas; y por eso con sus casas volantes ó toldos, sus ganados è hijos se transponen
de uno á otro punto de este continente, ó al occidente de la Cordillera, si por sus excesos
temen ser atacados por nosotros ó por sus mismos convecinos.

El cacicazgo por lo general, entre esta clase de indios, no es de sangre, como firmemente lo
observan sus ascendientes los Araucanos: es por eleccion, y solo para los casos de guerra y
parlamentos, y fuera de esto no le guardan respeto ni miramiento alguno, y en sus riñas salen
tan descalabrados los gefes como los demas, si no tienen la suerte de defenderse con destreza,
que en tales casos y resultas es cuando se acreditan para ser elevados á caciques. Pero reconocen
sin embargo con respetuosa sumision á los que llaman ulmenes, ò caciques gobernadores, de cuya
clase hay solo dos en el grande espacio de tierras que se halla desde la costa occidental del
Rio Negro, faldas orientales de la Cordillera de los Andes, fronteras de Cuyo y Córdoba, hasta
la nuestra del Salado. Uno de ellos manda en la parte del O, fronteras de Cuyo, Córdoba y montes
de su comprension, desde las sierras hasta el Rio Negro, y sobre las costas del mar hasta nuestros
establecimientos. He tratado á los dos, el primero en el centro de los terrenos de su gobierno,
y el segundo por medio de este, y emisarios que se le remitieron para que ocurriese á un parlamento.

Cuando estos ulmenes aparecen en las grandes concurrencias de sus indios y caciques subalternos,
van precedidos de varios indios músicos que les tocan unas flautas muy lúgubres, cornetas,
y arcos de cuerdas que hieren con otras, á manera de las que usan los negros, y á su retaguardia
los esclavos que tienen hechos de todas clases en sus guerras. Todos á proporcion salen á festejar
á su ulmen, y he visto quitarse las mantas y jergas, quedando desnudos, para regalarselas al
Gobernador que no se escusa de recibirlas: y este, que regularmente es dotado de buen pulmon,
les hace frecuentes arengas dirigidas siempre á infundirles espíritu contra sus enemigos, teniéndolos
siempre en menos. Comparecen luego los caciques subalternos á su presencia, confieren cuanto
de la última vez que se han visto y reunido ha pasado á sus familias, recomiendan la venganza
de sus desgracias, y si en la reunion hay 30 ó 40, el que tiene la palabra ha de saludar despues
del ulmen á todos, refiriéndoles lo mismo; por manera que se repite una misma cosa tantas veces
cuantos son los concurrentes, y lo mismo las respuestas; y de este modo, en falta de escritura,
transmiten á la posteridad por expresion ó noticias las desgracias á los demas, para que siempre
vivan en la memoria de las generaciones futuras los acontecimientos, á la manera que refiere
el Inca Garcilaso de la Vega, lo hacian sus mayores.

Enterado muy por menor el Exmo. Señor Gobernador de las precedentes ocurrencias, y convencido
de la nulidad de las ofertas de caciques subalternos, mientras los ulmenes no asistiesen á
sus propuestas, procuré atraer á estos por medio de emisarios que se le remitieron por mi conducto,
y solo pudo conseguirse la comparecencia de aquel del O, que yo habia tratado en el centro
de su gobierno, el cual se presentó con otros caciques sus subalternos ante el Superior Gobierno,
quien desde luego en la conferencia que presencié, no distó de asentir á la solicitud del establecimiento
de nuevas poblaciones con bastante llaneza. S. E. dirigió luego la palabra á los demas caciques,
y estos respondieron, que á presencia de lo dispuesto por su gefe, nada les restaba mas que
obedecer. Pero el cacique gobernador añadió, que consideraba oportuno formar un parlamento,
á que concurriese el cacique gobernador del sur, asentar en él los capítulos de paz, amistad
y poblaciones que hubiesen de establecerse, de cuyo modo se alejarian desconfianzas recíprocas.
Para ello se me encargó por la Superioridad procurase medios de hacerles entender los deseos
que animaban á S. E. de entablar una amistad mas íntima con dicho cacique ulmen, y que á la
manera de su compañero se prestase á venir y recibir personalmente las mas seguras pruebas
de sinceridad de ella.

En efecto, procuré inmediatamente hacérselo entender por medio de los caciques Quinteleu y
Quidulef, sus amigos, y que tambien me habian acreditado ser lo mios: y la respuesta dada por
el ulmen, mandando á sus dos hermanos mayores, fué, que se prestaria con igual franqueza; que
su ancianidad, ademas de ciego, no le permitian montar á caballo, pero sin embargo se animaria
á hacerlo, y partir el camino conmigo, pues deseaba la amistad del que se la brindaba, haciendo
acuerdo de su persona, que hasta entonces tenia la queja de habérsele considerado en muy poco
precio.

La Superioridad, que oyó á los enviados hermanos del cacique, sin perder de vista estas ocurrencias,
acudió cuanto antes le fué posible, á procurar el remedio de los males que afligian la campaña,
procurando un término que conciliase con las escaceses del erario, el preciso auxilio al establecimiento
de los primeros puntos de seguridad; para lo cual adoptó el proyecto que le presenté de su
órden, en 15 de Febrero de 1814, que pudo ordenarse para realizar la marcha en Abril de 1815,
y dejó de tener efecto por las ocurrencias posteriores, que son notorias y hasta perjudiciales
al estado.

El primer paso de esta exposicion debia ser, formar el parlamento con los indios, ya indicado,
asentando los capítulos de amistad y recíproco trato mas solemnes, poniendo término á los robos
y devastaciones, tantas veces requeridos, y señalar puntos precisos de entrada y salida á los
indios con sus frutos y especies que quisiesen introducir en la capital, escoltándolos. Que
las poblaciones no se harian sino en los puntos que conviniesen á ambos contratantes, para
lo cual antes deberian reconocerse desde el Rio Colorado hasta nuestras fronteras, por temerse
en varios parages de la costa invasion, que á ellos era tanto, ó mas perjudicial que á nosotros
en tales circunstancias: sobre cuyos principios estaba la negociacion harto adelantada, reservadamente
con los caciques en cambio de su interes.

De manera que, la maña en la relacion y la franqueza en el trato facilitaria el reconocimiento,
observando de paso, distancias, latitudes y longitudes hasta aquel punto, y los que fuesen
proporcionados para las poblaciones, á fin de no aventurarlas, como generalmente sucede, por
no anticipar prolijamente exactos reconocimientos ó calidades poco aparentes: y tambien porque
en nuestras mas avanzadas poblaciones al sur conviene haya una de respeto, que cubra aquellos
apreciables campos, y debia desde luego establecerse un fuerte y poblacion al pié de la primera
sierra, que sirviendo ademas de apoyo como primer punto del camino militar, fuese almacen de
víveres al siguiente para la continuacion de esta obra: y entre tanto completar el número de
las cuatro compañias que habian de formar la fuerza detallada, ponerse en disciplina conveniente,
y provision de caballos de sus propiedades, con todo lo demas concerniente á imponer el respeto
necesario, y sucesivamente deprimir, si fuese necesario, su animosidad hasta fijarse en la
confluencia del Rio Colorado.

Formada esta línea militar y de defensa con las cuatro compañias veteranas de á 125 hombres,
fuerza suficiente á poner respeto á este enemigo, se conseguiria con seguridad (habiendo vigilancia)
situar otras tantas poblaciones, que á favor de la bondad de sus terrenos y de la exportacion
de sus frutos, que puede hacerse por diferentes puntos, bien presto alternarian con las subalternas
de primer órden, y las aventajarian por los ramos particulares á ellas mismas que les harian
progresar.

Esta línea sobre el costado izquierdo del cuadro irregular que forman los terrenos, está mirando
al O, y tiene muy á sus alcances á los indios de aquel departamento, si cometiesen irrupciones,
para cortarles su retirada, y vivirian muy cuidadosos si alguna vez se excediesen.

Fijada la poblacion sobre el Rio Colorado, nada es mas interesante que el reconocimiento de
este rio hasta sus nacientes, y examinar si su caudal cuantioso de aguas las recibe del Rio
Diamante ó del Neuquen, como generalmente se presume: y sea de uno de ellos ó de ambos, resulta
que la línea militar puede extenderse hasta el Fuerte de San Rafael de Mendoza, si es el primero;
y siendo el segundo, aunque queda en mas proporcion para internarse á Penco, puesto que los
viageros luego que se apartan del que llaman Moylin 70 leguas al SO de la Laguna de la Sal,
hacen una pequeña travesía al Neuquen, que costean hasta las cumbres de la Córdillera por caminos
cómodos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01468</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>354</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17481</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

If you incur these principles to our state and population, to observe the progress of these maximum,
we amaze our lazy inaction and neglect our offense, much more remarkable a century to this part,
for failing to cast a glance over the conduct of nations cultured in the same hemisphere. It is true
that in all states and all peoples ages, has been orators against such vices, but is unfortunately
have been less, and the most neglected, and perhaps persecuted, and more if the measures of
a healthy moral and maximum philanthropic, were in inverse ratio to the interests of some, the ambition
of glory in others, and the rude and stupid ignorance, especially those who believe they AD
refused to everything but his biggest hit.

It is equally true that large companies usually have been attacked by ambition of inexperienced,
greedy and envious, destroying them by means specious entrepreneurs, and spreading erroneous opinions,
unsupported to support them. But yet to be abundant these common agents, enervating, cripple
and retard such works, is certainly note, and space for almost a century of disputes, could
not unroll the advancement of our borders, living and tenaciously urged by the Excellent.
Cabildo, chiefs and corporations all of this capital, where none have stopped taking part.

Nothing proves more our dwindling interest in the advancement of the country, all our shortage
shame and ignorance, and nothing in the end our indolence towards our true interest and subsistence,
apathy just referred. Anyone, interested in the general good want to impose the truth with which we
can appropriate degrading those attributes, be convinced to develop the chapter records only, representations,
reports, certificates the Treasury issued frankly, scientific surveys, statements, details, backgrounds
dressings and as deemed necessary, in order to find a wealth of documents, giving first in the
year 1741 of the previous century, continued for 45, 52, 53, 60, 68, 72, 74, 77, 84, 94, 96, 804,
810, and without interruption. Today we are no doubt less proportion than ever for execution,
but apparently in most moods, according to the charitable view of Government. However, until
now our merchants have had the quality of rooted and could not ignore their roots grow both as
progress in the province establishments, and could not look with indifference their existence,
especially since the year 1777, which was extended to this part of American commerce, and cut
the embarrassing ties that had bound shipments to any of the Peninsula, and already deployed
more proportionate to the regeneration of towns, agriculture and industry.

It seems indeed that an evil genius, and destroyer of our common happiness,
always precedes to block the roads so much to pave seeks, in order
not to be precarious the other mainland provinces and kingdoms in
all kinds of strange fruits, and other wealth we have in our soil,
and finally to deprive us of that through people to be made, we are
unique, because nature so ordained, gracing the point our position
with privilege to all other known balloon.

Is the more remarkable apathy on the advancement of frontiers, as they do not deal today more land
than those who possessed it, and concluded with the Indians, and Vera Head D. Juan de Garay with
60 soldiers and 30 families, while the city of Buenos restored Aires in 1580, to wit: 35 miles
NS, partly at least, listed the river Paraná Salado, and EO 120,
to enter the jurisdiction of Córdoba.

In direct ratio to the progression of those people said it's time soon need for new extensions,
but unfortunately have been neglected the cries of farmers and farmers, who narrowed the need,
have been compelled to be established between the same tribes of
Indians, to the southern part of Salt, to live at the mercy of them,
very his risk, and where every moment they are attacked and robbed.

Our livelihoods and meat supply, service of oxen, horses and mules, and finally our crops and
plantations, are branches that are mostly arbitrary pending of those enemies, and our defense
to its devastating and ongoing missions, is so urgent and necessary,
and puts those enemies in a massive respect.

Anyone that service experience, or because watchful eye on the occurrences This ground has seen
or have heard, however superficial, of the pathetic scenes that have
blood stained the campaigns of helpless victims, killed by the ferocity
of this enemy, so in time of peace known as the open war, defy the
indolence that our ancestors have left to run forever without applying
appropriate remedy to so serious evils, simply indicates only where
the bloody raids repeated, but such signs were causing other effects
applied to caustics Sick, removing both the dying any sleepy, finally
killed the evil dies and caustic or by his ineffectiveness.

The Supreme Government would now put an end to these tragedies, not to leave to future generations
a sad memory, as we now do to those who have preceded him. Search careful way they can make effective
as interesting works, encourages to citizens who can provide ideas provided according to their
knowledge, and truth, these, whom the Lord no less than interested in the happiness Governor
of the province can not without injustice refuse to so beneficial cooperation of view. And
for this reason I find myself in the case of my short target knowledge, that a contraction assiduous
this point in more than six years, who by the Lord Governor, has
been minister.

Do not remember the aforementioned scenes, nor cruel times we saw invasions bury the bodies
by hundreds, if not his memory afflict widows and orphans who still mourn their misery by these
unfortunate occurrences, and because I better take a veil over all and convinced them just where
we need to repair which threaten us again, and go to put them respect the Indians friendly,
and so insurance to their animosity, grading operations, according surtieren means that this
taken, in the absence of an imposing force and that could be available
to fix our lines in a way inaccessible to the enemy.

Two extremes (in my opinion irreconcilable), I have seen usually take the achievement of this
company. The first, the awesome force, to destroy and annihilate their extermination to these
Indians, it is not easy in a long time and the second, a mediator of friendship opposition of
minds, for reciprocal treatment that will soften, with the interest of some of our trade items
they crave too.

The first half agree that the lesson, and has for some time, until remake to tackle with more excitement,
stalking the most advantageous times to do so. His fierce and vindictive nature, causes never
forgive the insult, and not to forget, in Occurrence and parliaments all relate those events
with tears and renewed duels, and go to his children and descendants of the more serious charge of
their vengeance, which last both as aggressors aggrieved families.

The second, which is friendship, which enables them to retreat to his awnings steal with impunity,
as they do all they can cover their forces, and noiseless sweep us daily fields, reducing our cattle
and fields of salted peanuts appalling: no that it no longer met at different times of the year
several tribes to make substantial theft, eyeing before rodeos to
be assaulted, partners, or perhaps driven by our gauchos defectors
deserters.

This not only ruined our stay, but with a view to get rid of us all sorts of cattle, without having check
these facts need another observation, that those with collections tithes, either by a five-year
period, or comparing the last year by the former.

It is very painful thing to see many of our farmers disclosed three to four years, expend massive
flows to establish a herd of 10, 15 or 20 thousand head of cattle, and when on the night of
his meditated reward their labors rest, arranging the sale of livestock, woke up without a single
cow, habérsela stolen by Indians. D. Pedro Perez, D. Mariano Veliera, D. Agustin Garcia and others,
with almost all border on the line, can testify the truth of these facts.

Do not be too sure, that which makes it the boundary line exceeding annual thefts than 40,000
cattle, and perhaps equal or greater number of horses, mares and mules, without sufficient to contain
the Government's counterclaims, and its repeated offers good friendship, for being so lengthy fields,
as their populations in small tribes, evade easily by ensuring that those of S are those of
O, and these to those.

And indeed that have a perfect alternative to the robberies, making them an active trade seasonal
selling and interchangeable in their amounts to the Araucanian Indians bordering the Andes, whose
greed overwhelming rush our ruin, if not actively repaired.

Our compatriots who are familiar with them to escape punishment for their crimes sometimes serve
as a guide, and other real drivers, to whom not only protect Indians, but to defend their people by
force, if sometimes persecuted benefiting from their tents, as has been repeatedly and I have
experienced.

Six years of uninterrupted treatment with these infidels, having first gone carefully by their
more inland areas to the center of its greater number of ranch, and even with this reason
able to attract to the party and therefore friendly to the principal
chiefs, I have identified their locations, and less mistake made known
as they are in their false tenders, the cunning double deal with that
present themselves, always assuming representations who have not,
and offers that can never meet or have a view.

It is therefore necessary to bear in mind that every family is a patriarchy, and independent look
of others, and thus to fly home or awnings, their cattle and children are transposed from
one to another point on this continent, or westward of the range, if its excesses fear of being
attacked by us or by their own neighbors.

The chieftainship usually between this kind of Indian blood is not as strongly as Araucanians
observe their ancestors: it is by choice, and only for cases of war and parliaments, and out
of this does not hold any regard or respect for, and their quarrels
out so broken pate the chiefs as the others, if they have no chance
to defend himself with skill, that in such cases and result is when
is credited to be elevated to chiefs.

But they recognize however, with respectful submission to the callers ulmenes, governors or
chiefs, of which class there are only two in the large space of land which is from the west
coast of Black River, eastern slopes of the Cordillera de los Andes, Cordoba and Cuyo borders
until Salado ours. One of these commands in the part of O, boundaries of Cuyo, Cordoba and mountains
their understanding from the mountains to the Black River, and on the shores of the sea to our establishments.
I've tried them both, the first in the center of the land of his government, and the second by
this, and sent emissaries to him to happen to a parliament.

When these ulmenes displayed in large gatherings of Indian chiefs and subordinates preceded by several
Indian musicians who play a very mournful flutes, horns, and arcs of strings wound with others to
fashion using blacks, and his rear have made slaves of all sorts in their wars. All come in proportion
to celebrate his ulmen, and seen off the blankets and jargon, leaving
bare, for gifts to Governor excuse not to receive them: and this,
that is regularly provided with good lungs, makes frequent speeches
are always directed to instill spirit against his enemies, holding
them always less.

Then the chiefs appear subordinate to his presence, give as the last time you have seen and met
happened to their families, recommended revenge their misfortunes, and if the reunion is 30
to 40, who has been greeting word after ulmen of them all, referring to them as well, for so the
same thing is repeated many times how many of the attendees, and the replies, and thus, in the absence
of writing, transmitted to posterity by expression news or misfortune to others, to always live
in the memory of future generations of events, referring to the way the Inca Garcilaso de la
Vega, they did their elders.

Having far less than the Excellent. Governor of the previous occurrences, and convinced invalidity
of subordinate chiefs offerings, while being present at ulmenes their proposals, try to attract
these through emissaries who were sent to him through me, and could only be achieved by the appearance
of that of O, that I had tried in the center of his government, which was filed with other chiefs
his subordinates to the Superior Government who of course at the conference I attended, there was
far from assenting to the request for the establishment of new populations with enough sincerity.
Then addressed the word to the other chiefs, and they responded,
that at presence of the provisions of their leader, nothing remained
but that obey.

But the chief governor added that it considered it appropriate to form a parliament, to arise,
the chief governor of the south, settled in the chapters of peace, friendship and populations
that had been decided, which would go away as mutual distrust. For this I was asked by the Superior
procure the means to make them understand the wishes that encouraged them to engage SE more
intimate friendship with the chief ulmen, and to the mate way lends itself to come and personally
receive the safest evidence her sincerity.

Indeed, immediately tried to make him understand by the chiefs and Quinteleu Quidulef, friends,
and I also had proven to be as mine, and the response of the ulmen, sending his two older brothers,
was, to be provided with equal frankness that the elderly, and blind, was not allowed to mount
his horse, but nevertheless encourage to do so, and the road from me, because he wanted the friendship
of which she provided, making According to him, which until then had considered the complaint
of having been in a very short price.

Superiority, who heard the brothers sent the chief, without losing
sight of these occurrences, I came as soon as possible, seek to remedy
the ills afflicting the campaign seeking a term Shortages reconciled
with the treasury, the necessary assistance to the establishment of
the first points of safety, for which approved the draft I submitted
to the order, on February 15, 1814, which could be ordered to make
progress in April 1815 and ceased to have effect on subsequent occurrences,
which are well known and even harmful the state.

The first step of this exhibition was to be, to form the Indian parliament, as indicated, Chapters
settling mutual friendship and more solemn treatment, putting an end to thefts and devastation,
as often required, and identify specific points of entry and exit to the Indians with their fruits
and spices they wanted to introduce into the capital, escorted. That would make people not only
in points that suit both contracting for which should first be recognized
from the Rio Colorado to our borders, fearing Parages several invasion
coast, which to them was much, or more harmful to us in such circumstances:
on the principles of which the negotiation was fed forward, in confidence
with the chiefs in exchange for their interest.

So, the skill in the relationship and openness in the deal would facilitate the recognition, observing the
way, distances, latitudes and longitudes to that point, and those who were provided to populations,
in order not to adventure, as usually happens, for neatly anticipate no accurate survey or less
apparent qualities, and also because more advanced in our villages south should have one spare,
to cover any significant fields, and certainly ought to establish
a strong and population at the bottom of the first sierra, besides
serving as a first point of support military road, was warehouse the
following provisions for the continuation of this work, and meanwhile
the complement of the four companies that were to be detailed force,
put in appropriate discipline, and provision of horses from their
properties, with everything else relative to impose respect necessary,
and on depressed, if necessary, their animosity to look at the confluence
of the Rio Colorado.

Formed this military and defensive line with four companies to 125 male veterans, strong enough
to bring respect to the enemy, be achieved safely (having surveillance) put as many people
who favor the goodness of their land and export its fruits, which may be at different points,
or subordinate to quickly alternate first order, and special classes for aventajaría to themselves
that they would do progress.

This line on the left side of the box forming irregular land, is looking
W, and is very much at its scope to the Indians of that department,
if they make inroads, to cut off their retreat, and live very careful
if you are exceeded.

Population fixed on the Rio Colorado, nothing is more interesting than the recognition of this
river to its source, and considering whether the large flow of the receiving waters of Rio Diamond
or of Neuquen, as generally assumed, and either one of them or both, is military line that can
be extended to the Fort of San Rafael in Mendoza, where the first; and being the second, but is
in proportion to intern more Penco, since traveler after turning away from calling Moylin 70
leagues southwest of the Laguna de la Sal, make a small trip to Neuquen, that coast to the peaks
of the Cordillera paths comfortable.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>