<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04822</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>336970</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23147</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Cuando solemos encontrarnos con seres mezquinos, con almas
degradadas, para las cuales el respeto propio es vana palabra, que si llega a los oídos no
conmueve el corazón, ni tiñe de rojo las mejillas, decimos: «¡Alma de esclavo!» Y sin quererlo
pensamos en una vida de miseria que envileció el carácter y encanalló el espíritu. Dígase lo
que se quiera, esa nobleza es la única felicidad de los ricos. Por ella, sólo por ella, los
admira el mundo. Todo lo demás que en ellos envidia la multitud es como la corona de oropel
que ciñe la frente del comediante. ¡Noble dignidad, dignidad envidiable que pone a salvo las
prendas más altas del corazón!

Observad a todos aquéllos que vivieron una niñez miserable; en cuyo hogar faltó muchas veces
el pan; que no tuvieron ropas para cubrir el demacrado cuerpo; que imploraron avergonzados
la caridad pública, y no como el mendigo, con serena franqueza, sino ocultando la demanda en
una frase lisonjera; que pasaron, poco a poco, de la timidez bochornosa a la súplica sonriente;
de la petición insinuante a la explotación vergonzosa, y de allí... a la tolerancia interesada,
y veréis cómo, aunque estén en la opulencia, aunque la sociedad los mime y la fortuna los haya
indemnizado de cuanto en un tiempo les negó, aun tienen en lo más escondido del corazón el
vinagre y la hiel de la miseria. La pobreza desesperanzada imprime carácter, y en su seno se
crían la soberbia hipócrita, la modestia burlona, la astucia dolosa, que tienen flexibilidades
de víbora; la ruindad intrigante, la maledicencia ponzoñosa, y la envidia exangüe que todo
lo codicia y que todo lo afea.

En pos de esa noble dignidad corren todas las almas levantadas, alto el pensamiento, alto el
corazón: el estudiante que se afana por conquistarse digno puesto en la sociedad; el mercader
que gasta en el trabajo los años mejores de la vida; el menestral que lucha por conseguir vida
independiente. El deseo de alcanzarla es la única disculpa que tiene la avaricia.

Mi padre quiso darme esa codiciada felicidad; no pudo lograr sus propósitos; pero de él heredé
ese instinto de soberbia altivez con la cual rechacé en todo tiempo, de niño, de mozo, y de
hombre maduro, la humillación indigna, la reprensión inmotivada, el atropello brutal de quien
se consideraba superior a mí. De mi madre heredé plácida dulzura para la debilidad, sumisión
respetuosa para todo acto de justicia, tendencia irresistible para compadecerme del ajeno dolor,
y cierta delicadeza femenil que me ha causado muchas amarguras.

Entregado a estas meditaciones pasé una hora. Vino el sueño, y vino dulce y halagador, como
un amigo cariñoso que acude a nuestro llamado para darnos consuelo, para reanimar el abatido
corazón; como una hermana compasiva que se acerca a nuestro lecho, acaricia nuestra frente,
entorna nuestros ojos, y nos invita a reposar porque sabe que padecemos y necesitamos descanso.

XXXIX

Al día siguiente, después del desayuno, dije a mis tías lo que pasaba.

--¡Y te vas!--exclamó mi tía Pepa.--¿Te vas y nos dejas?

--Es preciso. Comprendo que esto ha de ser muy penoso para ustedes.... Lo comprendo, ya he
pensado en ello, pero ¿qué hacer?

--¡Ahora que estamos solas, cuando Angelina acaba de irse... cuando después de tantos años
de ausencia has vuelto a nuestro lado!

--Sí, tía, me iré; y no por gusto. ¡Bien sabe Dios cuánto me duele esta separación!... Pero
no se aflija usted. Es necesario.... Estoy obligado a....

--¡A vivir con tus tías!--exclamó interrumpiéndome.

--Estoy obligado a subvenir a las necesidades de ustedes.

--¿Y no te basta con lo que ganas en la casa de Castro Pérez? ¿Te pedimos algo que no puedas
darnos?

--No, tía; pero no puedo mirar tranquilamente la vida de trabajo que lleva usted. Andrés hace
por nosotros cuanto puede, y el pobre puede poco. No me avergüenzo de aceptar sus favores;
pero eso no debe seguir así, indefinidamente.... Ya sabe usted que en la casa de Castro Pérez
gano poco, y que no es posible ganar más.

--Pues yo creo que allí está tu porvenir....

No pude menos de sonreir al escuchar a mi pobre tía.

--¿Mi porvenir?

--Sí.

--No, tía; yo no me pasaré la vida escribiendo alegatos. Ese trabajo me mata. No porque sea
rudo, sino porque es insuficiente. Prefiero las faenas agrícolas y la vida agitada de los campos
que dan salud y buen humor.

La enferma permanecía silenciosa. Tía Pepa trató de convencerme de que no debía yo dejarlas.
Discutimos largamente el punto; ella, viva, nerviosa, desatando todas las dificultades; yo,
aparentando una serenidad que no tenía. Ni la anciana quería rendirse ni yo conseguía convencerla.

--¡Vamos,--exclamé--que resuelva mi madrina!

--Sí, hijo mío:--contestó la anciana--¡eso me toca a mí! Pepa te quiere mucho y se le hace
duro que nos dejes. Piensa tú, Pepa, que no estará muy lejos de nosotras; piensa que vendrá
frecuentemente, y considera que aquí, con Castro Pérez, no hará nada. Te irás, Rodolfo, te
irás, y nos quedaremos muy contentas. No hablemos más. Vístete, que como te veo te juzgo, vístete
y vete a la casa de Fernández. No saldrás descontento, es una persona muy fina. ¿No es verdad,
Pepa?

--Así lo haré, tía.

--Después, te vas a la casa de Castro Pérez, y le avisas que dentro de veinte días, o los que
sean, según lo convenido, tendrás que separarte de allí, y ¡ya está!

Y agregó un poco trémula y conmovida:

--Mira: siento que nos dejes; pero la razón me dicta que te deje ir; que no te impidamos lo
que vas a hacer. Yo el mejor día me iré también, y no quiero que a la hora de morir me atormente
la idea de que por culpa nuestra has perdido un bienestar que nosotras no podemos darte....

La voz de la anciana iba siendo más débil cada día, y a la menor emoción se le apagaba hasta
hacerse imperceptible. Para calmar a la enferma y dejarla tranquila le dí un abrazo y la besé
en la frente.

--No, madrina, ¡no hay que afligirse! Vendré a ver a ustedes cada ocho días. Además, la hacienda
de Santa Clara no está en el fin del mundo.... ¡Ya, ya verá usted a su sobrino, qué majo y
qué gallardo que viene, vestidito de charro, en un caballo soberbio! ¡Ya verá usted, tía Pepa,
qué elegante y guapo estaré con el pantalón ceñido, el jarano galoneado, la chaquetilla airosa
y la pistola al cinto! ¡Y «taca, taca, taca»! ¡Ahí está el ranchero! ¡Ya llegó! Y entrará Juana,
diciendo: «¡Señora... ya vino el charro!» Y usted, tía Pepilla, usted saldrá corriendo a recibirme
y abrazarme, o se asomará usted a la ventana para verme llegar, y ver a todas las muchachas
que han de mirarme con tamaños ojos, como diciendo: «¡Qué reguapo!» Y entraré, sonando las
espuelas, y ustedes se pondrán muy alegres. Y... ¡chas! ¡Ahí está el chorro de pesos!

Sonreía la enferma, sonreía tía Pepilla, y yo me paseaba por la estancia, afectando la gallarda
apostura de un jinete admirable.

Una hora después salía yo de la casa del señor Fernández. Presenté la tarjeta del doctor y
fuí recibido perfectamente. El hacendado me hizo pasar a su despacho, una pieza elegantemente
ajuarada. En dos por tres quedamos arreglados.

--Le espero a usted el día quince. Vendrán por usted. Mandaré un criado. ¿Tiene usted costumbre
de montar a caballo?

--No, señor, debo hacerlo como un colegial....

Sonrió el hacendado, y me dijo:

--Amiguito: ¡ya veremos!... Cabalgando se aprende....

Después se habló de mi familia, de mis tías, de la enfermedad de mi madrina, de mi abuelo,
a quien había tratado en no sé qué parte, y luego, en dos palabras me despidió.

--Bien:--dijo--¡asunto arreglado! Usted me perdonará... ¡estamos de viaje!... ¿Gusta usted
de almorzar?

Y se levantó y me condujo a la puerta.

En esos momentos apareció la señorita.

--¡Papá!

Sonrojóse al verme, y murmuró tímidamente:

--Usted dispense....

--¿Qué quieres, Gabriela?--le preguntó el caballero.

--¿A qué hora hemos de salir?

--Después de comer... a menos que tú quieras salir más tarde....

Saludé, y me fuí. ¡Linda criatura! Aun me parece que la veo con aquel vestido azul que parecía
un jirón de cielo; esbelta, donairosa, elegante, sencilla, húmedos los rubios cabellos, que,
atados con una cinta de seda, caían hacia la espalda sobre una toalla anchísima. ¡Nunca me
pareció más bella!

XL

Cuando llegué al despacho me encontré con el jurisperito. Salía para ir al Juzgado.

--Amigo:--me dijo muy gestudo y mohino--ya me cansé de esperar.... ¿Qué le ha pasado? ¿Por
qué viene usted a esta hora? Recuerde usted que el deber es lo primero. Déjese usted los amoríos
para los ratos de huelga.

Me sentí herido, y murmuré una disculpa, que no calmó la cólera de don Juan, sino que, por
lo contrario, le impacientó, porque, interrumpiendo mis excusas, agregó en tono despreciativo:

-¡Bien! ¡Bien! ¡Que no se repita esto!... Me voy al juzgado. Avise usted a las muchachas que
no me esperen.... Volveré entre cuatro y cinco. Ahí en mi bufete está un escrito.... ¡Cópiele
usted!

Se compuso el sombrero, y se fué. A poco, cuando principiaba yo a escribir, oí en el zaguán
voces femeniles que distrajeron mi atención. Luisa y Teresa, (no eran otras las que hablaban)
aparecieron en la puerta del escritorio. Venían muy majas y de ataque.

--¡Papá!--gritó la rubia, asomando su vivaracha cabecita.--¡Papá! ¡Ya estamos de vuelta!

Luego que supieron que don Juan había salido, y que no volvería hasta la tarde, las dos muchachas
se colaron de rondón en el despacho, y tomaron asiento en la banca de los clientes. Se abanicaban
furiosamente, y se miraban y sonreían como deseosas de decir algo que no les cabía en el cuerpo.

--¿No le robamos el tiempo?--preguntó la morena.

--No, señorita.

--¿De veras?--dijo la rubia.

--No.

--Pues entonces,--prorrumpió Luisa,--deje la pluma y charlemos un rato.

--Como ustedes gusten.

--¿A qué no sabe usted de dónde venimos?

--De la iglesia; de las tiendas; vendrán de comprar perendengues y moños.

--¡No!--exclamaron a una.

--No acierto....

--¡Adivine usted!...--dijo la morena.

--¡Adivine usted!...--repitió la rubia.

--No acierto, señoritas....

--¿Oyes, Luisa? ¡No acierta! Pues nosotras sabemos dónde estuvo usted hace media hora....

--¡Ah! No es difícil saberlo. Acabo de llegar, y ustedes me verían salir de casa..

--¿Oyes, Tere? ¡De... casa!

--Pues de allá salí hace una hora.

--¿Conque de casa, eh?--murmuró la morena.--¡De casa!

Se miraron discretamente, y sonrieron.

Luisa, para lucir sus lindas manos, se compuso el peinado, afirmando las horquillas con la
punta de los dedos. Teresa se acomodó en el asiento dejándome ver los pies, primorosamente
calzados; luego, cerró de un golpe el abanico, fingió que arreglaba las varillas, bajó los
ojos, y después de un rato de silencio, repitió, viéndome de hito en hito:

--¿Conque de casa, eh?

Me eché a reír. Aquel «conque» era la muletilla de las señoritas Castro Pérez, y en Villaverde
cuando de ellas se hablaba, todos decían «las niñas Castro Conque».

--¿De qué se ríe usted?--preguntó contrariada la rubia.

--De nada. Son ustedes muy maliciosas....

--¡Conque de casa!--volvió a decir.--No sabíamos que vivía usted allí, en el ¡«pa... la...
cio» de la marquesita! ¿Por qué no avisa usted cuando muda de casa?

La tormenta estaba encima.

--Son ustedes muy maliciosas. Es cierto que estuve en la casa del señor Fernández..., ¿y qué?

--¡Vaya! ¡Vaya! Confiesa usted...--exclamó Luisa, abanicándose.

--Nada tiene de extraño. Ya saben ustedes que los negocios.... Fuí a recoger una firma.

--¡Puede! Si nosotras estábamos allí.... Fuimos a pagar la visita. Ya nos daba vergüenza ver
a Gabriela. Figúrese usted que hace más de un año que vino acá. Papá decía a cada rato: «Niñas...
¿ya pagaron esa visita?» Nosotras no queríamos ir... porque... la verdad....

--¡No la digas;--interrumpió la morena--no la digas, que Rodolfo es de los interesados!

--¡Adiós! ¿Y por qué no? Una es muy dueña de decir lo que quiera....

--Sí; pero... ¡no a todo el mundo! ¿No ves que Rodolfo....?

--¡Diga usted, Teresa, diga usted!

--¡No, Tere!--suplicó Luisa.

--¡Pues lo he de decir!... Pues, ¡vaya, que... esa señorita nos... choca!

--¿Y por qué?

--¡Friolera!--exclamó Luisa.--¿No la ve usted tan pagada de sí, y tan orgullosa, que a todos
desprecia, y que dice que todas las vilaverdinas somos unas payas..., unas ridículas.

--Vean ustedes, señoritas: pienso que esa niña no es orgullosa, ni está pagada de sí; pienso
que no desprecia a nadie, y que, por lo contrario, es muy amable con todos; y de seguro que
es incapaz de decir eso que ustedes le atribuyen....

--¡Usted qué ha de decir!... Usted la defiende porque... ¡vaya! ¡porque está usted enamorado
de ella!

--¿Yo, Teresa?

--Sí.

--¿Quién ha dicho eso?

--¡Todo el mundo! ¡Todo el mundo lo dice!

--Pues «todo el mundo» dice mentira.

--¿Mentira? ¡Que me azoten en la plaza, y que no lo sepan en mi casa! Usted dirá lo que guste...
pero si no es verdad eso que cuentan, usted tiene la culpa de todo, porque le hace usted unos
osos terribles.... Noche a noche va usted a oirla tocar.... Allí se está usted horas y horas,
en la baranda de la Plaza. Y por eso Gabriela, que sabe que tiene... «au... ditorio», no se
quita del piano.... Y por cierto que... (¡no se enoje usted!) ¡por cierto que la pobrecilla
lo hace bien mal!... ¿Verdad, Luisa?

--¡Por Dios, Tere!--exclamó la morena.

--¡Cállate tú! Ahora verá usted, Rodolfo: le dijimos que tocara, y tocó la «Sonámbula» de Talberg.
¡Jesús nos asista! ¡Qué «Sonámbula»!

--No, hija, no; no digas eso.... Ella toca sin expresión, sin compás... pero en cuanto a ejecutar...
¡ejecuta mucho! Ya quisieran muchos, de esos que se llaman profesores, ejecutar como Gabriela.

--Pues, mira, Luisa; ¡yo ni eso le concedo! ¿Qué chiste tiene eso de aporrear el piano? Si
aquello me parecía un pleito de perros.

Y la rubia se tapó las orejas.

--Teresa, por Dios: ¡ten caridad!--dijo en tono compasivo la morena.--No hables así; dirán
que decimos eso por... ¡envidia!

--¿Envidia yo? ¿Y de qué? ¿Yo? ¡Gracias a Dios que no toco el piano!

--No; pero pensarán que tú no haces más que repetir lo que yo digo.

--Y dirán la verdad. Quién me dijo ahora, al salir de allá: «¿Viste, oiste? ¡Eso no es tocar!
¡Lástima de piano!» ¿No fuiste tú? Pues entonces ¿de qué te espantas? Yo diré lo que me dé
la gana. Ya lo sabes: ¡tan fea como tan franca!

Me indignaba la murmuración de aquellas niñas tan mal educadas y tan cursis.

--¿Fea? ¡Nada de eso! ¿Quién ha dicho que es usted fea? No lo digo yo, ni lo dice nadie, y
menos... Ricardo Tejeda.

Encendióse la rubia al oír este nombre. Ricardo había sido su novio, lo sabía yo muy bien,
él mismo me lo dijo en el Colegio, y Teresa no le perdonaba a mi amigo que, a poco de «terminar»
con ella, hubiera visto con demasiado interés a la elegante y encantadora señorita. De aquí
el odio a Gabriela; de aquí que murmurase de su hermosura; de aquí el que afeara todo en la
señorita Fernández.

--Sí;--contestó vivamente Teresa--ya sé que en Ricardo tiene usted un rival....

La maldiciente polluela estaba enamorada de amigo; le quería, a su manera, le amaba como loca,
y no podía olvidarle.

--Sí, ya sé que Ricardo está enamorado de Gabriela, lo sé; y sé también que por eso no habla
con usted, ni le busca como antes. ¡Antes tan amigos! ¡Ahora enemigos a muerte!

--¿Enemigos? ¿Quién ha dicho eso?

--Sí, se pasan pero no se tragan.... Pero esté usted tranquilo, Rodolfo; Ricardo no es temible...
¡no es temible!

--Vea usted, señorita: si Ricardo está creyendo que yo pretendo a Gabriela, es porque alguno
le ha engañado.... ¡Alguno que ha querido burlarse de nosotros...!

Luisa nos escuchaba atentamente, jugaba con el abanico, y sonreía al oirme. Teresa se quedó
un instante pensativa.

--Oiga usted, Rodolfo: ¿me quiere usted hacer un favor?

--Veamos, ¿cuál?...

--¿Tiene usted amores con esa señorita?

--No.

--¿De veras?

--De veras.

--Pues, enamórela usted; enamórela usted. Yo conozco muy bien a las mujeres, como que soy del
sexo. ¡Enamórela usted! ¡Yo le aseguro que en dos por tres se arreglan ustedes!

--¿Y Ricardo?--pregunté con mucha seriedad.

--¿Ricardo? ¡Qué rabie! ¡Quién le manda ser tonto!

Las muchachas se levantaron, chacharearon dos o tres minutos, y se fueron. Ya en la puerta
se detuvieron. Teresa se volvió hacia mí, y con tono entre suplicante y malicioso me dijo:

--Rodolfo: ¡enamórela usted!

XLI

Castro Pérez llegó un poco antes de las cinco. Entró silencioso, dejó en su mesa el sombrero
y el bastón, y luego, paso a paso, se dirigió a la mía:

--¿Acabó usted la copia?

--Aquí está.

Leyó el alegato, firmó, y volvió a su pieza. Yo le seguí.

--Deseo hablar con usted dos palabritas.

--¿De qué se trata?

Díjele que iba yo a separarme; que a ello me veía obligado por la necesidad; mis gastos iban
siendo mayores cada día, y lo que allí ganaba no me era suficiente para atender a mi familia.

--Vamos:--me interrumpió--¿a qué viene todo eso? Está usted disgustado porque esta mañana....

--No;--me apresuré a contestar--dí motivo para que usted me reprendiera. Tiene usted razón;
el deber es lo primero. No, señor: le aseguro que no es esa la causa de mi separación. No gano
aquí cuanto necesito, y, como es natural, estoy obligado a procurar que mis tías no carezcan
de nada. Tengo empleo en otra parte.... Allí ganaré más.

Encendióse el jurisperito, se irguió en la poltrona, se compuso las gafas, y mirándome por
encima de los cristales me dijo desdeñosamente:

--¡Bien! ¡Bien! Y... sepamos, ¿qué empleo es ese? ¿Va usted a meterse a maestro de escuela?

--No, señor.

--Pues, entonces?

--Voy a la hacienda de Santa Clara....

--¡Ya me lo imaginaba! ¡Lo de siempre! ¡Ese Fernández se ha empeñado en quitarme los escribientes!
¡Bien! ¡Bien! Haga usted lo que guste; haga usted lo que mejor le convenga; pero no diga que
aquí ha estado usted mal retribuído, ¡porque no es verdad! Nadie ha ganado aquí más que usted.
No diré que le pago un capital, ni mucho menos, porque el dinero no cae con la lluvia, pero...
es usted soltero, no tiene usted familia, ni obligaciones.... Con lo que tiene usted aquí...
¡le basta y le sobra! ¡Bien! ¡Bien!

Quise replicar, pero me pareció inútil toda aclaración. Castro Pérez prosiguió:

--No estará usted contento en Santa Clara. Lo anuncio desde ahora. Allí, según noticias, se
trabaja mucho, ¡mucho!... Usted no tiene costumbre de matarse así, de sol a sol, como un gañán.
Aquí está usted mejor; tiene usted tiempo libre para todo.... ¡Hasta para hacer versos! ¡Bien!
¡Bien! ¿Y cuándo se va usted?

--Dentro de quince días.

--¡Eso sí está malo, malísimo! ¡Bien! Se irá usted cuando guste. Hoy mismo llamaré al sustituto.
¡Queda usted libre desde hoy!

--Yo contaba con seguir aquí, al servicio de usted, hasta el día en que debo estar en la hacienda,
y he querido....

--No, joven, no; lo que ha de ser tarde que sea temprano.

Me sentí humillado, y callé.

--Vea usted, joven;--agregó con dulzura--quédese usted conmigo.... Le aumentaré los emolumentos;
le daré cinco pesos más. ¡Creo que con eso no tendrá usted dificultades!

--¡Imposible, señor! Acepté ya el destino, y no me parece conveniente rehusarle ahora.

--Tiene usted razón. ¡Bien! ¡Bien!

Abrió el cajón de la mesa, sacó un puñado de monedas, me hizo la cuenta, a tanto por día, como
a un criado, y me dió unos cuantos duros. De buena gana me hubiera yo negado a recibirlos,
a pretexto de generoso desprendimiento, pero aquel dinero me era necesario; era pan y vida
alegre para algunos días.

¡Triste condición la del pobre!--pensé.--¡Triste condición la de quién está obligado a servir
a otro! Y entonces recordé, uno por uno, todos los malos ratos que había pasado yo en la casa
del jurisperito, y en los cuales no reparé nunca, aunque no fueron pocos. Recelos, malos modos,
despótico trato, reprensiones inmotivadas, correcciones estúpidas, alardes de ciencia que tenían
por objeto mantener un crédito cimentado en arena, y, sobre todo, esa desconfianza ofensiva,
insultante, que hay en algunos ricos para con el desgraciado que les sirve y gana poco, de
quien se teme todo lo malo, y a quien se puede ultrajar impunemente, pues se sabe que el ultrajado
tendrá que callar, porque si habla y replica, y rechaza con noble energía la infame sospecha,
se quedará sin el mendrugo diariamente ganado a costa de un trabajo penoso.

Hasta entonces paré mientes en que el pobre, el que vive de un sueldo mezquino, está a merced
de quienes le pagan. ¿Qué hará si le echan a la calle? ¿Qué hará, si, lastimado en su honradez
y en su dignidad, protesta de su inocencia, y toma el sombrero, y se va? «¡No hará tal!--dice
el amo.--¿Qué come mañana? Tiene hijos, esposa...» Y fiado en esto le ultraja y atropella sin
piedad.

Pero entonces no había caído en mi corazón ni una gota de hiel. La juventud es generosa, es
buena, y no cree, no quiere creer que los demás son o pueden ser malos; piensa que sólo hay
corazones nobles y almas bondadosas.

No olvido ni olvidaré jamás que cierto día, en el despacho de Castro Pérez, recibí una buena
cantidad en metálico; conté y volví a contar las monedas, las revisé con el mayor cuidado,
y estaban completas. Contólas después el jurisperito, y le faltó una. No tardó en salir trémulo
y colérico.

--¡Aquí falta dinero!...--prorrumpió en voz alta, delante de Porras y Linares.

Volví a contar el dinero en presencia de todos. ¡Cabalito!

--¡Tiene usted razón!--murmuró don Juan.--¡Usted dispense!

Don Cosme no se dió cuenta de lo que pasaba. Porras me detuvo al paso, y, poniendo sus manos
en mis hombros, me dijo dulcemente:

--¡Este hombre no tiene remedio! ¿Quién le manda a usted gastar esas corbatas... tan bonitas¡
¡Paciencia, joven! ¡Paciencia!

Dieron las seis, recogí algunos papeles que tenía yo en el cajón de la mesa, dí las gracias
a Castro Pérez por sus bondades para conmigo, y me lancé a la calle.

XLII

Aquellos veinte días fueron muy amargos para mí. ¡Más de medio mes sin ganar un peso! Nuestros
gastos habían subido considerablemente; hubo que pagar a una criada, y fué preciso comprar
no sé qué medicinas muy caras que recetó Sarmiento, y vino de suprema clase para la enferma.
Andrés, generoso como siempre, acudió en mi auxilio.

--No te aflijas,--me decía,--el tenducho da para mucho. ¡Toma!

Y puso en mis manos un rollo de pesos.

Mi salida de la casa de Castro Pérez, salida que además de enojosa me pareció ofensiva para
mi buen nombre, me puso abatido y desalentado.

Todos aquéllos que me veían en la calle, sin ocupación ni empleo, y que antes me vieron en
el despacho del abogado, pensarían, sin duda, que Castro Pérez me había despedido por algo
vergonzoso. Dime a cavilar en esto, y me resolví a no salir de casa. Me pasaba yo el día leyendo,
escribiendo y cuidando del jardín. Las plantas que Angelina y yo habíamos sembrado prosperaban
a maravilla; los rosales recobraban su lozano follaje; las violetas macollaban que era una
gloria, y el cuadro de «no me olvides» parecía una alfombra de felpa.

Cierto día, aburrido de pasar el tiempo entre cuatro paredes, tomé el sombrero y me fuí de
tertulia a la casa de don Procopio. Allí estaban los pedagogos y el P. Solís. No bien me vieron
mis críticos se pusieron a sonreir como si de mí se burlaran, como si recordaran que me habían
puesto de oro y azul en sus periódicos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07318</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>101427</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21156</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> When we usually encounter petty beings with souls degraded,
for which self-respect is vain word, if not reach the ears touches the heart, or dyed red
cheeks, saying: "Soul of a slave!" And without wanting to think of a life of misery that debased
the character and spirit trap for fools. Say what you will, that nobility is the only happiness
of the rich. For her, only for her, admiring the world. Everything else that they envy the
crowd is like the crown of tinsel that surrounds the front of the actor. Noble dignity, dignity
enviable places except higher heart clothes!

Observe all those who lived a miserable childhood, in whose home is often missed bread, they
had no clothes to cover the emaciated body that begged ashamed public charity, and not as
a beggar, with quiet directness, but hiding the demand flattering phrase, which became, gradually,
the shy smile embarrassing to the appeal; suggestive of the request to the shameful exploitation,
and from there ... tolerance interested and you will see, whether in wealth, but the mime and society's
wealth has As compensation for a time denied even have hidden in the heart most vinegar and gall
of misery. Hopeless poverty gives character, and its breast hypocritical breed pride, modesty
mocking, malicious cunning, who have flexibilities Viper, the meanness intriguing poisonous
slander and envy all bloodless the greed and everything ugly.

In pursuit of that noble dignity are all souls uplifted, high thinking,
cease heart: the student who strives to conquer worthy place in society,
the merchant spent at work the best years of life, the tradesman who
struggle for life independent.

The desire to achieve it is the only apology that is greed.

My father wanted me that coveted happiness could not achieve their goals, but he inherited the
instinct of pride pride with which I rejected all the time, a boy,
a waiter, and mature man unworthy humiliation, reprimand unmotivated,
the brutal outrage of those who was considered superior to me.

I inherited my mother's placid sweetness for weakness, submission respectful to all acts of justice,
irresistible tendency to feel sorry for the pain of others, and a certain feminine delicacy
that has caused me a lot of bitterness.

Delivered to these meditations spent an hour. Wine sleep, and sweet wine and flattering, as a loving
friend who comes to our call to give comfort, to revive the depressed
heart as a compassionate sister who comes to our bed and caresses
our face, -closed our eyes, inviting us to rest because he knows that
we suffer and we need rest.

XXXIX

The next day, after breakfast, I told my aunt what was happening.

-
And you go! - Cried my aunt Pepa .-- You go and leave us?

- Is necessary.

I realize this must be very painful for you .... I understand, I have
already thought about it, but what to do?

- Now that we are alone,
when Angelina just left ... when after all these years of freedom
has returned to our side!

- Yes, Aunt, I will go, and not by choice.

God knows how painful is this separation! ... But Do not worry you.

It is necessary .... I am bound a. ...

- To live with your aunt! - Said interrupting me.

- I have to meet the needs of you.

- Do not you just what you want in the house of Castro Perez?

Did you ask something you can not us?

- No, aunt, but I can not look calmly working life takes you.

Andrés ago for us what he can, and the poor may soon. I am not ashamed to accept his favors;
but that should not go on indefinitely .... You know the house of Castro Pérez I earn little,
and it is not possible to earn more.

- Well, I think there is your future ....

I could not but smile to hear my poor aunt.

- My future?

- Yes.

-
No, aunt, I would not spend my life writing allegations.

This work is killing me.

Not because rude, but because it is insufficient. I prefer to farm work and the hectic life
of the fields giving health and good humor.

The patient remained silent. Aunt Pepa tried to convince me that I should not leave. We discussed
at length the point, she, living, nerve, unleashing all the difficulties, I pretending that
he had a serenity. Neither the old woman wanted to surrender and I managed to convince her.

- Come on - I cried - that solves my sponsor!

- Yes, my son - said the old woman - it's my turn! Pepa loves you and is made let us drive.
Think you, Pepa, which is not far from us, think that will come frequently, and believes that now,
with Castro Pérez, will do nothing. You go, Rodolfo, I go, and we'll be very happy. Say no more.
Get dressed, I see that as you judge, dress and go to the home of
Fernandez.

Discontent will not get is a very fine person.

Is not it true, Pepa?

- I will, aunt.

- Then you go to the house of Castro Pérez, and alerts you within twenty days, or those are, as agreed,
you have to separate you from there, and you're done!

He added a little tremulous emotion:

- Look, I feel that we leave, but reason dictates that you let me go, that it does not prevent you
you're doing. I am the best day I'll go too, and I will not die when I choke the idea that
because we have lost well-being that we can not give you ....

The old woman's voice was becoming weaker every day, and no emotion is turned off until be imperceptible.
To soothe the sick and leave it alone gave him a hug and kissed her on the forehead.

- No, godmother, we should not grieve! I will come to see you every week. In addition, the
estate Santa Clara is the world's end .... Ya, you'll see his nephew,
How cute and Gallardo is coming, charro dress in a magnificent horse!

You'll see, Aunt Pepa, how elegant and handsome I am with the tight pants, the Jarano gallon, airy
jacket and the pistol in his belt!

And "taca, taca, taca"! There's the ranch! Has arrived! And enter Juana saying: "Lady ...
wine and the charro! "And you, Aunt Pepilla, you'll run to meet me and embrace, or peek out the
window you see me come and see all the girls have to look at me with
eyes wide, as saying: "What reguapo!"

And I will come in, sounding the spurs, and you will become very happy. Y. .. Chas! There is a
stream of dollars!

The patient smiled, smiled Pepilla aunt and I walked around the room,
affecting the brave admirable bearing of a rider.

An hour later I went out of the house of Mr. Fernandez. Presented
the doctor card I obtained perfectly.

The farmer showed me into his office, an elegant piece trousseau. In two of three stayed fixed.

-
I hope you on the fifteenth.

Come for you. Send a servant.

Do you have custom Riding?

- No, sir, I do like a schoolboy ....

The farmer smiled and said:

- Friend: we'll see! ... Riding is learned ....

Then he spoke of my family, my aunts, my godmother's disease, my grandfather, who had tried not
to know how much, and then fired me two words.

- Well, - said - problem solved!

You forgive me ... We journey ... "Like you lunch?

And he rose and led me to the door.

In those moments came the lady.

- Dad!

Blushed when he saw me, and murmured shyly:

- You dispense ....

-
What is it, Gabriel? - Asked the gentleman.

- What time are we leaving?

-
After eating ... unless you want to go out later ....

I waved, and
left.

Linda creature! Although I think I see with that blue dress that seemed A patch of sky, slender,
grace, elegant, simple, moist blonde hair, which tied with a silk ribbon, fell to the back on
a towel very wide. I never seemed more beautiful!

XL

When I reached the office I met the legal expert. Left to go to court.

- Friend: - I said very gestudo and mohino - I'm tired of waiting
.... What happened?

Why what comes to you at this hour?

Remind yourself that duty comes first.

Let your love affairs for the moments to strike.

I was hurt, and mumbled an apology, which did not calm the anger of
Don Juan, but on Otherwise, you impatient, because, interrupting my
excuses, he added scornfully:

- Well!

Well! Do not repeat this! ... I'm going to court.

Tell the girls you I do not wait .... Return between four and five.

Here in my office is a letter .... Copy you!

It was made the hat, and left.

A little, when I was beginning to write, I heard in the hall feminine
voices that distracted my attention.

Luisa and Teresa, (the others were not speaking) appeared in front
of the desk.

They came very pestles and attack.

- Dad! - The blonde shouted,
poking his head .-- lively Dad!

We're back!

Then they learned that Don Juan was out and would not return until
the afternoon, the two girls of brashly slipped into the office, and
sat on the bench of the customers.

Fanned furiously, and looked and smiled as willing to say something they do not fit in the
body.

- Did not steal the time? - Asked the brunette.

- No, miss.

- Really? - Said the blonde.

- No.

- Well then - burst Luisa, - leave the pen and a chat.

- As you like.

-
What you do not know where we come from?

- In the church store, come
buy perendengues and bows.

- No! - Cry out with one.

- I fail ....

-
Guess you !...-- said the brunette.

- Guess you !...-- repeated the
blonde.

- No success, ladies ....

- Do you hear, Luisa?

No hits! Well we know where you were half an hour ago ....

- Ah! It is hard to say. I just came, and you would leave me home ..

- Do you hear, Tere? De .. home!

- Then from there I left an hour ago.

- "So at home, eh? - The brunette muttered .-- From home!

They looked quietly and smiled.

Luisa, to show off her beautiful hands, her hair was made, stating with forks fingertips. Teresa
sat in the seat letting me see your feet, carefully shoes, then slammed
the fan, pretended that he would set the rods, lowered eyes, and after
a pause, he repeated, looking at me straight in the eye:

- "So at
home, eh?

I laughed.

That "So" was the catch phrase of the Miss Castro Pérez, and Villaverde when they spoke, everyone
said "So Castro girls."

- What are you laughing? - Asked the blonde
upset.

- Sure.

You are very malicious ....

- So Home! - Again .-- say you did not
know who lived there in the "pa ... the ... price "of the marquise!

Why not warn you when moving house?

The storm was over.

- You are very malicious. It is true that I was in the house of Mr. Fernandez ... what?

- Go! Go! Confess you ...-- Luisa said, fanning herself.

- No wonder.

You know that business .... I went to collect a signature.

- You!

If we were there .... We pay a visit. Because we were ashamed to see Gabriela. Just imagine that over
a year ago he came here.

Dad said all the time: "Girls ... You already paid this visit? " We did not want to go ... because ...
truth ....

- Do not say, - interrupted the dark - do not say that Rudolph is
interested!

- Goodbye!

And why not?

An owner is to say what they want ....

- Yes, but ... Not everyone! Can not you see Rodolfo ....?

- Tell me, Teresa, you say!

- No, Tere! - Pleaded Luisa.

- Well I have to say! ... Well, go, let ... Miss that we ... hits!

- Why?

- Friolera! - Luisa said .-- Have not seen you so smug and so proud, that all despises, and
that says all we are a clown ... vilaverdinas, some ridiculous.

- Look here, ladies: I think that girl is not proud, nor smug, I think
who did not despise anyone, and that, by contrast, is very nice to
everyone, and insurance is unable to say that you attribute ....

-
You do have to say!

... You defend it because ... Go! Because you are in love it!

- Me, Teresa?

- Yes.

- Who said that?

- Everybody!

Everyone says so!

- Well, 'everyone' says lie.

- Lie? It whipped me in the street, and who do not know in my house!

You say what you like ... but if it is true what they have, you have
to blame for everything, because it makes you a bears terrible ....
Night after night you're going to hear it play .... Are you there
for hours, on the railing of the Plaza.

And so Gabriela, who knows he has ... Au ... auditorium "is not removed
from the piano .... And you are ... (You do not get mad!) Certain
that the poor thing do good evil ... Right, Luisa?

- By God, Tere!
- Said the brunette.

- Shut up you!

Now you see, Rodolfo: we told him to play, and played the "Sonnambula"
in Talberg.

Jesus help us!

What 'Sleepwalker'!

- No, child, no, do not say that .... She played
without expression, without a compass ... but as for running ... Runs
much!

And wanted many of those who call themselves teachers, run as Gabriela.

- Well, look, Luisa, and I grant you that!

Joke What's so bang on the piano?

If what I looked like a dog suit.

And the blonde covered her ears.

- Teresa, by God: ten charity! -
Sympathetically told the brunette .-- Do not talk like that, tell
we say that for ... Envy!

- Do you envy me?

And what?

Me? Thank God I do not play the piano!

- No, but you think you are only repeating what I say.

- And tell
the truth.

Who told me now, to go from there: "Did you see, you hear?

That's not playing! Too bad piano! "Were not you?

Then why do you frighten? I say whatever I want.

You know: as ugly as so frank!

I angered the defaming of those girls so rude and so cheesy.

- Ugly? Not so! Who said you're ugly? I do not say, nor what anyone says, and less ... Ricardo
Tejeda.

Kindled the blonde to hear this name. Ricardo had been her boyfriend, I knew very well, he
told me in college, and Teresa could not forgive my friend who, at
some "end" with it, it has seen much interest to the elegant and charming
lady.

Hence Gabriela hatred, hence murmur of her beauty here that everything
in afeara Miss Fernandez.

- Yes - strongly replied Teresa - I know
that you have a rival Ricardo ....

The cursing was in love with friend
Sora, he wanted his own way, loved him like crazy and could not forget
him.

- Yes, I know that Richard is in love with Gabriel, I know,
and I also know that we will not go with you, or you'll be looking
as before.

Before such good friends!

Now enemies to death!

- Enemies?

Who said that?

- Yes, you pass but do not buy .... But are you calm, Rodolfo, Ricardo is not scary ... Is not
scary!

- See you, lady: if Richard is thinking that I intend to Gabriela, is because some he cheated
.... Someone who wanted to make fun of us ...!

We listened intently Luisa, played with her fan, and he smiled at me hear. Teresa was a pensive
moment.

- Listen, Rodolfo: I want you to do a favor?

- Let's see, what ...?

-
Do you love with this lady?

- No.

- Really?

- Really.

- Well,
you enamórela; enamórela you.

I know women very well, as I am of sex. Enamórela you! I assure you that in two of three will manage
you!

- What about Ricardo? - Asked seriously.

- Ricardo?

How infuriating! Who sends to be silly!

The girls stood up, chattering two or three minutes, and left. At the door stopped. Teresa turned
to me, and malicious tone between pleading and said:

- Rodolfo: enamórela you!

XLI

Pérez Castro arrived a little before five o'clock.

He went silent, he left his hat on the table and staff, and then, step by step, he went to mine:

-
Have you finished the copy?

- Here it is.

Read the allegation, signed and returned to his room. I followed him.

- I want to talk with you two little words.

- What is it?

I told him I was going to be separated, which is why I was forced by necessity, my expenses were
still higher every day, and there I was earning enough to meet my family.

- Come on - I stopped - what is that? Are you upset because this morning ....

- No, - I hurried to answer - I gave you reason to rebuke me.

You are right; duty comes first. No, sir, I assure you that this is not the cause of my separation.
I do not win here what I need, and, of course, I am obligated to ensure that my aunts did
not lack nothing. I have work elsewhere .... They earn more.

Kindled the jurist, he stood on the chair, is composed glasses, and
looking at me above the glass told me scornfully

- Well!

Well! Y. .. know, what use is that?

Are you going to get a school teacher?

- No, sir.

- Well, then?

- I go to the hacienda of Santa Clara ....

- I thought so! The usual! That Fernández has worked to rid the scribes! Well! Well! Do what you
like, do what you suits you, but do not say here you have been underpaid, it's not true! No
one has won here more than you. I will not say I pay a lump sum or anything, because the money
does not come with the rain, but ... you're single, you have no family,
no obligations .... With what you have here ... Is enough and to spare!

Well! Well!

I wanted to reply, but I found it unnecessary to clarify. Pérez Castro continued:

- You will not be happy in Santa Clara. The announcement from now. There, according to news,
work hard, a lot! ... You do not have a habit of killing and, from sunrise to sunset, as a
farmhand. Here's your best, you have free time for all .... Up to verse! Well! Well! And when are
you going?

- Within fifteen days.

- That itself is bad, very bad! Well! Will leave you at your convenience. Today call the substitute.
You shall be free from today!
- I had to stay here, serving you until the day I should be on the
farm, and I wanted ....

- No, young man, no, what is to be late to
be early.

I felt humiliated, and silent.

- See you, young man -
added gently - you stay with me .... He would raise the salaries;
I'll give you five dollars more. I think with that you will not have
problems!

- Impossible, sir! Accepted as the destination, and I refuse
it now seems appropriate.

- You're right. Well! Well!

He opened
the desk drawer, pulled out a handful of coins, I made the account,
both by day as a servant, and gave me a few dollars. I gladly would
I have refused to receive them generous pretext of detachment, but
I needed that money, it was bread and life happy for a few days.

Sad
condition of the poor! - I .-- Sad condition of who is required to
serve another! And then I remembered, one by one, all the bad times
that had passed me in the house the jurist, and where ever I saw not,
although they were few. Mistrust, bad manners, despotic treatment,
reprimands unmotivated, corrections stupid feats of science that had
designed to maintain a credit founded on sand, and, above all, that
distrust offensive insulting, there are some rich towards the poor
that serves and earn little, who fears all evil, and who can offend
with impunity, it is known that the outraged will be silent, because
if you speak and reply, and rejects the infamous energy noble suspicion
will run the daily crust won at the expense of hard labor.

Until
then I stopped lying on the poor, who live on a paltry salary is at
the mercy of those who pay. What will you do if you take to the streets?
What will you do if, injured in his honor and their dignity, protesting
his innocence, and takes his hat, and go? "It will do this! - Says
master .-- What do you eat tomorrow? Have children, wife ... 'And
you trusted in this outraged and runs without piety.

But then my
heart had fallen into a drop of gall. Youth is generous, is good,
and does not believe, does not believe that others are or may be bad,
think that there is only noble hearts and good souls.

Do not forget
or never forget that one day, in the office of Castro Perez, received
a good amount in cash, told and retold coins, I checked with the greatest
care, and were complete. He told them after the jurist, and he was
missing. Trembling out soon and angry.

- Here you need money !...--
burst into loud, in front of Porras and Linares.

I went back to counting
money in front of everyone. Cabalito!

- You're right! - Muttered
Don Juan .-- You dispense!

Don Cosme did not realize what was happening.
Porras step stopped me, laid his hands on my shoulders, I said gently:

-
This man is hopeless! Who sends you spend those ties ... so pretty
Patience, young man! Patience!

Was six, I picked up some papers I
had in the desk drawer, I thanked Castro Pérez for their kindness
to me and threw me on the street.

XLII

Those twenty days were very
bitter for me. More than half a month without gaining weight! Our
costs had risen considerably, had to pay a maid, and was obliged to
buy I do not know why prescribing expensive medicines Sarmiento, and
wine of supreme class for the sick. Andrew, generous as ever, came
to my aid.

- Do not worry - I said - the tenducho goes a long way.
Take!

And handed me a roll of pesos.

I left the house of Castro
Pérez, besides annoying output seemed offensive to me my good name,
I got depressed and discouraged.

All those who saw me on the streets,
without occupation or employment, and before I saw the lawyer's office,
think, without doubt, that Castro Perez was fired for something I
embarrassing. Tell me to ponder on this, and I decided to stay at
home. I spent my day reading, writing and gardening. Plants that Angelina
and I had planted prospered to wonder, the roses recovered their lush
foliage, the tiller which was a violet glory, and the picture of "forget
me not" looked like a plush carpet.

One day, tired of spending time
within four walls, took his hat and went to gathering at the house
of Don Procopio. There were the teachers and the P. Solis. As soon
as I saw my critics began to smile as if to mock me as if I had remembered
since gold and blue in their newspapers</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>