<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05583</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>20356</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>15533</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Separáronse
del modo más cordial en la posada del Dragón, y D. Benigno, desmejorado y cojo, se fue a su
casa con toda la rapidez que lo permitía su detestable andadura, mientras Salvador buscaba
donde alojarse. Pocos días después hallábase instalado en habitación propia que alquiló en
la calle del Duque de Alba, no lejos de D. Felicísimo Carnicero, de felicísima recordación.
En Madrid no encontró novedad alguna, pues no merece tal nombre el furor con que todo el mundo
fraguaba levantamiento s y sediciones. Conspiraban las infantas brasileñas con sin igual descaro;
conspiraban los voluntarios realistas, ayudados por la turbamulta de frailes y clérigos mal
avenidos con la idea de perder su omnipotencia; conspiraban las monjas y los sacristanes, muchos
militares que se habían hecho familiares de los obispos, y para que no faltase su lado cómico
a esta comparsa nacional, también se agitaban en pro de D. Carlos muchos señores que habían
sido rabiosos democratistas y jacobinos en los tres llamados años de la titulada segunda época
constitucional. Antes habían gritado por el sistema y ahora suspiraban por los derechos de
la soberanía en su inmemorial plenitud.

Oyó también Salvador los despropósitos del vulgo, a quien se había hecho creer que el Rey no
vivía y que aquel buen señor que salía en coche a paseo era el cadáver embalsamado de Fernando
VII. Por un sencillo mecanismo, la napolitana, que a su lado iba, le hacía mover las manos
y la cabeza para saludar. ¡Y con un Rey relleno de paja se estaba engañando a esta heroica Nación!

Vio un cambio de ministros fundado en que los del 16 de Octubre parecieron un poco dañados
de liberalismo, pues la Corte deseaba un gobierno absolutamente agridulce que contentase a
todos y conciliara el día con la noche, cosa en verdad más difícil que asar la manteca. También
pudo ver la anulación del célebre codicilo, acto solemne de que se burlaron los carlistas,
y oyó contar la fuga de Calomarde vestido de fraile, y los desmanes del obispo de León, el
cual, ensoberbecido como un cacique indio y no pudiendo sublevar el reino, puso en armas su
diócesis, dando la comandancia de voluntarios realistas a la Purísima Concepción.

Otras muchas cosas supo y vio que no son para referidas a la ligera. Sus relaciones con gente
de varias clases le informaban de todo. Pipaón, D. Felicísimo Carnicero y el marqués de Falfán
no hacían misterio de los planes apostólicos, y Genara, furibunda sectaria del sistema del
justo medio o de la conciliación, era el órgano más feliz que imaginarse puede de los pensamientos
de aquel astuto Sr. Zea que gobernaba o aparentaba gobernar la nave (¡siempre la nave!), más
cercana a los escollos que al deseado puerto.

Genara se había establecido en su antigua casa, notoria tres años antes por la tertulia a que
concurrían literatos tiernos y políticos maduros; pero ya en el invierno de 1833 no se abrían
las puertas de aquella feliz morada para el primer poeta que viniese de su provincia cargado
de tragedias, ni para los tenores italianos, ni para los abogados oradores que empezaban a
nacer en las aulas con una lozanía hasta cierto punto calamitosa. El círculo era mucho más
estrecho y las amistades más escogidas, con lo que ganaba en consideración la casa. Y aquí
viene bien decir que la interesante señora había perdido por completo su afición a la poesía
lírica (que no hay cosa durable en el mundo), y tanto caso hacía ya del prisionero de Cuéllar
como de las nubes de antaño. Él era en verdad de un carácter poco a propósito para la constancia
en los afectos. No se sabe si en la temporada a que nos vamos refiriendo había dado a conocer
Genara preferencia o simpatía por alguna otra de las artes liberales, o por la artillería y
la náutica, como se dijo. Careciendo de noticias ciertas, nos abstenemos de afirmar cosa alguna;
que en casos dudosos vale más atenerse a la opinión buena, como mandan la moral de la historia
y la caridad cristiana.

D. Luis Fernández de Córdova, militar brillantísimo, pasaba, cuando vino de Berlín para encargarse
de la embajada de Portugal, largas horas en casa de Genara. También iban, aunque no con mucha
frecuencia, D. Francisco Javier de Burgos y Martínez de la Rosa. Era de los asiduos un joven
oficial granadino llamado Narváez, muy vivo de genio, ceceoso, pendenciero y expeditivo. Pero
la persona más digna de mención entre los que visitaban a la hermosa señora era un jesuita
del colegio Imperial, llamado el padre Gracián, hombre de mucha piedad y oración. Decían algunos
que de la amistad del buen religioso con Genara iba a salir la conversión de esta, o sea su
entrada en las buenas vías católicas. Otros declaraban haber notado en ella resabios de mojigatería;
pero sea lo que quiera, lo cierto es que las intenciones del padre Gracián eran altamente provechosas,
porque (digámoslo de una vez) se había propuesto reconciliar a la señora con su marido.

Que Pipaón visitaba casi diariamente a su antigua amiga y paisana no hay para qué decirlo.
Por añadidura, el excelentísimo D. Juan Bragas había simpatizado mucho con el jesuita Gracián.
Ambos platicaban con seriedad pasmosa de los negocios de Estado y de la Iglesia, deplorando
mucho la tibieza de creencias que tanto dañaba a la sociedad española en aquellos tiempos y
concluían deseando que viniesen otros mejores en que marchasen las naciones por el camino de
la piedad, dulcemente pastoreadas por los ministros del altar. Como Gracián se interesaba tanto
por sus amigos y quería llevar todos los beneficios posibles al seno de las familias cristianas,
tomó muy a pecho la realización del casamiento de Bragas con Micaelita, proyecto de que ya
hay noticias en el libro anterior.

Acompañando a Pipaón iba Salvador algunas veces a casa de Genara; solían comer juntos los tres,
y cuando se encontraban Monsalud y Gracián también hablaban largamente del Estado y de la Iglesia.
Un día, después de hablar con él, el jesuita pidió informes a la señora de la casa sobre aquel
desconocido amigo, quizás para ver si le podía reconciliar con alguien, porque el afán del
buen discípulo de San Ignacio era la reconciliación. Genara respondió:

--Si quiere usted ganar la palma del buen pacificador, hágale usted amigo de mi marido.

--¿No se quieren bien?--preguntó Gracián con astucia.

--Nada bien.... Es enemistad que data desde la guerra con los franceses. Ambos son tercos,
soberbios, y quizás en su juventud aconteciera alguna cosa de esas que siempre son motivo de
rivalidad entre los hombres....

--Alguna mujer....

--Puede ser, puede ser que eso haya sido--dijo ella con serenidad que tiraba a indiferencia.

Algo más dijeron sobre esto; pero no nos importa todavía, y siendo más urgente seguir los pasos
de la persona a quien aludían la dama y el sacerdote, vamos tras él sin pérdida de tiempo.
Algunos días le vimos entrar en la casa de D. Felicísimo Carnicero, con quien aún tenía algunas
cuentas pendientes. El agente le recibía como se recibe a todo aquel con quien se ha hecho
un negocio muy lucrativo, y haciéndole sentar a su lado dábale palmaditas en el hombro y hasta
se aventuraba a contarle cualquier sabrosa cosilla de la conspiración carlista.

Una mañana, al entrar en casa de Carnicero, encontró en la escalera a un coronel de ejército
amigo suyo. Era D. Tomás Zumalacárregui. Iba acompañado del conde de Negri, y esto le hizo
comprender que el valiente vizcaíno, resistente hasta entonces a los halagos de la gente mojigata,
se había dejado seducir al fin. Se saludaron y siguió adelante. Abriole la puerta Tablas. Al
entrar pisó al gato, que escapó mayando, y luego, a causa de la oscuridad de los destartalados
pasillos, tropezó con Doña María del Sagrario, que al choque dejó caer de las manos un enormísimo
plato de puches. Puso el grito en el cielo la señora, y al ruido alarmose tanto D. Felicísimo,
que se aventuró a salir de su nicho preguntando si había entrado en la casa un tropel de cristinos.
Salvador se deshacía en excusas, y al acercarse a la pared, manchósele la negra ropa de tal
modo que parecía un molinero. Al sacudirse, no sin comentar con algunas frases aquel rudimentario
blanqueo de las paredes, hubo de tropezar con una de las vigas que sostenían la casa y pareció
que toda la frágil fábrica se estremecía y que del techo caían pedazos de yeso, como si por
entre las maderas superiores corriesen a paso de carga belicosos ejércitos de ratones. Por
fin llegó a dar la mano a Carnicero y entraron juntos en el despacho.

--Parece que entra un temporal en mi casa--dijo el anciano colocándose en su nicho--. ¿Y qué
tal? ¿Ha encontrado usted en la escalera a Zumalacárregui y al señor conde? Buen militar y
buen diplomático, jí, jí...

--Zumalacárregui es una buena adquisición--respondió Salvador--. Tiene valor y talento.

--Pues hay otras adquisiciones mucho mejores todavía--dijo Carnicero frotándose las manos--.
¿Con que ese desdichado Gobierno del Sr. Zea ha emprendido el desarme de los voluntarios realistas?...
Sí, el fantasmón de Castroterreño en León y el mentecato de Llauder en Cataluña ponen despachos
al Gobierno diciendo que han quitado las armas a los voluntarios realistas. ¿Usted lo cree?
¿Usted cree que se pueden quitar los rayos al sol? Jí, jí. ¡Y creerá el bobillo que ha puesto
una pica en Flandes!... Yo llamo el bobillo a ese señor Zea, que es una especie de ministro
embalsamado, como el Rey ha venido a ser un Rey de papelón.

--El Gobierno se cree fuerte, Sr. Carnicero, y parece decidido a echar una losa sobre el partido
de D. Carlos. Mucho cuidado, amigo, que ahora parece que tiran a dar.

--¡Oh! por mí no temo nada--manifestó D. Felicísimo con énfasis, echándose atrás--. Pero vamos
a lo que urge. Ya sé a lo que viene usted hoy.

--A lo mismo que vine ayer.

--Y anteayer y el martes y el sábado pasado. Hoy no ha venido usted en balde. Al fin, al fin....

--¿Llegó?

--Sí, sí, el Sr. D. Carlos Navarro, nuestro valiente amigo, llegó anteanoche de su excursión
por el reino de Navarra y por Álava y Vizcaya. Es un guapo sujeto. Dice que en todo aquel religioso
país hasta las piedras tienen corazón para palpitar por D. Carlos, hasta las calabazas echarán
manos para coger fusiles. Las campanas allí, cuando tocan a misa dicen «no más masones» y el
día en que haya guerra los hombres de aquella tierra serán capaces de conquistar a la Europa
mientras las mujeres conquistan al resto de España.... Bueno, muy bueno.... ¿Con que usted
desea ver a ese señor? Le prevengo a usted que está oculto.

--No importa: sólo pienso hablarle de asuntos de familia. En el último verano estuvo en la
Granja pero no le pude ver, porque siempre se negó a recibirme. Ahora me será más fácil, porque
le escribirá usted dos palabras.

--Lo haré con mucho gusto; pero prevengo a usted también que el Sr. D. Carlos está enfermo
del hígado. Ya se ve ¡ha trabajado tanto! Es un incansable campeón de las buenas doctrinas.
Anoche se quejaba de atroces dolores, y, cosa rara en hombre tan religioso, jí, jí, más invocaba
a los demonios que a la Santísima Virgen. Si quiere usted tener segura la entrevista que desea,
se lo diremos al padre Gracián, jesuita, excelente sujeto que viene aquí algunas tardes, y
después solemos ir a tomar chocolate a casa de Maroto, adonde va también el Padre Carasa....
Pues bien, Gracián es amigo del Sr. D. Carlos, y ya hace tiempo que se ha propuesto reconciliarle
con su señora esposa.... ¡Oh! es un neblí para las reconciliaciones ese buen padre Gracián.

--Le conozco. Es un digno sacerdote que tiene las mejores intenciones del mundo, y si no consigue
hacer feliz a la humanidad toda es porque Dios no quiere.... En conclusión, entiéndanse usted
y el Padre Gracián para que yo pueda ver al Sr. Navarro y hablarle de un asunto que no es político
y sólo a él y a mí nos interesa. ¿Él vive...?

--No sé si debo decírselo a usted en este momento, antes de que el mismo Sr. D. Carlos, bellísima
persona, jí, jí... antes de que el mismo Sr. D. Carlos Navarro de licencia para que usted le
vea. Ya lo arreglaré yo. Vuélvase mañana por esta su casa.

Luego que Salvador se fue, D. Felicísimo escribió una carta en cuyo sobre, después de trazar
tres cruces, puso: A la Señora Doña María de la Paz Porreño, calle de Belén.

-III-

Las pobres señoras casi vivían en la misma estrechez que en 1822, porque las mudanzas políticas
y sociales se detenían respetuosas en la puerta de aquella casa, que era sin duda uno de los
mejores museos de fósiles que por entonces existían en España. Los períodos de tiempo en que
imperaba el absolutismo eran para el medro de la casa y abundancia de las despensas Porreñanas
lo mismo que aquellos en que prevalecía la vil canalla de los clubs. De modo que en punto a
comodidades y vituallas el agonizante marquesado habría terminado con un desastre igual al
que han sufrido formidables imperios si no viniera en su auxilio una industria que, si bien
es algo prosaica, tiene algo de noble por estar emparentada con la hospitalidad. Las dos ilustres
cuanto desgraciadas señoras aposentaban en su casa un caballero tan respetable como rico durante
las temporadas, a veces muy largas, que dicho sujeto pasaba en Madrid. El trato era excelente,
la remuneración buena, y la armonía entre el huésped y las damas tan perfecta que los tres
parecían hermanos. La familiaridad realzada por el respeto y una llaneza decorosa reinaban
en la silenciosa mansión que parecía habitada por sombras.

Bueno es decir, para que lo sepan los historiadores, que con las módicas ventajas pecuniarias
adquiridas por aquel medio honestísimo habían renovado las señoras parte del mueblaje, aunque
todas las piezas de antaño se conservaban, sostenidas por los remiendos y pulidas por el tiempo
y el aseo. ¡Cosa admirable! el reló 2 había vuelto a andar; mas por malicia del relojero o
por un misterio mecánico imposible de penetrar, andaba para atrás, y así después de las doce
daba las once, luego las diez y así sucesivamente. El cuadro de santos de la Orden Dominica
había sido restaurado por la misma Doña Paz, asistida de un hábil vejete carpintero, sacristán
y encuadernador, y emplasto por aquí, pegote por allá, con media docena de brochazos negros
en las sombras y una buena mano de barniz de coches por toda la superficie, había quedado como
el día en que vino al mundo. Por el mismo estilo se habían salvado de completa ruina las urnas
de santos y las cornucopias, que por no tener ya en sus cristales sino irregulares manchas
de azogue parecían una colección de mapas geográficos. Lo nuevo, que era muy humilde, consistía
en sillas de paja, cortinas de percal, ruedos de estera de colores; pero alegraba la casa y
su vetusto matalotaje. Por tal manera aquella imagen cadavérica de los pasados siglos se reía
en su tumba.

En la época en que nuevamente la encontramos, Doña María de la Paz se acercaba velozmente a
una vejez apoplética, marchando a ella con los pies gotosos, la cabeza temblona, los hombros
y el cuello crasos. Sus cabellos, no obstante, se conservaban negros lo mismo que el lunar,
y era que ella perseguía las canas como si fueran liberales, y no daba cuartel a ninguna, siendo
tan implacable con ellas, que cuando vinieron en tropel y no pudo arrancarlas por temor a quedarse
en el puro casco, las disfrazó vistiéndolas de luto para que nadie las conociera. Así cuando
esta operación no estaba hecha con habilidad (porque con las fuerzas había mermado la vista)
aparecían las sienes y la frente empañadas con ciertas nubes negras por encima de las cuales
brillaba la nieve remedando un admirable paisaje de invierno.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01572</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>169767</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14113</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Separáronse in
the most cordial at the Inn of the Dragon, and D. Benigno, faded and lame, he went to his home
with a speed that allowed his detestable career, while searching Salvador where to stay. A
few days later found ourselves installed in their own room he rented in Calle del Duque de
Alba, not far from D. Felicísimo Butcher, of most happy remembrance. In Madrid did not find
any new development, since it deserves the name the fury with which everyone s uprising brewing
sedition. Brazilian infantas conspired with unparalleled impudence; realistic volunteers conspired,
aided by the crowd of monks and clerics bad avenues with the idea of ??losing their omnipotence
conspired sacristanes nuns and many military family that had been made bishops, and not missing
his humorous side this national troupe, also waved towards D. Carlos many men who had been rabid
Jacobin democratic and called the three years of the second season entitled constitutional.
Before the system had shouted and now yearned for the rights of immemorial sovereignty in its
fullness.

Salvador also heard the absurdities of the vulgar, who had been led to believe that the King
would not lived and that this good man who went by car to ride was the embalmed corpse of Ferdinand
VII. For a simple mechanism, the Neapolitan, who was beside him, made him move his hands and
head in greeting. And with a straw-filled King was cheating on this heroic nation!

Saw a change of ministers based on the October 16 seemed a bit damaged of liberalism, since
the Court government wanted a bittersweet absolutely contented to and reconcile all the day through
the night, something actually more difficult to roast butter. Also could see the cancellation
of the famous codicil ceremony that mocked the Carlist and heard telling the flight Calomarde
monk dress, and the excesses of the Bishop of Leon, which, as an Indian chief arrogant and
unable to rouse the kingdom, he put his arms diocese, giving the
command of volunteers realistic to the Immaculate Conception.

Other learned and saw many things that are not for referring to the light. Their relationships
with people of various kinds will tell you everything. Pipaón, D. Felicísimo Butcher and the Marquis
de Falfán made no mystery of the apostolic plans and Genara, raging sectarian system fair means
or of the settlement, was the happiest body can imagine the thoughts
Mr. Zea beating of that ruling or seemed to rule the ship (the ship
ever!) plus close to the obstacles that the desired port.

Genara had settled in his old house, striking three years before the gathering to concurred tender
and political writers mature, but in the winter of 1833 did not open the doors of that happy
home for the first poet to come to the province charged tragedies, nor for the Italian tenor,
or for lawyers began to speakers born in classrooms with a freshness to some extent dire.
The circle was much more close friendships and greater choice, thus winning account of the house.
And here it is interesting that the lady had completely lost his love of poetry lyric (that there
is nothing durable in the world), and therefore if the prisoner had already de Cuéllar as clouds
of yesteryear. He was indeed a character little purpose for the record in their affections. It
is not known if this season we're referring to was released Genara preference or sympathy for
any of the other liberal arts, or by artillery and sailing, as stated. Lacking definite information,
we decline to say anything; that in doubtful cases is worth more to comply with the general good,
and sends the moral of the story and Christian charity.

D. Luis Fernández de Córdova, militarily brilliant, passed, when he came to Berlin to take charge
Embassy of Portugal, long hours at home Genara. Would also, though not very Frequently, D. Francisco
Javier de Burgos y Martínez de la Rosa. Regulars was a young Granada official named Narvaez,
lively genius, ceceoso, quarrelsome and expeditious. But the person most worthy of mention among
those who visited the beautiful lady was a Jesuit Imperial college, called the Father Gracian,
a man of great piety and prayer. Some said that the friendship of the good friar with Genara was going
to convert this, or is your way into the good Catholic. Others declared that they had noticed in her remnants
of bigotry; but whatever it wants, the truth is that the intentions
of Father Gracian were highly profitable, because (let's say once)
had proposed to reconcile the lady with her husband.

That Pipaón visited almost daily to his old friend and compatriot no what to say. Moreover,
His Excellency D. Juan Bragas had much sympathy with the Jesuit Gracian. Both talked seriously
stunning of the affairs of State and Church, deploring much the warmth of beliefs that hurt
both the Spanish society at the time and concluded that they should come forward with better ones
in the nation to march on the road piety, gently grazed by the ministers of the altar. As much interested
Gracian by his friends and wanted to take all possible benefits to the heart of Christian
families took to heart the realization of marriage with Micaelita
Panties, draft already Headlines in the previous book.

Salvador was accompanying Pipaón sometimes Genara house, they ate together three and when they
were Monsalud and thanks also spoke at length on the State and the Church. One day, after
talking with him, asked the Jesuit reports to the lady of the house
on that unknown friend, perhaps to see if he could reconcile with
someone, because the desire of good disciple of St. Ignatius was reconciliation.

Genara said

- If you want to win the crown of a good peacemaker, make you a friend of my husband.

- Do not you want it? - Gracian asked slyly.

- No good .... Is enmity
dating from the war with the French.

Both are stubborn, proud, and perhaps in his youth befall any of
those things that always cause for rivalry among men ....

- Some
women ....

- May be, may be that this has been - she said calmly
pulling indifference.

Anything else said about this, but we do not care yet, and still more urgent following the
steps of the person alluded lady and the priest, going after him without delay. Some days we saw
him enter the house of D. Felicísimo Butcher, who still had some scores. The agent received
as received to anyone with whom he has made a very lucrative business, and making him sit at his
side gave him pats on the shoulder and up ventured to tell any of
the tasty little thing Carlist conspiracy.

One morning, entering Butcher house, found the ladder to a colonel in army friend. Was D. Thomas Zumalacárregui.
Was accompanied by the Count de Negri, and this made him understand that the brave Biscayan
previously resistant to the blandishments of prudish people, had been won at last. They greeted
each other and moved on. He opened the door table. Al stepped into the cat, who escaped mayando,
then, because of the darkness of the dilapidated corridors, met with Dona Maria del Sagrario,
who dropped to his shock hands a enormísimo bowl of porridge. He put the fuss was mistress, and therefore
noise alarmose D. Very happy, to venture out of their niche asking if he entered the house
a crowd of Christines. Salvador melt-in excuses, and as he approached the wall, the black clothes
manchósele such So like a miller. When shaken, not without comment with some phrases that rudimentary
laundering of the walls, there were tripping over one of the beams that supported the house
and found fragile that the whole factory was shaking and falling chunks of ceiling plaster,
as if between the upper timber load step ran warring armies of mice.

For finally came to shake hands with Butcher and came together in the office.

- It seems that enters a storm in my house - said the old man standing
in your niche -.

And what such? Did you find the stairs to Zumalacárregui and the
Count?

Good military good diplomat, hee, hee ...

- Zumalacárregui is a good buy - responded Salvador -. Has value and talent.

- As there are other acquisitions much better yet - Butcher said, rubbing his hands -. How unfortunate
that the Government of Mr. Zea has undertaken the voluntary disarmament realistic? ... Yes,
the phantoms of Castroterreño in Leon and the fool to put offices
in Catalonia Llauder the Government saying they have removed the volunteers
realistic weapons.

Do you believe? Do you think you can remove the sun rays? Hee, hee. And believe the bobbin that
has a pike in Flanders!

... I call this gentleman Zea bobbin, which is a kind of minister embalmed, as the King has become
a King of newsprint.

- The Government will create strong, Mr. Butcher, and seems determined
to throw a slab on the match D. Carlos.

Beware, my friend, now seems to throw them.

- Oh! I fear nothing
for me - said D. Very happy with emphasis, leaning back -.

But we to what is urgent. I know what's coming you today.

- At the same I came yesterday.

- And the day before yesterday and Tuesday and Saturday. Today you have not been in vain. At
last, at last ....

- Did he?

- Yes, Mr. D. Carlos Navarro, our brave friend, arrived last night
of your trip for the kingdom of Navarre and Alava and Vizcaya.

It is a beautiful subject. Whoever said that religious country until the stones have a heart
to throb D. Carlos, to cast pumpkins hands to pick up guns. The bells there, when they play
at Mass say "no more Masons' and date on which the war the men of the earth will be able to conquer
Europe while women conquer the rest of Spain .... Well, very good .... How you To see that gentleman?
I warn you that is hidden.

- No matter: I only talk about family matters. Last summer was the Farm but I could not see, because
he always refused to receive me. Now I will be easier, because You will write two words.

- I will be happy, but I warn you that Mr. D. Carlos is sick liver. It is already has done so
much work! He is a tireless champion of good teachings. Last night he complained of dreadful pains,
and, strange to a man so religious, ji, ji, relied more the demons
that the Blessed Virgin.

If you want to be sure that you want to interview, we'll tell Father Gracian, a Jesuit, excellent
subject that comes here some evenings, and then we usually go to drink chocolate Maroto's house,
where the Father is Carasa .... Well, thanks a friend of Mr. D. Carlos,
and has long been proposed that reconcile him with his wife .... Oh!
is a falcon for the good Father Gracian reconciliations.

- I know.

It is a worthy priest who has the best intentions, and if it fails bring happiness to all mankind
because God does not want .... In conclusion, you entiéndanse and
Father Gracian for me to see Mr. Navarro and talk about an issue that
is not political and only he and I are both interested.

Does he live ...?

- Do not know if I should tell you right now,
before the same Mr. D. Carlos, beautiful person, hee, hee ... before
the same Mr. D. Carlos Navarro to leave for you to display.

And I'll fix it. Come back tomorrow for this home.

After Salvador was, D. Felicísimo wrote a letter in which over after draw three crosses, put
it: A Lady Doña Maria de la Paz Porreno, street of Bethlehem.

-III-

The poor lady almost lived in the same narrowness in 1822, because the removal policies friendly social
and stopped at the door of the house, which was without doubt one of the best museums of fossils
that then existed in Spain. The periods of time prevailing absolutism were to thrive in the house
and plenty of cupboards Porreñanas the same as those prevailing in the vile villain of the
clubs. So in point facilities and supplies the dying Marquis would have ended a disaster like
the empires have been formidable if not come to his aid an industry
that, while is somewhat prosaic, there is something noble for being
associated with hospitality.

The two illustrious As unfortunate ladies chamber to house a respectable gentleman so rich in
seasons, sometimes very long, that the subject spent in Madrid. The treatment was excellent,
good pay, and harmony between the host and the ladies so perfect that the three looked like brothers.
Familiarity enhanced by respect and a dignified simplicity reigned in the silent house seemed
inhabited by shadows.

Well, that is, to what historians know that with modest financial benefits honestísimo acquired
by that environment had renewed the ladies of the unfurnished, although All antiques are preserved,
supported by patches and polished by the time and toilet. Wonderful thing! the hourglass 2 had
returned to walking, but from malice or watchmaker by a mechanical mystery impossible to penetrate,
walked back, and well after midnight was eleven, then ten and so on. Table of Saints of the
Order Dominica had been restored by the same Doña Paz, old man assisted by a skilled carpenter,
clerk and binder, and filler here, goop there, with half a dozen black brushstrokes in the
shadows and a good coat of varnish car across the surface, had been as the day he was born. For
the same style had been saved from complete ruin the polls saints
and the cornucopias, which no longer have their windows but irregular
spots quicksilver seemed a collection of maps.

What is new, it was very humble, was in straw chairs, gingham curtains, hems of mat colors,
but glad the house and his ancient matalotaje. In such a way that ghastly image of yore laughed
in his grave.

By the time we find that again, Doña María de la Paz was coming swiftly apoplectic old age, going to
her with gouty feet, shaky head, shoulders crass and neck. Her hair, however, blacks were kept
the same as the lunar and was pursuing her white hair like liberals, and gave no quarter to
none, being as ruthless with them when they came in droves and could not pull them up for fear
of becoming in the pure hull, outfitting dressed in black so that
no one knew. So when this operation was not done with skill (because
the forces had diminished the view) appeared the temples and forehead
marred with some dark clouds over them Snow glistened mimicking a
wonderful winter landscape</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>