<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04822</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>266713</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>15529</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Mi madre,
Dios la tenga en el cielo, me abrazaba y se echaba a llorar: «Linilla,--me decía--Dios nos
dará pan; vamos a pedírselo». Y me ponía de rodillas, y me hacía rezar, con las manos juntas
sobre el pecho, como un angelito de esos que vimos el otro día en la capilla de San Antonio.

Mi padre era militar, andaba siempre en la guerra, o en conspiraciones, y por eso sus enemigos,
los del partido contrario, le perseguían de muerte.

No lo ví más que una sola vez. Habían triunfado los suyos y vino a vernos. Trajo mucho dinero,
y nos compró ropa y muebles, y a mí dulces y juguetes, y un rorro muy lindo, de cabellos rubios
y ojos azules, que decía «papá y mamá». No he olvidado a mi padre: era un caballero alto, de
ojos muy hermosos, con unos bigotes muy retorcidos. Me abrazaba cariñosamente, me besaba, y
alzándome exclamaba:--«¡Lina! ¡Linilla! ¿Quién es mi encanto? ¿Quién es mi presea? ¿A quién
quiero yo mucho, mucho... ¡mu... cho!»

Pero un día se fué a la guerra.... ¡Siempre la guerra y las revoluciones! Se fué muy de mañana,
e iban con él oficiales y soldados. Salimos a decirle adiós. Me tomó en brazos, me besó los
ojos, abrazó a mi madre, luego montó a caballo, y nos dijo: «¡Hasta la vista!...» y partió.
No volvimos a verle. Tres años duró esa guerra. El estaba en no sé qué Estado lejano, y nosotras
nos quedamos esperando su vuelta.

Un día recibió mi madre una carta. Mi padre nos llamaba. Fué preciso obedecerle, y después
de vender cuanto teníamos, muebles, ropa, todo lo que había en la casa, emprendimos el viaje,
solitas, en un carruaje que daba muchos tumbos y que hacía mucho ruido al rodar en los empedrados.
Caminábamos de día y de noche, y sólo nos deteníamos en las posadas para dormir y descansar
unas cuantas horas. Antes de amanecer, otra vez al carruaje, otra vez a los caminos desiertos,
temerosas de los ladrones. Solíamos pasar por algunos pueblos. El coche se detenía, bajábamos
para ir a la fonda, comíamos, y vuelta a caminar. Un día mi mamá se quejó diciendo que le dolía
la cabeza. Tenía fiebre, y fué preciso quedarnos en un pueblo, en un mesón. Dormía yo con ella,
y recuerdo que ardía en calentura, que su cuerpo quemaba como una brasa. Despertaba yo a media
noche, y decía yo: ¡Mamá! ¡Mamá! Y no contestaba, permanecía como muerta. Una vez, viendo que
no me respondía, me eché a llorar.... Entonces mi mamá volvió en sí, y me arropó diciendo cosas
que yo no entendí, cosas muy raras. Papá me ha contado que mi madre tenía tifo. La mesonera
llamó al señor cura, y cuando éste llegó la enferma había perdido el conocimiento. Vino el
médico del pueblo y declaró que ya era tarde, ¡que la agonía estaba próxima!

--No vivirá una hora...--dijo.--Padre, ¡póngale los óleos!

--Esta criatura no debe estar aquí...--respondió el sacerdote, poniéndose la estola--¡que la
lleven a mi casa!

Yo no quería separarme de allí. Resistí, lloré, sollocé... pero ¡en vano! Era yo una chiquitina
de siete años, y, sin embargo, comprendí lo que pasaba: que no volvería a ver a mi madre. Lloraba
yo y mis lágrimas eran lágrimas de inmenso dolor. Mi madre se moría; no había de verme más.
Me llevaron a la casa cural. Allí nada me divertía ni me consolaba; pasé el día sin comer,
huraña, renuente a las atenciones del padre y a los obsequios de una anciana, ama de gobierno
de aquella modesta casa. Me acurruqué en el sofá, y allí me rindió el sueño, y de allí me llevaron
a la cama. A media noche desperté, llorando, llamando a mi mamá. La anciana vino a verme, me
arropó y se estuvo acariciándome hasta que me quedé dormida. A la mañana, apenas abrí los ojos,
pregunté por mi madre. Me dijeron que estaba en el cielo. La anciana me lavó, me vistió, y
me dió el desayuno. Para distraerme me llevaron a la sala, y me dieron juguetes, muñecos de
nacimiento, pastores y pastoras, cabras, ovejas, una casita de cartón, un molino, con su rueda
que daba vueltas movida por un chorro de arena.

Cuando el sacerdote volvió de la iglesia me sentó a su lado y me hizo muchas preguntas: «¿Cómo
te llamas? ¿Cómo se llama tu mamá? ¿Tienes papá?» No sé lo que respondí.... El señor cura dice
que de mis respuestas sacó lo bastante para saber quiénes éramos, quién era mi padre. Encontró
en el baúl cartas y papeles, documentos que le dieron noticias acerca de la residencia de mi
padre. Le escribió inmediatamente, dándole la fatal noticia; pero la carta no llegó a sus manos.
Volvió a escribir y no recibió contestación. El autor de mis días había muerto también. Pereció
en una escaramuza. Su cadáver fué arrastrado y paseado como trofeo de gloria, al son de músicas
victoriosas, por una soldadesca ebria que celebraba un triunfo inesperado. El señor cura se
dirigió entonces a unos parientes míos, los cuales se negaron a recogerme... «No queremos niños»;--le
contestaron--«no queremos huérfanos; son ingratos, tarde o temprano dan el pago».

Me han contado que cuando el santo anciano recibió la carta de mis parientes, exclamó: «¡Corazones
de piedra! ¡Dios los perdone? ¿El trajo esta niña a mi casa? Pues mía es». Luego me llamó,
y tomando entre sus manos mi cabeza, me dijo dulcemente: «Muñeca: desde ahora yo soy tu padre;
¡yo soy tu papá!» «Papá le llamo desde entonces; desde entonces me llama «muñeca». Algunas
veces me dice «Linilla», como mis padres me decían.

Angelina había terminado el ramillete, un ramillete de violetas, y me le acercó para que aspirara
yo el suave aroma de las flores.

--¿Linilla? ¿Linilla te decían? ¡Pues Linilla he de llamarte yo! Siga el cuento....

--¿Cuento? ¡Historia de dolor!

--Prosigue.

--Así, de ese modo, fui a la casa del padre; padre ha sido para mí, y muy tierno y cariñoso.
Lo demás ya lo sabes; te lo habrán dicho tus tías....

--¿Y esa es la triste historia de tu vida? ¿A qué decirme, Linilla mía,--repuse--todo esto
que me apena y aflige? ¿A qué poner en duda mi cariño, que en duda le has puesto cuando me
desgarrabas el corazón, diciendo que no eras digna de mí? ¿Indigna de mi amor, Linilla mía?
¿Por qué? ¿Porque has sido desgraciada, porque eres huérfana? Al contrario, niña mía: ¿qué
mayores motivos para ser amada?

Angelina se quedó cabizbaja, como atormentada por un triste presentimiento, como temerosa de
decir algo que la avergonzaba.

--¡Habla!... ¡Contéstame!...

La huérfana callaba, baja la frente, mientras abría con la punta de los dedos el apretado seno
de una rosa pálida.

--Linilla... ¡no seas cruel!

Suspiró penosamente, sacudió la cabeza para echar hacia atrás una trenza que le caía sobre
el hombro, y murmuró bajito, bajito, tal vez deseosa de no ser oída:

--Aun no he dicho todo... y debo decirlo. ¡Oyeme, por piedad! No quiero decirlo... pero el
corazón me grita: ¡Habla! ¡Habla!

--Pues, dímelo!

--Sí, Rodolfo: no soy digna de tí. Tú mismo lo has dicho muchas veces, delante de tus tías,
delante de mí.

--¿Yo, Angelina?

--Sí.

--¿Yo?

--Sí, y... ¡cómo me has hecho llorar!

--¿Yo, Angelina?

--Muchas veces. ¡Para qué viniste! ¡Para qué te conocí! Rodolfo: ¿porqué me amas? ¿Porqué te
amo yo? ¡Qué de lágrimas me cuesta tu cariño! Mira: si no merezco que me ames, olvídame, olvídame;
me iré de aquí, llorando, sí, llorando... pero me iré, a la Sierra, a cualquiera parte....
Tú puedes ser feliz. Apenas empiezas a vivir.... El corazón humano es mudable; llegará día
en que me olvides.... ¡Amarás a otra, y serás amado, y serás dichoso!

--Angelina:--repliqué suplicante--¿a qué viene todo eso?

Oyeme: este pobre corazón mío, no había amado nunca: llegué a esta casa y me hablaron de tí;
me dijeron que eras huérfano, huérfano como yo, y me fuiste simpático; y me dijeron que eras
bueno, muy bueno, y me interesé por tí; leí tus cartas, vi tu retrato, y hallé que eras como
yo te había soñado; viniste, y me estremecí al oir tu voz; me hablaste... ¿te acuerdas?...
y se ahogó la voz en mi garganta, y palpitó mi corazón trémulo de amor. Después... ¡a qué decirlo!...
Me dijiste: «te amo», y quise callar, y no pude; y cuando intente matar tu cariño con una palabra
desdeñosa, se abrieron mis labios, y dijeron: «¡yo también te amo!»

--Sí, te amo, Angelina!...

--Oyeme. Me has lastimado el corazón; has entristecido mi alma.... Pero te perdono, te perdono,
porque lo has hecho sin saber lo que hacías.... Estoy segura de ello.

--¿Cuándo y cómo?

--Dijiste una vez... y lo has repetido muchas veces... «jamás me casaré con quien no sea digna
de mí; y no es digna de ser esposa de un hombre honrado aquélla cuyos padres...» Lo diré de
una vez.... La unión de los míos no tuvo la bendición del Cielo.

--¡Perdón!...--murmuré.

La huérfana calló, y de sus ojos húmedos se desprendieron dos lágrimas que cayeron en las violetas
como dos gotas de rocío.

--¡Perdón!--repetí, estrechando a la joven entre mis brazos, y atrayendo su gallarda cabeza.--¡Perdóname,
Linilla!

Y sobrecogida de espanto me apartó dulcemente.

--¡Cómo no perdonarte! Si te amo con toda el alma.... Ya sabes quien soy.... En mi vida no
hay nada que me avergüence... pero en los míos.... ¡Ya lo sabes todo!... Te hice sufrir, ¿verdad?
Sí, porque estás llorando.... ¡Perdóname!... Era preciso.. Más tarde habrías dicho que yo te
había engañado.

Tomé las manos de la joven y las llevé a mis labios. Ella, sonriendo, las retiró, diciéndome
graciosamente:

--«Y el cuento que entró por un caminito de plata salió por un caminito de oro».

XXIX

La revelación de Angelina me dejó triste, abatido, avergonzado. Entonces me dí cuenta de ciertas
melancolías de la niña, cuando yo hablaba de bodas y noviazgos. Me propuse calmar el ánimo
de la doncella, quitarle, en cuanto fuera posible, la mala impresión que mi ligereza y mis
imprudentes palabras le habían causado, y lo conseguí. Le hice ver que mi poca reflexión no
debía ser motivo de disgusto, y puse todo mi empeño en que comprendiera que cuanto yo había
dicho no era más que la repetición de opiniones leídas en no sé qué libro, oídas a no sé qué
personas. Nunca pensé que hería a Angelina en lo más vivo; jamás pude imaginar que la pobre
niña supiese la historia de su infeliz madre. Yo también la ignoraba, por culpa de mi tía,
quien siempre se rehusó a contarme cómo y de qué manera fué Angelina a la casa del P. Herrera,
del cariñoso anciano, del santo sacerdote que veía, y con razón, en su hija adoptiva, un ángel
bajado del cielo para alegrar las tristes horas de su vida rural. Y no me costó poco trabajo
conseguir que mi amada olvidara mis dichos inoportunos y crueles. Fallos, juicios y opiniones
oímos en el mundo que nos parecen atinados y justos, y los acogemos ligeramente, los repetimos,
los hacemos nuestros, y suele suceder que más tarde caemos en la cuenta de que hemos repetido
una tontería.

Linilla--así la llamé en lo de adelante--no volvió a tocar el punto, y siempre se mostró conmigo
afable y satisfecha. No salía yo a la calle más que a las horas de trabajo, y al volver del
despacho me pasaba las horas al lado de la huérfana, cada día más enamorado de ella. Una o
dos veces, en toda la temporada, fui a las rifas de Navidad, que congregaban todas las noches
en la Plaza a los pacíficos habitantes de Villaverde. Ni juegos ni músicas me eran gratos;
no paraba yo atención en la hermosura de mis paisanas, ni en la elegancia y gallardía de Gabriela.

--¿No vas a las rifas?--decían mis tías.

--No me divierto; prefiero quedarme en casa, leyendo o conversando con ustedes.

--¡No pareces muchacho, Rorró!...--replicaba la enferma.

--Todos los jóvenes de tu edad se perecen por ir allá;--decía tía Pepa--sólo tú, como un viejo
chocho, te estás entre las cuatro paredes.

Allí estaba yo bien, cerca de Angelina. No me cansaba de mirarla: cada palabra suya era para
mí un poema. Era yo muy dichoso. ¡Qué mayor ventura que no separarme de su lado!

Uno de los boticarios puso a mi disposición todos sus libros, doscientos o trescientos volúmenes
de versos y novelas. Entonces leí mucho, en voz alta, mientras trabajaban Angelina y mi tía;
entonces hice muchos versos, muchos, diariamente. Angelina era en ellos celebrada con un calor
y un entusiasmo tales que la buena niña se sonrojaba al oírlos.

--No digas esas cosas, Rorró,--solía decirme,--porque no las creo. ¡Si me pintas hermosa y
gallarda como una virgen de Murillo! Dime en prosa, aquí, hablándome, que me amas mucho, mucho,
y me tendrás contenta, satisfecha y feliz.

Angelina no era hermosa como una virgen de Murillo, pero sí lo era como alguna de Rafael, como
la Madona de la silla. No puedo ver el famoso cuadro sin recordar a la doncella. Idéntico el
óvalo del rostro, y la sonrisa, y la mirada, y los labios dulcemente expresivos.

A las veces, después de pasar en mi cuarto largas horas, salía yo con el papel en la mano,
aprovechando el momento en que Angelina se quedaba sola.

--¿Versos? ¿Versos para mí, no es eso?

Y me los arrebataba; los leía en voz baja, sonriente y ruborosa, mientras yo, colocado a su
espalda, la iba siguiendo en la lectura.

--¡Bonitos!--exclamaba.--Pero todas estas cosas me gustan más cuando me las dices sin pensarlas.
No sé por qué, pero los versos me parecen siempre ¡graciosas mentiras!

Doblaba la hoja, se la guardaba, y me señalaba un asiento:

--Aquí, cerca de mí. Dime, Rorró: ¿me quieres así, tanto como dices, como yo te quiero a tí?

Comenzaba la conversación, y seguía, y pasaba el tiempo, y no sentíamos correr las horas, felices,
dichosos, con la dicha de los que aman y son amados.

Nos dio por la jardinería. Preparamos los cuadros y sembramos rosales, claveles, lirios, azucenas,
que nos prometían para la próxima primavera abundantes flores. Plantamos en torno de la fuente
la flor preferida, la encantadora florecilla azul, la dulce myosotis, tan querida de los enamorados.

¡Qué cuidado con nuestras plantas! ¡Qué deseo de que florecieran pronto! Dividimos los arriates
en dos partes. Linilla sembraba una, yo la otra.

--¿Dónde brotará la primera flor? ¿En mis cuadros o en los tuyos?

--En los míos, porque ¡yo te quiero más que tú a mí!

--No; en los tuyos no será porque no me quieres como yo te quiero....

--Ya lo verás.

--Ya lo veremos.

El amor y la dicha de ser amada embellecían a la joven. Nunca más hermosa. Su pálido rostro
tomó suaves tintas de rosa; sus labios, antes descoloridos, se encendieron, y sus negros y
brillantes ojos fulguraban, húmedos y alegres. Ella, siempre tan modesta y enemiga de galas,
se tornó presumidilla. Peinaba graciosamente sus cabellos, y solía adornarse con alguna flor;
de ordinario con entreabierto capullo de rosa, purpúreo o blanco, que hacía parecer más intensa
la negrura de aquel pelo sedoso, negro como las alas del cuervo. Todas las noches, al despedirnos,
le decía yo:

--Linilla: esa flor....

Angelina desprendía de sus cabellos la deseada flor, y me la ofrecía por alto, como se ofrece
a un niño el incitante fruto acabado de cortar.

Yo me fingía enfadado:

--¿Así, señorita?

--¡Así, caballero!

--No; como tú sabes....

Linilla sonreía, besaba la flor, y me la daba. ¡Inolvidables besos! ¡Dulces besos recogidos
en la corola de una rosa!

XXX

Tuvimos una fiesta de Navidad muy alegre, como nadie se la esperaba. Andrés vino y dijo a mis tías:

--Señoras; es preciso que tengamos fiesta. En años pasados la Noche Buena estuvo para nosotros
muy triste.... Ahora no ha de ser así, no, señor, porque quiero que el amito esté contento.
Todo corre de mi cuenta. A ustedes les tocará lo más penoso, disponerla, y hacer los buñuelos.
¡Sin buñuelos no hay Noche Buena! ¡Allá usted, Angelina, usted que se pinta para todo eso!
Pondremos la mesa en la sala, y usted, doña Carmelita, cenará con nosotros. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10983</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>135588</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14228</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> My mother God
rest in heaven, hugged me and she started to mourn: "Linilla, - I said - God give bread, we
will ask him. " And I got on his knees, and I was praying with folded hands on his chest, like
an angel of those who saw the other day in the chapel of San Antonio.

My father was a soldier, he was always in war, or conspiracies, and
therefore his enemies, those of the opposite party of death haunted
him.

I did not see more than once. They had won their own and came to us. He brought a lot of money
and we bought clothes and furniture, and me sweets and toys, and a Rorro very cute, blond and
blue eyes, saying, "Papa and Mama." I have not forgotten my father was a tall, of beautiful
eyes, very twisted his mustache.

Hugged me warmly, kissed me, and Lina exclaimed :--«¡ lifting me! Linilla! Who is my charm? Who
is my medal? Who I want a long, long ... Mu ... cho! "

But one day he went to war .... Always the war and revolutions! It was early morning, and he went
with officers and soldiers.

We went to say goodbye. I picked her up, kissed me eyes, hugged my mother, then mounted his
horse, and said, 'Hasta la vista !...» and left. We did not see him. That war lasted three years.
He was not to know what state away, and we we wait your turn.

One day my mother received a letter. My father called us. Was obliged to obey, and then As we sell,
furniture, clothes, everything in the house, we started our journey soloists, in a carriage that
gave many bumps and it was very noise running down the pavements. We walked day and night, and
we only stopped at the inn to sleep and rest a few hours. Before dawn, the carriage again, again
empty roads, afraid of thieves. We used to go through some towns. The car stopped, got off to
go to the restaurant, ate, and from walking. One day my mom complained that it hurt head. He
had fever and was obliged to stay in a village in an inn. I slept with her, I remember burning
with fever, his body burned like an ember. I woke up at half night, and I said: Mom! Mom! And
did not answer, remained dead. Once, seeing did not respond, I began to mourn .... Then my
mom came to, and tucked me saying things I did not understand, very
strange things.

Dad told me that my mother had typhus.

The landlady called the Father, and when he arrived the patient had lost consciousness. Came
town doctor and stated that it was too late, that the agony was close!

-
No live one hour .-- ...-- said Father, Put the oils!

- This creature
should not be here ...-- replied the priest, placing the stole - that
take my home!

I did not want to part with there. I resisted, I cried, I wept ... but in vain! I was a little
one seven years, and yet, I realized what was happening: he would never see my mother. Crying
I and my tears were tears of great pain. My mother was dying, was not to see me anymore. They
took me to the rectory. There is nothing I amused or comforted me, I spent the day without eating,
sullen, unwilling to the attention of the father and the gift of an old woman, housekeeper of
this modest home. I snuggled on the couch, where I gave up the dream, and then took me to bed.
At midnight I woke up, crying, calling my mom. The old woman came to see me, me clothed and
was stroking until I fell asleep. In the morning, when I opened my eyes my mother asked. I
said I was in heaven. The old woman washed me, clothed me, and gave me breakfast. To distract
me to the room and gave me toys, dolls birth, pastors, goats, sheep,
a cardboard house, a mill with its wheel that spinning move by blasting.

When the priest returned from the church sat down beside me and asked me many questions, "How your
name? How's your mom? Do you Dad? "I do not know what I said .... The priest says that my answers
got enough to know who we were, who my father. Found in the trunk of letters and papers, documents
which gave news about the residence of my father. He wrote immediately, giving the fatal news,
but the letter did not come into his hands. Wrote again and received no response. The author of
my life had died too. Perished in a skirmish. His body was dragged and paraded as a trophy
of glory, the sound of music victorious, by a drunken soldiers celebrating an unexpected victory. The
priest is then went to my relatives, who refused to pick ... "We
do not want children", - he replied - "do not want orphans are ungrateful,
they eventually pay."

I am told that when the holy old man received a letter from my relatives, said: 'Hearts stone!
God forgive? "He brought this child into my home? Well mine is. " Then I called, and taking
my head between her hands, she said sweetly, "Doll: from now on I
am your father I am your father!

"" Dad called him since then and since then he calls me "doll." Some Sometimes I say "Linilla" as
my parents told me.

Angelina was over the bouquet, a bouquet of violets, and I approached
him to aspire I am the soft scent of flowers.

- Linilla?

Linilla "you say?

Linilla Well I call you me! Follow the story ....

- Do I? History of pain!

- Go on.

- So that way, I went to the house of the father, father has been
for me, and very tender and loving.

Otherwise you know, what you have told your aunt ....

- And that is the sad story of your life?

What say, Linilla mine - I said - all I grieve and grieve? Why question my love, that you have
put in doubt when I breaks the heart, saying you were not worthy
of me?

"Unworthy of my love, my Linilla?

Why? Why have you been unhappy because you are an orphan? On the contrary, my dear, what more
reason to be loved?

Angelina remained downcast as racked with a sad foreboding, as if
afraid say something that embarrassed her.

- Speak!

... Answer me!

...

The orphan was silent, low forehead, opening with the tip of the fingers
within the tight a pale pink.

- Linilla ... Do not be cruel!

Painfully sighed, shook his head to throw back a braid that fell over
shoulder, and whispered softly, softly, perhaps anxious not to be
heard:

- I have not said everything ... and I must say.

Listen, for pity's sake!

I do not want to say ... but My heart cries, Speak! Speak!

- Well, tell me!

- Yes, Rodolfo: I am not worthy of you.

You yourself have said many times in front of your aunts, before
me.

- Me, Angelina?

- Yes.

- Me?

- Yes, y. ..

How you made me mourn!

- Me, Angelina?

- Many times. Did you come! To what you knew! Rodolfo: Why do I love? Why you I love? What cost me tear
your love! Look, if you do not deserve to love me, forget, forget; I go from here, crying, yes, crying
... but I'll go to the Sierra, to any part .... You can be happy.

Just start living .... The human heart is fickle, the day will come
when I forget .... Love another and be loved, and be happy!

- Angelina
- I said pleading - what is that?

Listen: this poor heart of mine, had not ever loved: I came to this
house and told me about you; I said you were an orphan, an orphan
like me and you were nice to me, and I said you were good, very good,
and I became interested in you, I read your letters, I saw your picture,
and found that they were like I dreamed you, you came, and I shuddered
to hear your voice, I spoke ... Remember?

... and drowned the voice in my throat and my heart fluttered trembling with love. Then ... What
to say! ... You said: "I love you, and I wanted to be quiet, and I could not, and when you
try to kill your baby with a word disdainful, opened my lips and
said: "I love you too!"

- Yes, I love you, Angelina!

...

- Listen.

I have hurt the heart, has saddened my soul .... But I forgive, I forgive you, because you did not know what
you did .... I'm sure.

- When and how?

- You said once ... and
I've repeated many times ... "I will never marry anyone who is not
worthy me, and not worthy of being the wife of an honest man whose
parents it ... "I'll say once .... The union of mine did not have
the blessing of Heaven.

- Sorry !...-- muttered.

The orphan was silent, his eyes moist and fell off two tears that fell in the violet as two drops
of dew.

- Sorry! - Repeated, shaking the girl in my arms, and drawing his gallant head .-- Forgive Linilla!

And
awed me gently away.

- Do not forgive!

If I love you with all my heart .... You know who I am .... In my
life There is nothing I'm ashamed ... but in mine .... You know everything!

... I made you suffer, right?

Yes, because you're crying .... Forgive me ... It was necessary .. Later I would have told you had
cheated.

I took the girl's hands and took them to my lips. She smiled, withdrew them, saying gracefully:

-
"And the story that came by a little silver left by a little gold."

XXIX

Angelina's revelation left me sad, depressed, embarrassed. Then I realized certain melancholy of
the girl, when I talked about weddings and engagements. I set the mood calm of the girl, take,
as far as possible, the bad impression that my light and my careless words had caused, and got
it. I showed him my little thought not should be a source of disgust, and put all my effort that
I had understood that the that was just the repetition of opinions read in I do not know which
book they heard not know what people. I never thought Angelina wounded to the quick, I could
never imagine that poor she knew the story of his unhappy mother.

I also knew, because of my aunt who always refused to tell me how and how Angelina was the home
of P. Herrera, loving the old, the holy priest that I saw, and rightly, in his adopted daughter,
an angel down from heaven to brighten the dreary hours of rural life. And I had little difficulty
get my beloved forget my sayings inappropriate and cruel. Rulings, judgments and opinions hear
in the world that seem thoughtful and fair, and we slightly, repeat, we make our own, and
it often happens that later we realize that we have repeated nonsense.

Linilla - so I called in front - did not touch the point, and always
showed me friendly and happy.

I did not go out to the street rather than work hours, and returning
the I spent my office hours next to the orphan, more and more in love
with her.

One or twice all season, went to the Christmas raffle, which gathered every night Plaza on the
peaceful inhabitants of Villaverde.

Games or music or me were pleasant; I care not stop the beauty of my countrymen, or the elegance
and grace of Gabriela.

- Do not go to the sweepstakes? - Said my aunt.

- Do not I have fun, I prefer to stay home, reading or chatting with
you.

- You do not look young, the patient replied !...-- Rorra.

-
All young people your age die to go there, - said Aunt Pepa - only
you, as an old pussy, you're within the four walls.

While I was there, about Angelina.

I never tired of looking at it: every word was to me a poem. I was very happy. What greater chance
that separate me from your side!

One of the pharmacists put at my disposal all his books, two or three hundred volumes of poems
and novels.

Then I read a lot, loudly, while my aunt worked and Angelina; then
I made many verses, many daily.

Angelina was celebrated with a heat them and enthusiasm such that the good girl blushed to
hear them.

- Do not say those things, Rorra, - used to tell me - because I do
not think so.

If you paint me beautiful graceful as a Murillo virgin!

Tell prose, here, talking to me, love me long, long, and I have happy,
satisfied and happy.

Angelina was not beautiful like a virgin Murillo, but it was like one of Raphael, as the Madonna of
the chair. I can not see the famous picture without remembering the maid. The identical oval face,
and smile, and eyes, and lips sweetly expressive.

At times, after spending long hours in my room, I went out with paper
in hand, seizing the moment when Angelina was left alone.

- Verses?

"Verses for me, is not it?

And I will take them away, read them quietly, smiling and blushing,
while I placed her back, was following in reading.

- Nice! - Exclaimed
.-- But all these things I enjoy most when I say them without thinking.

I do not know why, but the lines always seem to me silly lies!

Fold the paper, it is kept, and I pointed to a seat:

- Here, near me. Tell me, Rorra: do you love me so much as say, as I love to you?

Began the conversation, and on, and spent the time and did not feel run times, happy, blessed with
the happiness of those who love and are loved.

We gave for gardening.

Prepare the tables and planted roses, carnations, lilies, lilies,
we promised for next spring full of flowers.

Planted around the source favorite flower, the lovely blue flower,
the sweet myosotis, so beloved of lovers.

What care with our plants! What I want to bloom soon! We divide the beds into two parts. Linilla
planted one, I the other.

- Where spring the first flower?

"In my pictures or yours?

- In mine, because I love you more than
you to me!

- No, not in yours because I want as I love ....

- You'll
see.

- We'll see.

The love and joy of being loved graced the young. Never more beautiful. Her pale face took soft
pink ink, her lips before discolored, burned, and his black and bright eyes gleamed, wet and happy.
She always so modest and enemy of galas, became presumidilla. Graciously combed her hair and
adorned with a flower used; usually with half-open rosebud, purple
or white, which made it seem more intense the blackness of that silky
hair, black as raven wings. Every evening, at parting, I told him:

-
Linilla: the flower ....

Angelina flowed from her hair the desired
flower, and I offered it for granted, as offered inciting a child
to finish cutting fruit.

I pretended anger:

- So, Miss?

- So, sir!

-
No, as you know ....

Linilla smiled, kissed the flower and gave it
to me. Inolvidables besos! Sweet kisses collected in the corolla of
a rose!

XXX

We had a very merry Christmas party, and nobody expected
it. Andrew came and told my aunts:

- Ladies, we must have party.
In years past Christmas Eve was for us very sad .... Now there must
be so, no, sir, because I want the little master is happy. Everything
runs in my account. To you I will be playing the most painful, arrange
it, and make the donuts. No donuts there Eve! There you, Angelina,
you are painting for all that! We will table in the room, and you,
Mrs. Carmelita, dine with us</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>