<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08503</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>122822</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24977</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

APOLO-BAMBA[1].

El pueblo de Apolo, hoy dia capital de la provincia, fué fundado á mediados del siglo anterior
por los misioneros franciscanos, que reunieron en aquel punto á los indígenas de la nacion
apolista, y formaron una mision, la cual habiendo sido adherida en el año de 1800 á las otras
poblaciones comarcanas, vino á componer la provincia de Caupolican.

Apolo se halla situado en el centro de una llanura ligeramente ondeada y cubierta de plantas
gramineas. Esta llanura, limitada al sud por unas montañas á las que sus valles y los recodos
que estos forman, dan un aspecto muy pintoresco, tiene como de cinco á seis leguas de ancho,
y su largo se estiende de norte á sud, como de doce á catorce, figurando un cuadrilongo. Al
este se levanta, semejante á una pared, una grande montaña que se dirige de norte á sud, y
á la que por su mucha elevacion se ha denominado Altuncama. Hay al oeste una colina baja, interpuesta
entre las llanuras de Apolo y las de Santa-Catalina que vienen á ocupar la parte oeste y sudoeste.
Este último valle horizontal, que tiene doce leguas de largo sobre cinco de ancho, está cubierto
en parte de pajonales, y lo atraviesa el rio Tupili, cuyas orillas se ven adornadas de anchurosos
y espesos bosques, los cuales contrastan de tal manera con lo raso del resto, que parecen haber
sido plantados por la mano del hombre.

El pueblo está formado de tres grupos distintos. El primero se encuentra situado ántes de pasar
el rio, y se compone de casas diseminadas: en este grupo, que se llama la parcialidad de la
Concepcion, es donde se hallan establecidos los mercaderes de toda especie de frutos, y á quienes
los habitantes nativos dan en su lengua particular el nombre de mataguas, es decir, forasteros.
El segundo grupo, colocado en el centro y sobre un ligero promontorio de greda rojiza, está
de la otra parte del rio, y encierra la casa consistorial, la iglesia parroquial y el convento
de los franciscanos, cuya fachada que mira al este, da sobre una plaza en la que los lados
norte y sud se componen de varios edificios, y la parte del este, frontera al convento, de
una serie de casas habitadas por los indígenas: estas casas, cada una de las cuales tiene una
sola puerta y como de quince á veinte varas de largo, se hallan colocadas sobre la colina en
forma de anfiteatro, de suerte que desde el convento se descubre todo cuanto pasa en el interior
de ellas. Tal era el modo como las habian dispuesto los franciscanos, con el objeto de estar
á la mira de todos los pasos de los indios, y de poder velar sobre sus acciones. En aquel entónces,
los comerciantes que venian á la provincia, estaban obligados á hospedarse en el convento para
efectuar sus trueques en presencia de los religiosos. Un arroyo separa esta segunda parte,
del tercer grupo que se encuentra situado sobre el camino de Aten, y dispuesto en el mismo
órden que acabamos de ver en aquella.

La temperatura de Apolo es agradable y sana; sin embargo, como sus llanuras dejan libre acceso
á todos los vientos, el aire viene á ser mas seco que en Santa-Cruz. Allí se cultivan los mismos
frutos que en los otros distritos; pero la coca es el solo objeto importante del comercio de
trueque. Tambien hay en Apolo como de dos mil á dos mil quinientas cabezas de ganado, y si
fuesen sus habitantes algo mas hacendosos y prolijos, tendrian ciertamente todo género de bienes
en abundancia. Un solo hecho bastará para justificar este aserto, por lo tocante á la gran
procreacion de los ganados. Un indio llamado Pedro Chambi, habia reunido con el producto de
su industria unas quince vacas, á cuya cria dedicándose luego con esmero, llegó de tal modo
á multiplicarlas, que fuera del gran número vendido por él mientras vivió, aun dejó en 1828,
al terminar sus dias, como mil cabezas. Se ve pues que con algun cuidado las llanadas y las
colinas podrian fácilmente cubrirse de ganados, tanto vacunos como lanares, y aun acaso de
caballares. Seria igualmente posible que las montañas de Altuncama, en vista de su elevacion,
produjesen la viña y las papas.

La estraccion de la cascarilla ha modificado algun tanto la manera de ser de estos habitantes,
enseñándoles á estimar el valor positivo de las cosas, y dándoles una idea del dinero. Por
el comercio de este específico han llegado á conocer tambien otros muchos objetos, que les
eran enteramente ignorados, y con cuya posesion disfrutan hoy en dia de mayores comodidades.
Si hubiese continuado este comercio, no hay la menor duda que los habitantes de Apolo estarian
ya bastante avanzados en el camino de una civilizacion, contra la que luchan incesantemente
aquellos que se han constituido en directores de estos indígenas, bajo el necio pretesto de
que la relacion comercial con los estrangeros corrompe sus costumbres. Aunque pueda esto verificarse
algunas veces, no por eso se han de negar las inmensas ventajas que necesariamente debe traer
consigo la frecuencia de estas relaciones. El natural de estos habitantes, indígenas todos
ellos de la nacion apolista, y cuyo número no pasa de dos mil setecientos setenta y cinco,
es el mas apacible, y dócil: amantes de los placeres, buscan ante todo las diversiones. Las
numerosas festividades del cristianismo, aumentadas todavía por los usos locales, les proporcionan
frecuentemente la ocasion de reunirse para entregarse á las dansas alegres y jocosas, estimuladas
por las repetidas libaciones de aguardiente, del cual abusan algunos hasta privarse de la razon.
Tal es el modo como pasan la vida, sin pensar en ocuparse, ni en su porvenir, ni en el de sus
hijos, confiados probablemente en la riqueza natural del pais, cuyos productos bastan para
la satisfaccion de sus necesidades. Con un carácter vivo y ligero, tienen muchísima habilidad
para imitar cuanto se les presenta: así es que reunen todas las cualidades que los hacen susceptibles
de civilizarse, mas ántes, quizas que las mismas naciones indígenas de los Andes. Falta únicamente
para que pueda esto llevarse á cabo, que algunos hombres benévolos, despojándose de sus intereses
particulares, quieran consagrarse al desarrollo de las facultades intelectuales de estos Indios
y á su educacion social, gobernándolos moral y físicamente.

Al sudeste de Apolo se encuentra el pueblo de Aten, que dista nueve leguas por el itinerario
siguiente:

                                                        Leguas.

Saliendo de Apolo, se anda por la llanura hasta Puente-Chico.                             
1

De aquí hasta Puente-Grande.                             2

Y hasta llegar á Pampa-Tupili.                           3

Se sube luego la cuesta de Chímasacro-Grande,            1

En seguida se baja, de ella y se toma la falda de la montaña hasta Chímasacro-Chico.      
1

Y se anda finalmente hasta Aten.                           1

                                                        --------
                                                     TOTAL 9

SANTA-CRUZ DE VALLE AMENO.

Su deliciosa posicion le ha hecho merecer á Santa-Cruz el sobrenombre de Valle-Ameno. Nada
efectivamente puede haber de mas encantador, de mas pintoresco y alegre que sus alrededores,
ni que sea mas apacible y risueño que su morada. Situado en un llano, sobre una pendiente apénas
perceptible que se inclina al sud, y al pié de un cerro de forma cónica, este pueblo se halla
tambien circundado por colinas bajas, pero que van levantándose gradualmente hácia el norte
hasta llegar á formar altas montañas, las que se ven coronadas de palmeras cuyo elegante follage
se entremezcla con las copas gigantescas de los árboles mas robustos. El contraste que presentan
los llanos con las colinas cubiertas de una vegetacion primorosa y variada, la corriente del
rio de Santa-Cruz que atraviesa el conjunto de este cuadro, esparciendo un saludable frescor,
todo en fin concurre para hacer que este lugar sea el punto mas agradable de la provincia.

Aunque pequeña, pues que solo contiene novecientos cuarenta y un habitantes, parte de ellos
de la nacion apolista, la parroquia de Santa-Cruz es muy aseada, y mirando sus bellísimos contornos,
fácilmente se desvia la atencion de la irregularidad de sus calles y edificios. El terreno
que la circunda produce con abundancia todos los frutos de la zona tórrida; así es que sus
habitantes son todos labradores, y no solamente recogen lo suficiente para su consumo, sino
que hacen tambien algun comercio con lo que les sobra; para lo cual ponen á curar al aire y
al sol los frutos del plátano, cortándolos primeramente en tiras ó tajadas largas, que despues
de secas se trasforman en escelentes orejones. Preparan asimismo el tabaco y la coca, y todos
estos productos vienen á servirles para operar sus trueques, á falta del dinero amonedado,
que aun no ha entrado allí en circulacion. Se ocupan igualmente los moradores de Santa-Cruz
en la cria del ganado vacuno, lo que se consigue con muchísimo provecho sobre las colinas.
Hay épocas en que se dedican activamente al acopio de la cascarilla, esplorando los bosques
de las montañas vecinas; pero se encuentran estos ya tan destruidos, que al presente se ven
obligados á correr diez ó doce leguas para llegar á encontrarla. En cuanto á la pesca y á la
caza esta comarca es tan abundante como la de Pata, y sus producciones naturales son enteramente
las mismas: se ha descubierto, sin embargo, en los bosques de Santa-Cruz, una infinidad de
maderas de ebanistería las mas finas y hermosas, tales como el guayabo, el granadillo, etc.

En resúmen, si esta poblacion quisiese aprovechar todos los recursos de que se encuentra rodeada,
dedicándose con mas ahinco, á la cria de los ganados, á la agricultura en el seno de esa tierra
tan fértil y en donde la naturaleza le brinda sus tesoros á manos llenas, á la estraccion juiciosamente
graduada de la cascarilla y al laboreo, en fin, de las minas de oro y de plomo, que se dice
haber en la sierra de Santa-Clara, no hay duda que conseguiría duplicar sus riquezas; mas para
esto seria preciso vencer primero esa apatía natural, que conduce á estos indígenas á no trabajar
sino lo muy medido para procurarse las cosas indispensables á la existencia. Verdad es tambien
que fuera menester, para mover y activar su ambicion, una poblacion mas numerosa y mercados
de esportacion mas estendidos.

Santa-Cruz era un lugar muy salubre hasta el año de 1830, en que ya empezaron á sentirse algunas
enfermedades, desconocidas hasta entónces, y las que atacaban con rigor á los habitantes. Hoy
en dia las fiebres intermitentes han asentado allí su dominio. Algunas personas han creido
que provenia esto de la introduccion de árboles pertenecientes á los valles calurosos[1]; pero
segun mis observaciones sobre la provincia del Valle-Grande[2], pienso que semejante cambio
es mas bien debido al desmonte causado por los incendios, que los habitantes tienen la costumbre
de promover cada año con el objeto de renovar la yerba de los llanos y de las colinas. Lo cierto
es que muchos lugares, muy sanos en otro tiempo, se hallan al presente invadidos por esa peste
destructora, que va en aumento á medida que el desmonte se estiende. Es pues un deber del gobierno
el tomar alguna sabia medida para cortar los progresos de semejante mal, y mejorar en lo posible
los lugares inficionados.

Santa-Cruz está situado al oeste sudoeste de Apolo-Bamba. Para venir á este lugar se andan
cinco leguas por el itinerario siguiente:

                                                         Leguas.

Se sube la cuesta de Santa-Teresa.                       1

Se baja despues esta, hasta Huilipisa.                   1

Y se sigue luego por un llano hasta Bacqueria.           1

De donde hay que andar, por un terreno igual, hasta llegar á Apolo.                       
2

                                                   TOTAL   5

ATEN.

Este pueblo, antigua mision de los franciscanos, se halla situado en medio de montañas, en
una hondonada bastante igual, y sus casas, aunque regulares, están desparramadas. Su clima
es caliente y húmedo, muy sano por consiguiente, á pesar de las lluvias que caen allí con frecuencia.
Su cultivo, sus producciones y su comercio son de la misma naturaleza que en Apolo: críanse
tambien algunos ganados en las llanuras herbosas de Tupili.

El número de sus habitantes alcanza poco mas ó ménos á mil treinta y tres; estos indígenas
pertenecen á una nacion diferente de la de los Apolistas, y hablan la lengua tacana, tal vez
una de las mas chocantes y duras, así como de las mas guturales de América. Su carácter, análogo
al lenguaje, es irascible, tenaz, lleno de altanería, y muy poco alegre; son sin embargo mas
inclinados al trabajo que los Apolistas, sobretodo á la agricultura y á las correrías escudriñadoras
en el seno de las florestas. Cada individuo de esta poblacion, como ya hemos dicho en otra
parte, está obligado á construir él mismo, sin ayuda de otros, la casa que mas tarde ha de
habitar con su familia; si llega á faltar á esta costumbre, probablemente conservada desde
su estado salvage, se llena de oprobio, despojándose de la dignidad de hombre. En estremo pródigos
y amigos de la ostentacion, y ansiando siempre poder adquirir ornamentos lucidos para engalanarse
ellos y sus mujeres, no hay trabajos, por penosos que sean, que no estén dispuestos á emprender
á fin de procurarse tal satisfaccion. Prefieren sobre todo los vasos y demás vajilla de plata,
para colocarla como un adorno sobre sus mesas, ó las vestimentas estrañas, cubiertas de galones
y de bordados relucientes, con que se componen para salir á las procesiones del culto católico,
tratando de distinguirse de los demás por lo brillante y singular de tales arreos.

Las facciones de los Atenianos son bastante toscas, sin que haya en esto diferencia alguna
entre ámbos sexos: tienen la nariz corta y chata, la tez demasiado trigueña, y casi todos ellos
están salpicados de manchas blancas por el cuerpo y en la cara, lo que contribuye á darles
un aspecto muy estraño.

Un episodio de la historia de la provincia, particular á Aten, hará conocer la índole de sus
habitantes[1]. En 1811, en consecuencia de haber sido derrotado por los Españoles el destacamento
del ejército patriota, que bajo las órdenes del general Pinelo se encaminaba del Cuzco hácia
La-Paz, el doctor Muñecas, secretario de aquel jefe y eclesiástico de mucho mérito, se refugió
con algunos otros oficiales y patriotas en el valle de Larecaja, donde logró con su influencia
sublevar en tropel á los habitantes contra los Españoles. Despues de una lucha larga y encarnizada,
despues de haber combatido con un valor heroico por la causa de la libertad y de la independencia,
estos soldados improvisados habiendo sido finalmente vencidos por las tropas aguerridas y ordenadas
de los Españoles, vióse forzado Muñecas á dejar Larecaja, de donde se encaminó, con algunos
de los suyos, por el rio Iuyo hasta Aten. Inmediatamente sublevó á los indios atenianos y logró
con ellos apoderarse de Apolo. Los Españoles, que no lo perdian de vista, poco tardaron en
mandar tropas para combatirlo. El capitan D. Agustin Gamarra fué comisionado para esta empresa;
y habiendo llegado á vencer en todos los encuentros á los patriotas, tan inferiores en número,
tan poco aguerridos, y desprovistos enteramente de armas, se aprestaba para la toma de Aten,
que debia coronar su triunfo. Doce Atenianos, mandados por el capitan Pariamo, no pudiendo
resistir en campo raso á cien soldados de tropa veterana y á quinientos flecheros, se emboscaron
á distancia de una legua del pueblo, en un espeso monte[2] que se halla situado sobre una colina,
resolviéndose á morir allí ántes que rendirse al enemigo. Despues de un combate de dos horas,
el capitan Pariamo fué el único que llegó á salvarse, y Gamarra, que se vió dueño del campo,
siguiendo la costumbre de los Españoles, empezó por castigar de la manera mas atroz á todos
aquellos que él suponia haber tomado las armas para alistarse en el ejército patriota.

Aumentándose las persecuciones de dia en dia, y cada vez con mas rigor, un indígena llamado
José Pacha, que era uno de los mas comprometidos, propuso á veinte ó treinta familias el abandonar
sus moradas para ir á buscar la quietud en lo mas escondido de las selvas. Esta poblacion emigrante
se alejó pues, conducida por Pacha, en busca de un recinto donde no pudiese llegar á ser descubierta;
y habiendo traspasado los desiertos, finalmente se detuvo en una hondonada, á la que dio el
nombre de Irimo: en este lugar, situado como doce ó catorce leguas al este de Aten, permanecieron
estos indios mas de siete años sin que se les pudiese descubrir. Como el cauto Pacha habia
tenido gran cuidado de que se tomasen todas las medidas necesarias, nada le faltaba á la nueva
colonia. Para poder vestirse plantaron algodon, y mientras que se ocupaban los hombres en la
caza y en labrar las tierras, las mujeres tejian y cuidaban de las faenas caseras. Pacha, que
se constituyó jefe de la colonia, estableció una policía interior muy severa, distribuyendo
los empleos segun la edad y los sexos; y todos los trabajos se hacian en comun, alternándose
de modo que los que un dia se ocupaban del cultivo, al siguiente iban á la caza, y vice versa;
así es que todos los productos se repartian por igual, como si no hubiese mas que una sola familia.

Para no renunciar á la religion católica, los moradores de esta pequeña república construyeron
una capilla, colocando en ella algunas imágenes de santos, que hablan tenido cuidado de traer
tambien consigo en su emigracion. Pacha, investido ya de los poderes civiles, quiso reunir
á ellos el desempeño de las funciones religiosas: él era quien bautizaba, quien santificaba
los matrimonios y enterraba los muertos, siendo á la vez el cura, el juez y el legislador de
su colonia. Entre las medidas rigurosas tomadas por él, para no ser descubiertos, habia dictado
una ley, la cual mandaba que fueran enterrados vivos todos aquellos que, bajo cualquier pretesto,
llegasen á ponerse en contacto con los habitantes de Aten; así es que pudieron vivir ignorados
por tan largo tiempo, sin que nadie fuese tan imprudente y audaz para quebrantar una ley de
esta naturaleza, y cuya infraccion traia en pos tan horribles consecuencias. Hubo, sin embargo,
una circunstancia que vino á ponerlos al cabo en descubierto.

Aconteció que una muchacha de trece años de edad, hija de un Manuel Cito, cuya familia se componia
de su muger y de esta sola niña, habiendo muchas veces oído hablar del gusto sabroso que da
la sal á los alimentos, concibió el deseo, y con este el proyecto, de procurarse esta sustancia.
Sin que sus padres se apercibiesen, escapóse del lugarejo y tomando la direccion de Aten, llegó
á este pueblo, donde, sin ser vista, se introdujo en una casa aislada, y apoderándose de toda
la sal que pudo encontrar, volvió á Irimo con el producto de su robo. Durante su ausencia,
que fué de tres dias, el vigilante jefe no dejó de apercibirse de la falta de la muchacha,
practicando mil pesquizas para saber de su paradero, é instando estrechamente á los padres
para que le dijesen qué era de ella. En medio de estas investigaciones se aparece la joven
fugitiva; y por el contenido de su carga se descubre que venia de Aten, donde, por otra parte,
ella misma confesó haber estado. Inmediatamente mandó Pacha que la castigasen con todo el rigor
de la ley; pero en el momento de la ejecucion, todos los habitantes reunidos imploraron su
gracia con tanta instancia, y la pobre niña hizo tantas protestas, que al fin otorgóle el jefe
su perdón. A los seis ó siete meses, enteramente olvidada de que habia escapado á la muerte,
tentó una segunda escursion con el mismo fin, y habiéndola hecho espiar Pacha por todas la
direcciones con la órden terminante de aplicarle las terrible pena decretada por él, fué prendida
cuatro dias despues, y ni sus lágrimas, ni su desesperacion pudieron enternecer á sus aprehensores,
que la hicieron pasar incontinenti por el horrendo suplicio de ser enterrada viva.

Los infelices padres, sobrecogidos de horror á la nueva de tal acontecimiento, huyeron precipitadamente
de Irimo, y fueron á Aten á quejarse al juez del espantoso castigo que acababa de sufrir su
hija; poniendo así en descubierto la mansion de Pacha. Ordenó la autoridad que inmediatamente
se aprehendiese á este, lo cual así que se efectuó, se le condujo á La-Paz para ser juzgado;
pero se tardó tanto en ajusticiarlo, que en 1823, cuando esta ciudad cayó en poder de los patriotas,
Pacha se vió comprendido en el indulto general y pudo entónces volver á su pais.

Irimo existe todavía, y se compone de las mismas familias, sometidas al presente á la jurisdiccion
civil y eclesiástica de Aten. Sus habitantes, por la grande fertilidad del terreno disfrutan
de todas las comodidades de la vida, bajo un temperamento suave y en una posicion deliciosa.

Las aguas del rio de Aten van á reunirse al Mapiri, uno de los tributarios del Beni: por lo
demás, esta es la sola corriente del centro de la provincia que no se dirige al Tuyche.

PARTIDO CHICO Ó PUEBLOS INTERIORES.

Bajo esta denominacion reunen generalmente las poblaciones del interior, tales como San-José
de Chupiamonas, Tumupaza, Isiamas y Cavinas, separadas todas ellas, por inmensos desiertos,
de las que acabamos de examinar. Voy pues á describir tambien estos pueblos, misiones antiguas,
fundadas igualmente, como queda dicho, por los padres franciscanos.

SAN-JOSÉ DE CHUPIAMONAS.

Saliendo al estenordeste de Apolo, y atravesando por caminos espantosos, llenos de peligros
de todo género, en medio de unos desiertos sin término, y al cabo de treinta y ocho leguas
de una marcha penosísima, se llega finalmente á San-José de Chupiamonas, que ha tomado su nombre
de un rio cuyas aguas rojizas van á reunirse, no léjos de allí, con las del rio Tuyche. El
pueblo compuesto de setenta y tres indígenas, en todo semejantes á los Atenianos, y que hablan
la misma lengua, está situado cerca de la confluencia que forma el mencionado rio con el Tuyche,
el cual es tan ancho en aquel punto, que es menester pasarlo en balsas: así es que los habitantes
son muy útiles á los viageros y á los comerciantes, ocupándose en pasarlos de una banda del
rio á la otra. En razon del número tan escaso de sus habitantes, se habia pensado en reunir
esta poblacion con la de Aten; pero las justas reclamaciones de los negociantes la han hecho
conservar como un punto indispensable para el comercio.

La temperatura de San-José es muy cálida, sin que por esto se conozcan allí en manera alguna
las enfermedades: su morada no puede ser mas agradable, pues parece que la naturaleza se hubiese
complacido en derramar sus dones en aquellos lugares salvages, con una prodigalidad digna de
la tierra de promision. El estrangero que llega á San-José quéda pasmado de admiracion al contemplar
una vegetacion tan hermosa, y la variedad infinita de frutos que allí abundan. Efectivamente
sus bosques ofrecen por todas partes la vainilla, el aceite de copaiba, recinas, cortezas aromáticas,
gomas, la cera y la miel de abeja y multitud de plantas medicinales. Críanse allí espontáneamente
los frutos mas esquisitos, y entre ellos el cacao, que sin ser plantado crece silvestre por
todas partes dando abundantes cosechas. La caza ofrece cantidad prodigiosa de pájaros y de
cuadrúpedos: entre estos pueden citarse la gran-bestia, el oso-hormiguero, los perico-ligeros,
muchos venados y javalíes, y una especie de cerdos muy pequeñitos, que llaman en el pais quebo-queres.
El Tuyche abunda tambien en pescados. Por último, esta tierra extraordinariamente fértil produce
arroz, maiz, yucas, maní, bananas, ananáes, algodon y caña-dulce; mas todas estas producciones
sirven tan solo para el consumo de la poblacion, y de ninguna manera para el comercio.

TUMUPAZA.

Doce leguas al nordeste de San-José, sobre una ligera colina compuesta de pedregales blanquiscos
y en medio de un campo horizontal, cubierto de bosques ó de pequeños herbazales, se encuentra
situada la mision antigua de Tumupaza[1], convertida al presente en una parroquia. Cuando por
los meses de agosto, setiembre y octubre sube uno sobre las colinas, apercibe á lo léjos, sobre
muchos puntos diferentes, la humareda producida sin duda por los fuegos de los salvages, que
viven desconocidos hasta hoy, en esos lugares tan fértiles circunvecinos á Tumupaza. Esta parroquia,
compuesta de ochocientas-ochenta y cinco almas, reune, con respecto á sus producciones de cultivo
y naturales, absolutamente las mismas circunstancias que San-José.

Estos Indios, pertenecientes á la nacion tacana, son bien constituidos y elegantes de talle,
tienen el cabello negro y muy fino, la cara regular y la tez de un blanco pálido; su fisonomía
es agradable y espresiva, y todo anuncia en ellos la alegría. Son por lo demás muy sóbrios:
todo su vestido consiste en una túnica hecha de un tejido de algodon, la cual les cae hasta
las rodillas, y no tiene sino medias mangas: andan siempre descalzos, y tampoco se cubren la
cabeza. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06722</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>467848</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22143</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

APOLLO-BAMBA [1].

The town of Apollo, today capital of the province, was founded about the middle of last century
by Franciscan missionaries, who met at that point to the natives
of the nation Apollos, and formed a mission, which having been stuck
in the year 1800 to the other neighboring towns people came to compose
the province of Caupolican.

Apollo is situated in the center of a plain, slightly wavy and plant cover grasses. This plain,
bounded on the south by mountains to the valleys and their corners These are, give a very picturesque,
is five to six miles wide, and its length extends from north to south, about twelve to fourteen,
appearing one oblong. Al this is raised, similar to a wall, a large mountain that runs from north to
south, and to that of their great elevation has been called Altuncama. There is a low hill west, filed
between Apollo and the plains of Santa Catalina which come to occupy the west and southwest. The
Last Valley horizontal, which is twelve miles long on five wide, is covered part of grasslands, and
Tupili crosses the river, whose banks are adorned widths and thick forests, which so contrasted
with the rest satin, they seem to have been planted by human hands.

The village consists of three distinct groups. The first is located before moving the river, and consists
of scattered houses: in this group, called the bias of the Concepcion, is where they are established
merchants of all kinds of fruit, and whom the native inhabitants are in their particular language
Matagua name, ie outsiders. The second group located in the center and on a slight hill of red
clay is on the other side of the river, and contains the town hall, parish church and convent
of the Franciscans, whose facade that faces east, overlooking a square in which the sides
north and south are composed of several buildings, and the eastern border to the convent, a number
of houses inhabited by indigenous people: these houses, each of which has a single door and
about fifteen to twenty yards long, are placed on the hill an amphitheater, so that from the convent
is found all that happens inside of them. Such was the manner in which the Franciscans had provisions
in order to be at the sight of all the steps of the Indians, and to ensure their actions. At that time,
traders who came to the province, were forced to stay in the convent make their exchanges in the
presence of the religious. A creek separates this second part, the third group that is located
on the path of Aten, and arranged in the same order we have just seen in that.

Apollo temperature is pleasant and healthy, but let their free access plains to all the winds,
the air becomes drier than in Santa Cruz. There are grown the same fruits than in other districts,
but coca is the only important object of trade barter. Also there in Apollo as two thousand
to two thousand five hundred head of livestock, and its inhabitants were a little more industrious
and neat, would have certainly all kinds of goods in abundance. A single fact will suffice to justify
this assertion, as regards to the great procreation of the stock. An Indian named Pedro Chambi,
had met with the product fifteen cows their industry, dedicated to breeding as carefully then,
so came to multiply, it was the large number sold by him while he lived, still left in 1828,
at the end of his days, like a thousand heads. It is seen that with some care because the plains
and could easily be covered hills of livestock, both cattle and sheep, and even perhaps to
equine. It would be equally possible that Altuncama mountains, in view of his elevation, produjesen
vines and potatoes.

The draw-modified hulls some way to be both of these people, teaching them to estimate the positive
value of things, and giving an idea of ??money. For trade in this particular have come to
know too many other objects, they were entirely ignored, and in whose possession they enjoy
today's comforts. If I had continued this trade, there is no doubt that the inhabitants of Apollo
would already well advanced in the way of a civilization, fighting relentlessly against those
who have become directors of these Indians, under the stupid pretext the business relationship
with the foreigners corrupting their morals. Although this can be verified sometimes, why not
have to deny the immense advantages which must necessarily bring get the frequency of these relationships.
The nature of these people, indigenous people all Apollos them in the nation, whose number does
not pass two thousand seven hundred and seventy-five is the most peaceful, and gentle, pleasure-loving,
looking at all the fun. The numerous festivals of Christianity, yet increased local usage,
provided they Used frequently meet to give herself the happy and playful danses, stimulated
by repeated libations of brandy, which misused by some to be deprived of reason. Such is the way go
through life without thinking of dealing, or in their future, nor in that of their children, probably
relying on the natural wealth of the country, whose products are sufficient to satisfaction of their
needs. With a lively and light, have a lot of skill to imitate as they show, so we gather all
the qualities that make them susceptible of civilized, but soon, maybe the same indigenous
Andean nations. Lack only to enable it to carry out some benevolent men, stripped of their interests
particular, want to devote to the development of intellectual faculties of these Indians and his social
education, moral governor and physically.

Apollo southeast of the town of Aten, a distance of nine miles per itinerary following:

Leagues.

                                                        Leaving Apollo, beat about the plain-Chico Bridge.

1

From here to Puente Grande. 2

And to arrive at Pampa-Tupili. 3

Go up the slope after Chímasacro-Large, 1

Then go down, it and take
the slope to Chímasacro-Chico.

1

                                                        
                                                     And he finally goes to Athens.

1

-------- TOTAL 9

SANTA CRUZ VALLEY AMENO.

Its position has made him delightful to Santa-Cruz deserve the nickname of Valle Ameno. Nothing indeed
could be more charming, more picturesque and lively than their surroundings, or that it is more
peaceful and cheerful your home. Located on a plain, on a slope scarcely perceptible leaning
to the south, and at the foot of a conical hill, this village is also surrounded by low hills,
but they will gradually rising towards the north to reach higher
to form mountains, which are topped with elegant palm trees whose
foliage mingles with the drinks giant tree more robust.

The contrast presented plains with hills covered with exquisite and varied vegetation, stream
Santa-Cruz River that runs through all of this table, scattering a healthy freshness, attends all in
order to make this place more enjoyable point of the province.

Although small, it contains only nine hundred forty-one inhabitants, some of them nation of
Apollo, the parish of Santa Cruz is very neat, and looking at its beautiful contours, easily
divert attention from the irregularity of its streets and buildings. Field surrounding it produces
in abundance all the fruits of the torrid zone, so their people are all farmers, not only collect
enough for their consumption, but they also do some trade with their abundance, for which
they put to air cure the sun the fruits of banana, cut into long strips or slices, that after
of dried apricots are transformed into eSCelente. Also prepare and coca snuff, and all these
products come to serve them to operate their exchanges, for want of money in coins, has not
yet entered it into circulation. Are active as the inhabitants of Santa Cruz in the breeding
of cattle, which is achieved with much advantage over the hills. There are times when actively
engaged in the collection of the husk, forest rover of the surrounding mountains, but found these
and so destroyed, which at present are required to run ten or twelve miles to get to find
it.

With regard to fishing and to the hunting this region is as abundant as the Pata, and natural products
are entirely the same: it has been found, however, in the forests of Santa Cruz, countless woods
of the finest cabinetry and beautiful, such as guava, granadillo, etc.

In short, if the population wanted to take advantage of all resources is surrounded, engaging more
actively, to the raising of livestock, agriculture within the land so fertile and where nature gives
you full hands treasures, to the judicious EXTRACTION graduated from the chaff and tillage, in
short, mines of gold and lead, said be in the mountains of Santa Clara, no doubt it would get
double their riches, but to this would be overcome first the natural
apathy, which leads to these indigenous people to not work but the
very measured to obtain the things necessary to existence.

Truth is also it was necessary to move and activate your ambition, a larger population and markets
exportation of more outstretched.

Santa-Cruz was a very safe place until the year 1830, which already began to feel some diseases,
hitherto unknown, and vigorously attacking the inhabitants. Today on day intermittent fevers
have settled there his domain. Some people have believed that came from this in the introduction
of trees in the hot valleys [1], but according to my observations on the province of Valle Grande
[2], I think such a change is rather due to deforestation caused by fires, where residents are
accustomed to promote each year with the aim of renewing the grass of the plains and hills. The fact
is that many places, very healthy in the past, are at present invaded by this pest destructive,
which is increasing in proportion as it extends clearing.

It is therefore the duty of the government taking a wise move to cut the progress of such
evil, and improve where possible tainted sites.

                                                         

Santa-Cruz is located west-southwest of Apollo Bamba.

To come to this place will go five leagues by the following schedule:

Leagues.

Go

up the hill of Santa Teresa. 1

                                                   He gets after it, until Huilipisa.

1

And it follows then by a plain to Bacqueria. 1

Where you have to walk for a ground well, until they came to Apollo. 2

TOTAL 5

ATEN.

This town, old mission of the Franciscans, is located amidst mountains, a hollow pretty equal, and their
houses, though regular, are scattered. The climate is hot and humid, very healthy therefore,
in spite of the rain that falls there frequently. Its culture, its production and trade are
of the same nature as in Apollo críanse also some cattle in the grassy plains of Tupili.

The number of inhabitants reaches, more or less one thousand thirty-three; these Indians belong to
a nation different from the Apollo, and speak the language Tacana, perhaps one of the most shocking
and hard, as well as the most guttural of America. His character, similar language, is irascible,
stubborn, full of arrogance, and little merry, are nevertheless more inclined to work than Apollos,
especially to agriculture and to scrutinizing raids within the forests. Each individual of this
population, as we have said elsewhere hand, is obliged to build his
own, without help from others, the house has later living with his
family, if it comes to miss the practice, probably conserved from
its savage state, is filled with shame, stripping the dignity of man.

Lavish in the extreme and friends of the show, and always longing to purchase ornaments to
spruce lucid they and their wives, no jobs, painful as they are, they are not willing to take To
obtain such satisfaction. Preferred over all other glasses and silverware, as an ornament
to place on their desks, or the strange dress, covered in gallons
embroidery and shiny, with which to go up to the processions of the
Catholic religion trying to distinguish itself from others by the
brilliance and uniqueness of such trappings.

The features of the Athenians are quite rough, with no difference in this between both sexes
have short, flat nose, too swarthy complexion, and almost all are dotted with white spots on the
body and face, helping them to look very strange.

An episode in the history of the province, particularly to Aten, will know the nature of their inhabitants
[1]. In 1811, in consequence of having been defeated by the Spanish detachment patriot army, which
under the command of General Pinelo was heading towards Cuzco La-Paz, Dr. Doll, chief secretary
and church that much credit, he took refuge with some other officers and patriots Larecaja Valley,
where he managed to influence in crowds to revolt against the Spanish people. After a long
and bitter struggle, after having fought with heroic courage in the cause of freedom and independence,
these improvised soldiers having been finally defeated by the battle-hardened troops and ordered
of the Spanish, saw himself forced to leave Larecaja Dolls, where he went, with some of their
own, by the river Iuyo to Aten. Immediately the Indians revolted and managed Athenians Apollo
seize them. The Spanish, who lost sight of him, soon soon send troops to fight. Captain D. Agustin
Gamarra was commissioned for this company; and having come to win every game to the Patriots, so
inferior in number, so little hardened, and entirely devoid of weapons, was ready for decision-Aten,
which was to crown his triumph. Twelve Athenians, led by Captain Pariaman unable stand in the
open field to a hundred soldiers to five hundred regular troops and archers, were ambushed
at the distance of a league from the village, in a dense forest [2]
which is situated on a hill there resolved to die rather than surrender
to the enemy.

After a two-hour battle, Pariaman Captain was the only one who came to save, and Gamarra, that
he was master of the field, following the custom of the Spanish, began to punish the most egregious
manner to all those he supposed to have taken up arms to join the patriot army.

Persecution increasing day by day, and each time with more rigor, an Indian named Joseph Pacha,
who was one of the most committed, proposed twenty or thirty families to abandon their homes to go
to find the best kept quiet in the forest. The migrant population away because, driven by
Pacha, looking for a venue where she could not get to be discovered; and having crossed the desert,
finally stopped in a ravine, to which he gave Irimo name: in this place, situated about twelve
or fourteen miles east of Athens, remained These Indians more than seven years without being
could discover. As the wary Pacha had Great care had to take whatever steps are necessary,
nothing was missing from the new colony. To planted cotton dress, and while men were engaged
in hunting and clearing of land, the women wove and took care of housework. Pacha, which is head
of the colony was established a very strict internal police, distributing
jobs depending on age and gender, and all work was done in common,
alternating so that one day dealing with the culture, the next went
to the game, and vice versa; so that all products were distributed
equally, as if there were more than one family.

In order not to renounce the Catholic religion, the inhabitants of this small republic built
a chapel, placing in it some images of saints, took care to bring speakers it also in their
migration. Pacha, already invested with civil powers, wanted to reunite to them the performance
of religious duties: he was the one who baptized, who sanctified marriages and burying the dead,
being at once the priest, the judge and the legislator colony. Among the stringent measures taken
by him, to avoid detection, had dictated a law which commanded them to be buried alive all those
who, under any pretext, tended to stay in touch with the people of Athens, so I could live
ignored for so long, no one would be so reckless and daring to break a law this nature, and whose
violation was bringing in so horrible after consequences.

There was, however, a circumstance that came to them after overdrawn.

It happened that a girl of thirteen years old, daughter of Manuel Cito, whose family was composed
of his wife and this one girl, having often heard of savory taste that gives salt to food, he conceived
the desire, and with this project, to procure the substance. Without their parents gird escapóse
the hamlet and taking the direction of Athens, arrived to this village, where, unseen, was
introduced in an isolated house, and seizing all salt could be found, returned to Irimo with
the proceeds of their theft. During his absence, that was three days, the caretaker boss stopped
perceiving the lack of girl practicing thousand pesquizas to know of his whereabouts, and
urging parents to closely to tell him what was hers. In the midst of these investigations are
featuring the young fugitive, and the content of their cargo is discovered that came from Athens,
where, on the other hand, she confessed to state. Pacha immediately sent to the punished to
the full rigor of the law, but at the time of execution, all the inhabitants gathered implored
his grace with such request, and the poor girl had so many protests that finally the head Gave
forgiveness. Six or seven months, entirely forgotten that he had escaped death tempted a second
excursions for the same purpose, and having done all the spy Pacha directions with strict orders
to apply the terrible punishment decreed for him, was pinned Four days later, and neither tears, nor
could soften his despair at his captors, incontinently that posed
by the horrendous ordeal of being buried alive.

The unhappy parents, overwhelmed with horror to the news of such an event, abruptly fled of Irimo,
and went to Aten to complain to the judge the awful punishment which had just suffered its daughter
thereby discovered the mansion in Pacha. Immediately ordered the authority apprehends this, which was
made so, you drove to La-Paz for trial but it took so long to execute
him, that in 1823, when the city fell to the Patriots, Pacha was seen
covered by a general pardon and could then return to his country.

Irimo still exists, and is composed of the same families, subject
to the jurisdiction this Aten civil and ecclesiastical.

Its inhabitants, the great fertility of the land enjoy all the comforts of life, under a mild,
in a delightful position.

The waters of the river to meet the Aten are Mapiri, a tributary of the Beni: at Moreover, this
is the only power center in the province that does not address the Tuyche.

PEOPLES PARTY OR SMALL INTERIOR.

Under this denomination usually meet people from inside, such as San-Jose of Chupiamonas, Tumupaza,
Cavinas Isiamas and separated all of them, vast deserts, from those just discussed. I will
therefore also describe these people, old missions, also founded, as stated above, by the Franciscan
Fathers.

SAN-JOSE DE CHUPIAMONAS.

Coming to the northeast of Apollo, and going through horrible roads full of dangers of all kinds,
in the middle of a desert without end, and after thirty-eight leagues a march excruciating,
it finally comes to St. Joseph of Chupiamonas, which takes its name a river whose waters are
reddish to meet, not far from there, the river Tuyche.

The people composed of seventy-three Indians, all similar to the Athenians, who speak the same
language, is located near the confluence of the said river which forms the Tuyche, which is so wide
at that point, it is necessary to pass it on rafts, so that people are very helpful to the travelers
and merchants, dealing in a band pass of river to the other. Because so little number of its inhabitants,
had intended to gather this population with that of Aten, but the just claims of the dealers
have made retained as an indispensable item for trade.

The San-Jose temperature is very warm, but why is there any way know diseases: their abode can
not be more pleasant, it seems that nature had pleased to pour out his gifts in uncivilized
places, with a bounty worth the promised land. The foreigner who comes to Saint Joseph is stunned
with admiration at the sight a vegetation so beautiful, and the infinite variety of fruits that abound
there. Indeed its forests offered all over the vanilla, balsam oil, Recinos, aromatic bark, gums,
wax and honey and many medicinal plants. There spontaneously Críanse the most exquisite fruits,
and including cocoa, which grows wild without being planted by bear
abundant crops everywhere.

The game offers prodigious amount of birds and quadrupeds: among
these may be mentioned the large beast, the bear-ant, the parrot-light
many deer and wild boar, and a kind of very little pigs, called on
the country Quebo-queres.

The Tuyche also abounds in fish. Finally, this extraordinarily fertile soil produces rice, maize,
cassava, peanuts, bananas, pineapples, cotton and sugarcane-sweet, but all of these productions
serve only for the consumption of the population, and in no way to trade.

TUMUPAZA.

Twelve miles northeast of San-Jose, on a small rocky hill composed of whitish and in the middle of
a horizontal field, covered with small forests or grasslands, is
old mission located Tumupaza [1], converted to this in a parish.

When the months of August, September and October, up one on the hills, warnings to the distance,
on many different points, the smoke produced no doubt by the fires of the savages, which unknown
until today live in such places as to Tumupaza surrounding fertile. This parish, It consists
of eight hundred-eighty-five souls, gathers, in regard to their crop productions and natural,
absolutely the same circumstances as St. Joseph.
These Indians, belonging to the nation tacana are well made and elegant
figure, have black hair and very fine, regular face and a pale white
complexion, her face is pleasant and expressive, and everything in
them the joy announces. Are otherwise very plain: all your dress is
a robe made of cotton fabric, which falls to them knees, and he has
only half sleeves, are always bare, and no cover head</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>