<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>495159</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24678</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> En la primera noche el capitán paladeó el voluptuoso egoísmo
del descanso á solas. Ya no tenía una mujer á su lado como prolongación inevitable; vivía entre
hombres... Y apreció la castidad como un placer que se le ofrecía con todos los encantos de
lo nuevo.

La segunda noche, en la estrecha y maloliente cámara del patrón, se sintió desvelado por los
recuerdos, que volvían á retoñar. ¡Oh, Freya!... ¡Cuándo la vería otra vez!...

El conde y él hablaron poco, pero pasaban largas horas juntos, sentados al lado de la rueda
del timón, mirando el mar. Eran más amigos que en tierra, aunque se cruzaban entre ellos escasas
palabras. La vida común aminoraba la altivez del fingido diplomático y hacía que el capitán
descubriese nuevos méritos en su persona.

La soltura con que andaba por el buque y ciertas palabras técnicas empleadas contra su voluntad
no permitieron á Ferragut más dudas sobre su verdadera profesión.

--Usted es marino--dijo de pronto.

Y el conde asintió, juzgando inútil el disimulo. Sí, era marino.

«Entonces, ¿qué hago yo aquí? ¿Para qué me han dado el mando?...» Así pensó Ferragut, sin atinar
por qué buscaba su concurso este hombre que podía dirigir el buque sin ayuda ajena.

Indudablemente era un oficial de marina, y también debían proceder de una flota todos los marineros
rubios que trabajaban como autómatas. La disciplina les hacía acatar las órdenes de Ferragut,
pero se adivinaba que para ellos su mando no pasaba de ser una simple delegación, y que el
verdadero jefe de á bordo era el conde.

La goleta pasó á la vista del archipiélago de Lípari; luego, torciendo el rumbo hacia el Oeste,
siguió las costas de Sicilia desde el cabo Gallo al cabo de San Vito. A partir de aquí puso
su proa al Sudoeste, yendo en busca de las islas Egades.

Debía esperar en estas aguas, donde empieza á angostarse el Mediterráneo entre Túnez y Sicilia,
irguiéndose el pico volcánico de la isla Pantelaria en mitad del inmenso estrecho.

Le bastaban al conde breves indicaciones para que el rumbo seguido por Ferragut fuese con arreglo
á sus deseos. Acabó por no ocultar la admiración que le inspiraba su maestría de navegante.

--Conoce usted bien su mar--dijo el conde.

El capitán se encogió de hombros sonriendo. Era verdaderamente suyo. Podía llamarle mare nostrum,
lo mismo que los romanos, sus antiguos dominadores.

Como si adivinase el fondo á simple vista, mantuvo el buque en los límites del extenso banco
de la Aventura. Navegaba lentamente con sólo algunas velas, cruzando y recruzando las mismas aguas.

Kaledine, al transcurrir dos días, empezó á inquietarse. Varias veces oyó Ferragut cómo murmuraba
el nombre de Gibraltar. El paso del Atlántico al Mediterráneo era el mayor peligro para los
que él esperaba.

Desde la cubierta de la goleta sólo se podía ver á corta distancia, y el conde trepó repetidas
veces por las escalas de cuerda de la arboladura, para abarcar con sus ojos un espacio más extenso.

Una mañana gritó desde lo alto al capitán, señalándole un punto del horizonte. Debía hacer
rumbo en la misma dirección. Allí estaban los que él buscaba.

Ferragut le obedeció, y media hora después fueron apareciendo, uno tras otro, dos buques prolongados
y bajos de borda, que navegaban con gran velocidad. Eran como destroyers, pero sin mástiles,
sin chimeneas, deslizándose casi á ras del agua, pintados de un color gris que les hacía confundirse
con el mar á cierta distancia.

Se colocaron á ambos lados del velero, aproximándose á él de tal modo, que parecía que iban
á aplastarlo con el encontrón de sus cascos. Varios cables metálicos surgieron de sus cubiertas
para enroscarse en los palos de la goleta, aprisionándola, formando una sola masa de los tres
buques, que siguieron unidos la lenta ondulación del mar.

Ulises examinó curiosamente á los dos compañeros de flotación. ¿Estos eran los famosos submarinos?...
Vió en su cubierta de acero escotillas redondas y salientes como chimeneas, por las que asomaban
grupos de cabezas. Los oficiales y tripulantes iban vestidos como pescadores de las costas
del Norte, con traje impermeable de una sola pieza y casco encerado. Muchos de ellos agitaron
en lo alto estos cascos, y el conde les respondió tremolando su gorra. Los marineros rubios
de la goleta gritaron, contestando á las aclamaciones de sus camaradas de los sumergibles:
«¡Deutschland über alles!...»

Pero este entusiasmo en medio de la soledad del mar, que equivalía á un canto da triunfo, duró
muy poco. Sonaron pitos, corrieron hombres por las aceradas cubiertas, y Ferragut vió invadido
su buque por dos filas de marineros. En un momento quedaron abiertas las escotillas, sonó un
ruido de maderas rotas, y las latas de esencia empezaron á transbordarse por ambos lados. En
torno del velero se pobló el agua de cajones abiertos, que se alejaban con mansa flotación.

El conde oía en la popa á un hombre vestido de tela impermeable, que era un oficial.

Relataba el paso por el estrecho de Gibraltar completamente sumergidos, viendo por el periscopio
los torpederos ingleses en patrulla de vigilancia.

--Nada, comandante--continuó el oficial--; ni el menor incidente... Una navegación magnífica.

--¡Que Dios castigue á Inglaterra!--dijo el conde, llamado ahora comandante.

--¡Que Dios la castigue!--repuso el oficial, como si dijese «amén».

Ferragut se vió olvidado, desconocido por todos estos hombres que llenaban la goleta. Algunos
marineros le empujaron en la precipitación de su trabajo. Era el patrón del velero, un civil
falto de jerarquía al estar entre hombres de guerra.

Empezó á comprender por qué motivo le habían dado el mando del pequeño buque. El conde se quedaba.
Le vió acercarse como si de repente se acordase de él, tendiéndole su diestra con una afabilidad
de camarada.

--Capitán, muchas gracias. Este servicio es de los que no se olvidan. Tal vez no nos veremos
nunca... Pero, por si alguna vez me necesita, sepa quién soy.

Y como si presentase á otra persona, dijo sus nombres ceremoniosamente: Archibaldo von Kramer,
teniente de navío de la flota imperial... Su personalidad de diplomático no era enteramente
falsa. Había servido como agregado naval en varias Embajadas.

Luego le dió instrucciones para el regreso. Podía esperar frente á Palermo. Un bote vendría
en busca suya para llevarle á tierra. Todo estaba previsto... Debía entregar el mando al verdadero
dueño de la goleta: un miedoso que se había hecho pagar muy caro el alquiler del buque, pero
sin atreverse á poner en riesgo su persona. En la cámara estaban los papeles en regla para
justificar esta navegación.

--Salude en mi nombre á las señoras... Dígales que pronto oirán hablar de nosotros. Vamos á
hacernos dueños del Mediterráneo.

Continuó el desembarque de combustible. Ferragut vió á Von Kramer introduciéndose por la capota
abierta de uno de los submarinos. Luego creyó reconocer en el otro sumergible á dos marineros
de los que habían tripulado la goleta, los cuales fueron recibidos con gritos y abrazos por
sus camaradas, metiéndose á continuación por una escotilla tubular.

La descarga duró hasta media tarde. Ulises no se había imaginado que el pequeño buque llevase
tantas cajas. Cuando la bodega quedó vacía, desaparecieron los últimos marineros germánicos,
y con ellos los cables que aprisionaban al velero. Un oficial le gritó que podía marcharse.
Los dos sumergibles, más achatados sobre el mar que á su llegada, con los depósitos henchidos
de esencia y aceite, empezaron á alejarse.

Al verse solo en la popa de la goleta, sintió una repentina inquietud.

«¿Qué has hecho?... ¿qué has hecho?», clamó una voz en su cerebro.

Pero contemplando á los tres viajeros y al muchacho que habían quedado como única tripulación,
olvidó sus remordimientos. Debía moverse mucho para suplir esta falta de brazos. En dos noches
y un día apenas descansó, manejando casi al mismo tiempo el timón y el motor, pues no se atrevía
á emplear todas sus velas con esta escasez de hombres.

Cuando se vió, en un amanecer, frente al puerto de Palermo, que empezaba á extinguir sus luces,
Ferragut pudo dormir por primera vez, dejando encargado á uno de los marineros la vigilancia
del buque, que se mantenía con el velamen recogido. A media mañana le despertaron unas voces
que gritaban desde el mar: «¿Dónde está el capitán?»

Vió un bote y varios hombres que saltaban á la goleta. Era el dueño, que venía á recobrar su
buque para hacerlo entrar en el puerto con toda legalidad. El mismo bote se encargó de llevar
á tierra á Ulises con su pequeña maleta. Le acompañaba un señor rojizo y obeso, que parecía
tener gran ascendiente sobre el patrón.

--Ya estará usted enterado de lo que ocurre--le dijo, mientras dos remeros hacían deslizar
el bote sobre las olas--. ¡Esos bandidos!... ¡Esos mandolinistas!...

Ulises, sin saber por qué, hizo un gesto afirmativo. Este burgués indignado era un alemán:
uno de los que ayudaban á la doctora. Bastaba oírle.

Media hora después, Ferragut saltó á un muelle, sin que nadie se opusiera á su desembarco,
como si la protección de su obeso compañero adormeciese todas las vigilancias. A pesar de esto,
el buen señor mostraba un deseo ferviente de apartarse de él, de huir, atendiendo á sus propios
asuntos.

Sonrió al enterarse de que Ulises quería salir inmediatamente para Nápoles. «Hace usted bien...»
El tren partía dos horas más tarde. Y lo metió en un coche de alquiler, desapareciendo con
precipitación.

El capitán, al quedarse solo, casi creyó que había soñado lo de los días anteriores.

Volvía á ver Palermo después de una ausencia de largos años. Experimentó la alegría de un siciliano
desterrado al cruzarse con varios carros del país tirados por rocines con plumas y cuyas cajas
pintarrajeadas representaban escenas de La Jerusalén libertada. Recordó los nombres de las
vías principales, que eran los de antiguos virreyes españoles. Vió en una plaza las estatuas
de cuatro reyes de España... Pero todos estos recuerdos sólo le inspiraron un interés fugaz.
Le preocupaban el movimiento extraordinario de las calles, el gentío formando grupos para escuchar
la lectura de los periódicos. Muchas ventanas tenían banderas nacionales entrelazadas con las
de Francia, Inglaterra y Bélgica.

Al llegar á la estación supo la verdad; se enteró del suceso al que había aludido el comerciante
mientras iban en el bote. ¡Era la guerra!... Italia había roto sus relaciones el día anterior
con los Imperios centrales.

Ulises se sintió agitado por la inquietud al recordar lo que había hecho en pleno Mediterráneo.
Creyó que los grupos populares que pasaban dando vivas detrás de las banderas iban á adivinar
su hazaña, cayendo sobre él. Necesitaba alejarse de este entusiasmo patriótico; y respiró satisfecho
al verse en el interior de un vagón... Además, iba á ver á Freya, y le bastaba evocar su imagen
para que se desvaneciesen todos sus remordimientos.

El viaje fué largo y difícil. Las necesidades de la guerra se hacían sentir desde el primer
momento, absorbiendo todos los medios de comunicación. El tren quedaba inmóvil horas enteras
para dejar paso á otros trenes cargados de hombres y de material militar. En todas las estaciones
había soldados en traje de campaña, banderas, muchedumbres que vitoreaban.

Cuando llegó á Nápoles, fatigado por un viaje de cuarenta y ocho horas, le pareció que el cochero
se dirigía con demasiada lentitud hacia el viejo palacio de Chiaia.

Al atravesar el zaguán con su pequeña maleta, le cortó el paso la portera, gruesa comadre de
pelo encrespado y polvoriento, que sólo había entrevisto algunas veces en las profundidades
de su caverna.

--Las señoras ya no viven en la casa... Las señoras han partido de repente con Karl, su empleado.

Y explicaba el resto de esta huída con una sonrisa hostil y maligna.

Comprendió Ferragut que no debía insistir. La mujerona estaba furiosa por la fuga de las damas
tedescas, y examinaba al marino como un presunto espía, bueno para una denuncia patriótica.
Sin embargo, por honradez profesional, le avisó que la signora rubia, la más joven y simpática,
había pensado en él al irse, dejando su equipaje en la portería.

Se apresuró Ulises á desaparecer. Ya enviaría alguien que recogiese sus maletas. Y tomando
otro carruaje, se dirigió al albergo de Santa Lucía... ¡Qué golpe inesperado!

Al verle entrar, el portero hizo un gesto de sorpresa y de asombro. Antes de que Ferragut alcanzase
á preguntarle por Freya, con la vaga esperanza de que se hubiese refugiado en el hotel, este
hombre le dió una noticia.

--Capitán, aquí ha estado su hijo esperándole.

El capitán balbuceó, desorientado: «¿Qué hijo?...» El hombre de las llaves bordadas trajo el
libro de viajeros, mostrándole una línea: «Esteban Ferragut. Barcelona.» Y Ulises reconoció
la letra de su hijo, al mismo tiempo que se le oprimía el pecho con una angustia indefinible.

La sorpresa le dejó sin voz, y el portero se aprovechó de su silencio para seguir hablando.

Era un muchacho simpático é inteligente... Algunas mañanas le había acompañado para enseñarle
lo mejor de la ciudad. Se había puesto en relación con los consignatarios del Mare nostrum,
buscando por todas partes noticias de su padre. Al fin, convencido de que el capitán estaba
ya de regreso á Barcelona, había partido á su vez el día anterior.

--Si llega usted doce horas antes, todavía lo encuentra aquí.

El portero no sabía más. Ocupado en cumplir los encargos de unas señoras sudamericanas, no
había podido saludar al joven cuando salió del hotel. Dudaba entre hacer el viaje en un vapor
inglés hasta Marsella ó ir por ferrocarril á Génova, donde encontraría buques directos para
Barcelona.

Ferragut quiso saber cuándo había llegado, y el portero, elevando los ojos, se entregó á un
largo cálculo mental... Al fin marcó una fecha, y el marino, á su vez, compulsó sus recuerdos.

Se dió en la frente una palmada, ruda como un puñetazo.

Era su hijo el joven que había visto entrando en el albergo cuando él marchaba á encargarse
de la goleta para llevar combustible á los submarinos alemanes.

VIII

EL JOVEN TELÉMACO

Siempre que el Mare nostrum volvía á Barcelona, Esteban Ferragut experimentaba una sensación
de deslumbramiento, lo mismo que si se abriese un glorioso ventanal en su existencia obscura
y monótona de hijo de familia.

Ya no vagaba por el puerto, admirando de lejos los grandes trasatlánticos anclados frente al
monumento de Colón ó los vapores de carga que se alineaban en los muelles comerciales. Un buque
importante era de su absoluta propiedad por algunas semanas. El capitán y los oficiales pasaban
el tiempo en tierra con sus familias. Tòni, el segundo, era el único que dormía á bordo. Muchos
de los marineros solicitaban permiso para vivir en la ciudad, y el vapor quedaba confiado á
la guarda del tío Caragòl, con media docena de hombres para la diaria limpieza.

El pequeño Ferragut podía hacerse la ilusión de que era el capitán del Mare nostrum. Se movía
en el puente imaginándose que estaba arrostrando una gran tormenta; examinaba los instrumentos
náuticos con una gravedad de experto conocedor; corría todos los departamentos habitables del
buque, bajaba á las bodegas, que se aireaban, abiertas, en espera de carga, y finalmente se
metía en el bote de servicio, desamarrándolo de la escala, para remar unas horas con más satisfacción
que en los ligeros yoles del Club de Regatas.

Sus visitas terminaban en la cocina, invitado por el tío Caragòl, que le trataba con una familiaridad
paternal. El joven remero estaba sudando. «¿Un refresquet?...» Y preparaba su dulce mixtura,
que hacía caer á los hombres de un solo salto en las nebulosidades de la embriaguez.

Esteban tenía en mucho los «refrescos» del cocinero. Su imaginación, excitada por la frecuente
lectura de novelas de viajes, le había hecho concebir un tipo de marino heroico, atrevido,
galanteador, y capaz de tragarse á jarros las bebidas más incendiarias sin pestañear. El quería
ser así; todo buen navegante debe beber.

Aunque en tierra no conocía otros licores que los inocentes y dulzones guardados por su madre
para las fiestas de familia, una vez pisaba la cubierta del buque sentía la necesidad de líquidos
alcohólicos, para hacer ver que era todo un hombre. «No había en el mundo una bebida que pudiese
con él...» Y al segundo «refresco» del tío Caragòl quedaba sumido en plácido nirvana, viéndolo
todo de color de rosa y considerablemente agrandado: el mar, los buques cercanos, los docks
y la montaña de Montjuich, que servía de fondo.

El cocinero, al contemplarle amorosamente con sus ojos enfermos, creía haber dado un salto
atrás de docenas de años y hallarse todavía en Valencia hablando con el otro Ferragut que se
escapaba de la Universidad para remar en el puerto. Casi llegó á creer que había vivido dos veces.

Escuchaba las quejas del muchacho, interrumpiéndolas con solemnes consejos. Este Ferragut de
quince años se mostraba descontento de la vida. Era un hombre, y tenía que vivir entre mujeres:
su madre y dos sobrinas que le acompañaban haciendo encajes, lo mismo que ella había acompañado
en otro tiempo á su suegra doña Cristina. Quería ser marino, y le obligaban á estudiar las
materias antipáticas del bachillerato. ¿Acaso un capitán necesita saber latín?...

Deseaba terminar su vida de estudiante, para hacerse piloto y seguir las prácticas en el puente,
al lado de su padre. Tal vez llegase á mandar á los treinta años el Mare nostrum ú otro buque
semejante.

Mientras tanto, la atracción del mar le arrastraba lejos de las aulas, yendo á ver á Caragòl
á la misma hora en que sus profesores pasaban lista á los alumnos, anotando sus ausencias.

El viejo y su protegido se recluían en la cocina con una inquietud de culpables. Pasos y voces
en la cubierta alteraban su conversación. «¡Escóndete!» Y Esteban se metía debajo de una mesa
ó se ocultaba en el cuartucho de las provisiones, mientras el cocinero salía al encuentro del
recién llegado con una cara seráfica.

Algunas veces era Tòni, y el muchacho osaba salir, contando con su silencio. También éste le
quería y aprobaba su aversión por los libros.

Si de tarde en tarde era el capitán el que venía al buque por unos momentos, Caragòl le hablaba
obstruyendo la puerta con su cuerpo, al mismo tiempo que sonreía maliciosamente.

Para Esteban, las dos cosas más dignas de admiración eran el mar y su padre. Todos los héroes
novelescos que desde las páginas de los libros habían pasado á alojarse en su imaginación tenían
el rostro y los gestos del capitán Ferragut.

De pequeño había visto llorar algunas veces á su madre con resignada tristeza. Años adelante,
al conocer con su precocidad de muchacho poco vigilado las relaciones que existen entre hombres
y mujeres, presintió que todas estas lágrimas debían ser motivadas por ligerezas é infidelidades
del lejano navegante.

El adoraba á su madre con una pasión de hijo único y mimado, pero no admiraba menos al capitán,
excusando todas las faltas que pudiese cometer. Su padre era el hombre más valiente y más hermoso
de la tierra. Así lo veía él. Y un día que, examinando los cajones de su camarote, encontró
varias fotografías de mujeres llevando al pie los nombres de lejanos países, su admiración
aún fué más grande. Todas debían haber enloquecido de amor por el capitán del Mare nostrum.
¡Ay! Por más que él hiciese al ser hombre, nunca llegaría á igualarse con este triunfador que
le había dado la existencia...

Cuando el buque llegó á Barcelona sin su propietario de vuelta de Nápoles, el hijo de Ferragut
no experimentó ninguna sorpresa.

Tòni, que era siempre de pocas palabras, las prodigó en la presente ocasión. El capitán Ferragut
se había quedado allá por un negocio importante, pero no tardaría en volver. Su segundo le
esperaba de un momento á otro. Tal vez hiciese el viaje por tierra, para llegar antes.

Esteban se asombró al ver que su madre no aceptaba esta ausencia como un suceso insignificante.
La buena señora se mostró preocupada y con los ojos lacrimosos. Su instinto femenil le hacía
presentir algo malo en el retraso de su marido.

Por la tarde, cuando la visitó, como de costumbre, su antiguo enamorado el catedrático, los
dos hablaron lentamente, con palabras medidas, pero entendiéndose con los ojos durante los
largos intervalos de silencio.

Llegado don Pedro á la cumbre de su carrera gloriosa con la posesión de una cátedra en el Instituto
de Barcelona, visitaba todas las tardes á Cinta, pasando hora y media en su salón con exactitud
cronométrica. Ni el más leve pensamiento de impureza agitó jamás al profesor. Lo pasado había
caído en el olvido... Pero él necesitaba ver diariamente á la esposa del capitán tejiendo encajes
entre sus dos pequeñas sobrinas, como había visto años antes á la viuda de Ferragut.

Le hacía saber los sucesos más importantes de Barcelona y del mundo entero; comentaban juntos
los futuros destinos de Esteban; oía él con arrobamiento su voz dulce, concediendo gran importancia
á los detalles de economía doméstica ó á las descripciones de fiestas religiosas, sólo porque
era ella la que hacía tales relatos.

Muchas veces quedaban en largo mutismo. Don Pedro representaba la paciencia, el humor igual,
el respeto silencioso, en aquella casa tranquila y limpia, que únicamente perdía su calma monástica
al presentarse el dueño por unos días, entre dos viajes.

Cinta se había acostumbrado á las visitas del catedrático. Al marcar el reloj las tres y media
presentía sus pasos en la escalera.

Si alguna tarde no llegaba, la dulce Penépole sufría una decepción.

--¿Qué le pasará á don Pedro?--preguntaba á sus sobrinas con inquietud.

Esta pregunta la hacía algunas veces extensiva al hijo; pero Esteban, sin odiar al visitante,
le apreciaba en muy poco.

Don Pedro pertenecía al grupo de aquellos señores del Instituto que pagaba el gobierno para
que fastidiasen con sus explicaciones y sus exámenes á la juventud. Recordaba aún los dos años
que había pasado en su cátedra, como en una cámara de tormento, sufriendo el suplicio del latín.
Además, era un miedoso, que siempre temía resfriarse y no osaba salir á la calle en los días
nublados si le faltaba el paraguas. A él que le hablasen de hombres valientes.

--No sé...--respondía á su madre--. Tal vez estará metido en cama, con siete pañuelos en la cabeza.

Cuando volvía don Pedro, la casa recobraba su normalidad de reloj pausado y seguro. Doña Cinta,
de consulta en consulta, había acabado por considerar indispensable su colaboración. El catedrático
suplía dulcemente la autoridad del marido viajero: él se había encargado de representar al
jefe de la familia en todos los asuntos exteriores... Muchas veces le esperaba con impaciencia
la esposa de Ferragut para pedirle un consejo urgente, y él emitía su opinión con voz lenta,
después de largas reflexiones.

Esteban encontraba intolerable que este señor, que no era mas que un pariente lejano de su
abuela, se mezclase en los asuntos de la casa, pretendiendo dirigirle á él como un padre. Pero
aún le irritaba más verlo de buen humor y con pretensiones de gracioso. Le daba rabia que llamase
á su madre Penépole y á él joven Telémaco... «¡Tío latero y pesado!»

El joven Telémaco no vacilaba en sus venganzas. De pequeño interrumpía sus diversiones para
«trabajar» en el recibidor, junto al perchero vecino á la puerta. Y el pobre catedrático encontraba
abollado su sombrero de copa, con los pelos en desorden, ó salía llevando en las haldas del
gabán varios salivazos.

Ahora el muchacho se limitaba á ignorar su existencia, pasando ante él sin reconocerle, saludándolo
únicamente cuando su madre se lo ordenaba.

El día en que trajo la noticia de la vuelta del vapor sin su capitán, don Pedro hizo la visita
más larga que de costumbre. Cinta derramó dos lágrimas sobre los encajes, pero tuvo que cortar
su llanto, vencida por el buen sentido de su consejero.

--¿Por qué llorar y calentarse la cabeza con tantas suposiciones sin fundamento?... Lo que
usted debe hacer, hija mía, es llamar á ese Tòni que es el segundo del buque. El debe saberlo
todo... Tal vez le diga la verdad.

Recibió Esteban el encargo de buscarle al día siguiente, y pudo darse cuenta de la inquietud
que experimentó Tòni al saber que doña Cinta quería hablarle. Salió del buque con lúgubre mutismo,
como si le llevasen á sufrir tormentos mortales. Luego canturreó sordamente, lo que era en
él indicio de honda preocupación.

No pudo asistir el joven Telémaco á la entrevista, pero rondó por las inmediaciones de la puerta
cerrada, alcanzando á oír algunas palabras en voz más fuerte que se deslizaron por las rendijas.
Su madre era la que hablaba con más frecuencia. Tòni repetía con voz sorda las mismas excusas:
«No sé. El capitán va á llegar de un momento á otro...» </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01154</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>646400</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22489</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> On the first night the captain tasted the voluptuous self the
break-out. I no longer had a woman at his side as an extension inevitable; living among men ...
And appreciated chastity as a pleasure that was offered with all the charms of new.

The second night, on the narrow, smelly standard camera, she was revealed by memories, returning
to sprout. Oh, Freya! ... When see her again! ...

The Count and he spoke little, but spent long hours together, sitting next to the wheel the helm,
watching the sea. Were more friends than on land, although they passed among them limited words.
The common life slowed down the arrogance of pretending diplomat
and was the captain discover new merits in him.

The ease with which he walked around the ship and certain technical
words used against their will Ferragut allowed no more doubts about
his true profession.

- You are a Marine - he said suddenly.

The Count nodded, judging dissimulation useless. Yes, it was ocean.

"So what am I doing here? What I have given command Ferragut thought ?...» So, without managing
Why sought their help this man who could run the ship without assistance.

Undoubtedly it was a naval officer, and a fleet should come from all sailors blonde who worked as
automatons. The discipline made them follow the orders of Ferragut, but they guessed that his
command was no more than a simple delegation, and that the real leader
board was the Count.

The schooner came in sight of the islands of Lipari, then twisting course toward the West, followed
the Sicilian coast from Cape Gallo after San Vito. From this set
her bow to the Southwest, going in search of the islands Egadi.

To expect in these waters, where it begins to narrow the Mediterranean
between Tunisia and Sicily towering volcanic peak of Pantelleria island
in the middle of the huge close.

Short enough for him to count instructions so that the direction taken by Ferragut was under to his
wishes. Ended up not hide the admiration he felt for his master navigator.

- Well you know the sea - said the count.

The captain shrugged smiling. It was truly yours. Could call mare nostrum, just like the Romans,
their former rulers.

As if divining the bottom to the naked eye, kept the ship on the edge of extensive bank of Adventure.
Sailed slowly with only a few candles, crossing and recrossing the same waters.

Kaledine, to spend two days, began to fret. Ferragut heard repeatedly muttering how Gibraltar's
name. The passage from the Atlantic to the Mediterranean was the greatest danger for he expected.

From
the deck of the schooner could only see a short distance, and the count rose again and times
scales of rope rigging, to cover his eyes with a larger space.

One morning he shouted from the top to the captain, pointing to a horizon point. Should do
course in the same direction. There were what he sought.

Ferragut obeyed him, and half an hour after they appeared, one after another, two long vessels
and low railing, sailing at high speed.

They were like destroyers, but without masts, without chimneys, sliding almost at water level,
painted a gray color that made them confused with the sea at a distance.

Placed on both sides of the boat, approaching it in such a way that seemed likely encontrón to
crush with their helmets.

Several metal wires grew out of their covers to screw in the sticks
of the schooner aground, forming a single mass of the three ships,
which together followed the slow wave of the sea.

Ulysses looked curiously at the two co-flotation. "These were the
famous underwater?

... Saw its steel roof hatches and chimneys protruding round, by
poking groups of animals.

The officers and crew were dressed as fishermen from the coast North,
wearing one-piece waterproof and waxed hull.

Many of them waved high in these helmets, and the Count replied waving his cap. Blonde sailors
the schooner shouted, responding to the cheers of his comrades of the submersible "Deutschland
über alles !...»

But this excitement in the solitude of the sea, which amounted to a song gives triumph lasted very
little.

Whistles sounded, the men ran covered sidewalks, and Ferragut saw invaded the vessel by two
rows of sailors.

At a time when the hatches were opened, hit a sound of broken timber and cans of essence began
to be transhipped from both sides. In around the boat was filled with water drawers open, they
walked away with gentle floating.

The Count heard in the stern a man dressed in waterproof fabric, which was an officer.

He related the passage through the Strait of Gibraltar completely submerged, looking through
the periscope the English torpedo on security patrol.

- Nothing
major - continued the officer -, nor the slightest incident ... A
great navigation.

- May God punish England!

"- Said the count, now called the commander.

- May God punish! - Said the officer, as if to say "Amen."

Ferragut saw forgotten, ignored by all these men who filled the schooner. Some sailors pushed
him in the haste of their work.

Was the patron of the boat, a civilian lack of hierarchy to be men of war.

Began to understand why he had been given command of the small vessel. The count remained. Saw
him approaching as if he suddenly remembered, holding out his right hand with kindness comradery.

-
Captain, thank you very much.

This service is for those who are not forgotten.

Maybe we will not never ... But if you ever need me, know who I am.

And as if presented to another person, said their names ceremoniously: Archibald von Kramer, Lieutenant
of the Imperial Navy ... His personality was not entirely diplomatic
false.

He had served as naval attache at various embassies.

Then he gave instructions for the return. Could expect to face Palermo. A boat would in search
of him to take you to the ground.

Everything was planned ... Should hand over the reins to the true owner of the schooner: a coward
who had become too expensive to pay the rent of the ship, but without daring to threaten him.
In the chamber were the papers in order to justify this navigation.

- Say hello on my behalf to the ladies ... Tell them you will soon hear about us. Let us make
us masters of the Mediterranean.

Continued unloading fuel.

Ferragut he saw Von Kramer introduced by the hood Open one of the submarines. Then she thought
she recognized in the other two sailors submersible of those who had manned the schooner, which
was received with shouts and hugs his comrades, then getting a tubular hatch.

The discharge lasted until midafternoon. Ulysses had not imagined that the small vessel will many
boxes. When the warehouse was empty, the last sailors disappeared Germanic and with them the
cables that held the boat.

An officer shouted that he could leave.

The two submersibles, more flattened on the sea on his arrival, with swollen deposits essence and oil,
began to move away.

Finding himself alone in the stern of the schooner, he felt a sudden uneasiness.

"What have you done? ... What have you done? "Cried a voice in his brain.

But looking to the three passengers and the boy who had been the only
crew forgot his remorse.

Should move a lot to make up for this lack of arms. Two nights and one day just rested, driving
around the same time the rudder and engine, it did not dare to employ all their sails with this
shortage of men.

When he found himself in a sunrise, opposite the port of Palermo, who began to extinguish their
lights, Ferragut could sleep for the first time, leaving manager to one of the sailors surveillance
the ship, which was maintained with the canopy collected. By mid-morning he was awakened voices
shouting from the sea, "Where is the captain?"

He saw a boat and several men who jumped to the schooner. He was the owner, who came to recover
their vessel to enter port it legally. The same can be commissioned to carry Ulysses ashore with
his little suitcase.

He was accompanied by a man red and obese, which seemed have great influence on the pattern.

- Since you will be aware of what happens - he said, as did two rowers glide the boat over the
waves -. These bandits ... These mandolinists! ...

Ulysses without knowing why, nodded. This was a German bourgeois indignation:
one of those who helped the doctor.

Hear enough.

Half an hour later, Ferragut jumped into a dock, no one objected to his landing like protecting
their fellow obese sleep every surveillance. Despite this, the good Lord showed a burning desire
away from him, to flee, according to their own issues.

He smiled when he learned that Odysseus wanted to leave immediately
for Naples.

"You do well ..." The train departed two hours later. And I got into a cab, disappearing precipitation.

The
captain, being alone, almost thought he had dreamed the previous days.

Palermo came back to see after an absence of many years.

Experienced the joy of a Sicilian banished to cross the country with several cars pulled by
hacks whose feathers and boxes defaced depicting scenes from the liberated Jerusalem. He recalled
the names of main roads, which were those of old Spanish viceroys.

He saw the statues in a square four kings of Spain ... But all these
things inspired him only a fleeting interest.

He was concerned about the extraordinary movement of the streets, the crowd forming groups to
hear reading newspapers. Many windows were intertwined with national flags France, England
and Belgium.

On arriving at the station knew the truth out about the incident he
had alluded to the merchant while they were in the boat.

It was war! ... Italy had broken off relations the day before with the Central Powers.

Ulysses felt troubled by anxiety, remembering what he had done in the Mediterranean. Popular
groups believed cheering passing behind the flags were going to guess
his achievement, landing on him.

Needed to get away from this patriotic enthusiasm, and felt satisfied to be inside of a car
... Also, going to see Freya, and its image was enough to evoke to vanish all his remorse.

The journey was long and difficult. The necessities of war were being felt from the first time
absorbing all the media.

The train stood still for hours to make way for other trains loaded
with men and military equipment.

In all seasons there were soldiers in battle dress, flags, crowds
cheered.

When he reached Naples, fatigued by a journey of forty-eight hours,
it seemed that the driver too slowly headed towards the old palace
of Chiaia.

In crossing the hall with his little suitcase, cut him off the goalkeeper, thick comadre frizzy
hair and dusty, there were only interviewed a few times in the depths of his cave.

- The ladies do not live in the house ... The ladies have gone suddenly
with Karl, his employee.

And he explained the rest of this flight with a hostile and evil smile.

Ferragut knew he should not insist. The big woman was furious about the leak of the ladies Tedesco, and
examining the ocean as a suspected spy, good for a complaint patriotic.

However, professional honesty, we warned that the blonde signora, the youngest and sympathetic had thought
of him to leave, leaving his luggage in the goal.

Ulises hastened to disappear. And send someone to collect your bags. And taking another carriage,
went to the harbor of Santa Lucia ... What unexpected blow!

At his entrance, the goalkeeper made a gesture of surprise and astonishment.

Before he reached Ferragut to ask for Freya, with the vague hope that they had taken refuge in
the hotel, this man gave him the news.

- Captain, his son was here, waiting.

The captain stammered, confused: "What son ?...»

The man brought the keys embroidered travel book, showing a line: "Esteban Ferragut. Barcelona.
"And recognized Ulysses the letter of your child while he pressed his chest with an indescribable
anguish.

The shock left him speechless, and the porter took advantage of his silence to keep talking.

It was a nice guy and intelligent ... Some mornings he had accompanied him to teach best of
the city. He had been connected with the consignees of the Mare Nostrum,
looking everywhere for news of his father.

At last, convinced that the captain was and back to Barcelona, ??had started to turn the previous
day.

- If you get twelve hours before, still here.

The doorman did not know more. Busy to meet the orders of a South American ladies, no was able
to greet the young man when he left the hotel. Torn between making the trip on a steam English
to Marseilles or go by train to Genoa, where to find direct ship Barcelona.

Ferragut wanted to know when he arrived, and the porter, raising his eyes, turned to a during
mental arithmetic ... Finally scored a date, and the sailor, in his
turn, was examined by his memories.

Was given a slap on the forehead, rough as a punch.

It was her young son had seen entering the harbor when he was going
to take charge the schooner to carry fuel to German submarines.

VIII

The young Telemachus

Whenever the Mare Nostrum back to Barcelona, ??Esteban Ferragut felt a sense glare, just as
if it was opened a glorious window in his dark existence child and family monotonous.

No longer wandering the harbor, admiring from afar the great ocean liners anchored off the Columbus
monument or cargo vapors that lined the commercial docks.

A vessel important was his absolute property for several weeks. The captain and officers spent
ground time with their families.

Toni, the second was the only one who slept on board. Many of the sailors asked permission to live
in the city, and the steam is entrusted to Caragol Uncle guard with half a dozen men for daily
cleaning.

The small Ferragut could be under the illusion that he was the captain of the Mare Nostrum. He
moved imagining that the bridge was braving a storm; examining instruments
water with a severity of knowledgeable expert, ran all departments
habitable ship, down to the cellars, which aireaban, open, pending
charge, and finally got into the boat service, undoing of the scale,
to row a few hours with more satisfaction Yoles that in light of the
Race Club.

His visits ended in the kitchen, invited by his uncle Caragol, who
treated him with a familiarity paternal.

The young oarsman was sweating. "A refresquet ?...» and preparing the sweet mixture, I did fall to
men of a single jump in the nebulosity of intoxication.

Stephen had much the "soft" chef. His imagination, excited by the frequent Travel reading novels had
made him conceive a type of marine heroic, daring, philanderer, and
able to swallow the beverage jars incendiary without blinking.

He wanted If so, every good mariner should drink.

While on the ground did not know other spirits that the innocent and sweet kept by his mother
family holiday once trod the deck of the ship felt the need for fluids
alcoholics, to show that he was a man.

"There was a beverage in the world that could with him ... And the second "refresh" the uncle
was sunk in a placid Caragol nirvana, seeing all pink and considerably enlarged: the sea, nearby ships,
the docks and the mountain of Montjuic, which served as background.

The cook, to behold with his eyes lovingly sick, he thought he had
a jump dozen years ago and is still in Valencia talking to the other
Ferragut that University escape to paddle in the harbor.

Almost came to believe that he had lived twice.

The boy listened to the complaints, interrupting with solemn advice.

This Ferragut fifteen years of life showed discontent. He was a man, and had to live among
women: his mother and two nieces who accompanied him making lace, as she had accompanied once
to his mother Dona Cristina. I wanted to be a sailor, and he was forced to study the Baccalaureate
unfriendly materials. Can a captain needs to know Latin? ...

Wanted to end his life as a student, to become a pilot and follow
the practices in the bridge next to his father.

Maybe you'll command the thirty years or another ship Mare Nostrum similar.

Meanwhile, the lure of the sea drew him away from the classroom, going to see Caragol at the
same time the roll call teachers to the students, noting their absence.

The old man and his protégé are recruited in the kitchen with a responsible
concern.

Steps and voices on the cover altered their conversation. "Hide!" And Stephen crawled under
a table or hidden in the storeroom of the provisions, while the cook came out to meet the newcomer
with a seraphic face.

Sometimes it was Toni, and the boy ventured out, with his silence. It also will wanted and approved
of his distaste for the books.

If from time to time was the captain who came to the ship for a few
moments, he spoke Caragol obstructing the door with his body, while
smiling slyly.

For Stephen, the two most worthy of admiration were the sea and his father. All heroes novelistic
that from the pages of the books had gone to stay in his imagination had the face and gestures
of Captain Ferragut.

As a child he had seen sometimes to mourn his mother with sad resignation. Years later, to meet
with his precocious little boy watched the relationships between
men and women, he felt that all these tears should be motivated by
indiscretions and infidelities Far navigator.

He loved his mother with a passion only child and spoiled, but not least the captain admired,
excusing all sins that might commit.

His father was the bravest man and most beautiful land. So he saw it. And one day, examining the
drawers in his cabin, found several photographs of women wearing the foot the names of distant countries,
his admiration was even larger. All must be mad with love for the captain of the Mare Nostrum.
Ay! For more than him to do to be a man, never get to catch up with
the winner to had given the existence ...

When the ship came to Barcelona
without their owner around Naples, the son of Ferragut experienced
no surprise.

Toni, who was always short, lavished on this occasion.
Captain Ferragut had been there for a business, but would soon return.
His second will expected at any moment. Perhaps hiciese land travel
to get there first.

Esteban was amazed to see that his mother did
not accept this absence as an insignificant event. The good lady was
concerned and the watery eyes. Her feminine instinct made him sensed
something wrong with the delay of her husband.

In the afternoon,
when he visited, as usual, his former love the professor, the two
spoke slowly, with measured words, but understood his eyes during
the long intervals of silence.

Pedro arrived at the pinnacle of his
illustrious career with the possession of a professorship at the Institute
Barcelona, ??visiting every afternoon to tape, and a half hours from
his room exactly clockwork. Not the slightest thought of impurity
professor never stirred. The past had forgotten ... But he needed
daily to see the captain's wife knitting lace between two young nieces
as she had seen years before the widow of Ferragut.

Let him know
the most important events in Barcelona and around the world, discussing
them the future destiny of Stephen, he heard her sweet voice with
rapture, to attach great importance to the details of domestic economy
or to the descriptions of religious holidays, just because it was
she who had such accounts.

Often remained in a long silence. Don
Pedro represented patience, humor equal respect silent, quiet and
clean the house, lost his composure only monastic the present owner
for a few days, including two trips.

Tape had been accustomed to
the visits of Professor. By checking the clock half past three sensed
his footsteps on the stairs.

If any evening did not arrive, the sweet
Penépole suffered a disappointment.

- What will happen to Don Pedro?
- Asked with concern to his nieces.

This question was sometimes extended
to the child, but Stephen, without hating the visitor liked him very
little.

Don Pedro belonged to the group of those gentlemen of the
Institute that the government paid for teaser with their explanations
and their reviews to the youth. Still remembered two years had happened
in his chair, and in a chamber of torture, suffering the punishment
of Latin. He was also a coward, always afraid and did not dare take
cold to go out on days cloudy if the umbrella was missing. He spoke
of you brave men.

- I do not know his mother answered ...-- -. May
be stuck in bed, with seven headscarves.

When I returned Don Pedro,
the house resumed its normal slow clock and safe. Doña Film, from
consultation to consultation, he had finally consider indispensable
for your cooperation. Professor sweetly made up for the husband's
authority traveler, he had to represent the head of the family in
all foreign affairs ... I often looked forward to Ferragut's wife
for advice urgently, and he issued his opinion in a slow voice, after
much reflection.

Esteban was intolerable that this man, who was but
a distant relative of grandmother, meddling in the affairs of the
house, trying to address him as a father. But irritated him even more
to see in a good mood and with claims of funny. He was angry that
flames Penépole his mother and him Telemachus ... "Uncle lateral and
heavy!"

The young Telemachus did not hesitate in their revenge. Small
interrupted their diversions for "Work" in the hall, next to the neighbor
to the door hanger. And the poor professor was dented his top hat,
hair in disarray, or in carrying out the Haldas several spit coat.

Now
the boy was confined to ignore its existence, going before him without
giving him, greeting him only when his mother told him to.

The day
brought news of the return of steam without their captain, Don Pedro
made the visit longer than usual. Tape shed two tears on the laces,
but had to cut her tears, overcome by the good sense to your counselor.

-
Why mourn and head warm with so many unfounded assumptions? ... What
you should do, my dear, is to call that Toni is the second ship. He
should know all ... Maybe tell you the truth.

Stephen received the
commission to seek the next day, and could see the concern Toni experienced
knowing that he wanted to talk Dona Cinta. Ship left the gloomy silence,
as if it leads to death suffer torture. Then she sang quietly, it
was in The indication of serious concern.

Unable to attend the young
Telemachus to the interview, but he hung near the door closed overheard
some words louder than they slipped through the cracks. His mother
was the one who spoke more often. Toni dully repeating the same excuses:
"I do not know. The captain is going to get from one point to another
... </suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>