<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05174</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>182042</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24595</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Mientras que la capital catalana y Málaga, Valencia, Alicante y Gibraltar
le disputan el tráfico que gira hácia el Mediterráneo, Sevilla, Coruña, Santander y Bilbao
le hacen competencia del lado del Atlántico. Su poblacion, que en tiempo de la dominación española
en América no bajaba de 100,000 habitantes, hoy está reducida á poco mas de 70,000.

Cádiz me interesaba por sus tradiciones bajo todos aspectos. De allí salieron las mas importantes
expediciones españolas, tanto en la época de las colonizaciones emprendidas sobre el Nuevo
Mundo, como durante la terrible guerra de la independencia de «Colombia,» Méjico, Perú, Chile,
Buenos-Aires, etc. La libertad colombiana no tuvo en ninguna parte enemigos tan implacables
como en Cadiz, residencia de la famosa compañía que tuvo el monopolio del comercio entre Europa
y varias colonias hispano-colombianas. Y cosa singular, que prueba cuánto los intereses del
monopolio influyen en la política de las naciones!--esa misma población gaditana que tan cruda
guerra hiciera á la revolución del Nuevo Mundo, era en la misma época el refugio de los patriotas
españoles y el arca de salvación para la nacionalidad de España, en su heroica lucha contra
Napoleón y el despotismo.... Cuántos males ha sufrido el pueblo español, por no haber comprendido
desde entonces que la causa de la libertad y del derecho era la misma en España que en Colombia,
y que los patriotas de uno y otro mundo debían aliarse como hermanos en vez de hacerse la guerra!

Otros recuerdos me asaltaban en Cádiz. Aparte de sus defensas heroicas contra los Ingleses,
en 1626, 1772 y 1797, y contra los Franceses en 1811; aparte también de sus interesantes episodios
políticos, su constitución liberal de 1812 y la heróica revolución de 1820 encabezada por Riego
y Quiroga, Cádiz me hacia recordar que allí había nacido ese feroz brigadier Enrile, pacificador
de espantosa memoria en mi patria; y que allí murió miserable, hambriento y lacerado por mil
amarguras, en el fondo de un calabozo, el ilustre y generoso Miranda, guerrero de la revolución
francesa y mártir de la independencia colombiana, tratado por unos con suprema ingratitud y
por otros con una fría crueldad!

La faja de altas murallas (dobles y aún triples en algunas partes) que rodea completamente
á Cádiz, tiene una circunferencia de 7,500 varas españolas. Así, por donde quiera que el viajero
pretende buscar una salida tropieza con una masa enorme de piedra, soldados y cañones, viendo
al pié las ondas espumosas del océano estrellándose con violencia en los bancos de arena y
los peligrosos arrecifes que avecinan la isla y sirven de asiento á castillos y fortificaciones.
Si la vista sobre la bahía es pintoresca y variada, la que se tiene sobre el océano, al sur
y sud-oeste, desde el paseo de la «Alameda» es de una majestad imponente. Desde el primer momento,
Cádiz me habia ofrecido muchas semejanzas de aspecto con la ciudad de Cartagena en «Nueva Granada».
Semejanza no es el término propio: es no sé qué analogía vaga en la configuracion de la isla
y las bahías, en la estructura exterior de la ciudad; algo de muy armónico en el estilo de
las fortificaciones, en la atmósfera y el cielo. Al recorrer el hermoso paseo de la Alameda,
las plazas y las calles, y observar las gentes allí, la comunidad de tipo me pareció evidente.
En cada elegante gaditana creia ver una hija de Cartagena: el acento, los modales, la soltura,
el garbo lleno de gentileza y dengue, el ojo negro y dulce, la sonrisa de adorable coquetería,
la tez de un moreno suave y pálido, el andar mesurado y señoril, la amabilidad y la franqueza
insinuante, y un no sé qué de voluptuoso en el vestir, en las formas delicadas pero expresivas
y en el juego del inevitable abanico,--todo contribuia á producirme una ilusion que me hizo
pensar en la patria.

El sol se hundia como una brasa fulgurante en las ondas de un horizonte infinito; la Alameda
estaba poblada de paseantes y habia por do quiera una encantadora animacion. El escenario parecia
una gran canasta de flores flotando entre los remolinos de un torrente. El mar producia al
pié de las murallas sus formidables chasquidos, lanzando nubes instantáneas de espuma, miéntras
que centenares de paseantes vagaban por en medio de las arboledas y los lindos jardines de
la «Alameda», casi bajo los balcones y las celosías de las espléndidas casas que dominan los
malecones y terraplenes. Los techos reverberando,--los pintorescos balcones verdes y azules,--las
altas y elegantes azoteas de estilo morisco,--los arbustos cuajados de flores y perfumes,--los
grupos animados de una poblacion en que se veian tipos muy variados,--los mármoles resplandecientes
de las casas mas lujosas,--los lejanos castillos destacándose sobre las ondas,--las montañas,
confusas en lontananza,--el mar encrespado y sacudiéndose bajo su manto de luz crepuscular,--el
sol, enorme por un efecto de óptica, como bañándose en el océano,--la brisa agitando suavemente
los árboles,--el cielo de una hermosura extraordinaria;--todo aquello me llenó de encanto,
de embriaguez, dejándome en el alma una hondísima impresion que nunca olvidaré.

El tiempo me faltaba para hacer observaciones detenidas. España es un país que no puede ser
bien estudiado en ménos de tres años, y yo solo pódia disponer de tres meses para recoger impresiones,
reparando en las cosas mas salientes é importantes. Ningun monumento me pareció en Cádiz digno
de especial atencion bajo el punto de vista artístico. Lo que hace de esa ciudad una poblacion
interesante es su posicion, su conjunto, su estilo particular de construcciones, su aire social,
sus recuerdos históricos y su valor económico.

Cádiz, que tanto habia decaido como plaza mercantil desde que perdió la explotacion de Colombia,
comienza á recobrar su animacion, gracias á las nuevas líneas de vapores, á notables mejoras
en las vias de comunicacion hácia el interior de la Andalucía, y al despertamiento económico
que ha tenido España desde 1855. Sus exportaciones consisten en sal, aceite, vinos, frutas
secas y otros artículos andaluces;--es una plaza importante de escala y depósito, y fabrica
algunos objetos de bellas artes, así como los de aplicacion á la marina. La pesca le procura
considerables utilidades. Asentada sobre una roca viva, ya que le faltan las aguas corrientes
las tiene superiores en sus vastas y numerosísimas cisternas. Posee hermosos hospitales y un
gran número de institutos de enseñanza, beneficencia, crédito, comercio y navegacion.

Desde luego que el clima, la influencia de la dominacion morisca y el gusto español, han determinado
en Cádiz el mismo género de construcciones que en casi toda la península y especialmente en
las Andalucías. Asi, las calles son en lo general ó en su mayor número angostas y sombrías,
tortuosas, desiguales y llenas de capricho. Pero hay allí un sello particular de elegancia
y gusto que no se encuentra en ninguna otra de las grandes ciudades españolas, exceptuando
á Sevilla. Se siente un vivo placer al recorrer casi todas las calles de Cádiz, ó al reposar
bajo la espesa sombra de las magníficas arboledas de las plazas de «San Antonio» y de «Mina».
Aparte del interes que excitan los corrillos de gentes de todas condiciones y las tiendas elegantes
llenas de curiosidades, donde quiera se camina de sorpresa en sorpresa al recorrer las mejores
calles, las que no empedradas ricamente embaldosadas.

Por todas partes los graciosos balcones, las discretas celosías, veladas en su interior por
finos cortinajes, tras de cuyos pliegues se alcanzan á ver medio escondidas algunas caras primorosas
como apariciones ideales; los aéreos miradores de cristal, empinados caprichosamente sobre
los techos; las ventanas con enrejados de hierro curiosísimos; las vastas azoteas adornadas
de jarrones con flores y pequeños arbustos bañados por el sol y agitados por las brisas marinas.
Pero nada tan curioso, tan deliciosamente bello y suntuoso como las casas de los mas ricos
propietarios, en las principales plazas y calles, verdaderos palacios de hadas, de un orientalismo
encantador. En todas ellas una portada magnífica de mármol ó rico jaspe, trabajada con esmero;
un zaguán que parece la antesala de una suntuosa habitación, con el pavimento y los muros de
mármol, el techo estucado y la puerta interior de soberbios cristales con labrados de arabescos
y bellos colores. La puerta está siempre abierta durante el dia. Os acercáis, y un criado desciende
la escalera al punto y os invita con la mayor atención á visitar la casa, aunque la familia
esté presente. Si aceptáis, el propietario (algún opulento negociante) se presenta, y con una
obligante cordialidad casi irresistible,--al ver que sois extranjero--os repite la invitacion,
os ruega que subais, os pregunta si quereis tomar un refresco, etc.

Yo había visto espléndidos palacios y suntuosos hoteles en Francia, en Inglaterra, en Barcelona
y Madrid; pero no tenia idea de casas tan preciosas, tan romanescamente orientales como las
que visité en Cádiz y Sevilla. Pasais adelante del zaguan, y os encontrais en un patio cuadrado
y claustrado, en cuyos cuatro costados se levanta el edificio, cubierto por una alta cúpula
de cristal que lo hace parecer un invernáculo. A los lados, en el piso bajo, se ven los vastos
salones destinados á los negocios ú oficinas del propietario; en el fondo hay un elegante pasadizo
que conduce á los patios interiores (los verdaderos patios), destacándose á los lados, ya en
caracol, ya en ángulos rectos, las escaleras monumentales que conducen á los tres, cuatro ó
cinco pisos de la casa. Desde la base hasta la cúpula de cristal se proyectan en todo el interior
del patio-salon tantos órdenes de balcones continuos y claustrados cuantos pisos tiene la casa.
No hay un pavimento en ese patio cubierto (que es como la sala central), en las escaleras,
los balcones interiores y todas las piezas del edificio, que no se componga de soberbias baldosas
cuadradas de mármol blanco y azul, ó negro ó jaspeado; no hay un balcon, una puerta, una baranda
que no tenga mil arabescos y primorosas molduras de un gusto exquisito; no hay una pared que
no esté ricamente estucada y labrada. Cada patio tiene en el centro una preciosa fuente de
mármol con surtidores que refrescan el aire, y en todo el recinto se ven grandes jarras de
gaspe, de porcelana, etc., conteniendo arbustos delicados, macetas de jazmines, rosas y claveles,
naranjillos en flor, enredaderas ó parásitas, que embalsaman aquella atmósfera embriagadora.
Se cree uno soñando con algo de los Cuentos orientales; y para que el deleite sea completo
para el amador de bellas artes, cada patio de esos tiene unas cuantas estatuas de mármol y
ostenta en sus muros diez ó doce hermosos cuadros de pintura.

La luz del sol, cayendo verticalmente á medio día, ó entrando debilitada por la parte baja,
prodúce los mas extraños efectos de brillantez, de sombra y claro oscuro; y por la noche, cuando
el interior está iluminado por el gas, ese museo-jardin en cuyo centro murmuran las aguas del
surtidor, es de una hermosura arrebatadora. Es allí donde se reúnen las familias, se reciben
las visitas y se goza en las tertulias domésticas, durante las horas mas calurosas en los meses
de estío, cuando no tiene la preferencia la azotea.

En Cádiz el mármol está prodigado en todas partes. En los grandes hoteles, en los numerosos
y espléndidos cafés, en los teatros, las iglesias, las plazas y todos los monumentos hay un
lujo de pavimentos que admira. El café de «Apolo», uno de los mas bellos y originales que he
conocido, divierte y llama la atención al viajero, y da una idea del carácter ardiente, cordial,
voluptuoso y expansivo de la población gaditana. Durante las primeras horas de la noche, las
plazas de San Antonio y Mina (la primera sobre todo) y las grandes calles adyacentes, tienen
mucha animacion y ofrecen los mas curiosos cuadros de costumbres. Las mujeres de Cádiz son
generalmente bellas, picantes y atractivas: eso, y la condición mercantil de la ciudad, hacen
la desgracia de ellas en las clases mas expuestas á debilidades y seducciones. Así, la prostitución
tiene en Cádiz proporciones que espantan. Es inaudito el número de mujeres desgraciadas en
ese género de establecimientos de corrupción, y de expertas en la infamia que especulan con
la dirección de esas casas, que son la ignominia de las sociedades europeas. Contáronme cosas
qué me aterraron, y anécdotas respecto de personas de la alta sociedad que, al ser ciertas,
darían una idea muy triste de la moralidad gaditana. No quiero creer todo lo qué se me dijo
por algunas personas; y sinembargo llevé de Cádiz, bajo ese aspecto, dolorosas impresiones....
Mucho podría decir sobre lo que he observado en las grandes ciudades españolas; pero el asunto
es repugnante y escabroso, y el mundo colombiano, por fortuna, no conoce ciertas cosas que
es mejor que ignore siempre. Hay tantos sofismas en la civilización europea...tantas miserias
que deshonran el progreso y hacen aveces tener vergüenza de lo que hace la humanidad.... En
España hay un contraste singular: la religion no es libre: el que no es creyente católico no
puede tributarle culto á Dios;--pero la prostitucion no solo está legitimada por la ley, sino
que la autoridad la reglamenta y dirige con esmero!

Bastaría para juzgar de la organización de ese país (cuyo pueblo tiene admirables cualidades
características y graves defectos de educación) el hecho simple de estos dos contrastes: la
ley especula con el juego por medio de las loterías, pero restrinje el trabajo inocente y fecundo;
mantiene y dirige la prostitucion, pero oprime la conciencia y condena a prisión al que distribuye
la Biblia y los Evangelios sin las notas del padre Scio!!

       *       *       *       *       *

Apesar del interes que podía tener la ciudad de Jerez, como población fuerte y gran centro
de producción vinícola, teníamos mas vivos deseos de navegar el bajo Guadalquivir desde su
desembocadura hasta Sevilla. Preferimos, pues, esa via, pero ántes de embarcarnos quisimos
conocer las interesantes poblaciones vecinas á Cádiz. Tomando un coche y saliendo del recinto
de la ciudad por la carretera que conduce á Jerez, es fácil visitar a San Fernando, Puerto-Real
y Puerto-Santa-María.

El paisaje, si se mira hácia el continente, es monótono, por la igualdad del terreno y la naturaleza
de los cultivos; pero es pintoresco y animado, si se tiende la vista del lado del mar, sea
para reparar en los astilleros de la bahía, donde hay bastante movimiento, sea para echar una
rápida mirada á las extensas salinas de San Fernando, cuya produccion es muy considerable y
ocupa á un gran número de trabajadores. La sal está monopolizada en España, probablemente para
probar á Dios una infinita gratitud por haber rodeado de mares á la península española. Ese
monopolio (que le produce al Estado una fuerte renta, no obstante el contrabando) proporciona
á los Españoles las inestimables ventajas de comer la sal de sus inmensas costas muy cara y
mala, sin que por eso dejen de hacer su negocio los especuladores en grande que explotan el
estanco de sales.

La ciudad de San Fernando, separada de Cádiz por fortalezas, murallas y un gran foso marítimo
que corta la isla de Leon, está situada hácia el extremo de esta, que se liga al continente
por dos puentes. En las cercanías hay numerosos huertos de frutales, y por todas partes se
revela en las vastas salinas, los artilleros y las fábricas, la naturaleza de su produccion.
Sus elementos principales son: la sal, en muy fuerte cantidad (que se exporta), tierras metalóideas,
encurtidos y objetos de fundición y de marina, como de artes y oficios. La situación, de la
ciudad es curiosa, por la forma que tiene el canal semi-circular que la rodea del lado del
continente y que determina la isla. Tal parece como si dos largas y angostísimas bahías ó lenguas
de aguas marinas fuesen á chocarse y confundirse bajo los puentes de Zuazo y Chiclana, que
dan paso hácia el interior del pais.

San Fernando tiene semejanzas generales con Cádiz en su estructura exterior, y el aspecto es
poco mas ó menos análogo. No tiene otra particularidad que su observatorio astronómico, que
es muy inferior al de Cádiz, tan famoso en la geografía española y colombiana. La población
de San Fernando alcanza á unos 17,000 habitantes, generalmente laboriosos y ocupados en rudos
trabajos de fabricación y artefactos. Los innumerables ventorrillos ó casas aisladas que avecinan
á San Fernando del lado de Cádiz tienen un aspecto original y pintoresco; es allí donde se
aglomeran los millares de obreros que trabajan en el astillero de la Carraca y en muchas fábricas
de las cercanías, formando en algunas horas del dia multitud de grupos tan animados como curiosos.
Al pasar por en medio de ellos se siente un fuerte olor de brea, sal y otras materias que revelan
desde el primer instante el género de ocupación de estas gentes.

El astillero de la Carraca, especie de población flotante y sólida al mismo tiempo, que se
compone de buques, almacenes y vastos talleres, ofrece un cuadro muy interesante, no tanto
por el mérito del establecimiento cuanto por el aire de los trabajadores, los edificios, etc.
Es en ese astillero, situado en la bahía, cerca de las salinas, como á 1,200 metros de San
Fernando, donde España tiene una de sus mejores fábricas navales. Allí se construyen buques
de guerra, y aún de comercio á veces, de todos tamaños y condiciones, y se hace el carenaje,
así como se trabajan en grande escala lonas para velas, jarcias, cordajes, etc. Millares de
obreros trabajan constantemente en ese punto de la bahía y su vecindad, ya en la fabricacion
naval, ya en la explotación y fabricacion de la sal. Después se extienden en varias direcciones
muchas obras de fortificación, que son en cierto modo los baluartes de Cádiz y del fondo de
la bahía.

Puerto-Real, situado en la costa continental, en el fondo de la bahía, es una bonita poblacion
de 5,000 almas. La vecindad de la embocadura del Zurraque (al sur) confundido ya con un brazo
de mar, y del Guadalete, que entra al norte, en el rincon de la bahía; la estructura moderna
de las calles y las casas (generalmente simétricas) y de su muelle y su puerto llenos de pescadores
de mariscos y bateleros cargando agua; el cuadro que forman á los dos lados, equidistantes,
él astillero de la Carraca y el del «Trocadero» (de uso mercantil) que está al poniente sobre
la bahía; la animacion de las gentes y la gracia de los huertos vecinos y las casas de campo,--todo
eso contribuye á hacer de Puerto-Real una poblacion pintoresca y alegre. Aquel es el lugar
de paseo y descanso para los ricos gaditanos, muchos de ellos poseedores de casas y quintas
de recreo en ese punto de la costa española.

«Puerto-Santa-María» es mucho mas considerable. Demora, como he dicho, en el fondo de un pequeño
golfo (al nor-oeste de Puerto-Real) cuyas aguas están separadas de la bahía de Cádiz por la
península ó lengua de tierra donde se encuentra el «Trocadero». Santa-María, que dista unos
14 kilómetros de Jerez y 21 de Cádiz, es el término de la carretera de Sevilla, y por allí
pasa el ferrocarril recientemente concluido. Desde allí se extiende un terreno de imponderable
riqueza en viñedos esmeradamente cultivados (así como otros muchos frutales), sea del lado
de Jerez, hácia el interior, sea por la costa, en la dirección de Rota (el país del famoso
tintilla) y del bajo Guadalquivir. La distancia entre Santa-María y Puerto-Real es tan corta,
con el Guadalete de por medio, que en realidad la primera parece pertenecer tanto á la bahía
misma como al golfo mencionado. Sus comunicaciones principales con Cádiz se sostienen por medio
de vapores que salen de un buen muelle y cruzan la bahía constantemente.

Santa-María es una bella población, con mas de 21,000 habitantes, con mucha actividad y movimiento
agrícolas, industrial y mercantil. Yace á la falda de una colina, dominando la márgen derecha
del Guadalete, y está literalmente rodeada de huertos y viñedos. Tiene numerosos institutos
públicos, bastantes fábricas (principalmente de excelentes licores, encurtidos, sombreros y
jabon), y aparte de su fuerte produccion de vinos, cultiva muchas artes y oficios. La estructura
general es buena, notablemente su hermosa calle llamada Larga. Se ve allí el tipo de las poblaciones
andaluzas, activas y laboriosas en lo general, donde no se revela casi nunca ningún síntoma
de miseria ó decaimiento.

       *       *       *       *       *

El tiempo nos faltaba para continuar la excursion. Así, entramos á un pequeño vapor costanero
y volvimos á Cádiz. Debíamos partir para Sevilla al día siguiente, y aprovechamos la segunda
noche que nos quedaba visitando un teatro y algunos cafés. Nada de particular en el teatro,
elegante y bien concurrido (porque el pueblo español es muy apasionado por los espectáculos
que impresionan fuertemente ó hacen reír); pero hallamos, cómo en casi toda España, una farsa
cantada á trozos, con el nombre de zarzuela, y las consabidas evoluciones coreográficas de
estilo francés,--pestes insoportables que van haciéndole perder su originalidad y su gracia
al teatro español. En vez de una buena comedia ó un buen drama (como hay de sobra en España)
el público tiene que tragarse como puede una opereta bufa de mal gusto, que degrada al mismo
tiempo á la comedia y la ópera.

En desquite, el café es en todas las ciudades españolas un elemento social sumamente curioso.
Para un habitante del norte de Europa nada puede ser mas desagradable quizas; pero para un
hijo del mediodía ó de Hispano-Colombia, con instintos de expansion y sociabilidad, la escena
tiene muchos atractivos. Ya he dicho, al hablar de Barcelona y Madrid, lo mas digno de atención
acercada los cafés en España. Como el espíritu de las poblaciones es enérgicamente liberal
en todas las grandes ciudades españolas, y muy particularmente en las Andalucías, el café,--elemento
de expansión franca y libre, de discusion y de censura,--es mucho mas importante aún en Cádiz,
Sevilla, etc., donde la opinion liberal saca de él todo el partido posible. El piano (mueble
infalible en los grandes cafés) contribuye á despertar los ánimos y aumentar el bullicio de
los centenares de parroquianos,--sirviendo no pocas veces de instrumento epigramático, segun
el humor de los concurrentes. Es muy frecuente el manifestar allí las tendencias de oposición
al gobierno nacional, de aversión al gobierno francés, etc., haciendo ejecutar (con aplausos
estrepitosos y unánimes) ya el himno de Riego, ya la Marsellesa, ú otra pieza que entrañe una
fuerte alusión política.

El café de Apolo, donde nos establecimos en Cádiz durante algunas horas, en dos noches, nos
procuró el medio de hacer curiosas observaciones en cuanto á las costumbres políticas de los
gaditanos. Hasta la singular estructura interior del café contribuía á hacer interesante la
escena, pues había cierta semejanza con las casas elegantes que he descrito, pudiéndose observar
desde uno de los altos balcones que dominaban el gran salón todos los grupos y pormenores simultáneamente.
Yo me aturdía de oir á los españoles hablando sobre los más graves asuntos: me parecía estar
en un café de Bogotá (donde se habla con absoluta libertad) aunque, á decir verdad, hallaba
mas tolerancia mútua en las francas y vehementes discusiones de los españoles. Se decian las
mayores claridades, sin insultarse, pero sazonadas con la consabida pimienta española de las
tres C.C.C., sin que hubiese el menor temor de una desavenencia. Hablaban de la reina...primores;
ponían al ministerio de vuelta y média, ó descargaban su hilaridad epigramática y sus terribles
censuras sobre el Capitán general, el Gobernador, el Obispo ó el primer personaje que hallaban
á la mano. Es realmente rara la facilidad y el chiste con que el pueblo español maneja el epigrama
y sabe aplicar un refrán en toda oportunidad.

Esa singular importancia política y social de los cafés en España me hizo reflexionar un poco.
Ella data de los tiempos del gobierno constitucional, de manera que es una institución muy
moderna. ¿Es un bien, ó es un mal?--me preguntaba yo. Desde luego que el café convertido en
club tiene sus ventajas: tiende á suprimir ese aislamiento que helaba á la sociedad española,
y la enervaba y mantenía en la impotencia moral é intelectual; distrae de la tentación del
juego, tan general en España (por causa de las instituciones), y es un gran elemento de fusión
de las clases sociales y de organización libre de la opinion pública, opuesto á las trabas
que la encadenan bajo formas mas generales y ostensibles. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03860</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>144594</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22381</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> While the Catalan capital and Malaga, Valencia, Alicante and Gibraltar traffic
dispute will turn towards the Mediterranean, Seville, Coruña, Santander and Bilbao competition
make it across the Atlantic. Its population, which at the time of Spanish rule America did not lower
than 100.000 inhabitants, is now reduced to just over 70,000.

Cadiz traditions I was interested in every respect. From there came the most important Spanish
expeditions, both at the time of settlements undertaken on the New World, and during the terrible
war of independence "Colombia," Mexico, Peru, Chile, Buenos-Aires, etc. Colombian freedom was
not anywhere as implacable enemies as in Cadiz, the residence of the famous company that had a
monopoly of trade between Europe and several Spanish-Colombian colonies. And strange to say,
that proves how much the interests of influence the political monopoly of the nations - the same
people who so raw Cadiz war do to the revolution of the New World, was at the same time the refuge
of the Patriots Spanish and the ark of salvation for the nationality of Spain, in their heroic
struggle against Napoleon and despotism .... Many ills suffered by the Spanish people, without understanding
since the cause of freedom and the right was the same in Spain than in Colombia, and that the patriots
of both worlds as brothers were to ally rather than make war!

Other memories assaulted me in Cadiz. Aside from its heroic defense against the English, in 1626, 1772
and 1797, and against the French in 1811, also apart of the interesting episodes political, liberal
constitution of 1812 and the heroic revolution of 1820 led by Irrigation and Quiroga, Cádiz me to
remember that there was born that fierce Brigadier Enrile, peacemaker awful memory of my homeland,
and died there miserable, hungry and lacerated by a thousand bitterness at the bottom of a dungeon,
the illustrious and generous Miranda, warrior revolution French and Colombian independence
martyr, treated by some with ingratitude and supreme by others with
a cold cruelty!

The belt of high walls (double and even triple in some areas) that completely surrounds at Cadiz,
has a circumference of 7.500 Spanish yards. Thus, wherever the traveler aims to find a solution
runs into a mass of stone, soldiers and guns, seeing foam at the bottom of the ocean waves crashing
violently into the sand banks and the dangerous reefs that serve the island ahead seating to
castles and fortifications. If the view of the bay is picturesque and varied, which has over the ocean
south and south-west from the walkway of the "Alameda" is a breathtaking majesty. From the outset,
Cadiz had offered me many similarities in appearance with the city of Cartagena in "New Granada."
Similarity is not the word itself: I do not know what analogy is vague in the configuration
of the island and bays, the exterior structure of the city, something very harmonious style
fortifications, in the atmosphere and sky. Touring the beautiful Paseo de la Alameda, the squares
and streets, and observe the people there, the guy community was apparent. In every elegant Cadiz
believed to see a daughter of Cartagena: the accent, the manners, the ease, panache full of kindness
and dengue, black eye and sweet, adorable smile of coquetry, the complexion of a soft, pale brown,
measured and lordly gait, kindness and openness insinuating, and I do not know what's voluptuous
dress, delicate but expressive forms and the inevitable game fan, - all contributed to produce
an illusion that made me think of the country.

The sun sank like a glowing ember in the waves of an infinite horizon, the Alameda was full
of walkers and had to do like a charming animation. The stage seemed a large basket of flowers
floating in the eddies of a stream. The sea produced the standing of its formidable walls
clicking, releasing clouds of foam snapshots, whilst hundreds of walkers roamed amid the groves
and beautiful gardens the 'Alameda', almost under the balcony and the shutters of the splendid houses
that dominate the levees and embankments. The reverberating roof, - the picturesque balconies
green and blue - the tall, graceful Moorish-style roofs, - the bush filled with flowers and perfumes,
- the animated groups of a population in which they looked very different types - gleaming marble
more luxurious houses - castles standing on the distant waves, - the mountains, confused in the
distance - the rough seas and swaying under her mantle of twilight, - the sun, a large optical
effect, such as swimming in the ocean - stirring gently in the breeze trees, - the extraordinary
beauty of heaven, - all this filled me with charm, intoxicated, leaving
the soul a very profound impression that I will never forget.

I needed time to look carefully. Spain is a country that can not be well studied in less than three
years, and I could only have three months to collect impressions, noticing things more salient
and important. No monument found me worthy Cadiz special attention under the artistic point of view.
What makes this city a population Interestingly, its position, as
a whole, their particular style of buildings, their social air, historical
memories and their economic value.

Cadiz, which had fallen as much commercial space since losing the exploitation of Colombia, begins
to regain its animation, thanks to the new steamship lines, to significant improvements on
the roads to the interior of Andalusia, and the economic revival Spain has had since 1855.
Its exports are salt, oil, wine, fruit dry and other Andalusian, - is an important place of
call and deposit, and manufactures some objects of art, as well as applicable to the marina.
Fisheries seeks him considerable profits. Sitting on a rock, as it lacks running water the higher
is its vast and numerous tanks.

Hospitals and has beautiful large number of educational institutions, charities, credit, trade and navigation.

Of
course, the climate, the influence of Moorish domination and the Spanish taste, have determined
Cadiz the same kind of constructions that almost the entire peninsula and especially in the
Andalucías. Thus, the streets are in general or in its more narrow and gloomy winding, bumpy
and full of whimsy. But is there a particular stamp of elegance and taste not found in any
of the other major Spanish cities, except to Seville. He feels a keen pleasure to go almost
all the streets of Cadiz, or to stand under the thick shade of the magnificent trees of the squares
of "San Antonio" and "Mina." Apart from the interest they excite people of all cliques of conditions
and the elegant shops full of curious, wherever you walk from one surprise to explore the best
streets, paved not richly tiled.

Everywhere graceful balconies, discrete lattice, obscured inside by fine curtains, behind which folds
half hidden from view some gorgeous faces as appearances ideals the viewpoints of crystal
air, capricious on steep ceilings, windows with iron gratings very curious, the vast rooftop
adorned of vases with flowers and small shrubs sunlit and agitated by sea breezes. But nothing so
strange, so deliciously beautiful and luxurious as the homes of the richest owners in the
main squares and streets, palaces true tale, of Orientalism charming. In all of them a magnificent
cover or rich marble and jasper, worked with care; an entrance that looks like the prelude to
a sumptuous room with the flooring and walls marble, stucco ceiling and superb interior door
glass with carved arabesques and beautiful colors. The door is always open during the day. You
approach, and a servant falls steps in and invites you to the point with the greatest care to visit
the house, although the family is present. If you accept, the owner (a wealthy businessman)
is presented, and a almost irresistible warmth compelling - to see that you are abroad - I repeat
the invitation, I pray that you may bring up, I asked if you want a drink, etc.

I had seen the splendid palaces and sumptuous hotels in France, England, Barcelona and Madrid, but
had no idea such a beautiful house, so as Eastern Romanesque I visited in Cadiz and Seville.
You pass in front of the vestibule, and you find yourself in a square courtyard and cloistered
on all four sides is the building covered by a high dome glass that makes it look like a greenhouse.
On the sides, on the ground floor, are the vast rooms for business or offices to the owner, at
the bottom there is an elegant catwalk leading to the courtyards (patios true), standing at the sides,
and in snail, and at right angles, the monumental staircase leading to the three, four or five
floors of the house. From the base to the glass dome is projected throughout the interior Quad-salon
continuous balconies so many orders and how many floors is cloistered home. There is no pavement
on the covered patio (which is how the central chamber), on the stairs the interior balconies and
all parts of the building, which is not composed of superb tiles square white marble and blue,
or black or mottled, there is a balcony, a door, a rail not have a thousand arabesques, and exquisite
moldings and tastefully, there is a wall not richly stuccoed and dressed. Each courtyard has at
its center a valuable source of marble fountains to cool the air, and around the campus are
large jars Gaspe, porcelain, etc., containing delicate shrubs, pots of jasmine, roses and
carnations, Naranjillos blossoms, vines or parasites, which embalm that heady atmosphere.
It is believed a dream with some of the oriental tale, and for the enjoyment is complete for the
lover of art, every yard of these are a few marble statues and holds within its walls ten or
twelve paint beautiful pictures.

Sunlight, falling vertically at noon, or weakened by entering the
lower part produces the most strange effects of brightness, shade
and chiaroscuro, and at night, when the interior is lighted by gas,
this museum-garden in the middle of the waters murmur supplier, is
a ravishing beauty.

This is where families gather, they are visits and enjoys home gatherings during the hottest
months in of summer, when there is no preference roof.

Cadiz is in marble lavished everywhere. In large hotels, in many and splendid cafés, theaters,
churches, squares and all the monuments there is a floor luxury he admires. Coffee 'Apollo', one
of the most beautiful and original I known, fun and draws attention
to the traveler, and gives an idea of ??the character ardent, cordial,
voluptuous and expansion of the population of Cadiz.

During the early hours of the night, plazas of San Antonio and Mina (the first in particular)
and large adjacent streets have great animation and offer the most curious customs boxes. The
women of Cadiz are usually beautiful, hot and attractive: that, and the commercial status of
the city makes the misfortune of them in the classes most exposed to weaknesses and temptations.
Thus, prostitution Cadiz is in proportion to scare. It's outrageous the number of women in unhappy
establishments that kind of corruption, and experts speculate the infamy the direction of those
houses, namely the ignominy of European societies. Contáronme things What terrified me, and
anecdotes about people of high society, to be true, would give a very sad idea of ??morality
Cadiz. I do not believe what I was told by some people, and took Cadiz HOWEVER, under this aspect,
painful impressions .... Much could be said about what I have observed in major Spanish cities,
but the matter is repugnant and shocking, and the Colombian world, fortunately, does not know
certain things it is best to ignore forever. There are so many fallacies in European civilization
so much misery ... dishonoring the progress and do sometimes feel ashamed of what makes humanity
.... In Spain is a singular contrast, religion is not free: the Catholic believer is not no
can worship God, - but prostitution is not only legitimized by the law, but authority that regulates
and manages the carefully!

Sufficient to judge the organization of that country (whose people have admirable qualities characteristics
and severe defects of education) the simple fact these two contrasts: law speculation the game
through the lottery, but restricts the innocent and productive work; maintains and manages the
prostitution, but press the conscience and conviction to imprisonment to which distributed the
Bible and the Gospels without notes Scio father!

* * * * *

Despite the interest that could have the city of Jerez, as strong and large population center wine
production, we had more strong desire to sail from the lower Guadalquivir
mouth to Sevilla.

       We prefer, therefore, this way, but we wanted before we embark interesting
to know the population living near Cadiz.

Taking a car and leaving the premises of the city by the road to Jerez, it is easy to visit
San Fernando, Puerto-Real and Harbor-Santa-Maria.

The landscape, if facing the mainland, monotonous, equality of the land and nature crop, but it
is picturesque and lively, if there is a tendency in view of the sea, is to repair in the shipyard
of the bay, where there is enough movement, is to take a quick glance
at the extensive salt marshes of San Fernando, whose production is
very significant and employs a large number of workers.

The salt is monopolized in Spain, probably prove an infinite gratitude to God for having surrounded
by the sea to the Spanish mainland. This monopoly (the state that produces a strong income,
however smuggling) provides the Spanish to the invaluable benefits of eating the salt of their
huge costs and expensive bad, but why stop doing business the big speculators who exploit salt
waterproof.

The City of San Fernando, Cadiz separate fortresses, ramparts and a large sea trench that cuts
the island of Leon, is located towards the end of this, which is linked to the mainland by
two bridges. Nearby there are numerous orchards, and everywhere revealed in the vast salt marshes,
the gunners and factories, the nature of their production.

Its main elements are: salt, in a very large sum (which is exported), land metalloids pickles
and cast objects and marina, as well as arts and crafts. The situation, of city ??is curious,
by the way for the semi-circular canal surrounding side continent and that determines the
island. It seems as if two long bays or languages ??slimmest sea ??water were to crash and confused
under the bridges of Zuazo and Chiclana, which give way into the country.

San Fernando has general similarities to Cadiz in its field structure, and appearance is little
more or less similar. There is another characteristic that its astronomical observatory, which is
much lower than in Cadiz, so famous in the Spanish and Colombian geography. The population
San Fernando reached about 17.000 inhabitants, generally industrious
and engaged in rough manufacturing jobs and artifacts.

The countless inns or isolated houses ahead San Fernando to Cadiz side has an original and picturesque,
this is where crowds of thousands of workers employed at the shipyard of the Ratchet and many
factories in the vicinity, forming at certain times of day many groups as lively as curious.
Passing through the midst of them feel a strong smell of tar, salt and other materials that reveal
from the first moment the kind of occupation of these people.

The yard of the Carrack, a kind of floating population and solid at the same time, which composed
of ships, vast warehouses and workshops, offers an interesting picture, not so much the merit of establishing
the air as workers, buildings, etc. It is in that shipyard, located on the bay near the salt, as
to 1.200 meters of San Fernando, where Spain has one of the best
naval factories.

There are built ships war, and sometimes even trade of all sizes and conditions, and becomes
the cowling, as well as working on a large scale canvas for sails, ropes, cables, etc. Thousands
of workers constantly work at that point in the bay and its vicinity, and in the manufacture
naval, and in the exploitation and manufacture of salt. After stretching in several directions
many works of fortification, which are in some way the defenses of Cadiz and background the
bay.

Port Royal, located on the mainland coast, at the bottom of the bay is a nice population of 5.000
souls. The vicinity of the mouth of Zurraque (south) and confused with one arm sea, and Guadalete,
which enters the north, in the corner of the bay, the modern structure the streets and houses
(usually symmetric) and its pier and harbor filled with fishing Seafood
and carrying water boatmen, the table to the two sides are equidistant,
The yard of the Ratchet and the "Trocadero"

(commercial use) that is to the west on the bay, the animation of the people and the grace of
the neighboring gardens and country houses - all this contributes to make Port Royal a picturesque
and lively population. That is the walking and break for the rich Cadiz, many owners of houses
and villas pleasure at this point in the Spanish coast.

"Port-Saint-Mary" is much more significant. Delay, as I said, at the bottom of a small Gulf (north-west
of Port-Royal) whose waters are separated from the Bay of Cadiz by peninsula or tongue of land where
the "Trocadero". Santa Maria, which is about 14 km from Jerez and Cádiz, 21, is the end of
the road to Seville, and there recently completed the railway passes. From there lies a land
of imponderable wealth of carefully cultivated vineyards (and many
other fruit trees), both from the point Jerez, towards the interior,
whether by the coast in the direction of Rota (the country's famous
tintilla) and the lower Guadalquivir.

The distance between St Mary and Port Royal is so short, the Guadalete involved, that in fact the
former seems to belong both to the bay same as the Gulf said. Its main communications with
Cadiz are sustained through vapor coming out of a good spring and consistently across the bay.

Santa-Maria
is a beautiful town with over 21.000 inhabitants, with much activity and movement agricultural,
industrial and commercial. Lies at the foot of a hill overlooking the right bank Guadalete, and
is literally surrounded by orchards and vineyards. It has many institutes public, many factories
(mainly of fine liquors, pickles, hats and soap), and apart from its strong production of
wines, cultivated many arts and crafts. The structure is generally good, notably the beautiful
street called Long. There is the type of populations Andalusia, active and industrious in general,
where there are rarely any symptoms reveals of poverty or decay.

* * * * *

The time we needed to continue the tour. So, we went to a small coastal steamer and returned
to Cadiz. Sevilla had to leave for the next day, and we take the second night we had visiting
a theater and some cafes. Nothing particular in the theater elegant and well attended (because the
Spanish people are very passionate about the shows to impress strongly or make you laugh), but found,
like most of Spain, a farce sung to pieces, with the name of zarzuela, and the usual choreographic
developments French style - that are making it unbearable pest lose
their originality and grace Spanish theater.

       Instead of a good comedy or a good drama (and there are plenty in
Spain) the public has to swallow how can a comic opera in bad taste,
which degrades the same time to the play and opera.

In retaliation, the coffee is in all Spanish cities most curious social element. To an inhabitant
of northern Europe nothing could be more unpleasant perhaps, but for a noon child of Hispanic
or Colombia, with the instincts of expansion and sociability, the scene has many attractions.
I said, speaking of Barcelona and Madrid, the most noteworthy approached the cafes in Spain.
As the spirit of the people is strongly liberal in all major Spanish cities, and particularly
in Andalusia, coffee, - element expansion frank and free discussion and censure - is more important
even in Cadiz Sevilla, etc., Where the liberal opinion it takes full advantage. The piano (furniture
infallible in the big brown) helps to raise the spirits and increase
the noise of hundreds of parishioners - not infrequently serving epigrammatic
instrument, according to the mood of the crowd.

It is common to express opposition there trends the national government, aversion to the French
government, etc., making run (with applause loud and unanimous) and the hymn of Irrigation,
and the Marseillaise, or another piece that involves an strong political reference.

Apollo Coffee, where we settled in Cadiz for a few hours in two nights, we sought a means of
making curious observations on the political practices Cadiz. Even inside the unique structure of coffee
helped to make interesting scene, having some resemblance to the elegant homes that I have described,
being observed from one of the top balcony overlooking the great room and details of all groups
simultaneously. I was stunned to hear the Spanish speaking on more serious matters: I seemed
to be Bogotá in a cafe (where they speak with absolute freedom) but, in truth, was mutual tolerance
in the most frank and earnest discussions of the Spanish. Were said more clarity, without insulting,
but seasoned with the usual Spanish pepper the three CCC, without having the slightest fear
of a disagreement. They talked about the queen ... workmanship; put to the ministry of turns,
or vented their hilarity epigrammatic and its terrible censorship
on the Captain General, Governor, the Bishop or the first character
were at hand.

It's really rare ease and wit with which the Spanish people manage the epigram and knows how
to apply a saying at every opportunity.

This unique political and social importance of the cafes in Spain made me think a little. She dates
from the time of constitutional government, so it is an institution very modern. Is it a good or a bad? -
I asked myself. Of course the coffee become club has its advantages: it tends to eliminate this
isolation that froze to Spanish society, and unnerved and kept in the intellectual and moral
impotence, distracts from the temptation of game, as general in Spain (because of the institutions)
and is an amazing fusion Social class and self-organization of public opinion, opposed to the
constraints strung under the more general and overt ways.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>