<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10013</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>293080</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21434</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> La joven,
sospechosa hacía algún tiempo por otros motivos, ha pedido permiso para retirarse, y no se
le ha negado. Inútil es agregar, que las señoras le aseguran una existencia honorable... ¡Y
bien, hijo mío! ¿qué dice de todo esto? ¿Le hace sufrir más? Está tan pálido como un muerto...

La verdad es, que estas noticias inesperadas habían excitado en mí tantas emociones agradables
y penosas á la vez, que me sentía próximo á desfallecer.

* * * * * * * * * * *

El señor Laubepin que debe partir mañana al amanecer, volvió esta noche á despedirse de mí.
Después de algunas palabras embarazosas de parte á parte:

--¡Ah, mi querido niño!--me dijo--no le interrogo sobre lo que aquí pasa: pero si tiene usted
necesidad de un confidente y un consejero, le pediría la preferencia.

Yo no podía efectivamente desahogarme en un corazón más amigo, ni más seguro. Hice al digno
anciano un relato detallado de todas las circunstancias que han señalado desde mi llegada al
castillo, mis relaciones particulares con la señorita Margarita. Hasta le he leído algunos
trozos de este diario, para precisar mejor el estado de esas relaciones y también el estado
de mi alma. Excepto el secreto que había descubierto la víspera en los archivos del señor Laroque,
nada le he ocultado.

Cuando terminé, el señor Laubepin cuya frente se había puesto recelosa hacía un momento, tomó
la palabra.

--Es inútil disimular, amigo mío--dijo--que al enviarle aquí, premeditaba unirlo con la señorita
Laroque. Al principio todo marchó conforme á mis deseos. Los dos corazones, que según mi opinión,
son dignos el uno del otro, no han podido aproximarse sin entenderse: pero ese extravagante
acontecimiento, cuyo teatro romántico ha sido la torre d'Elven, confieso que me desconcierta
enteramente. ¡Qué diantre! querido joven, saltar por la ventana, á riesgo de romperse la cabeza,
era, permítame que se lo diga, una demostración muy suficiente de su desinterés; fué, pues,
muy supérfluo agregar á este paso honorable y delicado, el juramento solemne de no casarse
jamás con esa pobre niña á no ser eventualidades que es absolutamente imposible esperar. Yo
me tengo por hombre de recursos, pero me reconozco enteramente incapaz de dar á usted doscientos
mil francos de rentas ó de quitárselos á la señorita Laroque.

--Entonces, señor, déme un consejo. Tengo más confianza en usted, que en mí mismo, pues conozco
que el infortunio expuesto siempre á la sospecha, ha podido irritarme hasta el exceso las susceptibilidades
de mi honor. Hable. Me inducirá usted á olvidar el juramento indiscreto pero solemne, sin embargo,
que en este momento es, según creo, lo único que me separa de la dicha, que había soñado para
su hijo adoptivo.

El señor Laubepin se levantó; sus espesas pestañas cayeron sobre sus ojos, y recorrió la habitación
á grandes pasos durante algunos minutos; luego, deteniéndose ante mí, y tomándome la mano con
fuerza:

--Joven--me dijo--es cierto, le amo como á un hijo; pero aun cuando debiera despedazar su corazón
y el mío con el suyo, jamás transigiré con mis principios. Mejor es ultrapasar el honor que
quedarse atrás de él: en materia de juramentos, todos los que no son exigidos bajo la punta
de un puñal ó ante la boca de una pistola, es menester no hacerlos ó cumplirlos: esa es mi opinión.

--Y también la mía. Mañana partiré con usted.

--No, Máximo, permanezca aquí algún tiempo todavía. Yo no creo en milagros, pero creo en Dios,
que rara vez permite que sucumbamos por nuestras virtudes... Demos un plazo á la Providencia...
Sé que le pido un gran esfuerzo de valor, pero lo reclamo formalmente de su amistad. Si en
un mes no recibe noticias mías, entonces partirá.

12 de octubre.

Hace dos días que puedo salir de mi retiro y pasar al castillo. No había visto á la señorita
Margarita desde el instante de nuestra separación en la torre d'Elven. Cuando entré, estaba
sola en el salón; al reconocerme hizo un movimiento involuntario como para levantarse, pero
permaneció inmóvil y su fisonomía se coloreó repentinamente de una púrpura ardiente. Esta fué
contagiosa, por que yo mismo sentí que me enrojecía hasta la frente.

--¿Cómo está usted, señor?--me dijo al tenderme la mano, pronunciando estas simples palabras
con un tono de voz tan dulce, tan humilde, ¡ay! tan tierno, que habría querido arrojarme de
rodillas ante ella. Sin embargo, fué preciso contestarla en el tono de una política helada.
Me miró dolorosamente: luego bajó sus grandes ojos con aire de resignación y continuó su trabajo.

Casi en el mismo instante, su madre la hizo llamar al lado de su abuelo, cuyo estado se agravaba
notablemente. Hacía muchos días que había perdido la voz y el movimiento; la parálisis le había
invadido casi entero. Los últimos destellos de su vida intelectual se habían extinguido: únicamente
persistía la sensibilidad con el sufrimiento. No podía dudarse que el fin del anciano se aproximaba,
pero la vida había tomado posesión muy fuertemente de aquel enérgico corazón, para desprenderse
de él, sin una lucha obstinada. El doctor había anunciado que la agonía sería larga. Desde
la aparición del peligro, la señora de Laroque y su hija le habían prodigado sus esfuerzos
y sus vigilias con la abnegación apasionada y el entusiasmo del sacrificio, que son la virtud
especial y la gloria de su sexo. Anteayer en la noche, sucumbían ya á la fatiga y á la fiebre;
el doctor Desmarest y yo, nos ofrecimos para suplirlas al lado del señor Laroque durante la
noche que comenzaba. Consintieron en descansar algunas horas. El doctor muy fatigado también,
no tardó en anunciarme que iba á recostarse en un lecho que había en la pieza vecina.

--Yo no sirvo aquí para nada--me dijo;--todo está hecho, usted lo ve, ya ni sufre el pobre
hombre... Es un estado de letargo que no tiene nada de desagradable, y cuyo despertar será
la muerte... de consiguiente puede uno estar tranquilo. Si nota algún cambio, me llama, pero
creo que esto no sucederá hasta mañana. Entre tanto yo me muero de sueño.--Lanzó un bostezo
sonoro y salió. Su lenguaje y su sangre fría ante el moribundo me chocaron. Es, sin embargo,
un hombre excelente, pero para tributar á la muerte el respeto que le es debido, es necesario
no ver únicamente la materia bruta que ella disuelve, sino también creer en el principio inmortal
que desliga.

Una vez solo en la cámara fúnebre, me senté al pie del lecho cuyas cortinas habían sido levantadas,
y traté de leer á la claridad de una lámpara que había cerca de mí, en una pequeña mesa. El
libro cayó de mis manos: no podía separar mi pensamiento de la singular combinación de acontecimientos,
que después de tantos años, daba á este culpable anciano al nieto de su víctima por testigo
y protector de su último sueño. Luego en medio de la calma profunda, de la hora y del lugar,
evocaba á mi pesar las escenas tumultuosas y las sanguinarias violencias que habían llenado
esta existencia que acababa. Buscaba impresión lejana de ellas, en la fisonomía de aquel agonizante
secular, sobre sus grandes rasgos cuyo pálido relieve se dibujaba en la sombra, como el de
una máscara de yeso, y sólo veía en ellos la gravedad y el reposo prematuros de la tumba. Por
intervalos me aproximaba á la cabecera, para asegurarme si el soplo vital movía aún aquel pecho
destruido.

En fin, hacia la media noche, me invadió una somnolencia irresistible y me dormí con la frente
apoyada sobre la mano. Repentinamente fuí despertado por no sé qué lúgubres estremecimientos;
levanté los ojos y sentí pasar un escalofrío por la médula de mis huesos. El anciano se hallaba
medio levantado en su lecho, y tenía fija sobre mí una mirada atenta, asombrada, en que brillaba
la expresión de una vida y de una inteligencia que hasta entonces me habían sido desconocidas.
Cuando mi mirada encontró la suya, el espectro se estremeció; abrió sus brazos en cruz, y me
dijo con una voz suplicante, cuyo timbre extraño suspendió el movimiento de mi corazón.

--¡Señor Marqués, perdóneme!

Quise levantarme, quise hablar, pero en vano. Me hallaba petrificado en mi sillón.

--¡Señor Marqués--continuó,--dígnese perdonarme!

Hallé en fin la fuerza suficiente para acercarme á él; á manera que yo me aproximaba, él se
retiraba penosamente hacia atrás como para escapar á un contacto pavoroso. Levanté una mano,
y bajándola suavemente ante sus ojos desmesuradamente abiertos y desesperados de terror.

--¡Morid en paz!--le dije--¡Yo le perdono!

No había aún acabado estas palabras cuando su fisonomía marchita se iluminó con un relámpago
de alegría y de juventud. Al mismo tiempo brotaron dos lágrimas de sus hundidas órbitas. Extendió
sus manos hacia mí: repentinamente, aquella mano se cerró con violencia y se extendió en el
espacio con un gesto amenazador: vi revolverse y rodar sus ojos entre sus órbitas dilatadas,
como si una bala le hubiera herido el corazón.

--¡Oh! inglés--murmuró.

Volvió á caer sobre la almohada como una masa inerte. Estaba muerto.

Llamé apresuradamente, y todos acudieron. Muy luego fué rodeado de piadosas lágrimas y oraciones.
Yo me retiré con el alma profundamente conmovida por aquella escena extraordinaria, que debía
permanecer secreta para siempre, entre aquel muerto y yo.

Este triste suceso de familia ha hecho pesar sobre mí cuidados y deberes de que tenía necesidad
para justificar á mis propios ojos la prolongación de mi morada en la casa. Me es imposible
concebir en virtud de qué motivos el señor Laubepin me ha aconsejado que demorare mi partida.
¿Qué puedo esperar de este aplazamiento? Me parece que esta circunstancia ha cedido á una especie
de vaga superstición y de debilidad pueril, á que no debía haberse doblegado jamás una alma
de su temple y á la que yo mismo he hecho mal en someterme. ¿Cómo no comprendí que me imponía
con un aumento de inútil sufrimiento, un papel sin franqueza y sin dignidad? ¿Qué haré yo en
adelante? ¿No es ahora cuando con justo motivo, podría reprochárseme el jugar con los sentimientos
más sagrados? Mi primera entrevista con la señorita Margarita había bastado para revelarme
todo el rigor, toda la imposibilidad de la prueba á que me hallaba condenado, cuando la muerte
del señor Laroque ha venido á dar por corto tiempo á mis relaciones alguna naturalidad, y una
especie de bienestar á mi permanencia en el castillo.

Rennes, 16 de octubre.

Todo está dicho, ¡Dios mío! ¡Cuán fuerte era este lazo! ¡De qué manera envolvía mi corazón!
¡Hasta qué punto le ha despedazado al romperse!

Ayer en la noche, cerca de las nueve, me hallaba yo de codos en mi ventana abierta, cuando
fuí sorprendido por una débil luz que se aproximaba á mi habitación á través de los sombríos
caminos del parque, y en una dirección que no acostumbran traer las gentes del castillo. Un
instante después llamaron á mi puerta, y la señorita de Porhoet entró jadeando.

--Primo--me dijo--tengo que hablar á usted.

--¿Hay alguna desgracia?--le pregunté, mirándola á la cara.

--No, no es eso precisamente. Usted mismo juzgará. Siéntese. Mi querido hijo; ha pasado usted
dos ó tres noches en el castillo durante la presente semana ¿no ha observado en él nada nuevo
ni de singular, en la actitud de las señoras?...

--Nada.

--¿No ha notado al menos en su fisonomía una especie de serenidad no acostumbrada?...

--Sí, tal vez... Apartando la melancolía del reciente duelo me han parecido más serenas, y
aún más dichosas que en otro tiempo.

--Sin duda, le habrían llamado la atención otras particularidades si hubiera usted, como yo,
vivido desde hace quince años en su intimidad cotidiana. Así es que á menudo he sorprendido
entre ellas los signos de una inteligencia secreta, de una misteriosa complicidad. A más, sus
hábitos se han modificado sensiblemente. La señora de Laroque ha echado á un lado su brasero,
su garita, y todas sus inocentes manías de criolla; se levanta á una hora fabulosa y se instala
desde la aurora con Margarita delante de la mesa de trabajo. A ambas les ha entrado un gusto
apasionado por los bordados, y se informan del dinero que una mujer puede ganar por día con
este género de labor. Para terminar, hay en esto un misterio cuya palabra en vano me desesperaba
por encontrar. Ella acaba de serme revelada y sin deber entrar en los secretos de usted antes
de lo que le convenga, he creído deber transmitírsela sin retardo.

Después de las protestas de absoluta confianza, que me apresuré á dirigirle, la señorita de
Porhoet continuó en su lenguaje dulce y firme:

--La señora de Aubry fué á verme esta noche á hurtadillas; comenzó por arrojarme sus horribles
brazos al cuello, lo que no me gustó nada, y luego, á través de mil jeremiadas personales,
que excuso repetir, me ha suplicado que detenga á sus parientes sobre el borde de su ruina.

--He aquí lo que ha oído escuchando á través de las puertas, según su graciosa costumbre; me
dijo que esas señoras solicitan en estos momentos autorización para abandonar todos sus bienes
á una congregación de Rennes, á fin de suprimir entre Margarita y usted los inconvenientes
que les separan. No pudiendo hacerle rico, ellas se hacen pobres. Me ha parecido imposible,
primo, dejar á usted ignorar esta determinación, igualmente digna de esas dos almas generosas
y de esas dos cabezas quiméricas. Me excusará agregar que su deber es desbaratar á toda costa
ese proyecto. Me parece inútil hablar del arrepentimiento que infaliblemente se prepara á nuestras
amigas, y de la responsabilidad terrible que las amenaza; usted lo comprende tan bien como
yo. Si pudiera, amigo mío, aceptar en el instante la mano de Margarita, el asunto terminaría
del modo más feliz; pero se halla ligado á este respecto por un compromiso que, por muy ciego,
por muy imprudente que haya sido, no es por eso menos obligatorio para su honor. Sólo le queda
un partido que tomar: dejar este país sin demora y cortar resueltamente todas las esperanzas
que entretiene su permanencia aquí. Cuando haya partido, me será más fácil volver á esas dos
niñas á la razón.

--Pues bien, estoy pronto; partiré esta misma noche.

--Muy bien--continuó:--cuando le doy este consejo amigo mío, yo misma obedezco á una ley de
honor bien rigurosa. Usted endulza los últimos momentos de mi larga soledad; me ha vuelto la
ilusión de los más dulces encantos de la vida, perdidos por mí hace tantos años. Alejándose
usted hago mi último sacrificio... es inmenso.

Se levantó y me miró un momento sin hablar.

--A mi edad no se abraza á los jóvenes--continuó, sonriendo tristemente,--se les bendice. Adiós,
querido hijo, y gracias... Que Dios le ayude... Yo besé sus manos temblorosas, y ella me dejó
precipitadamente.

Hice á toda prisa mis aprestos para la partida: luego escribí algunas líneas á la señora de
Laroque. La suplicaba renunciara á una resolución cuyo alcance no había calculado, y de la
que por mi parte, estaba firmemente determinado á no hacerme cómplice. Le daba mi palabra,
y ella sabía que podía contarse con ella, que no aceptaría jamás mi felicidad á costa de su
ruina. Al terminar, para apartarla mejor de su insensato proyecto, le hablaba vagamente de
un porvenir cercano en que fingía entrever esperanzas de fortuna.

A media noche, cuando todos dormían, di un adiós, un cruel adiós á mi retiro, á aquella vieja
torre ¡en que tanto había sufrido, donde tanto había amado! y me deslicé en el castillo por
una puerta excusada, cuya llave me había sido confiada. Atravesé furtivamente, como un criminal,
las galerías vacías y sonoras, guiándome lo mejor que pude en las tinieblas; llegué al fin
al salón, donde la había visto por primera vez. Ella y su madre lo habían dejado, hacía apenas
una hora; su presencia reciente se manifestaba aún por un perfume dulce y tibio, que me embriagó
súbitamente. Busqué y toqué la cesta en que su mano había colgado pocos instantes antes su
bordado, comenzado. ¡Ay, pobre corazón! Caí de rodillas ante el lugar que ocupaba, y allí,
con la frente sobre el mármol, lloraba y sollozaba como un niño. ¡Dios mío, cómo la amo!

Aproveché las últimas horas de la noche para hacerme conducir secretamente á la pequeña ciudad
vecina, donde tomé el carruaje de Rennes. Mañana en la noche estaré en París. ¡Pobreza, soledad,
desesperación, que allí os dejé, voy á hallaros de nuevo! ¡Ultimo sueño de mi juventud, sueño
del Cielo, adiós!

París.

Al día siguiente por la mañana, cuando iba á montar en el ferrocarril, entró en el patio del
hotel un carruaje de posta, y vi descender de él al viejo Alain. Cuando me vió, su fisonomía
se iluminó.

--Ah, señor, ¡qué fortuna que no haya partido! Tome esta carta.

--Reconocí la letra del señor Laubepin. Me decía en dos líneas que la señorita de Porhoet estaba
gravemente enferma y que me llamaba. No me tomé sino el tiempo necesario para mudar caballos
y me arrojé en la silla, después de haber decidido á Alain, no sin trabajo, á que se sentara
frente á mí. Entonces lo aturdí á preguntas. Le hice repetir la noticia que me trajo y que
me parecía inconcebible. La señorita Porhoet había recibido la víspera, de manos del señor
Laubepin, un pliego ministerial, que le anunciaba que era puesta en plena y entera posesión
de la herencia de sus parientes de España.--Y parece--agregaba Alain--que se lo debe al señor,
que ha descubierto en el palomar algunos papeles viejos, en los que nadie soñaba y que han
probado el buen derecho de la anciana señorita. Yo no sé lo que hay de verdadero en esto, pero
sí es lástima--me dijo--que á esta respetable señora se le haya metido en la cabeza ideas de
catedral y que no quiere abandonarlas... porque, note usted, que está más aferrada que nunca.
Al principio, cuando recibió la noticia, cayó redonda en el pavimento y se le creyó muerta;
pero una hora después empezó á hablar, sin fin ni tregua, de su catedral, del coro, de la nave,
del cabildo y de los canónigos, del ala del Norte y del ala del Sur, de tal modo que para calmarla
ha sido necesario traerle un arquitecto, albañiles, y poner sobre su lecho los planos del malhadado
edificio. En fin, después de tres horas de conversación sobre el asunto se amodorró un rato;
al despertarse, ha pedido ver al señor... al señor Marqués (Alain se inclinó cerrando los ojos)
y se me ha hecho correr en su busca; parece que quiere consultarle sobre el coro alto.

Este extraño acontecimiento me causó la más viva sorpresa. Sin embargo, con ayuda de mis recuerdos
y de los detalles confusos, que me daba Alain, llegué á darme una explicación de ellos, que
noticias más positivas debían confirmar muy luego. Como ya he dicho, el negocio de la sucesión
de la rama española de los Porhoet había pasado por dos fases. Había habido primero, entre
la señorita de Porhoet y una gran casa de Castilla, un largo proceso que mi vieja amiga había
acabado por perder en última instancia; luego un nuevo proceso, en el que la señorita de Porhoet
no figuraba, se había suscitado, á propósito de la misma sucesión, entre los herederos españoles
y la corona, que pretendía que los bienes volvían á ella por derecho de fundación del mayorazgo.

     »Dado en el Escorial el 10 de abril de 1716.

     YO EL REY.»

Al lado de esta pieza, que sólo era una copia traducida, había hallado el texto original con
las armas de España. No se me había ocultado la importancia de este documento, pero había temido
exagerármela. Dudaba mucho que la validez del título, sobre el que habían pasado tantos sucesos
y tantos acontecimientos, fuese admitida por el gobierno español, y hasta dudaba que tuviera
el poder de hacerle lugar, aun cuando quisieran hacérselo. Me decidí, pues, á dejar ignorar
á la señorita de Porhoet, un descubrimiento cuyas consecuencias me parecían ser muy problemáticas
y me limité á remitir el título al señor Laubepin. No recibiendo contestación alguna, no tardé
en olvidarlo en medio de los cuidados personales que me abrumaban entonces. El gobierno español,
obrando de una manera contraria á mi injusta desconfianza, no había vacilado en desempeñar
la palabra del Rey Felipe, y en el momento mismo en que un decreto supremo acababa de abocar
á la corona la sucesión inmensa de los Porhoet, por otro decreto la restituyó noblemente á
su legítimo heredero.

Eran las nueve de la noche cuando descendí del carruaje, en el húmedo umbral de la casita en
que acababa de entrar, aunque tardíamente, esta fortuna casi real. La sirvienta vino á abrirme;
lloraba amargamente. Oí al instante la voz grave del señor Laubepin que dijo:--Él es.--Subí
apresuradamente. El anciano me apretó la mano fuertemente y me introdujo, sin pronunciar una
palabra, en el cuarto de la señorita de Porhoet. El médico y el cura de la villa se mantenían
silenciosos en el hueco de una ventana. La señora de Laroque estaba arrodillada sobre una silla,
cerca del lecho; su hija de pie en la cabecera, sostenía las almohadas en que reposaba la pálida
cabeza de mi pobre y vieja amiga. Cuando la enferma me vió, una débil sonrisa iluminó su fisonomía,
profundamente alterada, y desprendió penosamente uno de sus brazos. Tomé su mano, caí de rodillas
y no pude contener mis lágrimas.

--¡Hijo mío, mi querido hijo!...--Luego miró fijamente á Laubepin. El viejo notario tomó entonces
del lecho una hoja de papel, y continuando, al parecer, una lectura interrumpida, leyó:

«Por estas causas, instituyo por este testamento ológrafo, por legatario universal de todos
mis bienes, tanto en España como en Francia, sin reserva ni condición alguna, á Máximo Santiago
María Odiot, Marqués de Champcey d'Hauterive, noble de corazón como de raza. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06144</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>145771</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19205</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The young suspected
for some time for other reasons, has requested permission to withdraw and not denied. Needless
to add, that the ladies will ensure an honorable life ... Y well, my son! What does all this?
Does it make you suffer more? Is as pale as death ...

The truth is, these unexpected news had aroused in me many pleasant
emotions and painful at the time, I felt close to fainting.

* * * * * * * * * * *

Mr. Laubepin must leave tomorrow at dawn, returned this evening to
bid me farewell.

After some awkward words of part to part:

- Ah, my dear boy! - I said - do not wonder about what is happening here, but if you have need
a confidant and a counselor, I would ask the preference.

I could not actually vent in a more friendly heart, or safer.

I did the worthy elderly a detailed account of all the circumstances that have been identified
since my arrival at castle, my special relationship with Miss Margaret.

So I've read some pieces of this newspaper, to clarify the status of these relationships and also
the state of my soul. Except the secret he had discovered the day before in the files of Mr. Laroque,
I hid nothing.

When I finished, Mr. Laubepin whose face had been suspicious had a moment, took word.

- It is useless to pretend, my friend - said - that when we send here, premeditated attach
to Miss Laroque. At first all went according to my wishes. The two hearts, which in my opinion
are worthy of each other, could not be reconciled without understanding: but that's fanciful event,
whose theater has been the tower romantic d'Elven, I confess that
I am baffled entirely.

What the devil! dear boy, jump out the window at the risk of breaking your head, was, let me tell
you, a very sufficient proof of his disinterest, was therefore very superfluous to add to this honorable and
sensitive way, the solemn oath not to marry with this poor girl never had it not been eventualities
that is absolutely impossible to expect. I I have me a man of resources, but I recognize myself
entirely unable to give you two hundred thousand francs of income
or to terminate Ms. Laroque.

- Then, sir, give me some advice.

I have more confidence in you, myself, because I know that misfortune always exposed to the suspect,
has been irritated to excess susceptibilities my honor. Talk. I will induce you to forget the
indiscreet but solemn oath, however, at this point is, I believe,
the only thing that separates me from that, he had dreamed his adopted
son.

Mr. Laubepin stood up, her lashes fell over his eyes, and around the room great strides for
a few minutes, then stopping in front of me and taking my hand with Strength:

- Young - he said - is true, I love him as a child, but even when he should tear his heart and
mine to yours, I will never compromise my principles. Best is to go beyond the honor stay behind
him, on oath, all of which are not required under the tip of a knife or at the mouth of a
gun, we must not make them or meet them: that's my opinion.

- And
mine.

Leaving tomorrow with you.

- No, Max, stay here a while yet.

I do not believe in miracles, but I believe in God rarely allowed to succumb to our strengths
... Let's run to Providence ... I know I ask a great deal of value, but formally claim his
friendship. If one month do not hear from me, then leave.

12 October.

Two days ago I can get out of my retirement and move to the castle. I had not seen Mademoiselle
Margarita from the moment of our separation d'Elven tower. When I entered, was alone in the
room, with the recognition made an involuntary movement to rise,
but remained motionless and her face was a purple colored suddenly
hot.

This was contagious, that I felt that I blushed to the front.

- How are you, sir - I said to reach out, uttering these simple words with a voice so sweet, so humble,
alas so tender, she had wanted to throw in knees before her. However, it was necessary to answer the
political tone of a cold. He looked painfully, then lowered her large eyes with an air of resignation
and continued his work.

Almost at the same moment, her mother summoned next to his grandfather, whose condition worsened
significantly. For many days he had lost his voice and movement, the paralysis had invaded almost
over. The last glimpses of his intellectual life had been extinguished, only sensitivity persisted
with suffering. There could be no doubt that the end of the old man approached, but life had
taken hold very strongly that strong heart, to discard him, without
a stubborn fight.

The doctor had said that the agony would be long. From the appearance of danger, Laroque Madame
and her daughter had lavished their efforts and their vigils with passionate dedication and
enthusiasm of sacrifice, which are under special and the glory of their sex. The day before
yesterday night, and he succumbed to fatigue and fever; Dr. Desmarest and I, we offered to
meet them beside Mr. Laroque during night began. Consented to rest for a few hours. The doctor
also very tired, he soon announced that he would lie on a bed that was in the next room.

- I worship here at all - I said, - everything is done, you see, and
not the poor suffer man ... Is a state of lethargy that has nothing
unpleasant, and which will arouse death ... of one can therefore rest
easy.

If you notice any changes, call me, but I think this will not happen until tomorrow. In the meantime
I'm dying of sleep .-- He gave a yawn sound and left. His language and his coolness under the
dying shocked me. It is, however, an excellent man, but taxed to death the respect that is due, it is necessary
not only see the raw material that it dissolves, but also believe in the immortal principle
that detaches.

Left alone in the funeral chamber, I sat at the foot of the bed whose curtains had been lifted, and
tried to read to the light of a lamp that was near me, on a small table. The book fell from
my hands, my mind could not separate the unique combination of events, that after so many years,
gave to this old man's grandson blame the victim as a witness and protective of his ultimate dream.
Then in the midst of profound calm, time and place, to my regret
evoked the tumultuous and bloody scenes of violence that had filled
this existence to an end.

Distant impression of them was looking in the face of this dying secular, their pale outline of
which is drawing attention to the shade, such as a plaster mask, and only saw in them the seriousness
and the rest premature grave. For intervals at the head approached me for sure if the breath of
life that was far the chest destroyed.

Finally, around midnight, I felt an irresistible drowsiness, and fell asleep with his head resting
on his hand. Suddenly I was awakened by tremors do not know what
grim; I looked up and felt a shudder pass through the marrow of my
bones.

The old man was half raised in bed, and had fixed a watchful eye
on me, astonished, that shone the expression of life and intelligence
that I had hitherto been unknown.

When my eyes met his, the spectrum shuddered, opened his arms crossed,
and I he said with a pleading voice whose timbre strange suspended
the movement of my heart.

- Marquis, forgive me!

I wanted to get up, I wanted to talk, but in vain. I was frozen in my chair.

- Marquis - continued - deign to forgive me!

Finally I found the strength to come to him to how I approached, he retreated painfully to escape
back to an awesome touch. I raised a hand, and lowering it gently to your eyes wide open and
desperate terror.

- Die in peace! - I said - I forgive!

He had not even finished speaking when his withered face lit up with lightning of joy and youth.
While two tears flowed from their sunken sockets.

Extended their hands to me, suddenly, the hand was slammed and stretched in space with a threatening
gesture, I saw squirming and rolling their eyes from their sockets dilated as if a bullet had
struck his heart.

- Oh! English - muttered.

Fell back on the pillow like an inert mass. He was dead.

Hastily called, and everyone came. Very soon he was surrounded by pious tears and prayers.
I retired with my soul deeply moved by this extraordinary scene, which was forever remain secret,
including the dead man and me.

This sad event has made the family even care about me and duties of
which needed to justify to myself the extension of my home in the
house.

It is impossible conceive under what grounds Mr. Laubepin has advised me to take to get my
game. What I can expect from this postponement?

I think that this phenomenon has yielded to a kind of vague superstition and childish weakness,
he was not a soul ever having bowed of his mettle and to which I myself have done wrong to submit.
How I did not realize that imposed with an increase in unnecessary suffering, a paper without
honesty and without dignity? What I do forward?

Is it not time with just cause, could reprochárseme playing with
the feelings more sacred?

My first interview with Miss Margaret had sufficed to reveal full
force, all the impossibility of proof to which I was convicted, when
death Mr. Laroque has come to take for a short time to my relationships
have naturally, and kind of welfare to my stay at the castle.

Rennes, October 16.

Everything has been said, my God! How strong was this tie! In what
way wrap my heart!

To what extent has shattered the break!

Last night, around nine, I was I leaning on my window open when I was surprised by a faint light
was coming to my room through the dark park roads and in a direction not usually bring the
people of the castle. A moment later he called at my door, and Mademoiselle de Porhoet came panting.

-
Primo - I said - I have to talk to you.

- Is there any trouble? - I asked, looking at her face.

- No, not just that. Judge for yourself. Sit. My dear son, have you spent two or three nights at
the castle this week have not seen anything new in it singular or in the attitude of the ladies?
...

- Nothing.

- Have not you noticed at least in his face a kind of serenity is not used? ...

- Yes, maybe ... Putting aside the recent melancholy of grief seemed to me more calm, and further
said that in another time.

- Without doubt, would have drawn attention to other particulars if you would like me lived
fifteen years in daily intimacy. So I have often surprised including signs of a secret intelligence,
of a mysterious complicity. Later, their habits have changed significantly. Madame de Laroque
has cast aside his brazier his box, and all innocent hobbies Creole rises to one hour and installed
fabulous from dawn to Margaret in front of the desk. They both entered a taste passionate
about embroidery, and reported the money that a woman can win a day with this kind of work.
Finally, it is in a mystery whose name in vain I despaired be found. She recently revealed to
avail me and without having to enter the secret from you before what suits you, I believed to
be transmitted without delay.

After the protests of absolute confidence, that I hastened to guide
you, Mademoiselle de Porhoet continued in his sweet, strong language:

-
Mrs. Aubry came to see me this night to sneak, began his horrible
throw his neck, so I did not like, and then, through a thousand lamentations
personal that excuse again, begged me to stop his relatives on the
brink of ruin.

- Here's what I've heard listening through the doors,
according to his usual funny, me said that these ladies are currently
seeking permission to leave all their assets to a congregation of
Rennes, in order to remove you from Margarita and disadvantages that
separate them.

Unable to make you rich, they become poor.

I have found it impossible cousin, leaving you to ignore this determination, equally worthy
of these two generous souls and chimeric these two heads. Excuse me add that his duty is to
thwart at all costs this project. It seems futile to talk of repentance that prepares our infallibly
friends, and the terrible responsibility that threat, you understand
as well as me.

If I could, my friend, accept at the moment the hand of Margarita,
the matter would end in the most happy, but is linked to this subject
by a compromise which, however blind however unwise it was, is no
less binding for that honor.

It only remains a party to make: to leave this country without delay and resolutely cut all hope
entertaining your stay here. When you party, I will make it easier to return to these two girls
to the right.

- Well, I am ready; be leaving tonight.

- Very Good - continued: - when I give this advice my friend, myself to obey a law While rigorous
honor. You sweetens the last moments of my long solitude has turned me illusion of the sweetest
charms of life lost me years ago. Away you make my last sacrifice
... is immense.

He got up and looked at me a moment without speaking.

- At my age not to embrace the young - he continued, smiling sadly, - bless them. Goodbye, dear
son, and thank you ... May God help you ... I kissed her trembling hands, and she left me precipitously.

I
rushed to my dressings for the game: after I wrote a few lines to Mrs. Laroque. The resignation
begged to reach a resolution which had not calculated, and for my part, he was determined
to not make me an accomplice. I gave my word and she knew she could
be counted, that would never accept my happiness at the expense of
ruin.

At the end, to turn away the best of his foolish project, spoke vaguely a near future in pretending
glimpse of hope of fortune.

At midnight, when everyone was asleep, say goodbye, a cruel farewell
to my retirement, to that old tower that had suffered so much, where
both had loved! and I slipped into the castle a side door, the key
was entrusted to me.

Crossed stealthily, like a criminal, empty galleries and sound, guiding
the best I could in the darkness, I finally the room, where he had
first seen.

She and her mother had left, was just an hour recently manifested their presence even for a
sweet, warm scent that I got drunk suddenly. I looked and touched the basket in his hand had
hung a few moments before his embroidery begun.

Alas, poor heart!

I knelt before her place, and there with the forehead on the marble, weeping and sobbing like a
child. God, how I love it!

I took the last hours of the night to secretly drive me to the small town neighbor, where I
took the coach of Rennes. Tomorrow night I'll be in Paris. Poverty, loneliness, despair, I
left there, I shall find you again! Last dream of my youth, sleep Sky, bye!

Paris.

The next day morning, when he was going to ride on the train, entered the courtyard of hotel
a post carriage, and saw him down the old Alain. When I saw his face lit.

- Ah, sir, how fortunate that no party! Take this letter.

- I recognized the letter of Mr. Laubepin. I said in two lines of Porhoet was Miss seriously ill and
called me. But I did not take the time to change horses and threw me in the chair, after having
decided to Alain, not without difficulty, to sit down compared to me. Then he stunned questions.
I made him repeat the news that brought me and seemed inconceivable.

Miss Porhoet had received the day before from Mr. Laubepin, a ministerial statement, which he announced
that he was brought into full and entire possession the inheritance of their relatives in Spain
.-- And it seems - added Alain - that it should be the Lord, he has discovered in the loft some
old papers, in which no one dreamed and have tasted good right to the old lady. I do not know
what is true in this, but it is a pity - I said - that to this respectable lady has her head
stuck in the ideas of Cathedral and does not want to abandon ... because, you note, which is more
wedded than ever. At first, when the news fell on the pavement round and was believed dead; but
an hour later he began to speak, without end or respite, its cathedral,
the choir, the nave, the council and the canons, North Wing and South
Wing, so that to calm has been necessary to bring an architect, builders,
and put on the bed of the ill-fated planes building.

     Finally, after three hours of conversation on the subject is drowsy
for a while; waking, asked to see Mr. ... Mr. Marquis (Alain bent
eyes closed) and made me run after him, seems to want to consult it
on the choir loft.

     

This strange event caused me the liveliest surprise. However, with the help of my memories and confusing
details that Alain gave me, I came to give me an explanation of them, were confirmed positive news
very soon. As I said, business succession of the Spanish branch of the Porhoet had gone through
two phases. There had been first among Mademoiselle de Porhoet and a big house of Castile,
a long process that my old friend had ended up losing in the final analysis, then a new process,
in which de Porhoet was not, had been raised, regarding the same succession, the heirs Spanish
and the crown, which meant that goods returned to it by right of establishment of the estate.

"Since at the Escorial on April 10, 1716.

I THE KING. "

Next to this piece, it was just a translated copy, had found the original text the arms of Spain.
I had not hidden the importance of this document, but had feared exagerármela. Doubted the
validity of title, on which they had spent so many events and many events were supported by
the Spanish government, and even doubted that would the power to make room, even if they wanted
to have them. I decided therefore to stop ignoring Mademoiselle de Porhoet, a discovery whose consequences
seemed to be very problematic and I merely brought the title to Mr. Laubepin. Not receiving any
answer, I soon to forget in the midst of personal care that overwhelmed me then. The Spanish government
acting in a manner contrary to my unjust suspicion, had not hesitated to play word of King Philip,
and the moment that a supreme decree just started tackling succession
to the crown of the Porhoet immense, by another decree the nobly restored
to its rightful heir.

It was nine o'clock at night when the carriage went down in the wet threshold of the cottage
I had just come in, albeit belatedly, this fortune almost real. The servant came to open up; wept
bitterly. Moment I heard the deep voice of Mr. Laubepin who said:
- He's climbed .-- hastily. The old man squeezed my hand tightly and
introduced me, without uttering a word, the fourth of Mademoiselle
de Porhoet. The doctor and the priest of the town remained silent
in the hollow of a window. Madame de Laroque was kneeling on a chair
near the bed, her daughter standing at the bedside, holding the pillow
on which rested the pale head of my poor old friend. When I saw the
patient, a weak smile lit her face, profoundly altered, and tore one
of his arms painfully. I took her hand, fell to my knees I could not
hold back my tears.

- My son, my dear son to !...-- Laubepin Then
stared. The old notary then took the bed a sheet of paper, and continuing,
apparently interrupted reading, read:

"For these reasons, instituted
by the holographic will, by universal legatee of all my estate, both
in Spain and France, without reservation or qualification, to a maximum
of Santiago Mary Odiot, Marquis d'Hauterive Champcey, noble-hearted
as to race</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>