<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01159</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>703813</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23130</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

3.ª En la gastro-atonía con secrecion aumentada de las mucosidades gástricas é intestinales,
plenitud venosa y entorpecimiento en la circulacion de la vena porta.

4.ª En la gastro-enteritis y el muguet de los niños despues de borax y casi con las mismas
indicaciones: vientre flojo, deposiciones amarillas, espumosas y como cortadas en pedacitos,
borborigmos, fiebre escasa, pulso pequeño, palidez y tristeza.

5.ª En el último período de algunas fiebres mucosas y catarrales, en simples corizas y bronquitis,
en personas pálidas y polisárcicas, muy dispuestas á padecimientos de larga duracion por su
disposicion orgánica, y caracterizados por flujos mucosos, aftas, y por la sensacion de corrosion.

6.ª En la esterilidad por esceso de flujo catamenial en mujeres débiles.

7.ª En las convulsiones epileptiformes de personas exánimes, sobre todo en la edad adulta;
en los calambres musculares y el cólico saturnino, con tal que las personas no sean irritables;
en las hernias de los niños de testura blanda: en estos casos es preferible el ácido sulfúrico
al licopodio, al azufre y aun á la nuez vómica.

El ácido sulfúrico está ciertamente muy olvidado, á pesar de que su esfera de accion no es
menor que la del ácido azótico. Si este es de grande importancia como antimercurial, el ácido
sulfúrico, por el azufre que entra en su composicion, es mas eficaz contra el herpes; pero
el herpes secundario ó mucoso, como lo prueban sus efectos fisiológicos que le hacen á propósito
para tratar con éxito el muguet, las aftas con ligeras escoriaciones laterales, en las irritaciones
crónicas y pruritosas de las membranas mucosas y de las grietas de los labios. Ultimamente,
no deja de ser útil en el tratamiento de algunas afecciones cutáneas con prurito general, manchas
rojizas, pruritosas, placas lívidas y azuladas, escoriaciones espontáneas cubiertas con costras
amarillas, sabañones, erupciones secas en las manos y entre los dedos de las mismas.

=Dósis.=--Las dósis y modo de administracion son las mismas que para el ácido clorhídrico.

THUYA OCCIDENTALIS (TUYA OCCIDENTAL).

§ I.--Historia.

La tuya occidental ó del Canadá es un árbol de la familia de las coníferas, Juss.--De la monoecia
monadelfia, Linn.--Aun ignorariamos probablemente que Boerhaave y algunos médicos ingleses
y americanos se han ocupado de la thuya del Canadá, si Hahnemann no se hubiera propuesto recoger
todos los hechos conocidos sobre el uso de esta sustancia, particularmente en la hidropesía
y en los dolores indeterminados de los miembros. A Hahnemann únicamente debe la terapéutica
esta preciosa adquisicion: sus trabajos sobre la thuya forman parte de la historia de la sícosis
ó de los condilomas, afeccion especial que este hombre incansable ha sometido el primero á
la observacion regular y á un tratamiento específico en el que este medicamento entra como
uno de sus primeros agentes.

Pero antes de todo dirémos algo sobre la sícosis. La definicion que se ha dado de esta palabra[26]
se aplica á la mentagra; pero en la palabra fic[27] se halla la definicion que da Celso de
la sícosis, que dice consiste en escrescencias carnosas, situadas comunmente en los límites
de las mucosas y de la piel, y que degeneran á veces en úlceras.

Se presenta la sícosis con tanta frecuencia á consecuencia de la sífilis, que ha dado lugar
á confundir estos dos vírus. Hahnemann quiere que se les distinga, pero no ha dado los caractéres
diferenciales. En una memoria del doctor Petroz sobre la sícosis, se halla lo siguiente: «Toda
especie de tumor que se forma debajo del epidérmis, en el espesor del dérmis, en el tejido
papilar y la sustancia gris de Malpigio, debe considerarse como un producto de la sícosis,
cuando no reconoce por causa la viruela ó el vírus sifilítico: cuando este existe, la formacion
de la escrescencia es debida á la complicacion de la sífilis con la sícosis.

Las producciones sicósicas son elevaciones del epidérmis ó del epitelio por las papilas hipertrofiadas
y situadas sobre un punto endurecido por una inflamacion crónica y que sobreviene ordinariamente
á consecuencia de un golpe, de una compresion, de un arañazo.

Las formas varian segun la testura de la parte en que se sitúan, y tambien probablemente, segun
que la escrescencia es puramente sicósica, ó mezclada con el vírus sifilítico, el herpetismo.....
En la piel presenta mas bien el aspecto de verrugas; en las mucosas, partes sexuales, márgen
del ano, en el borde del ojo y de los labios, tiene una forma mas carnosa, mas blanda, confundiéndose
por lo mismo con el grano canceroso. Las verrugas ficiformes ó pedunculadas, los condilomas,
las vegetaciones llamadas crestas de gallo y coliflores, son manifestaciones de la sícosis.

Se divide, pues, esta afeccion en aguda, crónica y sifilítica: esta última variedad no tiene
signo característico, á menos que no se acepte por tal su aparicion con los fenómenos primitivos
de la sífilis: los resultados del tratamiento prueban su naturaleza.

La sícosis aguda consiste especialmente en un grano duro por lo general, cónico y rubicundo
que degenera á veces en úlcera corrosiva de fondo grisáceo, bordes duros y elevados; se sienten
punzadas durante el trabajo de la degeneracion; el grano se pone muy dolorido y se forma la
úlcera: en estos casos es frecuente la fiebre. Algunas veces la escrescencia verrugosa, ficiforme,
lisa é indolente, se hiende ó abre con ó sin dolor, y se divide en varios lóbulos.

La sícosis crónica constituye las vegetaciones que hemos enumerado, y se presenta con preferencia
hácia los cuarenta años.

Se puede admitir con Boeninghausen, como signo de la sícosis hereditaria y de la indicacion
de la thuya, dos síntomas que despues enumerarémos entre sus efectos fisiológicos, y son el
abultamiento de la pulpa en la punta de los dedos, así de las manos como de los piés.

La distincion que acabamos de establecer, segun el parecer de algunos autores y la observacion
de los hechos, no escluye, en concepto de otros, la idea de que la sícosis es siempre de orígen
sifilítico. Conveniente es, sin embargo, indicar, sin pretender resolver la cuestion, que el
caballo y el perro padecen frecuentemente la sícosis; todo el mundo conoce esta afeccion de
la boca en el perro, que se estiende en pocos dias á toda la cavidad y la llena de vegetaciones.
La thuya es el específico, porque las hace desaparecer rápidamente, sin necesidad del fuego
ni de los cáusticos, y sin la escision: estas operaciones, en último resultado, favorecen la
reproduccion de las escrescencias sicósicas, y aun hacen que sean mas numerosas. Desarrollándose,
pues, la sícosis del caballo y del perro sin sífilis y sin fenómenos mistos, tienden á establecer
que esta afeccion es independiente de la sífilis.

Las vegetaciones poliposas son quizás una forma de la sícosis, así como tambien se ha dado
el mismo orígen á la zona, la viruela, y á ciertas úlceras que se presentan en el dérmis. Creemos
por lo menos que teniendo la thuya una poderosa accion electiva sobre el dérmis, obra muy favorablemente
en ciertas lesiones de esta parte.

Otros varios medicamentos tienen una accion análoga á la thuya, en cuanto á las diversas vegetaciones
ficiformes, como son: el ácido azótico, el licopodio, el carbonato de cal, el sílice, el bismuto,
la sabina; aun indicarémos, respecto á las escrescencias en general y ciertos pólipos, el fósforo,
el causticum, la dulcamara, el antimonio, el acetato de cobre, el teucrium marum, la artemisa.

En resúmen, el tratamiento de las vegetaciones y otras escrescencias de este género, así como
las terribles úlceras que suceden á ciertos ficus, granos y condilomas, es una de las mas bellas
conquistas de la terapéutica moderna; conquista que debemos á Hahnemann, quien, si bien ha
sido muy esclusivo al atribuir á la thuya una especificidad que no tiene, puesto que hay necesidad
de recurrir en muchos casos al ácido nítrico, al licopodio y otros medicamentos; es una verdad,
que la thuya obra con tanta mas eficacia cuanto mas independiente es la vegetacion de cualquier
otro vírus, que se desarrolla sobre las mucosas en los puntos próximos á la piel, y que presenta
una forma pedunculada, lisa, de color rojizo y de consistencia mas bien blanda que dura. Esto
no quiere decir que este medicamento no tenga mayores indicaciones en ciertos granos sicósicos
en la piel, con forma pedunculada y tambien verrugosa, pero siempre lisa y con cierta rubicundez.

§ II.--Efectos fisiológicos y terapéuticos.

Está perfectamente demostrado que la thuya posee una accion especial sobre el dérmis, y aun
sobre todas las partes de la superficie cutánea, sin que su influencia se límite por eso á
este sistema. Ofrece en el conjunto de sus síntomas, ya una escitacion sanguínea muy marcada
y fenómenos de irritacion de las membranas mucosas, ya la astenia y la alteracion de la nutricion;
presenta, en fin, neuralgias que se refieren, tanto al período hiperesténico, como al hiposténico,
y que consisten en dolores variados, ya esenciales, ya sintomáticos de las neuralgias reumáticas,
la hemicránea, los tics dolorosos, el clavo histérico.

Las afecciones febriles y flegmásicas propias de la thuya están aun mal definidas, y la clínica
posee pocos hechos al efecto, si se esceptúan algunos casos de fiebre intermitente ó remitente,
y mas bien fiebres catarrales en las que predominan los calofríos. La thuya, además, es eficaz
en el romadizo rebelde, el coriza, ciertas oftalmías, estomatitis, uretritis, cuando las mucosas
están tumefactas ó presentan algunos puntos de las mismas como hipertrofiados, desarrollo estraordinario
del sistema vascular, sensibilidad aumentada, flujo seroso, mucoso y aun purulento.

Su indicacion se estiende hasta la leucorrea serosa y gonorrea subaguda; al coriza con flujo
acuoso, romadizo, estado escrofuloso, á la ozena misma; á la catarata seguida de oftalmía con
quémosis, tubérculos mucosos de la conjuntiva, flujo sero-mucoso. El azufre es un buen auxiliar,
y debe insistirse en estos dos medicamentos administrados uno despues de otro ó alternándolos.

Es útil tambien la thuya en la gonorrea con escrescencias, en los condilomas exudantes, en
los chancros con vegetaciones carnosas; en cuyas tres indicaciones es insuficiente el ácido
nítrico, y en las que la thuya puede jugar sola ó alternada con él.

Este medicamento es el remedio por escelencia de los tubérculos mucosos, de las vegetaciones
pedunculadas ó de base ancha, lisas con ó sin irritacion de la mucosa colindante, en el ano,
ó en otros puntos. El licopodio es su análogo en estos casos. Sabemos que el ácido azótico
corresponde mejor á las vegetaciones múltiples, granuladas, exudantes y sangrantes; pero tambien
hemos espresado ya que la escision no es una práctica racional.

Las aftas repetidas ó múltiples de fondo pálido, con bordes irregulares y sensibles situadas
sobre mucosas irritadas, corresponden á la thuya. En los chancros serpiginosos que se curan
por un lado para estenderse por otro, y en las escoriaciones del prepucio y de la vagina con
exudacion serosa ó purulenta, se debe alternar el ácido nítrico con la thuya, si las preparaciones
mercuriales no tienen ya indicacion, ó si agravan el padecimiento.

La accion especial de la thuya sobre la piel inclina á emplearle con éxito en la viruela, y
algunos prácticos opinan, fundados en los hechos, que es el medicamento importante, si no específico,
y aun el preservativo. Se la ha dado, como al mercurio, la propiedad de impedir las cicatrices
indelebles de las pústulas de la viruela, administrándola hácia el fin del período de supuracion.

Se presentan ocasiones con frecuencia de emplear la thuya en algunas afecciones cutáneas, las
sifílides especialmente, con preferencia en las formas pustulosas, el acné, la mentagra, ciertos
sabañones, en manchas de un rojo oscuro, y en la rubicundez de la caparrosa en la nariz, los
labios y el menton. Esta rubicundez se diferencia de las otras afecciones análogas, por la
sensacion de calor y algunas punzadas, principalmente por la tarde y noche, por la disposicion
á la tumefaccion roja y caliente de los dedos de piés y manos, del pabellon de la oreja, de
las alas de la nariz, por la facilidad á abultarse, las venas y por la sensibilidad general
de la piel.

Esta disposicion de las venas, el sudor en las partes genitales, en las manos y en los piés;
la existencia anterior de nudosidades en la cara, las manchas rojizas, los granos verrugosos
y las escrescencias son circunstancias que pueden caracterizar las neuralgias propias de la
thuya; se observa tambien efervescencia sanguínea, pulsaciones arteriales, chasquido en las
articulaciones, preferencia marcada á afectarse, el lado izquierdo, la agravacion por la noche,
con el calor y el movimiento, y que los fenómenos de la circulacion se exacerban, por el contrario,
con el reposo.

Pretenden algunos que las muchas neuralgias que la thuya puede curar, son de orígen sicósico,
así como ciertos dolores reumáticos le tienen gonorréico, sifilítico..., lo cual es aun problemático
y que la práctica aclarará algun dia; mas sea de esto lo que quiera, la thuya no es el único
medicamento que se dirige á la causa mas bien que al síntoma; pero es una verdad práctica,
que cura en efecto ciertas neuralgias, manifestacion de una diátesis sicósica, y que la aparicion
de las escrescencias es precedida frecuentemente de neuralgias reumáticas, y que se manifiestan
muchas veces despues de la escision de aquellas, ó de la espontánea presentacion de las vegetaciones
sicósicas.

La hemicránea, que consiste en un dolor como de clavo histérico, ó que por lo menos ocupa un
punto limitado hácia las suturas, con conmociones vivas y como golpes de dolor, que se alivia
inclinando la cabeza hacia atrás, está en relacion con los efectos de la thuya.

Merece sin duda que se la use mas en las neuralgias histéricas, á parte de las reputadas esenciales,
y en ciertos casos de ninfomanía, á consecuencia del onanismo, con temblor de los miembros,
estremecimientos, sudores y calores frecuentes, movimientos congestivos en la cabeza y en el
pecho. Hay vértigos y sensacion como de embriaguez, oscurecimiento de la vista, incomodidades
en la cabeza por la mañana, lancinaciones en las sienes, malestar y endolorimiento ó dislaceracion
en el occipucio, encendimiento de la cara en momentos dados, sobre todo por la mañana al despertar;
en el pecho: opresion, agitacion y sensacion de hinchazon, violentas palpitaciones y sensibilidad
dolorosa del corazon.

Las neuralgias propias de la thuya son generalmente tirantes y lancinantes, como por sacudidas
ó circunscriptas á puntos limitados, rara vez son fijas, ocupan los músculos ó las articulaciones,
que dan chasquidos con el movimiento de estension. Atacan mas comunmente á las personas adultas,
que sudan estraordinariamente en las junturas, que tienen las venas superficiales muy pronunciadas,
la piel laxa y muy porosa, con granos, nudosidades y ciertas escrescencias ó vegetaciones adquiridas
ó congénitas.

Si nos fuera dable esponer algunos resultados de nuestra práctica, agregariamos que la thuya
es eficaz en ciertas laringitis, incontinencias de orina, catarro crónico de la nariz, tortícolis,
cefalalgia sorda, rebelde é insomnio. Pero preferimos terminar este capítulo, haciendo observar
que cuando se emplee la thuya en escrescencias y otras afecciones esteriores, debe usarse esterior
é interiormente en tintura poco diluida. Unas veces son ineficaces las dósis fuertes para el
interior, en otras, sucede lo contrario; es uno de los medicamentos mas difíciles de dosificar;
pero, repetimos, que es una de las mas preciosas adquisiciones de la terapéutica, aun cuando
limitase su uso á las escrescencias y vegetaciones, mal tratadas hasta hoy por la escision,
en atencion á la facilidad de reproducirse y multiplicarse, por la influencia del gérmen ó
diátesis, que no puede desconocerse sin inconvenientes.

=Dósis.=--Las dósis de la thuya para el interior son las mismas que las indicadas en el acónito,
carbonato de cal..... Se la emplea generalmente en solucion, en la proporcion de una parte
de la tintura para una ó dos de agua pura, tocando con ella las vegetaciones varias veces al
dia con un pincel. Se puede aplicar en pomada en algunas úlceras, compuesta con diez partes
de enjundia y una de tintura, dándola simultáneamente al interior.

VALERIANA OFFICINALIS (VALERIANA).

§ I.--Historia.

Se hace la tintura con la raiz fresca. Es de la familia de las dipsáceas, de Juss.--De la triandria
monoginia, Linn.--Tambien se la llama pequeña valeriana.

Fundados en numerosos documentos antiguos y modernos, bien podemos afirmar, así de este medicamento
como de otros muchos, que los trabajos de Hahnemann y sus discípulos, que nos han servido de
guía en nuestras propias esperiencias y aplicaciones clínicas, son altamente preferibles.

Los antiguos han recomendado escesivamente la valeriana: en la hemicránea, parálisis, amenorrea,
pleuresía, fiebres intermitentes, pútridas y nerviosas, el tifus. Tissot exageraba de tal manera
la eficacia de este medicamento, que creia incurable toda convulsion que se resistiese á su
uso, como si todas las convulsiones tuviesen un mismo carácter y reconociesen una misma causa.
Bouteille confiaba tanto en la valeriana que la proponia como profiláctica de la hidrofobia.
El profesor Trousseau hace de ella el medicamento esencial del histerismo. Giacomini es mas
moderado, pero sin atender, segun su costumbre, á las especialidades y á la accion electiva
del medicamento; creia á la valeriana un hipostenizante vascular y espinal, ni mas ni menos
que como la asafétida, árnica, zumaque venenoso y aun el plomo, medicamentos que confunde en
una accion general, aunque mas débil en la valeriana.

§ II.--Efectos fisiológicos y terapéuticos.

Tomada la valeriana á dósis fuertes, desplega una accion intensa, pero inconstante. Es indudable
que las angustias, las palpitaciones, el encendimiento de la cara, los vértigos congestivos,
los sudores, las laxitudes espontáneas, y la debilidad paralítica son efectos perturbadores,
de poca duracion, y casi inútiles para basar en ellos las indicaciones, como lo prueba suficientemente
la clínica; y los hechos son siempre mas elocuentes que las disertaciones y discursos.

Por los hechos y los síntomas que la esperimentacion fisiológica revela, la valeriana tiene
una accion electiva sobre los nervios espinales y ganglionares, de la cual resultan: la tension
y movilidad nerviosa, congestion y calores fugaces, espasmos parciales, sensibilidad é irritabilidad
escesivas, é insensibilidad despues; desórden, en fin, de la sensibilidad, y desarmonía de
la inervacion.

Pocos medicamentos habrá que se adapten mejor que la valeriana á la nerviosidad de las mujeres
delicadas y de los niños escesivamente sensibles y afectados por las lombrices; mas no corresponde
á la sobreimpresionabilidad de los sentidos y á la movilidad nerviosa, elemento importante
del histerismo, y por lo tanto en este mismo.

La valeriana está asimismo contraindicada en la bola histérica, pero no cuando solamente hay
sensacion de calor que asciende del epigastrio ó del ombligo hasta la faringe, con náuseas
casi siempre. Estas bocanadas de calor ascendente son un síntoma característico de su accion.

Altera la circulacion momentáneamente; y sin embargo, se adapta con exactitud á ciertas afecciones
reumáticas con fiebre subaguda, dolores erráticos numerosos, y sensacion de quebrantamiento
y debilidad, á título de regulador del sistema nervioso.

Bajo este punto de vista tambien está indicada la valeriana en las fiebres nerviosas y tifoídeas,
cuando el pulso es pequeño y rápido, si hay exaltacion de los sentidos de la vista y del oido
al tacto, salto de tendones sin constancia, inercia del sistema muscular, orinas abundantes,
bocanadas de calor que se elevan hácia la cabeza, erupcion miliar algunas veces, delirio tranquilo
que consiste en alucinaciones, el enfermo se cree, por ejemplo, en el borde de la cama, para
hacer sitio á otro.

Se preferirá igualmente la valeriana á cualquiera otro, en las fiebres verminosas de los niños
y en toda fiebre con predominio nervioso, principalmente cuando hay palidez, ansiedades, palpitaciones
de corazon, estremecimientos musculares.

Agregarémos á estas indicaciones algunos datos útiles para el uso de la valeriana en el estado
de nerviosidad é impresionabilidad de las personas hipocondríacas que duermen mal, que siempre
tienen dolores, procedentes de flatuosidades en su concepto, y de ciertas ideas que las angustian;
sienten con frecuencia hambre estraordinaria, con náuseas y aun vómitos, deposiciones diarréicas;
por lo general las orinas son abundantes y claras. Si bien la valeriana no es capaz de curar
completamente estos padecimientos nerviosos, en cuanto á sus causas diatésicas al menos, es
sin embargo muy útil y puede favorecer la eleccion de medicamentos mas fundamentales, por las
modificaciones que induce en el estado general. Si, en fin, la importancia de la valeriana
en el tratamiento del histerismo es inferior á la del eléboro en las mismas circunstancias,
el lector podrá juzgar de la riqueza terapéutica que le ofrece la materia médica, despues de
haber visto en esta obra un buen número de medicamentos eminentemente antihistéricos.

=Dósis.=--Las dósis de la valeriana son las mismas que las ya indicadas en otros medicamentos,
que se administran en diversas atenuaciones ó en tintura.

VERATRUM ALBUM (ELÉBORO BLANCO).

§ I.--Historia.

Esta planta es de la familia de las colchicáceas, Juss.--De la poligamia monoecia, Linn.--La
raiz fresca es la parte usada, y se la trata segun arte. Casi completamente abandonado este
medicamento durante muchos siglos, ha necesitado que Hahnemann, á quien tanto debe la terapéutica,
le sacará del olvido á principios de actual. Su disertacion histórica y médica sobre el eléboro
y el eleborismo de los antiguos[28], es un monumento de erudicion. El eléboro era el remedio
de todos los males graves y crónicos, pero sin fiebre. Acudian enfermos en gran número, aun
desde los países mas remotos, á Anticyra, ciudad de la Grecia, donde habia establecimientos
dirigidos por médicos que sometian los enfermos al eleborismo, medicacion en estremo violenta.

Tambien se trataba de este modo la enagenacion mental, la melancolía, las neuralgias, los reumatismos,
la gota, la epilepsia, los vértigos y las parálisis, la elefantiasis, las afecciones herpéticas,
los cálculos, la escrófula, la hipocondría, el cáncer oculto. Hipócrates trataba el cólera
de su tiempo, indígeno sin duda, con el eléboro. Este heróico medicamento, en fin, caia al
mismo tiempo que la Grecia sucumbía ante la grandeza absorbente de Roma; y en la edad media
no se volvió á hablar de él. Mas tarde se hizo alguna mencion indecisa. Se confundia, por lo
tanto, las diversas especies de eléboro, hasta que Hahnemann, no contento con dar á conocer
la grande importancia que los antiguos dieron á este medicamento, se entregó á numerosas esperimentaciones,
que, repetidas por algunos médicos, los hechos las han confirmado altamente, desde el cólera
asiático, hasta las neuralgias y toses convulsivas.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10983</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>90774</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20298</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

3. Th in the gastro-slack with increased secretion of gastric mucus and intestinal venous fullness
and obstruction in the circulation of the portal vein.

4. Th in the gastro-enteritis and thrush in children after borax and almost the same Indications:
belly loose, yellow stools, foam and as cut into small pieces rumbling,
low fever, pulse small, pale and sad.

5. ª In the last period of some mucous and catarrhal fever, coryza
and bronchitis in simple, polisárcicas pale in people very willing
to suffer for their long term Organizational, and characterized by
mucus, mouth, and the feeling of corrosion.

6. ª sterility in the catamenial flow in excess of weak women.

7.

Epileptiform seizures ª lifeless people, especially in adulthood; in muscle cramps and colic,
as long as people are not fussy; hernias in children testura soft: in these cases is preferable
to sulfuric acid the lycopodium, sulfur and even to the nux vomica.

Sulfuric acid is a certainly long forgotten, in spite of its sphere of action is not acid less than
the whip. If this is of great importance as antimercurial, acid sulfuric acid, the sulfur that
enters into their composition, is more effective against herpes, but Secondary herpes or mucous,
as evidenced by their physiological effects that make apropos to successfully treat thrush, canker
with minor abrasions side in irritation chronic itching of the mucous
membranes and the cracks of the lips.

Recently, no longer useful in treating certain skin conditions with
itching usually stains red, itching, livid and blue plates, abrasions
covered with scabs spontaneous yellow and chilblains, dry rashes on
the hands and between fingers of the same.

= Dose .=-- The dose and mode of administration are the same as for hydrochloric acid.

Thuja occidentalis (Western YOURS).

§ I. - History.

Yours or the Canadian West is a family tree of the coniferous Juss monoecy .-- From monadelfia,
Linn .-- Although Boerhaave and probably would ignore some British doctors and Americans have
dealt with the Canadian thuya If Hahnemann had not proposed listing
all known facts about the use of this substance, particularly in dropsy
and sorrows indeterminate members.

A therapy should only Hahnemann this precious acquisition: its work on thuya part of the history of
psychosis or of condylomata, special affection that this man has tirelessly to put the first
regular observation and specific treatment to which this drug enters as one of its first officers.

But
first of all we will say something about the psychosis.

The definition has been given of this word [26] applies to the mentagra, but the word fic [27]
is the definition that gives Celsus psychosis, which is said escrescencias fleshy, commonly located
on the edge of mucous membranes and skin, which sometimes degenerate into ulcers.

Psychosis occurs so often in consequence of syphilis, which has led to confuse these two viruses.
Hahnemann wants to distinguish them, but has not given the characters differential. In memory of
Dr. Petroz on psychosis, is as follows: "All kind of tumor that forms
beneath the epidermis, the thickness of the dermis, the tissue Papillary
and the gray matter of Malpighian should be regarded as a product
of psychosis, when not recognized because of smallpox or the syphilitic
virus, when it exists, the formation the escrescencia is due to the
complication of syphilis with psychosis.

The productions are elevations sicósicas epidermis or epithelium of
the hypertrophied papillae and situated on a point hardened by a chronic
inflammation that usually occurs in consequence of a stroke, a compression,
a scratch.

The forms vary according to testura the part where they are located, and probably also, according
to that is purely sicósica escrescencia, or mixed with the syphilitic virus, the herpes ..... In the
skin presents rather the appearance of warts, on mucous membranes, sexual parts, margin the
anus, on the edge of the eye and lips, it has a meatier, more tender,
confused through the same thing with grain cancer.

Ficiformes or pedunculated warts, warts, vegetations rattle calls and cauliflower, are manifestations
of psychosis.

Is divided, then, this condition in acute, chronic and syphilis: the latter variety is not hallmark,
unless it is not accepted as such its appearance with the primitive phenomena of syphilis: treatment
results prove their nature.

Acute psychosis is particularly hard grain usually conical, red-faced
which sometimes degenerates into gray background corroding ulcer,
hard edges and high, they feel stitches in the work of the degeneration,
the grain becomes very sore and is formed ulcer: in these cases is
often fever.

Escrescencia sometimes warty, ficiforme, smooth and indolent, or splits open with or without pain,
and is divided into several lobes.

Chronic psychosis is the vegetation that we have listed, and preference
is presented towards forty.

Boeninghausen can admit, as a sign of hereditary psychosis and the indication of the thuja, two
symptoms that then listed among its physiological effects, and are bulge of flesh at the tip
of the fingers and hands as the feet.

The distinction that we have laid down, according to the opinion of some authors and observation
of the facts, not deactivated when, by way of others, the idea that psychosis is always origin syphilitic.
It is convenient, however, indicate, without attempting to resolve the issue, the horse and dog frequently
suffer from psychosis, everyone knows the affection of mouth in the
dog, which extends in a few days to the entire cavity and fills it
with vegetation.

Thuya is specific, because it makes them disappear quickly without fire or caustics, and without
excision: these operations, in the final result, favor sicósicas escrescencias reproduction of, and
even make them more numerous. Developing, Therefore, the psychosis of horse and dog without syphilis and
no finches phenomena tend to establish that this condition is independent
of syphilis.

Polypoid vegetations are perhaps a form of psychosis and has also been given the same origin to the
area, smallpox, and to certain ulcers that occur in the dermis.

We at least they have a powerful thuya elective action on the dermis, work very favorably in
certain lesions of this part.

Several other drugs have an action similar to the thuja, as to the different vegetations ficiformes,
such as: acid whipping, club moss, lime carbonate, silica, bismuth, savin, even states with respect
to the escrescencias in general and certain polyps, phosphorus, the causticum, bittersweet, antimony,
copper acetate, the Teucrium Marum, mugwort.

In summary, treatment of vegetation and other escrescencias of this genre as well as the terrible
sores that happen to some ficus, beads and condylomas, is one of
the most beautiful achievements of modern therapeutics, conquest that
we owe to Hahnemann, who, although has been attributed exclusively
to the thuya to the specificity that has not, since there need in
many cases resorting to nitric acid, lycopodium and other drugs, it
is a truth thuya that work more effectively so as independent as is
the vegetation of any Another virus that develops on the mucous membranes
in the points next to the skin, and presents pedunculated form, smooth,
reddish and rather soft consistency that lasts.

This does not mean that this drug has no major indications in certain
grains sycotic skin, and also shaped pedunculated warty, but always
smooth, with some redness.

§ II .-- physiological and therapeutic effects.

It is well established that the thuya has a special action on the dermis, and even on all parts of
the skin surface without its influence to limit it this system. Offered in all their symptoms, and
a very strong blood excitation and phenomena of irritation of mucous
membranes, and asthenia and nutritional disorders; presents, in short,
neuralgia referred both hiperesténico period as the hiposténico, and
consist of pain varied as essential as symptomatic of rheumatic neuralgia,
migraine, painful tics, nail hysterical.

Febrile conditions typical of Thuya flegmásicas are still poorly defined, and clinical has few
facts to the effect, if excepting some cases of intermittent fever or sender and rather catarrhal
fever in predominantly chills. Thuya also is effective runny nose in the rebel, coryza, certain ophthalmia,
stomatitis, urethritis, when the mucous are swollen or have some
points the same as hypertrophied extraordinary development vascular
system, increased sensitivity, flow serous, mucous and even purulent.

Its indication extends to serosa leucorrhoea and subacute gonorrhea; the coryza with flow watery,
runny nose, scrofulous state, at the same ozena; to the cataract
followed with ophthalmia chemosis, conjunctival mucous tubercles,
sero-mucous flow.

Sulfur is a good auxiliary and it must be stressed these two drugs administered one after
another or alternating.

It is useful also in gonorrhea thuya with escrescencias in condylomata exudates, in cankers with
fleshy growths, in which three directions is insufficient acid nitric, and in which the thuja
can play alone or alternating with it.

This medicine is the cure for excellence of the tubers mucous vegetations
pedunculated or wide base, smooth, with or without irritation of the
adjacent mucosa, in the year, or elsewhere.

Lycopodium is its analogue in these cases. We know that whipped acid corresponds better to multiple
vegetations, granular, exuding and bleeding, but also We expresses as the excision is not a
wise practice.

Canker repeated or multiple pale background, with irregular borders
and placed sensitive on irritated mucous correspond to the thuja.

In that heal sores serpiginous on one hand to stretch it out for another, and abrasions in
the foreskin and the vagina serous or purulent exudation, you must toggle the thuya nitric acid, if the
preparations have no indication as mercury, or if aggravate the condition.

The special action on the skin thuya inclined to hire you in the smallpox successful and some
studies say, based on the facts that the drug is important, if no specific and even condoms. It
has been given, as mercury, the property to prevent scars indelible from the pustules of smallpox,
managing it towards the end of the period of suppuration.

Sometimes occur frequently use the thuya in certain skin conditions, the syphilids particularly
preferably in the form pustular acne, mentagra certain chilblains, patches of dark red and
the redness of the copperas in the nose, lips and chin.

This redness is different from other similar conditions, by sensation of heat and some stitches,
mainly afternoon and evening, by arrangement to the hot red swelling of the fingers and toes,
the pavilion of the ear, the nostrils, the ease to bulge, veins and general sensitivity skin.

This
provision of the veins, the sweat on his genitals, hands and feet; the former existence of
nodules on the face, red patches, beads warty and escrescencias are circumstances that may characterize
the inherent neuralgia thuja, is also observed blood effervescence, arterial pulsations, click on the
joints, strong preference to be affected, the left side, worsening
at night with heat and motion, and that the phenomena of the circulation
are exacerbated, however, with rest.

Some claim that many thuya neuralgia that can heal, are sycotic origin, and some will have gonorrhoeal
rheumatism, syphilitic ... which is still problematic practice and clarify some day, but this
is what you want, thuya is not the only drug targeting to the cause rather than the symptom, but
is a practical truth, In fact curing certain neuralgia, a manifestation of sicósica diathesis,
and the appearance of escrescencias is frequently preceded by rheumatic neuralgias, and are manifested
many times after excision of those, or the spontaneous presentation
of the vegetations sicósicas.

Migraine, which is a pain as hysterical nail, or at least has an limited
extent towards the sutures, with shocks and blows fresh and pain,
relieved tilting the head back, is in relation to the effects of thuja.

Definitely

worth it to be used in neuralgia more hysterical part of the reputed to essential and in some cases of
nymphomania, in consequence of masturbation, with trembling of the limbs, tremors, sweating,
and frequent hot flashes, congestive movements in the head and chest. There are dizziness and
feeling like a drunken, dimming of vision, discomfort in the head in the morning, lancinating
in temples, or laceration discomfort and endolorimiento in occiput, lighting of the face at a time
given, especially in the morning on waking; Chest, oppression, agitation, and feeling bloated, violent
palpitation and sensitivity heartache.

Neuralgia own thuya are generally tight and lancinating, as shock or confined to limited points
are rarely fixed, take the muscles or joints, that are popping with movement extent. More commonly
attack adults, sudan extraordinary that in the joints, superficial veins that have pronounced, lax
skin and very porous, with grains, lumps or growths and certain acquired escrescencias or defects.

If
we were possible exposes some results of our practice, add that thuya is effective in certain laryngitis,
urinary incontinence, chronic runny nose, stiff neck, dull headache,
insomnia and rebellious.

But we prefer to finish this chapter, noting that when used in escrescencias thuya and other
exterior conditions should be used exterior and internally in tincture bit diluted. Sometimes strong
doses are ineffective for inside, in others the opposite is true, it is one of the most difficult
drug to dose; but, again, that is one of the most precious acquisitions of treatment, even if limit
its use to the escrescencias and vegetation, poorly treated today by excision, In view of the
ease of reproduce and multiply, by the influence of germ or diathesis, which can not be ignored
without problems.

= Dose .=-- thuya doses for the interior are the same as reported in the aconite, calcium carbonate
..... It is used usually in solution, in the proportion of part of
the dye for one or two of pure water, playing with her several times
vegetations day with a brush.

Ointment can be applied in some ulcers, consisting of ten parts of substance and a dye, turning
it inside simultaneously.

Valeriana officinalis (valerian).

§ I. - History.

It makes the dyeing with the fresh root. It dipsáceas the family of De la Triandria Juss .-- monoginia,
Linn .-- Also called valerian small.

Founded in numerous ancient and modern documents, we may affirm, thus this drug like many others,
that the work of Hahnemann and his disciples, who have served guide
our own experience and clinical applications, are highly preferable.

The former have recommended valerian exceedingly: the migraine, paralysis, amenorrhea, pleurisy,
intermittent fevers, putrid and nerve typhus. So exaggerated Tissot the effectiveness of this
drug, that all seizure thought to be incurable resist their use, as if they had seizures all
the same character and acknowledged a common cause. Bouteille valerian so confident that he
proposed as a prophylactic of hydrophobia. Professor Trousseau makes it the essential drug
hysteria. Giacomini is more moderate, but unattended, as usual, to the specialists and elective
action medication, believed to valerian a vascular and spinal hipostenizante, neither more nor
less that as asafoetida, arnica, poison ivy and even lead, medicines
confused a general action, but weaker in valerian.

§ II .-- physiological and therapeutic effects.

Taken heavy dose of valerian, displays an intense action but fickle. Undoubtedly that anxiety, palpitations,
the lighting of the face, dizziness congested, sweats, the laxitudes
spontaneous and paralytic weakness are disruptive effects, of short
duration, and almost useless for them based on the indications, as
sufficient proof the clinic, and the facts are always more eloquent
than lectures and speeches.

For the facts and physiological symptoms that reveals esperimentacion, valerian has an elective action
on the spinal nerve and ganglion, which are: the tension and nerve mobility, congestion and
hot shooting, partial spasms, tenderness and irritability excesses,
and numbness after; disorder, in short, sensitivity, and disharmony
innervation.

Few drugs will be better suited to valerian to the nervousness of women delicate and exceedingly
sensitive children, affected by the worms, but not for to the injection
of the senses and nervous for mobility, an important element of hysteria,
and therefore on the premises.

Valerian is also contraindicated in hysterical ball, but not when
only sensation of heat rising from the epigastrium or the navel to
the throat, nausea almost always.

These upward heat puffs are a symptom of its action.

Alter the circulation momentarily, and yet fits exactly to certain
conditions subacute rheumatic fever, aches, erratic numerous, and
feeling of brokenness and weakness, as a regulator of the nervous
system.

Under this view also is indicated valerian in nervous and typhoid fever, when the pulse is small
and fast, if there is exaltation of the senses of sight and hearing to touch, break tendons without
constancy, inertia of the muscular system, increased urination puffs of heat that rises to the
head, miliary eruption sometimes quiet delirium consisting of hallucinations,
the patient is believed, for example, on the edge of the bed to make
room to another.

Valerian also be preferred to any other, in fevers of children verminous
and fever prevalence in all nervous, especially when there is pallor,
anxiety, palpitations of heart, muscle tremors.

Add to these some useful indications for the use of valerian in the state of nervousness and impressions
of the hypochondria people who sleep badly, always in pain, from flatuosidades in concept, and certain
ideas that the distressed; often feel extraordinary hunger, nausea and even vomiting, loose
stools; the urine usually are abundant and clear. Although valerian is not able to cure these
conditions completely nervous, as to its causes diathetic at least, however, very useful and
might lead to more fundamental choice of drugs, by induces changes in the general. If, finally,
the importance of valerian in the treatment of hysteria is inferior to that of hellebore in
the same circumstances, the reader can judge the therapeutic wealth offered by the medical field,
after have seen in this work a number of eminently antihysteric drugs.

= Dose .=-- doses of valerian are the same as those already identified
in other medicines, administered in various mitigations or tincture.

ALBUM Veratrum (Hellebore WHITE).

§ I. - History.

This plant belongs to the family of colchicáceas, Juss monoecy .-- In polygamy, Linn .-- The
fresh root is the part used, and treated according to art. Almost completely abandoned this
medicine for many centuries, has required that Hahnemann, whom he owes so much therapeutic
you out of oblivion to early today.

His dissertation on the medical history and hellebore and hellebore of the ancients [28], is a monument
of erudition. Hellebore was the remedy of all serious and chronic ailments, but no fever. Patients
flocked in large numbers, even from the most remote countries, to Anticyra, city of Greece,
where they had established directed by physicians who submitted the patients to hellebore,
in the extreme, violent medication.

Also it was thus the mental alienation, melancholia, neuralgia, rheumatism, gout, epilepsy,
dizziness and paralysis, elephantiasis, a condition herpetic calculations, scrofula, hypochondriasis, hidden
cancer. Hippocrates was cholera of his time, certainly indian with hellebore. This heroic medicine,
finally, fell to while Greece absorbent succumb to the greatness
of Rome, and in the Middle Ages not to speak of it again. Later they
made some mention undecided. Are confounded, so Thus, the various
species of hellebore, until Hahnemann, not content to make known the
great importance that the ancients gave to this drug, was given to
many experiments, which, repeated by some doctors, the facts have
confirmed the high, from cholera Asia, to the neuralgia and convulsive
coughs</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>