<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04598</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>247104</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20471</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Al llegar arriba atravesaron
una vasta antesala donde gran número de jóvenes se apresuraron a abrirles paso y saludarles
con la familiaridad que se usa en los pueblos pequeños. En el salón había ya bastantes damas,
todas disfrazadas, aunque la mayor parte de ellas, como Cecilia, sin máscara. Para los sarrienses
era aquello una sorpresa. En los cinco últimos años, los bailes del Liceo parecían visitas
de pésame. Media docena de señoritas más o menos jóvenes, con los hombros y el pecho al aire,
el rostro muy empolvado, departiendo en voz baja allá en un ángulo del vasto salón, mientras
a su lado las mamás sacaban tiras de pellejo a alguna amiga ausente. Otros tantos pollos dando
vueltas en la antesala, el aire triste, la mirada opaca, abrochándose mutuamente los guantes
con las horquillas de sus hermanas. Generalmente eran los mismos. Cada pollo bailaba dos o
tres polkas, rigodones o lanceros con las hermanas de sus amigos. A las doce o doce y media
salían todos en pelotón, remangándose los pantalones y las faldas respectivamente, y guareciéndose
debajo de los paraguas, charlando en voz alta al través de las calles solitarias y húmedas.
Los vecinos, a quienes el sueño no tenía presos, decían:--«Ahora salen del Liceo». Esto era
todo. Don Mateo, firme, indomable, conservaba tenazmente, con amoroso esmero, este exiguo rescoldo
del fuego del placer.

Gracias a su perseverancia, aquella noche se convirtió en viva y animada hoguera. La juventud
de la villa tuvo fuerzas para arrollar las ruines pasiones que agitaban los pechos de sus papás,
y entró en aquel solitario salón como un torrente desbordado, haciéndolo resonar con sus risas
y pláticas, con chillidos horrísonos:

--Alvaro, ¿me conoces? ¿me conoces? ¿Por qué no te casas? Mira que ya vas caminando para Villavieja.

--Periquito, ¿te gusto?... ¿Que alce la careta?... ¿Para qué lo necesitas? Tú no te enamoras
de las caras y haces bien. ¡Teniendo de aquí... y de aquí! ¿Eh? Adiós, adiós, Periquito.

--Hola, Delaunay... Hola, monsieur. ¿Cómo va ese tranvía aéreo? ¡Qué cosas se te ocurren! ¡Qué
gran cabeza tienes! ¡Lástima que seas tan desgraciado! Dicen que no eres hombre práctico. Sin
embargo, supiste arreglar a la hija del Rato... Adiós, adiós...

--¿Qué tal, Sinforoso? ¿Cuándo te dan la mano de Cipriana?... Bien te hacen penar, hombre.
¿Por qué no los amenazas con pasarte otra vez al Saloncillo?

Había muchas señoras con dominó negro, que eran las que daban estas bromas, demasiado vivas
a veces. La mayor parte de ellas eran viejas. A las jóvenes, les gustaba mostrar el palmito
y la esbeltez de su talle, con algún traje histórico. Había damas venecianas, romanas, del
bajo imperio, hebreas, de la época de Luis XV, del Directorio, de Felipe II, y hasta pasiegas
de los tiempos más recientes. Había también, algunas gitanas, nigrománticas y cautivas. Veíanse
trajes caprichosos y románticos, que no admitían clasificación; uno de noche estrellada, otro
de tulipán, otro de paloma viajera con una cartita al cuello. Los hombres en general no llevaban
disfraz: vestían la larga y desairada levita, que sólo salía a relucir en ocasiones como ésta.
Sin embargo, veíanse algunos con dominó, que les servía para acercarse y hablar a sus novias,
sin peligro de ser interrumpidos por las mamás. Un grupo de jóvenes afiliados al Camarote,
que venían de este modo, habían tenido la feliz ocurrencia de disfrazar a don Jaime Marín de
maragato. Cuando le tuvieron vestido de esta suerte, le dijeron que mejor que careta, convenía
que se pintase; a lo cual él se prestó. Tomó un chico el pincel y la caja de pinturas, y fingiendo
que le embadurnaba con mil colores, le paseó el pincel largo rato por la cara, mojado en agua
solamente. Pidió Marín un espejo para verse. Los maleantes jóvenes tuvieron buen cuidado de
no proporcionárselo. Todo se volvía gritar:--¡Pero qué bien está usted, don Jaime! ¡qué horrorosamente
pintado! Ni la madre que le parió puede conocerle. Bajo la fe de esta palabra, el buen Marín
se dejó llevar al Liceo. Sus amiguitos le aconsejaron que no dejase de dar bromas a ciertas
señoritas; a lo que él contestaba, que serían como sinapismos. Y en efecto, así que entró en
el salón, comenzó a dirigirse a las muchachas gritando con voz de falsete:

--Hola, Rosarito, ¿dónde has dejado a Anselmo? Ya sabemos que todas las noches a las diez le
tiras una cartita por el balcón.

--¡Pero, don Jaime!--exclamaba la niña mirándole con sorpresa.--¿Usted cómo viene así?

--¡Diablo! Ya me ha conocido--decía el buen Marín alejándose.

Dirigíase inmediatamente a otra, y pasaba lo mismo.

--Es particular--concluyó por decirse.--Todas me conocen al instante... Será por la voz, porque
lo que es pintado, ¡lo estoy de órdago!

Cuando estaba haciéndose esta reflexión, una mano huesuda le agarró por detrás.

--Gran burro, bobalicón, zoquete, ¿quién te ha metido aquí de este modo?

Era su amada compañera, la ingeniosa y severa doña Brígida.

--¡Anda, bestia, anda, que siempre has de servir de payaso en todas partes!

Y a empujones lo fué sacando del salón. La buena señora, que venía disfrazada con dominó y
careta, luego que le dejó en la antesala con orden expresa y terminante de irse inmediatamente
a casa, se volvió a meter en el centro del baile, donde tenía un asunto de importancia que
resolver, como luego veremos.

Rodeado por un grupo de máscaras estaba el simpático don Feliciano Gómez. Su gran pirámide
de cabeza monda y reluciente, descollaba soberbia por encima. Eran mujeres las que formaban
círculo en torno suyo, armando algarabía insufrible. Las bromas que le prodigaban tocaban a
menudo en la injuria.

--¡Feliciano, milagro que te han dejado venir al baile tus hermanas! ¿A qué hora te han mandado
retirarte? Dicen que doña Petra te castiga cuando llegas tarde, ¿es verdad? ¡Pobre Feliciano!
¡Qué severas son tus hermanas! Ya que no te han permitido casarte, debieran darte un poco más
de libertad.

El bravo comerciante, sin ofenderse, contestaba con sonrisa bondadosa a aquellas arpías. Al
fin, cansadas de su paciencia, le dejaron en paz.

El adorable Pablito, vestido correctamente de frac, con una flor blanca en el ojal, llevaba
a cabo mientras tanto la conquista de cierta hermosa hebrea, hija de un comandante de artillería
que acababa de llegar. La pobrecilla, al ver rendido a sus pies al joven más rico y más apuesto
de la villa, dejaba escapar por todos los poros de su lindo rostro ruborizado, el gozo íntimo
que le embargaba. ¡Qué sonrisas, qué gestos tan expresivos! Las muchachas de la población la
miraban con expresión de burla. Aquellas miradas decían:--«Goza, goza un poco, infeliz, que
pronto vendrá el desengaño».

Pablito, inclinado, sumiso, la vertía al oído frases ardientes e ingeniosas como éstas:

--Ayer cuando venía de Tejada, la he visto a usted con su papá, tan guapetona como siempre.

--¡Qué guasón! También yo le vi. Venía usted en coche abierto. Guía usted muy bien.

--Es favor, Carmencita. Guiar ahora esos caballos no tiene nada de particular, lo hace cualquiera.
¡Si los viera usted cuando los compré! El cochero de don Agapito los había echado a perder
enteramente; sobre todo el Gallardo, el de la izquierda, ¿sabe usted? un poco más obscuro que
el otro... Aquél era una cosa perdida. Si cae en otras manos, a estas horas no vale dos pesetas.
Hoy es mejor que el otro todavía... Cuestión de paciencia, ¿sabe usted?--añadió con fingida
modestia.

La linda hebrea protestó:

--Vamos, no se haga usted el pequeño, que ya sabemos que lo hace usted muy bien.

--Paciencia y un poco de costumbre--repitió Pablito bañándose en agua de rosas.

Después le explicó con toda latitud lo que en su concepto constituía un buen cochero. La mano
suave y firme al mismo tiempo, el ojo vivo, castigar fuerte cuando hace falta, pero sin irritarse;
luego un gran conocimiento de lo que son los caballos. Sin el estudio atento y reflexivo del
temperamento de estos animales, imposible guiar regularmente. Carmencita le escuchaba embelesada.

A Cecilia se le había acercado, poco después de entrar en el salón, Paco Flores, aquel ingeniero
que pidió su mano por mediación de Gonzalo. Desde que la joven le diera calabazas, él, que,
como hemos visto, sólo buscaba una mujer modesta, hacendosa y con algún dinero, se había enamorado
de ella y la perseguía a sol y sombra. En Sarrió, al ver la persistencia del ingeniero en festejar
a la primogénita de Belinchón, se creía que apetecía sólo con ansia la dote. Era un error.
Flores se había llegado a enamorar de veras. Si Cecilia se quedase pobre repentinamente, lo
mismo la haría su mujer. La conducta de ésta, también era adecuada para encender su ilusión.
A todos sus obsequios y galanterías respondía siempre con amabilidad y gratitud. No había peligro
de que la joven se retirase del balcón cuando él pasaba, ni esquivase su conversación cuando
le encontraba en alguna casa conocida o le diese alguno de esos desaires que tanto hacen gozar
a la mayoría de las muchachas. Le trataba como un buen amigo, guardándole todas las atenciones
que se deben a la persona que se estima. Pero en cuanto el ingeniero quería pasar adelante,
pedía un poco de amor, un rayo de esperanza, siquiera para el día de mañana, encontraba la
misma negativa, suave, firme y constante. Y lo peor era que Cecilia, al negar, no lo hacía
con placer, sino con repugnancia, como si le doliese causar disgusto a un amigo. Este sentimiento
hería aún más el amor propio del pretendiente.

Después que bailaron un vals, sentáronse fatigados en un ángulo del salón. Flores le había
cogido el abanico, y la abanicaba respetuosamente.

--Así quisiera pasarme la vida--dijo con acento sincero.

--¡Oh! Se cansaría pronto--respondió Cecilia sonriendo.

--¿Quiere usted probarlo?

La joven no contestó.

--No es usted, Cecilia, de las mujeres que hastían pronto. Posee usted en su corazón y en su
inteligencia recursos para tener siempre a sus pies al hombre que la ame. Hace más de dos años
que vivo enamorado de usted, y, en vez de cansarme, cada vez me siento más ligado a usted,
cada vez la adoro más perdidamente... hasta el punto de ser la burla de la población.

--Eso no se puede decir de antemano--repuso ella, un poco conmovida por el fuego y la emoción
que Flores había comunicado a sus palabras.--No es lo mismo ver a una mujer cortos instantes,
y hablarla de Pascuas a Ramos, que tenerla a su lado eternamente.

--¡Qué más quisiera yo, Cecilia! Tenerla junto a mí siempre, ¡siempre!--replicó en voz baja
y temblorosa el ingeniero, jugando con el abanico y mirando fijamente al suelo.--Consagrar
mi vida a servirla, a adorarla de rodillas... Yo sé que haría usted feliz a cualquier hombre,
pero a nadie tanto como a mí que conozco las grandes cualidades de su alma, que adivino además
en su corazón sentimientos que acaso sean enteramente desconocidos para otros... ¡Es terrible!
Eso de que usted no me haga concebir la más remota esperanza de que algún día, por lejano que
sea, mi cariño llegue a ablandarla, y me acepte siquiera por esclavo...

--Le acepto por amigo, por buen amigo--dijo la joven gravemente.

--Amigo, ¡oh!... Esa amistad, Cecilia, es una muralla de hielo que se interpone entre usted
y yo... Comprendo que no tengo mérito alguno para merecer el amor de usted... que hay cien
jóvenes en la villa que pudieran con más derecho solicitarlo... Pero lo extraño, lo que me
anima y desanima a un mismo tiempo, es que usted no se ha fijado en ninguno hasta ahora...
Su corazón permanece ocioso, indiferente... Digo, a no ser que tenga usted algún amor oculto.

Cecilia se estremeció levemente y levantó un poco los ojos hacia el sitio donde se escuchaba
la voz de Gonzalo. Después respondióle con más severidad que de ordinario:

--Deje usted de estudiar tanto mi interior, Flores; primero, porque lo más probable es que
sea tan vulgar como el de la mayoría de las mujeres, y segundo, porque, si hubiera algo de
particular en él, no sería fácil que usted lo descubriera.

--No se ofenda usted, Cecilia. Este estudio es una prueba nada más de lo mucho que usted me
interesa.

--No me ofendo--replicó la joven procurando sonreir.--Voy a saludar a Rosario. ¿Quiere usted
llevarme?

En la antesala, separada sólo por algunas columnas del salón, charlaban los padres graves,
echando ojeadas satisfechas a éste, donde veían a sus hijas divertirse. Alguna vez, se destacaba
un máscara del baile, y venía a embromarles. Era alguna vieja contemporánea que les hacía reir
y toser hasta reventar con historias antiguas. Don Rosendo charlaba en un rincón con don Melchor
de las Cuevas. Explicábale un vasto proyecto de puerto, grandioso como todos los suyos. Porque
no es posible representarse bien lo que había crecido la ciencia, ya grande, de Belinchón en
los últimos años. Era una ciencia más intuitiva que adquirida a fuerza de estudio, como acontece
a todos los grandes hombres. Al principio, cuando iba a escribir en El Faro sobre un tema que
no conocía, mostrábase receloso, vacilante, tímido. Mas en cuanto aprendió bien los tópicos
del periodismo, y tuvo a su disposición una buena cantidad de frases hechas, y sobre todo,
en cuanto recibió un diccionario enciclopédico en quince tomos, que le costó no menos de dos
mil reales, ¡aquello sí que fué cortar y rajar! No hubo asunto o problema científico, social,
económico y político en que don Rosendo dejase de meter la cucharada con gran lucimiento. Se
trataba de la peste que hacía estragos en el ganado: don Rosendo buscaba en su diccionario
las palabras ganado, caballo, toro, carnero, forrajes, industria pecuaria, etcétera, y así
que leía lo que decía sobre ellas, tomaba la pluma, y su genio periodístico se encargaba de
trazar uno o varios artículos, rebosando de filosofía y erudición. Venía, como ahora, la cuestión
del puerto, y acudía al diccionario en busca de las palabras puerto, dársena, mareas, dragas,
vientos, etc. Siete artículos llevaba escritos y publicados a la sazón, para demostrar la necesidad
de construir una gran dársena frente a Sarrió, en un punto denominado Fonil. Parecía un marino
consumado, harto de surcar los mares, encanecido en el estudio de los problemas hidráulicos.
Sin embargo, el señor de las Cuevas, aunque pasmado de aquel modo de barajar términos marítimos,
alguno de los cuales ni él mismo conocía, torcía el gesto a las explicaciones verbales que
don Rosendo le daba. Concluyó por decirle, poniéndole la mano en el hombro:

--Desengáñese usted, Belinchón: en la dársena de usted, con viento entablado del Noroeste,
no entran ni las sardinas.

El que más gozaba en esta fiesta, ¿quién lo diría? era un anciano, el buen don Mateo, a quien
se debía exclusivamente. Para él, aquel baile significaba uno de los grandes triunfos de su
vida. Más trabajo le había costado congregar allí a los enconados vecinos de la villa, que
tomar un reducto a los carlistas en la acción de Guardamino. No cesaba en toda la noche de
andar, mejor dicho, de arrastrarse de un lado a otro, expidiendo órdenes a los criados, al
conserje, a la orquesta.

--Gervasio, ahora las bandejas de dulces... ¡Coged uno de cada lado, mastuerzos!--¿Qué quiere
usted, señor Anselmo? ¿Piden los muchachos que en vez de vals sea rigodón? Pues toque usted
rigodón.--A ver, pollos, que hay una porción de señoras en el tocador que no tienen pareja
para salir.--¡Marcelino! ¿dónde se ha metido Marcelino? Baja al portal, que un pillo ha tirado
una pedrada al farol, y lo ha roto.--¡Pero, don Manuel, si no son más que las dos! ¿Se quiere
usted llevar ya a las niñas, y aun no hemos roto la piñata?

Aquella noche estaba rejuvenecido el buen señor. Gozaba por todos los jóvenes, como los místicos
gozan en una comunión general. De vez en cuando sus ojos opacos se fijaban por encima de las
gafas, en el globo de madera que colgaba en medio del salón, y lo acariciaba con una sonrisa
de placer. Aquel primoroso artefacto, venido de Burdeos, estaba pintado con rayas azules y
blancas. Por debajo de él pendía una multitud de cintas de varios colores, todas las cuales,
menos una, quedarían en las manos de las señoritas, al tirar por ellas. A la que diera con
la cinta que abría la piñata se le adjudicaba el globo, cargado, sin duda, de confites, y,
según se decía, de chucherías muy lindas.

Gonzalo, en el medio del salón, mostrábase también alegre, departiendo cuándo con una, cuándo
con otra dama. Había bailado con su cuñada un rigodón, y una polka y un vals con dos amigas
de su esposa. Sudaba copiosamente. No cesaba de limpiarse la frente con el pañuelo. Su gran
figura de coloso, descollaba como una torre por encima de todas las cabezas.

--¡Qué animado está el señor alcalde!--le decía una dama del bajo imperio.

--Hay que aprovecharse de la ausencia de Ventura--respondía el joven riendo.--¿Dónde está su
marido, Magdalena?

--Por ahí anda.

--Baile usted conmigo esta polka. Vamos a engañar a nuestros cónyuges respectivos.

--No puedo. La tengo comprometida con Peña.

Mientras así charlaba con todos los que se le acercaban, una mujer rebujada en dominó negro,
con máscara del mismo color, no le perdía de vista un momento, situada ahora en un punto, ahora
en otro; pero siempre a corta distancia de él. Por los agujeros de la careta se veían dos ojos
lucientes y fieros. Era doña Brígida, la ingeniosa compañera del rebajado Marín, que acechaba
el momento oportuno, como el barítono de Un ballo in maschera para dar la puñalada. La víctima
allí, era un príncipe; aquí, nada más que alcalde. Las razones que la eminente señora tenía
para meditar tal crimen, no serán tan poderosas como las del barítono a los ojos de un hombre;
mas de seguro lo parecen a cualquier mujer. El Faro de Sarrió, en su afán de morder a todos
los socios del Camarote, a sus parientes y amigos, la había emprendido desde hacía tres o cuatro
meses, con la esposa de Marín. Salieron a relucir todos los secretos domésticos; la vida del
matrimonio, la dependencia y degradación de Marín fueron puestas en caricatura. Se contaban
a este propósito, en letras de molde, todas las anécdotas más o menos chistosas que corrían
por la villa, y algunas más descubiertas o inventadas por los maleantes redactores. Y como
si esto fuera poco, no había número del citado periódico en que de un modo u otro no se hiciese
mención de la peluca de doña Brígida, que por tal circunstancia había llegado a ser popular
en Sarrió. La irritación, la rabia, el odio y el deseo de venganza que se habían despertado
en esta señora, nadie se los puede figurar. Baste decir que, cuando veía a cualquier redactor
de El Faro en la calle, empalidecía horriblemente; costaba gran trabajo impedir que se le arrojase
al cuello, como un gato rabioso. Hasta entonces no había podido satisfacer aquella ansia de
venganza que la devoraba. Por eso ahora, contemplando a Gonzalo, se relamía de gozo, se estremecía
de anhelo, como el tigre que divisa la presa. Aprovechando un instante en que nadie hablaba
con él, se fué hacia él muy quedo y por detrás. Y poniéndose repentinamente delante, escupió
más que dijo estas palabras:

--Gonzalo, ¿cómo eres tan borrico? Estás siendo la burla y la risa de todo el mundo. No hay
una sola persona en el baile que no sepa que tu mujer está durmiendo a estas horas con el duque
de Tornos.

El joven quedó como si le hubieran dado con un mazo en la frente. Se puso densamente pálido.
Trató de agarrar a la infame máscara para arrancarle la careta; mas no le fué posible. Doña
Brígida se había escabullido como una anguila por entre la gente. Como había muchas señoras
con el mismo disfraz, imposible saber quién era. Entonces se apresuró a salir del salón. Las
palabras aquellas le sonaban dentro de la cabeza como feroces martillazos. Temió caerse. En
la antesala respondió con sonrisa estúpida a las frases amicales que le dirigían. Su tío don
Melchor, viéndole tan pálido, vino hacia él:

--Qué tienes, Gonzalillo: ¿te sientes mal?

--Sí... Voy a tomar una taza de te.

--Te acompaño.

--No, no; vuelvo en seguida.

Y corrió, dejándole plantado cerca de la puerta.

Bajó las escaleras. Se encontró en la calle sin darse cuenta de lo que hacía. El aire frío
de la noche le refrescó la cabeza y le hizo volver en su acuerdo. Súbitamente tomó la resolución
de partir a Tejada. Buscó con la vista el coche y no le vió. Sin duda Ramón estaba en casa
aún. Miró el reloj. No eran más que las dos y media. Dirigióse a paso largo hacia la casa de
su suegro, en la Rúa Nueva, mas cuando hubo dado unos pasos, advirtió que iba sin sombrero
y de frac. Volvióse al Liceo. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01657</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>72356</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>18499</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> At the top crossed a vast hall
where many young people rushed to make way and greet with the familiarity that is used in small
towns. In the ladies room there was already enough, all dressed up, but most of them, like Cecilia,
without a mask. For Sarrio was that a surprise. In the past five years, the dances seemed visits
Liceo of condolence. Half a dozen or so young ladies, shoulders and chest into the air, face
was powdered, conversing quietly in a corner beyond the vast living room, while your moms side
drew some strips of skin from absent friends. Giving as many chickens around in the lobby, the
air sad, dull eyes, buttoning gloves each with the forks of his sisters. Were generally the same.
Every two or chicken dance three polkas, lancers rigodones with the sisters or their friends.
At noon or 0:30 squad went all in, roll up our pants and skirts, respectively, and sheltering
under the umbrella, talking aloud to through the deserted streets and humid. Neighbors, who
did not have prisoners sleep, saying: - "Now out of the Lyceum." This was everything. Don Mateo, firm,
indomitable, tenaciously preserved with loving care, this meager coals the fire of pleasure.

Thanks
to his perseverance, that night became alive and animated fire. Youth the town had the strength
to overwhelm the vile passions that stirred the hearts of their parents, and entered into this lonely
room like a raging torrent, making it resound with laughter and talks
with terrifying screams:

- Alvaro, do you know me?

Do you know me? Why do not you marry? Behold, you are walking to Villavieja.

- Parakeet, would you like? ... What lift the mask? ... What do you need? You do not fall in love
side and do well. Taking from here ... and here!

Huh? Bye bye, Parakeet.

- Hello, Delaunay ... Hello, monsieur. How's the aerial tram? What
things can you think!

What you big head! Too bad you're so unhappy! They say that there are practical man. No But did
you know fix Rato's daughter ... Bye bye ...

- What, Sinforoso? When you get the hand of Cipriana? ... Well make you grieve, man. Why not
spend the threats again to Saloncillo?

There were many ladies with black domino, who were giving these jokes, too alive sometimes.
Most of them were old. A young, they liked to show palm and the slenderness of her waist,
with a historical costume. There were ladies Venetian, Roman, the Lower Empire, Hebrew, at the
time of Louis XV, Board of Philip II, and even Pas of more recent times. There were also some Gypsies,
necromantic and captive. Could be seen Whimsical and romantic clothes, which did not support
classification, one starry night, another Tulip, another passenger pigeon with a little note to
the neck. Men generally had no costume: wearing the coat long and awkward, which only came to
light on such occasions. However, some could be seen with dominoes, which they used to come and
talk to their girlfriends, without danger of being interrupted by moms. A group of young members
of the cabin, coming this way, had the happy idea of ??dressing Don Jaime Marin maragato. When
I had dressed this way, they told him better than a mask, suited being painted, to which he was
paid. The boy took a brush and paint box, and pretending smeared him with a thousand colors, we walked
a long time brush his face, soaked in water only. Marin requested a mirror to see. The young
thugs were careful not provide it. Everything became shouting - but what good are you, Don
Jaime! Tut painted! Neither the mother who bore him can know. Under the faith of the word, good Marín
was carried away to the Lyceum. His friends advised him not to fail to make jokes at certain
ladies, to which he replied, that would be as poultices. And indeed, so I entered the room,
started talking to the girls screaming in a falsetto voice:

- Hello, Rosarito, where have you left Anselmo? We know that every night at ten he throw a little
note from the balcony.

- But, Don Jaime! - Exclaimed the girl looked at him with surprise
.-- how come you so?

- Diablo!

Since I have known - said the good Marín away.

Went immediately to another, and it was the same.

- It's individual
- completed by said .-- All at once I know ... Be by voice, because
what is painted, so I órdago!

When I was making this reflection, a bony hand grabbed him from behind.

-
Great ass, simpleton, blockhead, who has gotten you here this way?

It was his beloved companion, the ingenious and severe Dona Brigida.

- Come on, beast, go, you always serve as a clown everywhere!

And it was getting pushed from the room. The good lady, who came disguised domino mask, then
left him third on the express orders to leave immediately and strict
home, he put it back into the center of the dance, which was a matter
of importance resolve, as we shall see.

Surrounded by a group of masks was the sympathetic Feliciano Gómez. His great pyramid peel and
shiny head, towered above pride.

Were women who were circle around him, arming din unbearable. Jokes that he lavished touched
Injury often.

- Feliciano, a miracle that you have made your sisters come to dance! What time do you have sent
retire? Dona Petra say punishes you when you are late, is it true? Poor Feliciano! How severe are
your sisters! Since you have not been allowed to marry, should give a little of freedom.

Bravo dealer, without being offended, replied with a smile kindly to those harpies. Al Finally,
tired of his patience, he was left in peace.

The adorable Pablito, properly dressed in tails, with a white flower
in his buttonhole, had out while both the Hebrew conquest of some
beautiful daughter of an artillery commander who had just arrived.

The poor thing, seeing surrendered at his feet the young richer and more handsome of the town, let
out through every pore of his handsome face flushed, the intimate joy that was upon him. What
Smiles, gestures so expressive! The girls of the population watched with an expression of mockery.
Those eyes said: - 'Enjoy, enjoy a little unhappy that soon it will be disappointment. "

Pablito, bent, submissive, the ear was pouring hot and clever phrases
such as:

- Yesterday, when Tejada came from, I saw you with your
dad, so nice weekend as usual.

- What a joker!

I also saw him.

You came in open car. Guide you very well.

- You Please Carmencita. Now guide those horses do not have anything special, does anyone. If
you could see when I bought them! Don Agapito's coachman had spoiled entirely, especially the Gallardo,
the left, you know? a little darker than another ... That was one thing missing. If it falls
into other hands, at this hour is not worth two pesetas.

Today is better than the other yet ... Matter of patience, you know - he said with mock modesty.

The
beautiful Hebrew protested

- Come on, do not you do the little that we know that you do very well.

- Patience and a little practice - Pablito repeated bathing in rose water.

Then he said with complete freedom in his opinion what was a good driver. Hand soft and firm at the
same time, the living eye, strong punishment when necessary, but not irritated; They have a
great knowledge of what are the horses. Without the careful study and thoughtful temperament of
these animals, impossible to guide regularly. Carmencita listened spellbound.

A Cecilia had approached him shortly after entering the room, Paco Flores, one engineer who
asked for her hand via Gonzalo. From that she give him pumpkin, which, as we have seen, sought
only a modest woman, industrious and with some money, was in love it and the sun chased. In Sarrió,
seeing the continuing celebration engineer the eldest of Belinchón
it was believed that only wanted to forward to the dowry.

It was a mistake. Flores had really come to love. If you stay poor Cecilia suddenly, it would
make her his wife. The latter behavior was also proper to turn his
dream.

For all his gifts and compliments always responded with kindness
and gratitude.

There was no danger that the young man withdrew from the balcony
when he was passing, and dodging their conversation when I was in
a house known or give him any of those slights that both do enjoy
most of the girls.

He was a good friend, keeping him all the attention to be the person
himself or herself.

But when the engineer wanted to move forward, asked a little love,
a ray of hope, even for tomorrow, was the very negative, smooth, firm
and consistent.

And what was worse, Cecilia, to deny he did not with pleasure, but with disgust, as if you ache
cause annoyance to a friend. This feeling further hurt the pride of the suitor.

After dancing a waltz, and sat down exhausted in a corner of the room.

Flores had caught the fan, and fanned respectfully.

- So I would like to spend my life - said in a tone sincere.

- Oh! Would soon tire - Cecilia replied smiling.

- Will you try?

The young woman replied.

- Not you, Cecilia, of women who suddenly disgusted.

Has you in his heart and his intelligence resources to have on your feet the man who loves
her. More than two years ago I live in love with you, and instead of tired, every time I feel
more connected to you, each time more desperately in love ... to the point of being mocked
by the people.

- That you can not say in advance - said she, a little touched by the fire and excitement Flores
had told his words .-- is not the same seeing a woman briefly, and
talk of Easter to Ramos, his side have it forever.

- What else would
I, Cecilia!

Have her with me always, always! - Replied quietly and shaking the engineer, playing with
the fan and staring at the floor .-- Consecration my life to serve, to worship on their knees
... I know that would make you happy any man but no one much as I
do I know the great qualities of his soul, which I guess also feelings
in his heart that perhaps are wholly unknown to others ... It's terrible!

That you do not make me conceive the slightest hope that one day, distant Anyway, my love come
to soften it, and accept me as a slave even ...

- I agree for friend,
good friend - said the girl gravely.

- Man, oh ... That friendship,
Cecilia, is an ice wall that stands between you and I ... I understand
that I have no merit whatsoever to deserve your love ... there are
one hundred young people in the village that could apply more right
... But the strange thing, which I encouraged and discouraged at the
same time, is that you have not fixed in any so far ... His heart
remains idle, indifferent ... I mean, unless you have a secret love.

Cecilia shuddered slightly and lifted her eyes a little towards the place where you could hear
Gonzalo's voice. Answered after more severely than usual:

- Allow you to study both inside, Flores, first, because the most likely be as vulgar as that of
most women, and second, because if there was any in particular it would not be easy for you to
discover.

- Do not be offended, Cecilia. This study is proof of just how much you me interest.

- Do not offend me - said the young woman .-- I tried to smile and say hello to Rosario. Do
you want take?

In the lobby, separated only by a few columns of the hall, parents chatted serious casting glances
paid to this, where they saw their daughters play. Ever, highlighted a mask dance, and came
to teasing. It was some old contemporary that made them laugh and coughing to bursting with
old stories. Don Rosendo in a corner talking to Don Melchor de las Cuevas. Explicábale a huge
project to port, impressive as all his family. Because can not represent well what science had grown
as large, in Belinchón recent years. It was a more intuitive science gained power of study, as
it happens all great men. At first when I would write in El Faro on a topic did not know, showed himself
wary, hesitant, timid. But as well the subjects learned journalism, and had at its disposal a
lot of idioms, and especially received as an encyclopedic dictionary in fifteen volumes, which
cost no less than two thousand pieces, that really was cut and crack! There was no issue or scientific
problem, social, economic and political environment in which Don Rosendo ceases to get the
scoop with great splendor.

It was the plague that was raging in cattle: Don Rosendo looking in your dictionary the words
cattle, horse, bull, sheep, feed, livestock industry, etc., and so
I read what I said about them, took the pen, and his genius was responsible
journalism draw one or more articles, brimming with philosophy and
scholarship.

He came, as now, the question port, and went to the dictionary looking for words port, dock,
tides, dredging, winds, etc. Seven articles had been written and published at the time, to
demonstrate the need to build a large dock in front of Sarrió, at one point called tundish.
He looked like a sailor consummated, tired of sailing the seas, gray in the study of hydraulic
problems. However, Mr de las Cuevas, but astounded that shuffle mode maritime terms, some
of which even he knew, wry face the verbal explanations Rosendo gave
him.

He concluded by saying, putting his hand on his shoulder

- Undeceive you Belinchón: in the dock for you, the wind brought the Northwest not enter or
sardines.

The most enjoyed at this event, who knew? was an old man, the good
Don Mateo, who was due exclusively.

For him, that meant dancing one of the great triumphs of life. More work had cost him gather there
to the bitter neighbors in the village, which take a stronghold to the Carlist Guardamino action.
She kept on all night walking, rather, to crawl from one side to another, issuing orders to
the servants, the concierge, to the orchestra.

- Gervasio, trays of candy now ... Take one on each side, garden cress! - What do you, Mr.
Anselmo? "They ask the boys instead of waltz quadrille is? As you tap quadrille .-- Let's
see, Chickens, which is a lot of ladies in the toilet without partners
to leave .-- Marcelino!

Who ever put Marcelino? Go down to the portal, which has thrown a crook a stone to the light,
and has broken .-- But Don Manuel, if not more than two! Do you want you carry and girls, and
we have not broken the piñata?

That night the good man was rejuvenated.

Enjoyed by all young people, as the mystics have a general communion. From time to time her
dim eyes were fixed above the glasses, the wooden globe hanging in
the middle of the room, and caressed him with a smile pleasure.

That exquisite artifact, come from Bordeaux, was painted with blue
stripes white.

Below it hung a multitude of ribbons of various colors, all of which,
but one would be in the hands of the girls, pulling for them.

The one given to ribbon opening the piñata being awarded the globe,
loaded, no doubt, candy, and as was said, very nice goodies.

Gonzalo, in the middle of the room, also showed himself happy, when mingling with one, when with
another lady. Had danced a quadrille with his sister, and a polka and a waltz with two friends
of his wife. Sweating profusely. He kept wiping his forehead with his handkerchief. His great
Towering figure, stood out like a tower above every head.

- What is the mayor encouraged! - One lady told Empire.

- We must take advantage of the absence of Ventura - replied the young man, laughing .-- Where
is your husband, Magdalena?

- For there walks.

- You dance with me this polka. We're going to fool our respective spouses.

- I can not. I have it committed to Peña.

As well talking to all who approached him, a woman in black domino rebujos, mask the same color,
not a moment lost sight of, now located at a point now in another, but always within walking distance
from it. Through the holes in the mask were two eyes shining and wild. Dona Brigida was the
witty companion lowered Marin lurking timely, as the baritone of Un ballo in maschera to give
the stabbing.

The victim there was a prince, here, nothing more than the mayor. The reasons that the eminent
lady had to think that crime will not be as powerful as the baritone in the eyes of a man; but
surely I look like any woman.

Sarrió Lighthouse, eager to bite at all Cabin partners, relatives and friends had taken for
three or four months, with the wife of Marin. Surfaced all domestic secrets; life marriage,
dependency and degradation of Marin were put into a caricature. It had this purpose, in print,
all more or less humorous anecdotes running through the town, and some more discovered or invented
by the thugs editors. And To make matters worse, there was number of that newspaper which in
one way or another fails to take Wig mention of Mrs. Bridget, that that fact had become popular
Sarrio.

Irritation, anger, hatred and desire for revenge that had awakened
in this lady, nobody can bear.

Suffice it to say that when he saw any editor El Faro in the street,
paled horribly could scarcely prevent him throw the neck, like a rabid
cat.

Until then had been unable to satisfy that craving devoured her revenge.

So now, looking at Gonzalo, was lapped with joy, shiver of longing,
like a tiger prey currency.

Taking advantage of a moment nobody spoke with him, went to him very
quietly and behind.

And suddenly getting ahead, spit but he said these words:

- Gonzalo, how you're so colt? You're still the fun and laughter around the world. No one person
in the dance does not know that your wife is sleeping at this hour with the Duke Lathe.

The young man was as if he had been with a mallet on the forehead.
Got thick white. He tried to grab the infamous mask to tear the mask,
but it was not possible. Dona Bridget had slipped away like an eel
through the crowd. As there were many ladies in the same outfit, impossible
to know who he was. Then he hurried out of the room. The those words
sounded in his head as fierce hammer. He feared falling. In answered
the threshold stupid smile Amicale phrases addressed to him. His uncle
don Melchor, seeing him so pale, came to him:

- What are you, Gonzalillo:
Do ??you feel bad?

- Yes ... I'll take a cup of tea.

- I'll walk.

-
No, no, come back soon.

And ran, and left him standing near the door.

Down
the stairs. Was found in the street without realizing what he did.
Cold air of the night cooled the head and called him back in their
agreement. Suddenly he resolved leaving for Tejada. Looked around
the car and saw him no. Ramon was undoubtedly home yet. He checked
his watch. There were only two and a half. He went a long way towards
the house his father-in Rua Nueva, but when he had taken a few steps,
he said he was hatless and tails. He returned to the Lyceum</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>