<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document06464</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>79859</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>15352</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Sin cesar elogiaban, engañaban y robaban á este buen príncipe; y cada qual metia la mano como
á porfía en el erario. El principal ministro de hacienda de la isla de Serendib daba este precioso
exemplo, y todos los subalternos le imitaban con fervor. El rey, que lo sabia, habia mudado
varias veces de ministro, pero nunca habia podido mudar el estilo admitido de dividir las rentas
reales en dos partes desiguales; la mas pequeña para su magestad, y la mayor para sus administradores.

Fió el buen rey Nabuzan su cuita del sabio Zadig. Vos que tantas cosas sabeis, le dixo, ¿no
sabríais modo para que tope yo con un tesorero que no me robe? Sí por cierto, respondió Zadig;
un modo infalible sé de buscaros uno que tenga las manos limpias. Contentísimo el rey le preguntó,
dándole un abrazo, como haria. No hay mas, replicó Zadig, que hacer baylar á quantos pretenden
la dignidad de tesorero; y el que con mas ligereza baylare, será infaliblemente el mas hombre
de bien. Os estais burlando, dixo el rey: ¡donoso modo por cierto de elegir un ministro de
hacienda! ¿Con que el que mas listo fuere para dar cabriolas en el ayre ha de ser el mas integro
y mas hábil administrador? No digo yo que haya de ser el mas hábil, replicó Zadig, pero lo
que sí aseguro es que indubitablemente ha de ser el mas honrado. Tanta era la confianza con
que lo decia Zadig, que se persuadió el rey á que poseía algun secreto sobrenatural para conocer
á los administradores. Yo no gusto de cosas sobrenaturales, dixo Zadig, ni he podido nunca
llevar en paciencia ni los hombres que hacen milagros, ni los libros que los mentan: y si quiere
vuestra magestad permitir que haga la prueba, quedará convencido de que mi secreto es tan fácil
como sencillo. Mas se pasmó Nabuzan, rey de Serendib, al oir que era sencillo el secreto, que
si le hubiera dicho que era milagroso. Está bien, le dixo, haced lo que os parezca. Dexadlo
estar, que ganaréis con esta prueba mas de lo que pensais. Aquel mismo dia mandó pregonar en
nombre del rey, que todos quantos aspiraban al empleo de principal ministro de las rentas de
su sacra magestad Nabuzan, hijo de Nuzanab, viniesen con vestidos ligeros de seda á la antecámara
del rey, el primer dia de la luna del crocodílo. Acudiéron en número de sesenta y quatro. Estaban
los músicos en una sala inmediata, y dispuesto todo para un bayle; pero estaba cerrada la puerta
de la sala, y para entrar en ella habia que atravesar una galería bastante obscura. Vino un
uxier á conducir uno tras de otro á cada candidato por este pasadizo, donde le dexaba solo
algunos minutos. El rey que estaba avisado, habia hecho poner todos sus tesoros en la galería.
Quando llegáron los pretendientes á la sala, mandó su magestad que baylaran, y nunca se habian
visto baylarines mas topos ni con ménos desenvoltura; todos andaban la cabeza baxa, las espaldas
corvas, y las manos pegadas al cuerpo. ¡Qué bribones! decia en voz baxa Zadig. Uno solo hacia
con agilidad las mudanzas, levantada la cabeza, sereno el mirar, derecho el cuerpo, y firmes
las rodillas. ¡Qué hombre tan de bien, qué honrado sugeto! dixo Zadig. Dió el rey un abrazo
á este buen baylarin, y le nombró su tesorero: todos los demas fuéron justamente castigados
y multados, porque miéntras que habian estado en la galería, habia llenado cada uno sus bolsillos,
y apénas podia dar paso. Compadecióse el rey de la humana naturaleza, contemplando que de sesenta
y quatro baylarines los sesenta y tres eran ladrones rateros, y se dió á la galería obscura
el título de corredor de la tentacion. En Persia hubieran empalado á los sesenta y tres magnates;
en otros paises, hubieran nombrado un juzgado, que hubiera consumido en costas el triplo del
dinero robado, y no hubiera puesto un maravedí en las arcas reales; en otros, se hubieran justificado
plenamente, y hubiera caido de la gracia el ágil baylirin: en Serendib fuéron condenados á
aumentar el fisco, porque era Nabuzan muy elemente.

No era ménos agradecido, y dió á Zadig una suma mas quantiosa que nunra habia robado tesorero
ninguno al rey su amo. Valióse de este dinero Zadig para enviar á Babilonia expresos que le
informaran de la suerte de Astarte. Al dar esta órden le tembló la voz, se le agolpó la sangre
hácia el corazon, se cubriéron de un tenebroso velo sus ojos, y se paró á punto de muerte.
Partióse el correo, vióle embarcar Zadig, y se volvió á palacio, donde sin ver á nadie, y creyendo
que estaba en su aposento, pronunció el nombre de amor. Si, el amor, dixo el rey; de eso justamente
se trata, y habeis adivinado la causa de mi pena. ¡Qué grande hombre sois! Espero que me enseñeis
á conocer una muger firme, como me habeis hecho hallar un tesorero desinteresado. Volviendo
en sí Zadig le prometió servirle en su amor como habia hecho en real hacienda, aunque parecia
la empresa mas ardua todavía.

CAPITULO XV.

Los ojos azules.

Mi cuerpo y mi corazon, dixo el rey á Zadig... Oyendo estas palabras no pudo ménos el Babilonio
de interrumpir á su magestad, y de decirle: ¡Ouanto celebro que no hayáis dicho mi alma y mi
corazon, porque no oimos mas voces que estas en las conversaciones de Babilonia, ni leemos
libros que no traten del corazon y el alma, escritos por autores que ni uno ni otra tienen;
pero perdonadme, Señor, y proseguid. Nabuzan continuó: Mi cuerpo y mi corazon son propensos
al amor; á la primera de estas dos potencias le sobran satisfacciones, que tengo cien mugeres
á mi disposicion, hermosas todas, complacientes, obsequiosas, y voluptuosas, ó fingiendo que
lo son conmigo. No es empero mi corazon tan afortunado, porque tengo sobrada experiencia de
que el halagado es el rey de Serendib, y que hacen poquisimo aprecio de Nabuzan. No por eso
digo que sean infieles mis mugeres, puesto que quisiera encontrar una que me quisiera por mí
propio, y diera por ella las cien beldades que poseo. Decidme si en mis cien sultanas hay una
que de veras me quiera.

Respondióle Zadig lo mismo que acerca del ministro de hacienda. Señor, dexadlo á mi cargo;
pero permitidme primero que disponga de todas las riquezas que se expusiéron en la galería
de la tentacion, y no dudeis de que os daré buena cuenta de ellas, y no perderéis un ardite.
Dióle el rey amplías facultades, y escogió Zadig treinta y tres jorobados de los mas feos de
Serendib, treinta y tres pages de los mas lindos, y treinta y tres de los mas eloqüentes y
forzudos bonzos. Dexóles á todos facultad de introducirse en los retretes de las sultanas;
dió á cada jorobado quatro mil monedas de oro que regalar, y el primer dia fuéron todos felices.
Los pages que no tenian otra dádiva que hacer que la de su persona, tardáron dos ó tres dias
en conseguir lo que solicitaban; y tuviéron mas dificultad en salir non la suya los bonzos;
pero al cabo se les rindiéron treinta y tres devotas. Presenció el rey todas estas pruebas
por unas celosías que daban en los aposentos de las sultanas, y se quedó atónito, que de sus
cien mugeres las noventa y nueve se rindiéron á su presencia. Quedaba una muy jóven y muy novicia,
á la qual nunca habia tocado su magestad: arrimáronse á ella uno, dos y tres jorobados, ofrecréndole
hasta veinte mil monedas; pero se mantuvo incorruptible, riéndose de la idea de los jorobados
que creían que su dinero los hacia mas bonitos. Presentáronse los dos mas lindos pages, y les
dixo que le parecia el rey mas lindo. Acometióla luego el bonzo mas eloqüente, y despues el
mas intrépido: al primero le trató de parlanchin, y no pudo entender qual fuese el mérito del
segundo. Todo se cifra en el corazon, dixo: yo no he de ceder ni al oro de un jorobado, ni
á la hermosura de un page, ni á las artes de un bonzo; ni he de querer á nadie mas que á Nabuzan;
hijo de Nuzanab, esperando á que él me corresponda. Quedó el rey embargado en júbilo, cariño
y admiracion. Volvió á tomar todo el dinero con que habian comprado los jorobados su buena
ventura, y se le regaló á la hermosa Falida, que así se llamaba esta beldad. Dióle con él su
corazon, que merecia de sobra, porque nunca se vió juventud mas brillante y mas florida que
la suya, nunca hermosura que mas digna de prendar fuese. Verdad es que no calla la historia
que hacia mal una cortesía; pero confiesa que baylaba como las hadas, cantaba como las sirenas,
y hablaba como las Gracias, y estaba colmada de habilidades y virtud.

Adorábala el amado Nabuzan; pero tenia Falida ojos azules, lo qual causó las mas funestas desgracias.
Estaba prohibido por una antigua ley de Serendib, que se enamoraran de una de las mugeres que
llamáron luego los Griegos BOOPES; y hacia mas de cinco mil años que habia promulgado esta
ley el sumo bonzo, por apropiarse para sí la dama del primer rey de la isla de Serendib; de
suerte que el anatema de los ojos azules se habia hecho ley fundamental del estado. Todas las
clases del estado hiciéron enérgicas representaciones á Nabuzan; y públicamente se decia que
era llegada la fatal catástrofe del reyno, que estaba colmada la medida de la abominacion,
que un siniestro suceso amenazaba la naturaleza; en una palabra, que Nabuzan, hijo de Nuzanab,
estaba enamorado de dos ojos azules rasgados. Los jorobados, los bonzos, los asentistas, y
las ojinegras inficionáron de mal- contentos el reyno entero.

El descontento universal animó á los pueblos salvages que viven al norte de Serendib á invadir
los estados del buen Nabuzan. Pidió subsidios á sus vasallos, y los bonzos que eran dueños
de la mìtad de las rentas del estado, se contentáron con levantar las manos al cielo, y se
negáron á llevar su dinero al erario para sacar de ahogo al rey. Cantáron lindas oraciones
en música, y dexáron que los bárbaros asolaran el estado.

Querido Zadig, ¿me sacarás de este horrible apuro? le dixo en lastimoso tono Nabuzan. Con mucho
gusto, respondió Zadig; los bonzos os darán quanto dinero querais. Abandonad las tierras donde
tienen levantados sus palacios, y no defendais mas que las vuestras. Hízolo así Nabuzan; y
quando viniéron los bonzos á echarse á sus plantas, implorando su asistencia, les respondió
el rey con una soberbia música cuya letra eran oraciones al cielo, rogando por la conservacion
de sus tierras. Entónces los bonzos diéron dinero, y se concluyó con felicidad la guerra. De
esta suerte por sus prudentes y dichosos consejos, y por los mas señalados servicios, se habia
acarreado Zadig la irreconciliable enemiga de los mas poderosos del estado: juráron su pérdida
los bonzos y las oji-negras, desacreditáronle jorobados y asentistas, y le hiciéron sospechoso
al buen Nabuzan. Los servicios que el hombre hace se quedan en la antesala, y las sospechas
penetran al gabinete, segun dice Zoroastro. Todos los dias eran acusaciones nuevas; la primera
se repele, la segunda hace mella, la tercera hiere, y la quarta mata.

Asustado Zadig, que habia puesto en auge los asuntos de su amigo, y enviádole su dinero, no
pensó mas que en partirse de la isla, y en ir á saber en persona noticias de Astarte; porque
si permanezco en Serendib, decia, me harán empalar los bonzos. ¿Pero adonde iré? en Egipto
seré esclavo, en Arabia segun las apariencias quemado, y ahorcado en Babilonia. Con todo menester
es saber qué ha sido de Astarte: partámonos, y apuremos lo que me destina mi suerte fatal.

CAPITULO XVI.

El bandolero.

Al llegar á las fronteras que separan la Arabia petrea de la Syria, y al pasar por junto á
un fuerte castillo, saliéron de él unos Arabes armados. Vióse rodeado de hombres que le gritaban:
Ríndete; todo quanto traes es nuestro, y tu persona pertenece á nuestro amo. En respuesta sacó
Zadig la espada; lo mismo hizo su criado que era valiente, y dexáron sin vida á los primeros
Arabes que los habian embestido: dobló el número de enemigos, mas ellos no se desalentáron,
y se resolviéron á morir en la pelea. Víanse dos hombres que se defendian contra una muchedumbre;
tan desigual contienda poco podia durar. Viendo desde una ventana el dueño del castillo, que
se llamaba Arbogad, los portentos de valor que hacia Zadig, le cobró estimacion. Baxó por tanto,
y vino en persona á contener á los sujos, y librar á los dos caminantes. Quanto por mis tierras
pasa es mio, dixo, no ménos que lo que en tierras agenas encuentro; pero me pareceis tan valeroso,
que os exîmo de la comun ley. Hízole entrar en el castillo, mandando á su tropa que le tratase
bien; y aquella noche quiso cenar con Zadig.

Era el amo de este castillo uno de aquellos Arabes que llaman ladrones, el qual entre mil atrocidades
solia hacer alguna accion buena; robaba con una furiosa rapacidad, y daba con prodigalidad:
intrépido en una accion, de buen genio en el trato de la vida, bebedor en la mesa, de buen
humor quando habia bebido, y sobretodo sin solapa ninguna. Gustóle mucho Zadig, y con la conversacion
que se animó duró mucho el banquete. Díxole en fin Arbogad: Aconsejoos que tomeis partido conmigo,
no podeis hacer cosa mejor; no es tan malo el oficio, y un dia podeis llegar á ser lo que yo
soy. ¿Se puede saber, respondió Zádig, desde quando exercitais tan hidalga profesion? Desde
niño, replicó el señor. Era criado de un Arabe muy hábil, y no podia acostumbrarme á mi estado,
desesperado de ver que perteneciendo igualmente la tierra á todos, no me hubiera cabido á mí
la porcion correspondiente. Fiéle mi pena á un Arabe viejo, el qual me dixo: Hijo mio, no te
desesperes; sábete que en tiempos antiguos habia un grano de arena que se dolia de ser un átomo
desconocido en un desierto; andando años, se convirtió en diamante, y es hoy el mas precioso
joyel de la corona del rey de las Indias. Dióme tanto golpe esta respuesta, que siendo grano
de arena me determiné á volverme diamante. Robé primero dos caballos, me junté con otros compañeros,
púseme en breve en estado de robar caravanas poco crecidas; y así fué disminuyéndose la desproporcion
que de mi á los demás habia. Participé de los bienes de este mundo, v me resarcí con usura:
tuviéronme en mucho, llegué á ser señor bandolero, y gané este castillo tomándole por fuerza.
Quiso quitármele el sátrapa de Syria, pero era ya tan rico que nada tenia que temer: dí dinero
al sátrapa, y conservé así el castillo, y agrandé mis tierras, añadiendo á ellas el cargo que
me confirió el sátrapa de tesorero de los tributos que pagaba la Arabia petrea al rey de reyes.
Yo hice las cobranzas, y me exîmé de hacer pagos.

Envió aquí el gran Desterham de Babilonia, en nombre del rey Moabdar, á un satrapilla para
mandarme ahorcar. Quando él llegó con la órden, estaba yo informado de todo; hice ahorcar en
su presencia las quatro personas que traía consigo para apretarme el lazo al cuello, y le pregunté
luego quanto le podia valer la comision de ahorcarme. Respondióme que podria su gratificacion
subir á trecientas monedas de oro, y yo le hice ver con evidencia que ganaria mas conmigo:
le creé bandolero inferior, y hoy es uno de los mejores y mas ricos oficiales que tengo; y
si me quereis creer, haréis vos lo mismo. Nunca ha corrido tiempo mejor para robar, desde que
ha sido muerto Moabdar, y que anda en Babilonia todo alborotado. ¡Moabdar ha sido muerto! dixo
Zadig: ¿y que se ha hecho la reyna Astarte? Yo no lo sé, replicó Arbogad; lo que sí sé, es
que Moabdar se volvió loco, que fué muerto, que Babilonia esta hecha una cueva de ladrones,
todo el imperio en la desolacion, que se pueden dar buenos golpes, y que yo por mi parte he
dado algunos ballantes. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09191</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>321338</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14387</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Incessantly praised, cheated and stole to the good prince, and each put his hand like qual to
contention in the treasury. The chief minister of finances of the island of Serendib was this beautiful
exemplo, and all the underlings imitate him with fervor. The king, who knew, had moved several
times minister, but had never been able to move the accepted style of dividing the income real into
two unequal parts, the smaller one for his majesty, and more for their managers.

Good King relied Nabuzan his need of the wise Zadig. So many things you know, told him, do not
would know how to stop me with a treasurer who does not steal from me? " Yes indeed, "replied Zadig;
a sure way to pick you know one that has clean hands. Delighted the king asked him, giving him
a hug, as would. No more, "replied Zadig, which aim to Bayle to quanta the dignity of treasurer,
and that baylare lighter, more men will infallibly well. YOU ARE laughing at you, 'said the
king, so by diverting some of choosing a minister hacienda! With more than ready to give whatever
antics in the air has to be the most integrated and more able administrator? I'm not saying
it is to be the most able, "replied Zadig, but I do assure you is that undoubtedly has to be
the most honest. Such was the confidence with Zadig was saying it, that persuaded the king to possess
some secret knowledge supernatural administrators. I do not like things supernatural, he said
Zadig, and I have never bear with patience and men who do miracles, or the books that the mint,
and if you want your majesty allow me to do the test, will be convinced that my secret is so easy
as a single. More Nabuzan was astounded king of Serendib, to hear that the secret was simple,
that if I had said it was miraculous. Okay, I said to you, do as you please. Dexadlo be that
this test will earn more than what you think. That same day he sent a proclamation through name
of the king, who all aspired to employment quantos chief minister of the income Nabuzan his
sacred majesty, Nuzanab son, should come to light silk dresses to the antechamber King, the first
day of the moon's crocodile. Came to the number of sixty-four. Were musicians in a room immediately,
and arranged for a bayle, but the door was closed of the room, and she had to enter through a gallery
quite dark. Came a uxier to drive one after another to every candidate in this passage, where
you only dexaba few minutes. The king was advised, had actually put all their treasures in
the gallery. Quando suitors came to the hall, His Majesty commanded that Bayle, and never had
baylarines seen more moles or with less ease; all went head descends, the backs knees, and hands
attached to the body. What scoundrels! Zadig said in voice descends. To one swiftly moves, head
up, looking serene, the right body, and firm knees. What man so well, what sugeto honest! 'said
Zadig. He gave the king a hug baylarin to this good, and made him his treasurer, all others
were justly punished and fined, because while it had been in the gallery, each one had filled
his pockets, and could hardly take a step. Pitied the king of human nature, contemplating that
sixty baylarines four and sixty-three thieves were thieves, and given to the dark gallery running
title of temptation. Persia had been impaled in the sixty-three magnates; in other countries, had
appointed a court, which had consumed three times the costs stolen money, and had not put a
penny in the royal coffers, in others, would have justified fully, and would have fallen from grace
the lithe baylirin: in Serendib were condemned to increase the treasury, because it was very
Nabuzan item.

Was no less grateful, and gave a sum more quantiosa Zadig that nunra
treasurer had stolen neither the king his master.

Zadig value of this money to send him to Babylon Express report on the fate of Astarte. In giving
this order, her voice trembled, he rushed the blood towards the heart, is covered with a dark
veil their eyes, and stood on the point of death. Departed the post, board violates Zadig, and
returned to the palace, where without seeing anyone, and believing I was in his room, gave
the name of love. Yes, the love, the king said, that just question, and you have guessed the cause
of my pain. What a great man you are! I hope to teach me to know a strong woman, as I have done to
find a disinterested treasurer. Returning Zadig itself promised to serve in his love as he had done
in real estate, but seemed the most difficult undertaking yet.

CHAPTER XV.

Blue eyes.

My body and heart, the king said to Zadig ... Hearing these words could not help the Babylonian
to terminate his Majesty, and say, welcome Ouanto you have not told my soul and heart, because
we do not hear more voices that are in talks of Babylon, or read books do not address the heart
and soul, written by authors who have neither of them; but forgive me, Lord, so continue. Nabuzan
continued: My body and my heart are prone to love at the first of these two powers has plenty
of satisfaction, that I have a hundred wives at my disposal, all beautiful, obliging, obsequious,
and voluptuous, or pretending are with me. However my heart is not so lucky, because I have
had the most experience that flattered the King of Serendib, and they do very little appreciation
of Nabuzan. Why not I say that my wives are unfaithful because I want to find a like for me
own, and she turned a hundred beauties possess. Tell me if my hundred sultanas is a who really
loves me.

Zadig answered the same thing about the minister of finance. Lord dexadlo to my office; but
first let me have all the riches that were exhibited at the gallery of temptation, and do not
hesitate to give you a good account of them, and not lose a jot. The king gave him broad powers,
and chose Zadig humpback thirty-three the most ugly Serendib, thirty-three pages of the most
beautiful, and thirty-three of the most eloquent and strongmen monks. Dexóles power to all
toilets introduced in the sultanas; Hunchback gave to each four thousand gold coins to give away,
and the first day were all happy. The pages that had no other gift that you make your person,
take two or three days in getting what they requested, and had more difficulty in leaving his
non bonzes; but after they surrendered thirty-three devotees. Witnessed the king of all these
tests by giving a lattice in the chambers of the sultanas, and was stunned that their one hundred
ninety-nine wives surrendered to his presence. There was one very young and very novice to the qual
had never touched his majesty: arrimáronse to it one, two and three humps, ofrecréndole twenty thousand
pieces, but remained incorruptible, laughing at the idea of ??the humpback they thought their
money made them more beautiful. Presented themselves the two most beautiful pages, and they he
said that the king seemed nicer. Bonzo Acometióla then the most eloquent, and then the more
adventurous: at first I tried to talkative, and could not understand was the merit of qual second.
Everything is put at the heart, said: "I shall not transfer or the gold of a hunchback, or
to the beauty of a page, or to the arts of a Buddhist monk, and I wish to anyone but Nabuzan; Nuzanab
son, waiting for him to me appropriate. King was arrested in joy, love and admiration. He returned
to take all the money that had bought the humpback good chance, and gave to the beautiful
Falida, which was the name this beauty. With him gave him his heart, he deserved to spare, because
it never looked brighter and more youth flowery yours, never beauty that was more worthy of
pledge. It is true that history is not silent than to misspell a courtesy, but confesses that
Baylan as fairies, sing like sirens, and talked like the Graces, and was full of skill and virtue.

Adorábala
Nabuzan beloved but Falida had blue eyes, caused the most dire qual
misfortunes.

It was forbidden by an ancient law of Serendib, who fell in love with one of the women who Greeks later
called BOOP, and to more than five thousand years had passed this bonzo the supreme law, by appropriating
to himself the lady of the first king of the island of Serendib, for so that the curse of
the blue eyes had made fundamental law of the state. All classes of states made strong representations
to Nabuzan, and publicly stated that arrival was the fatal catastrophe of the kingdom, which
was filled to the extent of the abomination, threatening event that an accident of nature, in
short, that Nabuzan, son of Nuzanab, was in love with two blue eyes tear. The humpback, the
monks, the contractors, and the black-eyed bad-happy tainted the entire kingdom.

Universal discontent encouraged to savage peoples living north of
Serendib to invade Nabuzan good states.

Subsidies requested his subjects, and the monks who owned half of state revenues, were content
to raise his hands to heaven, and refused to take their money out of breath treasury to the
king. Beautiful singing prayers in music, and dexáron the barbarians ravaged the state.

Dear Zadig, "Take me out of this horrible predicament? said to him
in piteous tone Nabuzan.

With much taste, "replied Zadig, the monks will give you money quanto distributions. Leave the
land where have raised their palaces and defendais no more than yours. Nabuzan did so, and Quando
monks came to lie at his feet, imploring his assistance, he answered them King with a superb
music whose lyrics were prayers to heaven, praying for conservation of their land. Then the
monks gave money, and happily concluded the war. Of Thus blessed by his prudent advice, and the
most important services, had Zadig brought the irreconcilable enemy of the most powerful state,
sworn in loss The monks and Oji-black desacreditáronle humpback and settlements, and we did suspect
the good Nabuzan. The services that the man does remain in the anteroom, and suspicion enter the
cabinet, according to Zoroaster. Every day new charges were, the first is repelled, the second
makes a dent, the third wound, and the fourth killed.

Scared Zadig, who had put the issues on the rise of his friend, and
sent her money, no thought more than part of the island and go in
person to know news of Astarte, because if I stay in Serendib, he
said, I will impale the monks.

"But where shall I go? Egypt I'll be a slave, according to Saudi appearances burned and hanged
in Babylon. With all necessary is to know what became of Astarte: Partamona, and troubles that
I intended my luck fatal.

CHAPTER XVI.

The bandit.

On arriving at the borders between Saudi petrea of ??Syria, and to pass along to a strong castle,
left him a few armed Arabs. Saw himself surrounded by men who shouted: Give it up, all quanto
bring ours, and your person belong to our master. In response took Zadig the sword, so did the
young man who was brave, and to the lifeless dexáron first Arab that had rammed: doubled the
number of enemies, but they are not discouraged, and resolved to die in the fight. Víanse two men
defended themselves against a multitude; little contest so unequal could last. Looking from
a window the owner of the castle, Arboga named, the wonders of value to Zadig, charged him esteem.
Baxo therefore and came in person to restrain the sujos, and freed the two walkers. Quanto for
my land problem is mine, he said, not less than that encounter strange land, but you seem to me as
courageous, that I was exempt from the common law. Made him into the castle, ordering his troops
to treat him well, and wanted dinner that night with Zadig.

Was the master of this castle one of those Arabs who called thieves, the qual-thousand atrocities
used to do some good action, robbed with a furious rapacity, and gave lavishly: fearless in action, in
a good mood in the treatment of life, drinking at the table, good Quando had drunk humor, and above
all without any overlaps. Gustóle much Zadig, and the conversation which encouraged the banquet
last long. Arboga finally said to him: Aconsejoos you to take the game with me, you can not
do better, not so bad the office, and one day you can become what I am. Can you tell, "replied
Zadig, since Quando exercitais so noble profession? From child, "replied the master. It was
an Arab servant very clever, and could not get used to my state, desperate to see that land
belonging equally to all, I would not fit to me the relevant portion. My faithful old sentence
to an Arab, the qual said to me: "Son, do not despair, know ye that in ancient times had a grain
of sand that ached to be an atom stranger in a desert walk, he became a diamond, and is today
the most precious jewel in the crown of King of the Indies. Given me so much blow that answer, that
being grain Sandy Diamond I venture again. I won the first two horses, I joined with colleagues, I went
down shortly in the state of stealing caravans little flooding, and so was to reduce the disproportion
that I had to others. I participated in the goods of this world, v indemnified me with interest:
tuviéronme much, I became Mr. bandit stole this castle took him by force. He wanted her off the
satrap of Syria, but was already so wealthy that had nothing to fear: I gave money the satrap,
and preserve the castle, and enlarge my land, adding to them the charge I gave the satrap of treasurer
of the taxes paid by the Saudi petrea the King of Kings.

I made collections, and was relieved of payments.

Desterham sent here the great Babylon, on behalf of King Moabdar, to a satrapilla for hung. Quando
he arrived with the order, I was informed of everything, I hang on His presence the four persons
who brought them to tighten the noose around his neck, and asked quanto then you could invoke
the commission to hang myself. He replied that could gratification up to three hundred gold
coins, and I made do with evidence that would win me over: bottom bandit created him, and today
is one of the best and richest official that I have, and if you want me to believe, you will do
the same. Has never run better time to steal, since Moabdar has been killed, and who walks
in Babylon repite. Moabdar was dead! he said Zadig: What has been done the Queen Astarte? I
do not know, "replied Arboga, I do know, is Moabdar that went crazy, which was dead, that Babylon
is made a den of thieves throughout the empire in desolation, which
can give good shots, and I for my part I taken some Ballant</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>