<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10507</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>145630</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23334</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> «¿Qué has hecho, desgraciado, para que así
te castiguen los dioses?» «He enseñado a los mortales a que no piensen en la muerte» contesta
Prometeo. «¿Y cómo lo conseguiste?» «Les he hecho conocer la ciega esperanza».

Y durante miles y miles de años reinaba sobre el mundo la divinidad benéfica y consoladora
que el héroe sombrío había dado a los humanos, pagando esta generosidad con el tormento de
sus entrañas rasgadas por el águila, «perro alado de Zeus». Ella conducía los rebaños de hombres
en armas; ella había aleteado ante las proas de los descubridores; ella conmovía con su paso
quedo el silencio cerrado donde meditan sabios y artistas; ella guiaba las muchedumbres ansiosas
de bienestar y amplio emplazamiento que se descuajan de un hemisferio para ir a replantarse
en el otro.

Fernando la vio; la vio venir, con sus ojos entornados, por encima del azul del mar, como una
burbuja de oro desprendida del sol, como un harapo de luz que acabó por detenerse sobre el
filo de la proa, lo mismo que las imágenes divinas que adornaban las naves de los primeros
argonautas.

Sus alas se tendían majestuosas en el éter como velas cóncavas; su túnica arremolinábase atrás,
en pliegues armoniosos, impelida por el viento. Era igual a la Victoria de Samotracia, y lo
mismo que a ella, le faltaba la cabeza.

Por esto acabó de conocerla Ojeda. Ella no piensa, ella no tiene ojos...

Era la esperanza, la ciega esperanza que con el avance de su torso señalaba al Sur.

III

Después del almuerzo, los pasajeros del Goethe oyeron sonar a proa la banda de música, con
la lejanía soñolienta que infunde la inmensidad del Océano a todas las vibraciones.

--Van a vacunar a los de tercera--dijo Maltrana, siempre enterado de lo que ocurría en el buque.

Estaban aún frente a la isla, costeando sus rugosas montañas, pétreo oleaje de antiguas erupciones
llegadas hasta el mar. Bajaban por las laderas, como ovejas en tropel, blancas viviendas, medio
ocultas algunas de ellas en los repliegues sombreados de verde. Por encima de las cumbres iba
pasando la caperuza nevada del Teide como una cabeza curiosa, ocultándose o apareciendo, según
el buque marchaba cerca o lejos de la costa.

Maltrana no podía mantenerse tranquilo en el jardín de invierno mientras tomaba el café con
Fernando. Ocurría a bordo algo extraordinario sin que él lo presenciase.

--¿Le parece que vayamos a ver la gente de tercera?... Debe ser interesante.

Descendieron las escaleras de dos pisos, y saliendo del castillo central viéronse en la explanada
de proa, al pie del palo trinquete. Bajo el gran toldo que sombreaba este espacio aglomerábase
el hedor sudoroso de una muchedumbre. El médico del buque y varios ayudantes, todos con blusas
blancas, ocupaban el centro junto a una mesa cargada de botiquines. Y al son de la música pasaban
los emigrantes en interminable fila, todos con un brazo descubierto que presentaba a la lancera
del vacunador. El primer oficial, secundado por los ayudantes de la comisaría, organizaba el
desfile, cuidando de que todos, después de arremangarse el brazo, presentasen con la otra mano
el papel de su pasaje.

El acto de la vacunación era a la vez un recuento. Al partir de Tenerife, última escala del
viejo mundo, empezaba el gran viaje; nadie había de entrar en el buque hasta América, y la
comisaría necesitaba conocer el número de las gentes que iban a bordo. Los marineros recorrían
los sollados, los obscuros pasadizos, las bodegas, hasta los más apartados rincones, en busca
de viajeros ocultos empujando a los fugitivos que pretendían evitarse esta operación.

Los oficiales alemanes llamaban a cada momento para dar sus órdenes a un empleado de la comisaría,
hombre grueso y de bigotes canos que se expresaba en distintos idiomas, pasando de uno a otro
con asombrosa facilidad. Maltrana y él se saludaron afectuosamente.

--Ése es don Carmelo--dijo Ojeda--, un compatriota nuestro. Habla todas las lenguas de Europa;
además el árabe, y creo que un poco de japonés. Y con toda su sabiduría aquí le tiene usted
ganando unos cuantos marcos, sin otra satisfacción que ostentar una gorra de uniforme y que
los emigrantes le llamen oficial. Le busco todos los días en su despacho, que está abajo, siempre
con la luz encendida, y charlamos de lo que ocurre en el buque. ¡Qué hombre! Ahí donde le ve,
hizo sus estudios en Málaga, él solito, yendo por el puerto de barco en barco y diciendo a
todo marino que encontraba aburrido: «Vamos a echar un párrafo en su idioma, compañero».

Mientras hablaba Isidro de la mujer y los hijos de su amigo, andaluces trasplantados a Hamburgo,
y de las escaseces pecuniarias de éste, que le obligaban a buscar entre los pasajeros ricos
uno que quisiera entretener los ocios de la travesía estudiando idiomas, don Carmelo gritó
con el acento de su tierra:

--¡Too Dios con er papé en la mano!, ¡que se vea bien!

Y repetía la orden en italiano, en francés, en portugués y en árabe.

Habían desfilado los hombres, y eran ahora las mujeres, con una escolta de chiquillos, las
que se iban presentando a recibir la vacunación. Pasaban ante el médico brazos membrudos con
la blancura y la firmeza de la carne septentrional; brazos grasosos en los que se hundían los
dedos de los operadores; brazos de redondez ambarina, semejantes a los de las mujeres de Tiziano,
pero que ostentaban en su parte alta un obscuro triángulo de roñosa suciedad.

Luchaban al destaparse las mujeres con las mangas de la camisola o de la gruesa elástica, y
en este forcejeo se les abría el pecho, mostrando escapularios y medallas sobre las flacideces
de la maternidad. Las hembras árabes, morenas y huesosas, iban casi desnudas bajo sus barones
rayados; las gruesas napolitanas, de cabello revuelto y ojos de brasa, devolvían al corpiño
con tranquilo impudor las saltonas exuberancias surgidas al desabrocharse; las castellanas
angulosas de pelo aceitoso y retinto, peinadas como vírgenes prerrafaelistas, cubrían prontamente
su brazo con triples forros y se alejaban ruborizadas, moviendo la corta y bailarinesca balumba
de sus zagalejos trasudados. Unos chiquillos berreaban agarrándose a sus madres, trémulos de
pavor al ver las blusas blancas de los operadores; otros, con el sombrero en el cogote y mostrando
la sonrisa marfileña de sus dientes de lobo, se disputaban por quién avanzaría primero el brazo,
como si aquello fuese una fiesta.

Maltrana explicaba a su amigo el orden en que iban divididos los emigrantes. La proa era para
«los latinos»: españoles, italianos, portugueses, franceses, árabes, judíos del Mediodía y
hasta egipcios. Nadie podía adivinar el latinismo de estas últimas gentes; pero así los había
encasillado la comisaría. En la parte de popa se aglomeraban otras naciones: alemanes, rusos
y judíos, muchos judíos de diversas procedencias, polacos, galitzianos, rutenos, moscovitas
y balcánicos, cocinando aparte, según las preocupaciones y ritos de su religión. Los israelitas
llevaban carne sacrificada por los rabinos de Hamburgo. La bulliciosa latinidad gozaba el privilegio
sobre las otras castas de beber vino en las comidas dos veces por semana y tomar chocolate
al amanecer otras dos veces, en vez del café habitual.

Las lamentaciones de don Carmelo, que juraba para él solo con grandes aspavientos, interrumpieron
a Maltrana.

--¡Mardita sea mi arma! Ya me extrañaba yo que hisiésemos er viaje sin sorpresas. ¡Pero camará,
que no haya medio de librarse de esa gente!...

Cambió algunas palabras en alemán con el primer oficial y luego gritó a unos camareros españoles
que estaban al servicio de «los latinos»:

--A ve esos güenos mozos; ¡tráiganlos pa acá!

Avanzaron seis jóvenes, con la cabeza descubierta, las ropas haraposas y los pies metidos en
zapatos rotos o alpargatas deshilachadas.

--¿De moo que no tenéis pasaje y os habéis metió aquí de polisones sin má ni má, como si esto
juese la casa e toos? ¿Y creéis que esto va a quear ansí?... Tú, ¿de ónde eres?

Y los seis polisones fueron contestando al interrogatorio de don Carmelo. Uno era de Tenerife
y los restantes procedían de Andalucía y Galicia. Se habían introducido ocultamente en varios
buques, que los echaron en tierra al llegar a Canarias. ¡Y a buscar de nuevo un escondrijo
en la bodega de otro barco!... Así pensaban llegar, fuese como fuese, adonde se habían propuesto.
Los seis querían ir a Buenos Aires; y como bestias humildes, resignadas de antemano a los golpes
que creían merecer, bajaban la cabeza contentos con su desgracia si lograban alcanzar el término
del viaje.

Don Carmelo habló en voz baja con el primer oficial.

--Está bien--dijo solemnemente--. Pero como aquí nadie viene sin pasaje y el buque no pué retroceer
por vosotros, vais a golveros nadando a Tenerife. La isla está allí cerquita.

Y señalaba la costa que se veía en lontananza, entre la borda del buque y el filo del toldo.
El oficial se acariciaba impasible la barba rubia mientras el intérprete traducía sus órdenes.
Las mujeres abrían los ojos con asombro y terror.

--Que pongan una escaleriya pa que sartén con más fasiliá--ordenó don Carmelo.

Los camareros le obedecieron, colocando una pequeña escalera contra la borda, mientras el intérprete
repetía la orden. «¡Al agua, muchachos! E un remojonsito na más.»

Los polisones de más edad seguían con la cabeza baja, entre incrédulos y aterrados, dudando
de que esta orden pudiese ser cierta pero dudando igualmente de que todo fuese una burla, habituados
a durezas y castigos en los buques que les habían servido de refugio. Uno que era casi un niño
se atrevió a mirar por encima de la borda, apreciando con ojos de espanto la distancia enorme
que se extendía entre el buque y la costa.

--¡Yo no quiero!... ¡No quiero morir!... ¡Yo quiero ir a Buenos Aires! ¡Madre!... ¡Mamita!...

Y se echó al suelo gimiendo, agitando las piernas para repeler a los que se acercasen. Comenzaron
a partir suspiros y exclamaciones de los grupos de mujeres. Don Carmelo miró al primer oficial
que seguía acariciándose la barba.

--Güeno, niños; será pá más tarde. A la noche os iréis nadando. Mientras tanto, que os vacunen,
y luego comeréis... A ver unos pantalones viejos pa estos güenos mozos; no es caso de que vayan
enseñando las vergüensas al pasaje... Pero queda convenido ¿eh, niños? a la noche os marcharéis
nadando.

Súbitamente tranquilizados, los polisones se dejaron llevar por los marineros, que los empujaban
rudamente, acogiendo este trato con humildad y agradecimiento.

--Hay que ser enérgico--dijo don Carmelo a los dos amigos poniendo un gesto feroz--. Si no
fuese así, too er buque se llenaria de gente sin pasaje. Cuatro van a ir a las máquinas; siempre
hasen farta fogoneros; y los dos más pequeños ayudarán a la limpiesa de las cubiertas. Podíamos
desembarcarlos en Río Janeiro. Pero er comandante es güeno, y de seguro que los yevaremos hasta
Buenos Aires. Los tunantes van a salirse con la suya.

La música continuaba sonando y se reanudó el desfile de los brazos arremangados ante el grupo
de blusas blancas.

Ojeda estaba impresionado por la escena anterior. Creía oír aún los gemidos del mozuelo pataleando
en la cubierta: «¡Yo no quiero morir! ¡Yo quiero ir a Buenos Aires!...». El vagabundo de los
puertos tenía la misma ilusión que él y casi todos los que habitaban las cubiertas superiores.
Dormitando entre los fardos y barricas de un muelle, había visto también a la diosa alada y
sin cabeza; había sentido la caricia de la esperanza. Y allá marchaban todos, afrontando la
nostalgia del recuerdo o las necesidades del presente; revueltos, confundidos, igualados por
la ilusión común... ¡Buenos Aires! ¡Qué magia poderosa la de este nombre, que hacía correr
a los miserables, como ratones hambrientos, para ocultarse en las entrañas de los buques!...

Se impacientó Maltrana ante la monotonía del desfile.

--Después de éstos vacunarán a los de popa: gente menos limpia y presentable que «los latinos»,
con largas melenas y gabanes de piel de carnero. Arriba estaremos mejor.

Y subieron a lo más alto del buque, a la cubierta de los botes, buscando la sombra de un toldo
y dos sillones libres para descansar en la soledad azul impregnada de luz. La mayoría del pasaje
prefería quedarse abajo, refugiada en la suave penumbra de la cubierta de paseo.

Maltrana saludó a una señora que leía tendida en un largo sillón, la espalda sobre un cojín,
mostrando entre la flor nívea y rizada de su faldamenta el arranque de unas piernas enfundadas
en seda blanca y los altos tacones de los zapatos. Fernando, advertido por el codo del compañero,
se fijó en sus cabellos, de un rubio obscuro, recogidos en forma de casco; en sus ojos claros
y temblones como gotas de agua marina, que se elevaron unos instantes del libro para mirarle
con tranquila fijeza; en el color blanco de su cuello, una blancura de miga de pan ligeramente
dorada por el sol y la brisa del mar.

--Es la yanqui, la señora que come cerca de nuestra mesa--murmuró Isidro--. Habla con poca
gente; apenas se saluda con algunas viejas de a bordo; rehúye el trato de los demás... Yo soy
el único hombre con quien cambia el saludo, pero cuando intento hablarla finge que no me entiende...
Y sin embargo, adivino en ella un carácter alegre y varonil: debe ser un agradable compañero;
no hay más que ver con qué gracia sonríe. ¡Qué hoyuelos tan cucos se le forman junto a la boca!,
¡cómo se le aterciopelan los ojos!... Pero no hay confianza todavía entre las gentes de a bordo;
parece que estamos todos de visita.

Sentáronse a alguna distancia de la norteamericana y ésta volvió a bajar los ojos sobre el
libro, ladeándose en su sillón para ignorar la presencia de los recién llegados.

Tenían ante ellos el azul del Océano, liso, denso, sin una arruga y en el fondo, por la parte
de popa, un triángulo de sombra que empañaba el horizonte, una especie de nube gris y piramidal,
que era la isla... Calma absoluta... Sentados en mitad de la cubierta, no alcanzaban a ver
las espumas que la velocidad de la marcha arremolinaba contra los flancos del buque. Desde
esta altura sus ojos abarcaban únicamente el segundo término, o sea el mar inmóvil, que parecía
cubierto de una costra diáfana y transparente, una costra de vidrio reflejando el azul denso
y pastoso de la profundidad. A no ser por las vedijas negras que se escapaban de la chimenea,
para quedar flotando en la calma bochornosa de la tarde, se hubiese podido creer que el buque
no marchaba... Y la isla siempre a la vista, como los países encantados de las leyendas, que
parecen avanzar detrás de los pasos del que huye.

Un silencio de sesteo extendía su paz abrumadora sobre la cubierta inundada de luz. Bajo los
toldos se percibían leves ronquidos, acompasadas respiraciones, dorsos vueltos al exterior
sobre las sillas largas, cabezas incrustadas en almohadas o descansando sobre el respaldo,
con los ojos entornados y la boca abierta a la frescura de la sombra. Crujía el piso en los
lugares caldeados, bajo el paso tardo de algún transeúnte. Subían los ecos de la música, lejanos,
adormecidos, como si surgiesen de las profundidades del mar. Venían del otro lado de la chimenea
gritos de niños y choques de maderas, revelando los diversos incidentes de un juego deportivo.
El sol de la tarde incendiaba todo el Poniente con su lluvia cegadora.

--¿Por qué llamarían a esto el «Mar Tenebroso»?--dijo Maltrana, que no podía permanecer callado
largo tiempo.

Estas palabras despertaron en los dos el recuerdo de antiguas lecturas. Ojeda pensó en su drama
poético de los conquistadores cuya preparación le había obligado a estudiar la epopeya de los
navegantes que descubrieron las tierras vírgenes. Isidro se acordó de los trabajos realizados
en su época de mercenario de la literatura, cuando andaba a caza de notas en bibliotecas y
archivos para la confección de un libro que firmaría luego cierto personaje ansioso de entrar
en una Academia.

--Siempre es tenebroso lo que ignoramos--contestó Ojeda--. Una nube en el horizonte o varios
días sin sol bastaron para llamar Tenebroso un mar en el que se avanzaba con indecisión, temiendo
las sorpresas del misterio y el perder de vista las costas. Yo confieso que la geografía del
Mar Tenebroso antes de que la brújula hiciera posibles las largas exploraciones, es una geografía
que me encanta y rejuvenece: algo así como esos cuentos de hadas que nos deleitan como un perfume
de flores marchitas al evocar las primeras impresiones de la niñez.

Y los dos enumeraron en su animada conversación todos los intentos de los hombres, desde remotos
siglos, por romper el misterio del Mar Tenebroso.

Los nautas cartagineses bajaban hacia el Sur por las costas de África, trayendo, después de
un periplo de varios años, colmillos de elefantes que suspendían de los templos, adornos vistosos,
pellejos de hombres peludos y con rabo que debieron ser envolturas de grandes orangutanes.
Y tal valor concedía el Senado a tales descubrimientos, que guardaba como un secreto de Estado
la ruta de los navegantes, viendo en las tierras lejanas un seguro refugio para su pueblo si
una guerra infortunada hacía necesaria la expatriación.

En este mar de tinieblas, más allá de las columnas de Hércules, habían colocado Homero y Hesiodo
el Eliseo, morada de los bienaventurados, las Gorgonas, tierra de eterna primavera, y las Hespérides,
con sus manzanas de oro, guardadas por un dragón de fuego. Luego eran los navegantes árabes
los que se lanzaban en el mar de las tinieblas, y sus geógrafos poblaban el misterio de las
soledades marinas con poéticas invenciones, aderezando los descubrimientos lo mismo que un
cuento de Las mil y una noches. El emir Edrisi hablaba de las islas de Uac-uac, último término
del mundo en el siglo XII por la parte de Oriente: islas tan abundantes en riquezas, que los
monos y los perros llevaban collares de oro. Un árbol, del que había grandes bosques, daba
su nombre a las islas; el uac-uac, llamado así porque gritaba o ladraba con iguales sonidos
a todo el que ponía por vez primera el pie en el archipiélago. Y este árbol tenía en la extremidad
de sus ramas, primero, abundantes flores, y luego en vez de frutas, hermosas muchachas, beldades
vírgenes, que podían ser objeto de exportación para los harenes.

Por el Occidente habían avanzado los hermanos Almagrurinos, ocho moros vecinos de Lisboa, que
mucho antes de 1147--año en que los musulmanes fueron expulsados de la ciudad--juntaron las
provisiones necesarias para un largo viaje, «no queriendo volver sin penetrar hasta el extremo
del Mar Tenebroso». Así descubrían la isla de «los carneros amargos» y la isla de «los hombres
rojos», pero se vieron obligados a tornar a Lisboa faltos de víveres, ya que no podían comer
por su mal sabor los carneros de las tierras descubiertas. En cuanto a los hombres rojos, eran
de gran estatura, piel rojiza y «cabellera no espesa, pero larga hasta los hombros»; rasgos
que hicieron pensar a muchos si los hermanos Almagrurinos habrían llegado a tocar efectivamente
en alguna isla oriental de América.

Al mismo tiempo que la geografía árabe hacía surgir tierras del Mar Tenebroso, la leyenda cristiana
lo poblaba con islas no menos maravillosas. Cuando los moros invadían la Península derrotando
al rey Roderico, una muchedumbre de cristianos, llevando a su frente a siete obispos, se había
embarcado, para huir Océano adentro hasta dar con una isla en la que fundaba siete ciudades.
Muchos navegantes portugueses, arrebatados por la tempestad, habían ido a parar a esta isla,
donde eran magníficamente tratados por gentes que hablaban su mismo idioma y tenían iglesias.
Pero así que intentaban volver a su tierra, se oponían los habitantes, deseosos de que se guardase
secreta la existencia de la «Isla de las Siete Ciudades». Unos que habían logrado regresar
enseñaban arenas de aquellas playas, que eran de oro casi puro. Pero al armarse nuevas expediciones
para ir a su descubrimiento, jamás acertaban éstas con el camino.

Otra isla, la de San Brandán, o San Borombón, ocupaba a las gentes de mar durante varios siglos;
isla fantasma que todos veían y en la que nadie llegaba a poner el pie. San Brandán, abad escocés
del siglo VI, que llegó a dirigir tres mil monjes, se embarcaba con su discípulo San Maclovio
para explorar el Océano en busca de unas islas que poseían las delicias del Paraíso y estaban
habitadas por infieles. Durante la navegación, un día de Navidad, el santo ruega a Dios que
le permita descubrir tierra donde desembarcar para decir su misa con la debida pompa, e inmediatamente
surge una isla ante las espumas que levanta su galera. Terminados los oficios divinos, cuando
San Borombón vuelve al barco con sus acólitos, la tierra se sumerge instantáneamente en las
aguas. Era una ballena monstruosa que por mandato del Señor se había prestado a este servicio.

Después de vagar años enteros por el Océano desembarcan en una isla, y encuentran, tendido
en un sepulcro, el cadáver de un gigante. Los dos santos monjes lo resucitan, tienen con él
pláticas interesantes, y tan razonable y bien educado se muestra, que acaba por convertirse
al cristianismo y lo bautizan. Pero a los quince días el gigante se cansa de la vida, desea
la muerte para gozar de las ventajas de su conversión entrando en el cielo, y solicita permiso
cortésmente para morirse otra vez, petición razonable a la que acceden los santos. Y desde
entonces ningún mortal logra penetrar en la isla de San Borombón. Algunos marineros de las
Canarias la ven de muy cerca en sus navegaciones; los hay que llegan a amarrar sus bateles
en los árboles de la orilla, entre restos de buques cubiertos de arena; pero siempre surge
una tempestad inesperada, un temblor de tierra, y el mar los arroja lejos. Y pasan siglos y
siglos sin que nadie ponga el pie en sus playas. Los habitantes de Tenerife la veían claramente
en ciertas épocas del año y se presentaban a las autoridades cientos de testigos declarando
su configuración: dos grandes montañas con un valle verde en el centro.

--América estaba descubierta por entero--dijo Ojeda--cuando todavía enviaban los vecinos de
Tenerife expediciones a su costa, por estas aguas, en busca de la famosa tierra de San Borombón.
Y la isla, que se dejaba ver perfectamente desde lo alto de las montañas, difuminábase en el
horizonte y acababa por perderse cuando alguien iba a su encuentro en un buque. Hubo muchas
expediciones, unas pagadas por los regidores de la isla, otras de particulares, pero todas
sin éxito; y la gente, cada vez más convencida de la existencia de San Borombón, achacaba estos
fracasos a la impericia de los expedicionarios antes que renunciar al encanto de lo maravilloso.
Casi todos los mapas de la época situaban esta isla en las inmediaciones de las Canarias, y
ochenta años antes de a independencia de las colonias, cuando la América española iba ya pensando
en declararse mayor de edad, todavía salió de Tenerife una expedición mandada por un caballero
respetable, y como se trataba de una empresa misteriosa, iban dos frailes en su buque. Algunos
creían que esta isla fantasma era el lugar del Paraíso terrenal donde viven en bienaventuranza
eterna Elías y Enoch... La santa poesía se aprovecha siempre de las ficciones populares, y
por esto el Tasso, al encantar al caballero Rinaldo en los mágicos jardines de Armida, los
coloca en una isla de las Canarias, recordando sin duda la tradición de la de San Borombón.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00427</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>214252</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20723</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> "What have you done, unfortunate, so that The
gods punish you? "I've taught the mortals do not think about death," answered Prometheus. "And
how did you get?" "I have made known the blind hope."

And for thousands of years ruled the world the beneficent god and comforting the dark hero
had given humans, paying this generosity with the torment of his heart torn by the eagle, "winged
dog Zeus." She drove the herds of men arms, she had fluttered to the bows of the discoverers,
she moved with her step stay inside where meditate silence scientists and artists, she led the eager
crowds welfare and comprehensive site that is uprooting of one hemisphere to go to be replanted
on the other.

Fernando saw it, saw it coming, with their eyes closed, above the blue sea, as a gold bubble
detached from the sun, like a rag finally stop light on edge of the
bow, like the divine images that decorated the ships of the first
Argonauts.

Their wings were stretched in the ether as majestic sails concave,
his tunic arremolinábase ago in harmonious folds, impelled by the
wind.

Was equal to the Victory of Samothrace, and well as to her head was
missing.

For this just to know Ojeda. She does not think she has no eyes ...

It was the hope, blind hope that with the advancement of his torso pointed south.

III

After lunch, passengers heard Goethe sound like the band forward with sleepy remoteness gives the
vastness of the ocean to all the vibrations.

- Van to vaccinate
the third - said Maltrana, always aware of what happened on the ship.

They were still off the island, skirting its rugged mountains, ancient
stone surge eruptions arrivals to the sea.

Down the slopes, as sheep in the flock, white houses, medium some of them hidden in the folds of
green shades. Above the heights was from the snow cap of Mount Teide as a curious head, hiding
or appearing as the ship going near or far from the coast.

Maltrana could not keep quiet in the winter garden sipping coffee with Fernando. Something extraordinary
happened on board without his presence.

- Do you think we'll see people in third?

... Should be interesting.

They descended the stairs two floors, and leaving the castle esplanade in central viéronse fore,
at the foot of the foremast. Under the big awning that shaded this space aglomerábase the stench
of a sweaty crowd. The ship's doctor and several assistants, all
blouses white, occupied the center next to a table laden with kits.

And the music went migrants in an endless row, all with a bare arm that presented the Lancer of cattle.
The first officer, assisted by police aides, organized the parade, ensuring that everyone, after
rolling up his arm with the other hand submit the role of its passage.

The

act of vaccination was both a recount. Al from Tenerife, the last leg of old world, began the great
journey, one had to enter the ship to America, and police needed to know the number of people
who were on board. The sailors roamed the cockpit, the dark passageways, cellars, to the far
corners in search hidden passenger pushing the fugitives who sought to avoid this operation.

German officials called each time to give orders to an employee of the police station fat man
and white mustache that was expressed in different languages, from
one to another with amazing ease.

Maltrana and he was greeted warmly.

- That's Carmelo - Ojeda said - one of our compatriots. Speaks all languages ??of Europe; in
addition to Arabic, and I think a little Japanese.

And with all his wisdom here you have it earning a few frames, no
other satisfaction than hold a uniform and cap migrants be called
official.

I look every day in his office, which is below provided with the
light on, and we chatted about what happens on the ship.

What a man! Wherever you go, he studied in Manchester, all by himself, going through the port
from ship to ship and telling any seafarer who was bored: "Let's take a paragraph in your language,
mate."

As he spoke Isidro of women and children of his friend, Andalusians
transplanted to Hamburg and cash shortages thereof, which forced him
to look between the rich passengers one that would entertain the leisure
of the voyage studying languages ??shouted Don Carmelo with the accent
of his homeland:

- Too God PAPE er hand!, You look good!

And he repeated the order in Italian, French, Portuguese and Arabic.

Men had marched, and were now women, with a squad of kids, the that presented themselves to
receive the vaccination. Went to the doctor with brawny arms the whiteness and firmness of the flesh
North; fatty arms on the sinking operators fingers, arms round amber, similar to those of women
by Titian but they occupied in the upper part a dark triangle of filthy dirt.

Women fought to uncover the sleeves of the chemise or thick elastic and in this struggle, they opened
the chest, showing scapulars and medals on flacideces of motherhood.

Arab female, brown and bony, were almost naked under his barons scratched, the thick Neapolitan,
hair disheveled and eyes of coal, returned to bodice with tranquil immodesty the exuberance
hoppers emerged to unbutton, the Castilian angular retinto oily hair combed as virgins Pre-Raphaelites,
covered promptly his arm with triple lining and flushed away, shaking heap short bailarinesca
their petticoats transudates. Some kids bawling their mothers clutching, quivering dread to
see the white blouses operators, others with his hat in the neck, showing Ivorian smile teeth of
a wolf, who is vying for first would advance arm as if that were a party.

Maltrana explained to his friend, the order in which migrants were
divided.

The bow was for 'Latino' Spanish, Italian, Portuguese, French, Arabs, Jews of the South and to Egyptians.
No one could guess the latter Latino people, but it had the police
box.

In the stern was crowded other nations: Germans, Russians and Jews, many Jews from diverse backgrounds,
Poles, galitzianos, Ruthenians, Moscow and Balkan cooking aside,
to the concerns and rites of their religion.

The Israelites had meat slaughtered by the Rabbis of Hamburg. The bustling latinidad enjoyed the
privilege on the other castes to drink wine with meals twice a week
and make chocolate at dawn twice, instead of regular coffee.

The Lamentations of Carmelo, who swore to himself with great fanfare,
interrupted Maltrana.

- Cursed be my gun!

Me and I missed that trip hisiésemos er no surprises. But comrade, there is no way to get rid
of these people! ...

Exchanged a few words in German with the first officer then shouted at Spanish waiters they were
serving "Latinos'

- To see these lads Bueno, pa bring them here!

Advanced six young men, bareheaded, ragged clothes and his feet in
broken or frayed espadrilles shoes.

- Moo do you have no ticket and
you have got here without MA or ma bustles, as if this Juesas the
house and toos?

What do you think this is going to quear craving?

... You, what you HERE?

And the six bustles were answering the interrogation of Mr. Carmelo. One was from Tenerife and
the remainder came from Andalusia and Galicia. Had been made secretly in several ships, and put
them on the ground to reach the Canaries.

And a cache search again in the cellar of another boat!

... So get thinking, be that as it may, where they had proposed. The six wanted to go to Buenos Aires,
and as beasts humble, resigned in advance to blows they believed
deserved, lowered their heads happy with his misfortune if they could
reach the end trip.

Don Carmelo spoke quietly with the first officer.

- Okay - said solemnly -.

But as no one comes here without a ticket and the ship can no space
backwards for you, going to swimming golveros Tenerife.

The island is there near.

He pointed to the coast was seen in the distance between the ship's
rail and the edge of the awning.

The officer was stroking the beard impassive as the interpreter translated his orders. The women
opened their eyes in astonishment and terror.

- To place a pan escaleriya pa that more fasiliá - Carmelo ordered.

The waiter obeyed him, placing a small ladder against the side, while the interpreter repeated
the order. "The water boys! And one remojonsito nothing more. "

The older bustles with his head still low, between believers and terrified, wondering that this
order could be true but also doubting that it was all a joke, used
to hardness and penalties on ships that had served as a refuge.

One that was almost a child dared to look over the railing, with eyes of fear appreciating the
enormous distance which lay between the ship and shore.

- I do not
want!

... Do not want to die ... I want to go to Buenos Aires! Mother! ... Mammy! ...

And he dropped to the ground moaning, kicking their legs to repel them from talking. Began sighs
and exclamations from the women's groups. Don Carmelo looked at the first official that was
stroking his beard.

- Bueno, children, will Pá later. At night you may go swimming. Meanwhile, that you vaccinate
and then eat ... A look at some old pants Bueno pa these boys, if
not go teaching the vergüensas the passage ... But it is agreed eh,
boys? at night I marcharéis swimming.

Suddenly relieved, the bustles were carried away by the sailors, who
pushed roughly, accepting the deal with humility and gratitude.

-
Be strong - Carmelo said the two friends by putting a fierce gesture
-.

If not were so, too er ship would fill with people without passage. Four will go to the machines,
provided Farta hasen stokers, and two smaller ones will help the Maid of the covers. Could disembark
in Rio de Janeiro. But er commander is Bueno, and insurance to the
yevaremos Buenos Aires.

The crooks will get away with it.

The music continued to play and resumed the parade of bare arms to the group white blouses.

Ojeda was impressed by the previous scene. He seemed to hear the cries of the lad still kicking
on the cover: "I do not want to die! I want to go to Buenos Aires !...». The tramp ports had the
same enthusiasm that he and almost everyone who lived in the upper
decks.

Dozing between the bales and barrels of a dock, had also seen the winged goddess without head,
he felt the caress of hope. And there they marched all, facing nostalgia of memory or the needs
of the present, scrambled, confused, matched by common illusion ... Buenos Aires! What a powerful magic
of this name, which was run the miserable, and starving mice to hide in the bowels of the ship!
...

Maltrana grew impatient at the monotony of the parade.

- After they
vaccinate the stern, less clean and presentable people that "Latino"
with long hair and sheepskin coats.

Up will be better.

They went to the top of the vessel, the cover of the boats, seeking the shade of an awning and
two free chairs to relax in solitude imbued with light blue. Most of the passage preferred to stay
down, a refugee in the soft twilight of the promenade deck.

Maltrana greeted a lady who was reading lying on a long couch, back on a cushion showing between
the flower and ruffled their snowy faldamenta startup clad legs white silk and high heels shoes.
Fernando, warned by the side of the companion noticed his hair, dark-blond, collected in the
form of helmet, in her eyes and trembling like drops of sea water, which rose briefly in the
book to look at him with quiet firmness, in the white of her neck, a whiteness of crumb of bread
lightly golden by the sun and sea breeze.

- Is the U.S., the lady who come near our table - muttered Isidro -. Speak Low people, just
shaking hands with some old board, shun the treatment of others ... I am the only man who
changes the greeting, but when I speak it pretends not to understand me ... And yet, I guess
it a cheerful and manly: You must be a pleasant companion; there is more to do with how funny smiles.
Dimples as cuckoos What you are near the mouth!, How his velvety eyes! ... But there is no trust
between people still on board; it looks like everybody to visit.

They sat at some distance from the U.S. and it came back down on the eyes book, swaying in his chair
to ignore the presence of the newcomers.

They had before them the blue of the ocean, smooth, dense, without a wrinkle on the bottom, at
the Stern, a triangle of shadow that clouded the horizon, a kind of gray cloud and pyramidal
which was the island ... Absolute quiet ... Sitting in the middle of the cover, there could see
foam that swirled up speed against the flanks of the ship.

From this point his eyes covered only the second term, namely the calm sea, which seemed covered
with a transparent and transparent crust, a crust of thick blue reflecting glass and pasty depth.
But for the black tufts that escaped from the chimney, to be floating in the calm sultry afternoon,
they would have believed that the ship not going ... And the island is always in sight, as the country
legends delighted that appear to move behind the steps of the run.

The silence of siesta extended its overwhelming peace on the deck flooded with light. Under Awnings
are perceived slight snoring, rhythmic breaths, backs turned to the
outside on the long chairs, heads embedded in pillows or resting on
the back, with eyes closed and mouth open to the freshness of the
shade.

The floor creaked in more heated, under the slow pace of a passerby. They went up the echoes
of music, distant numb, as if from the depths of the sea. They came from the other side of the fireplace
cries of children and crash of timber, revealing the various incidents of a sports game. The
afternoon sun caught fire across the West with blinding rain.

- Why call this the "Dark Sea"? - Maltrana said that he could not
remain silent long time.

These words aroused in both the memory of past readings. Ojeda thought of his drama poetic conquerors
whose preparation had been obliged to consider the saga of the sailors who discovered the wilderness.
Isidro remembered the work done when he was a mercenary in the literature, when he was in
pursuit of notes in libraries and file for the making of a book he would sign after a character
eager to join in an academy.

- It is always scary what we ignore - said Ojeda -. A cloud on the horizon or more sunless days
Dark enough to call a sea in which advanced with hesitation, fearing the surprises of the mystery
and keep track of costs. I confess that the geography of Dark Sea before the compass made possible
the long explorations, is a geography I love and rejuvenate, something
like those fairy tales that delight us as a perfume wilted flowers
to evoke the first impressions of childhood.

And the two listed in animated conversation all attempts of men from remote centuries, to break
the mystery of the Dark Sea.

The Carthaginian sailors down south along the coast of Africa, bringing, after a journey of several
years, elephant tusks suspended from the temples, colorful ornaments, skins of hairy men with
tails that had to be large orangutan wraps. And the Senate gave such value to such discoveries,
he kept as a state secret the route of the sailors, seeing distant
lands a safe refuge for his people if ill-fated war necessitated the
expatriation.

In this sea of ??darkness, beyond the Pillars of Hercules, had placed Homer and Hesiod the Elysee,
the abode of the blessed, the Gorgons, the land of eternal spring, and the Hesperides, with
their golden apples, guarded by a dragon of fire. Arab sailors were then which were thrown into
the sea of ??darkness, and geographers populated the mystery of marine wilderness poetic inventions,
discoveries garnishing the same as a tale from the Arabian Nights. The Emir spoke Edrisi Islands Vac-uac,
ultimately the world in the twelfth century by the East: islands so abundant in wealth, which
monkeys and dogs wore gold collars. A tree, which had large forests, was its name to the islands, the
uac-uac, so called because crying or barking with similar sounds
anyone who first put foot on the archipelago.

And this tree was on the tip of its branches, first, abundant flowers, and then instead of fruit,
beautiful girls, beauties virgins who were eligible for export to the harems.

For the West had advanced Almagrurinos siblings, eight neighboring Moorish Lisbon, long before
1147 - the year in which the Muslims were expelled from the city - joined the supplies needed
for a long journey, "not wanting to return without penetrating to the end Dark Sea. " Just discovered
the island of "bitter rams' and the island of" men red ', but were forced to turn to Lisbon lacking
food, since they could not eat bad taste by the rams of the discovered lands. As for the red
men were a tall, reddish skin and "non-thick hair, but long to shoulder";
features that made many wonder if the brothers would come to play
Almagrurinos effectively on an island east of America.

While geography Arab land raised up the Dark Sea, the Christian legend the islands peopled with
no less wonderful. When the Moors invaded the Iberian Peninsula defeating Roderick King, a
crowd of Christians, leading to its front seven bishops, had board, to flee into the ocean until
he found an island where he founded seven cities. Many Portuguese navigators carried away
by the storm, had gone to this island where they were magnificently treated by people who
spoke the same language and had churches. But just trying to get back their land, was opposed
by the inhabitants, eager to be on guard secret the existence of the "Island of Seven Cities.
Some who had managed to return sands taught those beaches, which were almost pure gold. But
at the arming expeditions to go to their discovery, they never guessed right with the road.

Another island, St. Brendan or St. Borombón, employed people at sea
for several centuries; ghost island and everyone saw that no one came
to set foot.

St. Brendan, Abbot Scotland the sixth century, which came to lead three thousand monks, embarked
with his disciple San Maclovio to explore the ocean in search of some islands that had the delights
of paradise and were inhabited by infidels. While browsing, Christmas Day, the saint prays to
God allows you to find land where their land to say Mass with due pomp, and immediately comes
an island to the foam that lifts his hat. Finished the divine, when San Borombón back to the
ship with his acolytes, the land is instantly immersed in waters. It was a monstrous whale by order
of the Lord had given to this service.

After wandering for years by the Ocean landed on an island, and found, lying in a grave, the corpse
of a giant. The two holy monks raised, owe him interesting conversations, and so reasonable and
well educated shown, which eventually becomes to Christianity and baptized. But on the fifteenth
day the giant gets tired of life, wishes death to enjoy the benefits of conversion entering heaven,
and asks politely to die again, reasonable request that access to the saints. And then no
mortal is able to penetrate on the island of San Borombón. Some seamen Canaries are very close
in their navigation, there are those who come to tie their boats
in trees from the shore, among the remains of ships covered by sand,
but always comes an unexpected storm, an earthquake, the sea throws
them away. And centuries passed no one ever set foot on its shores.
The people of Tenerife showed clearly the at certain times of the
year and presented to the authorities claiming hundreds of witnesses
configuration: two big mountains with a green valley in the center.

-
America was discovered by a whole - said Ojeda - where neighbors still
sent Tenerife expeditions to the coast, these waters in search of
the famous San Borombón land. And the island, which could be seen
perfectly from the top of the mountains, in difuminábase horizon and
just getting lost when someone was going to meet on a ship. There
were many expeditions, some paid by the rulers of the island, other
individuals, but all without success, and people increasingly convinced
of the existence of San Borombón, blamed these failures to the inability
of the expedition before renouncing the charm of the marvelous. Most
maps of the time placed this island near the Canaries and eighty years
before the independence of the colonies, when Spanish America was
already thinking to declare adult, Tenerife still left an expedition
led by a gentleman respectable, and as it was a mysterious company,
were two brothers on his ship. Some phantom island believed that this
was the place of earthly paradise where they live in bliss Elijah
and Enoch eternal ... The holy poetry always take advantage of popular
fiction, and why Tasso, to love the knight Rinaldo in the magic garden
of Armida, the placed on an island in the Canaries, no doubt recalling
the tradition of St. Borombón</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>