<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04841</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>2521</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>736</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Fue en Nueva York secretario
de Narciso López, a quien conocía desde 1846, y redactor en jefe de La verdad. Publicó en Nueva
Orleans entre 1853 y 1854 el periódico El independiente, etc.

Se trasladó a Filadelfia en 1854, donde vivió como profesor de español y contrajo matrimonio
con Emilia Casanova, una destacada activista de la independencia cubana.

Regresó a La Habana en 1858, acogido a la amnistía. Aquí trabajó al frente de la imprenta La
Antilla, que publicara algunas obras de interés para nuestras letras, como los artículos de
costumbres de Anselmo Suárez y Romero, y colaboró en el periódico literario La Habana en compañía
de Sterling y Calcagno, con importantes juicios críticos sobre Betancourt y otros contemporáneos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02598</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>67489</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>709</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Secretary was in New York Narciso
López, whom he knew since 1846, and editor in chief of The Truth. Published in New Orleans between
1853 and 1854 the newspaper The Independent, etc.

He moved to Philadelphia in 1854, where he lived as a Spanish teacher
and married with Emilia Casanova, a leading activist in the Cuban
independence.

He returned to Havana in 1858, received amnesty. Here he worked at the forefront of printing the Antilla,
which published some works of interest to our letters, including
items manners of Anselmo Suárez y Romero, and assisted in the literary
journal in the company of Havana Sterling and Calcagno, with important
critical judgments about Betancourt and other contemporaries</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>