<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05994</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>78071</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19987</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Todo quedará en la oscuridad mas
profunda; imaginaremos reproducidas aquellas tinieblas que yacian sobre la faz del abismo antes
que la palabra criadora dijese: «hágase la luz.»

Pero conviene advertir que al dejar el mundo en tan horrible oscuridad, no hemos alterado ninguna
de sus otras leyes; existen como antes, las gigantescas moles recorriendo con asombrosa rapidez
y admirable precision sus órbitas inmensas. De donde se infiere que haciendo abstraccion del
olor, del sabor, del sonido, de los colores, de la luz, el mundo existe todavía, sin que nos
cueste ningun trabajo concebirle de esta manera. Aun mas, hasta de la sensacion del tacto podemos
prescindir, pues será fácil suponer que no percibimos ninguna impresion por este sentido; las
de color ó frio, blandura ó dureza, cuyas causas quedarian en los cuerpos, podemos sustituirlas
unas con otras y aun hacerlas desaparecer, sin que por eso creyésemos que el universo dejaba
de existir.

[50.] Despues de hechas todas estas abstracciones, ensayemos otra, y veamos lo que sucede.
Hagamos desaparecer la extension. A esta prueba el universo no resiste: las moles de los astros
desaparecen; la tierra se anonada bajo nuestras plantas; las distancias dejan de existir; el
movimiento es un absurdo; nuestro propio cuerpo se desvanece; el universo entero se hunde en
la nada, ó si continúa siendo algo, es cosa del todo diferente de lo que ahora nos figuramos.

Es indudable: si prescindimos de la extension, si esta sensacion, ó idea, ó sea lo que fuere,
que sobre ella tenemos, no la realizamos en lo exterior, si no la consideramos como una representacion
de lo que existe fuera de nosotros, todo se trastorna; no sabemos qué pensar ni de nuestras
sensaciones, ni de sus relaciones con los objetos que las causan: todo da vueltas en derredor,
nos falta una de las bases de nuestros conocimientos, tendemos en vano los brazos para asirnos
de algun punto fijo, y preguntamos con desconsuelo, si todo lo que sentimos no es mas que una
pura ilusion, si serán una verdad las extravagancias de Berkeley.

[51.] Aun con respecto á la extension es digno de observarse, que si bien la objetivamos trasladándola
á lo exterior, no es de todo punto exacto que esté representada por la sensacion. Mejor se
diria que es un receptáculo de ciertas sensaciones, que no un objeto de ellas; una condicion
necesaria para las funciones de algunos sentidos, que no una cosa sentida. La extension abstraida
de las sensaciones de la vista y del tacto, se reduce á lo que hemos dicho mas arriba, la multiplicidad
y la continuidad; el conocimiento de esto, nos viene de los sentidos, pero es diferente de
lo que nos representan los sentidos. Cuando á las impresiones que he recibido de la vista les
quito el color y la luz me queda ciertamente la idea de una cosa extensa, mas nó de una cosa
visible, ni de un objeto representado por la sensacion. De la propia suerte si despojo las
impresiones que me han venido por el tacto, de las calidades que afectan este sentido, no se
aniquila el objeto que las causaba, pero no está representado por las impresiones que él me
transmite.

[52.] Estas observaciones manifiestan que no trasladamos á lo exterior nuestras sensaciones,
que estas son un medio por el cual se informa, nuestra alma, mas nó imágenes en que ella contemple
los objetos. Todas ellas le indican una causa exterior; pero algunas, como las de la vista
y del tacto, le manifiestan de un modo particular la multiplicidad y la continuidad, ó sea
la extension.

De esto se infiere tambien, que el mundo exterior no es una pura ilusion, que existe en realidad
con sus moles inmensas, sus variados movimientos, su geometría infinita; pero que gran parte
de su belleza y encantos se hallan mas bien en nosotros que en él. La mano todopoderosa é infinitamente
sabia que le ha criado, ha ostentado su sabiduría y su poder de una manera particular en los
seres sensibles, y sobre todo en los inteligentes. ¿Qué seria el universo si no hubiera quien
sintiese y entendiese? En esa íntima relacion, en la incesante comunicacion de los objetos
con los seres sensibles, están la hermosura, la armonía, los arcanos de la naturaleza. El mas
precioso cuadro, si no hubiese quien le mirara y percibiese su belleza, seria un conjunto de
lineamentos, un geroglífico de caractéres indescifrados: pero desde el momento que está á la
vista de un ser que siente y conoce, el cuadro se anima, es lo que debe ser; y en esta misteriosa
comunicacion, el objeto gana en bellezas todo lo que comunica de hechizo.

Suponed que un conjunto de instrumentos dispuestos con el conveniente mecanismo ejecutan con
admirable precision las mejores concepciones de Bellini ó de Mozart; ¿á qué se reduce todo
falta un ser sensible? á vibraciones del aire combinadas con cierta ley; á puros movimientos
de un flúido sometidos á una precision geométrica. Introducid á un hombre: entonces la geometría
se convierte en armonía celestial, entonces hay música, hay encantos.

La simetría de las tablas de un jardin, la lozanía de sus arbustos, el color y esmalte de sus
flores, la fragancia de sus aromas, ¿qué son sin un ser sensible? figuras geométricas, superficies
dispuestas con arreglo á ciertas leyes, volúmenes de tal ó cual clase, columnas de flúidos
que salen de ellos, y se desparraman por el espacio; pero introducid al hombre, entonces las
figuras geométricas se revisten de mil gracias, las flores se cubren de galanos colores, las
columnas de flúido se convierten en exquisitos aromas.

CAPÍTULO X.

VALOR DEL TACTO PARA OBJETIVAR LAS SENSACIONES.

[53]. Se ha dicho que el tacto es el testigo mas seguro y quizás el único, de la existencia
de los cuerpos; pues sin él todas las sensaciones no pasarian de simples modificaciones de
nuestro ser, y no podríamos atribuirles ningun objeto exterior. Yo no creo que esto sea verdad.
Por el tacto recibimos una impresion lo mismo que por los demás sentidos; en todos los casos
esta impresion es una afeccion de nuestro ser, y nó una cosa externa; y cuando por la continuacion
de estas impresiones, por su órden y por su independencia de nuestra voluntad, juzgamos que
proceden de objetos que están fuera de nosotros, este juicio se verifica no solo con respecto
á las impresiones del tacto, sino tambien de los demás sentidos.

[54.] Una de las razones en que se ha pretendido fundar la superioridad del tacto para atestiguar
la existencia de los cuerpos, es que él nos da la idea ó la sensacion de la extension; porque
si suponemos que un hombre está privado de todos los sentidos excepto el tacto, y recorre con
su mano la superficie de su cuerpo, experimenta la continuidad de la sensacion, en la cual
va envuelta la de extension. Esta observacion de los partidarios de la supremacía del tacto,
no convence de lo que se proponen. Porque al recorrer con la vista varios objetos, ó las diferentes
partes de uno mismo, experimentamos la sensacion de continuidad tan claramente como con el
tacto. No se puede concebir por qué la sensacion de la extension ha de ser mas clara cuando
se pasa la mano á lo largo de una barandilla, que cuando se la mira con los ojos.

[55.] Los sostenedores de dicha opinion alegan que por el tacto de nuestro cuerpo adquirimos
una sensacion doble, lo que no se verifica con los demás sentidos: pasando la mano por la frente,
sentimos con la frente y con la mano; verificándose una continuidad de sensaciones, que todas
tienen su orígen y término en nosotros mismos. Así tenemos la conciencia de que nos pertenecen
tanto la sensacion de la mano como la de la frente.

Pero esta razon que algunos han creido concluyente, es sin embargo sumamente fútil: adolece
del sofisma que los dialécticos llaman peticion de principio, pues supone lo mismo que se trata
de probar. En efecto: el hombre destituido de todos los sentidos excepto el del tacto, experimentará
las dos sensaciones y su continuidad; pero ¿de esto qué podrá inferir? ¿Sabe por ventura que
tenga mano ni frente? suponemos que nó; la dificultad está pues en explicar cómo adquiere dicho
conocimiento. Ambas sensaciones le pertenecen, de esto tiene una conciencia íntima, pero ignora
de dónde dimanan. La coincidencia de las dos sensaciones ¿le prueba por ventura algo en favor
de la existencia de la frente y de la mano, objetos de que suponemos que no tiene ninguna idea?

Si esta coincidencia probase lo que se quiere, con mas razon probaria que la combinacion de
unos sentidos con otros, nos lleva al conocimiento de la existencia de los cuerpos, y por consiguiente
que dicho conocimiento no se engendra exclusivamente por el tacto. Yo experimento que siempre
que tengo la sensacion de un movimiento que es ponerme la mano delante de los ojos, pierdo
la vista de los objetos, y se me presenta otro que es siempre el mismo: la mano; si de esta
coincidencia infiero la existencia de los objetos externos, queda destruida la supremacía del
tacto, pues que para la formacion de semejante juicio influye la vista. Observo tambien que
al tener la sensacion que resulta de dar una mano con otra, experimento la sensacion de oir
el ruido de la palmada: luego si la coincidencia vale, influirá el oido como el tacto. Lo que
digo de la palmada, puede aplicarse á lo que experimento recorriendo con la mano una parte
del cuerpo, por ejemplo toda la longitud del brazo, de suerte que el roce produzca ruido. En
este caso, hay las dos sensaciones, coincidentes y continuas.

Se replicará tal vez que estos ejemplos se refieren á diferentes sentidos, y que producen sensaciones
de diversa especie: pero esto no altera nada: porque, si el ser que siente infiere la existencia
de los objetos de la coincidencia de las varias sensaciones, queda destruida la supremacía
del tacto que es lo que nos proponíamos demostrar.

[56.] La sensacion de la mano no es la misma que la de la frente, porque aquella estará mas
ó menos fria, mas ó menos caliente, mas ó menos fina, mas ó menos blanda, y así no será la
misma sensacion la causada en la mano por la frente, que la producida en la frente por la mano.
Siendo de notar que cuanto menor supongamos la diferencia entre las dos sensaciones, menos
viva será la percepcion de su dualidad, y por tanto menos notable la coincidencia en que se
funda el juicio. Por manera que bien analizada la materia venimos á parar á que para formar
juicio de la existencia de los objetos contribuye especialmente la diversidad de las sensaciones;
y por tanto será mas conducente á este fin, la combinacion de dos sentidos que las dos sensaciones
de uno solo. Así, lejos de que el tacto haya de considerarse como único ni superior en este
punto, solo ha de ser tenido como auxiliar de los otros.

[57.] Y en realidad, apenas cabe duda en que el tacto necesita tambien del auxilio de los demás
sentidos, y que los juicios que del mismo resultan se parecen á los que dimanan de estos. Es
probable que solo despues de repetidos experimentos referimos la sensacion del tacto al objeto
que la causa, y aun á la parte afectada. El hombre á quien se ha amputado la mano, experimenta
el dolor como si la conservase; y esto ¿por qué? porque con la repeticion de actos ha formado
el hábito de referir la impresion cerebral al punto donde terminan los nervios que se la transmiten.
Luego no hay una relacion necesaria entre el tacto y el objeto: y este sentido puede sufrir
ilusiones como los demás. Luego no es exacto lo que se ha dicho de que la idea del cuerpo nace
debajo de nuestra mano, si esto se entiende como privativo del tacto; pues lo mismo se verifica
de los demás sentidos y particularmente de la vista.

CAPÍTULO XI.

INFERIORIDAD DEL TACTO COMPARADO CON OTROS SENTIDOS.

[58.] Esta superioridad, ó mejor, este privilegio exclusivo que Condillac y otros filósofos
han concedido al tacto, á mas de no tener ningun fundamento como acabamos de ver, parece estar
en contradiccion con la misma naturaleza de este sentido. Cabalmente se da la supremacía al
mas material, por decirlo así, al mas rudo de todos ellos.

Nadie puede saber las ideas que de las cosas se formaria un hombre reducido á solo el tacto:
pero me parece que lejos de ponerse en comunicacion clara y viva con el mundo exterior, y de
que tuviese la suficiente basa para fundar sus conocimientos, debiera vegetar en la mas profunda
ignorancia, y sufrir las equivocaciones mas trascendentales.

[59.] Al comparar el tacto con la vista, y aun con el oido y el olfato, desde luego se ofrece
una diferencia importantísima, en favor de estos y contra aquel. El tacto no nos transmite
la impresion sino de los objetos que están inmediatos á nuestro cuerpo; cuando los otros tres,
y especialmente la vista, nos ponen en comunicacion con objetos muy distantes. Las estrellas
fijas están separadas de nosotros por una distancia tal que apenas cabe en nuestra imaginacion,
y sin embargo las vemos; no llegan á tanto ciertamente ni el olfato ni el oido; pero el primero
no deja de advertirnos de la existencia de un jardin que está á muchos pasos de nosotros; y
el segundo nos da noticia de una batalla que se ha trabado á muchas leguas de nuestra vivienda,
de la chispa eléctrica que ha rasgado la nube en el confin del horizonte, ó de la tempestad
que brama en la inmensidad de los mares.

[60.] Esa limitacion del tacto á lo que está en sus inmediaciones, traeria consigo la estrechez
de las ideas que se originarian de él solo, y lo constituyen por necesidad en un grado muy
inferior al de los otros tres, y en particular de la vista. Para formarnos ideas claras en
este punto, comparemos el alcance de la vista y del tacto con respecto á un objeto: un edificio.
Por medio de la vista tomamos en pocos instantes idea de la fachada, y de sus demás partes
exteriores: y en breve tiempo nos enteramos de su disposicion interior, y hasta de sus muebles
y adornos. ¿Cómo se puede lograr esto por el tacto? Es imposible. Aun suponiéndole muy delicado,
y muy tenaz memoria de las impresiones que anduviese comunicando, se necesitarian larga horas
para recorrer con la mano el frontispicio, y formarnos de él alguna idea. ¿Qué no seria con
respecto á todo lo exterior del edificio? ¿qué si hablamos de lo interior? Salta á los ojos
que seria menester renunciar á semejante tarea, y que tal preciosa labor de una cornisa, de
un pedestal, de un peristilo; tal magnificencia de una torre, de una cúpula; tal osadía de
un arco, de una bóveda, de una flecha, que el ojo aprecia en un instante, le costarian al pobre
que solo poseyese el tacto, andar mucho á gatas y encaramarse por peligrosos andamios, y exponerse
á resbalar por horrendos precipicios, y todavia sin poder lograr ni la millonésima parte de
lo que con tanta facilidad y rapidez consiguieron los ojos.

Extiéndanse estas consideraciones á una ciudad, á vastos países, al universo, y véase qué superioridad
tan inmensa tiene la vista sobre el tacto.

[61.] Esta superioridad no se presenta tan de bulto cuando se compara el tacto con otros sentidos;
sin embargo no deja tambien de existir, y en un grado muy alto.

Desde luego ocurre una diferencia, cual es la de las distancias. Es cierto que mediando estas,
tambien el tacto puede sentir en algun modo: como por ejemplo la presencia ó la ausencia del
sol por medio del calor y del frio; y de la misma manera la presencia ó la ausencia, y la mayor
ó menor cercanía de algunos cuerpos; pero estas impresiones, á mas de que están muy lejos de
tener la misma variedad y rapidez de las del oido, tampoco nos darian idea de distancia, si
no tuviéramos mas sentido que el tacto.

Calor y frio, sequedad y humedad, á esto se reducen las impresiones que algunos cuerpos distantes
pueden ejercer sobre el tacto; y claro es que las impresiones son de tal naturaleza que podrian
dar lugar á numerosas y graves equivocaciones.

[62.] Si suponemos que un hombre que solo posea el tacto, haya llegado á conocer la presencia
y la ausencia del sol sobre el horizonte, siendo su única norma la temperatura del ambiente,
y dependiendo esta de mil causas que nada tienen que ver con el astro del dia, sucederá con
mucha frecuencia que el cambio natural ó artificial de ella deberá inducirte á error. La humedad
que experimentará á las inmediaciones de un lago donde le llevan á bañarse, hará que con ella
conozca la inmediacion del agua; ¿pero no sentirá mil veces una impresion de humedad por causas
que obrarán sobre la atmósfera, del todo independientes de las aguas de un lago?

Es cierto que la concentracion de todas las fuerzas sensitivas en un solo sentido, la ninguna
distraccion, la atencion continua sobre un mismo género de sensaciones, podrá llevar la delicadeza
del tacto á un punto de perfeccion que probablemente no concebimos nosotros; así como el hábito
de encadenar las ideas con respecto á un solo órden de sensaciones, y de formar los juicios
con relacion á ellas solas, produciria una precision, exactitud y variedad muy superior á cuanto
podemos imaginar; pero por mas que sobre este punto se quieran extender las conjeturas, siempre
es claro que hay aquí un límite, cual es la naturaleza del órgano y de sus relaciones con los
cuerpos. Este órgano estaria siempre limitado á los objetos contiguos, para recibir impresiones
bien determinadas; y con respecto á los distantes, los que pudiesen obrar sobre él, lo ejecutarian
causándole la impresion que la naturaleza de ambos consiente; frio ó calor, sequedad ó humedad,
y aun si se quiere, cierta presion en mayor ó menor grado; y en cuanto á muchísimos otros,
es imposible imaginar que tuviesen accion ninguna. Por mas que se ensanche el círculo de esta
clase de sensaciones siempre ha de ser muy reducido. Además, es necesario advertir que esta
perfectibilidad del tacto por efecto de su aislamiento, no es propiedad suya exclusiva, sino
que se extiende tambien á los otros sentidos, como que está fundada en las leyes de la organizacion,
y en las de la generacion de nuestras ideas.

[63.] Para comprender la superioridad que en esta parte lleva el oido al tacto, basta considerar
1.º la relacion de las distancias; 2.º la variedad de los objetos; 3.º la rapidez de la sucesion
de las impresiones; 4.º la simultaneidad, tan vasta en el oido, y tan limitada en el tacto;
5.º las relaciones con la palabra.

Relacion de las distancias. Claro es que en este punto se aventaja al tacto el oido; aquel
necesita en general la inmediacion, este nó; y aun de suyo requiere para la buena apreciacion
del objeto, cierta distancia acomodada á la clase del sonido. ¿De cuántos y cuántos objetos
distantes, no nos informa el oido, con respecto á los cuales nada puede decirnos el tacto?
El galope del caballo que amenaza atropellarnos, el ruido del torrente que nos puede arrebatar,
el trueno que retumba y nos anuncia la tormenta, el estruendo del cañón que nos da noticia
de que ha principiado una batalla, el ruido de las carreras, de la gritería, de los tambores
y campanas, que nos indican el estallido de la cólera popular, la música estrepitosa que nos
informa de la alegría causada por una fausta nueva, el concierto dedicado á los placeres del
salon, el canto que nos hechiza con melancólicos recuerdos, con sentimientos de esperanza y
de amor, el ay! que nos avisa del sufrimiento, el llanto que nos aflige con la idea del infortunio;
todo esto nos dice el oido; sobre todo esto nada puede decirnos el tacto.

Variedad de los objetos. Los objetos distantes de que nos da noticia el tacto son por necesidad
muy poco variados; y por lo mismo las ideas que solo de él resultasen, estarian sujetas á una
confusion deplorable, y á mucha incertidumbre. El oido al contrario, nos informa de infinitos
objetos sumamente diferentes, y lo ejecuta con toda precision y exactitud.

Rapidez de la sucesion de las impresiones. Es evidente que en esta parte lleva el oido al tacto
una superioridad incalculable. Este cuando percibe por yuxtaposicion, necesita recorrer sucesivamente
los objetos y aun las diferentes partes de uno mismo, si ha de recibir impresiones variadas:
lo que exige largo tiempo por poco numerosos que sean. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01360</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>77157</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17879</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Everything will be in the dark over
deep, will imagine that darkness reproduced lying on the face of the deep before breeder say that
the word "Let there be light."

But it should be noted that leaving the world in such horrible darkness, we have not altered any
of its other laws exist as before, the giant moles touring with amazing speed admirable precision
and immense orbits. From this it follows that being disregarded smell, taste, sound, color,
light, the world still exists, without being no cost work conceived in this way. Even more, even
the sensation of touch can without, it will be easy to assume that we do not perceive any posters
in this sense, the Color or cold, tenderness or hardness, the causes remain in the body, we can
replace each other and even make them disappear, but why let us believe that the universe to
exist.

[50.] After taking all these abstractions, try anything and see what happens. Do away with the extension.
In this test, the universe does not stand: the masses of the stars disappear, the earth under
our feet crushes, the gap ceases to exist, the motion is an absurdity, our own body disappears,
the entire universe is plunged into nothing, or whether it is still
something, is something entirely different from what we imagine now.

Undoubtedly, if we dispense with the extension, if this feeling, or idea, or whatever it is,
that on it we have not performed on the outside, if not regarded as a representation of what exists
outside us, everything goes haywire, do not know what to think or our feelings or their relationships
with objects that cause them: everything revolves around, we lack a basis of our knowledge, we
tend in vain arms to cling of some fixed point, and asked in grief,
if all you feel is not more than a pure illusion, if you are a true
Berkeley extravaganzas.

[51.] Even with respect to the extension is worthy of remark, that while moving it objectify
to the outside, it is absolutely true that is represented by the sensation. Best I would say that
is a receptacle of certain feelings, not an object of them, a condition necessary for the functions of
some senses, not felt a thing. The abstracted extension the sensations of sight and touch,
is reduced to what we said above, the multiplicity and continuity and knowing this, comes from
the senses, but is different from what we represent the senses. As to the impressions I received
from them sight remove the color and light is certainly my idea of ??an extended thing, not
a thing visible, or an object represented by the sensation. Of its own destiny if you spoil
the impressions I have been through touch, qualities that affect this sense, not destroys the
object that caused it, but not represented by the impressions that
he'd transmitted.

[52.] These observations demonstrate that the outside to move our feelings, these are a means
by which we report, our soul, but no pictures in which she contemplates objects. All of them
tell an external cause, but some, like the view and touch, will manifest
in a particular way the multiplicity and continuity, I mean the extension.

From

this it also follows that the outside world is a pure illusion, that there is actually with huge
masses, its various movements, infinite geometry, but that much its beauty and charm are on
us rather than on it. And infinitely powerful hand knew that he has raised, has held its wisdom and power
in a particular way in sentient beings, and above all intelligent. What would the universe if
there was none felt and understood? In this intimate relationship, in the ongoing communication
of objects with sentient beings, are the beauty, harmony, the mysteries of nature. The most
beautiful picture, had it not who you look and perceive its beauty, it would be a set of lineaments,
a hieroglyphic of undecipherable characters, but from the moment which is at the view of one
who feels and knows, the picture comes to life, is what should be, and in this mysterious communication,
the object gains in beauty all that communicates spell.

Suppose that a set of instruments provided with the appropriate mechanism to execute admirable
precision the best conceptions of Mozart or Bellini, "it all comes down to needed to be sensitive?
to air vibrations combined with a certain law, to pure movement of a fluid subjected to a geometric
precision. Introduce a man, then the geometry heavenly harmony becomes, then there is music, there
are charms.

The symmetry of the tables in a garden, the freshness of your shrubs, color and glaze of flowers, fragrant
aromas, what is not a sentient being? geometric shapes, surfaces arranged according to certain
laws, volumes of this or that class, fluid columns emerging from them, and are scattered throughout
the space, but introduces man, then geometric figures are clothed in a thousand thanks, the
flowers are covered with Galanos colors, fluid column become exquisite
aromas.

CHAPTER X.

OBJECTIVE VALUE OF TOUCH FOR THE SENSATIONS.

[53]. It has been said that touch is the surest witness and perhaps the only, the existence bodies,
for without it all the feelings would pass no simple modifications ourselves, and we could
not attribute any external object. I do not think this is true. By touch we get an impression
as well as by the other senses, in all cases this impression is a
condition of our being, not an external thing, and when the continuation
of these impressions, by his order and independence of our will, we
judge that come from objects outside of us, this view is true not
only with respect to impressions of touch, but also the other senses.

[54.] One of the reasons we have tried to establish the superiority of touch to testify the existence
of bodies, is that he gives us the idea or the sensation of extension, because if we assume
that a man is deprived of all senses except touch and goes with hand the surface of your body,
you experience the continuity of feeling, in which the extension is wrapped. This observation of the
supporters of the supremacy of touch not convinced of what they propose. Because to go with
it several objects, or different parts of self, we experience the feeling of continuity as
clearly as the touch.

You can not conceive why the feeling of the extension has to be more clear when runs his hand
along a railing, which when viewed with the eyes.

[55.] Holders of this opinion claim that by the touch of our bodies acquire a double sensation,
which does not take place with the other senses, passing his hand
across his forehead, Sorry to the forehead and hand, verifying the
continuity of feelings, that all have their origin and end in ourselves.

Thus we have the awareness that we belong both the sensation of the hand like the front.

But this reason that some have thought conclusive, is nevertheless extremely trivial: suffers fallacy
of the begging call dialectical, it is the same as it is testing. In effect, the man removed
from all respects except that of touch, experience the two sensations and continuity, but it does
what it can infer? Do you know by chance that be hand or forehead? not supposed to, the difficulty
lies in explaining how they acquired the knowledge. Both belong sensations, this is an inner
consciousness, but ignores where they derive.

The coincidence of the two sensations do you test something for fortune the existence of the
forehead and hand, we assume that objects have no idea?

If this match to prove what you want, with more reason that the combination would prove some
way with others, leads us to knowledge of the existence of bodies, and therefore that knowledge
is generated not only by touch. I always experiment I have the feeling of a movement that is
to put your hand in front of the eyes, I lose In view of the objects, and another that comes
to me is always the same: the hand, if this coincidence infer the existence of external objects,
it is destroyed the supremacy of touch, then, that for the formation of such a view affects the
view. Also observed that to have the feeling that it is to lend a hand with another, experience
the sensation of hearing slap noise: if the match then it will influence the ear and touch.
What say the slap, you can apply to what I experience walking hand
part the body, such as the length of the arm, so that the friction
produces noise.

In this case, there are two sensations, coincident and continuous.

May be replied that these examples refer to different senses, and produce feelings of different
species, but this does not change anything, because if the sentient
infers the existence of objects in the overlap of the various sensations,
supremacy is destroyed touch that is what we intended to prove.

[56.] The sensation of the hand is not the same as that of the front, because that will be more
or less cold, more or less hot, more or less fine, more or less soft, and so will not same
feeling that caused in his forehead, that produced in the front by hand. Is worthy of note
that the lower suppose the difference between the two sensations, less living is the perception
of duality, and therefore less remarkable coincidence that cover the trial. So well analyzed by the
subject to come to stop that train view of the existence of objects contributes especially the diversity
of sensations; and therefore be more conducive to this end, the combination of two ways that
the two sensations of one.

Thus, far from the touch has to be regarded as unique or superior in this point, one has to be
taken as an auxiliary to the other.

[57.] And in fact, little doubt that the touch also need the help of others senses, and that trials
of the same result resembles those arising from them. Is likely that only after repeated experiments
refer the sensation of touch in order the cause, and even to the affected part. The man has amputee
hand experience pain as if retained, and this why? because the repetition of acts has made
the habit of referring the impression brain to the point where the nerves end the broadcast. Then
there is no necessary relation between touch and the object: and this sense may suffer illusions
as the other.

Therefore it is precisely what has been said that the idea of ??the
body grows under our hand, if this is understood as exclusive to the
touch, since the same is verified of the other senses, particularly
sight.

CHAPTER XI.

LOWER COMPARED TO OTHER SENSES TOUCH.

[58.] This superiority, or better, this exclusive privilege and other philosophers Condillac
granted to the touch, more of having no foundation as we have seen, appears to be in contradiction
with the very nature of this connection.

Is given supremacy fully to more material, so to speak, the rudest of them all.

No one can know the ideas of things a man would form reduced to only touch: but I think that far
to get in clear and vivid communication with the outside world, and they had sufficient knowledge
bases to support his claim, it should vegetate in the most profound ignorance, and suffer the most
far-reaching mistakes.

[59.] Comparing with the light touch, and even with the hearing and smell, of course is offered
a major difference in favor of this and against that. Touch conveys no but the impression of
objects that are immediate to our body when the other three, and
especially the view, put us in communication with distant objects.

Stars are still separated from us by such a distance that barely fits in our imagination, and yet
we see, certainly less than that or the smell or the ear, but the first continues to warn
of the existence of a garden that is many steps away from us, and the second gives us news
of a battle that has stuck to many miles of our home, electric spark that has torn the cloud in
the confines of the horizon, or the storm that rages in the immensity of the sea.

[60.] This limitation of touch with what is in the vicinity, would result in the narrowing of the
ideas originating in his own, and are by necessity at a very lower than the other three, and
in particular of the view. To form clear ideas this point, compare the sight and touch in relation
to an object: a building. Through the view we take in a few moments idea of ??the facade, and
its other parts field: and in short time we heard of his interior disposition, and even their
furniture and ornaments. How can this be done by touch? It is impossible. Even supposing very
delicate and very tenacious memory of the impressions that he wandered about communicating, it
would take long hours to go with the hand the frontispiece, and to form some idea of ??it. What would
not be with respect to everything outside the building? What if we talk about inside? Jump
to the eyes it would be necessary to renounce the task, and that
such a beautiful work of a ledge of a pedestal, a colonnade, such
magnificence of a tower, a dome, such boldness an arch, a vault, an
arrow, the eye seen in a moment, it would cost to poor only possessed
the touch, much to walk on all fours and climb to dangerous scaffolding,
and exposed horrendous to slide down cliffs, and still unable to achieve
or one millionth of which so easily and quickly got the eyes.

Let them stretch these considerations into a city, to vast countries, the universe and see what superiority
so vast is the view of the touch.

[61.] This superiority does not appear so evident when you compare the touch and other senses;
but not without also exist, and a very high degree.

Since then a difference occurs, which is the distance. It is true that mediate these, touch
can also feel in some way: such as the presence or absence of sun
through heat and cold, and just as the presence or absence, and most
or less proximity of some bodies, but these impressions, but they
are far from have the same range and speed of the ear, would give
us no idea of ??distance, if we had no more sense than touch.

Heat and cold, dryness and humidity, this is reduced to the impressions
that some distant bodies may exert on the touch, and clear is that
the impressions are of a nature that could give rise to many serious
mistakes.

[62.] If we assume that a man who owns one touch, you have come to know the presence and the
absence of the sun on the horizon, their only standard room temperature, and depending on this a
thousand reasons that have nothing to do with the star of the day, happen to change very often
that natural or artificial it will induce you into error. Moisture you will experience near a lake
where you have to bathe, will make her aware of the immediacy of
the water but do not feel a thousand times an impression of moisture
causes that will work on air, completely independent of the waters
of a lake?

It is true that the concentration of all forces in a single sensory effect, no distraction, continuous
attention on the same kind of feelings, may take the delicacy touch of perfection to a point
that we probably can not conceive, as well as the habit of linking ideas with respect to a single
order of sensations, and to form judgments in relation to them alone, would produce a precision,
accuracy and range as far superior to We can imagine, but more on this point wish to extend the
conjecture is provided is clear that there is a limit here, which is the nature of the court and
its relationship with bodies. This body would be always limited to adjacent objects, to receive impressions
well-defined, and with respect to the distant, which could act on it, execute give the impression
that the nature of both consent, cold or heat, dryness or humidity, and even if you will,
a certain pressure to a greater or lesser degree, and as to many others, is impossible to imagine
that they had no action. For over a widening circle of this kind of feelings must always be
very small. It is also necessary to note that this perfectibility of touch as a result of his
isolation, his property is not exclusive but also extends to other senses, as being founded on the laws
of the organization, and in the generation of our ideas.

[63.] To understand the superiority in this part has the ear to the touch, enough to consider
1. º The ratio of distances, 2. º a variety of objects, 3. º the
rapid succession impressions, 4. º simultaneity, so vast in the ear,
and so limited in touch; 5.

No word relationships.

Ratio of distances. It is clear that at this point leads to touch the ear, that usually needs
the immediacy, this is not, and even his need for good appreciation the object, distance to
class well-off sound. How many and how many objects distant, do not tell us the ear, with respect
to which nothing can touch you tell us? The gallop of the horse that threatens hit, the noise
of the stream that can take us, the thunder rumbles and announces the storm, the roar of the
cannon that gives us news that a battle has begun, the sound of racing, the shouting, drums
and bells, which indicate the eruption of popular anger, loud music us reports the joy caused
by a betrothal, the concert dedicated to the pleasures of salon, the song that enchants us
with wistful memories, feelings of hope and of love, oh! warns us of suffering, crying that afflicts
us with the idea of ??misfortune; all this tells us the ear, above
all tell us that nothing can touch.

Variety of objects. Distant objects gives us news that the feel is of necessity very little variety,
and therefore the ideas that only it turns out, would be subject
to deplorable confusion, and to great uncertainty.

The hearing on the contrary, reports of infinite very different objects, and executes it with precision
and accuracy.

Rapid succession of impressions. It is clear that this part has to
touch the ear incalculable superiority. This when seen by juxtaposition,
you need to go on objects and even different parts of oneself, whether
to receive various impressions: This requires a long time for small
numbers they are</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>