<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08295</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>8919</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24243</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Puede afirmarse sin temor de ser desmentidos que la elegancia y la belleza de La Habana se
habían dado cita aquella noche en la Sociedad Filarmónica. Porque allí estaba la marquesa de
Arcos, hija del famoso marqués Pedro Calvo, con Luisa, su hija mayor, entonces de quince años
de edad. Por ésta había improvisado Plácido aquellos versos que dicen:

      Andaba revoloteando
    En el ambiente exquisito,
    Muerto de sed un mosquito,
    Jugo de flores buscando;
    Llegó a tu boca, y pensando
    Que era una rosa o clavel,
    Introduciéndose en él,
    Porque allí el placer le encanta
    Murió en tu dulce garganta,
    Como en un vaso de miel.

Allí las hermanas Chacón, que merecieron por su hermosura figurar en el gran lienzo pintado
por Vermay[31] para perpetuar la memoria de la misa que se celebró en la inauguración del Templete
de la Plaza de Armas. Allí las Montalvo, de tipo teutónico, una de las cuales fue declarada
reina de la belleza, cuando la corrida de cañas el año anterior, en la antigua plaza de Toros
del Campo de Marte; allí la Arango, célebre por haber contribuido a la evasión del poeta Heredia,
y que después se casó con un Ayudante de campo del Capitán General Ricafort; allí las hermanas
Aceval, Venus de Milo en las formas, tan distinguidas por su talento como desdichadas por sus
pasiones; allí las hermanas Alcázar, modelos de perfección, así por la simetría de sus menudas
facciones, como por las rosas de sus mejillas y el color negro de sus cabellos; allí las Junco
y las Lamar, de Matanzas, conocidas bajo el poético vocativo de las Ninfas del Yumurí; allí
las tres hermanas de Gamboa, las cuales ya hemos tenido ocasión de describir; allí la Topete,
hija del Comandante general del Apostadero de La Habana, que más adelante inspiró a Palma su
inmortal «Quince de Agosto», allí la menor de las Gámez, Venus de Belvedere, cuyo cabello castaño,
ondulante y copioso, llevaba suelto sembrado de estrellas de oro; allí, en fin, entre otras
muchas que sería prolijo enumerar, Isabel Ilincheta, hija del que había sido asesor del Capitán
General Someruelos, quien poseía los rasgos principales del tipo severo y modesto celtíbero,
a que debía su origen.

Como modelos de varonil belleza, entre los jóvenes concurrentes al baile de la Sociedad aquella
noche, pudiera hacerse mención del Teniente coronel de Lanceros del Rey, Rafael de la Torre,
quien unos días después murió estrellado contra las ruedas de los quitrines en el Paseo, junto
a la estatua de Carlos III, víctima de la fogosidad de su caballo; Bernardo Echeverría y O'Gabán,
que en los días de gala gustaba vestir el uniforme de gentil-hombre de Cámara con entrada,
por cuanto podía lucir las bien hechas y rollizas piernas; Ramón Montalvo, en la flor de su
edad, bello como un inglés de la más pura sangre; José Gastón, el verdadero Apolo de Cuba;
Dionisio Mantilla, recién llegado de Francia, que venía hecho un cumplido parisiense; Diego
Duarte, el feliz campeón de las corridas de cañas celebradas el año anterior, con motivo de
las nupcias de Fernando VII con María Cristina de Nápoles; varios oficiales de la marina y
del ejército español en sus vistosos uniformes, más propios de una parada que de un baile particular.

También contribuyó al lustre de la fiesta la presencia de algunos jóvenes que empezaban a distinguirse
en el cultivo de las letras, a saber: Palma, que había sido uno de los competidores en la corrida
de cañas; Echeverría empleado en la Hacienda, que el año siguiente alcanzó el premio en el
concurso poético abierto por la Comisión de Literatura, con objeto de celebrar el nacimiento
de la Infanta de Castilla, Isabel de Borbón; Valdés Machuca, conocido por Desval en la república
de las letras; Policarpo Valdés, que se firmaba Polidoro; Anacleto Bermúdez, que solía publicar
versos bajo el nombre de Delicio; Manuel Garay y Heredia, que imprimía sus versos en La Aurora
de Matanzas; Vélez Herrera, el autor del romance cubano Elvira de Oquendo; Delio, el cantor
de las ruinas del Alhambra; Domingo André, joven abogado, elocuente y amable; Domingo del Monte,
que introdujo el romance cubano, de variados conocimientos y muy distinguido porte.

Diego Meneses, Francisco Solfa, Leonardo Gamboa y otros varios, que también se hallaban en
el baile, si se exceptúan el segundo que era dado a los estudios filosóficos, y el tercero
que entraba ya en la clase rica, no se hacían notables por su talento, aunque los tres solían
escribir en los periódicos literarios; y el último pasaba, además, por mozo de buen parecer
y varoniles formas. Los literatos, mejor dicho, los aficionados a las letras, sobre todo los
que cultivaban la poesía, empezaban a tener entrada con la gente que podía tenerse por noble
en Cuba, o que aspiraba, por su caudal, a la nobleza y alternaba con ella. Mostraban al menos
distinción por ellos algunas familias tituladas de La Habana y los atraían a sus fiestas y
reuniones, entre otras, por ejemplo, los condes de Fernandina, los de Casa Bayona, los de Casa
Peñalver, los marqueses de Montehermoso y los de Arco. Dichas fiestas y reuniones en los días
de pascuas de navidad se trasladaban a los lindísimos cafetales de San Antonio, de Alquízar,
de San Andrés y de la Artemisa, que pertenecían a la gente rica.

No se presentaron en los salones de la Sociedad nuestros amigos Gamboa, Meneses y Solfa, sino
hasta cerca de las once de la noche. Durante las primeras horas habían estado visitando los
bailes de la feria del Ángel, el de Farruco y el de Brito, sin olvidar la cuna de la gente
de color, en la calle del Empedrado, entre Compostela y Aguacate. En ninguno de esos sitios
habían tomado ellos parte activa, si se exceptúa el primero, quien al juego del monte perdió
en un instante las dos onzas de oro que aquella misma tarde le había metido su madre en el
bolsillo del chaleco. No conocía el valor del dinero, ni jugaba por amor a la ganancia, sino
por el placer de la excitación del momento; pero sucedió que los bailes no le prestaron atractivo
ninguno, desertados de las muchachas bonitas; que no logró ver a Cecilia Valdés en la ventana
de la casa, ni en la cuna, cosas todas que se conspiraron para ponerle de malísimo humor. Para
remate de desdichas, cuando perdidoso y disgustado volvía con sus amigos en busca del quitrín,
que había dejado apostado en la calle del Aguacate al abrigo de las altas paredes del convento
de Santa Catalina, descubrió que no estaba allí, ni fue posible encontrarle sino media hora
después y en punto opuesto y distante.

Por otra parte, preguntado el calesero sobre el motivo que le indujo a desobedecer una orden
terminante de su joven amo, dio al principio respuestas evasivas, y al fin, apretado, dijo
que un desconocido, medio cubierto el rostro con un pañuelo, le había forzado a abandonar el
puesto y fingir que se volvía a casa, valiéndose de amenazas terribles. No parecía creíble
el cuento: hubo empero que aceptarlo como bueno y verídico; lo que, si cabe, aumentó el mal
humor de Leonardo, porque en caso de ser cierta la relación del calesero, ¿quién podía ser
ese sujeto, ni qué interés tener en que el carruaje aguardase en una u otra esquina de la calle?
¿Por qué emplear amenazas? ¿Qué autoridad tenía para ello? Aponte no pudo decir si el desconocido
era militar o paisano, comisario de barrio o magistrado, hombre blanco o de color. Tal vez
era un inesperado y desconocido rival que de aquel modo se preparaba a disputarle el cariño
de Cecilia Valdés.

Corroboraba tan desagradable sospecha, el hecho de que ni ella, ni su amiga Nemesia se habían
presentado en parte alguna de la feria del Ángel. Además de eso, la circunstancia de no haber
abierto la ventana, aún cuando Gamboa hizo la señal convenida pasando la punta del bastón por
los pocos balaustres que aún le quedaban, casi no dejaba duda de que algo extraordinario había
ocurrido en el humilde y oscuro hogar.

Mas sea de esto lo que se fuere, que no hay tiempo de verificarlo ahora, Leonardo Gamboa entró
en el baile de la Filarmónica preocupado y de muy mal talante. Armada sin embargo la danza,
en la sala principal y el aposento del palacio, bastante espaciosos por cierto, según dice
el poeta:

      Una noche por fin: entre cristales
    La luz reverberaba en los salones;
    Y la sangre inflamaba con sus sones,
    La danza tropical;

no pudo nuestro héroe sustraerse a su arrobadora influencia. La orquesta, que dirigía el célebre
violinista Ulpiano, ocupaba el anchísimo corredor sobre la mano izquierda, como se sube de
la regia escalera de piedra oscura. Luego, a la derecha, estaba la puerta del salón, enfrente
de otra que daba sobre los más amplios balcones, que formaban los portales llamados del Rosario.
Dejados los sombreros y los bastones en manos de un lacayo negro, a la puerta de un cuarto
entresuelo que abría al descanso de la escalera de doble tramo, y tendiendo la vista por el
soberbio salón, que podía tener «la carrera de un caballo», si se nos permite la exageración,
descubrieron los estudiantes que las animadas parejas le llenaban de extremo a extremo. Recibían
los hombres de espalda, y las mujeres de frente, mientras esperaban su turno para hacer cedazo,
el aire fresco de la media noche, que entraba por las puertas y ventanas abiertas de par en par.

Como hemos dicho antes, allí se hallaba reunido lo más granado y florido de la juventud cubana
de ambos sexos, entregada, por el momento al menos, con alma y cuerpo a su diversión favorita.
Y a la luz deslumbrante de las arañas de cristal, en olas de una música tan plañidera como
voluptuosa, pues que procede del corazón de un pueblo esclavizado, al través de la nube sutil
de polvo que levantaban los bailarines con los pies, las mujeres parecían más hermosas, los
hombres más bizarros. ¿Podía, pues, entregarse el ánimo de la juventud a otros pensamientos
que los que le sugerían los halagadores objetos que tenía delante? No es posible.

Gamboa se ocupó, desde luego, en buscar compañera para tomar parte en el baile, aunque no le
gustaba mucho; pero Meneses, que rara vez bailaba, y Solfa, que no bailaba nunca, se quedaron
de espectadores en el medio del salón, observando el último, con sonrisa amarga, que mientras
aquella loca juventud gozaba a sus anchas de los placeres del momento, el más estúpido y brutal
de los reyes de España parecía contemplarla con aire de profundo desprecio desde el dorado
dosel donde se veía pintada su imagen odiosa.

Andando con algún trabajo entre las apiñadas filas de espectadores y bailarines, tropezó Gamboa
con la más joven de las señoritas Gámez, cuyo retrato hemos hecho arriba a vuela pluma, en
lo más empeñado de la danza. Por todo saludo, sin dejar de girar, como una sílfide, en brazos
de su pareja, le dijo ella antes con los ojos que con la lengua:--Ahí está Isabel.

--¿Bailando? preguntó el joven.

--¡Qué bailar! Esperando por Vd.

--¿Por mí? Qué descanso el suyo. Pues por un tris no vengo al baile esta noche.

En efecto, aquella señorita se hallaba a la sazón en toda apariencia comiendo pavo, según reza
la frase vulgar en Cuba, es decir, sentada a la izquierda, cerca de la puerta del aposento
entre una señora de mediana edad y el culto abogado Domingo André, con quien sostenía animada
conversación. No obstante su natural despreocupación, sintió Gamboa un arranque de celos que
le fue imposible reprimir, no ya porque estuviese de veras enamorado, sino porque el caballero
en cuya compañía la encontraba, era asaz galán y sabía insinuarse en el ánimo de las mujeres
discretas. De paso debemos decir, sin embargo, que el norte de las galanterías de André por
aquella época, se dirigían a otra beldad muy distinta de Isabel Ilincheta, la misma que perdió
por tímido y que ganó por osado el literato dominicano Domingo del Monte, si no estamos muy
equivocados, en la noche de que estamos hablando. Por lo que hace a Isabel, recibió a Leonardo
con una sonrisa adorable, lo cual, lejos de tranquilizarle, fue parte a causarle mayor desazón.
Cambiados los saludos de costumbre, pues la compañera de Isabel, madre de las Gámez, era amiga
del joven estudiante, lo mismo que André, en prueba de que no tenía nada de coqueta, tampoco
de vengativa, dijo muy risueña:

--Decía a este caballero poco hace, que tenía comprometida esta danza, y no me quiere creer.

--Es que Vd. no ha bailado ninguna todavía, que yo sepa, repuso André.

--Cierto que dos se han bailado solamente, replicó Isabel sin cortarse, pero hasta ahora que
se baila la tercera, no ha venido Vd. a invitarme.

--Lo que quiere decir en sustancia, continuó André, que he llegado en hora menguada. ¡Cómo
ha de ser!

--Esta señorita tiene razón, interpuso Leonardo repuesto de su embarazo. Por compromiso anterior,
en cualquier baile donde nos encontremos, me reserva ella la tercera danza. No he podido llegar,
pues, a mejor hora según veo. Por eso se dice que más vale llegar a tiempo que rondar un año.

--Ya, exclamó el galante abogado, el caso es que con las buenas mozas pocos somos los que llegamos
a tiempo.

André saludó y fue a formar coro a las dos hijas del potentado Aldama, de las cuales la menor,
de nombre Lola, cedía a muy pocas aquella noche la palma codiciada de la belleza. Entretanto
Leonardo e Isabel, cogidos por la mano, se metieron en las filas de la danza, no distante de
la cabecera, mediante el favor de amigos mutuos, que, aunque llegaron tarde, no les dejaron
incorporarse a la cola, como era de rigor. La cubana danza sin duda que se inventó para hacerse
la corte los enamorados. En sí el baile es muy sencillo, los movimientos cómodos y fáciles,
siendo su objeto primordial la aproximación de los sexos, en un país donde las costumbres moriscas
tienden a su separación; en una palabra, la comunión de las almas. Porque el caballero lleva
a la dama casi siempre como en vilo, pues que mientras con el brazo derecho la rodea el talle,
con la mano izquierda la comprime la suya blandamente. No es aquello bailar, puesto que el
cuerpo sigue meramente los compases; es mecerse como en sueños, al son de una música gemidora
y voluptuosa, es conversar íntimamente dos personas queridas, es acariciarse dos seres que
se atraen mutuamente, y que el tiempo, el espacio, el estado, la costumbre ha mantenido alejados.
El estilo es el hombre, ha dicho alguien oportunamente; el baile es un pueblo, decimos nosotros,
y no hay ninguno como la danza que pinte más al vivo el carácter, los hábitos, el estado social
y político de los cubanos, ni que esté en más armonía con el clima de la Isla.

La noche en cuestión lucía Isabel Ilincheta a maravilla las gracias naturales de que la había
dotado el cielo. Era alta, bien formada, esbelta, y vestía elegantemente, conque siendo muy
discreta y amable, está dicho que debía llamar la atención de la gente culta. Hasta la suave
palidez de su rostro, la expresión lánguida de sus claros ojos y finos labios, contribuía a
hacer atractiva a una joven que, por otra parte, no tenía nada de hermosa. Su encanto consistía
en su palabra y en sus modos. Entraba en la pubertad cuando perdió a su madre, y para educarla,
lo mismo que para libertarla de los peligros del mundo, su padre la puso al cuidado de las
religiosas Ursulinas, venidas de Nueva Orleans y establecidas en su convento de puerta de Tierra
desde principios de este siglo. Después de un pupilaje de más de cuatro años, en que recibió
una educación antes religiosa que erudita y completa, se retiró al campo, en el cafetal de
su padre, cerca de la población de Alquízar, junto con su hermana menor, Rosa y una tía, viuda
de un cirujano de marina, de nombre Bohorques. Este individuo había hecho varios viajes a la
costa de África en las expediciones despachadas por cuenta de la sociedad de Gamboa y Blanco.
Contrajo de esas resultas una enfermedad terrible, murió en la travesía y le arrojaron al agua,
cual otros muchos de los infelices salvajes a quienes había ayudado a plagiar de su nativo
suelo. En más de una ocasión fue la viuda, con tal motivo, el objeto de la munificencia de
don Cándido Gamboa. Leonardo la visitó en el cafetal de Alquízar, y no pudo menos de enamorarse
de la sobrina, cuya modestia y gracias realzaban su clara inteligencia y fina discreción.

No había nada de redondez femenil, y, por supuesto, ni de voluptuosidad, ya lo hemos indicado,
en las formas de Isabel. Y la razón era obvia: el ejercicio a caballo, su diversión favorita
en el campo; el nadar frecuentemente en el río de San Andrés y en el de San Juan de Contreras,
donde todos los años pasaba la temporada de baños; las caminatas casi diarias en el cafetal
de su padre y en los de los vecinos, su exposición frecuente a las intemperies por gusto y
por razón de su vida activa, habían robustecido y desarrollado su constitución física al punto
de hacerle perder las formas suaves y redondas de las jóvenes de su edad y estado. Para que
nada faltase al aire varonil y resuelto de su persona, debe añadirse que sombreaba su boca
expresiva un bozo oscuro y sedoso, al cual sólo faltaba una tonsura frecuente para convertirse
en bigote negro y poblado. Tras ese bozo asomaban a veces unos dientes blancos, chicos y parejos,
y he aquí lo que constituía la magia de la sonrisa de Isabel.

No debe extrañarse que, siendo Leonardo un tanto descreído y despegado, sintiese pasión por
una joven tal como la que acaba de describirse. Entraba él por las puertas doradas de la vida.
A pesar de sus connotaciones y de su riqueza, no había tenido aún trato con las mujeres de
su esfera y educación, ni había empezado a buscar en ellas tampoco la compañera futura de su
vida. La aspereza suya no era sino externa, estaba en sus maneras bruscas, porque allá en el
fondo de su pecho, como habrá ocasión de observarlo, había raudal inagotable de generosidad,
ternura de sentimientos. Dios, por dicha, no le había negado la capacidad de amar, sólo que
las mujeres con quienes hasta allí había tropezado, o habían cedido a la fogosidad de sus afectos,
a la intrepidez de sus pocos años, o a la influencia de su lluvia de oro. Ninguno de estos
móviles podía tener ascendiente en el ánimo de una joven rica, bien educada, modesta y virtuosa
como Isabel Ilincheta. Atraído Leonardo primero por sus prendas físicas, seducido después por
sus relevantes dotes morales, comprendió desde luego que para ganar su afecto fuerza era tocar
su corazón, hablar a su entendimiento. Por otra parte, aquella mujer que se presentaba a los
ojos de Leonardo bajo un nuevo aspecto, habitaba el trasunto del paraíso terrenal cuando la
vio por la primera vez.

Si podemos prescindir del esclavo y de sus padecimientos, que son, sin embargo, más llevaderos
en los cafetales, se convendrá en que Isabel, su hermana Rosa, su tía doña Juana, su padre
y criados, llevaban una vida de paz y quietud, lejos del bullicio de la ciudad, rodeados de
olorosas flores, de los cafetos y naranjos siempre verdes, de las airosas palmas, del clásico
plátano, embebecidos con el canto perenne de las aves y el susurro melancólico de la brisa
en los campos de Cuba. Hasta la estación de los aguinaldos y de los azahares, en que Leonardo
conoció a Isabel, contribuyó a rodearla de encanto a sus ojos y a despertar en su pecho algo
que no había sentido nunca a los 21 años de su vida: el amor.

CAPÍTULO IV

     Princesa.--Su nombre al menos,
     Rey.--Nunca, nunca, nunca.

        Sueños de amor y ambición.

El callejón de la Bomba, como el de San Juan de Dios, que parece ser su continuación, se compone
de dos cuadras. Es, si cabe, más estrecho, hondo y húmedo, aún cuando sus casas son en general
más amplias. En una de éstas, inmediato a la calle del Aguacate, vivía Nemesia Pimienta con
su hermano José Dolores, ocupando dos cuartos seguidos, cuyo mueblaje se reducía a un par de
sillas, un columpio, una mesita de pino y un catre de viento, que se abría de noche y se cerraba
de día, a fin de despejar el campo.

Anochecido ya, Nemesia salió de la sastrería de Uribe y se encaminó a paso menudo hacia el
barrio del Ángel. Prefirió para ello la calle del Aguacate, que si bien más solitaria y oscura,
por la ausencia de establecimientos públicos, conducía derecho a dos puntos en donde de paso
quería detenerse. Cuando llegó a las cuatro esquinas formadas por la calle de O'Reilly y la
traviesa que llevaba, se detuvo un breve rato, pensativa e indecisa. Miró primero atrás, luego
a su derecha, después adelante, fijando la mirada en la ventanilla de la casucha inmediata
a la taberna de la izquierda, aunque por estar en línea paralela a la observadora, sólo se
distinguían las molduras de los balaustres que sobresalían un poco del plano de la pared. Difícil
era, pues, saber si había o no persona asomada allí o a la puerta. En consecuencia, la mulata
se trasladó a la esquina de abajo y dio un silbido peculiar muy agudo, haciendo pasar el viento
con fuerza por entre los dientes del medio de la mandíbula superior.

Algunos segundos después vio asomar por los balaustres de la ventana un canto de la cortina
blanca; pero al acudir al reclamo, notó que descendía del terraplén del convento un caballero
a paso largo, que se dirigía derecho al punto objetivo de sus miradas. Estúvose a observar
lo que pasaba. ¿Quién sería ese sujeto? ¿Quién le aguardaba en aquella casa? Vestía de frac
oscuro, pantalón claro y sombrero de ala angosta y copa desproporcionadamente ancha, sobresaliéndole
por detrás el cuello blanco y recto de la camisa. No era joven, ni anciano, sino de mediana
edad. A pesar de la oscuridad, todo eso lo pudo notar Nemesia a la corta distancia a que se
encontraba, que no excedía de treinta pasos. Su porte, sus movimientos acompasados y firmes,
no podían confundirse con los de un mozalbete ni de un viejo.

Se dirigió, sin embargo, con aparente cautela al punto donde se veía el canto de la cortina
blanca, sostuvo un breve diálogo con la persona que se hallaba oculta detrás de sus pliegues,
y entonces, a paso largo siguió al abrigo de las altas paredes del convento, la vuelta de la
Punta. Nemesia le perdió bien pronto de vista en la oscuridad; pero no le quedó duda de que
le esperaba un carruaje a mediados de la cuadra, porque oyó distintamente el ruido de las ruedas
en las piedras de la calle, corriendo en sentido opuesto a aquél en que ella estaba, y favorable
al que seguía el desconocido.

Aguijada por la curiosidad, volvió la muchacha a silbar como lo había hecho antes; le contestaron
desde la ventanilla moviendo la cortina blanca, y acudió al punto; pero en vez de su querida
amiga Cecilia, sólo encontró a la abuela. ¿Cuál de las dos mujeres había recibido y hablado
con el caballero del frac oscuro y el sombrero de copa abultada? Nuevo motivo de curiosidad
y de mayor confusión.

--¡Ah! ¿Era Vd., Chepilla? exclamó Nemesia.

--Entra, le dijo ésta, pasando a la puerta y quitando con la punta del pie la media bala que
la aseguraba.

No se hizo de rogar la muchacha. Parecía seria y desazonada la abuela; y la nieta, sentada
en un rincón, con el traje flojo, el aspecto desaliñado, la cabeza doblada sobre el pecho,
los brazos extendidos y los dedos cruzados en la falda, era viva imagen del abatimiento y de
la desesperación.

--Entra, hija mía. Seas bienvenida, repitió Chepilla. Entra y siéntate; hazme el favor de sentarte,
añadió notando que la moza se mantenía en pie, como azorada y confusa.

--Ya es tarde y estoy de prisa, repuso ésta dejándose caer maquinalmente en la butaca de cuero
delante del nicho en que se veneraba la imagen de la Dolorosa.

Iba Chepilla a repetir la instancia, pero visto que la recién llegada se sentaba sin más demora,
se quedó parada entre ella y su nieta.

--Decía, agregó Nemesia a poco rato, que es tarde y venía de prisa. Fui a llevar unas costuras
al taller de señó Uribe, y me se ha hecho de noche. Porque resulta que Clarita su mujer es
muy conservadora, y después quiso que la ayudara a cerrar la saya de un túnico que está haciendo
para la Nochebuena chiquita.[32] José Dolores debe de estar esperándome. El salió del taller
mucho antes que yo, pues tenía que tocar en la salve del Santo Ángel Custodio. Por cierto que
ha habido mucha gente de fuste esta tarde en la sastrería, todos a buscar ropa para un baile
en la Filarmónica, y para las Pascuas de Navidad. A señó Uribe hay que hacerle el encargo con
tiempo. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10379</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>87848</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22062</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Can say without fear of contradiction that the elegance and beauty of Havana had met that night
at the Philharmonic Society. Because there was the Marchioness of Arcos, daughter of the famous
Marquis de Pedro Calvo, Luisa, his eldest daughter, then fifteen years old. For this was improvised
Plácido those lines:

      
    He went fluttering The exquisite
    atmosphere Parched mosquitoes,
    Juice of flowers looking;
    Came to your mouth, and thinking
    That was a rose or carnation,
    Introduced in it, Because
    there loves pleasure Sweet died
    in your throat, Like a glass
    of honey.

Chacón sisters there, they deserved for their beauty appear on the large canvas painting by Vermay
[31] to perpetuate the memory of the mass celebrated at the opening of the Temple Plaza de
Armas. There the Montalvo, Teutonic type, one of which was declared beauty queen, when the rod
run last year, in the old Plaza de Toros Champ de Mars, where the Arango, famous for contributing
to the avoidance of the poet Heredia and then married a Captain Field Assistant General Ricafort;
there sisters Aceval, Venus de Milo in the forms, so distinguished for his talent as for his
unhappy passions Alcázar sisters there, models of perfection, and by the symmetry of their tiny
factions, as the roses in her cheeks and the black of her hair there the Junco and Lamar, of Matanzas,
known under the vocative poetry of the Nymphs of Yumurí; there Gamboa's three sisters, which
we have already had occasion to describe him up there Topete daughter of General Commander of
the Naval Station in Havana, which later inspired his Palma immortal "Fifteen of August," there's
less of Gamez, Venus Belvedere, whose brown hair, copious wavy, wore loose star-studded gold, there,
in order, inter many too numerous to list, Ilincheta Isabel, daughter of former adviser of
Captain Someruelos General, who had the main features of severe type, modest Celtiberian, it owed
its origin.

As models of manly beauty, among the young attendees of the dance company that night, could be mentioned
Sunspear Lieutenant Colonel Rey, Rafael de la Torre, who died a few days later crashed into
the wheels of the chitin in the Walk, along the statue of Carlos III, a victim of the fire of
his horse and O'Gavan Bernardo Echeverría, in the days of gala liked to wear the uniform of Chamber
gentleman with input insofar as it might look well-made and plump legs, Ramón Montalvo in
his prime age, beautiful as the pure English blood, Joseph Gaston, the true Apollo of Cuba;
Dionisio Mantilla, newly arrived from France, which had made a compliment Paris; Diego Duarte,
the happy winner of the runs of reeds held the previous year, due to the marriage of Ferdinand
Maria Cristina of Naples, several naval officers and Spanish army in their colorful uniforms,
more appropriate to a stop a particular dance.

Also contributing to the luster of the festival the presence of some young people who began to distinguish
in the cultivation of letters, namely: Palma, who had been one of the competitors in the race of
reeds used in the Finance Echeverría, who the following year achieved the award in poetry
contest launched by the Literature Committee, to celebrate the birth of the Infanta of Castile,
Isabella of Bourbon Valdés Machuca, known as helpless in the republic letters; Policarpo Valdes,
who was signed Polidoro, Anacleto Bermudez, who used to publish verses under the name of delight,
Manuel Garay y Heredia, which printed his poems in The Aurora Matanzas, Velez Herrera, the Cuban
romance author Elvira de Oquendo, Delio, the singer the ruins of the Alhambra, Domingo André,
a young lawyer, eloquent and polite, Domingo del Monte, Cuba introduced the romance of wide-ranging
expertise and very distinguished bearing.

Diego Meneses, Francisco Solfa, Leonardo Gamboa and several others who were also in dance,
with the exception of the second was given to philosophical studies, and the third and entering
into the wealthy class, were not made notable by his talent, although the three used writing
in the literary journals, and the last went further by good-looking boy and masculine forms.
The literati, or rather, fans of the lyrics, especially who cultivated poetry, began to have
entry to people who could be taken by noble in Cuba, or aspiring, for his wealth, nobility and
alternated with her. Showed at least distinction by including some titled families of Havana
and appealed to their parties and meetings, including, for example, the counts of Fernandina,
the Bayonne house, the house Peñalver, the Marquis of Montehermoso and Arc. These parties and
meetings in the days Christmas Easter moved the prettiest coffee in San Antonio, Alquízar, San
Andrés and Artemis, who belonged to the wealthy.

Were not in the halls of our friends Gamble Company, Meneses and Solfa but until about eleven
o'clock at night. During the early hours had been visiting Fair balls Angel, Farruco and de
Brito, not to mention the birthplace of people of color, Stonehouse Street, between Compostela
and Avocado. In none of these sites They had taken an active part, excepting the first, who
lost the game Mount in an instant the two ounces of gold that same evening he had put his
mother in the vest pocket. He knew the value of money or playing for the love of gain, but for
the sake of the excitement of the moment, but it happened that the dances did not pay attractive
none, defected to the pretty girls, who failed to see Cecilia Valdés in the window home, or in
the crib, all of which conspired to put it a very bad mood. To Unfortunate auction when losing
and became upset with his friends in search of chitin, I had left on the street bet Avocado away
from the high walls of the convent Santa Catalina, he discovered that was not there, nor was it
possible to find half an hour later and point opposite and distant.

Moreover, the coachman asked about the reason that led him to disobey an order strict his young
master, gave evasive answers to the top, and finally, tight, said a stranger, half covered
his face with a handkerchief, he had been forced to leave position and pretend to be returned
home, using dire threats. It did not seem credible the story: There was, however, that accept
as good and true, what, if anything, increased bad Leonardo humor, because if true the relationship
of the coachman, who could be this guy, or what have interest in the carriage wait in one
or another corner of the street? Why use threats? What had authority to do so? Aponte could not
say whether the unknown was military or civilian, district commissioner or magistrate, a white man
or colored. Maybe was an unexpected and unknown rival in that way was preparing to dispute
the love Cecilia Valdés.

Corroborated unpleasant suspicion that neither she nor her friend had Nemesia presented in any
part of the show Angel. Besides that, the fact of not having open the window, even when Gamboa
was the agreed signal from the tip of the cane for few balusters that still had almost left no
doubt that something extraordinary had occurred in humble, dark home.

But this is what it may, there is no time to check now, Leonardo Gamboa entered the dance of the
Philharmonic worried and very bad mood. Navy, however, the dance, in the main hall of the palace
and the room quite spacious by the way, says the poet

      One night last, between crystals Light
    shimmered in the classroom; And the
    blood inflamed his sones, Tropical dance;

our
    hero could not avoid its overpowering influence.

The orchestra, directed by the famous Ulpiano violinist, held the very wide corridor on the left
hand as she climbs the the royal dark stone staircase. Then, right, was the door of the room,
opposite another that was about the most spacious balconies, which were called the gates of the
Rosary. Left hats and canes in the hands of a black servant at the door of a room mezzanine open
the rest of the double-leg ladder, and tending the hearing by the magnificent hall, which
could have "a horse race," if we are allowed to exaggerate, students discovered that they filled
animated couples end to end. Received back men and women face as they waited their turn to sieve
the fresh air of midnight, coming through the doors and windows wide open.

As we said before, there were assembled the cream and flower of Cuban
Youth of both sexes, delivered, for the moment at least, with soul
and body to your favorite.

And in the glare of the chandeliers, in waves of music as plaintive as voluptuous, because it
comes from the heart of an enslaved people, the subtle through the cloud of dust raised by the
dancers with their feet, women seemed more beautiful, the gallant men. Could he therefore
be given the encouragement of youth to other thoughts he suggested that the flattering objects
before him? It is not possible.

Gamboa took, of course, in seeking partner to take part in the dance,
but not liked, but Meneses, who rarely danced, and Solfa, who never
danced, they were viewers in the middle of the room, watching the
last, with a bitter smile, that while that crazy youth at home enjoyed
the pleasures of the moment, the most stupid and brutal of the kings
of Spain seemed to contemplate with an air of utter contempt from
gold canopy where they saw his picture painted hateful.

Walking with some difficulty between the crowded rows of spectators and dancers, stumbled Gamboa
with the youngest of the girls Gamez, whose portrait we made up pen flies in as committed to dance.
In all regards, while pivoting as a sylph in arms your partner, "she said before the eyes
than the tongue: - Here is Isabel.

- Dancing? asked the young man.

- What dance! Waiting for you

- Why me? What break yours.

As a tris not come to the dance tonight.

In fact, that young lady was at that time in any appearance eating turkey, as reads vulgar
phrase in Cuba, ie, sitting to the left, near the door of the room between a middle-aged woman
and the cult lawyer Domingo André, who held animated conversation. Despite his carefree nature,
Gamboa felt a surge of jealousy it was impossible to suppress, not because they were really in
love, but because the gentleman in whose company he found, was handsome and knew Asaz insinuate
themselves into the minds of women discrete. In passing, we should say, however, that the northern
compliments by André that time, they went to another beauty very different from Isabel Ilincheta,
it lost by shy and daring won for the writer Dominican Domingo del Monte, if we're not wrong
on the night that we are talking about. As far as Elizabeth, Leonardo received with an adorable
smile, which, far from reassuring, was party to cause further distress. Changed the usual greetings,
as the companion of Elizabeth, mother of Gamez, was a friend the young student, like Andre, in
proof that there was nothing coquettish, not of vindictive, very cheerful said:

- Said that this gentleman does little, he had committed this dance, and I want to believe.

- Is that you have not danced any yet that I know, "said André.

- True, only two have danced, "said Isabel without cutting, but until now danced the third,
did not come to invite you.

- What it means in essence, continued
André, I've arrived in an unlucky hour.

How has to be!

- This lady is right, Leonardo brought parts of their pregnancy.

For previous commitment, in any dance where we are, I reserved it the third dance. I can not make,
Therefore, a better time as I see it.

So they say you better be on time to be around a year.

- I cried the gallant lawyer, the fact is that few of us good girls that we time.

André was greeted and joined the choir at Aldama potentate two daughters, of whom the youngest,
named Lola, was down to very few that night coveted palm of beauty. Meanwhile Leonardo and
Isabella, holding his hand, reached into the ranks of dance, not far from the head, through mutual
friends for that, but arrived late, left them no join the queue, as was de rigueur. The Cuban
dance without a doubt that was invented to be court lovers. The dance itself is very simple, comfortable
and easy movements, being its primary purpose the approximation of the sexes, in a country
where the Moorish customs tend to their separation, in short, the communion of souls. Because
the gentleman has the lady almost always on edge, so that while with his right arm around
her waist, with the left hand pressed hers softly. Is not that dance, as the body is merely the bars,
is rocking like a dream, to the sound of music gemidora and voluptuous, it is two people talking
intimately dear is stroking two beings attract each other, and that time, space, status, custom
has kept away.

The style is the man, someone said promptly, the dance is a people, we say, and there is none
like dance more alive to paint the character, habits, social status political and Cubans, or
you're more in harmony with the climate of the island

The night in question Ilincheta Isabel looked wonderfully natural graces that had endowed the sky.
She was tall, shapely, slender and elegantly dressed, So be very discreet and friendly, is said
to draw the attention of the educated. To smooth pallor of her face, languid expression of
his clear eyes and thin lips, contributed to make it attractive to a young man who, on the other
hand, there was nothing beautiful. His charm was in his word and his ways. Entered puberty when
she lost her mother, and to educate, as well as to free it of the dangers of the world, her
father placed in the care of Ursuline Sisters, coming from New Orleans and settled in their convent
door Earth since early this century. After a boarding more than four years, he received religious
education before scholarly, comprehensive, retired to the country, in the coffee plantation his
father, near the town of Alquízar, along with her younger sister and an aunt Rosa, widow a naval
surgeon, named Bohorques. This individual had made several trips to the coast of Africa in
shipments released on behalf of the Society of Gamboa and White. These result contracted a
terrible disease, died on the journey and thrown into the water, which many of the unhappy savages
who had helped to plagiarizing from his native soil.

On more than one occasion was the widow, on this subject, the object of the bounty of Don Candido
Gamboa. Leonardo visited her in the coffee plantation Alquízar, and could not help falling in
love and niece, whose modesty and thanks enhanced her clear intelligence and fine discretion.

There
was nothing feminine roundness, and, of course, or pleasure, we have already mentioned, in
the forms of Isabel. And the reason was obvious: the pursuit on horseback, his favorite pastime
in the field, often swimming in the river of San Andres and San Juan de Contreras where all the
years spent bathing season, walks almost daily in the coffee his father and the neighbors,
their frequent exposure to the weather for fun and because of his active life, had strengthened
and developed his physique to the point to make him lose the soft, rounded forms of the young
men of his age and status. For lacked nothing manly and determined air of his person, should be added
that shaded his mouth expressive a dark mustache and silky, which
was only one common tonsure to become in black mustache and village.

Following this bozo sometimes sticking white teeth, young and even, and behold what was the
magic of the smile of Elizabeth.

No wonder that, being somewhat skeptical and Leonardo off, felt a passion for a young woman such
as the one just described. He came by the golden gates of life. Despite its connotations and
its wealth, had not yet had intercourse with women their area and education, and had begun to
look at them nor their future companion life. His roughness was only external, was in his brusque
manner, because there in the bottom of his chest, as you have occasion to observe, there were endless
stream of generosity tenderness of feeling. God, that, had not denied the ability to love,
only the women they had met up there, or had yielded to the impetuosity of his affections, at the
fearlessness of his few years, or the influence of his golden shower. None of these mobile could
have influence on the mind of a young rich, well educated, modest and virtuous as Isabel Ilincheta.
Leonardo attracted first by their physical clothes, seduced then by his outstanding moral qualities,
of course understood that to win her affection was playing strength your heart, speak to your
understanding.

Moreover, the woman who appeared to Leonardo's eyes in a new light, inhabited the transcript of
the earthly paradise where saw for the first time.

If we can dispense with the slave and of his sufferings, which are, however, more bearable in
coffee, it will agree that Elizabeth, her sister Rosa, his aunt Juana, his father and raised,
lived a life of peace and quiet away from the bustle of the city, surrounded by fragrant flowers,
the trees and evergreen orange, the graceful palms, the classic plantain, perennial astounded
with the singing of the birds and the rustle of the breeze melancholy
in the fields of Cuba.

Until the season of holiday bonuses and blossoms, in which Leonardo
Isabel met, contributed to surround her charm to your eyes and wake
up something in his chest that he had never felt at 21 years of his
life: love.

     
     

        CHAPTER IV

Princess .-- His name at least King .-- Never, never, never.

Dreams of love and ambition.

Pump Alley, such as San Juan de Dios, which seems to be its continuation,
is composed two blocks.

Is, if anything, more narrow, deep and moist, even when their houses are generally broader.
In one of these, immediately Avocado Street, lived with Pepper Nemesia his brother, Jose Dolores,
occupying two quarters in a row, unfurnished which was reduced to a pair of chairs, a swing,
a pine table and a cot of wind, which opened and closed at night day, to clear the field.

Dark and, Nemesia left the tailor shop and headed Uribe often step towards Angel neighborhood.
He preferred to do Avocado Street, which although more lonely and dark by the absence of public
facilities, driving right at two points where the step want to stop. When he reached the four corners
formed by the street and O'Reilly cross she wore, was arrested a short while, pensive and hesitant.
First looked back, then on your right, then forward again, staring at the window of the shack immediately
to the pub on the left, but to be in line parallel to the observer,
only distinguished balusters moldings protruding slightly from the
plane of the wall.

Difficult was therefore to know whether or not a person looking out there or the door. Consequently,
the mulatto moved to the bottom corner and gave a peculiar high-pitched whistle, passing wind
to force the teeth of the middle of the upper jaw.

A few seconds later he saw looming on the balustrade of the window curtain a song white, but when going
to claim, noted that the convent down the embankment a gentleman in stride, heading right to
the target point of your looks. Dwelt to observe what was happening. Who was that guy? Who's
waiting in the house? Dressed in tails dark, light trousers and narrow-brimmed hat and drink
disproportionately wide, protruding behind the white collar of his
shirt straight.

He was not young, nor old, but middle- age. Despite the darkness, all that I could see Nemesia
to the short distance to found, which did not exceed thirty feet. His stance, his rhythmic movements
and firm could not be mistaken for a youngster or old.

He went, however, with apparent caution to the point where you could see the edge of the curtain
white, held a brief conversation with the person who was hidden behind the folds, and then continued
to stride away from the high walls of the convent, around the Punta.

Nemesia he soon lost sight of in the dark, but he had no doubt that a carriage awaited him in the
middle of the block, because he heard distinctly the noise of wheels on the stones of the street,
running in the opposite direction to that in which it was, and favorable that was the unknown.

Goad
by curiosity, the girl returned to whistle as he had done before, they answered from the window
by moving the white curtain, and came to the point, but instead of
his beloved Cecilia friend, just found the grandmother.

Which of the two women had received and discussed the dark knight
coat and hat bulky?

New subject of curiosity and confusion.

- Ah! Was it you, Chepilla? Nemesia said.

- Come in, it said, turning to the door and remove the toe with the average bullet insurance.

No
request was made for the girl.

He seemed serious and upsetting the grandmother and granddaughter sitting in a corner, with the dress
loose, disheveled, her head bent over his chest, arms outstretched
and fingers crossed in her lap, was very picture of gloom and despair.

-
Come, my child.

You're welcome Chepilla repeated. Come in and sit down, do me the favor of sitting, added noting
that the girl was still standing, as bewildered and confused.

-
It's late and I'm in a hurry, "replied mechanically dropping it in
the leather chair front of the niche in which they worshiped the image
of the Dolorosa.

Chepilla would repeat the request, but saw that the newcomer would sit without further delay she
stood between her and her granddaughter.

- Said he added Nemesia a little while, it's late and went quickly. I went to take the seams
Sr. Uribe's studio, and I was done at night. It turns out that his wife is Clarita very conservative,
and then wanted to help her close the skirt of a garment that is doing little girl for Christmas
Eve. [32] José Dolores must be waiting for me. The workshop came long before me, because I had
to play in the salve of the Holy Guardian Angel. Indeed There have
been many people in the shaft this afternoon in the tailoring, all
to find clothes for a dance at the Philharmonic, and for the Christmas.
A Sr. Uribe must make the request to time</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>