<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>415885</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>20077</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Hacían cuentas, como si el buque fuese suyo. Mientras estaba en reparación
había podido tolerarse la conducta del capitán.

--Los ingleses pagaban--decía Tòni--. Pero ahora no paga nadie, el barco está sin ganar, y
gastamos todos los días... ¿qué es lo que gastamos?

Calculaban él y el cocinero detalladamente el costo del sostenimiento del vapor, asustándose
al llegar al total. Un día de su inmovilidad representaba más que lo que ganaban los dos hombres
en un mes.

--Esto no puede seguir--protestaba Tòni.

Su indignación le llevó varias veces á tierra, en busca del capitán. Temía hablarle, considerando
una falta de disciplina el ingerirse en la dirección del buque, é inventaba los más absurdos
pretextos para abordar á Ferragut.

Miró con antipatía al portero del albergo, porque siempre la contestaba que el capitán había
salido. Este individuo con aire de alcahuete debía tener gran culpa en la inmovilidad del vapor:
se lo avisaba el corazón.

Por no irse á las manos con él y porque no riese solapadamente al verle esperar horas y horas
en el vestíbulo, se apostaba en la calle, espiando las entradas y salidas da Ferragut.

Las tres veces que consiguió hablar con él obtuvo al mismo éxito. El capitán celebraba mucho
el verle, como si fuese un aparecido del pasado al que podía comunicar la alegría de su exuberante
felicidad.

Escuchaba á su segundo, alegrándose de que todo marchase bien en el buque. Y cuando Tòni, con
voz balbuciente, se atrevía á preguntarle la fecha de la partida, Ulises ocultaba sus vacilaciones
bajo un tono de prudencia. Estaba á la espera de un cargamento valiosísimo. Cuanto más aguardasen,
más dinero iban á ganar... Pero sus palabras no convencían á Tòni. Recordaba las protestas
de su capitán, quince días antes, por la falta de buena carga en Nápoles y su deseo de salir
sin pérdida de tiempo.

Al volver á bordo, el segundo buscaba á Caragòl, comentando ambos las transformaciones de su
jefe. Tòni lo había visto hecho otro hombre, con la barba recortada, vistiendo lo mejor de
su equipaje, delatando en el arreglo de su persona un esmero minucioso, una voluntad decidida
de agradar. EL rudo piloto hasta había creído percibir al hablarle cierto perfume femenil igual
al de la visitante rubia.

Esta noticia era la más inaudita para Caragòl.

--¡El capitán Ferragut perfumado!... ¡El capitán oliendo á... pulga!

Y elevaba los brazos, mientras sus ojos cegatos buscaban las botellas de caña y las alcuzas
de aceite para hacerlas testigos de su indignación.

Los dos hombres estaban acordes al apreciar la causa de sus tristezas. Ella era la culpable
de todo, ella la que iba á tener el buque encantado en este puerto, quién sabe hasta cuándo,
con su poder irresistible de bruja.

--¡Ah, las hembras!... El diablo va como un perro faldero detrás de sus enaguas... Son la podredumbre
de nuestra vida.

Y la iracunda castidad del cocinero seguía lanzando contra las mujeres injurias y maldiciones
iguales á las de los primeros padres de la Iglesia.

Una mañana, los tripulantes que limpiaban la cubierta hicieron pasar un grito de la proa á
la popa. «¡El capitán!» Lo veían aproximarse en un bote, y la voz se extendió por cámaras y
corredores, dando nueva fuerza á los brazos, animando los rostros soñolientos. El segundo salió
á la cubierta y Caragòl sacó la cabeza por la puerta de la cocina.

Desde su primera ojeada presintió Tòni que algo importante iba á ocurrir. El capitán tenía
un aire animoso y alegre. Al mismo tiempo vió en la exagerada amabilidad de su sonrisa un deseo
de seducir, de imponer dulcemente algo que consideraba de dudosa aceptación.

--Ya estarás contento--dijo Ferragut al darle la mano--. Pronto vamos á zarpar.

Entraron en el salón. Ulises miró su buque con cierta extrañeza, como si volviese á él después
de un largo viaje. Lo encontraba con aspecto diferente; surgían ante sus ojos detalles que
nunca habían atraído su atención.

Recapituló en una síntesis, que fué como un relámpago cerebral, todo lo que había ocurrido
en menos de dos semanas. Pudo darse cuenta por primera vez del gran cambio de su vida desde
que Freya había venido á buscarle en el vapor.

Se vió en su cuarto del hotel frente á ella, que iba vestida como un hombre y fumaba mirando
el golfo.

--Yo soy alemana y...

Iba á explicarse de pronto su vida misteriosa, hasta en los detalles menos comprensibles.

Ella, era alemana y servía á su país. La guerra moderna levanta las naciones en masa; no es,
como en otros siglos, un choque de exiguas minorías profesionales que tienen por oficio el
pelear. Todos los hombres vigorosos iban á los campos de batalla; los demás trabajaban en los
centros industriales convertidos en talleres de guerra. Y esta actividad general comprendía
también á las mujeres, que dedicaban al servicio de la patria su labor en fábricas y hospitales
ó su inteligencia más allá de las fronteras.

Ferragut, sorprendido por esta revelación brutal, quedó silencioso, y al fin se atrevió á formular
su pensamiento.

--Según eso, ¿tú eres una espía?...

Ella acogió con desprecio la palabra. Era un término anticuado que había perdido su primitiva
significación. Espías eran los que en otros tiempos, cuando sólo los soldados profesionales
tomaban parte en la guerra, se mezclaban voluntariamente ó por interés en las operaciones,
sorprendiendo los preparativos del enemigo. Ahora con la movilización en masa de los pueblos,
había desaparecido el antiguo espía de oficio, despreciable y villano, que arrostraba la muerte
por dinero. Sólo existían patriotas ganosos de trabajar por su país, unos con las armas en
la mano, otros valiéndose de la astucia ó explotando las cualidades de su sexo.

Ulises quedó desconcertado por esta teoría.

--¿Entonces, la doctora...?--volvió á preguntar, adivinando lo que podía ser la imponente dama.

Freya contestó con una expresión de entusiasmo y de respeto. Su amiga era una patriota ilustre,
una sabia que ponía todas sus facultades al servicio de su país. Ella la adoraba. Era su protectora:
la había salvado en los momentos más difíciles de su existencia.

--¿Y el conde?--siguió preguntando Ferragut.

Aquí la mujer hizo un gesto da reserva.

--También es un gran patriota... Pero no hablemos de él.

Había en sus palabras respeto y miedo. Se adivinaba su voluntad de no ocuparse de este altivo
personaje.

Un largo silencio. Freya, como si temiese los efectos de la meditación del capitán, la cortó
de pronto con su charla apasionada.

La doctora y ella habían venido de Roma á refugiarse en Nápoles, huyendo de las intrigas y
murmuraciones de la capital. Los italianos se peleaban entre ellos: unos eran partidarios de
la guerra, otros de la neutralidad. Ninguno quería ayudar á Alemania, su antigua aliada.

--¡Tanto que les hemos protegido!--exclamó--. ¡Raza, falsa é ingrata!...

Sus gestos y sus palabras evocaron en la memoria de Ulises la imagen de la doctora increpando
á la tierra italiana desde una ventanilla del vagón el primer día en que se hablaron.

Estaban las dos mujeres en Nápoles, entreteniendo su inútil espera con viajes á las poblaciones
cercanas, cuando encontraron al marino.

--Yo guardaba un buen recuerdo de ti--continuó Freya--. Adiviné desde el primer instante que
nuestra amistad iba á terminar como ha terminado...

Leyó en la mirada de él una pregunta.

--Sé lo que vas á decirme. Te extrañas de que te haya hecho esperar tanto, de que te hiciese
sufrir con mis caprichos... Es que te amaba y al mismo tiempo quería alejarte. Representabas
una atracción y un estorbo. Temí complicarte en mis asuntos... Además, yo necesito estar libre,
para dedicarme al cumplimiento de mi misión.

Hubo otra larga pausa. Los ojos de Freya se fijaron en los de su amante con una tenacidad escrutadora.
Quería sondear su pensamiento, darse cuenta de la madurez de su preparación, antes de arriesgar
el golpe decisivo. Su examen fué satisfactorio.

--Y ahora que me conoces--dijo con una lentitud dolorosa--, ¡márchate!... Tú no puedes quererme;
soy una espía como tú dices: un ser despreciable... Sé que no puedes seguir amándome después
de lo que te he revelado. Aléjate en tu buque, como los héroes de las leyendas; ya no nos veremos
más. Todo lo nuestro habrá sido un hermoso ensueño... Déjame sola. Ignoro qué suerte será la
mía, pero lo que me importa es tu tranquilidad.

Tenía los ojos llenos de lágrimas. Se dejó caer de bruces en el diván, ocultando el rostro
entre los brazos, mientras un hipo de llanto estremecía las adorables sinuosidades de su dorso.

Ulises, conmovido por este dolor, admiró al mismo tiempo la perspicacia de Freya, que adivinaba
todas sus ideas. La voz del buen consejo, aquella voz cuerda que hablaba en la mitad de su
cerebro siempre que el capitán se veía en un momento difícil, había empezado á gritar escandalizada
á las primeras revelaciones de esta mujer:

«Ferragut, ¡huye!... Estás metido en un mal paso. No te conviene el trato con tales gentes.
¿Qué tienes tú que ver con el país de esta aventurera? ¿Por qué arrostrar peligros por una
causa que nada te importa?... Lo que deseabas de ella ya lo tienes. ¡Sé egoísta, hijo mío!»

Pero la voz de su otro hemisferio mental, aquella voz fanfarrona y loca que le impulsaba á
embarcarse en los buques destinados al naufragio, á desafiar los peligros por el placer de
poner á prueba su vigor, también le dió consejos. Era villano abandonar á una mujer. Sólo un
miedoso podía hacerlo... ¡Tanto que parecía amarle esta alemana!...

Y con su exuberancia meridional, la abrazó y la levantó, apartando de su frente los bucles
de la cabellera, que se había deshecho, acariciándola como á una niña enferma, bebiendo sus
lágrimas con besos interminables.

¡No, no la abandonaría!... Es más: estaba dispuesto á defenderla de todos sus enemigos. El
no sabía quiénes eran estos enemigos; pero si necesitaba un hombre, allí le tenía á él...

En vano la voz cuerda le insultó mientras formulaba tales ofrecimientos. Se comprometía ciegamente;
tal vez esta aventura iba á ser la más terrible de su historia... Pero para acallar sus escrúpulos,
la otra voz gritaba: «Eres un caballero, y un caballero no abandona por miedo á una mujer horas
después de haber recibido el presente de su cuerpo. ¡Adelante, capitán!»

Una excusa de cobarde egoísmo emergió en su pensamiento, fabricado de una sola pieza. El era
español, era un neutral, que nada tenía que ver en la contienda del centro de Europa. Su segundo
le había hablado á veces de solidaridad de raza, de pueblos latinos, de la necesidad de acabar
con el militarismo, de hacer la guerra para que no hubiese más guerras... ¡Simplezas de lector
crédulo! El no era inglés ni francés. Tampoco era alemán; pero la mujer que él amaba lo era,
y no iba á abandonarla por unos antagonismos que le resultaban sin interés.

Freya no debía llorar. Su amante afirmó repetidas veces que deseaba vivir siempre á su lado,
que no pensaba abandonarla por lo que había dicho, y hasta empeñó su palabra de honor, como
prueba de que la ayudaría en todo lo que considerase posible y digno de él.

Así decidió atropelladamente de su destino el capitán Ulises Ferragut.

Cuando su amante le llevó otra vez á la casa de la doctora, fué recibido por ésta lo mismo
que si perteneciese á su familia. Ya no tenía por qué ocultar su nacionalidad. Freya le llamó
simplemente Frau Doktor. Y ella, con un entusiasmo verbal de profesora, acabó de catequizar
al marino, explicándole el derecho y la razón de su país al entrar en guerra con media Europa.

La pobre Alemania había tenido que defenderse. El kaiser era el hombre de la paz, á pesar de
que durante muchos años había preparado metódicamente una fuerza militar capaz de aplastar
á la humanidad entera. Todos le habían provocado, todos habían sido los primeros en agredirle.
Los insolentes franceses, mucho antes de la declaración de guerra, enviaban nubes de aeroplanos
sobre las ciudades alemanas, bombardeándolas.

Ferragut parpadeó de sorpresa. Esto era nuevo para él. Debía de haber ocurrido mientras estaba
en alta mar. El autoritarismo verboso de la doctora no le permitió duda alguna... Además, aquella
señora debía saber las cosas mejor que los que viven navegando.

Luego había surgido la provocación inglesa. Como un traidor de melodrama, el gobierno británico
venía preparando la guerra desde larga fecha, no queriendo presentarse hasta el último momento.
Y Alemania, amante de la paz, tenía que defenderse de este enemigo, el peor de todos.

--¡Dios castigará á Inglaterra!--afirmaba la doctora mirando á Ulises.

Y éste, para no defraudarla, en sus esperanzas, movía la cabeza galantemente... Por él podía
castigarla Dios.

Pero al expresarse de tal modo se sentía agitado por una nueva dualidad. Los ingleses habían
sido buenos camaradas; recordaba agradablemente sus navegaciones como oficial á bordo de buques
británicos. Al mismo tiempo le producía cierta irritación su poder creciente, invisible para
los hombres de tierra adentro, monstruoso para los que viven en el mar. Se les encontraba como
dominadores en todos los océanos ó sólidamente instalados en todas las costas estratégicas
y comerciales.

La doctora, como si adivinase la necesidad de atizar su odio contra el gran enemigo, apelaba
á los recuerdos históricos: Gibraltar robado por los ingleses; las piraterías de Drake; los
galeones de América apresados con metódica regularidad por las flotas británicas; los desembarcos
en las costas de España, que habían perturbado la vida de la Península en otros siglos. Inglaterra,
al iniciar su grandeza en el reinado de Elisabeth, era del tamaño de Bélgica. Si se había hecho
enorme, era á costa de los españoles y luego de Holanda, hasta dominar el mundo entero.

Y con tanta vehemencia hablaba la doctora en inglés da las maldades de Inglaterra contra España,
que el impresionable marino acabó por decir espontáneamente:

--¡Que Dios la castigue!...

Pero aquí reaparecía el navegante mediterráneo, el Ulises complicado y contradictorio. Se acordó
de pronto de las reparaciones de su buque, que debían ser indemnizadas por Inglaterra.

«¡Que Dios la castigue... pero que espere un poco!», murmuró en su pensamiento.

La imponente profesora se exasperaba al hablar de la tierra en que vivía.

--¡Mandolinistas! ¡Bandidos!--gritó, como siempre, contra los italianos.

Cuanto eran lo debían á Alemania. El emperador Guillermo había sido un padre para ellos. ¡Todo
el mundo sabía esto!... Y sin embargo, al estallar la guerra, se negaban á seguir á sus viejos
amigos. Ahora la diplomacia alemana debía trabajar, no para mantenerlos á su lado, sino para
impedir que se fuesen con los adversarios. Todos los días recibía noticias de Roma. Había esperanzas
de que Italia se mantuviese neutral. Pero ¿quién podía fiarse de la palabra de tales gentes?...
Y repetía sus insultos iracundos.

Se habituó el marino inmediatamente á esta casa, como si fuese la suya. Las contadas veces
que Freya se separaba de él, iba á buscarla en el salón de la imponente señora, que tomaba
con Ulises un aire de suegra bondadosa.

En varias de sus visitas se encontró con el conde. El taciturno personaje le tendía una mano,
guardando cierta distancia instintivamente. Ulises conocía ahora su verdadera nacionalidad,
y él no ignoraba esto; pero los dos continuaron la ficción del conde Kaledine, diplomático
ruso. Como todo lo de este hombre imponía respeto en la vivienda de la doctora, Ferragut, atento
á su egoísmo amoroso, no se permitía ninguna averiguación, acoplándose á las indicaciones de
las dos mujeres.

Nunca se había considerado tan feliz como en aquellos días. Experimentaba la monstruosa voluptuosidad
del que se halla sentado á la mesa en un comedor bien caldeado y ve por los cristales el mar
tempestuoso, con un buque que lucha contra las olas.

Los vendedores de periódicos pregonaban terribles batallas en el centro de Europa: ardían las
ciudades bajo el bombardeo, morían cada veinticuatro horas miles y miles de seres humanos...
Y él no leía nada, no quería saber nada. Continuaba su existencia como si el mundo viviese
en una felicidad paradisíaca, unas veces en espera de Freya, evocando en su memoria las esplendideces
de su cuerpo, los refinamientos y sensaciones nuevas que le procuraba su pasión; otras abrazado
á la realidad, con un arrobamiento que borraba y suprimía todo lo que no fuese ellos dos.

Algo, sin embargo, le sacó repentinamente de su egoísmo amoroso; algo que ensombrecía su gesto,
partía su frente con una arruga de preocupación y le había hecho ir á bordo.

Cuando quedó sentado en la gran cámara del buque, frente á su segundo, apoyó los codos en la
mesa y comenzó á chupar un grueso cigarro que acababa de encender.

--Vamos á salir muy pronto--repitió con visible preocupación--. Estarás contento, Tòni; creo
que estarás contento.

Tòni permaneció impasible. Esperaba algo más. El capitán, al iniciar un viaje, le decía siempre
el puerto de destino y la especialidad de la carga. Por eso, al darse cuenta de que Ferragut
no quería añadir nada, se atrevió á preguntar:

--¿Es á Barcelona adonde vamos?...

Vaciló Ulises, mirando hacia la puerta como si temiese ser escuchado. Luego avanzó el busto
hacia Tòni.

Se trataba de un viaje sin peligro alguno, pero que debía quedar en el misterio.

--Yo te lo cuento á ti porque tú sabes todas mis cosas, porque te considero como de mi familia.

El piloto no parecía emocionarse con esta muestra de confianza. Permaneció impasible, mientras
en su interior empezaban á despertar todas las inquietudes que le habían agitado en los días
anteriores.

Siguió hablando el capitán. Los tiempos eran de guerra, y debían aprovecharlos. Para los dos
no representaba una novedad transportar cargamentos de material militar. El había llevado una
vez desde Europa armas y municiones para una revolución de la América del Sur. Tòni le había
contado sus aventuras en el golfo de California mandando una pequeña goleta que servía de transporte
á los insurrectos de las provincias septentrionales alzados contra el gobierno de Méjico.

Pero el segundo, á la vez que movía la cabeza afirmativamente, le miraba con ojos interrogantes.
¿Qué iban á transportar en este viaje?...

--Tòni, no se trata de artillería ni de fusiles; tampoco de municiones... Es un trabajo corto
y bien pagado, que nos hará perder poco camino en nuestra vuelta á Barcelona.

Se detuvo en su confidencia, sintiendo una última vacilación, y al fin añadió bajando la voz:

--¡Los alemanes pagan!... Vamos á proveer de esencia de petróleo á los submarinos que tienen
en el Mediterráneo.

Contra lo que esperaba Ferragut, su segundo no hizo un gesto de sorpresa. Permaneció impasible,
como si esta noticia resultase sin sentido para él. Luego sonrió levemente, moviendo los hombros
lo mismo que si hubiese escuchado algo absurdo... ¿Acaso los alemanes tenían submarinos en
el Mediterráneo? ¿Podía una de estas máquinas navegantes, pequeñas y frágiles, hacer la larga
travesía desde el mar del Norte al estrecho de Gibraltar?

Estaba enterado de los grandes males que causaban los submarinos en las cercanías de Inglaterra,
pero en una zona reducida, en el limitado radio de acción de que eran capaces. El Mediterráneo,
afortunadamente para los buques mercantes, se hallaba á cubierto de sus traidoras asechanzas.

Ferragut le interrumpió con una vehemencia meridional. Este hombre, extremado en sus pasiones,
se expresaba ya como si la doctora hablase por su boca.

--Tú te refieres á los submarinos, Tòni, á los pequeños submarinos que existían al empezar
la guerra: cigarros de acero frágiles, que navegan mal á ras del agua y pueden abrirse al menor
choque... Pero ahora hay algo más: hay el sumergible, que es como un submarino resguardado
por un casco de barco, el cual puede marchar oculto entre dos aguas y al mismo tiempo puede
navegar sobre la superficie mejor que un torpedero... Tú no sabes de lo que son capaces los
alemanes. Son un gran pueblo, ¡el primero del mundo!...

Y con impulsiva exageración, insistió en proclamar la grandeza alemana y su espíritu inventivo,
como si le correspondiese una parte de esta gloria mecánica y destructora.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07947</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>600746</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17878</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Accounts were, as if the ship was theirs. While it was being repaired he could
tolerate the conduct of Captain.

- The British paid - said Toni -.

But now will not pay, the ship is without a win, and we spend every day ... What do we spend?

Calculated
and cook it thoroughly support the cost of steam, frightened to reach the total. A day of immobility
represented more than the amount earned by two men in a month.

-
This can not go - Toni protested.

His outrage led him to the ground several times, looking for the captain. Afraid to talk, considering
a lack of discipline to interfere in the direction of the ship, and
invented the most absurd Ferragut pretexts to address.

He looked harbor antipathy goalkeeper, because he always replied that
the captain had out.

This individual must have air pimp great fault in the stillness of steam: it warned the heart.

Not
to go to blows with him and why not wait to see him covertly riese
hours in the hall, they bet on the street, watching the entrances
and exits da Ferragut.

The three times I got to talk to him got the same success.

The captain held much see him as if he were a ghost of the past that could communicate the joy
of exuberant happiness.

Listened to his mate, glad that everything went well on the ship. And when Toni, faltering
voice, he dared ask the date of departure, Odysseus hid his hesitation in a tone of caution.
I was waiting for a precious cargo.

The more we wait, more money going to win ... But his words were not convincing to Toni. Protests
remembered their captain, a fortnight before, the lack of good charge in Naples and his desire
to leave without delay.

Returning on board, the second sought to Caragol, commenting both
the changes in their boss.

Toni had been done another man, with beard, wearing the best your
luggage, betraying in arranging his person a thorough dedication,
a strong will please.

The rough pilot was believed to perceive the true talk like women's
perfume Visitors to the blonde.

This news was most unlikely to Caragol.

- Captain Ferragut scented!

... Captain smelling of ... bug!

And raised arms, while their short-sighted eyes looking cane bottles and flasks oil to make them
witnesses of his indignation.

The two men were consistent in assessing the cause of his sadness. She was to blame all, she
who was delighted to have the ship in this port, who knows how long, with irresistible power of
a witch.

- Ah, the females! ... The devil is like a lap dog behind her skirts ... Are rot of our lives.

And the angry chef chastity against women still throwing insults and
curses equal to those of the early Fathers of the Church.

One morning the crew who cleaned the deck posing a cry from the bow
to the stern.

"Captain!" They saw a boat approaching, and the word spread and cameras corridors, giving
new force to the arms, encouraging the sleepy faces. The second came Caragol to the deck and
put his head out the kitchen door.

Since its first look at Tony sensed that something important was about
to happen.

The captain had a brave and cheerful air.

At the same time saw the kindness of her smile exaggerated desire
to seduce, to impose something gently considered of doubtful acceptance.

-
I'll be happy - Ferragut said to shake his hand -.

Soon we shall sail.

They entered the room. Ulysses watched his ship with some surprise, as if he were returned to
him after a long journey. I was looking different, arose before his eyes details had never
attracted attention.

Recapitulated in a synthesis that was like a lightning stroke, all that had occurred in less than two
weeks.

Could see for the first time of great change in her life since Freya
had come to pick you up steam.

Was seen in his hotel room in front of her, who was dressed as a man and smoked looking the
Gulf.

- I am German y. ..

Suddenly he would explain his mysterious life, even less comprehensible
detail.

She was German and served his country. Modern war nations mass rises, it is not, as in other centuries,
a small minority clash of professionals whose job is the fight.

All strong men went to the battlefields, the others working in the
industrial centers of war turned into workshops.

And this included general activity also to women who engaged in the
service of parental work in factories and hospitals or intelligence
beyond his borders.

Ferragut, surprised by this revelation brutal, fell silent, and finally
dared to ask their thinking.

- According to this, are you a spy?

...

She noted with disdain the word. It was an outdated term that had lost its original significance.
Spies were in other times, when only professional soldiers took part in the war, mingled voluntarily
or by interest in the operations, surprising the enemy's preparations.

Now with the mass mobilization of peoples, had gone the old spy craft,
despicable villain, who face death for money.

There were only patriots tiding of work for their country, some with weapons hand, other craft
using or exploiting the qualities of their sex.

Ulysses was taken aback by this theory.

- So, Dr. ...?-- again asked,
guessing what could be the awesome lady.

Freya said with an expression of enthusiasm and respect.

His friend was a distinguished patriot, wise to put all his faculties to the service of their
country. She adored her. It was his protector: had saved the most difficult moments of its existence.

-
And the Count? - Kept asking Ferragut.

Here the woman made a gesture given reservation.

- It is also a great patriot ... But enough about him.

There was respect and fear his words. It was evident desire not to deal with this arrogant character.

A
long silence. Freya, as if fearing the effects of meditation master, the cut suddenly with his
impassioned speech.

The doctor and she had come to Rome to take refuge in Naples, fleeing
from the intrigues and gossip of the capital.

The Italians were fighting among themselves: some were in favor of war, others of neutrality. No
one wanted to help Germany, its former ally.

- Both have protected them! - He said -.

Raza, false and ungrateful ...

His gestures and his words evoked the memory of Ulysses in the image
of Dr. scolding to the Italian land from a car window on the first
day he spoke.

Were the two women in Naples, entertaining his futile hopes to travel to the populations nearby,
where they found the ocean.

- I kept a good memory of you - continued Freya -. I guessed from the first moment our friendship
was going to end up as over ...

He read the look of him a question.

- I know what you're going to say. Strange that I made you wait so long, that made thee suffer with
my whims ... Is that I loved you while I wanted to get away. Posed, an attraction and a hindrance.
I feared in my affairs complicate ... Also, I need to be free to
devote to fulfilling my mission.

There was another long pause. Freya's eyes were fixed on her lover with a tenacity searching. I
wanted to probe his mind, realizing the maturity of its preparation, before risking the decisive
blow. His examination was satisfactory.

- And now that I know - he said with painful slowness - leave! ... You can not love me; I am
a spy as you say, a wretch ... I know you can not still love me after from what I have revealed.
Get away on your ship, like the heroes of legend, and we will not
more.

All we will have been a beautiful dream ... Leave me alone.

I do not know what fate will be the mine, but I care about is your peace of mind.

His eyes filled with tears. He fell face down on the couch, hiding his face between the arms
while crying hiccups shook the lovely curves of her back.

Odysseus, moved by the pain, while he admired the perspicacity of Freya, who guessed all your
ideas. The voice of good counsel, that voice spoke rope in the middle of Brain saw the captain
at a difficult time, had begun to scream shocked to the first revelations of this woman:

"Ferragut, run! ... You're in a bad way. You do not want the deal with such people. What hast thou
to do with the country of this adventure? Why face a hazard cause anything to you? ... What you wanted
it you have it. Be selfish, my son! "

But the voice of his other mental hemisphere, and that swaggering voice that drove him to mad loaded
on ships destined for shipwreck, to defy the dangers for the sake
of test their effect, also gave advice.

Villain was a woman to leave. Only afraid he could do ... Both seemed
to love the German!

...

And with its lush southern hugged her and lifted her up, away from his forehead loops of the
hair, which had been destroyed, caressing her like a sick child, drinking their tears with endless
kisses.

No, do not leave! ... What is more, he was ready to defend it against all enemies. The I did
not know who these enemies, but if I needed a man, there he was to
him ...

In vain the voice rope insulted him while formulating such
offers.

Undertook blindly maybe this adventure was going to be the most terrible in its history ...
But to allay her scruples, another voice shouted: "You are a gentleman and a gentleman does
not leave for fear of a woman hours after receiving this from your body. Go ahead, captain! "

A selfish coward excuse emerged in his thinking, made in one piece. He was Spanish, was a neutral,
that had nothing to do with the war in Central Europe.

His second had spoken at times of solidarity of race, Latino people, the need to end to militarism,
to make war so that there are no more wars ... Simplicity Reader
gullible!

He was not English or French.

Nor was German, but the woman he loved was, and was not going to abandon it for some antagonism
that seemed uninteresting.

Freya should not mourn.

Her lover said repeatedly that he wanted to live always at his side,
was not going to abandon it for what he had said, and even gave his
word of honor as evidence that would help in everything we consider
it possible and worth it.

So its fate decided hastily Captain Ulysses Ferragut.

When her lover took him back to the house of Dr., was received by it as well that if it belonged
to his family.

And had no reason to hide their nationality. Freya called simply Frau Doktor. And she, with
teacher verbal enthusiasm, finished catechize the ocean, explaining the law and reason of
his country to go to war with half Europe.

Poor Germany had to defend himself. The Kaiser was a man of peace, notwithstanding for many
years had methodically prepared a military force capable of crushing to humanity. All had caused,
all had been first to attack him. The arrogant French, long before declaring war, sent clouds
of airplanes on German cities bombed.

Ferragut blinked in surprise. This was new to him.

Must have occurred while at sea. Verbose authoritarianism of Dr no doubt allowed ... Besides,
that lady should know things better than those living at sea.

Then had come the English challenge. As a traitor of melodrama, the British government preparing for war
came from a long time, not wanting to appear until the last minute. And Germany, lover of peace,
had to defend against this enemy, the worst.

- God punish England! "- Said the doctor, looking at Ulysses.

And that, not disappoint, his hopes, he shook his head gallantly ...
For he could punishing God.

But to express felt so agitated by a new duality. The English had been good comrades pleasantly
recalled his voyages as an officer on board ship British. While some irritation caused him increasing
his power, invisible to men inland, monstrous for those living at
sea.

They were found as dominant in all the oceans or solidly installed
in all strategic costs and commercial.

The doctor, as if divining the need to stoke their hatred against
the great enemy, appealed to historical memories: Gibraltar won by
the English, the piracy of Drake, the American galleons with methodical
regularity captured by the British fleet, the landings off the coast
of Spain, which had disrupted the lives of the peninsula in other
centuries.

England at the beginning of his greatness in the reign of Elizabeth,
was the size of Belgium.

If you had done large, was at the expense of the Spanish and Dutch, to dominate the world.

And so vehemently spoke the English doctor gives the evils of England
against Spain the ocean impressionable spontaneously ended by saying:

-
May God punish!

...

But here the navigator reappeared Mediterranean, Ulises complicated and contradictory. It was
agreed Suddenly the repairs of his ship, which should be compensated for England.

"May God punish ... but wait a bit! "he muttered in his thinking.

The imposing teacher was exasperated when talking about the land they lived.

- Mandolinists! Bandits! - Shouted, as always, against the Italians.

How much were they owed to Germany.

Emperor William had been a father to them. All everyone knew this! ... And yet, at the outbreak
of war, refused to follow their old friends. Now German diplomacy should work, not to keep his side,
but for were to prevent adversaries. Every day he received news from Rome. There was hope
to keep Italy neutral. But who could trust the word of such people? ... And he repeated his angry
insults.

The ocean immediately got used to this house, as if it were theirs. The few times Freya was separated
from him, was going to look in the hall of the imposing lady, who
took Ulises air with a gentle mother.

In several of his visits he met the Count. The taciturn character handed him a hand instinctively
keep a certain distance. Ulysses knew now his true nationality and he did not know this, but the
two continued the fiction of Count Kaledine, diplomat Russian. Like everything about this
man commanded respect in the house of Dr., Ferragut, attentive his selfish love, not allow
any investigation, links to instructions the two women.

He had never so happy as in those days. Experienced the monstrous pleasure which is sitting at table
in a well-heated room and go to sea crystals stormy, with a ship
against the waves. 

Newsboys hawked the terrible battles in central
Europe were burning cities under bombardment, thousands died every
twenty four hours and thousands of human beings ... And he did not
read anything, do not want to know. Continued its existence as if
the world lived happiness in a paradise, sometimes waiting for Freya,
evoking his memory esplendideces your body, refinements and new sensations
that he tried his passion, others embraced to reality, with a rapture
that erased and deleted everything that was not two of them.

Something,
however, he suddenly pulled his selfishness love, something that overshadowed
his gesture, started his forehead with a wrinkle of concern and made
him go on board.

When he sat in the great chamber of the vessel,
against his mate, his elbows on the table and began to suck on a fat
cigar he had just lit.

- We shall go very soon - repeated with obvious
concern -. You'll be glad, Toni, I think you'll be happy.

Toni was
unmoved. I expected something more. The captain, a journey, he always
said the destination port and the specialty of the load. So, realizing
that Ferragut would not add anything, ventured to ask:

- Is it where
we're going to Barcelona? ...

Ulysses hesitated, looking toward the
door as if fearing to be heard. Then he saw the bust to Toni.

It
was a journey without danger, but that it should be a mystery.

-
I'll tell it to you because you know all my stuff, because I feel
like my family.

The pilot did not seem excited about this show of
confidence. Impassive, while inside were beginning to awaken all the
concerns that had been agitated in the days above.

He kept talking
about the captain. Were times of war, and should use them. For both
not a novelty carrying shipments of military equipment. He had led
a time in Europe arms and ammunition for a revolution in South America.
Toni had told his adventures in the Gulf of California by sending
a small schooner that served as transport to the insurgents in the
northern provinces rose up against the government of Mexico.

But
the second, at the time she moved her head yes, him with questioning
eyes. What were they going to carry on this trip? ...

- Toni, it's
not artillery or rifles, nor of ammunition ... It is a short work
and well paid, we will lose little way in our return to Barcelona.

He
stopped in his confidence, feeling one last hesitation, and finally
said, lowering his voice:

- The Germans paid! ... Let us provide
essential oil to the submarines have in the Mediterranean.

Contrary
to expected Ferragut, his second did not make a gesture of surprise.
Impassive, as if this news was meaningless to him. Then he smiled
slightly, shaking his shoulders the same as if he had heard something
absurd ... Did the Germans had submarines the Mediterranean? Could
one of these machines sailors, small and fragile, making long crossing
from the North Sea to the Strait of Gibraltar?

Was aware of the great
evils which caused the submarine near England but in a small area
in the limited range that they were capable. The Mediterranean Fortunately
for merchant ships, was to shed its treacherous wiles.

Ferragut interrupted
him with a vehemence south. This man, extreme in their passions, expressed
as the doctor spoke as if his mouth.

- You're referring to the submarine,
Toni, to the small submarine that existed at the start war: steel
cigar fragile, plying evil to separate water and can be opened to
retail Shock ... But now there's more: there is the sub, which is
guarded like a submarine by a ship's hull, which may go blind in midwater
and at the same time can navigate on the surface better than a shortstop
... You do not know what they are capable German. They are a great
people, the world's first! ...

And with impulsive exaggeration, insisted
glorifying German and inventiveness, as if a share of this glory mechanical
and destructive</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>