<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10990</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>525993</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18000</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Mientras leía estos párrafos, que ya le eran
familiares, su pensamiento trabajaba aparte a impulsos de la alegría. ¡El buen amigo Pablo!
¡Y qué a tiempo llegaban sus consejos!... Le sacaba de Ibiza en el instante más oportuno, cuando
se veía en guerra abierta con todas aquellas gentes rudas, que deseaban la muerte del forastero.
No se equivocaba el capitán. ¿Qué hacía allí, como un Robinsón, que ni siquiera podía disfrutar
la placidez de la soledad?... Valls, oportuno como siempre, le libraba del peligro.

Su vida de horas antes, cuando aún no había recibido la carta, parecíale absurda y ridícula..
Ahora era otro hombre. Sonreía con lástima y vergüenza de aquel loco que el día anterior, llevando
la escopeta al hombro, había emprendido el camino de la montaña para buscar a un antiguo presidiario,
retándolo a bárbaro combate en la soledad del bosque. ¡Como si toda la vida del planeta estuviese
concentrada en la pequeña isla y hubiera que matar para poder existir en ella!... ¡Como si
no hubiese vida ni civilización más allá de la sábana azul que rodeaba a este pedazo de tierra,
con su grupo humano de almas primitivas, petrificadas en las costumbres de otros siglos! Ésta
era la última noche de su existencia salvaje. Al día siguiente, todo lo ocurrido no sería más
que una aglomeración de recuerdos interesantes, con cuyo relato podría entretener a sus amigos
del Borne.

Cortó Febrer repentinamente sus pensamientos, separando los ojos del papel. Al encontrar su
mirada una mitad de la habitación en la sombra y otra mitad en una luz rojiza que hacía temblar
los objetos, pareció volver del lejano viaje al que le arrastraba su imaginación. Aún vivía
en la torre del Pirata; aún estaba en medio de lobregueces, de una soledad poblada por los
rumores de la Naturaleza, en el interior de un cubo de piedra cuyas paredes parecían sudar
lóbrego misterio.

Algo había sonado fuera de la torre: un grito, un aullido, distinto del de la otra noche, más
sofocado, más lejano. Jaime tuvo la sensación de que este grito venía de muy cerca, de que
tal vez lo lanzaba alguien oculto en los grupos de tamariscos.

Concentró su atención, y al poco rato el aullido volvió a sonar. Era el mismo aucamiento de
la otra noche, pero sordo, quedo, ronco, como si el que lo lanzaba tuviese miedo de que el
grito se esparciese demasiado, colocando sus manos en torno a la boca para enviarlo con esta
bocina natural únicamente hacia la torre.

Pasada la primera sorpresa, rio silenciosamente, encogiendo los hombros. No pensaba moverse.
¿Qué le importaban ya estas costumbres primitivas, estos retos de payeses? «Aúlla, buen hombre;
grita hasta que te canses: estoy sordo.»

Y para distraer su atención volvió a leer la carta, complaciéndose en el saboreo de la larga
lista de acreedores, muchos de cuyos nombres evocaban visiones coléricas o grotescos recuerdos.

El aullido continuó sonando a largos intervalos, y cada vez que su ronca estridencia cortaba
el silencio, Febrer se estremecía de impaciencia y de cólera. «¡Cristo! ¿Iba a pasar así la
noche, desvelado por esta serenata amenazadora?...»

Pensó que tal vez el enemigo, oculto en la maleza, veía las rendijas de la puerta iluminadas
y esto le hacía persistir en sus provocaciones. Apagó la vela y se tendió en la cama, experimentando
una sensación de bienestar al verse en la obscuridad, con la espalda hundida en las crujientes
blanduras del jergón. Podía aullar horas y horas hasta perder la voz aquel bárbaro. Él no quería
moverse. ¿Qué le importaban sus insultos?... Y rio con una alegría de bienestar animal, en
la blandura de su lecho, mientras el otro enronquecía oculto tras los matorrales, con el arma
preparada y el ojo atento. ¡Qué chasco para el enemigo!...

Febrer casi se durmió arrullado por estos gritos de amenaza. Había colocado tras la puerta
la misma barricada de la noche anterior. Mientras sonasen los gritos tenía la certeza de que
ningún peligro le amenazaba. De pronto, se incorporó, repeliendo ese sopor que precede al sueño.
Ya no sonaban aullidos. Lo que le había desvelado era el misterio del silencio, más amenazador
e inquietante que las vociferaciones de la hostilidad.

Avanzando la cabeza, creyó percibir entre los rumores confusos y fundidos de la respiración
nocturna un roce, un leve crujir de madera, algo semejante al ligero peso de un gato trepando
de peldaño en peldaño por la escala de la torre, con largas pausas de inmovilidad.

Jaime buscó el revólver y aguardó con él en la diestra. El arma parecía temblar entre sus dedos.
Comenzaba a sentir la cólera del hombre fuerte que adivina junto a su puerta el rondar de un
enemigo.

La lenta ascensión se detuvo, tal vez en mitad de la escala, y tras largo silencio, oyó el
solitario una voz queda, una voz que sonaba sólo para él. Era la voz del Ferrer: la reconocía.
Le invitaba a salir; le llamaba cobarde, uniendo a este insulto otras injurias para la odiada
isla donde había nacido.

Con irreflexivo impulso, se levantó Jaime de la cama, sonando ruidosamente el jergón bajo el
hundimiento de sus rodillas. Al estar de pie, en la obscuridad, con el revólver en la mano,
volvió a tenerse lástima por este movimiento y a despreciar a su retador. ¿Por qué hacerle
caso? Debía volver a acostarse... Hubo una larga pausa, como si el enemigo, al escuchar los
crujimientos del jergón, esperase que el habitante de la torre fuera a salir de un momento
a otro. Pero transcurrió algún tiempo, y la voz ronca e injuriosa volvió a sonar en la calma
de la noche. Le llamaba cobarde otra vez; invitaba a salir al mallorquín. «Sal, hijo de...»

Febrer, ante este insulto, tembló, guardándose el revólver en la faja. ¡Su madre, su pobre
madre, pálida, enferma, dulce como una santa, resucitando con el más infamante de los insultos
en la boca de aquel presidiario!...

Anduvo instintivamente hacia la puerta, tropezando a los pocos pasos con la mesa y las sillas
amontonadas. No; la puerta no... Un rectángulo de luz brumosa y azul se marcó en el muro lóbrego.
Jaime acababa de abrir la ventana. El fulgor sideral iluminó débilmente la contracción de su
rostro, un rictus frío, desesperado, cruel, que le daba gran semejanza con el comendador don
Príamo y otros navegantes de guerra y destrucción, cuyos retratos se empolvaban en el palacio
de Mallorca.

Sentóse en el alféizar, echando las piernas fuera, y lentamente empezó a descender, tanteando
con los pies las oquedades del muro para evitar que rodasen piedras sueltas, denunciándole
con su estrépito.

Al tocar tierra sacó el revólver de la faja, y agachándose, casi de rodillas, con una mano
en el suelo, comenzó a seguir el contorno de la base de la torre. Sus pies se enredaron en
las raíces de los tamariscos que el viento había dejado al descubierto, y se hundían en la
arena como marañas de serpientes negras. Cada vez que un tropezón de éstos le hacía vacilar,
obligándole a rudos tirones para seguir adelante, cada vez que una piedra rodaba o crujía,
deteníase, conteniendo su respiración. Temblaba, no de miedo, sino de ansiedad y zozobra, con
la inquietud del cazador que teme llegar tarde. ¡Ah, si caía sobre el enemigo, si le pillaba
cerca de la puerta, lanzando a media voz sus mortales injurias!...

Arrastrándose como una bestia, casi a flor del suelo, llegó a ver el extremo inferior de su
escala, luego los peldaños superiores, y al fin la puerta negra en mitad del cubo de la torre,
que aparecía blanco bajo el fulgor de las estrellas. ¡Nadie! El enemigo había huido.

La sorpresa le hizo incorporarse, avizorando con inquietud la negra y ondulante mancha de matorrales
que se extendía ladera abajo. Este examen duró poco. Un culebreo rojo, una ondulación llameante
y breve, seguida de una nubecilla y de un trueno, salió de entre los tamariscos, a corta distancia
de él. Jaime creyó recibir en el pecho una piedra, un guijarro caliente que tal vez había hecho
saltar el estrépito de la detonación.

«¡No es nada!», pensó.

Pero al mismo tiempo viose en el suelo, sin saber cómo, tendido de espaldas.

«¡No es nada!», pensó otra vez.

Y revolviéndose instintivamente, dio la vuelta, quedando con el pecho en tierra, apoyado en
una mano y tendiendo la otra, que empuñaba el revólver. Sentíase fuerte, repetía en su interior
que aquello no era nada, pero el cuerpo se negó con súbita torpeza a obedecer su voluntad.
Parecía pegado al suelo por una dolorosa simpatía.

Vio agitarse los matorrales como movidos por una bestia obscura, cautelosa y maligna. Allí
estaba el enemigo. Primero avanzó la cabeza, luego el busto, al fin sacó las piernas de entre
el ramaje crujidor.

Febrer, con la rápida visión que acompaña al ahogado y al moribundo en sus últimos instantes,
visión en la que se concentran los fugitivos recuerdos de toda la vida anterior, pensó en su
juventud, cuando tiraba a la pistola en el jardín de Palma tendido en el suelo y fingiéndose
herido, como un ensayo de ilusorios encuentros. Por primera vez iba a servirle esta caprichosa
precaución.

Vio claramente el bulto negro del enemigo inmóvil ante el punto de mira de su revólver. Le
vio cada vez más turbio, más indeciso, como si la noche se obscureciese por momentos. Avanzaba
cautelosamente, también con un arma en la mano, sin duda para rematarlo. Entonces tiró del
gatillo una, y otra, y otra vez, creyendo que el arma no funcionaba, sin llegar a oír sus detonaciones,
diciéndose en su desesperación que el enemigo iba a caer sobre él, privado de defensa. Ya no
le veía. Una niebla blanca se extendió ante sus ojos; le zumbaron los oídos... Pero cuando
creía sentir cerca de él a su contrario, la niebla se deshizo, volvió a ver la luz tranquila
y azul de la noche, y a pocos pasos, tendido igualmente en el suelo, un cuerpo que se revolvía,
que se arqueaba, arañando la tierra, lanzando un ronquido angustioso, un hipo de muerte.

Jaime no pudo comprender este prodigio. ¿Realmente era él quien había tirado?...

Quiso levantarse, y sus manos, al palpar el suelo, chapotearon en un barro denso y caliente.
Se tocó el pecho, y también lo encontró mojado por algo tibio y espeso que chorreaba en hilillos
sutiles e incesantes. Intentó contraer las piernas para arrodillarse, y las piernas no le obedecieron.
Sólo entonces se convenció de que estaba herido.

Sus ojos perdieron la limpieza de su visión. Contempló doble la torre, luego triple, después
toda una cortina de cubos de piedra que se extendía por la costa hundiéndose mar adentro. Esparcióse
un gusto acre por su paladar y sus labios. Le pareció que bebía algo caliente y viscoso, pero
que lo bebía al revés, por un capricho del mecanismo de su vida, viniendo el extraño licor
a su paladar desde lo más recóndito de sus entrañas. El bulto negro que se revolvía entre ronquidos
a pocos pasos de él agrandábase cada vez que en sus contorsiones tocaba el suelo. Era ya una
bestia apocalíptica, un monstruo de la noche que al arquearse llegaba a las estrellas.

El ladrido de un perro y voces de personas disolvieron estas fantasmagorías de la soledad.
De la sombra surgieron luces.

--¡Don Chaume!¡Don Chaume!...

¿De quién era esta voz femenil? ¿Dónde la había oído?...

Vio bultos negros que se movían, que se inclinaban, llevando en las manos estrellas rojas.
Vio un hombre que retenía a otro más pequeño, y en la mano de este último un relámpago blanco,
tal vez un cuchillo, con el que pretendía rematar al monstruo pataleante.

No vio más. Sintió que unos brazos suaves, de fina epidermis y dulce calor, le cogían la cabeza.
Una voz, la misma de antes, trémula y llorosa, sonó en sus oídos:

--¡Don Chaume!¡Ay, don Chaume!...

Percibió en su boca un roce dulce, algo suave que le acariciaba sedosamente, y poco a poco
fue extremando su contacto hasta convertirse en un beso frenético, desesperado, rabioso de dolor.

El herido, antes de perder la vista, sonrió débilmente al reconocer junto a sus ojos unos ojos
lacrimosos de amor y de pena: los ojos de Margalida.

IV

Al verse Febrer en una pieza de Can Mallorquí, tendido en una cama alta--tal vez la cama de
Margalida--, fue dándose cuenta de lo ocurrido poco antes.

Había llegado por su pie a la alquería, apoyado en Pep y su hijo, sintiendo a sus espaldas
unas manos de simpático tacto que parecían temblar. Eran remembranzas vagas, imprecisas, rodeadas
de un nimbo de blanca niebla; algo semejante a la confusa memoria de hechos y palabras luego
de un día de embriaguez.

Recordaba que su frente había buscado con mortal pereza un apoyo en el hombro de Pep; que las
fuerzas le iban abandonando, como si la vida se escapase con el chorreo caliente y viscoso
que cosquilleaba a lo largo de su pecho y su espalda. Recordaba también que tras sus pasos
sonaban gemidos sordos, palabras entrecortadas implorando el auxilio de todos los poderes celestiales.
Y él, en medio de su debilidad, latentes las sienes por el zumbido cerebral que acompaña al
desvanecimiento, hacía esfuerzos para concentrar sus energías en las piernas, avanzando paso
tras paso, con el temor de quedarse para siempre en el camino. ¡Qué interminable la bajada
a Can Mallorquí! Había durado horas, había durado días: en su memoria obscura aparecía esta
marcha casi tan larga como toda su vida anterior.

Cuando brazos amigos le ayudaron a subir al lecho y a la luz de un candil fueron despojándolo
de sus ropas, experimentó Febrer una sensación de bienestar y descanso. ¡No levantarse más
de estas blanduras! ¡Permanecer en ellas para siempre!...

¡Sangre!... El rojo escandaloso de la sangre por todas partes: en la chaqueta y la camisa,
que cayeron como guiñapos al pie de la cama; en la blancura rígida de las gruesas sábanas;
en el cubo de agua que se iba coloreando al mojar Pep un trapo para lavar el busto del herido.
Cada prenda arrancada de su cuerpo esparcía en torno una menuda lluvia. Las ropas interiores
despegábanse de la carne con un tirón doloroso. La luz del candil, en su llamear vacilante,
sacaba de las sombras una eterna nota roja.

Las mujeres prorrumpían en lamentos. La madre de Margalida, olvidando toda prudencia, juntaba
las manos y elevaba los ojos con una expresión de terror. «¡Reina Santísima!...» Febrer, a
quien el descanso en la cama había devuelto la serenidad, extrañábase de estas exclamaciones.
Él se sentía bien: ¿por qué se alarmaban de tal modo las mujeres? Margalida, silenciosa, con
los ojos agrandados por el terror, iba de un lado a otro, revolviendo ropas, abriendo arcas,
con la precipitación del miedo, pero sin aturdirse al oír los gritos furiosos de su padre.

El buen Pep, ceñudo, con una palidez verdosa en su tez obscura, manejaba al herido al mismo
tiempo que daba órdenes. «¡Hilas! ¡muchas hilas!... ¡Silencio las hembras! ¿A qué tantos gritos
y lamentos?...» Lo que debía hacer su mujer era ir en busca de cierto pucherete que contenía
un ungüento maravilloso guardado a prevención desde los tiempos de su valeroso padre, un verro
temible habituado a las heridas.

Y cuando la madre, afligida por las órdenes furiosas, quería unirse a Margalida para buscar
el remedio, la reclamaba otra vez su marido junto al lecho. Debía sostener al señor: lo había
puesto de lado para examinar y lavar al mismo tiempo el pecho y la espalda. El pacífico Pep
había visto de mozo sucesos más estupendos que aquél, y entendía algo de heridas. Al borrar
las manchas de sangre con el trapo mojado, dejó al descubierto dos orificios en el busto de
don Jaime, uno en el pecho y otro en la espalda... Bueno: la bala le había atravesado el cuerpo;
no habría que extraerla, y esto llevaban adelantado.

Con sus manos rústicas, a las que pretendía infundir cierta delicadeza femenil, pugnaba por
formar unos tapones de hilas, intraduciéndolos en aquellos orificios de carne rota y sanguinolenta,
que seguían vomitando mansamente el rojo líquido. Margalida, frunciendo las cejas y desviando
la vista para no encontrarse con los ojos del herido, intervino, apartando a Pep. «¡Deje, padre!»;
tal vez ella sabría hacerlo mejor... Y Jaime creyó percibir en su carne viva, sensible, vibrante
por el cruel rasguño, una impresión de frescura, de dulce calma al hundirse en ella los tapones
manejados por los dedos de la muchacha.

Quedó Jaime inmóvil, sintiendo en la espalda y en el pecho los trapos amontonados por las dos
mujeres en su horror a la sangre.

El optimismo que le había animado al doblarse sus piernas y caer junto a la torre volvió a
reaparecer. Seguramente, aquello no era nada: una herida insignificante; sentíase mejor. Le
molestaba, como si fuese algo inoportuno, el gesto triste y silencioso de los que le rodeaban,
y sonrió para animarlos. Intentó hablar, pero el primer intento de palabra le produjo una gran
fatiga.

El payés le atajó con un gesto. «¡Quieto, don Jaime: debía permanecer inmóvil!» El médico iba
a llegar. Su hijo había montado en la mejor caballería de la casa, para traerlo de San José.

Y al ver a don Jaime con los ojos muy abiertos, persistiendo en su sonrisa animosa, Pep siguió
hablando para entretener al herido.

Estaba él durmiendo con la pesadez de un sueño inconmovible, cuando le despertaron las voces
y tirones de su mujer, los gritos de los atlots que corrían hacia la puerta queriendo salir.
Fuera de la alquería, por la parte de la torre, sonaban tiros. ¡Otro ataque al señor, lo mismo
que dos noches antes!... Pepet, al escuchar los últimos disparos, pareció alegrarse. Eran de
don Jaime: conocía el estampido de su revólver.

Pep había encendido el farol que le servía para salir al campo, su mujer cogió el candil, y
todos corrieron cuesta arriba hacia la torre, sin pensar en el peligro. El primero que encontraron
fue el Ferrer, moribundo, con la cabeza chorreando sangre, lanzando aullidos y retorciéndose
lo mismo que un demonio... Ya había acabado de penar. ¡Que Dios le acogiese en su misericordia!
Pep había tenido que ir a las manos con su hijo, rabioso y maligno como un mono, el cual, al
ver al moribundo, extrajo de su faja un gran cuchillo, pretendiendo rematarlo. ¿De dónde habría
sacado Pepet aquella arma? ¡El demonio son los muchachos! </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05529</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>297103</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16124</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> As I read these paragraphs, which were already
family, his mind worked apart impulses of joy. Good friend Paul! And what in time came his
advice! ... He drew from Ibiza in the most opportune moment, when looked at open war with all those
rude people who wanted the death of a stranger. The captain was not mistaken. What was there, as
Robinson, who could not even enjoy the tranquility of solitude? ... Valls, timely as always, fought
the danger.

His life of hours earlier when he had not received the letter, it seemed absurd and ridiculous .. Now
it was another man. Smiling with pity and shame that crazy that the day before, leading the shotgun over
his shoulder, had taken the path of the mountain to look for a former inmate, challenging him to
savage fighting in the lonely forest. As if all life on earth was concentrated on the small
island and had to kill to be in it! ... As if had no life or civilization beyond the blue sheet
surrounding this piece of land, with primitive human group soul, petrified in the customs of
other ages! This was the last night of wild life. The next day, everything that happened it would
not be than an agglomeration of interesting memories, with whose story could entertain your friends
Borne.

Febrer cut suddenly thought, separating the eyes from the paper. Having found her eyes half of the
room in shadow and half in a reddish light that shook objects seemed to come from the Far trip
that drew his imagination. Still alive in the Pirate's Tower, still standing in the midst
of gloom, one populated by lonely Rumors of Nature, within a block of stone walls seemed to
sweat murky mystery.

Something had blown off the tower: a scream, a howl, as distinct from
the other night, more smothered farthest.

Jaime had the feeling that this cry came from very close, that someone threw perhaps hidden
in groups of tamarisk.

He focused his attention, and soon the cry rang again.

It was the same aucamiento of the other night, but deaf, softly, hoarse, as if they were afraid
of throwing the cry from spreading too much, putting his hands around his mouth to send with this
natural horn only to the tower.

After the first surprise, laughed quietly, shrugging his shoulders.
I did not think to move.

What do you care about these customs and primitive peasants these challenges? "Howl, good man;
scream until you get tired, I am deaf. "

And to distract his attention he read the letter, delighting in the taste of the long list of
creditors, many of whose names evoke visions angry or grotesque memories.

The howling continued playing at long intervals, and each time he cut husky shrillness silence, Febrer
shook with impatience and anger. "Christ! Was she going to pass and the night, kept awake
by this serenade threatening ?...»

He thought that perhaps the enemy, hiding in the bushes, he saw the cracks in the door lit
and this made him persist in their provocations. Blew out the candle and lay in bed, experiencing
a sense of comfort at being in the dark, back deep in the crisp softness of the mattress. I could
scream for hours until he lost that great voice. He did not want move. What do you care about
your insults?

... And laughed with a joy of animal welfare, the softness of his bed, while the other hoarse
hidden behind the bushes, gun prepared and watchful eye. What a disappointment for the enemy!
...

Febrer almost fell asleep lulled by the cries of threat. Had placed behind the door the same
roadblock last night.

While the screams had sounded confident that no danger threatened him. Suddenly he sat up,
repelling the drowsiness that precedes sleep. No longer sounding howls. What he had revealed the
mystery of silence was more ominous and disturbing that the shouts of hostility.

Moving his head, thought he saw between the confused sounds of breathing and cast night-a touch,
a slight creak of wood, something like the light weight of a cat climbing from step to step
on the scale of the tower, with long intervals of immobility.

Jaime looked for the gun and waited with him in the right hand. The weapon seemed to tremble
in his fingers. Beginning to feel the wrath of the strong man who reads his door the prowl for
a enemy.

The slow ascent is stopped, maybe in the middle of the scale, and after a long silence, he heard
the solo voice is a voice that sounded just for him.

Ferrer was the voice of: the recognized. Invited him to leave, he was called a coward, joining
this insult other injuries to the hated island where he was born.

With thoughtless impulse, Jaime rose from the bed, sounding loudly under the mattress collapse
of his knees. When standing in the dark, revolver in hand, again be sorry for this movement and
despise his challenger.

Why do case? Should go back to bed ... There was a long pause, as if the enemy, to hear crujimientos
the mattress, it is expected that the inhabitant of the tower was out of a time to another.
But it was some time, and the hoarse voice and offensive was played
again in the quiet night.

I called him coward again, invited to leave the Spaniard. "Go, son of ...

Febrer, to this insult, trembled, keeping the gun in his belt. His mother, his poor mother,
pale, sick, sweet as a saint, rising with the most infamous of insults in the mouth of that
inmate! ...

Instinctively went to the door, stumbling a few steps to the table and chairs piles. No, the
door will not ... A rectangle of light misty blue wall marked in
dark.

Jaime had just opened the window. The outer glow dimly lit contraction of face, a cold sneer,
desperate, cruel, giving him a strong resemblance to the Commander Don Priam and other navigators
of war and destruction, whose portraits are powdered in the palace de Mallorca.

He sat on the sill, throwing his legs out, and slowly began to descend, feeling Foot the cavities
of the wall to prevent loose stones rodasen, denouncing with noise.

At touchdown pulled the revolver from his belt, and crouching, almost
on their knees, one hand on the ground, began to follow the contour
of the base of the tower.

His feet became entangled in the roots of the tamarisk trees that
the wind had laid bare, and sank in sand and tangles of black snakes.

Each time a trip of these made him hesitate, forcing a rude jerk
to move forward, each time a rolling stone or bay, he stopped, holding
his breath.

Trembling, not fear, but anxiety and distress, with Hunter's concerns
that he fears to be late.

Ah, if he fell on the enemy, if he catches near the door, throwing its deadly insults softly!
...

Crawling like a beast, almost on the surface of the soil, came to
see the bottom of its scale, then the upper echelons, and finally
the black door in the middle of the cube tower appearing white under
the glare of the stars.

No! The enemy had fled.

The surprise made him sit up, uneasily eyeing the black and slick
undulating bush extending down the slope.

This test was short. A wriggle red, a fiery wave and brief, followed by a cloud and thunder,
came out of the tamarisk, a short distance him. Jaime believed he received a stone chest, a
hot beach had perhaps skip the noise of the detonation.

"It's nothing," he thought.

But at the same time saw himself on the floor, not knowing how, on his back.

"It's nothing," he thought again.

And turning instinctively turned away, leaving his chest on the ground, supported by one hand
and holding out the other, wielding the gun. He felt strong, repeated inside that it was nothing,
but the body refused to sudden clumsiness to obey his will. It seemed
low to the ground by a painful sympathy.

He saw the bushes shake as if moved by a dark beast, cautious and evil. There was the enemy. First
moved the head, then the bust, finally pulled the legs from Crackler the branches.

Febrer, with quick overview that accompanies drowning and dying in their last moments vision
in which the fugitives are concentrated memories of previous life, he thought of his youth, when he
threw the gun in the garden of Palma lying on the ground and pretending injured, as a test of
deceptive encounters. For the first time was to serve this whimsical caution.

He clearly saw the black bulk of the enemy motionless at the sight of his gun. Le became increasingly
cloudy, more hesitant, as if the night is obscured by time.

Advanced cautiously, also with a gun in hand, undoubtedly for the kill. Then pulled trigger
one, and again and again, believing that the weapon did not work,
without ever hearing their detonations, saying in desperation that
the enemy would fall upon him, deprived of defense.

No I saw him.

A white mist spread before his eyes, ringing in the ears ... But
when feel close to him believed his opponent, the fog broke, he returned
to see the light quiet and blue of the night, and a few steps, also
lying on the ground, a body that is stirring, that arched, scratching
the earth, throwing a harrowing snoring, a hiccup of death.

Jaime could not understand this miracle. Really it was he who had
thrown?

...

Wanted to get up, and his hands, when touching the ground, splashing
in a hot and dense clay.

He touched his chest and found it wet with something warm and dripping in thick rivulets subtle
and relentless. He tried to get the legs to knees, and legs would
not obey him.

Only then was convinced he was injured.

His eyes lost their vision clearing.

Double watched the tower, then triple, then whole blocks of stone curtain that stretched along
the coast sank offshore. Esparcióse a pungent taste in your mouth
and lips.

He thought he was drinking something hot and sticky, but drink it upside down, by a quirk
of the mechanism of his life, coming from the strange liquor your palate from the depths of her womb.
The black lump which turned between snoring a few feet from him every time agrandábase in their
contortions touched the ground.

It was already a apocalyptic beast, a monster of the night came to bow to the stars.

A dog barking and voices of people dissolve the phantasmagoria of solitude. From the shadows
emerged lights.

- Don Chaume! Don Chaume! ...

Who was this female voice? Where had he heard? ...

He saw black shapes that were moving, who bowed, carrying in her hands red stars. He saw a man
who was holding a smaller one, and hand the latter a white flash, maybe a knife, to pre-finish
the monster pataleante.

Saw nothing. Arms felt soft, thin skin and sweet heat, took her head. A voice, the same as
before, shaking and crying, rang in his ears:

- Don Chaume! Oh, don Chaume! ...

He sensed in his mouth a sweet touch, something that was stroking silky smooth, and gradually
was exaggerating his contact into a kiss frantic, desperate, angry pain.

The wounded man, before losing his sight, he smiled weakly to recognize with eyes eyes tearful
love and grief: Margalida eyes.

IV

Finding himself in a piece Febrer Can Mallorquí, lying on a bunk bed - the bed may Margalida
- was realizing what had happened shortly before.

Reached by foot to the farm, supported by Pep and his son, feeling behind a nice touch hands
seemed to tremble. Memories were vague, imprecise, surrounded a halo of white mist, something
like the confused memory of facts and words after a day of drunkenness.

He remembered that his face had looked with mortal laziness support Pep's shoulder, that forces
were abandoning him, as if life is to escape the hot and sticky blast that tickled over his chest
and back.

Also recalled that in his footsteps groans sounded deaf, broken words imploring the aid of
all the heavenly powers. And he, in the midst of his weakness, latent cerebral temples by the buzz
that accompanies the fading, made efforts to concentrate its energies on the legs, moving step
by step, with the fear of being stuck on the road. What an endless fall a Can Mallorquí! Had lasted
for hours, had lasted days: in its report that appeared dark running almost as long as all his previous
life.

When arms friends helped him get on the bed and the candlelight were stripping their clothes,
Febrer experienced a feeling of wellbeing and relaxation.

Do not get up of these blandishments! Stay on them forever! ...

Blood! ... The shocking red blood everywhere: on the jacket and shirt, they fell like rags at the
foot of the bed in the whiteness of the thick rigid sheets; in the bucket of water that was coloring
the Pep wet cloth to wash the breast of the wounded.

Each garment torn from his body scattered around a tiny rain. Undergarments despegábanse of the
flesh with a painful jerk. Candlelight, as flickering flame pulled
out of the shadows an eternal red note.

The wife cried in mourning. Margalida's mother, forgetting all prudence, coupled raised hands
and eyes with an expression of terror. "Holy Queen !...» Febrer to whom bed rest had restored
calm, we missed these exclamations. He felt good, why are so alarmed women? Margalida, silent,
eyes wide with terror, went back and forth, stirring clothes, opening chests, with precipitation
of fear, but not stunned to hear the angry shouts of his father.

Good Pep, frowning, with a greenish pallor in his dark complexion, driving the injured to the
same while giving orders. "Hylas! Many lint! ... Females Silence! Why so many cries and laments
?...» What to do his wife was to go in search of a stew containing Saved wonderful ointment
for prevention from the time of his courageous father, a Verro accustomed to the terrible wounds.

And
when the mother, afflicted with raging orders, wanted to join to
find Margalida The remedy, again claimed her husband's bedside. Should
hold the lord had set aside to examine and clean both the chest and
back. The peaceful Pep boy had seen more great events than that, and
understood something of wounds. Clearing blood stains with a cloth
wet, exposed two holes in the bust Don Jaime, a chest and another
in the back ... Well, the bullet had passed through his body; would
not be removed, and this led advance.

With its rustic hands, which
sought to infuse some feminine delicacy, struggled form a lint plugs,
be translated into those holes torn flesh and bloody, who followed
meekly throwing the red liquid. Margalida, frowning and shifting the
view to avoid meeting the eyes of the wounded, intervened, pushing
Pep. "Stop, Father!"; maybe she would know it better ... And James
thought he saw in the raw, sensitive, vibrant by the cruel scratch,
an impression of freshness, sweet calm it will sink plugs handled
by the fingers of the girl.

Jaime remained motionless, feeling in
the back and chest rags piled by the two women in their horror of
blood.

The optimism that had encouraged him to bend his legs and
fall next to the tower again reappear. Surely it was nothing: a small
wound, he felt better. Le annoyed, as if something unfortunate, sad
and silent gestures of those around him, and smiled to encourage them.
He tried to speak, but the first attempt it was a big word fatigue.

The
peasant stopped him with a gesture. "Quiet, Don Jaime was to remain
still!" The doctor was to arrive. His son was riding the best horse
in the house, to bring to San Jose.

And to see Don Jaime with his
eyes wide open, persisting in his smile bouncy, Pep continued talking
to entertain the wounded.

Was he sleeping with the heaviness of an
unshakable dream when he was awakened by voices and pulls his wife,
the cries of atlots running to the door wanting out. Outside the farmhouse,
on the side of the tower shots rang. Another attack on Mr., as that
two nights before! ... Pepet, to hear the last shots, he seemed happy.
Were Don Jaime knew the roar of his gun.

Pep had lit the lantern
she used to take the field, his wife took the candle, and everyone
ran up the hill to the tower, without thinking of the danger. The
first found Ferrer was, dying, his head dripping blood, howling and
writhing the same as a demon ... And had just grieve. May God welcome
you in his mercy! Pep had to go to blows with his son, mad and evil
like a monkey, which, when see the dying, his belt pulled a large
knife, intending to finish him off. Where would Pepet taken that weapon?
The boys are the devil</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>