<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04252</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>169791</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>744</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Un oficial que mandaba en la primera batería subió a tomar órdenes, y antes de hablar cayó
muerto a los pies de su jefe; otro guardia marina que estaba a su lado cayó también mal herido,
y Uriarte quedó al fin enteramente solo en el alcázar, cubierto de muertos y heridos.

Ni aun entonces se apartó su vista de los barcos ingleses ni de los movimientos de nuestra
artillería; y el imponente aspecto del alcázar y toldilla, donde agonizaban sus amigos y subalternos,
no conmovió su pecho varonil ni quebrantó su enérgica resolución de sostener el fuego hasta
perecer. ¡Ah!, recordando yo después la serenidad y estoicismo de D. Francisco Javier Uriarte,
he podido comprender todo lo que nos cuentan de los heroicos capitanes de la antigüedad. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00804</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>310244</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>705</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

An officer who commanded the first battery up to take orders, and fell before speaking dead
at the feet of his head, another Marine guard standing at his side also fell badly wounded, and
Uriarte was finally entirely alone in the castle, covered with dead and wounded.

Even then withdrew his view of the British ships or the movements of our artillery, and the impressive
aspect of the quarterdeck and poop, where his friends and subordinates were dying, did not
touch his manly chest and broke his strong resolution to hold fire until perish. Ah, I remember
after the serenity and stoicism D. Francisco Javier Uriarte, I could
understand everything they tell us about the heroic masters of antiquity.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>