<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>58579</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16516</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Los ánimos estaban un poco abstraídos. Reinaba cierta inquietud
en la tertulia, motivada por la presencia del P. Gil, a quien ninguno de sus colegas, si se
exceptúa el P. Norberto, mostraba simpatía. La conversación fue rodando de uno en otro asunto,
todos de poca monta. En un momento de silencio, D. Juan Casanova, que tenía la cabeza inclinada
hacia un lado, sin duda por el excesivo peso del cerebro, la descargó algún tanto, diciendo
con su acostumbrada solemnidad:

--Eloisa, hoy he hallado a su hermano Álvaro en el paseo de la Atalaya. Llevaba un pantalón
de cuadros.

D.ª Eloisa suspiró, como siempre que se tocaba el punto de su hermano.

--Estos días ha estado un poco enfermo. Me lo ha dicho el criado--manifestó dirigiendo una
mirada tímida a la mesa donde jugaba su marido.

D. Martín y su cuñado hacía tiempo que no se relacionaban. Por el motivo baladí de un mueble
de la casa que aquél pretendía llevar a la suya, sin derecho alguno, rompieron de un modo violento.
D. Martín (¿cómo no?) puso la mano en la cara a su cuñado, y a más de esto le desafió. Desde
entonces, absoluta separación entre ambos. D. Álvaro vivía en su enorme casa, enteramente solo,
y D. Martín en la suya con su esposa. Ésta, de vez en cuando, a escondidas de don Martín, iba
a visitar a su hermano.

--No parece que goza de buena salud--dijo el P. Gil, a quien sin saber por qué interesaba aquel
hombre.

--¡Oh! Sumamente enfermizo y delicado. Sólo cuidándose mucho puede ir viviendo.

Los clérigos, como siempre que se trataba de Montesinos en presencia de su hermana, guardaban
un silencio sombrío, con la cara larga y enfoscada. Si no estuviera ella, de seguro hubieran
soltado alguna frase de indignación o algún sarcasmo contra aquel impío, que tenía escandalizada
a la villa con sus opiniones y con su conducta. A duras penas respetaban el lazo estrecho de
familia.

Hubo un silencio lúgubre, porque las damas, comprendiendo lo que pasaba en lo interior de sus
directores espirituales, no osaban hablar. D.ª Eloisa tornó a exhalar otro suspiro y dijo con
acento dolorido, como si terminase en alta voz un monólogo:

--¡Qué lástima que le hayan pervertido en Madrid! Álvaro tiene buen corazón... y todos dicen
que es hombre de talento.

Los clérigos se sintieron molestados por aquellos elogios. Uno de ellos, el P. Melchor, se
atrevió a decir con sonrisita de suficiencia:

--Señora, permítame usted que no reconozca talento en quien no admite las verdades de nuestra
santa religión.

--A lo menos fue el primero en su cátedra y pasaba entre sus profesores por un chico despejado.

--Y lo será, señora,--dijo el P. Gil, a quien el tonillo agresivo de su compañero había disgustado.--Se
puede tener talento y estar obcecado en cualquier asunto. Su hermano, desgraciadamente, lo
está en lo que se refiere al más interesante para el hombre. Mas no hay razón para negarle
el talento. Los grandes heresiarcas lo han tenido; si no fuese así, seguramente no habrían
podido dar apariencia de verdad al error y engañar tanta gente.

Aunque se sintiese herido en lo vivo por esta réplica indirecta, el P. Melchor no osó responder,
y prefirió hacerse el distraído devorando su enojo. Por más que no la confesasen, todos los
clérigos de Peñascosa sentían la superioridad del P. Gil, que achacaban, por supuesto, a que
era el único entre ellos que había seguido la carrera lata de teología. Ningún otro intentó
tampoco llevarle la contraria por temor de hacer un mal papel.

La conversación se encauzó por otro lado. Charlose animadamente del proyecto de construcción
de una nueva iglesia, cerca de la plaza, echado a volar por varios vecinos y al cual se oponía
con todas sus fuerzas el cura, por temor de que se dividiera la parroquia. Los jugadores seguían
en sus alternativas de silencio y ruidosos altercados. El P. Gil quedó mudo y pensativo, impresionado
con lo que acababa de oír y decir. La figura de Montesinos, a quien no había visto más de tres
o cuatro veces en su vida, y eso de lejos, flotaba en su imaginación despertando en él viva
curiosidad. La afirmación de doña Eloisa de que había sido siempre el primero entre sus condiscípulos,
contribuyó a hacer más grande, por no decir más interesante a sus ojos, aquel hombre. Un deseo
vago, indefinido de acercarse y conquistarle nació en su mente. Cuando la llegada de D. José
María el boticario y de Osuna dio la señal de disolverse la tertulia, aún rodaba este pensamiento
por su cerebro en busca de forma.

La noche seguía encapotada y triste. El cielo dejaba caer con pertinacia una lluvia menuda
y fría. En la puerta de la casa los tertulios se dividieron: la mayor parte se quedó por las
inmediaciones de la plaza, otros siguieron por la calle del Cuadrante. Y en ella se fueron
separando todos hasta que quedaron solos el P. Gil, Osuna y su hija, los únicos que vivían
en el Campo de los Desmayos. Obdulia maniobró para que el P. Gil la tapase con su paraguas.
El jorobado marchaba detrás, satisfecho de no pasar por la humillación de que su hija le tapase,
pues a causa de la gran diferencia de estatura así sucedía siempre.

Caminaron unos instantes en silencio, escuchando el estruendo lejano del mar que batía contra
las peñas y el leve rumor de la lluvia sobre el paraguas. La joven esperaba que el P. Gil sacara
la conversación de su altercado con el P. Narciso, y de intento prolongaba indefinidamente
el silencio. Viéndole taciturno y abstraído, se aventuró a decirle con voz temblorosa:

--¿Está usted enfadado conmigo, padre?

--¿Por qué?--preguntó el clérigo con sorpresa, saliendo repentinamente de su meditación.

--Por la disputa que he tenido con D. Narciso.

--¡Ah! Sí... en efecto, no me ha gustado la actitud rebelde en que usted se ha colocado frente
a él. Es indigno de una joven humilde y virtuosa como usted...

Obdulia guardó silencio, sintiendo en el corazón la censura de su director. Al cabo dijo, poniéndose
colorada, lo cual nadie pudo advertir:

--Tiene usted razón; he cometido un pecado y me arrepiento...

Después de una pausa larga, añadió humildemente:

--No puede usted figurarse cuánto me disgusta el observar la envidia de D. Narciso.

--¿La envidia?--preguntó el sacerdote con sorpresa.--¿A quién tiene envidia?

--A usted, padre, a usted--repuso con firmeza la joven.

--No, hija, no--dijo el P. Gil todo azorado.--Yo no puedo excitar la envidia de nadie... Soy
un pobre clérigo... un miserable pecador...

--Pues así y todo... yo me entiendo...

Repuesto de su turbación, el sacerdote dijo entonces con aspereza:

--Ruego a usted que no vuelva a decir esas cosas, ni que las piense... Se lo prohíbo... Advierta
usted que se trata de dos sacerdotes--añadió después de una pausa, dulcificando la voz.

Obdulia no replicó. Muda y con el corazón apretado por una pena extraña, siguió marchando al
lado del clérigo. Éste dirigió la palabra a Osuna sin volverse:

--Al llegar al Campo vamos a sentir el aire, señor Osuna.

--¿Cuándo no sopla en ese maldito Campo?--replicó el jorobado con mal humor.

Y en efecto, al abocar a él, una ráfaga violenta les azotó el rostro y estuvo a punto de volverles
los paraguas. La sotana del clérigo, las enaguas de la joven tremolaron: les costaba trabajo
avanzar.

Por fin alcanzaron el gran portal de Montesinos. Se limpiaron el rostro con el pañuelo y repusieron
el desorden de sus vestidos. El P. Gil volvió a dirigir una mirada curiosa y escrutadora a
la oscura puerta en cuya cima ardía siempre la lamparita de aceite.

--Adiós, señor Osuna, que usted descanse--dijo tendiendo la mano al jorobado.

Luego tuvo un momento de indecisión: iba a tendérsela a Obdulia; pero turbado por la mirada
intensa y extática que la joven le clavaba, la llevó al sombrero y se inclinó gravemente, diciendo:

--Buenas noches, señorita.

Alzó de nuevo el paraguas y salvó de prisa la distancia que le separaba de la rectoral. Los
ojos de Obdulia, inmóvil a la puerta mientras su padre llamaba, le siguieron algún tiempo.

Antes de penetrar en la rectoral, el P. Gil volviose y quedó inmóvil también algunos instantes.
Pero sus ojos no buscaron la puerta de donde aquélla acababa de desaparecer. Fueron más arriba,
abrazaron de una vez la extensa y sombría fachada de la gran casa solariega que, avezada a
los golpes del huracán, dormía grave y desdeñosa bajo la intemperie. Contemplola larga, atentamente.
Sus ojos brillaron con un fuego de gozo místico. Era la mirada del apóstol, ávida, tierna,
clemente. Tal debió ser la expresión que reflejaron los ojos de San Pedro a la vista de Roma.

IV

Desde aquella noche el P. Gil no soñó con otra cosa. La fiebre del apostolado le encendió de
tal modo que no dejó rincón vacío en su cerebro para otro pensamiento. Dentro de él entablose
una lucha sorda entre el deseo vivo y ardiente de ennoblecer su vida con la conquista de un
enemigo encarnizado de la Iglesia, y el miedo desapoderado, loco, que sin saber por qué le
inspiraba. En sus continuos paseos por la estancia que ocupaba en la rectoral, mientras con
el breviario en la mano decía los rezos obligatorios, a menudo se detenía ante la ventana,
levantaba la punta del visillo y dirigía una mirada tímida y ansiosa al palacio de Montesinos.
Allí estaba, adusto, impenetrable, hostil como un baluarte fabricado por la impiedad. Los balcones
eternamente cerrados. El hombre misterioso que lo habitaba debía de odiar tanto la luz del
sol como la de la fe. El P. Gil dirigía luego la vista al cielo y daba gracias a Dios desde
el fondo del corazón por haberle tenido siempre de su mano, por haberle hecho nacer y vivir
en la región luminosa de las santas creencias cristianas.

En vano trató de inquirir pormenores de la vida y carácter de aquella oveja descarriada a quien
ansiaba traer al redil. Los datos que le suministraron eran contradictorios. Mientras su hermana
y algunas otras personas se lo presentaban como un perfecto caballero, un hombre de buen fondo,
extraviado por las malas compañías y la lectura de libros impíos, otras, que también pretendían
conocerle desde la infancia, lo pintaban como un ser avieso, mal intencionado, riendo siempre
de las desgracias y las flaquezas del prójimo, insolente y agresivo de palabra, ya que de obra
no podía serlo por su natural débil y enfermizo. A este propósito narraban algunas anécdotas
de su infancia y adolescencia que acreditaban esta opinión. Otros, en fin, le tenían por un
desdichado, por un hombre a quien los desengaños de su carrera literaria y los profundos pesares
domésticos habían llenado el corazón de hiel. Suponían que Montesinos, aficionado a las letras,
enamorado de la gloria, había ido a Madrid. En vez de ella, sólo halló glacial indiferencia:
esto, unido a la catástrofe de su matrimonio, le había obligado a retirarse de nuevo a Peñascosa
«rabo entre piernas,» como decían pintorescamente los graves biógrafos. Y terminaban afirmando
que Montesinos desahogaba su amargura y despecho blasfemando de palabra cuando se le presentaba
la ocasión y publicando artículos en los periódicos y revistas de los masones. El P. Gil no
sabía a qué atenerse. Inclinábase, no obstante, a esta última opinión, que conciliaba hasta
cierto punto la benévola de su hermana y ciertos amigos con la mala fama que tenía en el pueblo.
Lo que no dejaba de sorprenderle era que mientras el clero y los tradicionalistas de Peñascosa
le detestaban cordialmente, los pocos republicanos y masones que había en la villa no le demostraban
estimación alguna. Decíase que Montesinos se reía de ellos con más gana aún que de los católicos,
y que había huido constantemente su trato.

Todas estas noticias, que recogía de un lado y de otro disimulando, por supuesto, su proyecto,
no eran a propósito para apartarle de él. El misterio impenetrable que envolvía el carácter
de aquel hombre le interesaba cada día más, y más le atemorizaba. Sabía cuánto importaba atraer
un alma perdida al seno de la Iglesia; pero cuando esta alma era la de un hereje, un enemigo
encarnizado de ella, el acto crecía desmesuradamente a los ojos de Dios. Dando vueltas a la
idea, concibió varias veces el propósito de acercarse inmediatamente a él, hablarle y convencerle
con razones y con ruegos; mas pronto lo abandonaba temiendo un fracaso. No era que le mortificase
lo más mínimo en su amor propio: estaba resuelto a padecer por Dios con alegría toda clase
de martirios, cuanto más una injuria. Lo que temía era tener que renunciar a una empresa tan
noble y gloriosa. Poco a poco llegó a convencerse de que el mismo Dios se la encomendaba especialmente,
que ésta era la tarea principal que le había impuesto al enviarlo a Peñascosa. Y convencido
de que lo sublime del propósito no empece a que se adopten los medios más eficaces para llevarlo
a feliz remate, resolviose a comunicarlo con su madrina doña Eloisa y a pedirle ayuda. Grande
fue el gozo de la buena señora al recibir la confidencia. Aplaudió de todas veras el proyecto,
que satisfacía los deseos más ardientes de su corazón, y prometió hacer cuanto humanamente
fuese posible por que tan hermoso sueño se realizase. Hubo entre ambos largas pláticas, en
que se buscaron y ponderaron los medios de llevarlo a cabo; se trazaron y se rechazaron diferentes
planes; por último, quedaron convenidos en que el excusador fuese a la morada de D. Álvaro
por encargo de su hermana a pedirle una limosna para las viudas y los huérfanos de unos pescadores
que habían perecido recientemente en la mar. Aprovechando la ocasión, podía tantearle, hacerse
amigo suyo y dar comienzo poco a poco a la obra de su conversión. D.ª Eloisa no dudaba del
éxito, fiada en el buen fondo de su hermano y en la virtud y la ciencia de su ahijado. Cuando
alguna vez le había hablado de las prácticas religiosas, Álvaro había respondido con alguna
invectiva grosera contra los clérigos de Peñascosa; a unos los consideraba idiotas, a otros
malvados; de todos se reía a mandíbula batiente. Pero ¿qué podía decir de este muchacho tan
bueno, tan estudioso, de costumbres tan puras y austeras?

Él no estaba tan confiado. A medida que se acercaba el día de la visita, sentíase más agitado
y medroso. Pedía con insistencia a Dios que le diese fuerzas y valor, y preparaba sus argumentos
y hasta sus frases con una atención exagerada. Una mañana, después de haber estado en oración
largo rato, salió de la rectoral con paso firme, salvó la pequeña distancia que le separaba
del palacio de Montesinos, penetró en el lóbrego portal y tiró del grasiento cordel de la campana.
Ésta sonó a lo lejos cascada y triste. El corazón del sacerdote se contrajo, a pesar del ánimo
que la oración le había infundido. Presentose al cabo de un buen rato de espera un criado anciano
de semblante hosco. Al ver al excusador, sus ojos duros y penetrantes expresaron asombro.

--¿D. Álvaro está?

Tardó en contestar.

--¡Ya se ve que está!--respondió al cabo.--No sale nunca.

--¿Y se le puede ver?

--¿Por qué no?

--Pues avísele usted que el teniente cura de la parroquia desea hablar con él por encargo de
su señora hermana D.ª Eloisa.

--No hay necesidad. Venga usted conmigo--replicó bruscamente.

Y después de cerrar y trancar con cuidado la puerta, echó a andar delante. No dejó de sorprenderle
al excusador el aire de autoridad del viejo doméstico, y lo poco en que tenía la voluntad de
su amo para recibir o no las visitas. Después de atravesar un gran patio húmedo, mal empedrado,
donde crecía por todas partes la hierba, rodeado de columnas toscas de piedra manchadas de
musgo, ascendieron por una escalera de piedra y tosca también, con los pasos gastados por el
uso. En el piso principal salvaron un ancho corredor abierto, con el pavimento de madera, tan
deteriorado que era preciso ir con cuidado para no meter el pie por algún agujero. Por todas
partes se observaba un abandono extraño; las paredes sucias, descascarilladas, el suelo con
un dedo de polvo, los techos agrietados: no parecía una casa habitada, sino una antigua abadía
solitaria. La gran casa solariega de los Montesinos se pudría, se derrumbaba, sin que su dueño
intentase en ella la menor reforma, sin que lo advirtiese siquiera. En el piso segundo el criado
le condujo al través de varias salas destartaladas y lóbregas, abrió al fin una puerta de cristales
con visillos sucios, después de echar una mirada por el interior, dijo:

--No está aquí. Habrá subido a la biblioteca.

Vuelta a desandar lo andado. Hallaron en el corredor una puertecita estrecha, y por ella entró
el criado seguido del clérigo, subiendo por una escalera de caracol más oscura y más sucia
aún que el resto de la casa. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04050</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>482628</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14791</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The mood was a bit oblivious. There was some concern in the party,
motivated by the presence of P. Gil, whom none of his colleagues, if except P. Norberto, showed
sympathy. The conversation was rolling from one to another subject, all unimportant. In a moment
of silence, D. Juan Casanova, who had his head tilted to one side, no doubt by the excessive weight
of the brain, somewhat discharged, saying with his usual solemnity

- Eloise, today I found his brother Alvaro in the Paseo de la Atalaya. He wore trousers frame.

Ms
Eloisa sighed, as long as he played the point of his brother.

-
These days have been a little sick.

I was told the servant - said sending a shy glance at the table where
he played her husband.

D. Martin and his brother for some time that were not related. For the trivial reason of furniture
of the house that was meant to bring to his own, without right, broke in a violent way. D. Martin (what
else?) Put his hand on his brother's face and challenged him over this. From then, total separation
between them. D. Álvaro living in his huge house, all alone, and D. Martin in his with his wife.
This, from time to time, hidden from Mr. Martin, was to visit his brother.

- Not appear to enjoy good health - said P. Gil, who did not know why he was interested man.

- Oh! Very sickly and delicate. Just taking care a lot can go on living.

Clerics, as always when Montesinos was in the presence of his sister, kept gloomy silence, with
a long face and plastered. If it were not, would insurance released a statement of outrage and sarcasm
against that wicked one, who was shocked the villa with his views and his conduct. With great
difficulty adhering to the narrow loop family.

There was a gloomy silence, for the ladies, realizing what was happening
in the interior of spiritual directors dared not speak.

Ms Eloisa turned to breathe another sigh and said painful accent, as if to end in a monologue
aloud:

- Too bad you have been perverted in Madrid!

Alvaro has a good heart ... and they all say he is a man of talent.

Clerics felt annoyed by those accolades. One of them, Father Melchior, is dare say smirk:

- Madam, permit me not to recognize talent who does not admit the truth of our holy religion.

-
At least it was the first in his chair and went among their teachers for a guy clear.

- And it will, madam, - said Fr Gil, whom the aggressive twang of
his partner was upset .-- It can have talent and be blinded in any
case.

His brother, unfortunately, what is in regard to the most interesting to man. But there is no reason
to deny talent. The heretics have been great, if not so, would certainly not have could give
the appearance of truth to error and deceive many people.

Although it felt wounded to the quick by the indirect reply, Fr Melchor
did not dare answer, and preferred to be distracted eating the anger.

For most who do not confess all Peñascosa clergy felt the superiority of P. Gil, who blamed,
of course, to was the only one among them who had followed the race can of theology. No other
attempt not contradict him for fear of making a bad paper.

The conversation was directed by the other side. Charlose lively construction project of a new
church near the plaza, flown by several neighbors and which opposed with all their might the
priest, fearing to divide the parish. The players were alternatives in their silence and noisy altercation.
Fr Gil remained silent and pensive, impressed with what he had to hear and say. Figure of Montesinos,
who had not seen more than three or four times in his life, and that from a distance, floating
in his mind waking up at Viva curiosity. The claim that Mrs. Eloisa had always been the first among
his classmates, helped to make it bigger, if not more interesting
to your eyes, man.

A desire vague, indefinite and conquer approach was born in his mind. When the arrival of
D. José Maria Osuna, the apothecary and gave the signal for the dissolution of the gathering,
even the thought rolled for his brain for shape.

The night was overcast and gloomy. The sky would drop with obstinacy a fine rain and cold. At
the door of the house the circles were divided: most stayed for the near the square, others went
down the street of the Quadrant.

And on it went separating all until they were alone Fr Gil, Osuna and his daughter, the only
living Field of fainting. Obdulia arranged that the P. Gil's tapase with his umbrella. The hunchback
moved back, glad not to go through the humiliation of having her daughter tapase, for because
of the large difference in height so it was good.

They walked a few moments in silence, listening to the distant roar
of the sea beating against the rocks and the faint sound of rain on
the umbrella.

The girl expected to P. Take out Gil the conversation of his altercation
with Fr Narciso, and indefinitely prolonged attempt silence.

Seeing taciturn and withdrawn, he ventured to say in a trembling voice:

- Are you angry with me, father?

- Why? - Asked the clerk in surprise, suddenly out of his meditation.

-
The dispute I had with D. Narciso.

- Ah!

Yes ..

In fact, I did not like the rebellious attitude that you have placed
in front him.

It is unworthy of a humble and virtuous young as you ...

Obdulia was silent, feeling in the heart of the censorship of his director. Finally he said,
putting red, which no one could see:

- You're right, I have committed a sin and repent ...

After a long pause, he added humbly:

- You can not imagine how much I dislike the look of envy D. Narciso.

-
Envy? - Asked the priest with surprise .-- Who is jealous?

- You,
Father, to you - the young woman said firmly.

- No, my dear, no -
said Fr Gil all bewildered .-- I can not be envied by anyone ... I
a poor clergyman ... a miserable sinner ...

- Well, even so ... I
understand ...

Replace your embarrassment, the priest then said sharply:

-
I beg you not to say those things again, or that thinks ... Forbid
it ... Note you are two priests - added after a pause, his voice softening.

Obdulia

no reply. Muda and heart squeezed by a strange sentence, continued
marching next to the cleric.

He spoke to Osuna without turning

- At the Country are going to feel the air, Mr. Osuna.

- When does not blow in that damn field? - Said the hunchback with bad humor.

And indeed, to engage with it, a violent gust struck them face and
was about to return umbrellas.

The cleric's robe, the petticoat of the girl waving: they had trouble
forward.

Finally reached the great portal of Montesinos.

They wiped his face with his handkerchief and restored the disorder of his clothes. Fr Gil
returned to lead a curious look, searching for the dark door on top
of which always burning oil lamp.

- Goodbye, Mr. Osuna, you rest
- said extending his hand to the hunchback.

Then he had a moment of indecision going to lie to Obdulia, but troubled by the look intense
and ecstatic that she nailed him, took his hat and bowed gravely, saying:

- Good evening, miss.

Again raised the umbrella and quickly saved the distance that separated him from the rectory.
The Obdulia eyes, motionless at the door while his father called, and followed him for some time.

Before
entering the rectory, Father Gil turned and also stood a few moments. But his eyes sought the
door where it had disappeared. Were above once embraced the vast and sombre facade of the
great manor house, seasoned with Hurricane shocks, serious and disdainful slept under the weather.
Contemplola long, carefully. His eyes shone with a mystical fire of joy. It was the look of
the apostle, greedy, tender, lenient. Perhaps the expression should be reflected in the eyes of
San Pedro in view of Rome.

IV

Since that night, Fr Gil did not dream of anything else.

Apostolate fever reddened with so that did not leave empty corner in your brain to another thought.
Within it entablose a silent struggle between the living and burning desire to enrich your life
with the conquest of a bitter enemy of the Church, and fear repossession, crazy, not knowing why
he inspired. In his ongoing walk around the room it occupied in the rectory, while with breviary
in his hand saying the obligatory prayers, often stopped at the window the tip of the curtain
rose, and looked timid and anxious at the palace of Montesinos. There was, stern, impenetrable,
hostile as a stronghold built by the impious. Balconies closed forever. The mystery man who
had lived to hate both the light sun as that of faith. Fr Gil then directed at the sky and
gave thanks to God from the bottom of my heart for having always had his hand, having been born
and live region in light of the holy Christian beliefs.

He tried in vain to inquire into details of the life and character of those lost sheep who longed
to bring into the fold. Who provided data were contradictory. While her sister and some others
had it as a perfect gentleman, a man of substance, astray by bad company and wicked reading books,
others also claimed known each other since childhood, painted as being perverse, mean-spirited,
always smiling the misfortunes and frailties of others, insolent, aggressive speech, since
labor could not be natural for his weak and sickly. In this regard recounted anecdotes of his childhood
and adolescence evidencing this view. Still others, he had a unfortunate for a man whom his literary
career disappointments and deep sorrow household had filled the heart of gall. Assumed that Montesinos,
fan letters, love of glory had gone to Madrid. Instead of it, was the only glacial indifference this,
coupled with the disaster of his marriage, he had been forced to
retreat back to Peñascosa "Tail between his legs," as a serious biographer
quaintly said.

And claimed Montesinos vented his bitterness and spite blaspheming word when presented the occasion
and publishing articles in newspapers and magazines of the Masons. Fr Gil knew what to expect.
Bowed, however, this latter view, that reconciled to some extent the benevolent of her sister and
some friends with the bad reputation it had in the village. What surprise did not stop was that
while the clergy and traditionalists Peñascosa cordially detested him, the few Republicans
and Masons in the town had not demonstrated any estimates. Montesinos was said that they laughed
even more wins than Catholics constantly and had fled their treatment.

This news, which gathered on one side and other hiding, of course, your project, were calculated
to take away from him. Impenetrable mystery that surrounded the character the man was interested in becoming
more and more frightened him. He knew how to attract matter a lost soul in the bosom of the
Church, but when this soul was that of a heretic, an enemy bitter of it, the act grew enormously
in the eyes of God. Circling the idea conceived several times in order to immediately close to
him, talk and convince with reasons and entreaties but soon left him fearing failure. Not that
you fret her least in his self: he was determined to suffer for God with joy all kinds of
martyrdom, the more an insult. The fear was having to give an undertaking as noble and glorious.
Gradually he became convinced that God Himself enjoined especially this was the main task imposed
on him by sending him to Peñascosa. And convinced sublime that purpose is without prejudice
to the adoption of the most effective means to carry to a successful auction, resolviose to communicate
with her godmother and Dona Eloisa help. Grande was the joy of the good lady to get the confidence.
Earnestly applauded the project, satisfying the most ardent desire of his heart, and promised
to do everything humanly possible that such a beautiful dream come true. There were long talks
between the two in were sought and weighted means of carrying it out, were drawn and rejected
different plans and, finally, were agreed that the toilets were at the house of D. Álvaro on
behalf of his sister to ask for alms to widows and orphans of fishermen who had recently died
at sea.

Seizing the opportunity, might therefore need to be friend and slowly begin the work of his conversion.
Ms Eloisa not doubt the success, confident in the proper fund of his brother and virtue and science
of his godson. When ever told him about religious practices, Alvaro had responded with some rude
invective against clerics Peñascosa; thought about the idiots, other wicked all laughed heartily.
But what could I say about this boy so Well, as scholars, as pure and austere habits?

He was not so confident. As he approached the day of the visit, he felt more restless and fearful.
Insistently asked God to give strength and courage, and prepare their
arguments and even his sentences with exaggerated care.

One morning, after having been in prayer long time, left the rectory
with a firm step, saved the little distance between him Montesinos
Palace, entered the dark portal and pulled the bell cord greasy.

This sounded far waterfall and sad.

The priest's heart contracted, despite encouragement that the sentence
had been infused.

Presented itself after waiting a long time a servant elder sullen
countenance.

Seeing the toilet, his eyes hard and penetrating expressed astonishment.

-
D. Alvaro is?

Slow to answer.

- You can see that is! - Said after .-- never leaves.

- What can you do?

- Why not?

- Well, tell you that the curate of the parish want to talk to him on behalf of your sister
Ms Eloisa.

- No need. Come with me - he replied sharply.

And after you close and lock the door carefully, he walked forward.

Do not fail to surprise the air of authority to excuse the old home,
and what little they had the will his master to receive or not receive
visits.

After crossing a large courtyard, wet, poorly paved, which grew all over the grass, surrounded
by rough stone columns stained moss, rose by a rough stone staircase and also the steps spent
by the use. Saved on the main floor wide open corridor, with wooden
floors, so deteriorated that it was necessary to be careful not to
put his foot through a hole. For all hand there is a strange abandonment,
the walls dirty, chipped, ground with a finger of dust, cracked ceilings;
there seemed an inhabited house, but an ancient abbey lonely. The
great manor house of Montesinos was rotting, crumbling, no owner it
tried to reform the child, without even notice it. On the second floor
raised led him through several rooms at the dilapidated and gloomy,
finally opened a glass door with dirty curtains, after taking a look
on the inside, said:

- He is not here. There will be uploaded to
the library.

Return to retrace his steps. They found a small door
in the corridor close, and she came followed by the priest's servant,
up a spiral staircase darker and dirtier even as the rest of the house.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>