<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10032</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>146695</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21832</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Pero don Eleazar ha encontrado la horma de su zapato; mientras sus agentes, divididos en dos
bandos que operaban en sentido contrario, preparaban su golpe, él no contaba con que en esta
tierra del papel-moneda, una nueva emisión es asunto de poca monta, y la cuerda tirante con
que él tenía presos a sus deudores, se ha aflojado; la nueva emisión se ha hecho y he aquí
que la baja más espantosa se ha operado.

En esta situación, don Eleazar ha resuelto no reconocer sus operaciones. El tiene razón hasta
cierto punto; exige fair play, como los luchadores ingleses. En la casa de la Bolsa, todo es
permitido como en la guerra; jugar públicamente al alza y clandestinamente a la baja; lanzar
un gato, dar una noticia de sensación, asegurar que la guerra con Chile es un hecho, que nuestra
escuadra está en un estado atroz, que nuestro ejército será derrotado en caso de una batalla;
en una palabra, sembrar el terror sin consideración de ningún género por el patriotismo; pero
jugar con armas de doble carga, no. ¡Eso no, eso nunca!... Don Eleazar en estas materias es
correctísimo, y, sobre todo, cuando en vez de ser él quien apunta, acontece que es contra él
contra quien se vuelven las bocas de los cañones. Pero lo peor de todo, mi amigo, no es eso.
Lo peor es que don Eleazar, aprovechando su desgracia, porque es capaz de aprovechar todo y
sacar de todo ventaja, ha resuelto no pagar a nadie. A él lo sitian por hambre, pero él les
cercena el agua y el pan, y con la misma cuerda con que lo ahorcan, él procura ahorcar a sus
adversarios.

--Quiere decir que yo me encuentro en la calle--le dije al oírle terminar su relación.

--¡Oh, no! ¿cree usted que don Eleazar es hombre de despedirlo por cosas de tan poca monta?...
No. Su quiebra es una quiebra que no lo arruina ni lo lleva al tribunal; todo se resuelve para
él en no pagar; las deudas de Bolsa no son deudas, y en el caso de don Eleazar ha pasado ni
más ni menos lo que sucede en una casa mala de juego cuando se apagan las luces: cada jugador
defiende con el puño lo que puede, y le aseguro que su patrón sabrá defender lo suyo. No se
alarme: no perderá el puesto.

--No me alarmo, don Benito, por tan poca cosa--le repuse riéndome a carcajadas.--¡Soy yo quien
resuelvo no volver al escritorio de don Eleazar! No me cuadran ni el hombre ni el empleo.

--Hace usted bien, amigo: eso lo honra.

--No, don Benito; ni me honra ni me deshonra; no hago una quijotada, ni tendría derecho para
hacerla. Don Eleazar se ha portado bien conmigo; me ha pagado religiosamente mis sueldos y
ha tenido el buen gusto de no imponerme de sus negocios.

--¿Y qué va usted a hacer?

--No lo sé, pero mañana lo sabré. Desde luego disponga usted de mi cuarto: ¡tenemos que separarnos!

--¿Separarnos? ¡Jamás!--me contestó el buen viejo irguiendo su noble cabeza y acompañando sus
palabras con un gesto enérgico que denotaba el profundo sentimiento que le había ocasionado
mi resolución.--¿Separarnos? ¡Nunca!--me repitió:--mire, Julio... Mira, hijo mío--agregó,--déjame
que te tutee, mis canas me dan derecho para ello, ¿es cierto?

Y como yo le hiciera un signo afirmativo, prosiguió conmovido:

--Yo he respetado hasta hoy la resolución de tu tío, pero debo confesarte que he sufrido al
verte en casa de don Eleazar. Ese empleo no te corresponde, y lo que no me explico es cómo
Ramón te ha colocado allí...

--Mi tía, usted sabe...

--Sí, que lo gobierna como a un trompo; pero esa no es una razón para que te descuide. Mira--me
dijo,--desde hoy yo me encargo de ti. ¡Qué diablos! Soy viejo, pero tengo el alma joven todavía:
seré tu padre y tu hermano al mismo tiempo. Tengo mala fama en el mundo: las mujeres como misia
Medea me aborrecen, porque no creo en deidades políticas; y los hombres como don Eleazar tampoco
me pueden pasar, porque no sé hacer negocios de los que ellos hacen. Viviremos juntos; de cuando
en cuando oirás en mi cuarto alguna voz de mujer... ¡qué quieres!... Soy hombre... súfreme
estos extravíos. Las mujeres me enloquecen, por eso he tenido el tino de no volverme loco por
una sola: me he enloquecido por todas y no me he casado con ninguna; espero no caer en la tentación
de hacerlo en los años que tengo. Soy risueño, despreocupado y franco: vivo sin misterios y
tomo la vida tal como es. Allá en mis mocedades he leído mucho; pero una sola lectura me ha
aprovechado de todas las que he hecho: ahí está junto a la cabecera de la cama: Rabelais.

Cuando tengas mi edad y hayas corrido el mundo, verás que tenía razón: es el único libro que
ayuda a bien morir, por eso lo abominan los jesuitas. No tengo hijos, o más bien dicho, no
sé si los tengo, porque, si lo supiera a ciencia cierta, no los negaría como padre; pero en
la duda, tú bien sabes que es mejor abstenerse, porque esto de tomar como propias las obras
de otros, es un poco grave. Y yo huyo del ridículo sobre todo. No tengo ningún amigo de mi
edad: mis amigos son los jóvenes de la tuya, vivo con ellos, enamoro con ellos y escandalizo
también con ellos este salón porteño en que hay muchas mujeres lindas y tanto tonto que se
las lleva.

Y, al terminar, don Benito me estrechó fuertemente en sus brazos y contra su pecho, y yo no
pude contener las lágrimas que me saltaron a los ojos.

Al día siguiente me presenté en lo de don Eleazar, de mañana. El patio estaba lleno de gente
que cuchicheaba y accionaba con animación: las puertas del escritorio cerradas. Me acerqué
y golpeé los cristales: al abrirme don Anselmo, que me reconoció, dos o tres de las personas
del patio se arrojaron sobre la puerta del escritorio con la pretensión de entrar.

--Perdonen ustedes, no pueden ustedes entrar...--les dijo don Anselmo, y les dio casi con la
puerta en las narices.

Y pude ver que uno de ellos levantaba el puño de la mano en actitud amenazante.

En dos palabras di cuenta a don Anselmo de mi resolución de abandonar la casa.

--Vaya, vaya, ¿a usted también lo ha picado la tarántula?

--A mí no me ha picado ninguna tarántula; ni quiero, ni tengo nada que ver con los que protesten
afuera ni contra los que se encierran adentro, vengo a agradecer a don Eleazar el honor que
me ha hecho y a comunicarle mi resolución. ¿Me quiere usted anunciar?

--No se si podrá recibirlo a usted...--me dijo don Anselmo moviendo la cabeza.

--Vea usted si puede... quiero cumplir lo que yo considero un deber.

Don Anselmo pasó a la habitación contigua, que era la de don Eleazar, y después de un rato regresó.

--Dice don Eleazar que puede pasar--me dijo.

Yo entré resueltamente. No olvidaré nunca el cuadro que se presentó a mi vista. Casi en el
medio de la habitación, junto a un escritorio elevadísimo, donde don Anselmo acostumbraba a
escribir bajo el dictado de don Eleazar, sentado sobre un esqueleto de silla, estaba éste,
desayunándose, delante de una mesita muy poco más grande que el plato en que comía. Un sirviente
gallego le servía sin pausas, plato tras plato, y don Eleazar comía con la gravedad de un oso
que devora su ración. En un rincón de la pieza, de pie, tres hombres presenciaban esta colación
matutina en completo silencio.

--Entre usted, señor don Julio, ¿también nos abandona usted en los días de prueba?...

Yo expliqué las causas de mi renuncia, procurando convencerlo de que ella era completamente
extraña al reciente desastre comercial; pero don Eleazar, conmovido, a pesar del apetito con
que devoraba sus viandas, se daba maña para lamentarse con palabras que partían el corazón.

--Bien, joven, puesto que usted lo ha resuelto, separémonos; pero usted me hará justicia algún
día... ¡Vea usted la situación a que me veo reducido! ¡Todo lo he perdido! Desde hoy vivo de
la caridad de mis parientes; sí, señor, de la caridad de la familia... Aquí me tiene usted
preso; ¡yo preso en este país que he colmado de beneficios! ¡No ve usted, señor, que hasta
la autoridad se complota en mi contra! ¡Vea usted, señor, todos esos hombres que se acercan
a los vidrios y que me amenazan, me son completamente desconocidos! ¡Yo nunca he tenido trato
con ellos! ¡No los conozco! ¡Y me persiguen, señor, me persiguen a muerte! ¡Vean ustedes a
lo que estoy reducido! ¡A no poder comer estos bocados en mi casa, porque son hasta capaces
de envenenarme! ¡Y si no fuera por mi fiel Juan (exclamaba mirando expresivamente al gallego
que le servía el almuerzo), si no fuera por él, quién sabe lo que habría sido de mí!

Pero yo te recompensaré algún día... tú sabes que todo lo he perdido, que no tengo nada, que
me es imposible por consiguiente satisfacer mis compromisos! ¡Dilo, Juan, a todos; es posible
que a ti te crean!... ¡Dígalo usted, joven, asegúrelo, usted sabe mis negocios, todos son claros,
tan públicos, tan legítimos!... ¡Ustedes lo saben, señores... yo he sido víctima de gente (agregaba
encarándose con don Anselmo que le contestaba con un signo afirmativo) sin ley ni principios!...
¡Usted lo sabe, don Anselmo, usted sabe todos mis negocios, conoce mi casa!... ¡No me es posible
cumplir, y no lo siento tanto por mí, sino por tanta persona excelente a quien tendré que perjudicar,
contra todos mis sentimientos!... ¡Vean ustedes, vean ustedes cómo amenazan esos hombres! ¡Se
creería que yo me he quedado con algo de ellos!... ¡Gracias, Juan, gracias, hijo mío, sírveme
el té, no tengo apetito!... ¡pruébalo tú primero, mira si tiene mal gusto!... ¡Ah, señores,
yo tengo la conciencia tranquila!...

Y mientras don Eleazar se lamentaba, todos lo oíamos en silencio, como consternados por la
horrible desgracia de ese hombre providencial que engullía como un tiburón, en medio de la
catástrofe de su fortuna. Fueme necesario cortar de un golpe aquella eterna elegía y despedirme
para siempre de ese antro en que había estado ocho meses.

¡Lo que es el mundo de malo! Al salir, los acreedores del patio, que echaban espuma por la
boca, decían que don Eleazar había realizado quinientos mil duros de ganancia y que ellos se
quedaban en la calle. ¿Quién podía creerlo?

XI

Rigurosamente encorbatado de blanco, con un frac de Poole y un par de pumps de Thomas, don
Benito penetraba una noche en mi cuarto, elegante y joven como un muchacho de veinticinco años.

Yo me vestía lentamente; aquella noche hacía mi estreno en el club. ¡El club!... No es necesario
decir que es el Club del Progreso de que hablo, y que el baile en perspectiva es un baile de
julio: la gran attraction de la season porteña.

--¿Todavía en ese estado?...--me dijo al verme complicado en los preparativos de la camisa;--¡es
la una casi!...

--¡Ah! ¿qué cree usted? Es cosa seria preparar una camisa... recuerde usted que me estreno.

--¡Ca! un hombre elegante no se fabrica; nace... Mírame--me dijo--cuadrándose en el medio del
cuarto.

--Bueno, tenga paciencia, yo no soy usted... yo no soy elegante...

--Sí, pero te cuadra Blanquita, ¿no?... Y no supongo que te prenderás como un tendero para
enamorarla, mira que es mujer tan suelta y ligera como la madre... y quiero que la conozcas.

--No embrome con Blanquita, ya sabe que Blanca no me cuadra y que yo tengo una novia en...

--Está bien, cásate con aquélla, pero enamora a ésta... no seas tonto...

--¿Y si no me hace caso?

--¡Qué no! La madre te adora y la madre es la protectora de esa criatura.

--¡Oh! Fernanda me conoce desde muchacho: tenía veinticuatro años cuando yo tenía diez o doce,
pero la hija...

--La hija es igual a la madre; ambas son mujeres de coraje y de avería, lindas como unas tórtolas
y peligrosas como dos lobas.

--Esta noche estarán radiantes, serán las reinas del baile, el señor Montifiori hará brillar
su legación vacante.

--¡Montifiori!... ¿Qué clase de hombre es Montifiori?...

--Te lo diré después... vamos, átate la corbata pronto.

--¿Va bien así? Muy grande el moño, ¿no?...

--No; está bien, las mujeres no se fijan en eso; el pescuezo de los hombres les es indiferente.
Bueno, ponte el frac; ¡excelente! Estás hecho un lord. ¡Si yo tuviera tu cuerpo y tus años
y tú mi experiencia!...

--¡Siempre el viejo proverbio, don Benito!... ¡Ah! no hay nada completo en el mundo.

Di una vuelta por mi cuarto, tomé mis guantes, puse el gas a media luz y salimos yo y mi viejo
compañero. Hacía un frío de todos los diablos, pero el cupé de don Benito estaba a la puerta;
nos encerramos en él y empezamos a deslizarnos sobre los rieles del tranvía a todo trote. En
cinco minutos estábamos en la cuadra del Club del Progreso: tuvimos que esperar algunos minutos
más para que le llegara a nuestro carruaje el turno de acercarse, y por fin bajamos en la puerta
entre un grupo de hombres y mujeres que subían apresuradamente la escalera muellemente tapizada
y adornada con flores y guirnaldas verdes.

¿Quién no conoce el Club en una noche de baile? La entrada no es por cierto la entrada del
palacio del Elíseo y la escalera no es una maravilla de arquitectura.

Sin embargo, para el viejo porteño que no ha salido nunca de Buenos Aires, o para el joven
provinciano que recién llega de su provincia, el Club es, o era en otro tiempo, algo como una
mansión soñada cuya crónica está llena de prestigiosos romances y en el cual no es dado penetrar
a todos los mortales.

Don Benito conocía la casa desde su fundación y gozaba en ella de una influencia única. Al
entrar, jóvenes y viejos lo saludaron con cariño como un antiguo amigo.

El buen viejo, poniéndome el brazo izquierdo sobre la espalda, me condujo al quiosco de cristales
donde nos sacamos los paletós y nos consultamos un momento la figura sobre los espejos.

En aquel momento la orquesta tocaba la última parte de las cuadrillas de Carmen...

    Toreador, toreador en garde...

y la música de Bizet, saturada, por decirlo así, en la sangre misma de Merimée, distribuía
al cuerpo de las mujeres que formaban los cuadros, los tonos calientes con que el joven maestro
ha rimado ese extraño poema de amores plebeyos y bajas venganzas.

El salón, híbrido, y en el cual el gusto refinado de un clubman de raza tendría mucho que rayar,
desaparecería ante la masa compacta de hombres y mujeres que lo llenaban.

Mi viejo amigo me dio el brazo y entramos juntos a ocupar nuestro lugar en aquel bouquet porteño
que julio forma todos los años con la exactitud con que se celebra un aniversario.

Es en un baile del Club del Progreso donde pueden estudiarse por etapas treinta años de la
vida social de Buenos Aires: allí han hecho sus primeras armas los que hoy son abuelos. La
dorada juventud del año 52 fundó ese centro del buen tono, esencialmente criollo, que no ha
tenido nunca ni la distinción aristocrática de un club inglés ni el chic de uno de los clubs
de París. Sin embargo, ser del Club del Progreso, aun allá por el año 70, era chic, como era
cursi ser del Club del Plata, con perdón previo de sus socios.

La entrada era cosa ardua: no entraba cualquiera: era necesario ser crema batida de la mejor
burguesía social y política para hollar las mullidas alfombras del gran salón o sentarse a
jugar un partido de whist en el clásico salón de los retratos que ocupa el frente de la calle
Victoria.

En esta última sala, larga y fría como un zaguán, que ha sido empapelada cien veces por lo
menos de verde o celeste claro y que ha consumido cincuenta distintas partidas de tripe de
lo de Iturriaga, ha nacido una generación de la cual van quedando muy escasos representantes.
Allí ha mordido la maledicencia urbana a los jugadores trasnochadores, a los maridos calaveras,
a la juventud disoluta y disipada, y cada mordisco de mamá indignada ha hecho los estragos
de la viruela en el retrato moral de las víctimas. La maledicencia de la gran aldea es como
la calumnia del Barbero de Sevilla: del venticello pasa al huracán y ¡ay de aquel que se encuentre
envuelto en la ráfaga!

El Club del Progreso ha sido la pepinera de muchos hombres públicos que han estudiado en sus
salones el derecho constitucional; literatura fácil que se aprende sin libros, trasnochando
sobre una mesa de ajedrez; ¡y a mí, no sé por qué, se me ocurre que algunos de los retratos
de los hombres de Mayo que presencian aquel grupo de pensadores, hacen una mueca cada vez que
un pollo acompaña un discurso sobre la libertad del sufragio con un golpe que asienta sobre
el damero una reina jaqueada por la chusma de los peones sobrevivientes!

¡Falta allí el retrato del padre Castañeda! ¡Y sobre todo, falta el espíritu! ¡También veinte,
treinta años, de hacer lo mismo!

Hasta hace muy poco, la biblioteca no era muy copiosa que digamos. Mucha Memoria, mucho Registro
Oficial, pero a condición de no encontrarse nunca cuando se pedían; y en la mesa de lectura,
todos los diarios porteños, vacíos y estériles como sábanas de monja, luciendo el artículo
editorial al frente, extenso riel de plomo en que, para valerme de una figura bíblica, se fatigan
los caballos de la imaginación. En la mesa de lectura el Illustrated London New y la Revue
(casi sería inútil agregar des Deux Mondes, si no habláramos en el club); la Revue en que M.
de Mazade produce el artículo burgués que en un tiempo firmaron Forcade y Lanfrey y algunos
diarios franceses que casi siempre sirven de adorno, como esos ramos secos que se pudren en
las salas por olvido de los sirvientes. A pesar de esto, cualquiera creería que allí se lee...
¡nada de eso! Allí se conversa: en el grupo de muchachos alegres y espirituales, que entra
a las 12 de la noche repitiendo la última nota de Tamagno, no falta un ejemplar de denso burgués
pantagruélico, gastrónomo noctámbulo, engordado y enriquecido por el vientre libre de sus vacas,
que se hace servir allí mismo un chorizo por noche, mientras que, con el profundo desdén del
bruto feliz, descuidado el traje, pelado a la mal-content, mira todo lo que le rodea con satisfecha
apatía, llevando la mano al renegrido cabello y dragándose la caspa de aquella mollera inerte
con la uña afilada del índice.

No falta tampoco el idiota de la aldea, magín descompuesto, candidato de pillos, víctima de
las bromas aldeanas, enloquecido con ideas sobre filantropía, abriendo la boca de admiración
y pestañeando con un ojo que sufre de perlesía intermitente, mientras la pupila del otro se
le sale como el carozo de un durazno prisco.

Ni el Tenorio de suburbio que no se modifica; que se viste hoy como ayer, con abalorios de
altar mayor y prendas de precio fijo; sano, insulso, inofensivo, olvidado por los buenos y
mortificado por los que todavía creen que es de buen tono zaherir o burlarse de los inocentes.

Y entre esta sociedad híbrida e incolora como la Memoria de un ministro, mi amigo don Benito,
cuya acrisolada y noble honradez se confunde por el positivismo contemporáneo con el sueño
de un iluso, solía de repente estallar con noble sarcasmo, sintiendo probablemente cuán estériles
han sido las desgracias del pasado y cuán injustamente ha repartido el destino sus favores
en el presente.

Pero el club es el club, y aquella noche, los violines, riendo bajo la cuerda de los arcos,
transmitían la alegría y el entusiasmo singular de la música a todos los semblantes.

De pie, delante de la puerta que da paso a la gran escalera del comedor, yo seguía el vuelo
espiralado de las parejas impelidas por el soplo caliente de un vals de Metra. No sé por qué,
esos valses fascinadores, de cumplidas y ondulantes frases, que parecen dibujadas en el éter
por la batuta mágica del maestro, me produjeron una profunda melancolía, trayéndome al recuerdo
unos versos en que Hugo contempla, a través de los cristales empañados por el frío de la noche,
el cuerpo de su amada enlazado por el brazo de un rival feliz.

¡Pero qué variado espectáculo!

¡Cuánta mujer ideal y atrayente bajo la trama cariñosa de esas telas modernas, cómplices de
la carne y del contorno que este siglo materialista teje con las alas de pájaro o pétalos de
flores exóticas! ¡Cuánto ser grotesco de fealdad repugnante, de doloroso raquitismo, brincando
sin gracia, marcando la nota chillona del ridículo!

¡Cuánto contraste!

¡Cuánta cara foránea, ahorcada por cuellos anticuados, encorbatada de raso tórtola, bizantinamente
enfracada, con pantalón en forma de caño y botines de brasileño guarango!

¡Cuánto gallo viejo sin púas, forcejeando contra el tiempo en vano, con las armas débiles de
los untos! ¡Cuánto ser insípido, abriendo la boca satisfecha y marchitando con su trato insoportable
a tanta mujer linda y atolondrada que busca su ideal sin encontrarlo!

¡Cuánta mamá achatada por la gente que pasa, sirviendo de mojón en los sofás de lampás crema!

¡Cuánto marido tolerante que entrega su mujer a la garra de los halcones y que se sitúa en
el buffet con el sentido práctico de un convencido!

¡Cuánto viejo fatuo, teñido de pies a cabeza, prendido como un paje, que apesta a menta desde
lejos y que instala sus pretensiones intolerables ante cualquier mujer bonita, para que el
mundo le cuaje el sabroso renombre de afortunado! ¡Cuánto muchacho alegre y filósofo, pollos
de la aldea, que conocen la aldea y que toman la partida con el buen humor de los descreídos!

El baile estaba en su apogeo, cuando sentí en torno un murmullo. Dos mujeres del gran mundo
entraban en el salón y las parejas se abrían para darles paso. Don Benito acompañaba a una
de ellas, y la otra, contra la más estricta regla de nuestros salones, caminaba sola al lado.
Don Benito vino derecho adonde yo conversaba con un grupo de amigos.

--¡Julio!--me dijo con la más perfecta y aristocrática urbanidad:--¡Fernanda!--Y dándose vuelta
y señalando a la más joven, repitió, como toda presentación:--¡Blanca!

Me incliné reverenciosamente y al levantar los ojos, vi la imagen doble de mi compañera de
teatro ¡dieciocho años ha!...

--Me parece que nosotros somos viejos amigos--me dijo Fernanda.--Y como queriéndome dar confianza,
agregó:--¡Pero usted es un hombre!

--¡Señora... señorita!....

Y a una finísima mirada de don Benito, imperceptible casi, yo extendí mi brazo y Blanca se
colgó de él con franco y dulce abandono.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10957</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>289093</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19817</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

But Don Eleazar has found his match, while their agents, divided into two gangs operating in
the opposite direction, preparing his coup, he did not expect that in this land of paper money,
a new issue is small matter, and the tightrope with he had imprisoned his debtor, become loose,
the new issue has been done and lo that the decline has taken place more frightening.

In this situation, Mr. Eleazar has decided not to reorganize its operations. He has reason to
certain point, demands fair play, as the British fighters. In the house of the stock, everything
is allowed as in war, playing up publicly and covertly to fall; launch a cat, give notice of
sensation, ensuring that the war with Chile is a fact that our squad is in a dreadful state, that
our army will be defeated if a battle; in short, spread terror, regardless of any kind by patriotism,
but double play with guns loaded, no. That does not, it never! ... Don Eleazar in these matters
is most correct, and especially when rather than he who aims happens that is against him against
whom become the mouths of cannons. But worst of all, my friend, is not it. The worst thing is
that Don Eleazar, taking advantage of his misfortune, because it is capable of fully exploiting
and Take advantage of all, has decided not to pay anyone. A besieging him from starvation,
but he will cuts off water and bread, and with the same rope to hang him, he attempts to hang
her adversaries.

- Means that I am on the street - told the hear to end their relationship.

- Oh, no! Do you think man Don Eleazar is fired for such petty things? ... No. Your bankruptcy
is a bankruptcy that does not spoil or takes it to court, everything is solved for him in not
paying the debts are not debts Exchange, and in the case of Mr. Eleazar has not spent more or
less what happens in a bad home game when the lights go out, every player defend the fist that
can, and I assure you that your employer will know hold their own.

No panic: not lose the job.

- It alarmed me, Don Benito, by so little - I replied laughing heartily
.-- I who I resolve not to return to the desk of Don Eleazar!

I do not add up neither man nor employment.

- You do well, my friend, that honors him.

- No, Don Benito, and I honor or dishonor me, do not do a quixotic,
and would be entitled to it.

Don Eleazar has been good to me, I religiously paid my salary and has had the good sense not
to impose their business.

- What are you doing?

- Do not know, but tomorrow I'll know. Since then have you in my room: we must part!

- Separate Us?

Never! - I answered the old man craning his noble head and accompanying
his words with a strong signal that denoted a deep feeling that had
caused my resolution .-- Separate Us?

Never! - I repeat - look, July ... Look, my son - said, - let me tute you, my gray hairs I am entitled
to do so, is it true?

And as a sign I did so, continued shaky

- I have observed to date the resolution of your uncle, but I must confess that I have suffered
the see you at Don Eleazar. Such use does not love you, and I do not understand is how Ramon
has placed you there ...

- My aunt, you know ...

- Yes, that governs like a spin, but that is no reason for you to neglect. Look - I said, - today
I'll take care of you. What the hell! I am old, but I have a young soul yet: I'll be your
father and your brother at the same time. I have a bad reputation in the world: women misia
Medea hate me because I do not believe in political gods, and men like Don Eleazar also I can
go, because I can not do business that they do. We will live together, from when then hear
in my room a woman's voice ... What you want! ... I am a man ... súfreme these aberrations.
Women drive me crazy, so I had the good sense not to go crazy for one: I've gone mad for all
and I'm not married with any, I hope not into temptation to do so
in the years that I have.

I'm smiling, carefree and frank live without mysteries I take life as it is. Back in my youth
I read a lot, but I was reading one advantage of all that I have
done: there is next to the bedside: Rabelais.

When you're my age and you run the world, you'll see he was right: it is the only book help them
to die, so I despise the Jesuits.

I have no children, or rather, not I know if I have, because if they knew for sure, do not deny
a father, but doubt, you well know that it is better to abstain,
for it to take as their own works others, is a minor.

And I fled the mostly ridiculous.

I have no friends of my age: my friends are young people of yours,
I live with them, fall in love with them and scandalized this room
also with them in Buenos Aires there are many beautiful women and
so stupid that the leads.

And at the end, Don Benito wrung me in his arms and against his chest, and I do not could contain
the tears that sprang to my eyes.

The next day I showed up at the Don Eleazar, tomorrow.

The courtyard was crowded they whispered and gesticulated with animation:
Desktop doors closed.

I went and hit the glass: to open up Don Anselmo, who recognized
me, two or three people patio door fell upon the desk with the intention
of entering.

- Excuse me, can not you go ...-- Anselmo said, and
gave almost the door in his face.

And I could see that one of them raised his fist in a threatening manner.

In two words don Anselmo realized my decision to leave the house.

- Well, well, have you also been bitten by the tarantula?

- I do
not bitten any tarantula, nor I, nor I have nothing to do with those
who protest outside or against those who shut themselves in, I come
to thank Don Eleazar the honor has already made me tell my resolution.

Can I do you advertise?

- If you can not receive you ...-- Anselmo said, shaking his head.

- See if you can ... I want to fulfill what I consider a must.

Don Anselmo went on to the next room, which was that of Don Eleazar, and after a while back.

-
Don Eleazar says that can happen - he said.

I went resolutely. I will never forget the picture presented to my sight. Almost in the middle
of the room, next to a very high desk, where Mr. Anselmo used to written under the dictation
of Mr. Eleazar, skeleton sitting on a chair, was it, breakfasting in front of a table little
bigger than the dish I ate. A servant served non-stop Galician dish after dish, and Don Eleazar
ate to the severity of a bear who devours his ration.

In a corner of the room, standing, three men witnessed this collation morning in complete silence.

-
Between you, Don Julio, "We also leave you in the days of trial? ...

I explained the reasons for my resignation, trying to convince him that she was completely foreign trade
to the recent disaster, but Don Eleazar, moved, despite the appetite devouring their meats, it was
contrived to lament with words that broke their heart.

- Well, young man, since you solved it, Let us part, but you will do me some justice day ... You
see the situation that I am reduced! I lost everything! From now live the love of my family,
yes, sir, charity of the family ... Here you have me prisoner, I caught in this country who
have lavished benefits!

Do not you see, sir, that even authority is plotting against me! You see, sir, all those men
who come the glass and threatening me, are completely unknown to me! I have never had dealings
with them! I do not know! And follow me, sir, follow me to death! You see a I'm small! A not to
eat these snacks at home, they are even able to poison!

And if not for my faithful John (exclaimed looking expressively Galician that served lunch),
if not for him, who knows what would have happened to me!

But I will reward you someday ... you know that everything I lost,
I have nothing that therefore I can not fulfill my commitments!

Say, John, at all, it is possible than you might think you are! ... Say you, Young, secure,
you know my business, all are clear, as public as legitimate!

... You know, gentlemen ... I have been a victim of people (adding faced with Don Anselmo answered
with an affirmative sign) without law and principles! ... You know, Don Anselmo, you know all
my business, she knows my house!

... I can not meet, and do not feel much for me, but so wonderful person who I have to injure, against
all my feelings!

... You see, you see how threatening these men! It I believe I stayed
with some of them!

... Thanks, John, thank you, my son, pour me tea, I have no appetite! ... Try it yourself first,
see if you have bad taste!

... Ah, gentlemen, I have a conscience! ...

And while Don Eleazar complained, all I heard in silence, as appalled
by the horrible disaster of that providential man who swallowed like
a shark, in the midst of catastrophe of his fortune.

FUEM necessary to cut a blow that eternal farewell elegy and forever
from that den that had been eight months.

What is wrong with the world!

Upon leaving the creditors of the courtyard that the foaming mouth, said Don Eleazar had made
five hundred thousand dollars of profit and that they lived on the
street.

Who could believe it?

XI

Strictly wearing ties in white, with a fraction of Poole and a pair
of pumps by Thomas, Don Benito penetrated one night in my room, elegant
young as a boy of twenty years.

I dressed slowly, that night I made my debut at the club. The club! ... It is not necessary say
it is the Progress Club of which I speak, and that dance is a dance perspective July: the
great attraction of the season in Buenos Aires.

- Are you still
in that state told me I ?...-- complicated preparations for his shirt
- is one almost!

...

- Ah! What do you think? Is serious prepare a shirt ... I remember you opening.

- Ca! an elegant man is not made, born ... Look at me - I said - Picture in the middle of room.

-
Well, be patient, I'm not you ... I'm not smart ...

- Yes, but you Blanquita block, right?

... And I guess you tend to come on as a woo, look who is a woman so loose and light as the
mother ... and I want to know.

- Do not kid with Whitey, and I know that White block and I have a girlfriend ...

- Okay, marry it, but it falls to ... Do not be silly ...

- What
if my advice?

- Do not!

The mother loves you and the mother is the protector of that child.

- Oh! Fernanda known me lad was twenty years old when I was ten or twelve but the daughter ...

- The daughter is like the mother, both are women of courage and breakdown,
pretty as a dove and dangerous as two wolves.

- Tonight will be radiant,
are the queens of the dance, Mr. Montifiori will shine his legation
vacancy.

- Montifiori!

    ... What kind of man is Montifiori?

...

- I'll tell you later ... go, tie the tie soon.

- Will right? Very big the bow, right? ...

- No, it is well, women do not look at it, the neck of men are indifferent.

Well, put on your coat, excellent! You're a lord. If I had your body and your years and you
my experience! ...

- Always the old proverb, Don Benito! ... Ah! nothing is complete in the world.

I wandered through my room, I took my gloves, put the half-light gas
and left me and my old partner.

It was cold all the devils, but Coupe Don Benito was at the door; lock ourselves into it and
started to slide on the rails of the tramway to everyday use. In five minutes we were on the
block from Club del Progreso, we had to wait a few minutes more so that you come to our carriage
approaching the turn, and finally got off at the door among a group
of men and women coming up the stairs softly upholstered hastily and
adorned with flowers and green wreaths.

Who does not know the Club for a night of dancing? The entrance is certainly no input Elysee Palace
and the ladder is not a marvel of architecture.

However, for the old Buenos Aires who has never left Buenos Aires, or the young provincial who
just arrived from the province, the Club is or was at one time, something like a dream mansion whose
chronicle is full of prestigious romances and which is not as penetrating
to all mortals.

Don Benito knew the house from its foundation and enjoyed it a unique influence. Al come, young
and old greeted him affectionately as an old friend.

The good old, putting his left arm back, took me to the glass booth
where we took the overcoats and we consulted a moment the figure on
the mirrors.

At that time the orchestra played the last part of the gangs of Carmen ...

Toreador, en garde toreador ...

and Bizet's music is saturated, so to speak, in the very blood of Merimee, distributed the
body of the women who made the paintings, the warm tones that the young master been rhyme that
strange love poem commoners and low revenge.

The lounge, hybrid, where the refined taste of a clubman race would have much to scratch, disappear
before the compact mass of men and women who filled.

My old friend gave me his arm and together we take our place at the Buenos Aires bouquet that way
every year in July with the accuracy with which they celebrated an anniversary.

It is a dance club where Progress can be studied in stages thirty years of Buenos Aires social
life: there have made their first steps by today's grandparents.

The gilded youth of the center founded 52 years of good tone, mainly Creole, which has not
nor ever had the distinction aristocratic English club or one of the chic clubs Paris. However,
being of the Club del Progreso, even back in 70, was chic, as was be corny Club del Plata,
with forgiveness after their partners.

The entrance was something hard, did not enter either: he had to be the best whipped cream
social and political bourgeoisie to tread the soft carpets of the
great room or sit play a game of whist in the classic games of the
portraits is at the forefront of the street Victoria.

In this last room, long and cold as a vestibule, which has been papered it a hundred times less than
green or light blue and has spent fifty different items casings what's Iturriaga, born a generation
which are being very few representatives.

There has bitten the urban gossip revelers players, husbands skulls a dissolute and dissipated
youth, and every bite of indignant mom has made havoc of smallpox
in the moral portrait of the victims.

The slander of the large village is like slander of the Barber of Seville: the passing of Hurricane
VENTICELL and woe to him who is involved in the blast!

The Progress Club has been the pepinera of many public men who have studied in their Banquet constitutional
law, literature easy to learn without books, burn the midnight lamp on a chess table, and I do
not know why, it strikes me that some of the portraits May the men
who witness this group of thinkers, makes a face every time a chicken
accompanied by a discourse on freedom of suffrage with a blow that
sits on the checkerboard a queen check by the mob of survivors pawns!

Missing father's portrait there Castañeda! And above all, lack the spirit! Also twenty thirty
years, to do the same!

Until recently, the library was not very heavy so to speak.

Many memory, much Register Official on condition of not being ever when asked, and at the table reading
Buenos Aires all day, empty and sterile as sheets of a nun, wearing
article editorial front, long lead track, in order to avail myself
of a biblical figure, fatigue horses of the imagination.

At the table reading the Illustrated London and New Revue (Would be almost useless to add des
Deux Mondes, if not to talk in the club), the Revue in which M. of Mazade Article bourgeois occurs at
a time and Lanfrey Forcade signed and some French newspapers almost
always serve as decoration, as these branches dry rot in forgotten
rooms for servants.

Despite this, anyone would think it reads ... None of that!

There he speaks: in the group of kids happy and spiritual, which falls at 12 pm, repeating
the last note of Tamagno, not missing a copy of dense bourgeois gargantuan,
gourmet night owl, fattened and enriched by the free womb of his cows
that right there made to serve a sausage per night, while the deep
disdain Gross happy, sloppy dress, stripped to the ill-content, look
what surrounds you with a satisfied apathy, putting his hand to blackish
hair and dander that dredging inert mollera with the sharp nail of
the index.

Not lacking either the village idiot, Magin decomposed, the candidate of crooks, victim village
jokes, crazy ideas about philanthropy, gasping with admiration and
blinking with one eye palsy suffering from intermittent, while the
pupil of another comes out as the pit of a peach Prisco.

Neither Tenorio suburb that does not change, that is seen today as yesterday, with beads altar
and fixed-price items, healthy, tame, inoffensive, good and forgotten
mortified by those who still believe that it is fashionable to censure
or ridicule of the innocent.

And between this company and colorless Hybrid Memory of a minister, my friend Don Benito, purge
and noble whose honesty is confounded by the contemporary positivism
sleep a dreamer, he would suddenly explode with noble sarcasm, probably
feeling how sterile have been the misfortunes of the past and how
fate has dealt unfairly favors its in the present.

But the club is the club that night, violins, laughing under the bowstrings,
conveyed the joy and excitement of music unique to every face.

Standing in front of the door that leads to the grand staircase from
the dining room, I followed the flight coiled couples impelled by
the hot breath of a waltz by Metra. I do not know why these fascinating
waltzes, compliments and undulating phrases that seem drawn into the
ether magic baton by the teacher, gave me a deep melancholy, bringing
me to remember Hugo verses that provides, through the windows fogged
by the cold of the night, the body of his beloved bound by the arm
of an opponent happy.

But several show! 

Much ideal and attractive
woman under the loving story of these modern fabrics, accomplices
meat and contour this materialistic century woven with bird wings
or petals exotic flowers! How disgusting to be grotesque ugliness
of painful stunting, jumping graceless, marking shrill note of ridicule!

What
a contrast!

How many foreign faces, necks hanged for outdated, wearing
ties satin dove, Byzantine enfracada with trousers in the form of
pipe and boorish Brazilian booty!

How old cock free picks, struggling
against time in vain, with weak arms the unguents! How to be tasteless,
gasping and withering satisfied with your treatment unbearable so
many beautiful and reckless woman seeking without finding your ideal!

Mom
much flattened at the people passing, serving on the sofas Cairn Lamp
cream!

How tolerant husband who gives his woman hawks claw and is
in the buffet with the practicality of a believer!

How old fool,
dying from head to toe, turned on a page, who reeks of mint from further
and install their claims intolerable to any beautiful woman, so that
will curdle the tasty world renowned lucky! How happy boy and philosopher,
chickens the village, who know the village and taking the game with
the good humor of the disbelievers!

The dance was at its height,
when I heard about a whisper. Two women in the big world entered the
room and couples parted to give way. Don Benito accompanied a of them,
and the other against the strictest rule of our rooms, walking alone
on the side. Don Benito came straight to where I was talking to a
group of friends.

- Julio! - Told me with the most perfect and aristocratic
manners: - Fernanda! - And turning around and pointing to the youngest,
he repeated, as any presentation: - White!

I leaned revere and look
up, I tuck my partner eighteen years has theater! ...

- I think we
are old friends - Fernanda told me .-- And as if to reassure, Added:
- But you're a man!

- Lady ... Miss !....

And a fine view of Don
Benito, almost imperceptible, I extended my arm and White hung him
with a frank and sweet abandon</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>