<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07054</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>3238</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>765</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> No has sido tú en esta época la única
cordobesa a quien hizo el amor profetisa. Otra hubo antes que tú, que compitió en esto contigo.
No merece tanto, porque el hombre cuyo valer futuro descubrió ella en su amorosa visión profética,
vale mil y mil veces menos que el que por esfuerzo de su reveladora inteligencia y de su enérgica
voluntad ha duplicado o triplicado la grandeza del mundo conocido, y ha magnificado el concepto
de la creación en toda mente humana. Comparada a la gloria de ese hombre, vale poco la que
se alcanza derrotando ejércitos, conquistando reinos y avasallando y humillando a los príncipes
más poderosos. Merece, sin embargo, más que tú esta mujer de que te hablo, porque tú no revelaste
a Colón mismo lo que él ya sabía de su propio valer. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09257</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>593243</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>737</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Was not you at this time the only Cordoba
who made love prophetess. Another came before you, who competed in this with you. Not worth much,
because the man whose future worth loving discovered her in his prophetic vision worth a thousand
times less than the strain of his intelligence and his revealing strong will have doubled or tripled
the greatness of the known world, and has magnified the concept of creation in every human mind.
Compared to the glory of man, which is worth little is achieved by defeating armies, conquering
kingdoms and subjugating and humiliating the chief more powerful. It is nevertheless more than
you this woman that I speak, because you have revealed no Columbus himself what he already knew his
own worth</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>