<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02429</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>0</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>14028</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>Quiero pasar en silencio, por no molestar al lector y porque no me tilde de prolijo y tal vez
de goloso, los hojaldres hechos de flor de harina y manteca de cerdo en pella; los multiformes
bizcochos, entre los cuales sobresale la torta o bollo maimón; los nuégados, los polvorones,
las sopaipas, los almíbares y las perrunas, exquisitas, a pesar de lo poco simpático del nombre
que llevan. Pero ¿cómo no detenerse en el debido encomio de ciertas empanadas, en mi sentir
deliciosas, y tan propias y privativas de por allá, que la mujer que no haya nacido cordobesa
no poseerá jamás el quid divinum que para amasarlas se requiere, ni acertará a darles el debido
punto de cochura? Estas empanadas son, en dicho sentido, incomunicables. Aunque en mayor escala,
acontece con ellas lo que con el turrón de Jijona, que al instante se conoce la falsificación.
Bien puede tener la mas docta cocinera la receta auténtica, exacta, minuciosa, de estas empanadas;
apuesto a que no las hace, si no es de mi provincia. A quien no ha comido de tales empanadas
le parecerá abominable que, constando el relleno de boquerones o sardinas con un picadillo
de tomates y cebollas, se tomen las empanadas con chocolate; pero así es la verdad, y están
buenas, aunque parezca inverosímil.

No es nuevo este arte de repostería y pastelería, ni su florecimiento entre las cordobesas.
Según un escrito fehaciente, reimpreso y divulgado poco ha (la verdadera historia de la Lozana
Andaluza), dicho arte florecía ya a principios del siglo XVI. Aquella insigne mujer, que era
cordobesa, hacía con admirable perfección casi todo cuanto aquí hemos mentado, si bien el autor
lo refiere de corrida, sin detenerse tanto como nosotros en el asunto. Probado deja, sin embargo,
que ya entonces era parte este gay saber en la educación de mis paisanas, y que de madres a
hijas ha venido trasmitiéndose hasta ahora por medio de la tradición. Así es que cualquiera
cordobesa, si no es manca y tiene mediano caletre, podrá jactarse en el día, como ha más de
tres siglos se jactaba la Lozana, si es que la modestia lo permite, de que sobrepuja a Platina
De voluptatibus y a Apicio Romano De re coquinaria.

Con todo, acerca de lo último (en lo tocante a cocina propiamente dicha), no hay, hablando
con franqueza, tanto de que jactarse como en la parte de repostería. Este arte, incluyendo
en él, aunque parezca disparatado, todo lo relativo a la matanza, es, en la provincia de Córdoba,
un arte más liberal, menos entregado a manos mercenarias. Apenas si hay hidalga, por encopetada
y perezosa que sea, que, según ya hemos dicho, no trabaje en estos negocios col seno e colla
mano. Ya sazona el adobo; ya hecha con su blanca diestra el aliño a las longanizas; ya rellena
tal cual chorizo con un embudito de lata; ya pincha las morcillas para que se les salga el
aire, valiéndose de una aguja de hacer calceta o de una horquilla que desprende de sus hermosos
cabellos.

Suele, en verdad, venir a las casas, en los días de matanza, o en los que preceden a la Noche-buena,
cuando se hacen mil golosinas, o durante la vendimia, para hacer el arrope y las gachas de
mosto, o poco antes de Semana Santa, para solemnizarla con hojuelas, pestiños, gajorros y piñonate,
alguna mujer perita, de tres o cuatro que hay siempre en cada lugar, la cual se pone al frente
de todo; pero rarísima vez la señora abdica en esta mujer por completo y se sustrae a toda
responsabilidad. Esta mujer no pasa de ser una ayudanta, una altera ego. Quien en realidad
dirige es el ama. Y sólo cede el ama la dirección, o, para hablar con rigorosa exactitud, no
la cede ni dimite, sino que comparte la responsabilidad y divide el imperio, cuando se da la
feliz circunstancia de que haya alguna mujer que sea un genio inspirado, con misión y vocación
singular para tales asuntos. Así sucedía en mi lugar con una mujer que llamaban Juana la Larga,
la cual murió ya; y es muy cierto que ha dejado una hija heredera de sus procedimientos arcanos:
pero el genio no se hereda, y la hija de Juana la Larga no llega, ni con mucho, adonde llegaba
su madre: es mucho menos larga en todo, como lo reconocen y declaran cuantas personas competentes
han conocido a la una y a la otra.

Con la cocina, con el guiso diario, hay muy distinto proceder. Una señora cuidadosa y casera
tendrá cuenta con lo que se guisa, irá a la despensa, dará órdenes: pero el verdadero guisar
queda enteramente al cuidado de la cocinera. De aquí lo decaído del arte. La cocina cordobesa
fue, sin duda, original y grande. Hoy es una ruina, como los palacios de Medina-Azahara y los
encantadores jardines de la Almunia. Sólo quedan algunos restos, que dan señales, que son como
reliquias de la grandeza pasada; restos que un hábil cocinero arqueólogo pudiera restaurar,
como ha restaurado Canina los antiguos monumentos de Roma.

Sería menester una pericia técnica, de que carezco, para caracterizar aquí la cocina cordobesa,
excelente aunque arruinada, y para definirla y distinguirla entre las demás cocinas de los
diversos pueblos, lenguas y tribus del globo.

El lector me perdonará que hable casi como profano en esta materia trascendente.

Yo creo que, sin desestimar la cocina francesa, que hoy priva y prevalece en el mundo, hay
restos y como raíces en la de Córdoba, que no deben menospreciarse. ¿Quién sabe si darán aún
opimos frutos sin desnaturalizarse con ingertos, sino conservando el ser castizo que tienen?

Las habas, a pesar del anatema de Pitágoras, que tal vez las condenó como afrodisíacas, son
el principal alimento de los campesinos de mi tierra. El guiso en que las preparan, llamado
por excelencia cocina, es riquísimo. Dudo yo que el más científico cocinero francés, sin más
que habas, aceite turbio, vinagre archi-turbio, pimientos, sal y agua, pueda sacar cosa tan
rica como dicha cocina de habas preparada por cualquiera mujer cordobesa. Del salmorejo, del
ajo-blanco y del gazpacho, afirmo lo propio, Será malo; harán mil muecas y melindres las damas
de Madrid si le comen; pero tomen los ingredientes, combínenlos, y ya veremos si producen algo
mejor.

Por lo demás, el salmorejo, dentro de la rustiqueza del pan prieto,

    Y los rojos pimientos y ajos duros,

de que principalmente consta, debe pasar por creación refinada en las artes del deleite, sobre
todo si se ha batido bien y largo tiempo por fuertes puños y en un ancho dornajo. En cuanto
al gazpacho, es saludable en tiempo de calor y después de las faenas de la siega, y tiene algo
de clásico y de poético. No era más que gazpacho lo que, según Virgilio, en la segunda Égloga,
preparaba Testilis para agasajo y refrigerio de los fatigados segadores:

    Allia, serpyllumque, herbas contundit olentes.

Dejo de hablar de la olla, caldereta, cochifrito, ajo de pollo y otros guisados, por no tener
diverso carácter en Córdoba que en las restantes provincias andaluzas. Sólo diré algo en defensa
de la alboronía, por haberse burlado de ella un agudo escritor, amigo mío, y por habernos suministrado
la ciencia moderna un medio de justificarla, y aun de probar, o rastrear al menos, que la antigua
cocina cordobesa fue una cocina aristocrática o casi regia, que ha venido degenerando. El sabio
orientalista Dozy demuestra que la inventora de la alboronía, o quien le dio su nombre, fue
nada menos que la Sultana Boran, hermosa, distinguida y comm'il faut entre todas las Princesas
del Oriente. Tal vez el creador de la alboronía dedicó su invención a esta Sultana, como hacen
hoy los más famosos cocineros, dedicando sus guisos y señalándolos con el nombre de algún ilustre
personaje. Así hay solomillo a la Chateaubriand, salmón a la Chambord, y otros condimentos
a la Soubisse, a la Bismarck, a la Thiers, a la Emperatriz, a la Reina y a la Pío IX. Para
mayor concisión se suprime el nombre de lo guisado y queda sólo el del personaje glorioso;
por donde cualquiera se come un Pío IX o un Chateaubriand, sin incurrir en antropofagia.

Sin duda, así como, en vista del aserto irrefragable de Dozy, la alboronía viene de la Sultana
Boran, la torta maimón y los maimones, que son unas a modo de sopas, deben provenir del Califa,
marido de la susodicha Boran, el cual se llamaba Maimón, ya que no provengan del gran filósofo
judío Maimónides, que era cordobés, y compatriota, por lo tanto, de los maimones, sopa, torta
y bollo.

Fuerza es confesar, a pesar de lo expuesto, que estas cosas se han maleado. Son como los refranes,
que fueron sentencias de los antiguos sabios y han venido a avillanarse; o como ciertas familias
de clara estirpe, que han caído en baja y oscura pobreza. Lástima es, por cierto, que así pase;
pues los primeros elementos son exquisitos para la cocina en toda la provincia de Córdoba.

Entre las jaras, tarajes, lentiscos y durillos, en la espesura de la fragosa sierra, a la sombra
de los altos pinos y copudos alcornoques, discurren valerosos jabalíes y ligeros corzos y venados:
por toda la feraz campiña abundan la liebre, el conejo, la perdiz y hasta el sison corpulento,
y toda clase de palomas, desde la torcaz hasta la zurita. No bien empieza a negrear y a madurar
la aceituna, acuden de Africa los zorzales, cuajando el aire con animadas nubes. El jilguero,
la oropéndola, la vejeta y el verdearon alegran la primavera con sus trinos amorosos. El gran
Guadalquivir da mantecosos sábalos y sollos enormes; y dan ancas de ranas y anguilas suaves
todos los arroyos y riachuelos. Sería proceder en infinito si yo contase aquí los productos
del reino vegetal, la Flora de aquella tierra predilecta del cielo, sobre la cual, según popular
convencimiento y arraigada creencia, está verticalmente colocado, en el cenit, el trono de
la Santísima Trinidad. Baste saber que las mil y tantas huertas de Cabra son un Paraíso. Allí,
si aun estuviese de moda la mitología, pudiéramos decir que puso su trono Pomona; y extendiéndonos
en esto, y sin la menor hipérbole, bien añadiríamos que Pales tiene su trono en las ermitas,
Ceres en los campos que se dilatan entre Baena y Valenzuela, y Baco el suyo en los Moriles,
cuyo vino supera en todo al de Jerez.

La cordobesa mira con desdén todo esto, o bien porque le es habitual y no le da precio, o bien
por su espiritualismo delicado. Sin embargo, algunas señoras ricas se esmeran en cuidar frutas
y en aclimatar otras poco comunes hasta ahora en aquellas regiones, como la fresa y la frambuesa.
Asimismo suele tener la cordobesa un corral bien poblado de gallinas, patos y pavos, que ella
misma alimenta y ceba; y ya logra verse, aunque rara vez, la desentonada y atigrada gallina
de Guinea. El faisán sigue siendo para mis paisanas un animal tan fabuloso como el fénix, el
grifo o el águila bicípite.

Donde verdadera y principalmente se luce la cordobesa es en el manejo interior de la casa.
Los versos en que Schiller encomia a sus paisanas, pudieran con más razón aplicarse a las mías.
No es la alemana la que describe el gran poeta: es la madre de familia de mi provincia o de
mi lugar:

      Ella en el reino aquél prudente manda;
    Reprime al hijo y a la niña instruye,
    Nunca para su mano laboriosa,
    Cuyo ordenado tino
    En rico aumento del caudal refluye.

¡Cómo se afana! ¡Cómo desde el amanecer va del granero a la bodega, y de la bodega a la despensa!
¡Cómo atisba la menor telaraña y hace al punto que la deshollinen, cuando no la deshollina
ella misma! ¡Cómo limpia el polvo de todos los muebles! ¡Con qué esmero alza en el armario
o guarda en el arca o en la cómoda la limpia ropa de mesa y cama, sahumada con alhucema! Ella
borda con primor, y no olvida jamás los mil pespuntes, calados, dobladillos y vainicas que
en la miga le enseñaban, y que hizo y reunió en un rico dechado, que conserva como grato recuerdo.
No queda camisa de hilo o de algodón que no marque, ni calceta cuyos puntos no encubra y junte,
ni desgarrón que no zurza, ni rotura que no remiende. Si es rica, ella y su marido y su prole
están siempre aseados y bien vestidos. Si es pobre, el domingo y los días de grandes fiestas
salen del fondo del arca las bien conservadas galas: mantón o pañolón de Manila, rica saya
y mantilla para ella; y para el marido una camisa bordada con pájaros y flores, blanca como
la nieve, un chaleco de terciopelo, una faja de seda encarnada o amarilla, un marsellé remendado,
unos zahones con botoncillos de plata dobles y de muletilla, y unos botines prolijamente bordados
de seda en el bien curtido becerro. Sobre todo esto, para ir a misa o a cualquier otra ceremonia
o visita de cumplido, se pone mi paisano la capa. Sería una falta de decoro, casi un desacato,
presentarse sin ella aunque señale el termómetro treinta grados de calor. En efecto, la capa,
como toda vestidura talar y rozagante, presta a la persona cierta amplitud, entono y prosopopeya.
No es esto decir que en mi tierra no se abuse de la capa. Me acuerdo de un médico que nos visitaba
en el lugar, siendo yo niño, el cual no la abandonaba jamás; iba embozado en ella y no se desembozaba
ni aun para tomar el pulso, tomándole por cima del embozo. Claro está que quien no se quita
jamás la capa, menos se quita el sombrero, sino en muy solemnes ocasiones. Hombre hay que ni
para dormir se le quita, trayéndole hacia la cara para defenderla del sol o de la luz, si duerme
la siesta al aire libre; así como se le lleva hacia el morrillo o cogote, sosteniéndole con
la mano, para saludar a las personas que más respeto y acatamiento le merecen. Pero volvamos
a nuestra cordobesa.

Pobre o rica se esmera, como he dicho, en la casa. En algunas hay ya habitaciones empapeladas,
pero lo común es el enjalbiego, lo cual será grosero y rústico si se quiere, mas alegra con
la blancura y da a todo un aspecto de limpieza. La misma ama, si es pobre, y si no la criada,
enjalbiega a menudo toda la casa, incluso la fachada. Esta manía de enjalbegar llegó a tal
extremo, que una señora de mi lugar, algunos años ha, enjalbegaba su piano; el primero que
apareció por allí. Ahora hay ya muchos y buenos, hasta de palo santo, y se cuentan por docenas
las señoras y señoritas que tocan y cantan.

</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10892</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1061</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>12868</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I pass over in silence, not to annoy the reader and because I tittle of neat and perhaps the greedy,
the pastries made of flour and lard in pella, the manifold cakes, among which stands the cake
or bun maimón; the nuego, polvorones, the sopaipas, syrups, and the canine, exquisite, despite
the cute little name they lead. But why not stop in the praise of some pies because, in my opinion
delicious, and so depriving themselves and there, a woman who was not born in Cordoba not possess
the crux never knead divinum that is required, and struck him due firing point? These empanadas
are, in that sense, incommunicable. Although larger scale what happens to them with frosting Jijona,
who instantly called counterfeiting. May well have learned the most authentic recipe cook, accurate,
thorough, these empanadas; I bet she does not, if it is not my province. Who has not eaten such
empanadas will seem abhorrent, consisting the anchovies or sardines stuffed with a picadillo tomatoes
and onions, pies are made with chocolate, but that's the truth, and are good, although it seems
unlikely.

Not new this art of baking and pastry, and its flowering between Cordoba.

According to a reliable written, little has been reprinted and released (the true story of Lozana
Andaluza), this art flourished as early as the sixteenth century. That famous woman, who was Cordoba,
made with remarkable perfection almost all this you have lied, but the author refers you to
run without stopping much as we do in the matter. Tested leaves, however, was already then eastern
gay knowledge in the education of my countrywomen, and that mothers daughters has been transmitting
it to date by means of tradition. So any Cordoba, if not maimed and has medium caletre may
boast on the day, as more than three centuries boasted the Lozana, if modesty allows, which
surpasses Platina In voluptatibus and Roman Apicius De re coquinaria.

In all, about the latter (with regard to proper cooking), no talking
frankly, as much to boast about at the bakery.

This art, including in it, although it seems crazy, everything about the killing, is in the
province of Cordoba, an art more liberal, less given to mercenary hands. There is hardly noble,
by swanky and lazy it is, that, as we have said, do not work in these businesses within and colla
col hand. And adobo seasoning, and his white right hand made the sausage dressing, and fill as
it embudito chorizo ??with tin, and click the black pudding for them comes out air, using a
knitting needle or a fork off of her beautiful hair.

Often, indeed, come home, in the days of slaughter, or in the preceding Night-good when making a
thousand sweets, or during harvest, to make the syrup and porridge
wine, or just before Easter, to solemnize with pancakes, fritters,
and Piñonate gajorros, a woman adept, three or four that are always
at each site, which takes the lead everything, but very rarely Mrs.
abdicates in this woman completely and removes all responsibility.

This woman is nothing but a helper, an alter ego. Who really addressed is the housekeeper. And the love
it gives only the direction, or to speak with rigorous exactness, no the sag or resigns, but
shares the responsibility and divided the empire, when given the happy circumstance that there is any
woman who is an inspired genius, with mission and vocation unique to such matters. This was so
in my place with a woman named Juana la Larga She died already, and it is certain that has
left an heiress daughter of arcane procedures: but genius is not inherited, and the daughter
of Juana la Larga not arrive, or by far reached where His mother is much less long at all, as
many people recognize and declare competent have met one and other.

In the kitchen with the daily dish, very different proceeding. A woman carefully and home will have
what is wise, go to the pantry, give orders, but the actual cooking left entirely to the care of
the cook. From here it lapsed art. Cordovan cuisine was certainly original and great. Today is
a ruin, as the palace of Medina Azahara and Almunia lovely gardens. Only a few traces remain, giving
signals, which are like relics of past greatness, remains a skilled
cook archaeologist could restore Dog and restored the ancient monuments
of Rome.

It would need a technical expertise that I lack, to characterize the cuisine here in Cordoba,
excellent, though ruined, and to define and distinguish it from other kitchens diverse peoples,
languages ??and tribes of the globe.

The reader will forgive me almost profane to speak on this important
matter.

I believe that, without underestimating the French cuisine, private
and prevails today in the world, there remains as rooted in Cordoba,
which should not be underestimated.

Who knows whether they will still OPIM denatured fruits without grafts,
but retaining the castizo be having?

Beans, despite the anathema of Pythagoras, that perhaps condemned
as an aphrodisiac, are the main food of the peasants in my home.

The stew that prepare them, called ultimate kitchen is delicious. I doubt that the more scientific
French chef, without further than beans, oil, cloudy, cloudy arch-vinegar, pepper, salt and
water, can make something so rich as that cooking beans prepared by any woman in Cordoba. The
gazpacho, the garlic-white and gazpacho, I say the same, will be bad, make a thousand faces
and fussiness ladies Madrid if you eat, but take the ingredients, combine them, and we'll see
if they produce something better.

Moreover, the gazpacho, within the tight rustiqueza bread,

And the
red peppers and garlic hard

that mainly consists, must pass through
fine arts creation of delight on especially if it has been well beaten
by strong and long cuffs and a wide trough.

As the gazpacho, healthy in hot weather and after the harvest chores,
and has something classical and poetic.

    Gazpacho was nothing more than what, according to Virgil, in the
second Eclogue, Testilis preparing for entertainment and refreshment
of the weary reapers

Allia, serpyllumque, Herba contundit olentes.

Let's talk about the pot, stew, cochifrito, garlic chicken and other dishes, not having Cordoba
different character than in other Andalusian provinces. Just say something in defense the alboronía,
for having made fun of her a keen writer, my friend, and for providing
us modern science a means to justify and even to prove, or to trace
at least the old Cordoba kitchen was a kitchen almost aristocratic
or royal, who has been degenerating.

    Sage Dozy Orientalist shows that the inventor of the alboronía, or
who gave it its name, was Sultana nothing less than the Boran, beautiful,
distinguished and comm'il faut among all Princesses East.

Perhaps the creator of the alboronía dedicated his invention to the Sultana, as do Today the
most famous chefs, devoting her cooking and assigned the name of some illustrious character. Thus
there is the Chateaubriand steak, salmon Chambord, and other seasonings the Soubisse, the Bismarck, the
Thiers, the Empress, the Queen and Pius IX. To more concise name deleted from the stew and it is
only the glorious character; where anyone eats a Pius IX or Chateaubriand, without incurring cannibalism.

Without
doubt, and, given the irrefutable assertion of Dozy, the alboronía comes from the Sultana Boran,
cake and maimones maimón, which are a way of soups, must come of Califa, Boran aforementioned
husband, whose name was Maimon, since it does not come from the great philosopher Jewish Maimonides
was Cordoba, and compatriot, therefore, the maimones, soup, cake and bun.

Force is to confess, despite the above, that these things have been perverted. They are like
proverbs, they were statements of the ancient sages and have come to abasement, or as some
families of clear lineage, which have fallen into poverty, low and
dark.

Pity is, of course, that this happens; as the first elements are fine for cooking in the province
of Cordoba.

Among the rock rose, tamarisk, mastic and durum, the thickness of the craggy mountains, shaded
of the tall pines and oaks copudos, courageous run wild boars and
roe deer and deer light: across the fertile countryside abound hare,
rabbit, partridge and even the big ssion, and all kinds of pigeons
from the dove to zurita.

As soon begins to blacks and mature olives, thrushes come from Africa, curdling the air with animated
clouds. The goldfinch the oriole, the old man and the green happy with their songs of spring love.
The large Guadalquivir gives huge buttery shad and pike, and frog legs are soft and eels all the
rivers and streams.

Would proceed if I tell here infinite products the plant kingdom, the Flora of the land beloved
of heaven, on which, as popular conviction and strong belief, is vertically placed at the zenith,
the throne the Holy Trinity. Suffice to know that the thousand or so gardens are a paradise Cabra.
There if it was even fashionable mythology, we might say he put his throne Pomona, and extending
in this, and without the slightest hyperbole, either add that Palestine has its throne in the
chapels, Ceres in the fields which extend between Baena and Valenzuela, and Bacchus in his Moriles
which surpasses all the wine of Jerez.

The Cordoba looks with disdain all this, or because it is common and does not give money or by its
spiritualism delicate. However, some women are careful to look rich fruit and other rare acclimate
so far in those regions, such as strawberries and raspberries. Cordoba also usually have a well
populated poultry chickens, ducks and turkeys, which she feeding and fattening itself, and it does
look, though rarely, the tiger out of tune and chicken of Guinea. The pheasant is still an animal
for my countrywomen as fabulous as the phoenix, bicípite tap or the eagle.

Which looks real and is primarily the management of Cordoba is inside the house. The verses in
which Schiller praised his countrywomen, could a fortiori apply to mine. German is not that described
by the great poet is the mother of my province or my place

Him in the kingdom that sends prudent; Restrain the child and the child instructed, Never for
laborious hand, Whose ordered tino In rich flow increased reflows.

How is busy! How from the dawn of the barn is the winery, and cellar to the pantry! I glimpse
the lower web and makes the point that the sweep, if not sweep herself! How to clean the dust from
all furniture! With what care up in the closet or saved in the ark or the clean comfortable
bed and table linen, perfumed with lavender!

      She overboard with delicacy, and never
    forgets a thousand stitches, lace, hems
    and green beans that in the crumb
    taught him, and he
    did and met a rich sampler, which remains a sweet memory.

It is not linen shirt or cotton do not check or sock which does not overshadow and collect points,
Darn tear or not, or not mend broken. If rich, she and her husband and her children are always
neat and well dressed. If he is poor, the Sundays and major holidays ark out of the bottom
of the well-preserved galas: Manila shawl or shawl, rich saya and blanket for her, and her husband
a shirt embroidered with birds and flowers, white Snow, a velvet waistcoat, a strip of red
or yellow silk, a Marseille patched some chaps with double silver buttonwood and crutch, and a neatly
embroidered boots Silk in the well tanned calf. Above all this, to go to church or any other ceremony
or visit fulfilled my countryman becomes the layer. It would be a lack of decorum, almost in
contempt, presented without her even point the thermometer thirty degrees of heat. Indeed, coating,
as every garment cut and ruddy, the person pays a certain extent, and dignity, solemnity.
This is not to say that in my land should not be abused layer. I remember a doctor who visited
us in place, when I was child, who never abandons us, was wrapped in it and not blatant even to take
the pulse, taking him for top of her veil. It is clear that he is not removed layer never less took
off his hat, but on very solemn occasions. Man is neither sleep is taken away, bringing to the face
to defend it from the sun or light, if he sleeps outdoor nap, and it leads to the rubble or neck,
holding with hand to greet the people most respect and deference I deserve. But back our Cordoba.

Strives
poor or rich, as I said, at home. In some rooms there is already papered, but the common thing the
enjalbiego, which will be rude and rustic if you like, but rejoices with whiteness and gives every
appearance of cleanliness. The same love, if he is poor, if not the maid, enjalbiega often throughout
the house, including the facade. This mania reached such a whitewash end, a lady from my place,
some years ago, whitewashed his piano, the first arrived there. There are now many good, even
rosewood, and the dozens ladies and girls who play and sing.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>