<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>266235</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23990</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Burlarse en
aquel acto solemne donde se festejaba la regeneración moral y material de Peñascosa, era una
insolencia, y como decía muy bien D. Juan Casanova, «no daba buena idea de la cultura de la
prensa de Lancia.» No se besaron, pues, aunque D. Gaspar mostró ciertas tendencias a hacerlo,
aproximando demasiadamente sus narices color violeta al rostro del aparecido; pero éste lo
retiró, dando pruebas de prudencia, pues se hablaba en términos muy graves por Peñascosa de
las narices de D. Gaspar.

Terminado el himno, comenzó de nuevo y se repitió indefinidamente hasta los postres. El gobernador
volvió a dirigir la palabra al público. A unos gobernadores les da por destituir ayuntamientos,
a otros por llevarse los colchones que les pone la Diputación provincial. A éste le daba por
la elocuencia. Le contestó D. Peregrín Casanova, y tuvo ocasión de llamarle «mi distinguido
compañero» y aludir a los altos deberes que impone el gobierno de una provincia, «que él había
tratado de cumplir en otro tiempo en la medida de sus débiles fuerzas.» Habló también D. José
María el boticario, abogando por el fomento de la religión como «elemento de progreso» (le
quedaban ciertas frasecillas del tiempo en que era librepensador) y como «freno para los apetitos
bastardos.» Habló don José el estanquero; habló D. Remigio Flórez, el fabricante de conservas
alimenticias; habló el director de El Porvenir de Lancia (que hacía pocos días se había batido
a sable con D. Rosendo Belinchón, director de El Faro de Sarrió). Y habló otra vez el gobernador.
Un redactor de El Joven Sarriense trató de pronunciar algunas palabras, pero le interrumpieron
con algunos murmullos desde los palcos, y se sentó muy desabrido. Por último, D. Gaspar de
Silva avanzó por el escenario con un papel en la mano. «¡Silencio! ¡Chis, chis!... ¡Que se
callen!--¡Silencio! ¡Fuera!--¡Chis, chis!» En medio de un silencio religioso, el famoso vate
de Peñascosa comenzó a leer con voz dramática una Oda a la Religión. Los temas sagrados no
eran su especialidad. Había preferido siempre poner la lira al servicio de la libertad y de
las ideas democráticas. Su mejor composición era un soneto al pacto sinalagmático bilateral.
Comprendiendo, sin embargo, con profunda intuición, el sublime destino que el cielo le había
designado, cantaba, como los vates y semidioses de la antigüedad, todo lo que se ofrecía a
su vista, la paz y la guerra, la democracia y los señoríos, la religión y el libre pensamiento.
Esta oda, que empezaba: «¡Oh dulce religión inmaculada!» era inspiradísima y fue recibida con
vivas muestras de aprobación. El banquete terminó de noche cerrada.

A las seis, el sacristán y algunos empleados del municipio comenzaron a iluminar los farolillos
a la veneciana del Campo de los Desmayos, de tal modo que a las ocho estaban casi todos encendidos.
La velada se presentó muy alegre. En uno de los ángulos del Campo bailaban los aldeanos al
son de la gaita y el tambor; en otro hacían lo propio las artesanas al compás de la banda municipal.
La gente discurría por el espacio libre cada vez con menos desahogo, pues la calle del Cuadrante
no cesaba de vomitar blusas azules y pañuelos de percal sobre el citado Campo. Lo más exquisito
de la sociedad peñasquense se refugió en el pórtico de la iglesia, estableciendo la consabida
división de castas. Organizose un paseo inmediatamente donde los forasteros de Lancia pudieran
apreciar de un solo golpe de vista todo lo grande y majestuoso que encerraba Peñascosa en su
seno. Allí estaba la tertulia en masa de D.ª Eloisa, y además, otra parte de la nobleza de
la villa, con la cual no hemos podido poner al lector en relación. Después de haber disfrutado
por largo rato del placer de verse, como los inmortales en el Olimpo, aislados y encima del
resto de los seres de la creación, aquella sociedad hizo irrupción en el Campo de los Desmayos,
para contemplar los fuegos artificiales de los renombrados pirotécnicos palentinos. Entró sin
descomponerse, con un desdén y una gravedad calculados para henchir de respeto el corazón de
las castas inferiores.

Deslizándose como un mono por los parajes oscuros, buscando la proximidad de las mujeres obesas,
y cuando no, la de las que estaban en regulares carnes, andaba nuestro amigo Osuna, el administrador
de la casa Montesinos. A la hora en que le sorprendemos no se había ganado más que una bofetada;
caso extraño, porque en estas noches de jolgorio solía encontrarse con media docena, por lo
menos. Algo desengañado bajo este aspecto, no tanto por las bofetadas como por lo que las precedía,
movíase impaciente echando miradas carniceras en torno suyo, sin hallar un sitio lo bastante
ameno y deleitoso para fijar sus pasos. Aquella noche se habían dado cita todas las flacas
de Peñascosa. Mas hete aquí que cuando empieza a arder la primera rueda de pólvora, columbra
no muy lejos a la fresca D.ª Teodora, al sueño constante de su existencia, más radiante y más
lozana que nunca, con sus cabellos blancos y sus mejillas rosadas de cutis terso y brillante.
Verla y emprender la marcha hacia ella fue todo uno. Pero esta marcha en tales circunstancias
era más difícil de lo que cualquiera puede imaginarse. La gente se apiñaba a ver los fuegos
y permanecía inmóvil, formando una espesa muralla. Nuestro jorobado la atravesó con arte diabólico,
retorciéndose como una lagartija para pasar por los agujeros más estrechos. Después de un buen
rato logró colocarse detrás de la simpática jamona. Estaba escoltada por los dos hermanos Casanova,
que la habían acompañado en unión de la doncella. Continuaban disputándose su corazón, con
empeño rabioso por parte de D. Peregrín, con noble y severa tranquilidad por la de D. Juan.
En este certamen de amor la virtuosa y madura señorita padecía mucho, por creerse culpable
de las reyertas que a lo mejor estallaban entre los dos hermanos. Procuraba conservar la neutralidad,
pero se echaba de ver que D. Peregrín llevaba la peor parte. Explicábale éste, con el tono
de suficiencia que le caracterizaba, algunos pormenores interesantes de la industria pirotécnica
y citaba algunos fuegos que había visto, en su época de covachuelista, verdaderamente asombrosos.
El pobre D. Juan, que no había salido jamás del estrecho recinto de Peñascosa y que no podía
citar nada, callaba como siempre. Pero la pulquérrima jamona le dirigía de vez en cuando una
mirada suave y una sonrisa más suave aún, que podían indemnizarle de su vida sedentaria.

Cuando D.ª Teodora volvió la cabeza para ver quién la apretaba tanto y se encontró con Osuna,
cambió de color. Aquel maldito jorobado no la dejaba jamás en paz. En la tertulia, en el paseo,
en el teatro, en la iglesia, en todas partes donde tuviera ocasión de aproximarse, era sabido
que se veía necesitada a sufrir el contacto asqueroso de sus piernas y a veces de sus manos
también. Osuna conocía bien el terreno que pisaba. La bella y pudorosa jamona se hubiera caído
antes muerta de vergüenza que confesar a alguno los atentados de que era objeto. Pero si no
los confesaba, cualquiera podría cerciorarse de ellos, observando el estado de agitación en
que se hallaba. En esta ocasión el jorobado anduvo audaz en demasía. D.ª Teodora comenzó a
dar muestras tales de inquietud que para cualquiera serían visibles. D. Juan no las vio, sin
embargo. Era un varón puro y magnánimo, incapaz de sospechar las grandes suciedades que puede
haber sobre la tierra. Pero D. Peregrín, como hombre de mundo, concluyó por advertir algo de
lo que pasaba. Espió a Osuna con el rabillo del ojo, y cuando penetró en su espíritu gubernamental
el convencimiento de la trasgresión que se estaba cometiendo, comenzó a roncar y silbar por
la nariz como un vapor en peligro, lanzando al mismo tiempo centelleantes miradas de indignación
al audaz jorobado. Éste prescindió en absoluto de aquellos silbidos temerosos, y no vio siquiera
la expresión fatídica de los ojos del ex-gobernador interino de Tarragona. ¿Qué había de suceder?
La caldera del remolcador, no teniendo más desahogo que el de la nariz, estalló con horrible
estruendo.

--¡Oiga usted, grosero, sucio, cínico, desorejado!--rugió D. Peregrín cogiendo por el cuello
al contrahecho y sacudiéndole con rabia.--Si usted continúa en modo alguno molestando a esta
señora, con esta mano (alzando la derecha) le doy una bofetada en esta mejilla, y con la otra
(alzando la izquierda) le doy otra bofetada en la opuesta. Acto continuo le vuelvo a usted,
y con estas botas gordas que usted ve aquí le doy a usted dos puntapiés en el trasero.

El físico de D. Peregrín no era a propósito para infundir terror pánico en el corazón de sus
enemigos. Sin embargo, su continente severo y administrativo como pocos y el torrente de voz
grandioso con que la naturaleza le dotara suplían bastante bien la deficiencia de otros órganos.
Además, Osuna era un ser más débil y más ruin que él. Por esto y por el tumulto que se armó
en seguida, en vez de hacerle frente, se escurrió entre la muchedumbre y desapareció en un
momento. D.ª Teodora, al verse objeto de la curiosidad pública, se desmayó. D. Juan y la doncella
la sostuvieron. D. Peregrín siguió increpando a su enemigo ausente. La muchedumbre rió, gritó,
se agitó tumultuosamente. Al fin todo quedó en paz, y la pudibunda jamona tornó a su domicilio,
donde la dejaremos esparciendo un torrente de lágrimas.

Obdulia, agitada todo el día por un vivo dolor y por un deseo rabioso de reparar la injusticia
que se había cometido con su amado director espiritual, no salió de casa ni de la cama. Estaba
realmente enferma. Tenía fiebre, la fiebre que produce en los temperamentos como el de ella
un pensamiento único que se va exacerbando por grados. Al llegar la noche se levantó y se vistió
apresuradamente. Sus grandes ojeras azuladas se marcaban ahora de un modo chocante. Una arruga
profunda, signo de resolución inquebrantable, le surcaba la frente. Llamó a la doncella y le
manifestó que quería salir a ver los fuegos. Todo lo que ésta hizo por disuadirla, representándole
el grave daño que podía ocasionarle el frío y la humedad de la noche, fue inútil. Cogió la
mantilla, se la echó encima de la cabeza con mano convulsa, obligó a la doméstica a ponerse
la suya y se lanzaron a la calle. El Campo de los Desmayos hervía ya de gente. Les costó mucho
trabajo avanzar hasta colocarse en el medio. Obdulia quería a todo trance acercarse a la casa
del párroco, donde se alojaba el prelado. Había visto brillar las gafas de éste y ocultarse
en seguida en una de las ventanas. Debajo, a la puerta misma de la rectoral, un grupo numeroso
de muchachas bailaba la giraldilla, cantando a grito pelado coplas de circunstancias improvisadas
en el momento. Aludían en ellas a la nueva iglesia, piropeaban al obispo, al gobernador, a
los próceres de Peñascosa, sin que faltase tampoco, por supuesto, la consabida puntadita a Sarrió.

La imaginación de la hija de Osuna trabajaba sin descanso, aumentando la calentura que la consumía.
Mas por encima de los mil pensamientos y fantasmas que daban vueltas en ella, asomaba una idea
fija, tenaz, que la impulsaba inconscientemente a abrirse paso con los codos por la muchedumbre,
seguida de la doncella, que no comprendía el afán de su señorita. Cuando estuvieron próximas
a la rectoral, la joven se detuvo unos minutos. Observó con el rabillo del ojo a su doncella,
y cuando la vio más absorta en la contemplación de los fuegos que se estaban quemando, maniobró
hábilmente y se alejó de ella ocultándose entre la gente. Una vez sola, se detuvo otra vez.
Después de dirigir infinitas miradas de ansiedad y temor a la casa del párroco, después de
resolverse más de veinte veces y de arrepentirse otras tantas, al fin se deslizó como una sombra
por detrás de las muchachas que bailaban y del círculo de espectadores que tenían en torno,
y se introdujo en el portal de la casa. Dentro de él había unos cuantos criados que charlaban
contemplando desde allí lo que podían. Tenían la puerta abierta, y Obdulia, sin decirles palabra,
se introdujo por ella y subió unas cuantas escaleras. Pero deteniéndose de repente y permaneciendo
un instante indecisa, tornó a bajarlas y se dirigió al grupo de los domésticos.

--¿El secretario del señor obispo está arriba?--preguntó al más próximo.

--¿D. Cayetano?... Sí, señora, arriba está--respondió uno de los más lejanos.

--¿Podría hablar unas palabras con él?

--¿Por qué no?... Le avisaré... Suba usted conmigo.

Ascendieron ambos por la sucia escalera de D. Miguel, pues ni por la llegada del prelado se
había limpiado.

--Tenga usted la bondad de aguardar un momento.

Poco después se presentaba el secretario, un clérigo de media edad, feo, desgarbado, pero de
mirada inteligente y franca. La miró con gran curiosidad y preguntó, esforzándose en mostrarse
amable:

--¿Preguntaba usted por mí, señora?

--Sí, señor.

--Usted me dirá...

--Deseo hablar con el señor obispo.

Volvió a mirarla el secretario con mayor curiosidad aún, y después de un instante de vacilación,
apareciendo en su rostro un esbozo de sonrisa, respondió:

--Usted comprenderá que la hora no es oportuna... Su Ilustrísima se va a retirar en seguida
a descansar...

--Es urgente y de mucha importancia lo que tengo que comunicarle...--dijo precipitadamente.

Otra vez la contempló el clérigo con penetrante mirada, advirtiendo su agitación.

--Bueno... Lo que puedo hacer en su obsequio es avisar a Su Ilustrísima... No respondo de que
la reciba a usted a estas horas... Puede usted pasar a esta sala y aguardar un momento. No
tardaré en traerle la respuesta.

Abrió la puerta del saloncito de recibo, hizo traer un quinqué y la dejó sola. En aquel instante
la joven sintió que le abandonaban todas sus fuerzas. El corazón comenzó a darle fuertes golpes
en el pecho. La habitación se movía suavemente como la cámara de un buque. Se vio obligada
a sujetarse con las dos manos al respaldo de una butaca para no venir al suelo. El secretario
apareció a los pocos minutos, y sin traspasar el marco de la puerta, dijo con afectada solemnidad:

--Su Ilustrísima va a llegar en este momento.

Obdulia cerró los ojos y se agarró con más fuerza a la butaca. Cuando los abrió tenía delante
de sí la figura imponente del prelado.

La estancia se hallaba a media luz a causa de la pantalla que cubría el quinqué. Los contornos
de aquella figura se esfumaban en la sombra. Pero los diamantes del pectoral lanzaban destellos
y los cristales de las gafas brillaban también con los débiles rayos de luz que sobre ellos
caían. Avanzó algunos pasos por la sala. Obdulia se dejó caer de rodillas.

--¿Es para algún asunto de conciencia, hija mía?--preguntole el prelado dulcemente, dándole
al mismo tiempo su anillo a besar.

--Sí, señor--respondió la joven con voz alterada por la emoción.--Es para un asunto de la conciencia
de Su Ilustrísima.

--¿De mi conciencia?--exclamó el obispo, irguiéndose lentamente y dejando caer sobre ella una
mirada de sorpresa y curiosidad.

--La conciencia más pura, Su Ilustrísima lo sabe mejor que yo, está sujeta a error. Cuando
pensamos estar haciendo el bien hacemos el mal. El alma de Su Ilustrísima es noble y es santa,
según dicen todos los que la conocen. Por algo Dios le ha elegido para apacentar su rebaño.
Pero los ojos de Su Ilustrísima no llegan a todas partes como los de Dios. Su brazo se extiende
en vano para bendecir. La bendición no alcanza a todos. Entre los pastores que Su Ilustrísima
tiene colocados para ayudarle los hay que guardan con fidelidad y amor el rebaño, los hay también
que tienen la vista y el amor fijos en sí mismos...

--Levántese usted, hija mía... ¿Qué quiere decir con estas palabras?

--Lo que quiero decirle, señor--profirió la hija de Osuna con audacia, serenándose de pronto
bajo el impulso de la exaltación,--es que teníamos en esta villa un coadjutor celoso, modelo
de abnegación, de mansedumbre, de actividad, que había logrado a fuerza de inmensos sacrificios
inspirar devoción y piedad a muchos que jamás las habían sentido, que sin violencia ninguna
había puesto en orden la parroquia y devuelto a Dios lo que le pertenecía... Pues bien, he
sabido... hemos sabido con dolor los feligreses todos, que en vez de dejarle en el cargo que
desempeñaba interinamente, Su Ilustrísima se lo ha dado a otra persona...

El obispo la contempló en silencio un buen espacio. La joven, bajo aquella mirada, que pasaba
por los cristales de las gafas penetrante, indagadora, volvió a perder la serenidad.

--¿Es el coadjutor interino quien la envía a usted para dirigirme una representación?--preguntó
con extremado sosiego, recalcando cada sílaba de un modo que resultaba epigramático.

--¡Oh! ¡No, señor!--exclamó toda turbada la joven, poniéndose roja.--El señor coadjutor no
tiene aspiración ninguna. Está tan contento con el cargo como sin él. Nada sabe ni nada quiero
que sepa... He sido yo quien por el odio que me inspira la injusticia me atreví a dar este
paso... acaso imprudentemente...

--¡Sin acaso! ¡Sin acaso!--murmuró el prelado, sacudiendo la cabeza.

Quedósela otra vez mirando fijamente sin pestañear, absorto en intensa contemplación. Obdulia
bajó la cabeza.

--Hija mía--siguió diciendo gravemente,--la juventud tiene sus derechos. Puede ser aturdida,
imprevisora, gozar sin medida de los dones con que Dios nos ha favorecido, vivir ofuscada sin
el pensamiento del pecado... Pero la juventud no tiene derecho a jugar con nuestra salvación
eterna, con la vida y con la muerte. La Santa Iglesia Católica tiene sus ministros encargados
de velar por la fe. Yo, aunque indigno, soy uno de ellos y soy responsable ante Dios y ante
el Sumo Pontífice de mis actos. No he aprendido en ningún Santo Padre ni en ninguna decretal
que los prelados tuviéramos que dar cuenta de ellos a las niñas como usted...

--¡Oh, señor obispo... yo no quería!...

--Escuche usted, escuche usted con paciencia, hija mía, escuche usted de rodillas a su prelado.

Obdulia se arrodilló de nuevo llena de confusión, roja como una amapola. La figura corpulenta
del obispo se agrandó desmesuradamente delante de sus ojos; su blanca cabeza coronada por el
morado solideo resplandecía de majestad.

--Los cargos de la Iglesia católica no deben ser empleos codiciados: no se buscan, se aceptan
con humildad y resignación. Cuanto más alto, más duro y espinoso es para el que quiere servir
a Dios. Usted, al hablar de injusticia, los ha considerado por lo visto como una granjería,
y ha pecado gravemente. Si no he dado el cargo de coadjutor a la persona por quien usted se
interesa, esa persona debe agradecérmelo, pues la he librado de muchas terribles responsabilidades
que dificultarían su salvación eterna.

Obdulia, viendo el rayo marchar otra vez hacia su confesor, halló palabras para desviarlo.

--Vuelvo a decirle, señor obispo, que el padre Gil nada sabe de este paso... que se morirá
de pena y de vergüenza si llega a conocerlo, porque es la modestia y la humildad personificadas.
La estimación y el respeto que le profeso, como todos los vecinos de este pueblo, y mi deseo
de ver la parroquia en orden y bien servida, me impulsaron en un momento de ligereza a acudir
a Su Ilustrísima...

--Pero ¿no comprende usted, hija, que al dar este paso, extraño en una joven sensata y piadosa,
se compromete usted, y lo que es peor, compromete usted a un sacerdote gravemente?

--¡Oh Virgen Santa! ¿Qué he hecho?--exclamó la joven tapándose la cara con las manos.--Sí,
sí, comprendo ahora que he sido una loca, que tratando de hacer un bien he causado un terrible
mal... Su Ilustrísima me desprecia y tiene razón, porque no soy más que una pobre tonta...
Pero no es eso lo malo... Lo horrible es que de aquí en adelante estará prevenido contra un
pobre inocente... ¡Jesús de mi corazón, qué tentación ha sido la mía!...

Y rompió a sollozar perdidamente murmurando frases ininteligibles. El prelado se inclinó hacia
ella y le habló con dulzura.

--Sosiéguese usted, hija mía. Sosiéguese usted y aprenda que un sucesor de los Apóstoles no
puede sentir prevención ni odio. Si usted ha pecado, pida la absolución a su confesor. Serénese
usted, que ningún mal ha causado más que a sí misma... Ni el inocente ni el culpable tienen
nada que temer de mí. Que lo teman todo de Dios...

Después de pedir muchas veces perdón y derramar infinitas lágrimas, Obdulia besó otra vez con
devoción el anillo del prelado, y se levantó. Sin alzar los ojos del suelo murmuró débilmente:

--Adiós, señor obispo. Perdone Su Ilustrísima el disgusto que le he causado, y olvídelo.

--Que la Virgen Santísima la proteja, hija mía. Rece una salve por mí, que bien la necesito--respondió
el prelado, dejándola pasar y mirándola con expresión de lástima hasta que traspasó la puerta.

Salió aturdida, loca de vergüenza, con las manos trémulas y las mejillas encendidas. En cuanto
llegó a casa se metió en la cama, con una fiebre altísima.

XI

Ya está descifrado el enigma, padre Gil--dijo D. Álvaro desde su butaca viéndole entrar. La
sonrisa con que acompañó estas palabras era tan contraída y extraña que daba frío.

--¿Qué enigma?--preguntó el P. Gil, un poco agitado por el presentimiento de alguna desgracia.

--No se asuste usted; no es el de la Creación: un enigma más modesto, el de la venida de mi
mujer a Peñascosa hace unos meses... Entérese usted de esa carta.

El joven presbítero tomó de las manos del mayorazgo la que le presentaba y se puso a leer:

       *       *       *       *       *

«Mi querido Álvaro: Acabo de saber que Joaquina dio a luz hace seis días un niño, el cual se
ha inscrito en la parroquia y en el registro civil con tu apellido. He procurado informarme,
y me han dicho que era perfectamente legítimo, puesto que tu esposa ha estado en Peñascosa
hace unos meses y ha dormido en tu misma casa. Te escribo apresuradamente para preguntarte
si es cierto. Lo dudo mucho, porque no me has dicho jamás una palabra del asunto. Contéstame
inmediatamente.

JULIO.»

       *       *       *       *       *

El P. Gil dejó caer los brazos, dobló la cabeza y murmuró sordamente:

--¡Qué infamia!

El mayorazgo soltó una carcajada.

--Pero ¿aún cree usted que hay infamias en el mundo? ¿De qué le sirve a usted tanto como ha
leído? Quisiera que me explicase cómo es posible hacer porquerías dentro de una letrina. Por
lo visto, todavía se encuentra usted asistiendo a la primera representación de la comedia.
Yo estoy en la segunda, y puedo decir anticipadamente lo que ha de suceder.

--De todos modos, D. Álvaro, me duele en el alma esta indignidad que con usted se ha cometido
sin merecerla.

--¿Indignidad? ¿Llama usted indigna a la araña que ahoga a la pobre mosca en su tela, o al
milano que cae sobre el inocente polluelo y lo arrebata por el aire? Pues la misma fuerza infame
(¡ésa sí que es la infame!), la misma fuerza que mueve a la araña y al milano es la que habita
dentro de mi mujer. La mosca, el pollo y yo merecemos la misma suerte por haber nacido. Porque
el delito mayor--del hombre es haber nacido, ya lo ha dicho Calderón, que era sacerdote como usted.

El P. Gil meditó unos momentos, y dijo al cabo, como si se hablase a sí mismo:

--No puedo acabar de persuadirme a que en nosotros no exista más que la fuerza ciega; que esta
luz que de vez en cuando brilla en el corazón de los hombres, y que se llama unas veces justicia,
otras amor y abnegación, dependa exclusivamente de combinaciones químicas. La infamia es infamia
siempre, y despierta en nuestro espíritu un sentimiento de repugnancia. La araña y el milano
no saben que hacen el mal, pero su esposa lo sabe.

--¿Y qué importa? Dote usted a la bestia con la conciencia de sus actos y habrá usted formado
al hombre. La conciencia no es más que una antorcha. Los crímenes lo mismo pueden ejecutarse
en las tinieblas que a la luz. Si yo pensase, como usted, que hay un Dios creador consciente
de todos los seres, le mandaría un «besa la mano» felicitándole por haber formado una criatura
tan amable y encantadora como mi mujer y dándole las gracias por haberla reservado para mi
uso particular. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>210677</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21221</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> In mock where
the ceremony that celebrated the moral and material regeneration Peñascosa was a insolence,
and as rightly said D. Juan Casanova, "was not a good idea of ??the culture of Lancia press.
"kissed not because, although D. Gaspar was certain tendencies to do so, their noses too close
to the face of purple appeared, but this one withdrew, giving evidence of prudence, because
it spoke in terms of very serious Peñascosa D. noses Gaspar.

Finished the anthem, started again and repeated indefinitely to desserts. Governor again addressed
the floor to the public. A few governors to oust gives municipalities, others because they take
the mattresses placed the Provincial. To him was by eloquence. D. replied Peregrin Casanova,
and was able to call him "my distinguished companion "and allude to the high duties imposed
by the government of a province," he had tried to meet once the extent of weak forces. "He also
spoke D. José Mary the apothecary, advocating the advancement of religion as "an element of progress"
(le frasecillas were certain that the time was a freethinker) and as "obstacle to the desires
bastards. "Jose spoke the tobacconist, spoke D. Remigio Flórez, the manufacturer of canned food,
spoke the editor of El Porvenir Lancia (a few days ago that he had fought a saber D. Rosendo
Belinchón, director of The Lighthouse Sarrió). And the governor spoke again. An editor of The
Young Sarrio tried to say a few words, but he was interrupted with a few murmurs from the boxes,
and sat very bland. Finally, D. Gaspar Silva walked across the stage with a paper in his hand.
"Silence! Chis, hush! ... That shut up! - Silence! Out! - Chis, hush! "In the midst of a religious
silence, the famous bard of rocks began to read an ode to dramatic voice of religion. No sacred
subjects were his specialty. He had always preferred to put the lira to the service of freedom
and democratic ideas. His best composition was a sonnet to synallagmatic bilateral pact. Understanding,
however, with profound insight, the sublime destination that heaven had designated sang, as
poets and demigods of antiquity, all that is offered his view, peace and war, democracy and
manors, religion and free thought. This ode, which began: "Oh sweet religion immaculate!" Was
spirited and was greeted with live samples approval. The banquet ended dark.

At six o'clock the sexton and some city employees began to illuminate the lanterns the Venetian
Field of fainting, so that the eight were almost all on.

The evening was made very happy. In one corner of the villagers danced to Country sound of the
bagpipe and drum, and another did the same the craft to the beat of the municipal band. People ran
through the free space less and less relief, as the street Quadrant could not stop vomiting
blue blouses and scarves on the above Country percale. The most exquisite peñasquense society took refuge
on the porch of the church, establishing the familiar caste divisions. Organizose a walk immediately
where strangers could Lancia see at a single glance all the great and majestic in its enclosed
Peñascosa breast. There was the mass gathering of Ms Eloisa, and also another part of the nobility
The villa, with which we could not put the reader in relationship. Having enjoyed for a long time
the pleasure of seeing, as the immortals on Mount Olympus, isolated and above other created
beings, that society was breaking into the field of Fainting to watch the fireworks from the
renowned pyrotechnic Palencia. Entered without decomposition, with a disdain and severity of respect
calculated to replenish the heart of the lower castes.

Flowing down like a monkey through the beautiful dark, seeking the proximity of the obese women
and if not, the of which were in regular meat, he was our friend Osuna, administrator Montesinos
home.

By the time he was not surprised won more than a slap; strange case, because in these nights of
fun used to meet half a dozen, so less. Somewhat disappointed in this aspect, not so much as slapping
what preceded them, She moved impatiently glancing butchers around him, without finding a place
enough pleasant and delightful to set their steps. That night they had met all the skinny of
rocks. But lo, when it starts to burn the first round of gunpowder, discerns not far from the cool
Ms Theodora, the constant dream of its existence, more radiant and lush than ever, with his
white hair and pink cheeks smooth and shiny skin. Verla and set out for it was all one. But
this way in such circumstances was more difficult than anyone can imagine. People thronged to
see the fireworks and remained motionless, forming a thick wall. Our hunchback's through with
diabolical art, writhing like a lizard to pass through the narrow holes. After a good time managed
to get behind the cute buxom. He was escorted by two brothers Casanova, who had come along together
with the maid. Continued fighting over their hearts, furious effort by the D. Peregrin, with
noble and severe tranquility by D. Juan. In this contest the virtuous and mature love girl suffered
a lot, believe guilty of the best fights that erupted between two brothers. Sought to maintain
neutrality but missed seeing D. Peregrin took the brunt. Explicábale it in the tone sufficiency that
characterized him, some interesting details of the fireworks industry and cited a number of
fires he had seen during his time as clerks, truly amazing. D. Poor Juan, who had never left
the narrow space of rocks and could not cite anything, silent as ever. But he ran buxom pulquérrima
occasionally a soft look and a soft smile still, they could compensate for his sedentary life.

When Ms Theodora turned his head to see who pressed both and found Osuna changed color. That damned
hunchback never gave her no peace. At the gathering, on the promenade, in the theater, church, anywhere
where I had occasion to approach, was known need was seen to suffer the nasty touch their legs
and sometimes their hands too. Osuna was familiar with his ground. The beautiful and buxom pudorosa
had fallen before dying of embarrassment to admit to any attacks
he was receiving.

But if the confession, anyone could ascertain them, noting the state of agitation he was. On
this occasion, the hunchback walked excessively bold. Ms Theodora began show signs of anxiety such
that for any would be visible. D. Juan did not see no however. It was a pure and magnanimous
man, incapable of suspecting the big dirt can have on earth. But D. Peregrin, a man of the
world, concluded by noting some what was happening. Osuna spied the corner of my eye, and when
his spirit went into government the conviction of the violation being committed, he began to
snore and whistle for nose as a mist in danger, while throwing glances of indignation flashing
the bold hunchback. He ignored those whistles at all afraid, and did not see even fateful
expression of the eyes of former acting governor of Tarragona. What had happened? The boiler
of the tug, having no more relief than the nose, broke out with horrible noise.

- Listen, rude, dirty, cynical, earless! - Roared D. Peregrin catching by the neck the deformed and
shaking with rage .-- If you continue in this way annoying Madam, with this hand (holding the
right) give a slap on the cheek, and with the other (Holding the left) will give you another slap
in the opposite direction. Continuous act will come back to you, and with these boots fat you see
here I give you two kicks in the butt.

Physicist D. Peregrin was no purpose to instill panic in the heart
of enemies.

However, severe and administrative continent as few and the voice stream great that nature endow
him pretty well made up for the deficiency of other organs. In addition, Osuna was to be weaker
and more wretched than he. For this and the uproar that ensued then, instead of coping, slipped
into the crowd and disappeared in a time. Ms Theodora, to be the subject of public curiosity,
she fainted. D. Juan and the Maiden sustained it. D. Peregrin kept
shouting at his enemy away.

The crowd laughed, cried, stirred noisily. At last all was peace, and returned to his buxom
prudish home where we will spread a flood of tears.

Obdulia, busy all day by a sharp pain and a rabid desire to redress injustice had been committed
to his beloved spiritual director, did not leave home or bed. Was really sick. Had a fever,
the fever that occurs in the temperament like hers a single thought to be exacerbated by degrees.
At night he got up and dressed hastily. Her large blue circles are now marked in a way shocking.
A Wrinkle deep, unshakable resolution sign, he furrowed his brow. She called the maid and said
he wanted to go out and see the fireworks.

All it did to dissuade her, by representing the serious damage that could cause the cold and damp
night, it was useless. He took the blanket, threw it over the head with convulsive hand, forced
to be domestic hers and took to the streets. The Field of boiling and people fainting. It took
a lot further work to be placed in the middle. Obdulia wanted at all costs approach the house the
pastor, where he was staying prelate. He had seen it shining glasses and hide immediately in one
window. Below, on the very doorstep of the rectory, a large group giraldilla girls danced, singing
as loud improvised couplets of circumstances at the time. Them alluded to the new church, compliments
to the Bishop, the Governor, Peñascosa the founding fathers, without missing either, of course,
the usual little stitch to Sarria.

The imagination of Osuna's daughter worked tirelessly to increase the fever that consumed her.
But over a thousand thoughts and ghosts circling it, sticking out an idea fixed, stubborn,
who unwittingly drove his way with his elbows through the crowd, followed by the maid, who did
not understand the desire of his lady. When they were coming to the rectory, she stopped a few minutes.
Observed from the corner of the eye to her maid, and when he saw more absorbed in the contemplation
of the fires that were burning, maneuvered skillfully and moved away
from her hiding among the people.

Once alone, he stopped again. After conducting countless looks of anxiety and fear of the priest's
house after met more than twenty times and to repent so many, finally slipped like a shadow behind
the girls dancing and having a circle of spectators around, and entered the door of the house. Inside
it had a few servants who talked looking from there they could. Was wide open, and Obdulia,
without saying word was introduced by her and climbed a few stairs. But stopping suddenly and
remaining an indecisive moment, turned to lower them and went to the group home.

- Is the secretary of the bishop's up? - Asked to nearest.

- D. Cayetano? ... Yes, ma'am, is up - said one of the most distant.

- Could you speak a word with him?

- Why not? ... I will tell ... Go up with me.

Rose both in the dirty step D. Miguel, as neither by the arrival of
the prelate had cleared.

- Have the kindness to wait a moment.

Appeared shortly after the secretary, a middle-aged cleric, ugly, ungainly, but look smart and
outspoken.

He looked with great curiosity and asked, trying to appear friendly:

-
You ask me, ma'am?

- Yes, sir.

- You tell me ...

- I talk to the
bishop.

The secretary looked at her more curiously still, and after a moment's
hesitation, appearing on her face a hint of a smile, replied:

- You
understand that the time is appropriate ... Your Excellency is going
to retire soon to rest ...

- It is urgent and very important I have
to tell ...-- said abruptly.

Again looked at the priest with penetrating eyes, noticing her agitation.

-
Well ... What I can do is tell your gift to His Grace ... Do not answer
that you receive it at this time ... Can you pass this room and wait
a moment.

No take to bring the answer.

He opened the door of the boudoir of receipt, he brought a lamp and
left her alone.

At that moment She felt that leaving all his strength. The heart started pounding him chest.
The room was moving slowly as the chamber of a vessel.

Was forced to be held with both hands on the back of a chair for
not coming to the floor.

Secretary appeared within minutes, without crossing the door frame,
said with affected solemnity

- Your Excellency will arrive at this
time.

Obdulia closed her eyes and gripped more tightly to the chair.

When he opened them before him him the towering figure of the prelate.

The room was half-lit because of the screen that covered the lamp. Contours of that figure
faded into the shadows. But diamonds sparkled pectoral and glass lenses also shone the faint
rays of light on them fell. Advanced a few steps down the hall. Obdulia dropped to his knees.

- Is it for a matter of conscience, my daughter - the prelate asked him sweetly, giving at the
same time to kiss his ring.

- Yes, sir - the young voice replied with emotion altered .-- It is for a matter of conscience of
His Excellency.

- About my conscience? - Said the bishop, rising slowly and dropping on it a look of surprise
and curiosity.

- The pure consciousness, His Excellency knows better than me, is
subject to error.

When believe we are doing good do evil. The Soul of Your Grace is noble and holy, according to
all who know her.

For something God has chosen to shepherd his flock. But the eyes of His Excellency does not
reach all parts as those of God. His arm is extended in vain to bless. The blessing does not reach
everyone. Among the pastors that His Excellency is positioned to help the need to keep faithful
and love the flock, there are also with the light and love fixed upon themselves ...

- Get you, my dear ... What do you mean by this?

- What I tell you, sir - Osuna's daughter uttered boldly, suddenly
sobering under the impulse of exaltation - is that we had in this
town a zealous coadjutor, model self-denial, humility, duty, who had
made immense sacrifices to force inspire devotion and piety to the
many who never had felt that without any violence had arranged the
parish and returned to God what belonged to him ... Well, I known
... we learned with pain all the faithful, instead of letting him
in the position that performed in the interim, Your Excellency has
given it to someone else ...

The bishop gazed in silence for a space.

The young woman under his gaze, which passed by penetrating glass lenses, inquisitive, lost
again serenity.

- Is the interim coadjutor who sends you to address a representation? - Asked with extreme calm,
stressing each syllable in a way that was epigrammatic.

- Oh! No, sir - all troubled the girl exclaimed, turning red .-- Mr.
coadjutor not has no suction.

He is so happy with the job and without it. Nothing I know or anything you know ... It was I
who by hate injustice inspires me I dared to take this step ... perhaps
unwisely ...

- No case!

No chance! - Murmured the prelate, shaking his head.

Quedósela again staring without blinking, absorbed in intense contemplation. Obdulia lowered
his head.

- My daughter - she went on gravely, - youth has its rights.

You may be dazed, forethought as enjoyable without the gifts that
God has favored us, living obfuscated without the thought of sin ...
But youth is not entitled to play for our salvation eternal, life
and death.

The Holy Catholic Church has its ministers to ensure the faith. I, though unworthy, I am one
of them and I am responsible before God and Supreme Pontiff of my
actions.

I have not learned any Pope or any decretal prelates that we had to account for them girls like
you ...

- Oh, my lord ... I did not want! ...

- Listen, you listen with patience, my dear, I heard you on your knees to your bishop.

Obdulia knelt again full of confusion, as red as a poppy.

The portly figure be enlarged enormously from the bishop before his
eyes, his white hair crowned purple skull shining majesty.

- The
offices of the Catholic Church should not be coveted jobs: not searched
accepted with humility and resignation.

The higher, harder and thorn is for those who want to serve God. You, speaking of injustice,
has apparently seen as a means of gain, and sinned grievously. If I have not given the post
of coadjutor to the person for whom you interest, that person should
thank me because I have fought many terrible responsibilities that
hamper their eternal salvation.

Obdulia, watching the lightning march again towards his confessor, found words to deflect.

- Again I say, my lord, Gil's father knows nothing of this happened ... to die of sorrow and shame
if it comes to know, because it is the modesty and humility personified.

The estimation and respect that teachers, like all residents of this
village, and my desire to see the parish in order and well served,
I drove in a moment of levity to go His Grace ...

- But do not you
understand, my dear, that in taking this step, unusual in a young
wise and pious you commit yourself, and what is worse, you commit
yourself to a priest seriously?

- Oh Holy Virgin!

What have I done? - Said the girl covered her face with her hands .-- Yes yes, I understand
now that I've been a fool, than trying to do good I have done a terrible bad ... His Excellency
and rightly despises me because I'm just a poor dumb ... But is not that bad ... The horrible
thing is that from now on will be warned against poor fool ... Jesus in my heart, what temptation
was mine! ...

She broke into sobs madly muttering unintelligible phrases.

The bishop leaned her and spoke softly.

- Sosiéguese you, my dear. Sosiéguese you and learn that a successor of the Apostles did not
prevention may feel no hatred. If you have sinned, ask for absolution from his confessor. Serénese
you, no punishment has caused more than herself ... Neither the innocent
and the guilty are nothing to fear from me.

I fear that all of God ...

After asking many times for forgiveness and shed countless tears, kissed her again with Obdulia
devotion ring prelate, and rose. Without raising his eyes from the ground muttered weakly

- Goodbye, Mr. Bishop.

Excuse me Your Excellency the disgust that I have caused, and forget it.

- May the Blessed Virgin protect you, my child.

Say a save for me, well I need it - answered The prelate, letting go and looking at her expression of
shame until it broke through the door.

Left stunned, mad with shame, his hands trembling and her cheeks flushed.

As came home got into bed with a raging fever.

XI

Already guessed the riddle, father Gil - said D. Álvaro from his chair
when he saw him enter.

The smile that accompanied these words was so surprised that was contracted and cold.

       

- What enigma? - Asked P. Gil, a little shaken by the presentiment of some misfortune.

- Do not be frightened, not that of Creation: an enigma more modest, the coming of my Peñascosa
woman a few months ago ... Know you this letter.

The young priest took from the hands of primogeniture which presented
itself and began to read:

* * * * *

"My dear Alvaro: I know that
Joaquina gave birth six days ago a child, which enrolled in the parish
and civil registration with your name.

I have tried to inform me and they said it was perfectly legitimate,
since your wife has been in Peñascosa few months ago and has stayed
in your own home.

       I write in haste to ask if true.

I doubt it, because I've never said a word about it. Answer me immediately.

JULY.

"

* * * * *

Fr Gil dropped his arms, bent his head and muttered hoarsely:

- What a disgrace!

The mayorazgo laughed.

- But do you think there is still infamous in the world? What works for you much as it has read?
I want to tell me how it is possible to crap in a toilet. For Apparently, you are still attending
the first performance of the comedy.

I am in the second, and I can say in advance what will happen.

- Anyway, D. Álvaro, it hurts in the soul is unworthy that you have made without merit.

- Indignity? Do you call the spider outraged that drowns the poor flies in his web, or milano
falling on the innocent chick and grabs the air?

For the same force infamous (Now that's the infamous!), The same force that moves the spider
and the dove is the living inside my wife. The fly, chicken and I deserve the same fate for
being born. Because felony - the man is being born, has already said Calderon, who was a priest
like you.

Fr Gil thought for a moment and said at last, as if speaking to himself:

-
I can not quite persuade us that there is more than blind force, that
light occasionally shines in the hearts of men, and sometimes called
justice others love and devotion, depend exclusively on chemical combinations.
Is infamy infamy always in our minds and awakens a feeling of disgust.
The Spider and the Kite not that they do evil, but his wife knows.

-
What does it matter? Empower you to the beast with an awareness of
their actions and you will be formed man. Consciousness is not just
a torch. The same crimes can be executed in darkness than light. If
I thought like you there is a God conscious creator of all beings,
we send a "kissing hand" praising him for having been a child so kind
and lovely as my wife and thanking her for having reserved for me
particular application</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>