<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02135</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>847</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19525</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Fernanda, picada repentinamente por vivísima curiosidad, una curiosidad insana que la puso
agitada y anhelante sin saber por qué, se inclinó otra vez hacia María Josefa, y metiéndole
la boca por el oído, le preguntó con voz alterada:

--Pero ¿quién es su padre?

La solterona se volvió hacia ella y le clavó una mirada donde se traslucía junto con la sorpresa
la misma indulgencia compasiva.

--Pero ¿de veras no sabes?...

La joven hizo signo negativo. Y al mismo tiempo se sintió embargada por terrible emoción. Una
corriente de aire frío atravesó su ser interior repentinamente. Quedó pálida, pendiente de
los labios de María Josefa, como si de ellos esperase la salud o la muerte. Aquélla advirtió
bien su turbación, y dijo después de mirarla un instante fijamente:

--No te lo digo... ¿Para qué?... Acaso sea todo una calumnia.

Fernanda se repuso instantáneamente.

--Está bien--respondió haciendo un gesto de displicencia.--Cálleselo. Después de todo, ¿a mí
qué me importa todo eso?

Este gesto hirió a la solterona, que se apresuró a decir con aguda sonrisa:

--Pues precisamente porque a tí te importa es por lo que temo decírtelo.

--No entiendo...

María Josefa se inclinó hacia ella y le dijo:

--Porque dicen que el padre de la criatura es Luis.

Como ya antes había sentido la puñalada, Fernanda quedó impasible y preguntó con indiferencia:

--¿Qué Luis?

--El conde, muchacha.

--¿Y por qué me ha de importar a mí que sea Luis el padre?

María Josefa quedó un poco desconcertada.

--Como ha sido tu novio...

--¡Pero como ya no lo es!--replicó encogiéndose de hombros desdeñosamente.

Y se puso a hablar con Granate, que tenía del otro lado. Aquella indiferencia era pura comedia
que su orgullo lograba representar. Una tristeza inexplicable y penetrante cayó sobre su alma
y la invadió por completo, sin dejarle fuerzas para pensar ni para hacer nada. Si Granate no
fuese un animal, hubiera comprendido enseguida que la sonrisa con que acogía sus barbarismos
y barbaridades era una verdadera mueca sin expresión alguna, y que los monosílabos y respuestas
incoherentes que dejaba escapar de sus labios denunciaban bien claramente que no le escuchaba
a él, sino a Paco Gómez, Manuel Antonio y los demás que seguían charlando de la niña expósita.

¡Con qué interés ardiente recogía todas las palabras que se cambiaban entre aquellos maldicientes!
Y a medida que iban poniéndole en claro el suceso y que iban acumulando pormenores, entreverando
frases burlonas y reticencias de efecto cómico, su corazón se apretaba, se apretaba poco a
poco, como si todos ellos lo fuesen oprimiendo entre sus manos, uno después de otro, para hacerle
daño. Pero su rostro permanecía impasible. Ni la más leve contracción acusaba el dolor que
la mordía.

La tertulia se deshizo a las doce, como siempre. Fernanda sintió gran consuelo al respirar
el aire frío y húmedo de la noche. Tenía ansia de quedarse a solas con su pensamiento y darse
cuenta cabal de lo que acababa de aprender.

Había llovido mucho. Las calles, empedradas de grueso guijarro, resplandecían a la luz de los
reverberos. Al salir de la casa unos tomaron por la calle abajo; otros, entre ellos Fernanda,
hacia arriba en dirección a la plaza. Pocos pasos habían dado cuando sintieron el estrepitoso
trotar de unos caballos que doblaban en aquel instante la esquina y bajaban hacia ellos.

--Ahí está el barón y su criado--dijo Manuel Antonio.

Era la hora, en efecto, en que el excéntrico barón de los Oscos salía a dar su paseo habitual
por las calles de Lancia. Su famoso caballo las desempedraba haciendo cabriolas, levantando
tal estrépito que, aun siendo el corcel de su criado mucho más paciente, parecía que atravesaba
la ciudad un escuadrón. Al cruzarse con los tertulios, Manuel Antonio, con el desparpajo que
le caracterizaba, gritó: «Buenas noches barón.» Pero éste volvió hacia ellos el rostro espantable,
los miró fijamente con sus ojos encarnizados y siguió adelante sin contestar. El marica, corrido,
dijo:

--¡Va borracho, como siempre!

Todos asintieron burlando. Pero en el fondo sintieron todos, unos más y otros menos, el mismo
estremecimiento al ver aquella figura siniestra. Fernanda, por mujer y por el estado especial
de su alma, se inmutó visiblemente: después de pasar siguió todavía con ojos de temor a los
dos jinetes hasta que se perdieron entre las sombras.

Al meterse en la cama, con el corazón apretado, quiso analizar la emoción que la dominaba;
quiso remontarse a la causa. Sintió vergüenza de ella. Su orgullo le hizo exclamar con rabia
y en voz alta:

--¿A mí que me importan esas picardías? ¿Qué tengo que ver con él ni con ella?

Pero acabado de proferir tales palabras sintió las mejillas caldeadas por el llanto. La heredera
de Estrada-Rosa se volvió rápidamente y hundió el rostro, cubierto de rubor, en las almohadas.

VII

El aumento del contingente.

Las terribles dificultades que debían de surgir para el matrimonio de Emilita, a causa de las
opiniones antibélicas de su padre, se orillaron con más facilidad de lo que podía esperarse.
La historia no hablará (aunque mejor razón tendrá que para otros muchos sucesos) de aquel día
solemne en que Núñez fue de uniforme a pedir a D. Cristóbal la mano de su hija, de aquel abrazo
memorable con que éste le recibió, estrechándole calurosamente contra su pecho civil, de aquella
fusión increíble de dos elementos heterogéneos creados para repelerse, y que gracias al amor
de un ángel dulce y revoltoso se compenetraban y entendían. Si por casualidad esta página privada
fuese objeto de atención para algún historiador, no tendría más remedio que afirmar la grandísima
importancia de semejante concordia, que hasta entonces se había juzgado inverosímil, y al mismo
tiempo presentar con imparcialidad el reverso, descubriendo a las futuras generaciones en qué
modo el benemérito patricio D. Cristóbal Mateo fue víctima de una injusticia social y de la
persecución de sus conciudadanos.

Es de saber, que todo el mundo en Lancia se creía autorizado para dar cantaleta a este respetable
y antiguo funcionario acerca del matrimonio de su hija. Unas veces directa, otras indirectamente,
siempre que tocaban tal punto aludían a las opiniones contrarias al desenvolvimiento de las
fuerzas de tierra sustentadas por él hasta entonces. Al matrimonio dio en llamársele «el aumento
del contingente,» y algunos llevaron su procacidad hasta darle tal nombre delante de su futuro
yerno. Fácil es de concebir cuánta saliva habría tenido que tragar antes de perder, como lo
hizo, una molesta y mal entendida vergüenza.

Pero a despecho de todas las diatribas y murmuraciones de los vecinos, que reflejaban, en el
sentir de Mateo, más que su naturaleza jocosa, la envidia que ardía en la mayor parte de los
corazones, «el aumento del contingente» se abría paso. El plazo fijado para realizarlo fue
el mes de Agosto. Cuando llegó el momento había adquirido tal importancia que, como sucede
generalmente en los pueblos pequeños, apenas se hablaba de otra cosa. Las relaciones del Jubilado
y sus cuatro hijas eran numerosísimas, y todas ellas aspiraban a ser invitadas el día de la
boda. Por otra parte, la misma aspiración alimentaban en su pecho algunos dignos y pundonorosos
oficiales del batallón de Pontevedra amigos del futuro. No siendo posible reunir tanta gente
en el hogar poético del Jubilado, se pensó en celebrar la boda en el campo. La casa más a propósito
era la de la Granja por su proximidad a la población. D. Cristóbal se la pidió al conde, con
quien tenía extremada confianza, lo mismo que sus hijas, y éste se apresuró a ponerla a su
disposición.

En la iglesia de San Rafael se consumó de madrugada aquella venturosa alianza, prenda segura
de paz entre el elemento civil y el militar. Bendíjola fray Diego que, por ser el sacerdote
más bizarro y el más firme bebedor de anisado de la capital, gozaba de gran prestigio entre
la oficialidad. Asistieron al acto más de veinte damas y casi otros tantos caballeros. En cuanto
terminó se trasladaron todos a la Granja para pasar allí el día. Por hallarse tan cerca de
la población no se necesitaban carruajes. Sin embargo, fueron los del conde de Onís y de Quiñones
para trasportar a los novios y a algunas personas de edad avanzada, como las dos señoritas
de Meré. Entre los invitados estaba casi toda la tertulia del maestrante, bastantes de la de
las de Meré y un número crecido de oficiales.

El conde había hecho asear, hasta donde era posible, el vetusto caserón. Casi todos lo conocían
como su propia casa. Era el sitio obligado de las giras campestres por hallarse tan cerca y
por el hermoso bosque que tenía. Los condes jamás habían negado el permiso. En cuanto llegaron
y gustaron el chocolate, que les esperaba en el vasto salón con pavimento de ladrillo de la
planta baja que servía de comedor, se diseminaron sin ceremonia por la casa y por la finca
dispuestos a matar las horas del mejor modo posible hasta que sonase la de comer. La novia,
con Amalia, que había sido su madrina, y otras dos señoras se fue a sentar gravemente en una
de las habitaciones. Tenía los ojos brillantes, las mejillas coloradas y procuraba inútilmente
disfrazar con un continente digno y serio la profunda emoción que la embargaba. Las que la
acompañaban, casadas todas, la acariciaban sin cesar, pasando la mano por sus cabellos, dándole
palmaditas en las mejillas, cogiéndole las manos y de vez en cuando inclinándose para estampar
un beso en su frente con esa condescendencia, mitad cariñosa, mitad irónica, con que las veteranas
del matrimonio contemplan a las bisoñas. No hay una de aquéllas que al acercarse a una novia
no sienta vibrar en su pecho el eco de cierta música lejana y divina; viene a sus labios el
gusto de la miel de la remota luna; pero llega ¡ay! con el dejo amarguillo de algunos años
de prosa matrimonial. En toda mujer casada hay un poeta desengañado de su musa. De aquí la
sonrisa baironiana que aparece en su rostro al observar la dicha que arde en los ojos de una
desposada.

Emilita había cambiado de carácter en un cuarto de hora. Todo lo juguetona y pizpireta que
se había mostrado hasta entonces, aparecía ahora grave y espetada. Disertaba sabiamente con
las matronas, sus compañeras, acerca de la instalación de la despensa, del servicio doméstico
que todas consideraban en espantosa decadencia, del precio de la carne. Tan vieja se había
hecho en este cuarto de hora, que sorprendía no ver ya alguna hebra de plata entre sus cabellos
de oro.

En cambio a sus hermanas, por extraño contraste, les habían quitado algunos años de encima
desde que la menor tomara la investidura. Habían retrocedido hasta la infancia. Como criaturas
ávidas de aire y de luz para desarrollarse, lanzáronse al bosque las tres, animando con sus
gritos e inocentes carcajadas el silencio y la paz que allí reinaba. ¡Virgen del Amparo lo
que saltaron, lo que rieron, las diabluras que llevaron a cabo en poco tiempo aquellas loquillas!
Para entregarse a los juegos inocentes, que exigía el retroceso sensible que habían experimentado
de pronto, se quitan las mantillas y dejan suelto el cabello, tiran los guantes, el abanico,
la sombrilla, todo lo que pudiera simbolizar la juventud, y se quedan gozosas con los atributos
de la adolescencia. No sólo dejan flotando sobre la espalda su cabellera angelical, sino que
se despojan del reloj, de las pulseras y sortijas que entregan a su papá, colgándose antes
de su cuello para hacerle mil caricias como niñas sencillas y apasionadas que eran; hecho lo
cual y al observar que algunos dignos oficiales del batallón de Pontevedra las contemplan,
huyen ruborizadas y confusas, se recogen las enaguas con alfileres hasta dejar descubierto
el pie y parte de la pierna, y en la inocencia de su corazón huyen, huyen siempre por el bosque
adelante, esquivando como las ninfas de Diana las miradas ardientes de la oficialidad.

Y cuando llegan a un rincón apartado y solitario donde las sombras se espesan, donde no llegan
los ruidos mundanales ni penetran los ojos maliciosos de los hombres, llaman con gritos de
alegría, como pajaritos de Dios, a sus compañeras, las invitan a venir a disfrutar de aquella
amable seguridad donde libremente pueden mostrar sus gracias y recrearse sin peligro de ser
sorprendidas. Entonces una propone jugar a la cuerda y las demás acceden batiendo las palmas.
Jovita es la primera. Salta, salta hasta que queda rendida y se deja caer sobre el césped,
llevándose la mano al corazón, que palpita con la fatiga, no con la agitación insana de las
pasiones juveniles. Luego salta otra, luego otra y otra hasta que todas se tienden exánimes
pero risueñas, reflejando en sus mejillas sudorosas y en sus ojos entornados la dulce alegría
que se escapa de un pecho inocente. Y en cuanto descansan se propone jugar «al milano que le
dan--cebollita con el pan.» ¡Qué risa! ¡qué algazara! ¡cómo resuena el dormido bosque con las
voces argentinas de aquellas bellas y tiernas criaturas! Cansadas de este juego se diseminan
por un momento. Algunas forman grupo sentadas al pie del tronco de un roble y se cuentan en
voz baja como suave gorjeo mil puerilidades encantadoras; otras se entregan apasionadamente
a la busca de florecillas azules y hacen con ellas ramilletes que colocan en el pecho; otras
se persiguen, como las golondrinas en el aire, con chillidos penetrantes. Otras, las más resueltas,
dedican sus esfuerzos a la caza de cigarras y otros bichos temerosos. Pero luego tornan a juntarse
porque hay una chica muy aturdida que apuesta a encaramarse en un árbol si la ayudan, y hay
otra maligna que dice que sí, que ella la ayudará. Manos a la obra. Empezó la animosa joven,
que se llama Consuelo, a poner sus piececitos en las rugosidades del roble más asequible. La
compañera maligna, que no es otra que Socorro, la tercera sirena del Jubilado, la sostiene.
Encarámase al fin la primera en la cruz de dos ramas; asciende después a otra; aplauden las
ninfas y la alientan con gritos de entusiasmo...

Mas he aquí que Rubio, el teniente de la tercera, hombre acreditado de audaz entre sus compañeros
de arma y de un genio devastador para el sexo femenino, se presenta de improviso asomando su
cabeza temeraria por encima de unas matas. Las ninfas, al verle, lanzan un grito y quedan petrificadas
en la actitud en que las sorprende. Consuelo, desde lo alto del árbol, le apostrofa con violencia.
Si en su mano estuviera trasformaría inmediatamente en ciervo a aquel nuevo Acteón. Acá, para
inter nos, es posible que prefiriese trasformarle primeramente en marido, sin perjuicio de
acudir más adelante a la metamorfosis clásica... Pero Rubio, el teniente de la tercera, conoce
perfectamente el valor de estos gritos y estos apóstrofes. No se inmuta; sonríe maliciosamente
y llama con voz ronca a sus hermanos de armas. ¡Qué confusión, qué espanto entre aquellas risueñas
hijas de los bosques al aproximarse en columna cerrada los hijos de Marte! Sin recoger las
mantillas, ni los guantes, ni las sombrillas, nada en suma de lo que las pertenecía, huyen
y se desbandan por la floresta lanzando gritos de terror. Pero los sátiros de pantalón encarnado
las persiguen con saña, las atrapan aquí y allá y las traen cautivas enmedio de risotadas odiosas.
Mientras tanto la pobre Consuelo, encima del árbol y bloqueada por tres de estos silvanos voluptuosos,
se niega terminantemente a bajar mientras no se alejen por lo menos cincuenta varas. Ellos
¡los crueles! se niegan. Ruega la ninfa, se irrita, está a punto de llorar; pero ni su enojo
ni sus lágrimas consiguen ablandar el corazón empedernido de los infames sátiros. Por fin se
resigna a descender y, aunque toma muchas y castas precauciones, éstos logran ver un pie deliciosamente
calzado y un nacimiento de pierna que les hace rugir de gozo. Pero ¿dónde está Rubio? ¿Dónde
está el más terrible y feroz de todos ellos? No se sabe, mas al cabo de mucho tiempo sale de
la espesura arrastrando consigo a Socorro, la más sentimental de las ondinas de D. Cristóbal.
En los rasgos crueles de su fisonomía viene pintada la expresión del triunfo, y en los de ella
la vergüenza y la sumisión de una cautiva. Muchas horas después, en las últimas de la noche,
sentado a una mesa del café de Marañón y rodeado de ocho o diez de sus colegas, el teniente
de la tercera narraba con sonrisa malévola el vencimiento de la ninfa, calculando lo menos
en veinticinco o treinta los besos que logró robarle en distintos sitios de su rostro hechicero;
y todos los hijos de Marte aplaudían y celebraban con homéricas carcajadas aquel nuevo triunfo
de su heroico compañero.

Finalmente, los vencedores no se mostraron demasiado tiranos, y el orden se restableció gracias
a la llegada oportuna de las señoritas de Meré, que venían acompañadas de María Josefa y de
Paco Gómez. Las autoras y únicas responsables de todo aquello habían sacado el fondo del cofre.
Carmelita traía un vestido de alepín de seda negra que sólo salía a relucir en las grandes
ocasiones, al paso que Nuncita, por contar menos años y respetabilidad, podía lucir un traje
claro con flores bordadas, como sólo se ven en los retratos del siglo pasado. Estaban alegres,
rebosando satisfacción por los ojos; pero las piernas no respondían a aquella eterna juventud
de sus corazones: caminaban apoyándose en sendas muletas y agarrándose con la mano libre al
brazo de sus acompañantes. Fueron recibidas con vivas y hurras. Se oyeron asimismo algunas
frases harto familiares, de esas que nadie más que las benditas de Meré consentían y reían.
Por eso tenía poco mérito el embromarlas. Jamás se dio el caso de verlas enfadadas con sus
amigos, y eso que algunos se deslizaban en sus guasas hasta llegar no pocas veces a la grosería.
En cambio eran muy propensas a la guerra intestina, esto es, a irritarse una con otra; pero
ya sabemos en qué paraban siempre estas misas.

El espíritu temerario del teniente Rubio, apretado por las circunstancias, engendró una idea
felicísima, es a saber: que para mejor pasar el rato hasta la hora de comer se construyese
un columpio, donde las damas pudieran gozar la dicha de sacudirse el diafragma algunos instantes,
y los caballeros la de proporcionársela moviendo galantemente el aparato. Dicho y hecho: se
buscan cuerdas, se sierra una tabla; en menos de un cuarto de hora queda todo terminado. Rubio,
mientras se lleva a cabo, no deja de hacer guiños expresivos a sus compañeros, que comprenden,
sonríen, callan, profundamente admirados, como siempre, de la audacia y penetración del teniente
de la tercera. Ya está amarrado el columpio. ¿Quién es la primera? Todas manifiestan la misma
vergüenza, idéntico rubor colorea sus mejillas. A una se le ocurre malignamente proponer que
lo estrene Nuncita. Las demás aplauden la idea. Nuncita resiste aterrada. Carmelita ni concede
el permiso ni lo niega. Las instancias se repiten sin cesar. Los mancebos encuentran la idea
cada vez más original. Al fin, casi a viva fuerza, entre los aplausos frenéticos del corro,
Cuervo, el hercúleo alférez de la primera, levanta en brazos a la Niña y la sienta en la tabla.

--¡Agárrate bien, Nuncia!--le grita Paco Gómez, mientras el citado alférez y algunos otros
amigos empiezan a mecerla.

--¡Suave, suave!--exclama Carmelita.

No hay cuidado; así lo hacen, porque temen dar con ella en tierra. Pero aun moviendo el columpio
con parsimonia, el aire consigue levantar, al poco tiempo, las enaguas de la antigua doncella.
Los oficiales ríen y empujan el columpio para que se vea más.

--¡Fuerte, fuerte, que algo se pesca!--les grita Paco Gómez.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09333</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>1413</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17346</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Fernanda, chopped suddenly by vivid curiosity, a curiosity that made her insane agitated and
anxious without knowing why, he leaned over to Maria Josefa, and thrusting the mouth by his
ear, asked in an agitated voice:

- But who is your father?

The maid turned to her and planted a glance which shone through with
the surprise the same indulgence compassionate.

- But do you really
do not know ...

She made negative.

And at the same time he was overcome with terrible emotion. A cold air flow through his inner
self suddenly. He was pale, yet Josefa Maria's lips, as if they expect health or death. It
warned While his confusion, and said after looking at her intently for a moment:

- No I tell you ... Why? ... Perhaps it is all a calumny.

Fernanda recovered instantly.

- Okay - said with a gesture of disdain .-- Cálleselo.

After all, did for me What do I care all that?

The gesture struck the maid, who hastened to say with a keen smile

-
Well, just because you care is so afraid to tell you.

- I do not
understand ...

Maria Josefa leaned forward and said

- Because they
say that the child's father is Luis.

As soon as he felt the stab, Fernanda was unmoved and asked casually:

-
What Luis?

- Earl, girl.

- Why do I have to import to me that Luis
is the father?

Maria Josefa was a little puzzled.

- How was your boyfriend ...

- But as it is not! - Replied, shrugging his shoulders contemptuously.

And he began to talk to Garnet, who was the other side. That indifference was pure comedy that
his pride could represent. An inexplicable and pervasive sadness fell upon his soul invaded and
completely, without leaving the strength to think or to do anything. If Garnet is not I was an
animal, would have understood immediately that the smile with which
he welcomed their barbarism and atrocities was a real face without
expression, and monosyllables and answers incoherent let slip from
her lips clearly denouncing it that was not listening him, but Paco
Gomez, Manuel Antonio and the others were chatting about the foundling.

With

what ardent interest collected all the words that were exchanged between those slanderers! And as we
were putting it clear the event and details were piling up, mingling mocking phrases and reticence
of comic effect, squeezing his heart, little is pressed little, as if they all were pressing
in their hands, one after another, to make damage. But his face remained impassive. Not the slightest
contraction accused the pain the bite.

The gathering broke up at noon, as usual. Fernanda felt great comfort in breathing cold, damp
air of the night. Was craving to be alone with his thoughts and be fully aware of what had just
learned.

It had rained a lot. The streets, paved with thick stone, sparkled in the light of lamps. When
leaving the house took some down the street, others, including Fernanda upward toward the square.
Few steps were taken when they heard the loud trotting horses at
that moment that bent the corner and down towards them.

- There is
the Baron and his servant - said Manuel Antonio.

It was time, indeed, that the eccentric baron Oscos went for his usual walk through the streets
of Lancia. The unpaved his famous prancing horse, raising such a crash, even if the horse of his
servant, much more patient, it appeared that crossing the city a squadron. When crossing the
circles, Manuel Antonio, with the impudence to characterized him, he shouted: "Good evening, Baron."
But he turned to face them fearful, stared at them with his fierce eyes and moved on without answering.
The queen, running, said:

- Va drunk, as usual!

Everyone nodded laughing. But deep felt all, some more than others, the same thrill to see that
sinister figure. Fernanda, for women and special status of his soul, visibly flinch, after
spending continued even through the eyes of fear of two riders until
they were lost in the shadows.

When you get into bed, his heart tightened, wanted to analyze the
emotion that dominated; wanted to go back to the cause.

He felt ashamed of it. His pride made him cry with rage and loud

- Me I care about these pranks? What I have to do with him or her?

But I just felt utter such words heated cheeks with tears.

The Heiress Estrada, Rosa quickly turned and buried her face covered with blushes, in pillows.

VII

The
increase of the quota.

The terrible difficulties should arise Emilita for marriage because of the anti-war views of his
father, he bashed her with more ease than could be expected. History does not speak (although better
reason to have that many events) that day Nunez was solemn in uniform to ask D. Christopher
the hand of his daughter, that embrace memorable it received him warmly against his chest shaking
civilian, that incredible fusion of two heterogeneous elements created to repel, and thanks to the
love a sweet and naughty angel interpenetrate and understood. If by chance this Page Private object
of attention was a historian, would have no choice but to affirm the very great importance of
such agreement, which until then had considered unlikely, and at the same time to present fairly
the back, discovering how future generations So the distinguished
patrician D. Christopher Matthew was the victim of social injustice
and persecution of their fellow citizens.

You know, everyone in Lancia authorized to give thought to this respectable old song and a former
official on the marriage of his daughter. Sometimes directly, sometimes indirectly, always played
such an extent that alluded to the opinions against the development of ground forces supported
by him until then. The couple gave to be called "the increased the quota, "and some carried
their impudence to give such a name in front of his future son.

It is easy to conceive how much saliva would have had to swallow before losing, as he, an annoying
and misunderstood shame.

But despite all the rants and complaints of the neighbors, reflecting, in Matthew felt, rather
than its playful nature, envy that burned most of the hearts, "the increased quota" was making its
way. The deadline to do it was the month of August. When the time came he had acquired such
importance that, as usually in small towns, barely talked about anything else. Retired relationships
and four daughters were numerous, and they all aspired to be invited on the day of wedding.
Moreover, the same aspiration in his heart some decent and honorable Pontevedra battalion officers
friends of the future. Not being able to gather so many people Poetic Home for the Elderly,
was thought to hold the wedding in the country. The purpose home more Farm was its proximity
to the population.

D. Cristobal asked for the count, with who had extreme confidence, like his daughters, and he
hastened to put to provision.

In the Church of San Rafael was consummated early in the morning that fortunate partnership, the
sure pledge peace between the civilian and military. Fray Diego blessed him, as the priest
most bizarre and stronger anise drinker of the capital, enjoyed great prestige among the officers.
Event was attended by over twenty women and nearly as many gentlemen. As ended all moved to
the farm to spend the day. For being so near the population does not need coaches. However,
were the Count de Onis and Quiñones to transport the bride and groom
and some older people, as the two ladies de Mere.

Among the guests were almost all the gathering of the Grandee, enough of that of the de Mere and
a growing number of officers.

The count had been clean, as far as possible, the ancient mansion. Almost everyone knew him
as their home. It was the site of picnics obliged by being so close and by the beautiful forest
that I had. The counts had never refused permission. When they arrived and tasted the chocolate,
which awaited them in the vast living room with brick paving floor that served as dining-room
without ceremony spread through the house and farm ready to kill the hours until the best possible
way to sound the eating. The bride, Amalia, who was her godmother, and two other ladies went
to sit in a severely rooms. Her eyes were bright, her cheeks red and tried in vain dress with a
dignified and serious continent's deep emotion that seized. Which the accompanied, married all
the cherished endlessly, passing his hand through his hair, giving pat on the cheek, taking her hands
and occasionally leaning over to print a kiss on her forehead with the condescending, half tender,
half ironic, that the veterans contemplate marriage to the fledgling. No one of those that
when approaching a girlfriend not vibrate in your chest feel the echo of distant music and
some divine comes to her lips like honey from the remote moon, but it comes oh! with some
years left bitterish matrimonial prose. In every married woman is a disillusioned poet of his
muse.

Hence the baironiana smile on your face to see the joy that burns in the eyes of a bride.

Emilita
character had changed in a quarter of an hour. All playful and pert that had shown until then,
now appeared serious and brochette. Discoursed wisely with midwives, their partners, about the
installation of the pantry, domestic service all considered in terrible decline, the price
of meat. So old that had done in this quarter of an hour, which surprised not to see and a strand
of silver in her hair gold.

In contrast to her sisters, strange contrast, I had taken some years off since the lower take
up office. Had regressed to childhood. As creatures eager to air and light to grow, the forest
lanzáronse three, encouraging their loud screams and innocent silence and peace that reigned there.
Virgen del Amparo what they jumped, they laughed at the mischief that took place in those short little
crazy! To indulge in innocent games, which required that they had experienced recoil Suddenly,
the blankets are removed, leaving the hair loose, pull the gloves, fan, the umbrella, anything
that might symbolize youth and joyful stay with attributes adolescence. Not only do they float
on your back your hair angelic, but clock shed, bracelets and rings that deliver to his dad,
hanging before his neck to make a thousand strokes as simple and passionate girls who were,
done and observing that some officers of the battalion worthy of the contemplation Pontevedra,
fleeing blushing and confused, we include skirts with pins to leave open the foot and leg,
and the innocence of his heart run away, always fleeing through the woods forward, dodging and
nymphs of Diana the burning eyes of the officers.

And when they reach a secluded and lonely where shadows thicken, which fail worldly noises
nor penetrate the malicious eyes of men, called with cries of joy, like birds of God, her friends,
invite them to come and enjoy this nice free security where they can show their thanks and
be safe recreation surprised. Then a proposed play the string and the other access clapping his
hands. Jovita is the first. Jump, jump until it is exhausted and is dropped on the grass touching
his heart, throbbing with the fatigue, not the insane turmoil youthful lusts. Then jump another,
then another and another until they all tend lifeless but smiling, reflecting on their sweaty
cheeks and his eyes narrowed the sweet joy escaping from an innocent chest. And as lie intends
to play "the kite that dan - onion with the bread. "What a laugh! What merriment! The sleeping
forest resounds with silvery voices of those beautiful and gentle creatures! Tired of this game
spread for a moment. Some are group sitting at the foot of an oak tree trunk and counted in
low voice, as soft chirping thousand charming childish, others passionately delivered in search
of blue flowers and bouquets made with them placed on the chest, others pursued, like the swallows
in the air with piercing shrieks. Others, the more determined, devote their efforts to hunt
grasshoppers and other bugs fearful. But then turn to join because there is a very giddy girl who bets
to climb a tree if the help, and there other malignant says yes, she will help. Hands. He began the
spirited young called Consuelo, to put their feet upon the oak ridges more affordable. The
evil companion, which is nothing to Socorro, the third siren retired, holds. Climb at the end
of the first in the cross of two branches; rises after another, applauding nymphs and encourage
with shouts of enthusiasm ...

But behold, Rubio, the lieutenant of the third, a man attested to
their peers bold Gun and a devastating genius for females, it occurs
suddenly rear its bold head above a thicket.

The nymphs, seeing him, cry out and are petrified attitude in the surprise. Consuelo, from the top
of the tree, he apostrophizes violence. If your hand was immediately trasformaría deer that
new Actaeon. Here, for between ourselves, it is possible that a husband preferred to first transform it,
without prejudice go ahead on the classic metamorphosis ... But Rubio, the lieutenant of the third,
known well the value of these cries, and these apostrophes. Do not flinch, smile mischievously
and called hoarsely to their brothers in arms. What confusion, fear among those smiling daughters
of forests to approach their children in close column of Mars! No pick blankets, and gloves, and
umbrellas, anything short of what belonged flee and disband the forest screaming in terror. But
the red pants satyrs pursue them with a vengeance, are caught here and there and bring them captive
in the midst of hideous laughter. Meanwhile the poor Consuelo, and locked up the tree for
three of these sylvan voluptuous absolutely refuses to go down when not away at least fifty
yards. They Cruel! denied. Pray the nymph, irritated, is about to mourn, but not anger or get tears
soften the hardened heart of the infamous satyrs. Finally resigned to descend and, although it takes
many precautions castes, they fail to see a foot deliciously shoes and a leg birth makes them roar with
delight. But where is Rubio? Where is the most terrible and ferocious of them all? It is not
known, but long after leaving the woods dragging Socorro, the most sentimental of the sprites
of D. Cristobal. In the cruel features of his face is painted the expression of triumph, and
in hers shame and submission of a captive. Many hours later, the last of the night, sitting at a coffee
table and surrounded Marañón eight or ten of his colleagues, Lt. the third narrated with evil
smile expiration of the nymph, calculating at least in three or four who managed to steal kisses
in different places on his face sorcerer and all the sons of Mars cheered and celebrated with
this new triumph Homeric laughter of his heroic partner.

Finally, the winners were not too tyrants, and order was restored by the timely arrival of the
Miss de Mere, who were accompanied by Maria Josefa and Paco Gomez. The authors and solely
responsible for everything that had drawn the bottom of the chest. Carmelita Alepin wore a dress
of black silk that came to light only in large occasions, whereas Nuncita and therefore had fewer
years and respectability, could wear a suit clear with embroidered
flowers, as only seen in pictures of the last century.

Were happy eyes brimming with satisfaction, but the legs did not respond to that eternal youth
their hearts, walking paths relying on crutches and with his free hand holding the arms of
their escorts. They were received with cheers and hurrahs. It also heard some Family tired phrases,
such that no more than blessed to Meré indulged and laughed. That's why the teasing had little
merit. Ever there was a case of seeing them angry with friends, and that some slipped in together
until reaching quite a few times to rudeness. On the other hand were very prone to internal strife,
that is, to chafe each other, but we know how long these masses stopped.

The reckless spirit of Lieutenant Rubio, crowded by circumstances engendered an idea most happy,
to wit: that to better spend the time until dinner time to be constructed a swing, where the
ladies could enjoy the happiness of a few moments to shake off the diaphragm, and to provide
them knights gallantly moving the unit. Said and done: the search strings, a table saw, in less
than a quarter of an hour is all over. Rubio, while carrying out, it is still expressive wink
to his companions, including, smiling, silent, deeply admired, as
always, boldness and penetration of Lieutenant of the third.

Already tied the swing. Who is first? All show the same shame, her cheeks flushing same. One
would think wickedly propose Nuncita try it out. The others applaud the idea. Resists Nuncita
terrified. Carmelita or grant nor denies permission. Instances are repeated endlessly. The young
men find the idea increasingly original. Finally, almost by force, between the frantic applause
of the circle, Cuervo, the Herculean ensign of the first, lifted the girl in his arms and sits
on the table.

- Hold on tight, Nuncia! - Paco Gómez yells, while the lieutenant said, and some other friends
start rocking.

- Soft, soft! - Carmelita exclaims.

Do not worry, they do so because they fear to find her on the ground.

But even moving the swing sparingly, the air gets up, before long, the skirts of the old maid.
The officers laugh and push the swing to make it look more.

- Strong,
strong, that something is caught! - Paco Gómez yells.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>