<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04261</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>164213</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24866</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Algunas veces sacrificaban
mucho en este oráculo, y así mataban muchos ganados y aves, y algunos hombres y mujeres.

Sin estos oráculos, habia el de Aperahua, en donde por el troncon de un árbol respondia el
oráculo, y que junto á él se halló cantidad de oro; y el de Pachacama, ques de los Yuncas,
y otros muchos, así en la comarca de Andesuyo, como en la de Chinchasuyo y Omasuyo, y otras
partes deste reino, de los cuales pudiera decir algo más; mas, pues que lo dije en la Primera
parte[87], que trata de las fundaciones, no trataré desto más que de los oráculos, los que
tenian más devocion todos los Incas con las demás naciones, sacrificaban algunos hombres y
mujeres y mucho ganado; y á donde no habia este crédito, no derramaban sangre humana ni mataban
hombres, sino ofrecian oro y plata. A las guacas que tenian en ménos, que eran como ermitas,
ofrecian chaquira y plumas y otras cosas menudas y de poco valor. Esto digo, porque la opinion
que los españoles tenemos en afirmar que en todos los templos sacrificaban hombres, es falsa;
y esto es la verdad segund lo que yo alcancé, sin tirar ni poner más de lo que yo entendí y
para mí tengo por cierto.

En este lugar entra bien, para que se entienda, lo de la capaccocha, pues todo era tocante
al servicio de los templos ya dichos y de otros; y por noticia que se tiene de indios viejos
que son vivos y vieron lo que sobre esto pasaba, escribiré lo que de ello tengo entendido que
es verdad. Y así, dicen que se tenia por costumbre en el Cuzco, por los reyes, que cada año
hacian venir á aquella ciudad á todas las estatuas[88] y bultos de los ídolos que estaban en
las guacas, que eran los templos donde ellos adoraban; las cuales eran traidas con mucha veneracion
por los sacerdotes y camayos dellas, ques nombre de guardianes; y como entrasen en la ciudad,
eran recebidas con grandes fiestas y procesiones y aposentadas en los lugares que para aquello
estaban señalados y establecidos; y habiendo venido de las comarcas de la ciudad, y áun de
la mayor parte de las provincias, número grande de gente, así hombres como mujeres, el que
reinaba, acompañado de todos los Incas y orejones, cortesanos y principales de la ciudad, entendian
en hacer grandes fiestas y borracheras y táquis.

Ponian en la plaza del Cuzco la gran maroma de oro que la cercaba toda, y tantas riquezas y
pedrería, cuanto se puede pensar por lo que se ha escripto de los tesoros questos reyes poseian;
lo cual pasado, se entendia en lo que todos los años por ellos se usaba, que era, questas estátuas
y bultos y sacerdotes se juntaban para saber por boca dellos el suceso del año, si habia de
ser fértil, ó si habia de haber esterilidad; si el Inca tenia larga vida, ó si por caso moriria
en aquel año; si habian de venir enemigos por algunas partes, ó si algunos de los pacíficos
se habian de revelar. En conclusion, eran repreguntados destas cosas y de otras mayores y menores
que va poco desmenuzarlas; porque tambien preguntaban si habria peste, ó si vernia alguna morriña
para el ganado, y si habria mucho multiplico dél. Y esto se hacia y preguntaba, no á todos
los oráculos juntos, sino á cada uno por sí; y si todos los años los Incas no hacian esto,
andaban muy recatados y vivian descontentos y muy temerosos, y no tenian sus vidas por seguras.

Y así, alegrado al pueblo y hechas sus solenes borracheras y banquetes y grandes táquis y otras
fiestas que ellos usan, diferente en todo á las nuestras, en que los Incas están con gran triunfo
y á su costa se hacen los convites, en que habia suma de grandes tinajas de oro y plata, y
vasos de otras cosas, porque todo el servicio de su cocina, hasta las ollas y vasos de servicio,
era de oro y plata;--mandaban á los que para aquello estaban señalados y tenian las veces del
Gran Sacerdote, que tambien estaba presente á estas fiestas con tan grand pompa y triunfo como
el mesmo rey, acompañado de los sacerdotes y mamaconas que allí se habian juntado,--que hiciesen
á cada ídolo su pregunta destas cosas, el cual respondia por boca de los sacerdotes que tenian
cargo de su bulto; y éstos, como estaban bien beodos, adivinaban lo que más vian que hacia
al gusto de los que preguntaban, inventando por ellos y por el diablo, questaba en aquellas
estátuas. Y hechas las preguntas á cada ídolo, por ser los sacerdotes tan astutos en maldades,
pedian algund término para responder, para que con más devocion y crédito dellos oyesen sus
desvarios; porque decian que querian hacer sus sacrificios, para que estando gratos á los altos
dioses suyos, fuesen servidos de responder lo que habia de ser; y así, eran traidos muchos
animales de ovejas y corderos, y cuis y aves, que pasaba el número de más de dos mill corderos
y ovejas; y estos eran degollados, haciendo sus exorcismos diabólicos y sacrificios vanos á
su costumbre; y luego denunciaban lo que soñaban ó lo que fingian, ó por ventura lo que el
diablo les decia; y al dar de las respuestas, teníase gran cuenta en mirar lo que decian y
cuantos dellos conformaban en un dicho ó suceso de bien ó de mal; y así hacian con las demás
respuestas, para ver cuál decia verdad y acertaba lo que habia de ser en el dicho año.

Esto hecho, luego salian los limosneros de los reyes con las ofrendas que ellos llaman capaccocha,
y juntándose la limosna general, eran vueltos los ídolos á los templos; y si pasado el año
habian acaso acertado alguno de aquellos soñadores, alegremente mandaba el Inca que lo fuese
de su casa.

La capaccocha, como digo, era ofrenda que se pagaba en lugar de diezmo á los templos, de muchos
vasos de oro y plata y de otras piezas y piedras, y cargas de mantas ricas, y mucho ganado.
Y á las que habian salido inciertas y mentirosas, no les daban el año venidero ninguna ofrenda,
ántes perdian reputacion. Y para hacer esto, se hacian grandes cosas en el Cuzco, mucho más
de lo que yo escribo. Y agora, despues de fundada la Audiencia y haberse ido Gasca á España[89],
entre algunas cosas que se trataban en ciertos pleitos, se hacia mencion de esta capaccocha;
y ello y todo lo demás que hemos escripto es cierto que se hacia y usaba. Y contemos agora
de la gran fiesta de Hátun Raimi[90].

CAP. XXX.--De cómo se hacían grandes fiestas y sacrificios á la grande y solene fiesta llamada
Hátun Raimi.

Muchas fiestas tenian en el año los Incas, en las cuales hacian grandes sacrificios conforme
á la costumbre dellos, y ponerlas todas en particular, era menester hacer de solo ello un volúmen;
y tambien hacen poco al caso y ántes conviene que no se trate de contar los desvaríos y hechicerías
que en ellas se hacian, por algunas causas; y solamente porné la fiesta de Hátun Raimi[91],
porque es muy nombrada. En muchas provincias se guardaba, y era la principal de todo el año
y en que más los Incas se regocijaban, y más sacrificios se hacian; y esta fiesta celebraban
por fin de agosto, cuando ya habian cogido sus maices, papas, quinua[92], oca[93], y las demás
semillas que siembran. Y llaman á esta fiesta, como he dicho, Hátun Raimi, que en nuestra lengua
quiere decir fiesta muy solene, porque en ella se habian de rendir gracias y loores al gran
Dios hacedor de los cielos y la tierra, á quien llamaban, como muchas veces he dicho, Ticiviracocha,
y al Sol, y á la Luna, y á los otros dioses suyos, por les haber dado buen año de cosechas
para su mantenimiento. Y para celebrar esta fiesta con mayor devocion y solenidad, se dice
que ayunaban diez ó doce dias, abstiniéndose de comer demasiado y no dormir con sus mugeres,
y beber solamente por la mañana, que es cuando ellos comen, chicha, y despues, en el dia, tan
solamente agua, y no comer ají, ni traer cosa en la boca, y otras cirimonias que entre ellos
se guardaban en semejantes ayunos. Lo cual pasado, habian traido al Cuzco mucha suma de corderos,
y de ovejas, y de palomas y cuis, y otras aves y animales, los cuales mataban para hacer el
sacrificio; y habiendo degollado la multitud del ganado, untaban con la sangre dellos las estátuas
y figuras de sus dioses, ó diablos, y las puertas de los templos y oráculos, á donde colgaban
las asaduras; y despues de estar un rato, los agoreros y adivinos miraban en los livianos sus
señales, como los gentiles, anunciando lo que se les antojaban, á lo cual daban mucho crédito.

Y acabado el sacrificio, el grand sacerdote con los demás sacerdotes iban al templo del sol,
y despues de haber dicho sus salmos malditos, mandaban salir á las vírgenes mamaconas arreadas
ricamente y con mucha multitud de chicha quellas tenian hecha, y entre todos los que se hallaban
en la gran ciudad del Cuzco se comian los ganados y aves que para el sacrificio vano se habian
muerto, y bebian de aquella chicha, que tenian por sagrada, dándosela á beber en grandes vasos
de oro, y estando ella en tinajas de plata de las muchas que habia en el templo.

Y habiendo comido y muchas veces bebido, estando, así el rey como el grand sacerdote, como
todos los demás, bien alegres y calientes dello, siendo poco mas de mediodia, se ponian en
órden y comenzaban los hombres á cantar con voz alta los villancicos y romances que para semejantes
dias por sus mayores fué inventado, que todo era dar gracias á sus dioses, prometiendo de servir
los beneficios recebidos. Y para esto tenian muchos atabales de oro engastonados algunos en
pedreria, los cuales les tañian[94] sus mujeres, que juntamente con las mamaconas sagradas
les ayudaban á cantar.

Y en mitad de la plaza tenian puesto, á lo que dicen, un teatro grande con sus gradas, muy
adornado con paños de plumas llenos de chaquira de oro, y mantas grandes riquísimas de su tan
fina lana, sembrados de argenteria de oro y de pedreria. En lo alto de este trono ponian la
figura de su Ticiviracocha, grande y rica; al cual, como ellos tenian por Dios soberano hacedor
de lo criado, lo ponian en lo más alto y le daban el lugar más eminente; y todos los sacerdotes
estaban junto á él; y el Inca con los principales y gente común le iban á mochár, tirándose
los alpargates, descalzos, con grand humildad; y encogian los hombros y, hinchando los carrillos,
soplaban hácia él, haciendo la mocha, que es como decir reverencia.

Abajo deste trono se tenia la figura del sol, que no oso afirmar de lo que era hecha, y tambien
ponian la de la luna y otros bultos de dioses esculpidos en palos y en piedras; y crean los
letores, que tenemos por muy cierto, que ni en Jerusalem, Roma, ni en Persia, ni en ninguna
parte del mundo, por ninguna república ni rey dél se juntaba en un lugar tanta riqueza de metales
de oro y plata y pedreria como en esta plaza del Cuzco, cuando estas fiestas y otras semejantes
se hacian; porque eran sacados los bultos de los Incas, reyes suyos, ya muertos, cada uno con
su servicio y aparato de oro y plata que tenian, digo los que habiendo sido en vida buenos
y valerosos, piadosos con los indios, generosos en les hacer mercedes, perdonadores de injurias;
porque á estos tales canonizaba su ceguedad por sanctos, y honraban sus huesos, sin entender
que las animas ardian en los infiernos, y creían questaban en el cielo. Y lo mesmo era de algunos
otros orejones ó de otra nacion, que por algunas causas que en su gentilidad hallaban, los
llamaban tambien sanctos. Y llaman ellos á esta manera de canonizar ylla, que quiere decir
cuerpo del que fué bueno en la vida[95]; y en otro entendimiento, yllapa significa trueno ó
relámpago; y asi llaman los indios á los tiros de artilleria yllapa, por el estruendo que hace[96].

Pues juntos el Inca y el grand sacerdote con los cortesanos del Cuzco y mucha gente que venia
de las comarcas, teniendo sus dioses puestos en tálamo, los mochaban, que es hacerles reverencia,
lo que ellos usaban ofreciéndoles muchos dones de ídolos de oro pequeños y ovejas de oro, y
figuras de mujeres, todo pequeño, y otras muchas[97] joyas. Y estaban en esta fiesta de Hátun
Raimi quince ó veinte dias, en los cuales se hacian grandes táquis y borracheras y otras fiestas
á su usanza; lo cual pasado, daban fin al sacrificio, metiendo los bultos de los ídolos en
los templos, y los de los Incas muertos en sus casas.

El sacerdote mayor tenia aquella dignidad por su vida, y era casado, y era tan estimado, que
competia en razones con el Inca, y tenia poder sobre todos los oráculos y templos, y quitaba
y ponia sacerdotes. El Inca y él jugaban muchas veces á sus juegos, y eran estos tales de grand
linaje y de parientes poderosos, y no daban la tal dignidad á hombres bajos ni oscuros, aunque
tuviesen mucho merecimiento.--Nobles se llaman todos los que vivian en la parte del Cuzco,
que llamaban orencuzcos y anancuzcos[98], y los hijos descendientes dellos, aunque en otras
partes residiesen en otras tierras. Yo me acuerdo, estando en el Cuzco el año pasado de mill
quinientos y cincuenta por el mes de agosto, despues de haber cogido sus sementeras, entrar
los indios con sus mugeres por la ciudad con gran ruido, trayendo los arados en las manos y
algunas pajas y maíz, hacer fiesta en solamente cantar y decir cuanto en lo pasado solian festejar
sus cosechas. E porque no consienten los apos[99] y sacerdotes questas fiestas gentílicas se
hagan en público, como solian, ni en secreto lo consintirian, si lo supiesen; pero como haya
tantos millares de indios sin se haber vuelto chripstianos, de creer es, que, en donde no los
vean, harán lo que se les antojare. La figura de Ticiviracocha, y la del sol y la luna, y la
maroma grande de oro, y otras piezas conocidas, no se han hallado, ni hay indio, ni chripstiano
que sepa ni atine á dónde están[100]; pero aunque mucho, esto es poco para lo que está enterrado
en el Cuzco y en los oráculos y en otras partes deste grand reino.

Pues con la más brevedad que pude escribí lo que entendí de la gobernacion y costumbre de los
Incas, quiero volver con mi escriptura á contar lo que hobo desde Manco Capac hasta Guascar,
como atrás prometí. Y así, deste como de otros no dan mucha noticia los orejones, porque, á
la verdad, hicieron pocas cosas; porque los inventores de lo escripto y los más valerosos de
todos ellos, fueron Inca Iupanqui y Tupac Inca, su hijo, y Guayna Capac su nieto; aunque tambien
lo debe causar la razon, que ya tengo escripta, de ser éstos los más modernos.

Luego, pues, que fué muerto Manco Capac y hechos por él los lloros generales y osequias, Sinchi
Roca Inca toma la borla ó corona con las cirimonias acostumbradas, procurando luego de alargar
la casa del sol y allegar á sí la más gente que pudo con halagos y grandes ofrecimientos, llamando,
como ya se llamaba á la nueva poblacion, Cuzco. Y algunos de los indios naturales dél afirman,
que á donde estaba la grande plaza, ques la misma que agora tiene, habia un pequeño lago y
tremedal de agua que les era dificultoso para el labrar los edificios grandes que querian comenzar
y edificar; mas, como esto fuese conocido por el rey Sinchi Roca[102], procura con ayuda de
sus aliados y vecinos deshacer aquel palude, cegándolo con grandes losas y maderos gruesos,
allanando por encima donde el agua solia estar, de tal manera, que quedó como agora lo vemos.
Y aún cuentan más, que todo el valle del Cuzco era estéril y jamás daba buen fruto la tierra
dél de lo que sembraron, y que de dentro de la grand montaña de los Andes trajeron muchos millares
de cargas de tierra, la cual tendieron por todo él; con lo cual, si es verdad, quedó el valle
muy fértil, como agora lo vemos.

Este Inca hobo en su hermana y mujer muchos hijos: al mayor nombraron Lloque Yupanqui[103].
Y visto por los comarcanos al Cuzco la buena órden que tenian los nuevos pobladores que en
él estaban, y cómo traian á su amistad las gentes más por amor y binivolencia que no por armas
ni rigor, algunos capitanes y principales vinieron á con ellos tener sus pláticas, holgándose
de ver el templo de Curicancha y la buena órden con que se regian; que fué causa que firmaron
con ellos amistades de muchas partes. Y dicen más, que como hobiesen venido al Cuzco, entre
estos que digo, un capitan del pueblo que llaman Zañu[104], no muy léjos de la ciudad, que
rogó á Sinchi Roca[105], con gran veemencia que en ello puso, que tuviese por bien que una
hija que él tenia muy apuesta y hermosa, la quisiese recibir para darla por mujer á su hijo.
Entendido esto por el Inca, pesóle, porque era lo que se le pedia cosa, que si lo otorgaba,
iba contra lo establecido y ordenado por su padre, y si no concedia al dicho deste capitan,
quél y los demás los tenian por hombres inhumanos, publicando que no eran más de para sí. Y
habiendo tomado consejo con los orejones y principales de la ciudad, paresció á todos que debia
de recibir la doncella para la casar con su hijo, porque hasta que tuviesen más fuerza y potencia,
no se habian de guiar en aquel caso por lo que su padre dejó mandado. Y así, dicen que respondió
al padre de la que habia de ser mujer de su hijo, que la trajiesen; y se hicieron las bodas
con toda solenidad, á su costumbre é modo, y fué llamada en el Cuzco Coya; y una hija que tenia
el rey, que habia de ser mujer de su hermano, fué colocada en el templo de Curicancha, á donde
ya habian puesto sacerdotes y se hacian sacrificios delante de la figura del sol, y habia porteros
para guarda de las mujeres sagradas de la manera y como está contado. Y como este casamiento
se hizo, cuentan los mismos indios que aquella parcialidad se juntó con los vecinos del Cuzco,
y haciendo grandes convites y borracheras, confirmaron su hermandad y amistad de ser todos
unos; y por ello se hicieron grandes sacrificios en el cerro de Guanacaure y en Tampuquiro
y en el mesmo templo de Curicancha. Lo cual pasado, se juntaron más de cuatro mill mancebos,
y hechas las cirimonias que para ello se habian inventado, fueron armados caballeros y quedaron
tenidos por nobles, y les fueron rasgadas las orejas y puestos en ellas aquel redondo que usar
solian.

Pasado esto y otras cosas que sucedieron al rey Sinchi Roca, que no sabemos, despues de ser
viejo y de dejar muchos hijos y hijas, murió y fué muy llorado y plañido, y le hicieron osequias
muy suntuosas, guardando su bulto para memoria que habia sido bueno, creyendo que su ánima
descansaba en los cielos.

Muerto, de la manera que se ha contado, Sinchi Roca, Lloque Yupanqui, su hijo, fué recebido
por Señor, habiendo primero ayunado los dias para ello señalados; y como por sus adivinanzas
y pensamientos se tuviese grande esperanza que en lo futuro la ciudad del Cuzco habia de florescer,
el nuevo rey comenzó á la ennoblecer con nuevos edificios que en ella fueron hechos, y rogó,
á lo que cuentan, á su suegro, quisiese con todos sus aliados y confederados pasarse á vivir
á su ciudad, á donde le seria guardado su honor y en ella ternia la parte que quisiese. Y el
señor ó capitan de Zañu[106] haciéndolo asi, se le dió y señaló para su vivienda la parte más
occidental de la ciudad, la cual, por estar en laderas y collados, se llamó Anancuzco; y en
lo llano y mas bajo, quedóse el rey con su casa y vecindad; y como ya todos eran orejones,
ques tanto como decir nobles, y casi todos ellos hobiesen sido en fundar la nueva ciudad, tuviéronse
siempre por ilustres las gentes que vivian en los dos lugares de la ciudad, llamados Anancuzco
y Orencuzco. Y aun algunos indios quisieron decir que el un Inca habia de ser de uno destos
linajes, y otro del otro; mas no le tengo por cierto, ni que es mas de lo que los orejones
cuentan, que es lo que ya está escripto. Por una parte y por otra de la ciudad habia grandes
barrios en los collados, porque ella estaba atrazada en cerros y quebradas, como se contó en
la Primera parte desta Corónica[107].

No dan relacion que en estos tiempos hobiese guerra notable; ántes afirman, que los del Cuzco,
poco á poco, con buenas mañas que para ello tenian, allegaban á su amistad muchas gentes de
las comarcas de su ciudad y acrescentaban el templo de Curicancha, así en edificios como en
riqueza; que ya buscaban metales de plata y oro, y dello venia mucho á la ciudad al tianquez[108]
ó mercado que en ella se hacia; y metíanse en el templo mujeres para no salir dél, segund y
como está dicho en otros lugares.

Y reinando desta manera Lloque Yupanqui en el Cuzco, pasándosele lo mas de su tiempo, allegó
á ser muy viejo, sin haber hijo en su mujer. Mostrando mucho pesar dello los vecinos de la
ciudad, hicieron grandes sacrificios y plegarias á sus dioses, así en Guanacaure como en Curicancha,
y en Tamboquiro; y dicen que por uno de aquellos oráculos donde iban [por] respuestas vanas,
oyeron que el Inca engendraria hijo que le sucediese en el reino; de lo cual mostraron mucho
contento, y alegres con la esperanza, ponian al viejo rey encima de su mujer la Coya, y con
tales burlas, á cabo de algunos dias, claramente se conoció estar preñada, y á su tiempo parió
un hijo.

Lloque Yupanqui murió, mandando primero que la borla ó corona del imperio fuese puesta y depositada
en el templo de Curicancha, hasta que su hijo tuviese edad para reinar, al cual pusieron por
nombre Mayta Capac; y por gobernadores dicen que dejó á dos de sus hermanos, los nombres de
los cuales no entendí.

Muerto el Inca Yupanqui, fué llorado por todos los criados de su casa, y en muchas partes de
la ciudad, conforme á la ceguedad que tenian, se mataron muchas mujeres y muchachos, con pensar
que le habian de ir á servir al cielo, donde ya tenian por cierto que su ánima estaba; y santificándole
por sancto, mandaron los mayores de la ciudad que fuese hecho bulto para sacar á las fiestas
que se hiciesen. Y cierto, grande es el preparamiento que se hacia para enterrar á uno de estos
reyes, y generalmente en todas las provincias le lloraban, y en muchas dellas se tresquilaban
las mujeres, ciñéndose sogas de esparto; y al cabo del año se hacian unas lamentaciones y sacrificios
gentílicos, mucho más de lo que se puede pensar. Y esto, los que se hallaron en el Cuzco el
año de mill quinientos y cincuenta, verian lo que allí pasó sobre las honras de Paulo[109],
cuando le hicieron su cabo de año; que fué tanto, que las más de las dueñas de la ciudad subieron
á su casa á lo ver; y yo me hallé presente, y cierto era para concebir admiracion. Y háse de
entender que era aquello nada en comparacion de lo pasado. Y diré agora de Mayta Capac.

Pasado, pues, lo que se ha escripto, Mayta Capac, se fué haciendo grande; el cual, despues
de haber hecho las cirimonias que se requerian, le fueron abiertas las orejas; y siendo más
hombre, en presencia de muchas gentes, así naturales como extranjeros, que para ello se juntaron,
rescebió la corona ó borla del imperio; é porque no tenia hermana con quien casar, tomó por
mujer á una hija de un[110] señorete ó capitan del pueblo de Oma, que estaba del[111] Cuzco
hasta dos leguas; la cual por nombre habia Mama Cahua Pata.

Hechas las bodas, estaba un barrio cerca de la ciudad, donde vivia un linaje de gente á quien
llamaban Alcaviquiza[112], y estos no habian querido tener amistad con los del Cuzco ninguna,
y estando llenos de sospechas unos de otros, dicen que yendo á tomar agua una muger del Cuzco
á ciertas fuentes que por allí estaban, salió un muchacho del otro barrio y le quebró el cántaro
y habló no sé qué palabras; la cual, dando gritos, volvió al Cuzco; y como estos indios son
tan alharaquientos, salieron luego con sus armas contra los otros, que tambien habian tomado
las suyas al ruido que oian, para ver en lo que paraba el negocio; y llegando el Inca con su
gente cerca, se pusieron en órden de pelea, habiendo tomado por achaque cosa tan liviana como
entre la india y muchacho habia pasado, para querer sojuzgar los de aquel linaje ó que la memoria
dellos se perdiese.

Y esto por los de Alcaviquiza bien era entendido; y como hombres de valor, salieron á la batalla
con grand denuedo, que fué la primera que se dió en aquellos tiempos, y pelearon gran rato
así los unos como los otros, porque habiendo sido el caso tan súpito, no habian podido allegar
favores ni buscar ayudas los de Alcaviquiza; los cuales, aunque mucho pelearon, fueron vencidos
despues de ser muertos todos los más, que casi no escaparon cincuenta con la vida. Y luego
el rey Mayta Capac, tomando posesion en los campos y heredades de los muertos, usando de vencedor,
lo repartió todo por los vecinos del Cuzco, y se hicieron grandes fiestas por la vitoria, yendo
todos á sacrificar á los oráculos que tenian por sagrados.

Deste Inca no cuentan los orejones más de que Mayta Capac reynó en el Cuzco algunos años; y
estando allegando gente para salir á lo que llaman Condesuyo, le vino tal enfermedad, que hobo
de morir, dejando por su heredero al hijo mayor, llamado Capac Yupanqui.

Paréceme, que destos Incas que al principio de la fundacion del Cuzco reinaron en aquella ciudad,
que los indios cuentan pocas cosas dello; y, cierto, debe ser lo que dicen, que entre los Incas,
cuatro ó cinco dellos fueron [los que] tanto se señalaron y que ordenaron é hicieron lo que
ya [he] escripto.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10629</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>166526</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>23089</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Sometimes sacrificed much of
this prophecy, and so they killed many cattle and poultry, and some men and women.

Without these oracles, had that of Aperahua, where by a tree Troncon replied Oracle, which
was found near him much gold, and that of Pachacamac, the Yuncas approaches, and many others,
and in the region of Andesuyo, as in that of Chincha and Omasuyo, and other parts of this kingdom,
from which I could say more, but, as I said it in the first part [87], which deals with the
foundations, I will not desto rather than the oracles, which had more devotion all the Incas
with other nations, sacrificed some men and women and many cattle, and to where there was this
credit, no human blood was not killed men, but they offered gold and silver. At guacas who had
less, they were like shrines, they offered beads and feathers and other small things of little
value. I say this because the opinion The Spanish have to say that in every temple they sacrificed
men, is false; and this is the truth according to what I caught, without pulling or put more
of what I understood and for me I have indeed.

Here goes well, that is understood, what the Capaccocha, respect for all was the service of the
temples and these and other, and by news that has old Indian they are alive and saw what happened
on this, I'll write what I have understood that it true. And they say that you had the habit
in Cuzco, for kings, which each year they made to come to that city to all the statues [88] and bundles
of idols that were in the buried treasures, which were the temples where they worship, which
were brought with great reverence Camay for priests and Dellas, parks guardians name, and as they
entered the city, were acknowledge them as received with great festivities and processions
and the room in places for that were identified and established, and having come from the
districts of the city, and even most of the provinces, large number of people, both men and women,
which reigned, accompanied by all the Incas and apricots, courtiers
and rulers of the city, they understood making great parties and drinking
and táquis.

They placed in the plaza of Cuzco the great chain of gold that encircled all, and so much wealth and
stones, as you can think of what has been the treasures questo eScript kings possessed; This
past was understood as every year they are used, which was, orchestras statues and packages and
priests gathered to find out through the mouth of them observing the event of the year, if
he would be fertile, or if he was to be sterile, if the Inca had long life, or if it even would die
that year, if enemies were to come somewhere, or if some of the peaceful they were to reveal. In
conclusion, were cross-examined about these things and other major and minor that will soon
crumble, because also wondered if there was fever, or if any homesick Vernia for livestock,
and if there would be multiple of a lot.

And this was done and asked not to all oracles together, but every man for himself: and if every
year the Incas did not do this, vivian went very modest and very unhappy and fearful, and did not
have their lives for granted.

And so glad the people and made its drunkenness a solemn banquets and other large táquis parties
that they use, different across to ours, where the Incas are with big win and at his expense treats
are made, that sum had large jars of gold and silver vessels of other things, because all the service
of his kitchen, to the pots and cups service was gold and silver, - sent to those who for what
were identified and had the time of High Priest, who was also present to the holidays with
such great pomp and triumph as the king himself, accompanied by priests and virgins who had
assembled there - that would make to each idol a question about these things, and he replied by
the mouth of the priests who had by their bulk, and these, as they were well inebriated, divined
what most Viana to the taste of those who asked, invented by them and by the devil, quests in those
statues. And made the questions to each idol, the priests being so astute in evil, Algund
term called to respond to that with more devotion and hear his credit Dellos ravings, because
they said they wanted to do their sacrifices, for being pleasant to the high their gods, were
served to respond to what was to be, and so were brought many animals, sheep and lambs, and
guinea pigs and birds, which passed the number of sheep more than two mill and sheep, and
they were slaughtered, by their exorcisms and demonic sacrifices vain to their manner, and then
denounced what they dreamed or what they pretended, or perchance
what Devil told them, and to give the answers, had a great mind to
look at what they said and formed in a few Dellos the event or good
or bad, and so they made with other answers, to see what was right
was telling the truth and what was to be in the same year.

This done, then left the begging of the kings with the offerings they call Capaccocha, and joining
the alms were usually returned to the temples of idols, and if last
year perhaps had one of those dreamers successful, happily ordered
it was the Inca from home.

The Capaccocha, as I was offering that is paid in lieu of tithes to the churches, of many gold and
silver vessels and other parts and stones, and loads of rich rugs, and much livestock. And
to those who had left uncertain and deceitful, not give them any offerings next year, before lost
reputation. To do this, we were doing great things in Cuzco, much more of what I write. And
now, after establishing the Audiencia Gasca and gone to Spain [89] between some things that
were discussed in some lawsuits, mention was made of this Capaccocha;
and this and everything else that we eScript is true that to and used.

And count agora of the great feast of Hatun Raimi [90].

CAP. XXX .-- How he did big festivals and sacrifices to the big party called solene Hatun Raimi.

Many
parties were in the year the Incas, where they made great sacrifices as to the custom of them, and
put them all in particular, was necessary to make it only one volume; and also do little and before
you should not try to count the rantings and witchcraft that they were doing, for certain causes,
and only the party of Hatun porno Raimi [91] because it is named. In many provinces are kept,
and was the principal of the year and they rejoiced over the Incas, and more sacrifices they
made, and this event celebrated last August, when they had taken their mails, potatoes, quinoa
[92], goose [93], and other seeds sown. And called to this feast, as I said, Hatun Raimi, which
in our language means very solene party, because she had to give thanks and praise to the great
God maker of heaven and earth, whom he called, as I have often said, Ticiviracocha, and Sun, and to
the moon and the other gods to his own, for they have given good year of crops for maintenance.
And to celebrate this event with greater devotion and solemnity, are said that ten or twelve
days fasting, abstinence from eating too much and not sleeping with their wives and drink only
in the morning, when they eat, chicha, and later in the day, so only water and not eat chili,
or bring anything into the mouth, and others among them cirimonias were kept in such fasts.
That past, had brought to Cuzco large sum of lambs and sheep, and doves and guinea pigs, and birds
and animals, who kill to make sacrifice, and having the crowd of cattle slaughtered, blood
smeared with Dell's statues and figures of their gods, or devils, and the gates of the temples and
oracles, to which hung the offal, and after spending some time, the soothsayers and diviners
looked in the light their signals, like the heathen, preaching what they wanted, which gave them
much credit.

And finish the sacrifice, the grand priest with the other priests went to the temple of the sun,
and after saying his psalms cursed, sent out to the virgins virgins herded richly and very many
quella chicha had made, and among those who were in the great city of Cuzco ate the cattle and
poultry for slaughter had vainly dead, and drank of that chicha, which had held sacred, giving
it to drink in large vessels gold, and she sat in silver pots of
many who were in the temple.

And having eaten and drunk often, still, and the king and the grand priest as everyone else, happy and
warm dello well, being little more than noon, were put into order and the men began to sing Christmas
carols loudly and for such romances days for their elders was invented, it was all thanks to
their gods, promising to serve RECEIVED benefits. And for this they had many golden drums
engastonados some in jewels, which rang them [94] their wives, along
with the sacred virgins helped them to sing.

And in the middle of the square was wearing, to what they say, a large theater with bleachers,
very feathers adorned with panels of gold-filled beads, and blankets of their much larger delicious
fine wool Argenteria planted gold and jewels. On top of this they placed the throne Ticiviracocha
figure of his great and rich, which, as they had for God's sovereign maker of the servant,
put him on top and gave him the most eminent, and all priests stood by him, and the Inca with the
main and common people were going to Mocha, pulling the sandals,
barefoot, with great humility, and shrugged his shoulders and puffing
out his cheeks, blowing towards him, making the mocha, which is to
say reverence.

Deste below throne had the figure of the sun, which I dare not say what was done, and also they
placed the moon and other packages of gods carved on sticks and stones, and create letores, we have
very certain, that neither in Jerusalem, Rome, or Persia, or in any part of the world, no republic
or king was collected in a place so rich in metals gold and silver and jewels as the square of
Cuzco, where these and other similar parties you were doing, because the packages were removed
from the Incas, their kings, already dead, each with appliance service and gold and silver they
had, say those who having been in good life and courageous, pious with the Indians, they make
grants generous, forgiving of insults; for to this such saints canonized by his blindness, and served
his bones, not understanding that the souls were burning in hell, and believed quest in the
sky. And do the same, was of some other dried apricots or any other nation, that for some
causes that were in their paganism, the also called saints. And they call this way of Ylla
canonized, which means body that was good in life [95], and other
understandings, yllapa means thunder or lightning, and so call the
Indians to yllapa artillery shots, the noise that do [96].

Then together the Inca and the grand priest with the courtiers of Cuzco and many people who
came of the districts, taking their gods put in thalamus, mocha, which is to make obeisance,
what they wore offering many gifts of gold statues and sheep small gold and figures of women, all
small, and many others [97] jewels. And they were at this event Hatun Raimi fifteen or twenty
days in which they made great táquis and drunkenness and other holidays
his style, which last gave an end to sacrifice, putting the bulk of
the idols temples, and the Incas killed in their homes.

The high priest had that dignity for her life, and was married, and was so esteemed that competed
in the Inca reasons, and had power over all oracles and temples, and removed and put priests.
The Inca and he played many times at his games, and it was these such grand powerful lineage
and relatives, and did not give a dignity to the low men and dark, although Nobles .-- they
had much merit called all who lived in the Cuzco they called anancuzcos orencuzcos and [98],
and children descendants of them, although other parties residing in other lands. I remember,
being in the last year Cuzco mill five hundred and fifty for the month of August, after having
taken their fields, enter Indians with their wives in the city with great noise, bringing the plow
in the hands and some straw and corn, to celebrate in just sing and say what they used to celebrate
in the past their crops. And because they do not allow the apos [99] and priests orchestras
parties Gentiles made in public, as usual, or what consintirian secret, if they knew, but as
has many thousands of Indians not to have become Christians, to believe is that, where not see,
what they will antojare. Ticiviracocha figure, and the sun and moon, and large gold rope, and other
familiar pieces have not been found, nor an Indian, nor chripstiano who can not hit upon where they
are [100], but even a lot, this is too much for what is buried in
Cuzco and the oracles and in other parts of this grand kingdom.

For brevity the more I wrote what I understood from the governorship and custom of Incas, I
return to my escriptura to tell what hobo from Manco Capac to Huascar, as earlier promised.
And so, dest as other do not give much notice the pears, because, the truth, did little things,
because the inventors of eScript and the most courageous all were
Inca Iupanqui and Tupac Inca his son and his grandson, Huayna Capac,
but also the cause of reason, that I have eScript, if they the latest.

Then, then, that Manco Capac was dead and made him the general crying osequias, Sinchi Inca Roca takes
the fringe or crown with cirimonias usual, trying to stretch after the house of the sun and furnish
to it the more people he could with praise and great offers, calling, named as the new population,
Cuzco. And some of the Indian state's natural, that where was the great square, the same approaches
that we now have, had a small lake and bog water was difficult for them till the big buildings
that they wanted to start and build, but, as this was known by King Sinchiroca [102], aims
to help its allies and neighbors undo that Palud, blinding him with large slabs and sliced ??thick
paving above where the water used to be, so that was as now we see it. And still have more that
the whole valley of Cuzco was sterile and never gave good fruit land that of what they have sown,
and that in the grand mountains of the Andes brought many thousands loads of land, which stretched
around him, with which, if true, was the valley very fertile, as
now we see it.

This Inca hobo in his sister and wife many children, the largest named Lloque Yupanqui [103]. And
as seen by their neighbors to Cuzco the good order which had the new settlers in he was, and
how he brought his friends love more people and not for weapons binivolencia or rigor, some captains
and principal men came to take his talks with them, rejoiced to see the temple of Curicancha
and good order with which they governed, and that was because they signed with them friends
of many parts. And say again that as hobiesen come to Cuzco, including these I say, a captain
of the village called ZANU [104], not far from the city, Sinchiroca begged [105], with great
veemencia to put it, she might rely upon rather than a daughter he had very handsome and beautiful,
wanted to take it for women to receive his son. Got this for the Inca, grieved, because that
was what was asked something, that if granted, went against the established and ordained by
his father, and if not granted to this captain said, nickel and the other men had for the treatment,
they were not publishing more than for himself. Y having taken counsel with the apricots and major
city, all that ought to paresció to receive the maiden to marry his son, because until they had
more strength and power guide had not at that case as he directed his father. And, they say
it responded the father of which was to be wife of his son who brought her, and made the wedding
with all solemnity, his custom and manner, and in Cuzco was called Coya, and a daughter who had
King, who was to be his brother's wife, was placed in the temple of Curicancha, whither had already
priests and sacrifices were made before the figure of the sun, and had porters to guard women
as sacred as it is told. And as this marriage was made, have the Indians that this bias is coupled
with the citizens of Cuzco, and making great treats and drunkenness, confirmed their brotherhood
and friendship to be all some, and therefore made great sacrifices in the hill and Tampuquiro
Guanacaure and he himself Curicancha temple. That past, gathered over four youths mill, and
made the cirimonias that this had been invented, they were armed men and were held by nobles, and
they were torn ears and put them to use that round they used to.

After this and other things that happened to King Sinchiroca, we do not know, after being old
and leaving many sons and daughters, died and was very crying and wailing, and made him osequias
very sumptuous package for keeping its memory had been good, believing that his soul resting
in heaven.

Dead, as has been counted, Sinchi Roca, Lloque Yupanqui, his son, he was received by Lord, having
first fasting day for this identified, and their guesses as and thought it had great hope that in future
the city of Cuzco was to Florescer, the new king began to ennoble with the new buildings in
it were made, and prayed, to what they say, to his father, wished with all his allies and confederates
to go live to his city, to where he would save his honor and Terni The party she wanted. And
ZANU lord or master [106] doing so, was given and noted for housing the most West Berlin, which,
being on slopes and hills, called Anancuzco; and the plain and lower, he remained the king
and his house and neighborhood, and as we all were dried apricots, approaches to saying nobles,
and nearly all hobiesen been found a new city, tuviéronse always distinguished the people who lived
in both places in the city, called Anancuzco and Orencuzco. And even some Indians wanted to say
that the Inca had to be a one desto lineages, and one from another, but I have certainly not,
nor is more than the dried apricots count, that is what is already eScript. On the one hand
and the other part of the city had large neighborhoods in the hills, because she was behind
on hills and ravines, as told in First Part of this crown [107].

Relationship are not in these times hobiese notable war, before they assert, that those of Cuzco,
gradually, with good tricks that this had, cleave unto his friend of many people the regions
of your city and the temple of Curicancha acrescentaban and buildings as wealth already sought
gold and silver metals, and them came much to the city to tianquez [108] market or therein to, and
in the temple metíanse women not to leave the second and as has been said elsewhere.

And in this way Lloque reigning Yupanqui in Cuzco, pasándosele the most of his time, Allegan
to be very old, without his wife's child. Despite showing a lot of the neighbors dello city,
made great sacrifices and prayers to their gods, as well as in Guanacaure Curicancha, and Tamboquiro,
and say that one of those oracles which were [for] answers vain heard that the Inca would engender
child to succeed to the kingdom which he showed much happy and joyful in hope, put the old king
on his wife Coya, and such taunts, to within a few days, clearly knew to be pregnant and gave
birth to their time a son.

Lloque Yupanqui died, sending first the fringe or crown of the empire were laid and deposited Curicancha
in the temple until the age their child had to reign, which began by Mayta Capac name, and the
governors say that he left two of his brothers names which did not understand.

Inca Yupanqui died, was mourned by all the servants of his house, and in many parts of the city,
according to the blindness they had, they killed many women and children, to think you had to go
to serve the sky where they had already certain that his soul was, and sanctifying by holy, sent the biggest
of the city that was made to remove the package holiday to them to. And true, there is great
preparation that was done to bury one of these kings, and generally in all the provinces he wept,
and many of them are shorn women, tightening ropes of straw, and the year after they made a howling
and sacrifices heathen, much more than you might think. And this, which is found in the Cuzco year five
hundred and fifty mill, they would see what happened there on the funeral of Paul [109] when
he made his year out, that was then, that most of the owners of the city rose to his house
to see, and I found myself present, and was to devise some admiration. And it is plain understand
that it meant nothing in comparison to the past. And tell agora Mayta Capac.

Lastly, then, what has been eScript, Mayta Capac, was doing great, who, after cirimonias have
done that were required, we were open ears, and being more man, in the presence of many nations,
natural and foreign, that this came together, rescebió the crown or tassel of the empire: and because
they had married sister with whom he took to to wife a daughter of a [110] SEÑORET or captain
of the town of Oma, who was the [111] Cuzco two leagues, which had named Cahua Mama Pata.

Made the wedding, was a neighborhood near the city where he lived a race of people whom Alcaviquiza
called [112], and these had not wanted to be friends with any of Cuzco, and were filled with
suspicions of each other, say that water going to take a wife of Cuzco to certain sources that
were there came a boy from another neighborhood and broke the pitcher and spoke not know what words
which, screaming, he returned to Cuzco, and as these Indians are so alharaquientos, then left
with their weapons against the other, who had also taken their own noise that they heard, to
see what came of the business, and came with the Inca People nearby were placed in order of
battle, having taken on something as light as pretext between India and boy had passed, to want
to subjugate those of the lineage or the memory Dell lost.

This is for those of Alcaviquiza well was understood, and as men of courage, they went to war with
grand courage, which was the first to be given at the time, and fought great time and one
as the others, because, having been the case so Supit, had not been getting of favors or seek
help from Alcaviquiza, which, although much fought, were defeated after being killed all over,
that hardly fifty escaped with their lives. And then King Mayta Capac, taking possession in
the fields and fields of the dead, using the winner, distributed it all for the citizens of Cuzco,
and made great feasts for the victory, going all to sacrifice to the sacred oracles they had for.

Deste
Inca did not have the apricots over Mayta Capac reigned at Cuzco
few years, and being aide to people to leave what they call Condesuyo,
there came such a disease, that hobo died, leaving as his heir to
the eldest son, called Capac Yupanqui.

It seems to me, referring to this Incas at the beginning of the founding
of Cuzco reigned in that city The Indians have little of it; and,
indeed, must be what they say, that among the Incas, Dellos were four
or five [which] both identified and ordered and did what and [I] eScript.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>