<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>217415</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22510</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El mastín, viendo al recién llegado achicarse, se creció horriblemente. ¡Guau,
guau! gritó, buscando el registro más feroz y amenazador que pudo hallar en su pecho. Al mismo
tiempo clavaba una mirada de exterminio en el presbítero y avanzaba, aunque con cierta cautela,
hacia él. Éste, aterrado por aquellos ladridos salvajes, dio tres o cuatro pasos atrás y extendió
el brazo con el paraguas, que traía para quitarse el sol, hacia adelante. «¡Paraguas! El recurso
de los cobardes,» debió pensar el mastín. Y se encrespó de tal modo ante aquel ultraje, que
no lo hubiera pasado bien el clérigo a no salir a la puerta una vieja chillando:

--¡Cuco! ¡Cuco! ¡Aquí, Cuco! ¡Fuera, Cuco! ¡Maldito perro! ¡Aquí!... ¡Aquí! ¡Ven aquí!

El perro vaciló un instante, dejó de ladrar y mostró bastante claramente la resolución de volverse
otra vez a dormir como si no hubiera pasado nada; pero la vieja no se dio por satisfecha; exigía
un acto de sumisión.

--¡Aquí, Cuco! ¡Aquí, ahora mismo!

El Cuco bajó la cabeza humildemente y emprendió hacia ella una marcha lenta, penosísima, como
si el camino estuviera erizado de peligros.

--¡Aquí! ¡Venga usted aquí!

«Me trata de usted, ¡malísimo!» se dijo el perro, a quien no hacían efecto las pompas y vanidades.
Y avanzó con mayores precauciones aún, asegurando bien la pezuña a cada paso que daba, meneando
el rabo de un modo vertiginoso.

--¡Aquí! ¡Aquí!--seguía gritando la vieja.

Por fin, a una velocidad máxima de seis pasos por minuto, llegó el Cuco a su destino. La vieja
le cogió por la parte de oreja que le quedaba y dio tres o cuatro tirones con fuerza. El perro
lanzó un aullido de dolor. Luego le cogió por la otra, y otros tantos tirones. Mayor y más
triste aullido aún. Cumplidos sus deberes con la justicia de la tierra, el mastín se retrajo
de nuevo hacia la tabla del hórreo, no sin lanzar por lo bajo algunas imprecaciones y blasfemias.
Esta escena se repetía unas cuantas veces al día, siempre que alguna persona sospechosa, como
ahora, llegaba con propósitos hostiles a la rectoral. El Cuco deploraba en su fuero interno
que no le hubieran rapado mejor las orejas.

--Buenas tardes, D. Gil--dijo la vieja, cambiando súbito la expresión colérica por otra sonriente,
melosísima, dando muestras de que le conocía.

El P. Gil, a quien no sucedía otro tanto, respondió muy cortésmente y preguntó por D. Restituto.

--El señor cura debe de estar hacia el establo. Pase usted, D. Gil. Iré a llamarlo.

--No hay necesidad: yo mismo iré a buscarlo. ¿El establo está aquí?...

--Sí, señor; aquí detrás de la casa.

Dio la vuelta a toda ella el sacerdote, subió algunos pasos por una calleja sucia, y se encontró
con una misérrima fábrica hecha de piedras del río sin labrar apenas, con una puerta desvencijada.
Estaba cerrada, y a nadie vio por allí delante. Iba a dejar aquel sitio y volverse a la casa,
cuando detrás del establo oyó ruido de voces. Fuese hacia allá, y halló, en efecto, a don Restituto,
sorprendiéndose no poco del traje y la situación en que se le apareció.

El anciano cura vestía unos calzones anchos de pana, remendados, como los que gastan los paisanos
por aquella tierra; traía en los pies almadreñas con escarpines de paño burdo, chaqueta lustrosa
por el uso, y camisa de lienzo hilado por el ama, sin alzacuello ni cosa que lo valga. Era
el traje de un labrador, sin quitar ni poner nada. Pero lo que hacía verdaderamente peregrino
y estrafalario el atavío es que en la cabeza traía un bonete viejo y grasiento.

El P. Gil quedó asombrado de aquella figura, y más asombrado, cuando advirtió la ocupación
a que el párroco se entregaba. Estaba, con una rodilla hincada en tierra, desollando un becerro.
Le ayudaba en la operación el criado. Tenían al animal extendido entre los dos, la mayor parte
de él en carne viva ya. Volvió la cabeza D. Restituto al sentir pasos, y hallándose con su
joven compañero, se puso en pie y vino hacia él con las manos ensangrentadas empuñando un enorme
cuchillo.

--¿Qué milagro es éste, amigo? ¡El futuro cura de Peñascosa se digna hacernos una visita!...
Mira, no te doy la mano, porque ya ves cómo la tengo. Bien de salud, ¿verdad?... Por aquí tampoco
hay novedad.

D. Restituto trataba de tú, familiarmente, a todos los clérigos más jóvenes que él desde la
primera entrevista. Cuando Gil le hubo explicado el motivo de su viaje, mostró cierta extrañeza,
pero se apresuró a responderle:

--Bueno, bueno. Yo voy a concluir en seguida. Vete a casa, y espérame.

Pero el joven manifestó deseos de ir a la iglesia.

--¿A la iglesia?--dijo sorprendido. Entre ellos era costumbre confesarse en casa.--Está bien.
No hay inconveniente. Pide al ama la llave, y espérame allí. No tardaré.

¡Pluguiera a Dios que hubiese tardado más! Y sobre todo, pluguiérale que hubiera tenido tiempo
a lavarse bien. Porque el teólogo despedía de sí un vaho de matadero que derribaba. Mientras
duró la confesión, y duró bastante, el P. Gil apenas pudo pensar en otra cosa. Sentíase asfixiado
por aquel olor nauseabundo; acudíanle unas congojas y sudores que estuvieron a punto varias
veces de privarle del sentido. Don Restituto sintió verdadera satisfacción en poder sacar a
relucir su antigua batería de proposiciones teológicas. A cada duda que su atribulado penitente
le ofrecía, contestaba victoriosamente con un texto latino. Como el veterano descuelga con
gozo sus armas a la señal de guerra, así el viejo opositor a la lectoralía de Lancia descolgó
de su memoria los textos enmohecidos ya de Perronne y de Balmes. ¿Cómo dudar de la inmortalidad
del alma, cuando ésta es una cosa simple, y las cosas simples no pueden descomponerse? ¿Quién
se atreve a imaginar que la Iglesia católica puede algún día perecer, cuando están ahí sangrando
las palabras de Jesucristo: «Las puertas del infierno no prevalecerán (non pr?valebunt?)» ¿Cómo
se ha de dar más crédito a la palabra de los hombres que a la de Dios? Pues qué, ¿la Divina
Sabiduría no ha dicho: «Yo para esto nací y para esto vine al mundo, para dar testimonio a
la verdad?» Y este testimonio ¿no está bien claro y bien patente en las obras visibles que
exceden al poder natural, por ejemplo, en la curación de los enfermos, en la resurrección de
los muertos y en otros admirables milagros llevados a cabo por Nuestro Señor Jesucristo y por
los Santos Apóstoles?

El P. Gil recibió la absolución, prometiendo no ser más demente ni idiota; así juzgaba don
Restituto al que dudaba de las verdades reveladas por angélico ministerio. Poco después de
besar aquella mano no bien purgada de la sangre del becerro, y cuando se hubo levantado para
rezar ante un altar la penitencia, nuestro presbítero se sintió indispuesto. Tuvo que salir
inmediatamente de la iglesia, acometido de violentas náuseas. En el pórtico devolvió toda la
comida. Llevole a casa el cura, y quiso curarle con una taza de salvia, remedio supremo que
empleaba contra todas las dolencias que afligen al género humano; pero su joven compañero,
que sabía a qué atenerse sobre su enfermedad, rehusó obstinadamente toda medicación. El párroco
entonces pasó a mostrarle la huerta, en la cual tenía cifrado tanto orgullo como en la profundidad
de sus conocimientos teológicos. Estaba llena de árboles frutales y legumbres. No se veía una
flor ni un arbusto de adorno. Desde allí pasaron a un vasto prado, donde tenía unos cuantos
operarios alzando pared. D. Restituto comenzó a darles instrucciones, aprobó algunas cosas,
reprobó otras, olvidándose por completo de su huésped. Uno de los operarios le participó que
el molino había parado porque el hijo de Cosme había desviado el agua más arriba para secar
el cauce del riachuelo y pescar las anguilas. D. Restituto se enfureció y anunció su propósito
de demandar a Cosme y pedirle indemnización de daños y perjuicios. De él no se burlaba nadie;
estaba resuelto a hacer que se respetase su propiedad. Desde allí se corrieron a los maizales,
y el párroco mostró a su compañero con extremado gozo el estado magnífico de las plantas. El
agua había venido muy a tiempo, pero más que al agua se debía a la gran cantidad de abono que
había echado.

--Tú dirás: ¿dónde podrá hacer D. Restituto tanto estiércol para una tierra como ésta, de quince
días de bueyes? Voy a explicártelo. Yo, aunque tengo nueve cabezas de ganado, no podría abonar
ni la mitad de la tierra que llevo. ¡Aquí del intelectus! En todas las parroquias, como tú
sabes bien, hay una porción de pobretes, a los cuales no es posible sacarles un cuarto ni por
bautizos ni por matrimonios ni por nada. Pues bien, a estas calamidades vivientes les obligo
a echar de vez en cuando delante de sus casas (vulgo pocilgas) una buena cantidad de hoja seca
o tojo. Con el agua y el paso de los transeúntes y el estiércol de las reses que cruzan se
convierte al cabo de algún tiempo en abono. Cuando ya está bien podrido me lo traen y voy formando
montón hasta que llega el tiempo de distribuirlo por la tierra. ¿Qué tal?

Desde allí saltaron a una heredad de prado. D. Restituto, en cuanto se vio en ella, dejó escapar
una risita aguda y burlona, que hizo levantar la cabeza a su joven compañero y mirarle con
curiosidad.

--Este es el prado del molino de abajo... el prado del molino de abajo, ya sabrás... ¿Cómo?
¿no sabes la historia de este prado? Pues ha corrido mucho por la villa... Pertenecía a los
mansos de la parroquia, y había quedado trasconejado cuando la venta de todos ellos. Yo lo
llevaba, y nadie en la parroquia se atrevía a denunciarlo. Pero había aquí un tabernero rico
llamado Lino (que ya reventó, a Dios gracias, el año pasado), y este Lino le tenía muchas ganas
al prado. Al fin dio el soplo en la administración, guardando la mano, porque no quería ponerse
mal conmigo, y lo sacaron a subasta. Dos días antes de hacerse, vino por acá el muy hipócrita
y me dijo: «Señor cura, voy a hacer postura al prado del molino de abajo, pero si usted lo
quiere me quedo en casa.» El tunante trataba de sonsacarme la cantidad que yo pensaba ofrecer.
«No, no lo quiero; puedes rematarlo cuando gustes,» le contesté. El hombre, viendo que yo no
iba al remate, y sabiendo que ningún vecino estaba en situación de tirarle, se las prometía
muy felices. Y mandó a Lancia a un primo hermano suyo. Pero a éste le fui a tropezar camino
de Peñascosa, y le hablé muy al caso, representándole el pecado en que incurría rematando bienes
de la Iglesia, le prometí darle en arriendo el prado, y le puse cuarenta duros en la mano.
¿Qué había de hacer el hombre? Fue a Lancia, lo remató y me lo traspasó a mí acto continuo...
¡Vaya una risa que se armó en el pueblo, amigo! Lino enfermó de rabia, y en cuanto se le presentó
ocasión, que fue al cabo de dos meses, viniendo de una romería, le pegó una puñalada a su primo...
¡Pero, anda, que buenos cuartos le costó la tal puñaladita! No lo hizo con diez mil reales.

Como ya el sol declinaba, después de haberle enseñado un lagar, que acababa de construir para
la sidra, D. Restituto llevó de nuevo a su penitente a casa y le convidó a chocolate. Pero
el excusador no se sentía aún bien. Además tenía prisa. Rehusó todo convite y emprendió el
camino de Peñascosa. El cura le acompañó un buen trecho.

Fuera ya de sus fincas y comprendiendo por el continente reflexivo del excusador de Peñascosa
que su ánimo seguía embargado por pensamientos serios, D. Restituto quiso volver a la carga,
aunque le pareciese sobradamente demostrado que todas las dudas de su compañero no eran más
que bombas de jabón, las cuales deshace con un soplo cualquiera que haya saludado siquiera
la Sagrada Teología.

--Debes fijarte, querido--le decía con protección ilimitada,--que las verdades de la fe no
son contrarias a la razón, sino que están sobre ella. Lo contrario de lo verdadero, ¿qué es?
Lo falso, ¿no es cierto? ¿Y cómo ha de tenerse por falso lo que está divinamente confirmado?
Las cosas que sabemos por revelación divina no pueden ser contrarias al conocimiento natural,
porque el conocimiento natural viene también de Dios, puesto que Dios es el autor de nuestra
naturaleza. Porque exceda a la razón una cosa no debe reputarse contraria a ella. Así dice
San Agustín que aquello que como verdad se demuestra por los libros santos, sea del Antiguo,
sea del Nuevo Testamento, de ningún modo puede serle contrario. El entendimiento humano no
puede llegar, naturalmente, a conocer la existencia de Dios, supuesto que nuestra inteligencia
en el modo de la presente vida comienza su conocimiento por el sentido, y por lo tanto, las
cosas que no caen bajo el sentido no pueden percibirse sino en cuanto por los sentidos puede
colegirse su conocimiento...

La tarde estaba fría y apacible. La campiña se extendía debajo del cielo trasparente, reflejando
con tonos verdes, claros, amarillentos, los rayos del sol que se ocultaba. El mar era una mancha
azul allá a lo lejos. Los dos clérigos habían atravesado ya el caserío principal, donde las
mujeres, sentadas a la puerta de casa, les daban las buenas tardes y los niños acudían a besarles
la mano. Estaban en la región abierta, ligeramente ondulada, que caracteriza la costa en aquel
país. El P. Gil, silencioso, caminaba con la cabeza baja, levantándola de vez en cuando para
enderezar su mirada vaga, perdida, hacia lo lejos, a las tierras rojas y a las rocas peladas
que festonaban la orilla del mar. El sol moría despidiendo su última llamarada, que enrojecía
una parte del horizonte. Y de allí venía una leve brisa helada que coloreaba los dedos y la
punta de la nariz, vigorizando los músculos y produciendo cosquilleo en los ojos. La campiña
se preparaba a dormir, exhalaba un suspiro de bienestar, mezcla confusa de voces y mugidos,
rechinar de carros, tañido de esquilas y rumor de olas, fundido todo y armonizado en la amplitud
de la llanura ilimitada. El P. Gil se esforzaba en atender a los argumentos que su anciano
compañero iba vertiendo con voz profunda y solemne. Eran los mismos que había estado oyendo
durante siete años en las cátedras del seminario de Lancia.

Al dejar la senda y penetrar en una callejuela estrecha vieron llegar un hato de ganado avanzando
lentamente. D. Restituto atajó su discurso teológico y se llevó la mano a los ojos a guisa
de pantalla.

--Son mis vacas--dijo sordamente.

Y antes que llegasen se puso a gritar al criado que las conducía:

--¿Qué tiene la Parda, que cojea?

--Debió meterse una espina.

--Pues en cuanto llegue al corral la registras bien y se la sacas, ¿entiendes?... Es la mejor
vaca que tengo--añadió por lo bajo, dirigiéndose a su compañero.

Y como ya estuviera entre ellas, el cura se acercó solícito, paternal, a la Parda y comenzó
a acariciarle el testuz, bajando al mismo tiempo la cabeza, para mirarle las patas.

--¡To, Parda!... ¡to! ¡to!... Espina debe de ser, porque en las patas no veo nada. Después
que se la saques la lavas bien con un poco de vino y romero... Di a Teresa que te lo prepare...
Nacida y criada en casa, ¿sabes tú?--prosiguió volviéndose al excusador con la fisonomía enternecida.--Me
daba D. Jovino, tu feligrés, sesenta duros por ella... ¡Como si me diera ochenta! Esta alhaja
no sale de casa. ¡Qué anchura de pechos, eh? ¡Qué cuarto trasero! (Y se lo acariciaba blandamente
con la palma de la mano.) No da mucha leche, pero toda es manteca... Esta otra también nació
en casa... ¡Quieta, Guinda, quieta!... Es más torpe que la otra... Una novilla todavía... No
hace quince días que ha parido por primera vez... Ésta se deshace en leche... ¡Repara, repara
que ubre! ¡No puede andar con ella!... Cada chorro suelta como el dedo... Mira, mira... ¡Quieta,
Guinda!...

Y bajándose tiró de una de las tetas al animal e hizo salir dos o tres chorros de leche que
humedecieron el suelo. Al mismo tiempo volvió su faz, congestionada por la posición tanto como
por el gozo, hacia el joven coadjutor. Éste sonrió por complacencia, pero separó al instante
la vista, no pudiendo reprimir bien la repugnancia que sentía.

Se puso de nuevo el hato en marcha y ellos también. D. Restituto cogió otra vez el hilo de
su discurso.

--Ya sé que hay quien dice que por la razón no puede demostrarse que Dios es, y que esto sólo
puede obtenerse por la fe y la revelación... Error crasísimo. La falsedad de esta opinión se
manifiesta por el arte de la demostración, que deduce por los efectos las causas, y por el
orden mismo de las ciencias, porque si no hay ninguna sustancia cognoscible fuera de lo sensible,
no habrá tampoco ninguna ciencia supranatural, como se dice in quarto Metaphysicorum. Hay que
distinguir lo que es conocido per se simpliciter, y lo que es conocido quoad nos. Simpliciter
que Dios es por sí, es conocido...

D. Restituto tenía una memoria felicísima. Al cabo de tantos años recordaba perfectamente su
Dogmática, y la recitaba vertida al castellano con el mismo énfasis que si la hubiera inventado.
También la recordaba el P. Gil, porque la tenía más reciente, pero escuchaba con atención,
por humildad, esforzándose en admirar la fortaleza de aquellos argumentos, en considerarlos
irrefutables. El anciano teólogo se detenía a menudo, balbucía olvidando alguna demostración,
pero súbito tomaba vuelo y se lanzaba vigoroso sobre las premisas, haciéndoles sudar inmediatamente
las conclusiones apetecidas.

--...Todo lo que se mueve se mueve por algo. O lo que mueve es movido o no. Si no se mueve,
tenemos lo que buscamos, un móvil inmóvil, y a esto llamamos Dios. Si se mueve, es por algo
que le mueve, y entonces, o hay que seguir así hasta el infinito, o tenemos que llegar a algún
móvil inmóvil; pero en el orden del movimiento no puede haber proceso infinito... ergo hay
que suponer un primer móvil inmóvil. Probemos ahora que todo movimiento se determina por algo.
Si algo se mueve a sí mismo, es necesario que tenga en sí el principio de su movimiento...

Caminaban por una senda estrecha abierta entre los maizales. El teólogo iba delante y el P.
Gil detrás. Súbito aquél paró en firme el paso y la lengua. Al doblar un recodo se encontró
de frente con el hijo de Cosme, que traía colgado a la espalda un cesto mediado de anguilas.
Verlo el teólogo y arrojarse sobre él sin conmiseración fue todo uno.

--¡Granuja! ¡Grandísimo perro! ¿Conque eres tú el que me quitas el agua del molino? ¡Te voy
a desollar vivo! ¿Es tu padre quien te enseña esas picardías? ¿Es el maestro quien te las enseña?
¡Desvergonzado, cínico!

Le tenía asido fuertemente por entrambas orejas, y a cada interrogación le daba una fuerte
sacudida. El chico, comprendiendo bien que aquellos interrogantes tenían un fin puramente retórico
y no debían ser contestados, limitábase a lanzar gritos de dolor inarticulados.

--¡Ven acá, pilluelo! ¡Quiero llevarte delante de tu padre! ¡A ver si me dices ahora que yo
te tengo mala voluntad! ¡Has de parar en un presidio! ¡Ven aquí, ven!

Y como no era factible llevarle cogido de las dos orejas, el anciano teólogo se avino, aunque
con profundo dolor, a soltar una, comunicando instantáneamente a la otra su parte de presión
para que no se desperdiciase nada. En esta forma, con el rostro encendido y los ojos llameando
de cólera, dio la vuelta hacia el pueblo sin despedirse de su compañero, llevando medio en
suspensión al chico, que lanzaba quejidos lastimeros.

El P. Gil le contempló estupefacto hasta que le perdió de vista. Permaneció todavía unos momentos
inmóvil, abstraído. Y emprendió de nuevo su camino que se acercaba cada vez más a la orilla
del mar, para bajar por una rampa suave a Peñascosa. La luz desaparecía por momentos. El frío
aumentaba. El océano en calma había perdido su bello color azul, cambiándolo por otro gris
con reflejos acerados. De vez en cuando un soplo de viento helado hacía correr por la tersa
superficie de las aguas un estremecimiento que las rizaba leve y momentáneamente, como si al
mar se le pusiera carne de gallina. Y este estremecimiento se comunicaba al joven presbítero
y llegaba hasta el fondo de su ser. Lo que sentía en su alma no era ni dolor, ni agitación,
ni congoja; era tan sólo frío, un frío mortal que le roía los huesos. Nunca se había visto
tan solo y desvalido. Sus ojos iban obstinadamente fijos en el suelo. No se atrevía a levantarlos
e interrogar la inmensidad como otras veces. Estaba seguro de su respuesta y la temía.

Cuando llegó a las primeras casas del arrabal de la Gusanera había cerrado ya la noche. Al
pasar por delante de una de las más pobres y sucias llamó su atención el estrépito de golpes
y gritos que de adentro partía. Detuvo el paso asustado y procuró averiguar qué era aquello.
Por las pequeñas ventanas iluminadas no se veía más que agitarse violentamente algunas sombras.
A sus oídos llegaban, entre el confuso vocerío, algunas blasfemias que le estremecían. De pronto
se abre con violencia la puerta y sale precipitadamente una masa negra, disparada por unas
manos que cierran de nuevo al instante. El P. Gil reconoció en aquella masa negra a un clérigo.
Se aproximó solícito y vio que era el P. Norberto, con manteos y sin sombrero.

--¡D. Norberto! ¿Qué es eso? ¿Qué le pasa?

--Hola, querido. Nada, nada... no es nada--respondió sin aturdimiento.

--Sí le pasa algo... ¿Qué le han hecho a usted en esa casa?

--Nada, nada... Vámonos que se reúne gente.

--¿Se va usted a ir sin sombrero?

--Es verdad... Voy a pedirlo... Aguarda un poco.

Pero en aquel instante salió de una de las ventanas de la casa y voló por el aire el sombrero,
cayendo enmedio de la carretera, esto es, cerca de los clérigos. Al mismo tiempo una voz ruda
dijo, acompañándolo de varias interjecciones:

--Toma la teja, ladrón. Si vuelves por aquí, te vas sin las orejas.

El P. Norberto se apresuró a recogerla del suelo y echó a andar.

--Pero explíqueme usted...--le dijo el coadjutor juntándose a él y haciendo esfuerzos por seguirle
el paso.

--Ya te lo explicaré... Ahí más abajo.

Cuando hubieron salido de la Gusanera, salvado la plaza y entrado en la calle del Cuadrante,
D. Norberto acortó un poco el paso. El excusador aprovechó la ocasión para insistir en sus
preguntas.

--Vamos a ver, ¿qué le ha pasado a usted?

--Pues mira, en esa casa vive una muchacha, una niña que apenas tiene quince años, a quien
su madre ha prostituido, entregándola a ese chalán que llaman Pepe el Manchego.

--¿Y usted ha ido allí a ver si la sacaba de sus garras?

--La había visto ya otras dos veces, y no parecía mal dispuesta; pero no sé quién dio soplo
a ese hombre, y hoy se presentó de repente y armó un alboroto.

--¡Jesús! ¡Está usted herido!--exclamó el padre Gil, viendo correr algunas gotas de sangre
por las mejillas de su compañero. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>462719</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20080</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The mastiff, watching the newcomer shrink, it grew horribly. Wow, Wow! he shouted,
looking fierce and menacing record he could find in his chest. At the same time extermination
riveting look at the priest and went, though cautious, to him. That, terrified by those wild barking,
swam three or four steps back and spread the arm with the umbrella, which brought to remove the sun,
forward. "Umbrellas! The appeal of cowards, "he must have thought the mastiff. And so bristled at
this outrage, which I had not had a good cleric not to leave the door an old screaming:

- Cuckoo! Cuckoo! Here, Cuckoo! Outside, Cuckoo! Damn dog! Here! ... Here! Come here!

The dog hesitated for a moment, stopped barking and was quite clearly the decision to become back
to sleep as if nothing had happened, but the old woman was satisfied;
required an act of submission.

- Here, Cuckoo!

Here, now!

El Cuco humbly bowed his head toward her and began a slow, excruciating,
as if the path was fraught with danger.

- Here!

Come here!

"I is you, awful!" He told the dog, who did not effect the pomps and vanities. And he advanced with
even greater caution, lock the hoof at each step he took, shook the
tail of a rapid mode.

- Here!

Here! - Was shouting the old.

Finally, at a maximum speed of six steps per minute, arrived at their destination Cuco. The old
caught him by the left ear and gave him three or four pulls hard. The dog a howl of pain.
Then he took the other, and many other tugs. More and more still sad howl. Fulfilled his duties
with the law of the land, shrank mastiff back to the table in the barn, but not releasing it under
some curses and blasphemies. This scene was repeated a few times a day, provided that any person
suspected as now arrived for purposes hostile to the rectory. El Cuco deplored in their hearts
that had not shaved best ears.

- Afternoon, D. Gil - said the old, angry expression suddenly changing
the other smiling melosísima, showing who knew him.

Fr Gil, who was not happening as much, answered very politely and
asked D. Restituto.

- The priest must be toward the barn.

Come in, D. Gil. I'll call him.

- No need: I will fetch it myself. "The barn is here? ...

- Yes, sir, here behind the house.

He turned it all the priest, went a few steps in a dirty alley, and found a miserable factory made
of uncut stones from the river only, with a rickety door. It was locked, and nobody was there before.
Going to leave that place and come back to home behind the barn when he heard the sound of
voices. He went thither, and found, in fact, Don Restituto, not a little surprised the suit and
the situation in which he appeared.

The old priest was wearing corduroy trousers wide, patched, as they spend the peasants through the
land, wore on her feet clogs with socks of coarse cloth, shiny coat through use, and spinning
linen shirt he loves, without collar or anything like it. Was the costume of a peasant, without
removing it or put anything. But what really made pilgrim and outlandish attire is that the old
head and wore a greasy cap.

Fr Gil was shocked by that figure, and more astonished, when he warned
the occupation that the pastor was delivered.

I was, kneeling on one knee on the ground, skinning a calf. He helped in the operation servant.
The animal had spread between the two, most raw it now. He turned his head D. Restituto steps, feeling,
and being with young fellow stood up and came toward him with bloody
hands clutching a huge knife.

- What miracle is this, man?

The future priest Peñascosa deigns to visit us!

... Look, do not shake hands, because you see how I have it.

Good health, right? ... Not here no novelty.

D. Restituto was you, familiar to all young clerics he from first interview. When Gil had explained
the reason for his trip, showed some surprise, but was quick to respond:

- Well, well. I will close immediately. Go home, and wait.

But the young man expressed a desire to go to church.

- To the church? - Said in surprise. Among them was customary confession at home .-- All right.
No problem. Calls to love the key, and wait there. It will not take.

Would to God that had taken more! And above all, would have had time pluguiérale to wash. For the
theologian dismissed him a whiff of cutting down slaughterhouse. While confession lasted, and lasted
a long time, Fr Gil could hardly think of anything else. He felt suffocated for that foul smell;
acudíanle some worries and sweats that were about several to deprive of sense sometimes. Don
Restituto felt great satisfaction in order to get shine your old battery theological propositions.
Each question his troubled penitent offered him, he answered triumphantly with a Latin text.
As the veteran off-hook with joy their weapons to the signal of war, the old opponent of the
Lancia picked lectoralía of memory texts already Perronne rusty and
Balmes.

How can one doubt of immortality the soul, when it is something simple, and simple things
can not be broken? Who dare to imagine that the Catholic Church may someday die, when there
bleeding Christ's words: "The gates of hell shall not prevail (non pr?valebunt?)" How be given
more credence to the word of men than of God? What! Divine Wisdom has said: "For this I was
born and for this I came into the world, to testify to the truth? "And this testimony is not
is clear and well illustrated in the works visible exceed the natural power, for example, in
healing the sick, the resurrection of the dead and other wonderful miracles performed by Our
Lord Jesus Christ and the Apostles?

Fr Gil received absolution, promising not to be insane or an idiot, so don judged Restituto who
doubted the truths revealed by angelic ministry. Shortly after kissing the hand not well purged
from the blood of the bullock, and when he had risen to praying before an altar of repentance,
our priest fell ill. Had to leave immediately from the church, seized with violent nausea. On
the back porch all food. The priest brought him home, and tried to cure him with a cup of sage,
the supreme remedy used against all the ailments that afflict mankind, but his young companion,
I knew what to expect about your condition, obstinately refused all medication. The pastor then
went on to show the garden, in which encryption was so proud and in depth of theological knowledge.
It was full of fruit trees and vegetables. There was not a flower or ornamental shrub. From
there they went to a vast lawn, where he had a few raising operators wall. D. Restituto began
giving instructions, adopted a number of things failed other, forgetting
all about his guest.

One of the workers took him to the mill had stopped because the son of Cosimo had deviated above
the water to dry the bed of the creek and catch eels. D. Restituto was furious and announced plans
Cosme to sue and ask for damages and losses. Of it is not mocked; was determined to make his
property was respected. From there he ran into the cornfields, and the pastor was a fellow with
extreme joy the great state of plants. The water had come just in time, but most of the water
was due to the large quantity of fertilizer had missed.

- You say: where you can make D. Restituto much manure to a land like this, fifteen days of oxen? I'll
tell you. I, though I have nine heads of cattle, could not pay even
half of the land that I have.

Here's intelectus! In every parish, as you You know, there are a lot of wretches, to whom it is
not possible for them out one quarter or baptisms or marriage or anything. However, these
calamities forced them living to take from time to time outside their
homes (commonly pens) a good amount of dry leaf or gorse.

With water and the passage of pedestrians and cattle manure is crossing becomes after some
time pass. When it is well rotted and I'll bring me forming lot until the time comes to distribute
the land. What?

From there they jumped to an inheritance of meadow. D. Restituto, as it was, let out a sharp, mocking
laugh, he did raise his head to his young companion and look at him curiosity.

- This is the meadow below the mill ... the meadow below the mill, you already know ... How?
Do not you know the history of this field? Well, much has run the town ... Belonged to the meek
of the parish, and had been trasconejado when selling them. I had, and nobody in the parish
dared to denounce him. But here was a rich landlord called Lino (already busted, thank God,
last year), and that he was eager Lino the meadow. At the end gave the breath in the administration,
keeping the hand, not wanting to be wrong with me, and brought it to auction. Two days before done,
came here the very hypocritical and I said, 'Father, I do stand in the meadow below the mill,
but if you I want to stay home. "The rascal probe for the amount I planned to offer. "No, I do
not want, you can top it when you like," I replied. The man, seeing that I went to auction, and knowing
that any neighbor was in a position to throw, they were promised very happy. Lancia Y sent to his
cousin.

But this road trip we went to of rocks, and spoke highly relevant, represents sin incurred goods
topping of the Church, I promised him rent the pasture and put him forty dollars in hand.
What was the man do? It was a Lancia, finished him off and handed it to me to me in the next
breath ... What a laugh that was assembled in the town, buddy!

Lino ill with rabies, and as was presented occasion that was after two months, coming from a
pilgrimage, he stuck a knife to his cousin ... But, go, good rooms that cost him so puñaladita!
He did not do ten thousand.

As the sun went down, after having taught a winery, he had built for
cider, D. Restituto led back to his penitent home and invited him
to chocolate.

But the toilet was still not good. Also in a hurry. Refused all treat and started Peñascosa
way. The priest accompanied him some distance.

Out and understanding their properties and the continent reflective Peñascosa toilets that his
heart was seized with serious thoughts, D. Restituto wanted to return to the load though he
seemed well established that all doubts of his companion were only that pumps soap, which
breaks with a blow anyone who has even hailed Sacred Theology.

- You look out, dear - he said with unlimited protection, - the truths of faith are contrary to
reason, but above it. The opposite of truth, what is? False, is not it? And how has to be taken
for false what is divinely confirmed? The things we know by divine revelation can not be contrary
to natural knowledge, because the natural knowledge also comes from
God, because God is the author of our nature.

Because the ratio exceeds one thing should not be considered as contrary to it. Thus says San Augustine
as truth that which is shown by the holy books, is the Old, New Testament is in any way may find
otherwise. The human mind can, of course, aware of the existence of God, our intelligence course
in the way of this life begins his knowledge of the meaning, and therefore, the things that do not
fall under the senses can not perceive it as by the senses can colleagues their knowledge ...

The
evening was cold and quiet. The countryside stretched under heaven transparent, reflecting in
shades of green, clear, yellow, the rays of setting sun. The sea was a stain blue yonder. The
two priests had crossed the main building, where women sat at the front door, gave them a good
afternoon and went to kiss children hand. In the region were open, slightly undulating, which
characterizes the coast at that country. Fr Gil, silent, he walked with his head down, lifting
it from time to time to straighten his eyes wandering, lost, into the distance, the red soil
and bare rocks that festooned the sea. The sun died firing his last flare, which reddened part of
the skyline. And there came a slight breeze that colored frozen fingers and tip of the nose,
invigorating the muscles and causing tingling in his eyes. The countryside was preparing to
sleep, breathed a sigh of welfare welter of voices and lows, gnashing
of cars, ringing of bells and the murmur of waves, melting everything
and harmonized to the extent the limitless plain.

Fr Gil was trying to meet his old arguments companion was teeming with deep and solemn voice. Were
the same as had been hearing for seven years in the chairs of the seminar Lancia.

By leaving the path and enter a narrow street they saw a herd of cattle
moving slowly.

D. Restituto interrupted his theological and put his hand to his
eyes by way screen.

- Are my cows - said softly.

Before they arrived he shouted to the servant that led:

- What is Brown, limping?

- He should get a spine.

- Then when he arrives at the register pen well and the bags, you know? ... It is the best cow I have - he
said softly, turning to his companion.

And as I was among them, the priest approached caring, paternal, and started the Brown to stroke
his forehead, while lowering his head to look at her legs.

- To, Brown! ... To! To! ... Spine should be, because the legs do not see anything. After that it
serves the wash well with a little wine and rosemary ... Teresa gave
it to you prepare ... Born and raised in the house, do you know? -
Continued turning to the toilet with the face tenderly .-- Me D. was
Jovino, your parishioners, sixty dollars for it ... As if to give
me eighty!

This gem not leave the house. What width of breasts, eh? What back room! (And he softly stroked
with the palm of your hand.) does not give much milk, but everything is butter ... This one also
born at home ... Quiet, Guinda, still! ... It is more awkward than the other ... One heifer
still ... No a fortnight ago has given birth for the first time ...
It collapses in milk ... Repairs, repairs that udder!

You can not go with it! ... Each jet off as the finger ... Look, look ... Quiet, Cherry! ...

And
get off a shot the animal's teats and output two or three squirts
of milk moist soil.

At the same time turned his face, flushed by the position as well as by joy, to the young priest.
He smiled for complacency, but immediately separated sight, it was unable to suppress his revulsion.

He
got back up and herd them too. D. Restituto picked up the thread again his speech.

- I know some say that reason can not prove that God is, and this only can be obtained by faith
and revelation ... Crasísimo error. The falsity of this view manifested by the art show, which
follows the effects of causes, and the same order of science, because
if there is no knowable substance out of the sensitive there will
be no science nor supernatural, as they say in quarto Metaphysicorum.

Must distinguish what is known per se simpliciter, and what is known quoad nos. Simpliciter
God is in itself, is known ...

D. Restituto had a most happy memory. After so many years remembered very well his Dogmatic,
and poured into Castilian recited with the same emphasis as if he had invented. Father also remembered
Gil, because I had more recent, but listened attentively, humility, striving to admire the strength
of those arguments, consider irrefutable.

The old man stopped theologian often stuttered forgetting some demonstration but suddenly took
flight and threw strong on the premises, making them sweat immediately prized conclusions.

--...
Everything that moves is moved by something. Or what moves is moved or not. If not moving, we
have what we want, a mobile stationary, and this we call God. If it does, is something moves
him, and then either have to go on ad infinitum, or we have to reach some still mobile, but in
the order of movement can not be infinite process ... ergo there
that still pose a mobile first.

Let us now prove that all motion is determined by something. If something moves himself, he
must have within itself the principle of their movement ...

Walking down a narrow path open between the cornfields.

The theologian went ahead and P. Gil back. Suddenly it stood firm step and tongue. As we rounded
a bend was found head-Cosme's son, who brought her back hung a basket of eels mediated. View theologian
and thrown on him without pity was all one.

- Rogue!

Great dog! "So you're the one I take away the water mill? I'll to flay alive! Is it your father
who will teach those naughty? Are you a teacher who teaches them? Shameless, cynical!

He had grasped tightly by both of his ears, and every question he gave a strong shock. The boy,
realizing well that those questions were a purely rhetorical and
should not be answered, just kept throwing inarticulate cries of pain.

-
Come here, you rascal!

I want to take before your father! See if you tell me now that I I have bad you will! You have
to stop at a prison! Come here, come!

And as it was feasible for both ears caught the old man consented theologian, although with
deep pain, to drop one to instantly communicate pressure other hand
so that nothing is wasted.

In this way, with his face flushed and eyes blazing anger, he turned to the town without saying goodbye
to his companion, bringing average suspended the boy, throwing plaintive moans.

Fr Gil looked at him stunned until he lost sight of. He stood still a moment motionless, oblivious.
And again undertook his way to getting closer to the edge the sea, down a gentle ramp Peñascosa.
The light disappeared at times. Cold increased. The quiet ocean had lost its beautiful blue,
gray changing to another with a steely glare. Occasionally a gust of cold wind made for the
smooth running surface waters with a slight shudder that rippled and momentarily, as if sea
??is put goosebumps. And this thrill was communicated to the young priest and down in the
depths of his being. What she felt in her soul was no pain, no agitation, or distress, was just cold,
deadly cold gnawing bones. Never seen so alone and helpless. His
eyes were fixed on the ground stubbornly.

She dared not lift and question the immensity as usual. He was sure his response and feared.

When
he reached the first houses in the suburbs of the worms had already closed the night. Al pass
one of the poorest and dirty got his attention the noise of blows and started screaming inside.
Stood still scared and tried to figure out what it was. Lighted by small windows could be seen
but not violently shaken some shadows. To his ears came, among the confused shouting, some swearing
that he shook. Suddenly violently opens the door and rush out a black mass, triggered by a
hands immediately closed again. Fr Gil acknowledged in that black mass to a cleric. He approached
and saw that it was diligent Fr Norbert, with his cloak and no hat.

- D. Norberto! What is that? What happens?

- Hello, darling.

Nothing, nothing ... is not - responded without stunning.

- If something
happens ... What have they done to you in that house?

- Nothing,
nothing ... Come to meet people.

- Are you going to go without a
hat?

- It's true ... I will ask ... Wait a little.

But at that moment out of a window of the house and flew off his hat, falling in the middle of
the road, that is, close to the clerics.

At the same time a rough voice said, accompanied by several interjections:

-
Take the tile thief.

If you come back here, you leave without the ears.

Fr Norberto was quick to pick it up and started walking.

- But you
explain to me ...-- said the coadjutor with him and making efforts
to keep step.

- I'll explain ... There below.

When they had gone to the worms, bran into the square and the streets of the Quadrant, D. Norberto
shortened a little step.

The toilet used the occasion to press their questions.

- Let's see,
what happened to you?

- Well, look at that house lives a girl, a
girl just fifteen years old, who her mother is a prostitute, delivering
it to the horse trader called Pepe the Manchego.

- And you've gone
there to see if her out of his clutches?

- I had already seen twice,
and seemed ill-disposed, but do not know who gave breath that man,
and now suddenly appeared and made a fuss.

- Jesus!

Are you hurt! - Gil said the father, seeing a few drops of blood running the cheeks of your
partner

.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>