<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document02451</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>26641</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18540</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Y volviendo á nuestra historia, dicen que despues de haber hecho en esta provincia de Cacha
este milagro, que pasó adelante, siempre entendiendo en su obra, como ya habeis oido, y como
llegase á un sitio que agora dicen el Tambo de Úrcos, que es seis leguas de la ciudad del Cuzco,
subióse á un cerro alto y sentóse en lo más alto dél, de donde dicen que mandó que produciesen
y saliesen de aquella altura los indios naturales que allí residen el dia de hoy. Y porque
este Viracocha allí se hubiese sentado, le hicieron en aquel lugar una muy rica y suntuosa
guaca, en la cual guaca, porque se sentó en aquel lugar este Viracocha, pusieron los que la
edificaron un escaño de oro fino, y el bulto que en el lugar deste Viracocha pusieron, le sentaron
en este escaño; el cual bulto de oro fino, en la parte[6] del Cuzco que los chripstianos hicieron
cuando le ganaron, [valió ó pesó] diez y seis ó diez y ocho mill pesos. Y de allí el Viracocha
se partió y vino haciendo sus gentes, como ya habeis oido, hasta que llegó al Cuzco; donde
llegado que fué, dicen que hizo un Señor, al cual puso por nombre Alcaviza, y puso nombre ansímesmo
á este sitio, do este Señor hizo, Cuzco; y dejando órden como despues quél pasase produciese
los orejones, se partió adelante haciendo su obra. Y como llegase á la provincia de Puerto
Viejo, se juntó allí con los suyos que ante él inviaba en la manera ya dicha, donde como allí
se juntasen, se metió por la mar juntamente con ellos, por do dicen que andaba él y los suyos
por el agua ansí como si anduvieran por tierra. Otras muchas cosas hobiera aquí más escripto
deste Viracocha, segund que estos indios me han informado dél, sino, por evitar proligidad
y grandes idolatrías y bestialidad, no las puse; donde le dejaremos y hablaremos del producimiento
de los orejones de la ciudad del Cuzco, que ansímesmo van [usan] y siguen la bestialidad é
idolatría gentílica y bárbara que ya habeis oido[7].

En el lugar y sitio que hoy dicen y llaman la gran ciudad del Cuzco, en la provincia del Perú,
en los tiempos antiguos, ántes que en él hobiese Señores Orejones, Incas, Capaccuna, que ellos
dicen reyes, habia un pueblo pequeño de hasta treinta casas pequeñas pajizas y muy ruines,
y en ellas habia treinta indios, y el Señor y cacique de este pueblo se decia Alcaviza; y lo
demas dentorno deste pueblo pequeño, era una ciénega de junco, [y] yerba cortadera, la cual
ciénega causaban los manantiales de agua que de la sierra y lugar do agora es la fortaleza
salian; y esta ciénaga era y se hacia en el lugar do agora es la plaza y las casas del marqués
don Francisco Pizarro, que despues esta ciudad ganó; y lo mismo era en el sitio de las casas
del comendador Hernando Pizarro; y asimismo era ciénaga el lugar y sitio do es en esta ciudad,
de la parte del arroyo que por medio della pasa, el mercado ó tiánguez, plaza de contratacion
de los mismos naturales indios. Al cual pueblo llamaban los moradores dél desde su antigüedad
Cozco; y lo que quiere decir este nombre Cozco no lo saben declarar, mas de decir que ansí
se nombraba antiguamente.

Y viviendo y residiendo en este pueblo Alcaviza, abrió la tierra una cueva siete leguas deste
pueblo, do llaman hoy Pacaritambo, que dice Casa de producimiento; y esta cueva tenia la salida
della cuanto un hombre podia caber saliendo ó entrando á gatas; de la cual cueva, luego que
se abrió, salieron cuatro hombres con sus mujeres, saliendo en esta manera. Salió primero el
que se llamó Ayar Cache y su mujer con él, que se llamó Mama Guaco; y tras éste salió otro
que se llamó Ayar Oche, y tras él su mujer, que se llamó Cura; y tras éste salió otro que se
llamó Ayar Auca, y su mujer, que se llamó Ragua Ocllo; y tras éstos salió otro que se llamó
Ayar Mango, a quien despues llamaron Mango Capac, que quiere decir el rey Mango; y tras éste
salió su mujer que llamaron Mama Ocllo; los cuales sacaron en sus manos, de dentro de la cueva,
unas alabardas de oro, y ellos salieron vestidos de unas vestiduras de lana fina tejida con
oro fino, y á los cuellos sacaron unas bolsas, ansí mismo de lana y oro, muy labradas, en las
cuales bolsas sacaron unas hondas de niervos. Y las mujeres salieron asimismo vestidas muy
ricamente, con unas mantas y fajas, que ellos llaman chumbis, muy labradas de oro, y con los
prendederos de oro muy fino, los cuales son unos alfileres largos de dos palmos que ellos llaman
topos; y ansí mismo sacaron estas mujeres el servicio con que habian de servir y guisar de
comer á sus maridos, como son ollas y cántaros pequeños, y platos y escudillas y vasos para
beber, todo de oro fino. Los cuales, como fuesen de allí hasta un cerro questá legua y media
del Cozco, Guanacaure, y descendieron de allí, á las espaldas deste cerro, á un valle pequeño
que en él se hace, donde como fuesen allí, sembraron unas tierras de papas, comida destos indios,
y subiendo un dia al cerro Guanacaure para de allí mirar y devisar donde fuese mejor asiento
y sitio para poblar; y siendo ya encima del cerro, Ayar Cache, que fué el primero que salió
de la cueva, sacó una honda y puso en ella una piedra y tiróla á un cerro alto, y del golpe
que dió, derribó el cerro y hizo en él una quebrada; y ansímismo tiró otras tres piedras, y
hizo de cada una una quebrada grande en los cerros altos; los cuales tiros eran y son, desde
donde los tiró hasta donde el golpe hicieron, segun que ellos lo fantasean, espacio de legua
y media y de una legua.

Y viendo estos tiros de honda los otros tres sus compañeros, paráronse á pensar en la fortaleza
deste Ayar Cache, y apartáronse de allí un poco aparte, y ordenaron de dar manera como aquel
Ayar Cache se echase de su compañía, porque les parescia que era hombre de grandes fuerzas
y valerosidad, y que los mandaria y subjetaria andando el tiempo, y acordaron de tornar desde
allí á las cuevas donde habian salido; y porquellos al salir habian dejado muchas riquezas
de oro y ropa y del más servicio dentro de la cueva, ordenaron, sobre cautela, que tenian necesidad
deste servicio, que volviese á lo sacar Ayar Cache; el cual dijo que le placia, y siendo ya
á la puerta de la cueva, Ayar Cache entró agatado, bien ansí como habia salido, que no podian
entrar ménos; y como le viesen los demás dentro, tomaron una gran losa, y cerráronle la salida
y puerta por do entró; y luego, con mucha piedra y mezcla, hicieron á ésta en toda [entrada?]
una gruesa pared, de manera que cuando volviese á salir, no pudiese y se quedase allá. Y esto
acabado, estuviéronse allí hasta que dende á cierto rato oyeron cómo daba golpes en la losa
de dentro Ayar Cache, y viendo los compañeros que no podia salir, tornáronse al asiento de
Guanacaure, donde estuvieron los tres juntos un año y las cuatro mujeres con ellos; y la mujer
de Ayar Cache, que ya era quedado en la cueva, diéronla á Ayar Mango, para que le sirviese.

Y el año cumplido que allí estuvieron, paresciéndoles que aquel sitio no era cual les convenia,
pasáronse de allí media legua más hácia el Cuzco, á otra quebrada, questuvieron otro año, y
desde encima de los cerros desta quebrada, la cual se llama Matagua, miraban el valle del Cuzco
y el pueblo que tenia poblado Alcaviza, y parescióles que era buen sitio aquel do estaba poblado
aquel pueblo de Alcaviza; y descendidos que fueron al sitio y ranchería que tenian, entraron
en su acuerdo, y parescióles quel uno dellos se quedase en el cerro de Guanacaure hecho ídolo,
é que los que quedaban, fuesen á poblar con los que vivian en aquel pueblo y que adorasen á
éste que ansí quedase hecho ídolo, y que hablase con el sol, su padre, que los guardase y aumentase
y diese hijos, y los inviase buenos temporales. Y luego se levantó en pié Ayar Oche y mostró
unas alas grandes y dijo quél habia de ser el que quedase allí en el cerro de Guanacaure por
ídolo, para hablar con el sol su padre. Y luego subieron el cerro arriba, y siendo ya en el
sitio do habia de quedar hecho ídolo, dió un vuelo hácia el cielo el Ayar Oche, tan alto, que
no lo devisaron; y tornóse allí, y díjole á Ayar Mango, que de allí se nombrase Mango Capac,
porque él venia de donde el sol estaba, y que ansí lo mandaba el sol que se nombrase; y que
se descendiese de allí y se fuese al pueblo que habian visto y que le seria fecha buena compañía
por los moradores del pueblo; y que poblase allí; y que su mujer Cura, que se la daba para
que le sirviese, y quél llevase consigo á su compañero Ayar Auca.

Y acabado de decir esto por el ídolo Ayar Oche, tornóse piedra ansí como estaba, con sus alas,
y luego se descendió Mango Capac y Ayar Auca á su ranchería; y descendidos que fueron, vinieron
donde el ídolo estaba muchos indios de un pueblo de allí cercano, y como vieron el ídolo hecho
piedra, que le habian visto cuando el vuelo dió en lo alto, tiráronle una piedra y desta piedra
le quebraron al ídolo una ala; de donde, como ya le hubiesen quebrado una ala, no pudo volar
ya más; y como le viesen hecho piedra, no le hicieron más enojo.

Y volviéndose estos indios que esto hicieron ansí á su pueblo, Mango Capac y su compañero Ayar
Auca salieron de sus rancherías, llevando consigo sus cuatro mujeres ya nombradas, y caminaron
para el pueblo de el Cozco, donde estaba Alcaviza. Y ántes que llegasen al pueblo, dos tiros
de arcabuz, estaba poblado un pueblo pequeño, en el cual pueblo habia coca y ají; y la mujer
de Ayar Oche, el que se perdió en la cueva, llamada Mama Guaco, dió á un indio de los deste
pueblo de coca un golpe con unos ayllos y matóle y abrióle de pronto y sacóle los bofes y el
corazon, y á vista de los demás del pueblo, hinchó los bofes soplándolos; y visto por los indios
del pueblo aquel caso, tuvieron gran temor, é con el miedo que habian tomado, luego en aquella
hora se fueron huyendo al valle que llaman el dia de hoy Gualla, de donde han procedido los
indios que el dia de hoy benefician la coca de Gualla. Y esto hecho, pasaron adelante Mango
Capac y su gente, y hablaron con Alcaviza, diciéndole que el sol los inviaba á que poblasen
con él alli en aquel pueblo del Cozco; y el Alcaviza, como le viese tan bien aderezado á él
y á su compañía, y las alabardas de oro que en las manos traian, y el demás servicio de oro,
entendió que era ansí y que eran hijos del sol, y díjoles que poblasen donde mejor les paresciese.
Y el Mango Capac agradescióselo, y paresciéndole bien el sitio y asiento do agora es en esta
ciudad del Cuzco la casa y convento de Santo Domingo, que ántes solia ser la Casa del Sol,
como adelante la historia lo dirá, hizo allí el Mango Capac y su compañero, y con el ayuda
de las cuatro mujeres, una casa, sin consentir que gente Alcaviza les ayudase, aunque los querian
ayudar; en la cual casa se metieron ellos dos y sus cuatro mujeres. Y esto hecho, dende á cierto
tiempo el Mango Capac y su compañero con sus cuatro mujeres, sembraron unas tierras de maiz,
la cual semilla de maiz dicen haber sacado ellos de la cueva, á la cual cueva nombró este Señor
Mango Capac, Pacarictambo, que dice, Casa de producimiento; porque, como ya habeis oido, dicen
que salieron de aquella cueva. Su sementera hecha, holgábanse y regocijábanse Mango Capac y
Alcaviza en buena amistad y en contentamiento.

Dende á dos años que allí vino Mango Capac, murió su compañero Ayar Auca, y quedó la mujer
en compañía de las demás de Mango Capac, sin que en ella hobiese habido hijo ninguno de Ayar
Auca, y ansí, quedó solo Mango Capac con su mujer y las otras tres de sus compañeros ya dichos,
y sin que tuviese que ver con ninguna dellas para en cuanto á tenellas por mujeres propias,
sino con la suya propia; en la cual, dende á poco tiempo hubo un hijo, al cual hizo llamar
Sinchi Roca. Y siendo ya Sinchi Roca mancebo de hasta quince ó diez y seis años, murió su padre
Mango Capac, sin dejar otro hijo sino fué este Sinchi Roca. É dende cinco años que murió Mango
Capac, murió Alcaviza. Y como fuese ya de edad de veinte años este Sinchi Roca, hijo de Mango
Capac, usó por mujer una señora llamada Mama Coca, hija de un cacique Señor de un pueblo questá
una legua del Cuzco, que llaman Zañu, en la cual señora hubo Sinchi Roca un hijo llamado Lloque
Yupanqui. Este Lloque Yupanqui nació con dientes, y luego que nació, anduvo, y nunca quiso
mamar; y luego habló cosas de admiracion, que á mi parescer debió de ser otro Merlin, segun
que las fábulas dicen. Y ansí como este nació, que tomó una piedra en las manos y tiróla á
otro muchacho descendiente de Alcaviza, que al presente por allí pasaba, el cual iba por agua
á una fuente con cierta vasija en las manos, de la cual pedrada Lloque Yupanqui, el recien
nacido, quebró una pierna al muchacho de Alcaviza ya dicho, del cual caso los agoreros dijeron,
que los que descendieren de este Lloque Yupanqui serian grandes Señores, y que señorearian
aquel pueblo; y que los descendientes de los de Alcaviza serian echados de aquel pueblo por
los descendientes de Lloque Yupanqui; lo cual así fué, como la historia lo dirá adelante, segun
que lo dijeron los que dieron razon dello. Y porque este Lloque Yupanqui no hizo cosas más
notables questa ya dicha, en el tiempo que vivió, le dejaremos.

Y despues de los dias de éste sucedió en su lugar un hijo suyo, que se llamó Capac Yupanqui,
del cual se dice no haber procurado[9] más ser que su padre Lloque Yupanqui le dejó. Y despues
de los dias de éste, sucedió en su lugar un hijo suyo que se dijo Mayta Capac, el cual dicen
no haber procurado más ser que sus pasados. Y despues de los dias de éste, sucedió en su lugar
un hijo suyo que se dijo Inca Roca Inca, del cual dicen haber habido en seis mujeres que tuvo,
treinta hijos y hijas. Y despues de los dias deste, sucedió en su lugar un hijo suyo y mayor
de los otros, que se llamó Yaguar Guacac Inca Yupanqui. Déste dicen que nació llorando sangre,
y por eso le llamaron Yaguar Guacac, que dicen, llorar sangre. Deste dicen que tuvo veinte
mujeres, en las cuales hubo cincuenta hijos y hijas; del cual dicen no haber procurado más
ser que le dejaron sus pasados.

Y despues de los dias deste, sucedió en su lugar un hijo suyo que llaman Viracocha Inca, porque
era muy amigable á los suyos y afable y los gobernaba en mucha quietud, dándoles siempre dádivas
y haciéndoles mercedes. Y como éste fuese ansí, amábanle los suyos con gran voluntad; y levantándose
un dia por la mañana, salió alegre á los suyos, y preguntándole los suyos que de qué se regocijaba,
dicen que les respondió que el Viracocha Pachayachachic le habia hablado aquella noche, diciendo
que Dios le habia hablado aquella noche (así); y luego se levantaron todos los suyos y le llamaron
Viracocha Inca, que quiere decir, Rey y Dios; y desde allí se nombró este nombre.

En el tiempo deste Viracocha Inca habia más de doscientos Señores caciques de pueblos y provincias,
cincuenta y sesenta leguas en la redondez desta ciudad del Cuzco, los cuales se intitulaban
y nombraban en sus tierras y pueblos Capac Inca, que quiere decir Señores é reyes; y lo mismo
hacia este Viracocha Inca, é intitulábase, como arriba diximos, Dios; de donde vieron los demás
Señores ya dichos, que se intitulaba de más sér que ninguno dellos. Y como un Señor destos,
de nacion Chanca, que se decia Uscovilca, el cual era señor de mucha suma de gente é tenia
seys capitanes muy valerosos, sus sujetos, que se llamaron Malma[10], y otro Rapa, y otro Yanavilca[11],
y otro Teclovilca, y otro Guamanguaraca, y otro Tomayguaraca; y este Uscovilca, como tuviese
noticia que en el Cuzco residia Viracocha Inca y que se intitulase de mayor señor que él, siendo
él más poderoso de gente é intitulándose él Señor de toda la tierra, pareciéndole bien ver
qué poder era el de Viracocha Inca, y para ver esto, estando este Uscovilca en el pueblo de
Paucaray[12], que es tres leguas de Párcos, entró en consulta con los suyos qué órden debiesen
tener para este hecho; y viendo que su poder era grande, acordaron en su acuerdo que debian
ir sus capitanes á descubrir por las partes de Condesuyo é provincias, é ansímismo por la parte
de Andesuyo á lo mismo, y que él ansímismo, con dos capitanes de los suyos y con la gente que
le quedase, fuese por medio destas dos provincias derechamente á la ciudad del Cuzco, y que
desta manera seria Señor de toda la tierra, y que él de su mano sujetaria á Viracocha Inca.
Y ansí, salió de su acuerdo; y desque hobo salido, mandó que para un dia señalado se juntase
toda su gente en aquel lugar é llano de Paucaray[13], donde él era natural; y ansí se juntaron
todos los suyos el dia que les fué mandado. Y siendo ansí juntos, mandó á sus capitanes que
hiciesen tres partes toda aquella gente; y siendo ya apartados y hechas las tres partes, mandólos
proveer de armas á todos, que fueron lanzas, alabardas y hachas, y porras, y hondas y ayllos
y rodelas; de las cuales, siendo ya proveidos deste menester, mandóles proveer de muchos mantenimientos
para su camino, como es carne seca, y maíz, y pescado seco y de las demas comidas, haciéndoles
la gracia y merced de todo el despojo que en la guerra hobiesen de ganado, ropa y oro y plata
é mujeres y otras piezas é anaconas que ansí en la guerra hobiesen. Y dando una parte destas
gentes á los capitanes de los suyos, que se llamaron Malma y Irapa[14], á los cuales mandó
que luego se partiesen, y que fuesen conquistando por la provincia de Condesuyo hasta donde
gente no hallasen que conquistar pudiesen. Y ansí se fueron estos dos capitanes ya dichos,
llevando la gente ya dicha; y al tiempo que se despidieron del Señor, diéronle grandes gracias
y loores, ansí los capitanes como la demás gente, por la merced que les fué hecha del despojo.
Y ansí fueron conquistando estos dos capitanes Malma y Irapa por la provincia de Condesuyo,
llevando gran poder de gente; y fué tanta la ventura destos dos capitanes, que ganaron é sujetaron
yendo desdel pueblo de Paucaray por la provincia de Condesuyo, hasta llegar á las dichas cincuenta
leguas más allá de los Charcas.

Dejaremos estos capitanes y hablaremos de los otros dos que invió ansímismo Uscovilca por la
parte de Andesuyo, los cuales se llamaron Yana Vilca y Toquello Vilca[15]; á los cuales como
les diese su Señor Uscovilca la otra parte de gente, partieron de allí de Paucaray; á los cuales,
al partir, les fue mandado por Uscovilca que no llegasen al Cuzco con diez leguas, sino que
pasasen apartados dél, porquel Uscovilca queria esta empresa del Cuzco para sí. Y ansí, se
apartaron estos dos capitanes, metiéndose por la provincia de Condesuyo, ganando y conquistando
provincias hasta llegar á los Chiriguanes, donde los dejaremos y hablaremos de Uscovilca.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05425</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>271017</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17010</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

And back to our story, say that after you have done in this province Cacha this miracle, which
passed on, always understanding in his work, as you heard, and as get to a place that now say
the Urcos Tambo, which is six miles from the city of Cuzco, went up to a high hill and sat on top
of him, from where they say they ordered that occur and to depart from that height the natives
who live there to this day. And because this Viracocha had been sitting there, I did in that
place a very rich and sumptuous guaca, which guaca, because he sat in that place that Viracocha,
which put the built a seat of pure gold, and the package in place Deste Viracocha began, he
sat in this seat, which lump of pure gold in the [6] that the Christians did Cuzco when he won [won
or weighed] sixteen or eighteen thousand pesos. And from there the Viracocha parted and came by his
people, as you heard, until he came to Cuzco, where that was reached, they say he made a Lord
to whom his name Alcaviza, and named "Likewise to this site, do the Lord did, Cuzco, and after
leaving Quél pass order as occur dried apricots, broke out doing his work. And reach the province of
Puerto Old, gathered there with his family before him winters in the way and that, where as
there came together, went through the sea along with them, do tell who was he and his ANSI
water-like walking on land. Many other things here more eScript hobiera Deste Viracocha, second
that these Indians have informed me of him, but, to avoid prolixity and large idolatry and bestiality,
not put them, where you leave and talk about the place of the dried apricots in the city of
Cuzco, "Likewise they [use] and follow the bestiality é gentile idolatry and barbaric and
have heard [7].

In the place and say site today and called the great city of Cuzco,
in the province of Peru, in ancient times, rather than the Lords hobiese
apricots, Incas, Capaccuna, they Kings say, there was a small town
thirty small thatched houses and very shabby, and they had thirty
Indians, and Mr. and chief of this village was called Alcaviza; and
dentorno other small this town was a swamp reed [and] herb grass,
which marsh caused springs of water and place the saw do agora is
the strength went out, and this marsh was and is the place to do agora
is the plaza and the homes of the Marquis Don Francisco Pizarro, who,
after the city won, and the same was at the site of the houses Commander
of Hernando Pizarro, and was also swamp the place and do is place
in this city Part of stream della passes through the market or Tianguez,
marina hiring Indian natives thereof.

To which the inhabitants of the village called from their age Cuzco, and what is meant by this
name declare Cozco do not know, but to say that ANSI was formerly named.

And living and residing in this town Alcaviza, the earth opened seven leagues from this cave
people do call today Pacaritambo, says House to produce, and exit this cave had della fit as
a man could crawl out or entering, the cave where, after opened, came four men with their
wives, leaving in this way. Came first Ayar was called Cache and his wife with him, called Mama
Guaco, and after this came another Ayar Oche was called, and after him his wife, who was called
Cura, and after this came another that Ayar called Auca, and his wife, called Ragua Ocllo, and
after them came another one called Ayar Mango, who then called Mango Capac, which means the King
Mango, and after this left his wife called Mama Ocllo, who brought in their hands, inside the
cave, a gold halberds, and they came dressed in a robe of fine wool woven gold, and he took
a bag necks, craves the same wool and gold, very cultivated, in which
took some deep pockets of niervos.

And the women went very well dressed richly, with blankets and sashes, which they call chumbis
very wrought gold, and the very thin gold fillets, which are about two feet long pins they call
topos, and so they took it to service these women who were to serve and cook for food to their
husbands, such as pots and small pots, plates and bowls and cups drink, all of fine gold. Which,
as there were up hill and half a league quest of Cuzco, Guanacaure, and descended from there
back to the Deste hill to a small valley that it is done, where as they were there, they planted
a land of potatoes, food of these Indians, and up the hill one day there Guanacaure to watch
and where was best seat deviser and place to settle, and now the top of the hill, Ayar Cache,
who first came out of the cave, took a sling and a stone put into it and Tirol to a high hill,
and hit which gave, brought down the hill and made it a creek, and threw ansímismo three other
stones, and each made a big ravine in the mountains high; which shots were and are, where the
blow threw far made, according as they fantasize, space league and a half a league.

And seeing these shots of deep three other colleagues, they stood in the strength to think Deste
Ayar Cache, and they parted on a little aside, and ordered him to give way Ayar Cache perceiving
his company, because they parescia was a man of great strength and bravery, and that would
send and subjetaria in time, and agreed to turn from thence to the caves where they had left,
and leaving porquellos had left great riches gold and clothing and more service in the cave,
ordered on caution, they had need Deste service, get back to what Ayar Cache, which said he was happy,
and now the at the door of the cave, Ayar Cache entered agate, or ANSI, as he had left, they
could not get less, and as others might see him inside, took a large slab and output cerráronle
and went door-to-do, and then, with a lot of stone and mortar, made to it at all [in?] a thick
wall, so that when you go out again, and could not stay there. And this finished, they tarried
there until a certain time from then to hear how banged on the slab Ayar Cache inside, he saw
the fellow who could not leave, turned about to seat Guanacaure, where they were all three together
for a year and four women with them, and women Ayar Cache, already
been in the cave, gave him to Ayar Mango, to serve him.

And next year there were fulfilled, Paresce that was not the place which suited them, pasáronse
half a league from there to Cuzco, to another stream, questuvieron another year, and from the
top of the remote portion of this gorge, which is called Matagua, watching the valley of Cuzco
and the people who had Alcaviza town, and it was good site parescióles do that was populated Alcaviza
that town, and were relegated to the site and ranch they had, came in their agreement, and
one of them quel parescióles would stay on the hill of Guanacaure made idol é that those who
remained, were to settle with those who lived in that town and pay homage to he craves to stand
there like an idol, and to speak with the sun, his father, who guard them and the increase and
give children and good winter storms. And then stood up and showed Ayar Oche large wings Quél
said was to be for him to be there on the hill by Guanacaure idol, to talk to the sun their
father. And then rose up the hill, and being already in the site do was to be made idol, took
a flight to Ayar Oche sky, so high that deviser not, and it became there, and said to Ayar Mango,
that there be appointed Mango Capac because he came from where the
sun was gone, and craves the sun sent him the appointment, and that
is descended from there and were the people who had seen and that
date would be good company by the villagers, and to populate it there,
and cure his wife, who gave it to serve him, and chelate taking his
companion Ayar Auca.

And just said that the idol Ayar Oche, it became a stone just as he was, with its wings, and then
fell Auca Ayar Mango Capac and his ranch, and were descended, came where the idol was many Indians
from a village near there, and they saw the idol made stone, which had seen him when the flight
got on top, and in this tiráronle stone stone you broke a wing idol, whence, as I had broken a
wing, could not fly and more, and as he turned to stone they saw, they did not do more anger.

Turning
these Indians that this longing that his people did, Mango Capac and his partner Ayar Auca left their
villages, carrying four women named, and walked for the people of the Cuzco, where he was Alcaviza.
And before they reached the village, two shots musket, was populated a small town, where people
had coca and chili, and the woman Ayar Oche, who was lost in the cave, called Mama Guaco, gave
to an Indian of those on this coca people hit and killed him with a ayllos and opened it suddenly
and took him out of his lungs and heart, and to view the rest of the people, puffed out his
lungs by blowing, and seen by the Indians that case the people had great fear, and with the
fear that had taken, then this hour were fleeing the valley they call today Gualla, whence have
proceeded Indians that benefit today's coca Gualla. And that fact, passed out Mango Capac
and his people, and spoke with Alcaviza, saying that the sun that
populated the winters with him there in that town of Cuzco, and the
Alcaviza, as well as seeing him dressed to him and his company, and
gold halberds in their hands they carried, and other service gold
knew that he craves and they were sons of the sun, and said that village
where they see Paresce.

And the Mango Capac agradescióselo and Paresce well site and do agora seat is in this Cuzco house
and convent of Santo Domingo, who used to be the Casa del Sol and tell the story later, there was
the Mango Capac and his partner, and with the help of the four women, a house without allowing
people Alcaviza assist them, although they wanted help, in whose house they got two of them and
his four wives. And this fact, from then to some Mango Capac time and his companion with his
four wives, a land of corn planted, seed corn which they say have
brought them to the cave, to which the Lord appointed cave Mango Capac,
Pacarictambo, he says, producing House, because, as you heard, say
who left the cave.

Its sowing done, and regocijábanse holgábanse Mango Capac Alcaviza in friendship and contentment.

Dende
to two years there came Mango Capac, Ayar Auca his partner died and the woman was in the company
of others of Mango Capac, without it there hobiese Ayar any child Auca, and so they, Mango Capac
left alone with his wife and three of his companions and said, and without having to do with
any Dell tenella as women to own but his own, in which, from then to little time there was
a son, whom he called Sinchiroca. And when it Sinchiroca youth of fifteen or sixteen years,
his father died Mango Capac, while another child but this was Sinchiroca. Dende É Mango died five
years Capac, died Alcaviza. And as was already twenty years old this Sinchi Roca, son of Mango
Capac, used by women a lady called Mama Coca, daughter of a lord of a village chief quest a
league from Cuzco, called ZANU, which was Mrs. Sinchiroca a son named Lloque Yupanqui. This
Lloque Yupanqui was born with teeth, and then he was born, walked, and never wanted suck, and
then spoke with admiration things, which I Paresce Merlin must have been another, according
to that the fables say. And thus was born like this, he took a stone in the hands and Tirol
Alcaviza descendant of another boy who was passing by this, which was water to a source with some
pot in his hands, which Lloque stone Yupanqui, the newly born, the boy broke his leg in Alcaviza
already said, which if the doomsayers said, than fall, this would be great lords Lloque Yupanqui,
and señorearian that town, and that the descendants of those driven from Alcaviza that people
would by Lloque descendants Yupanqui which was well, as history will say later, according to said
that they gave reason dello. And because this Lloque Yupanqui did things and this remarkable orchestra,
at the time he lived, we will leave.

And the days after it happened instead of his child, who was called Capac Yupanqui which is said
not to have sought [9] rather be Lloque Yupanqui his father left him. And then of days of it,
came in place of his child was said Mayta Capac, which is said sought
to be failing more than their past.

And after days of it, came into place his child was said Inca Roca Inca, which they say have
been in six women who had, thirty sons and daughters. And after the days dest, came into place
and increased his child the other, called Yaguar Guacac Inca Yupanqui. Deste say he was born crying
blood, and so I called Yaguar Guacac, they say, mourn blood. Deste say they had twenty women,
which had fifty sons and daughters, which say they have not tried more be handed down by his
past.

And after the days dest, came in place of his child called Viracocha Inca, because was very friendly
and affable to his men and ruled very quiet, always giving gifts and making grants. And as this
was craving, amábanle their own with a strong will, and arose a day in the morning, left his men
cheerful, and asking what his own who rejoiced, say they responded that he had spoken Pachayachachic
Viracocha that night, saying that God had spoken that night (well) and then raised all his
family and called him Inca Viracocha, which means King and God, and from there was appointed
this name.

At the time of this Viracocha Inca lords had over two hundred chiefs of villages and provinces,
fifty or sixty leagues in the roundness of this city of Cuzco, which was entitled and appointed
in their land and villages Inca Capac, which means lords and kings, and so towards this Viracocha
Inca, é intitulábase, as above diximos, God where others saw And those gentlemen who was entitled
to be that none of them more. And as a lady of this, of Chanca nation, which was said Uscovilca,
who was lord of a large sum of people and had Seys very brave captain,
his subjects, who were called Malma [10] and one Rapa, and another
Yanavilca [11] Teclovilca and another and another Guamanguaraca, and
another Tomayguaraca, and this Uscovilca, as had news resided in Cuzco
Inca Viracocha and is entitled to greater lord than he, being The
most powerful people and entitled him Lord of all the earth, as it
seemed good to see what power was that of Viracocha Inca, and to see
that, while this Uscovilca in the town of Paucaray [12], which is
three leagues of PARC, entered into consultation with his people what
order debiesen have for this fact, and seeing that his power was great,
agreed in their agreement that debian go to their captains to find
out the parts of provinces Condesuyo é, é ansímismo by the of Andesuyo
to the same, and that he ansímismo, with two masters of their own
and with people you stay, come by these two art provinces straight
to the city of Cuzco, and in this way would be Lord of all the earth,
and that he would subject his hand Viracocha Inca.

And thus, out of his agreement, and after he left hobo, he commanded for a day signal is coupled
all the people in that place and plain Paucaray [13], where he was natural and so they got together
all his family the day that it was commanded. And being ANSI time, he commanded his captains
hiciesen three parts all those people, and now the sections and made of three parts, mandolin
supplying arms to all who were spears, halberds and axes, and clubs and slings and ayllos and
shields, of which, being already provided Deste necessary, he commanded them to provide many
maintenance on its path, such as dried meat, and corn, and dried fish and other foods, making
grace and mercy of all the plunder in war hobiesen livestock, clothing and gold and silver
women and other parts é é yanaconas craves hobiesen the war. And giving a share of this people
to the captains of their own, who called Irapa Malma and [14], to
whom he sent they then departed, and were conquered by the province
as far Condesuyo they found that people could win.

And thus it was these two captains and said, bringing people and said, and fired while the Lord
gave him great thanks and praises, ANSI masters like other people, for the favor to them was made
of plunder. And thus these two captains were conquering Irapa Malma and the province of Condesuyo, bringing
great power of people, and so was the chance of these two art masters, who won e Subject Paucaray DeSdel
people going through the province of Condesuyo, until they reached the said fifty leagues beyond
the Charcas.

We leave these captains and discuss the other two that he sent the Uscovilca ansímismo Andesuyo part,
which is called Yana and Toquello Vilca Vilca [15] whom when give them their Lord Uscovilca
the other party of people, left Paucaray there, to whom, departing, they were commanded by Uscovilca
not arrived to Cuzco with ten leagues, but pasasen sections of, Becausethe Uscovilca wanted this
company in Cuzco for himself. And thus, the Apart from these two masters, getting by the province
of Condesuyo, winning and conquering provinces to arrive at the Chiriguanos, where we shall
leave and discuss Uscovilca.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>