<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10900</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>578927</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19773</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Parece, empero, esto menos tolerable, á causa de no reconocer ni aun las leyes naturales, que
cualquier hombre, por bárbaro y salvaje que sea, con sólo ser hombre, venera y aprecia.

Los hijos, por la mayor parte, no tienen ningún respeto á sus padres; antes tienen sobre ellos
dominio, haciéndose obedecer de ellos con grande descaro; y si les da gusto, osan poner en
los padres las manos.

En sus enfermedades no se mueven á compasión, antes los abandonan con increíble ingratitud
y los dejan en manos de la hambre y enfermedad; cosa que ni aun con las bestias usan; y fuera
muchas veces entre ellos mejor ser perro que hombre, porque de ellos se compadecen y quitan
la comida de la boca para sustentar una tropa de galgos.

Encontróse acaso el P. Machoni en una ocasión con algunos de estos bárbaros que llevaban á
enterrar á la madre de uno de ellos difunta, que poco antes se había convertido á nuestra santa
fe, y con ella querían enterrar á un hijito suyo de pocos meses, porque ninguna india, aun
sus parientas, quería tomar el trabajo de criarle: quitósele luego de las manos el Padre y
por más que con la paga por delante se lo pidió y suplicó, ninguna se movió á compasión; por
lo cual se vió obligado mientras vivió el niño á mantenerle con leche de cabra ú oveja, no
sin increíble dolor, viendo entre tanto á muchas madres tener pendientes de sus pechos gran
número de perritos para que no se muriesen de hambre.

Sus casamientos los celebran de mucha edad (si es que entre ellos merecen el nombre de casamientos,
pues cansada la mujer del marido, y éste de ella, tienen franqueza y libertad de tomar otra
ú otro á su antojo) no casándose sino cuando ya están cansados de torpezas, no experimentando
ellos en sí ni el temor ni la vergüenza que la naturaleza mezcló sabiamente en los placeres
vedados para contener en la raya de lo debido el genio de la concupiscencia desenfrenada.

No es fácil de explicar cuanto trabajase el buen P. Misionero con otro compañero Jesuita, en
instruir en los principios de la ley divina á gente que parecía no tener ni aun el primer instinto
de la naturaleza, ni de qué medios de caridad y de celo se valieron para hacerlos, de bestias,
racionales, y de racionales, cristianos.

Eran los primeros con el azadón en la mano á romper la tierra, á manejar los arados y á hacer
todo lo demás que es necesario en la labor de los campos para adiestrarlos á hacer lo mismo.

Después visitaban los enfermos y hacían con ellos todos los oficios de caridad que haría una
amorosa madre, quitándose de la boca la comida y el sustento que les tenía señalado la piedad
de los españoles por remediar sus necesidades.

Sufrían con increíble paciencia sus contínuas impertinencias y necedades, con la esperanza
del bien que podían sacar de ellos. Pero esto era lo menos respecto de lo que trabajaban en
provecho de sus almas; porque la deshonestidad, la venganza, la embriaguez la barbaridad y
otros mil vicios heredados con la sangre, crecidos con los años, y con la costumbre convertidos
en naturaleza, era poco menos que imposible desarraigarlos de sus corazones; mas pudo tanto
la incontrastable virtud del Altísimo y la fineza de un celo apostólico, que poco á poco se
empezó á ablandar la dureza de corazones tan obstinados y á domesticarse la barbaridad de ánimos
tan salvajes.

El primer fruto que se sazonó con los sudores y fatigas de estos fervorosísimos operarios,
fueron muchas almas de niños que apenas lavadas en las aguas saludables del santo bautismo,
volaron con la cándida estola de la inocencia á la eterna bienaventuranza, á tomar posesión
de aquella gloria, que en adelante gozarían los fieles de su nación; después lograron las almas
de muchos adultos que asaltados de una peste que se encendió entre ellos, cambiaron gustosos
la vida con la esperanza del eterno descanso en el cielo, por medio del santo bautismo.

Uno, entre los demás, joven de pocos años, que no menos en las llagas de su cuerpo, que en
la paciencia del ánimo, parecía otro Job, se alistó en el número de los hijos de Dios con suma
alegría y júbilo de su espíritu, y haciendo fervorosísimos actos de fe, esperanza y caridad,
pasó de esta peregrinación á la patria celestial.

Llevaba muy mal el común enemigo los progresos de la fe en nación tan bárbara é inculta; por
eso aplicó luego todo su esfuerzo para atajarlos y sofocar la semilla del Evangelio, antes
que se arraigase en los corazones de los bárbaros.

El primer medio de que se valió fué procurar la muerte de los Misioneros que le hacían tan
cruda guerra, incitando á los infieles á que se la diesen.

Intentáronlo ellos muchas veces; y una, entre otras, estuvieron ya conjurados á matar al P.
Machoni.

Habían estado algo lejos del pueblo haciendo un baile con grande bulla y algazara, y poniendo
en medio de la rueda un calabazo, que por arte del demonio danzaba también con ellos, se convinieron
todos en darle aquella noche la muerte, para verse libres de una vez de su celo y reprensiones.

Oyóles acaso el Padre, y saliendo de su Rancho á saber la causa de aquella novedad intempestiva,
encontróse con una india que venía del baile, bien que no tan fuera de sí como ellos, que estaban
totalmente embriagados; preguntóla el Padre por qué sus parientes metían tanto ruido y daban
tantas voces.

Ella, que sabía muy bien lo que trataban, procuró encubrirlo con una falsa risa, respondiendo
no sabía la causa.

Temióse el Misionero no fuese alguna borrachera; y para certificarse y atajarla, instó á la
india descubriese la verdad.

Ella, recelando por esta instancia que ya el P. lo supiese, le descubrió toda la conjuración
que contra su vida tenían tramada.

Recogióse en su Rancho ofreciendo á Dios su vida en sacrificio por el bien de aquellas almas,
y estuvo toda aquella noche esperando le viniesen á matar; mas Nuestro Señor le libró para
otras cosas de su servicio, porque avisados los infieles por la dicha india de que el Padre
Misionero sabía ya sus intentos, no se atrevieron á darle la muerte, recelando también no viniesen
luego los españoles á vengarla.

Viendo el demonio que se le había desvanecido esta traza, se valió de otra, y fué introducir
en el pueblo el pernicioso error de que lo mismo era echarles á los niños el agua del bautismo
en la cabeza que despedirse del cuerpo sus almas; y se imprimió tan altamente este engaño en
sus fantasías, que convirtiéndose el amor á los Padres en odio y aversión, los miraban con
mal corazón y huían de ellos como enemigos jurados de su bien.

Y daba á eso calor el creerse ellos neciamente eternos; y aunque veían todos los días quedárseles
muertos en sus brazos sus amigos y parientes, con todo eso, á la evidencia de los ojos prevalecía
el error del entendimiento.

Procuraban los nuestros con todas las fuerzas de su celo desvanecer aquel engaño y errada persuasión,
fomentada del demonio para daño de aquella reciente cristiandad, y Dios Nuestro Señor, que
suele mirar á los nuevos fieles con ojos de mayor piedad, quiso remediar bien presto este daño
y consolar y animar juntamente la virtud de sus siervos.

Pasó el caso de esta manera:

Iba un día el P. Machoni llevando de Rancho en Rancho una holla de comida para darla á los
enfermos; encontróse con una india que traía al pecho un niño que estaba ya para espirar; no
pudo ella huir y esconder tan presto su criatura de suerte que el Padre no la viese.

Procuró éste con dulcísimas palabras y mucha afabilidad mitigar el odio de la madre y ganarla
el ánimo, á fin de poder bautizar al niño; mas todo fué en vano, porque el demonio hablando
por boca de una mujer en todo suya, no menos por la infidelidad que por la lascivia, y vomitando
contra el Misionero y contra aquel Santo Sacramento tantas injurias y blasfemias cuantas diría
un dementado en lo más ardiente de sus furias, exhortaba á la madre no permitiese lavar á su
hijo en las santas aguas del bautismo; porque le sucedería lo que á otra madre mal aconsejada,
que ofreciendo su hijo para ser bautizado, lo mismo fué caer sobre el niño el agua santa, que
salir de esta vida.

Era la india de buen natural y no se dejaba fácilmente trabucar el juicio con las necedades
locas de los suyos, y mucho menos de la falsa aprensión de que el santo bautismo era tósigo
para quitar la vida, conociendo á tantos españoles viejos, con canas, que habían sido bautizados;
por eso de buena gana ofreció el niño al Padre; el cual, lleno de una generosa y humilde confianza
en Dios, rogó á Su Majestad y le suplicó quitase aquel embarazo á la santa fé, pues no le costaría
más que una insinuación de su voluntad; luego se volvió á San Francisco Xavier, pidiéndole
que mirase con ojos de misericordia á aquella ciega gentilidad; y pues tanto procuraba la honra
de Dios alcanzase de Su Majestad que aquel santo Sacramento no sólo sirviese para librar el
alma de aquel inocente de la esclavitud del demonio, sino también para librarle de la enfermedad
corporal; y ofreció en agradecimiento de aquel beneficio, que esperaba recibir, le llamaría
Francisco Xavier.

Oyó el cielo los fervorosos ruegos de su siervo, pues luego que fué el niño bautizado, quedó
sano de su enfermedad.

Lo mismo sucedió á una muchacha, ya casadera, á quien por estar toda helada y yerta, la lloraban
sus parientes por muerta; mas luego que fué bautizada, por las grandes instancias con que lo
había pedido, como si volviese de un profundo sueño, volvió en sí y á la vida. Con lo cual,
poco á poco cesó en el pueblo aquel falso temor, y las madres á porfía daban sus hijos para
que fuesen lavados en las santas y saludables aguas del bautismo.

Bramaba de rabia el demonio viendo desvanecidos sus enredos; por eso puso todo su esfuerzo
en empañar el terso esplendor de los procederes de uno de los Misioneros, infamándole con mil
calumnias por medio de unos apóstatas que estaban muy sentidos de que les impedía poder saciar
el apetito de la carne, con todos los más torpes y sucios placeres del sentido; mas, á pesar
suyo, salió triunfante la inocencia de costumbres y fervor de vida apostólica de aquel buen
Padre y fué obligado el demonio por entonces á dejar franco el paso al Santo Evangelio en las
provincias amplísimas del Chaco, donde no sólo procuran los Jesuitas la conversión de los infieles,
sino la reforma de los españoles é indios, acudiendo á confesar y á predicar los fuertes de
españoles que por allí hay como San Joseph y Valbuena; y acompañando á los soldados cuando
van de las ciudades á sujetar á los bárbaros que continuamente invaden aquella provincia, los
sirven de capellanes, exponiéndose á los mayores riesgos y peligros de perder la vida, sin
tener cuenta con las suyas; y al mismo tiempo procuran reducir á los que apresan los españoles
y bautizar á los párvulos.

En estas empresas había trabajado gloriosamente nueve años el P. Machoni, cuando en el nuevo
gobierno de 1719 vino señalado por secretario del P. Provincial Joseph de Aguirre, por cuya
causa fué preciso encargar el cuidado de aquella Reducción al P. Joaquín de Yegros, con otros
dos compañeros Jesuitas.

El nuevo Provincial y Secretario procuraron fomentar con todo esfuerzo la conversión de nuevos
infieles, á que cooperó como siempre el señor gobernador de la provincia D. Esteban de Urizar.

El año, pues, de 1719, en una entrada que á los infieles hicieron los vecinos de la ciudad
de San Miguel de Tucumán, descubrieron un nuevo río que se juzgó entonces ser el Pilcomayo;
á la ribera de este río supieron vivía mucha gente blanca, que tuvieron por españoles.

Con esta noticia determinó el señor gobernador que el año siguiente fuesen á descubrir totalmente
este río los tercios de la provincia de Tucumán, pidiendo para capellán á uno de los Padres
que estaban en la Reducción de San Esteban.

Concediólo luego el P. Provincial, y esperanzado de que de este descubrimiento se seguiría
á Dios mucha gloria, determinó que por la parte del río Paraguay entrasen por el Pilcomayo,
que desemboca en aquel río, algunos Misioneros de los Guaranís, con orden preciso de que sin
detenerse á reducir nación ninguna y sólo ganando la voluntad de los naturales, penetrasen
hasta encontrar con los soldados españoles que entraban por la provincia de Tucumán, ó llegasen
al paraje de los Chiriguanás.

Todo esto era prevención para dos fines: el primero, que descubierta la tierra y el río, se
pudiese entrar por el Tucumán, Paraguay y Frontera de Santa Fé, dándose la mano toda la gente
de estas provincias, para conquistar todo el Chaco, en que se lograría la conversión de muchas
almas.

El segundo, abrir por aquí camino más breve para las Misiones de los Chiquitos, cosa que siempre
sumamente se ha deseado, por evitar la suma distancia que hay por el camino de Tarija, porque
se presumía que los Zamucos se acercaban mucho al Chaco y al Pilcomayo, y por allí también
entró en esta ocasión un Jesuita para venirse á encontrar con los demás.

Señaló, pues, el P. Provincial para entrar por lo boca del río Pilcomayo á los PP. Gabriel
Patiño y Lucas Rodríguez, ambos nacidos en la ciudad de la Asunción, y á la sazón Misioneros
de los Guaranís; y del colegio del Paraguay despachó al hermano Bartolomé de Niebla, andaluz,
y á un donado portugués llamado Faustino Correa, con algunos indios Guaranís, para que si fuese
necesario defendiesen á los Padres de las invasiones de los infieles.

Por los Zamucos entraron con algunos indios Chiquitos los PP. Felipe Suárez y Agustín Castañares.

Los de la provincia de Tucumán no pudieron encontrar con Pilcomayo y hallaron por fin que el
descubierto por los Tucumaneses el año de 1719 no podía ser aquel río por ser éste pequeño
y el Pilcomayo muy grande.

Los Chiquitos, habiendo caminado por los Zamucos, hacia donde se juzga caer este río, nunca
pudieron dar con él.

Los que entraron por la boca del Pilcomayo iban en un barco y algunos botes: caminaron por
dicho río, siempre á diversos rumbos, por las repetidas vueltas con que corre: al principio
hallaron algunos rastros de indios, pero no los vieron.

Caminaron así cosa de ochenta leguas, parte por el río, parte por lagunas, porque hay muchas
á la orilla de este río, las cuales, cuando baja el río, quedan divididas de él y hechas lagunas;
mas cuando crece, queda toda la campaña hecha un mar de agua, porque se incorporan con él.

A estas ochenta leguas reconocieron que la madre del río no era tan honda que pudiese navegar
por él el barco sin peligro manifiesto de encallar; por lo cual determinó el P. Patiño pasar
en los botes con el hermano Niebla tres españoles y treinta y cuatro indios á registrar lo
restante hasta conseguir el fin de su empresa, dejando en el ínterin en el barco al Padre Lucas
Rodríguez, al donado y á la demás gente para que aguardasen.

Fueron, pues, navegando los dos botes y caminaron otras trescientas leguas, en que en diversas
partes vieron indios de varias naciones, que ya confinaban con los Chiriguanás.

Llegaron por fin á una nación no conocida, cuyos indios parecían de buenos naturales, y eran
de hermosos rostros y de buena estatura; las indias tan blancas, que parecían españolas; tenían
crías de yeguas y muchas ovejas, de cuya lana hacen muy buenos tejidos; los caballos eran sin
número. La tierra fertilísima, en que tienen labranzas de los frutos del país.

Saltaron en tierra y dieron á los naturales muchos donecillos que ellos aprecian y por esto
les mostraron mucho afecto, en que concibieron esperanzas de reducirlos después fácilmente.

Mas algunos Tobas y Mocovíes que había entre ellos malograron estas esperanzas, porque hablando
á aquellos indios, les incitaron contra los nuestros, maquinando una alevosa traición contra
sus vidas.

Estaban allí de paz unos y otros, tratándose con muchas caricias todo el tiempo que fué preciso
para descansar, cuando habiendo ido tres de nuestros indios á cortar leña, les acometieron
los alevosos Tobas y Mocovíes con los indios de aquella nación; mataron á los dos á flechazos
y al otro hirieron malamente, de suerte que murió de allí á algunos días.

Los demás se retiraron á los botes que mandó el Padre cubrir de algunos cueros de vaca para
resistir.

Vinieron siguiendo á los nuestros más de 600 infieles, hasta los bateles disparándoles una
tempestad tan espesa de saetas, que parecía una manga de langostas, pero ninguna les hizo daño,
porque hallaban resistencia en los cueros, que despedían las flechas; y aun siendo preciso
que el P. Patiño estuviese por dos veces en la proa descubierto á los tiros, aunque por todas
partes le caían las flechas, ninguna le tocó. Visto esto procuraron retirarse de las furias
de aquellos bárbaros, que con su traición deshicieron por ahora y frustraron las esperanzas
de poder penetrar el Chaco, donde se esperaba, como dije, reducir muchas naciones.

Volviéronse, pues, sin otro fruto, desandando con mucho trabajo el camino de cuatrocientas
leguas que hasta allí habían navegado.

Mas volviendo á la Reducción de San Esteban, este mismo año de 1721, se contaban en ella muchas
familias.

Encendióse por este tiempo una pestecilla de viruelas, de que murieron luego dos.

Los demás cobraron tanto miedo á la muerte, que les amenazaban las viruelas, que el mismo día
que aquellos dos murieron, dejaron descuidar á los nuestros y todos se huyeron menos dieciocho
adultos y veinte muchachos.

Luego que lo advirtieron los PP. Joaquín de Yegros y Lorenzo Fanlo montaron á caballo en su
seguimiento, y fueron á alcanzarlos por unos cerros hacia Salta; mas siendo mucha la espesura
de los bosques, y fragosidad de las sierras, se desmontaron, y á pie los siguieron, con increíble
fatiga, porque no huían por vía recta, sino oblícua siempre, porque decían que así no les podría
seguir la peste, cansada de los matorrales y revueltas. Tanta es su barbaridad.

Quedaron los Padres sin fuerzas antes de poderles dar alcance; y volviéndose á su pueblo á
cuidar de los que habían quedado enfermos, despacharon tras los fugitivos á dos indios que
llevaban consigo para detenerlos, porque de los dieciocho adultos se les murieron los catorce,
á quienes asistieron con grande caridad, sin recelo del contagio, y todos los demás enfermaron.

Los dos indios encontraron de allí á algunas leguas á los huídos, y por más que hicieron, sólo
les pudieron reducir á que bajasen donde estaban los Padres.

Procuraron éstos que volviesen á la Reducción; mas sólo consiguieron por entonces esperanzas
de que se volverían acabada la peste. Por tanto, dejándolos allí se volvieron los Padres al
pueblo á cuidar de los que habían quedado, enfermos los más, de los cuales murieron presto
catorce adultos, á quienes asistieron con grande celo y caridad, hasta darles sepultura por
sus propias manos.

Los fugitivos volvieron después de algún tiempo á su pueblo, por las diligencias de los nuestros,
que siempre tienen que trabajar aquí gloriosamente, por la innata barbarie de todas estas naciones,
como se conocerá por lo referido.

Al presente se halla este pueblo en sumo peligro de su destrucción, porque los Mocovíes y Tovas,
que hasta ahora han estado enfrenados por el valor del gobernador de la provincia de Tucumán,
principal promotor de esta Reducción, ahora vuelven á alzar cabeza; y habiendo muerto á los
soldados del fuerte de San Joseph y tenido atrevimiento para sitiar el de Valbuena, se teme
que den en este pueblo de San Esteban y le destruyan por estar indefenso; bien que no por esto
pierden los Jesuitas las esperanzas de hacer mucho fruto en el Chaco, cumpliéndose la profecía
de su primer apóstol San Francisco Solano, que predicó el Evangelio á los Lules, y de quien
hay tradición en aquella tierra, que habiendo profetizado la ruina de la ciudad de Eteco, que
ha más de treinta años que sucedió, predijo también que se convertirían estos indios del Chaco.

Quiera Nuestro Señor se cumpla cuanto antes esta profecía.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document06309</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>108879</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17907</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

It seems, however, this less tolerable, owing to failure to recognize and even natural law, which
any man, savage and barbaric it is, just by being a man, revered and treasured.

The children, for the most part, have no respect for their parents, before they have on domain,
making them obey with great chutzpah, and if they feel like, dare
to put parents hands.

In their illnesses are not moved to compassion, before leaving with the incredible ingratitude
and left to hunger and disease, something that even with the animals
used, and out often including better be a dog than man, because they
feel sorry and remove food from the mouth to support a troop of dogs.

Perhaps he found Fr Machoni once with some of these barbarians who had to to bury the mother
of one of them deceased, who shortly before had been converted to our holy faith, and she
wanted to bury his son to a few months, because no india, even her relatives wanted to take
the job of raising him: quitósele hands after the Father and more than pay it forward and
begged asked, none moved to compassion by which was forced as to keep the child lived with
goat milk or sheep, no without incredible pain in the meantime to
see many mothers have big breasts earrings number of dogs so they
will not starve.

Celebrate their weddings the very old (if they each deserve to be called marriages, for women
tired of her husband, and he on them have openness and freedom to make other or another to
his will) not married but when they are tired of awkward, experiencing
them itself or fear or shame that the mixed nature in the pleasures
wisely forbidden to hold the line because of the genius of unbridled
lust.

It is not easy to tell how good work P. With a fellow Jesuit missionary in instruction in the principles
of divine law to people who seemed to be neither the first instinct
of nature, or what means of charity and zeal they used to make, beasts,
rational, and rational Christian.

They were the first with a hoe in hand to break ground, to handle the plow and to do everything
else that is needed in the work camps to train them to do the same.

After visiting the sick and they did with them all the offices of charity that would make a
loving mother, removing food from the mouth and support that they had identified the mercy
of the Spanish to remedy their needs.

Suffered with incredible patience their impertinence and folly continuous, hoping the good that
could draw from them. But this was the least about what worked in out of their souls, for dishonesty,
revenge, drunkenness and barbarity thousand other inherited defects in the blood, grown over the
years, and with custom converted in nature, was almost impossible
to uproot from their hearts, but such was the undeniable virtue of
the Almighty and the finesse of an apostolic zeal that little by little
began to soften the hardness of heart so stubborn and to domesticate
the barbarity of encouragement so wild.

The first fruit is seasoned with the sweat and toil of these fervorosísimos operators, were
many souls of children who are just washed in the healthy waters of holy baptism, flew with the
naive innocence stole to the eternal bliss, to take possession of that glory, that henceforth
they would enjoy the people of his nation, after the souls managed
of many adults who assaulted a fever that went on between them, willingly
changed life in the hope of eternal rest in heaven, through the holy
baptism.

One, among others, young a few years, not least in the wounds of his body, which the patience
of mind, seemed like another Job, he enlisted in the number of children
of God with great happiness and joy of his spirit, and making fervorosísimos
acts of faith, hope and charity went on this pilgrimage to the heavenly
homeland.

She wore very badly the common enemy of faith in progress as barbaric
and uncivilized nation, for That was then applied all their efforts
to stop them and suffocate the seed of the Gospel, before that is
rooted in the hearts of the barbarians.

The first half was that he used to seek the death of the missionaries who were so hard battle,
prompting them to unbelievers issued the necessary orders.

Intentáronlo them many times, and, among others, were as conspirators to kill P. Machoni.

They had been something away from people doing a dance with a great noise and clamor, and putting
wheel in the middle of a gourd, which is also art of the devil danced with them, they agreed
all night to give death to be freed at once from his zeal and rebukes.

Perhaps

the Father heard him, and leaving his ranch to learn the cause of the novelty unexpectedly, there
an India that came from the dance, though not so beside himself as
they did, they were totally drunk, said the father why her relatives
got so much noise and gave many voices.

She, who knew what they were trying, tried to cover it up with a fake smile, responding I did
not know the cause.

Missionary Temióse was not a drunk, and to address it certified and urged the India discovered
the truth.

She, fearing for this instance and the P. I knew, I discovered the
whole conspiracy who had plotted against his life.

Rancho Recogióse in offering to God his life in sacrifice for the good of souls, and was waiting
all night should come and kill him, but the Lord delivered him to other things in their service,
because the unbelievers advised by said that the Father india Known
missionary and his attempts, did not dare to give the death, fearing
they should come also then the Spanish to avenge.

Seeing the demon that had vanished this Trace, he used another, and
was introduced in the village the pernicious error that the same was
throw it to the children the water of baptism the head that their
souls leave the body, and printed so highly this deception their fantasies,
which became the Fathers love to hate and loathing, looked on with
bad heart and fled from them as sworn enemies of their property.

And gave to that heat they foolishly believe eternal, and though every day were quedárseles dead
in his arms his friends and relatives, with all that, to the prevailing
evidence of their eyes the error of understanding.

Tried ours with all his zeal fade forces that deception and mistaken persuasion encouraged the
devil to recent damage that Christianity and God, our Lord, people
look to the new believers to greater piety eyes, wanted it quickly
remedy this damage and comfort and cheer along the virtue of his servants.

If

passed this way:

Would one day P. Machoni Rancho Rancho carrying a pot of food to give it to the sick there an India
that brought the chest a boy who was now for exhaling, not could she so quickly flee and hide
her child so that the Father did not see her.

He tried it with sweet words and great kindness to mitigate the hatred of the mother and win mood,
in order to baptize the child, but all was in vain, because the devil
talking by the mouth of a woman around him, not least because of the
infidelity that lust, and vomiting against Holy Missionary and against
that many insults and profanity Sacramento say how many insane in
the most ardent of his fury, calling the mother to allow her to wash
son in the holy waters of baptism, for what would happen to another
mother ill-advised, to offer his son to be baptized, as the child
was dropped on holy water, which out of this life.

India was the good-natured and not easily distort the trial left with nonsense crazy of his own, let
alone the false apprehension that the holy baptism was tósigo to take life, met so many old Spanish,
with gray hair, who had been baptized; so willingly gave the child to the Father, who, filled with
a generous and humble trust in God, prayed to His Majesty, and begged off that pregnancy to
Santa Fe, since it would cost more than a hint of his will, then returned to San Francisco Xavier,
asking him to look with eyes of mercy to those blind heathen, and they both sought to honor
God reached His Majesty to that holy Sacrament not only serve to rid the this innocent soul from
the bondage of the devil, but for deliverance from disease body, and offered in appreciation
of that benefit, which expected to receive, would call Francisco
Xavier.

Heaven heard the fervent prayers of his servant: for after the child was baptized, was sound of their
disease.

The same thing happened to a girl, and marriageable, whom for being all cold and stiff, the
crying their dead relatives, but after she was baptized, by large
bodies with which they requested, and upon his return from a deep
sleep, he came to himself and to life.

Whereupon, little by little ceased in the false fear that people, and mothers gave their children
to contention for that might be washed in the holy waters of baptism and healthy.

Howled with rage the demon vanished seeing their entanglements, so put all your effort to tarnish
the splendor of the smooth proceedings of one of the missionaries, with a thousand reproach
slander by some apostates who were very way that prevented them from satisfying appetite of the
flesh, with all the most awkward and dirty pleasures of sense, but in spite yours, emerged triumphant
innocence of manners and fervor of apostolic life of this good Father and was then forced the
devil to safe conduct to leave the Holy Gospel in the very broad provinces of Chaco, where
the Jesuits not only seek the conversion of the infidels, but the reform of the Spanish and Indians,
coming to confess and preach the strong Spanish that is where we like St. Joseph and Valbuena,
and accompanied the soldiers when ranging from cities to hold the barbarians who continually invade
that province, the serve as chaplains, exposing the dangers and risks
of loss of life, not have their own features and at the same time
seeking to reduce those who prey on the Spanish and baptize infants.

In these companies had worked nine years gloriously P. Machoni, when the new government of 1719
came P. designated by secretary Provincial Joseph de Aguirre, for
which because it was necessary to entrust the care of that reduction
to P. Joaquin Yegros, other two fellow Jesuits.

The new Provincial Secretary sought to encourage all efforts to convert new infidels, to cooperate
as ever the governor of the province D. Esteban de Urizar.

Year, then, in 1719, in an entry that the infidels were residents of the city San Miguel de Tucumán,
discovered a new river which was considered then to be the Pilcomayo; to the banks of the river
knew many white people lived, they were by the Spanish.

With this news the governor determined that next year were to fully discover this river thirds
of the province of Tucumán, asking for a chaplain to one of the Fathers who were in the Reduction
of San Esteban.

Then Concediólo P. Provincial, and hopeful that this discovery would much glory to God, determined
by the Paraguay River entered through the Pilcomayo which empties into that river, some Missionaries
of the Guarani, in precise order that no stop to reduce any nation and just winning the will of
the natives will penetrate to meet with the Spanish soldiers who
entered the province of Tucumán, or they the site of the Chiriguanos.

All this was preventing two purposes: first, he discovered the land and the river, could enter
the Tucuman, Paraguay and Frontera de Santa Fe, shaking hands with
everyone of these provinces to conquer the Chaco, which achieved the
conversion of many souls.

The second, open shortest path here for the Chiquitos missions, which always is highly desired
to avoid the short distance to the path of Tarija, because Zamucos presumed that were very close
to the Chaco and the Pilcomayo, and there also On this occasion entered
a Jesuit to come to find others.

He noted, therefore, the P. Provincial enter the Pilcomayo river mouth to the PP. Gabriel Lucas
Patiño Rodríguez, both born in the city of Asunción, and at the time
Missionaries of Guarani, Paraguay's college and sent his brother Bartolomé
de Niebla, Andalucia, and donated to a Portuguese named Faustino Correa,
with some Guarani Indians, so that if Parents must defend the invasion
of infidels.

By Zamucos Chiquitos Indians came in with some PP. Philip Smith and Augustine Castañares.

The province of Tucuman were unable to find Pilcomayo and finally
found the Tucumaneses discovered by the year of 1719 could not be
that river, as this is small and large Pilcomayo.

The Chiquitos, having walked the Zamucos, where it is judged to fall
into the river, never could find him.

Those who entered the mouth of the Pilcomayo were on a ship and some boats, walked the river,
always at different directions, by repeated laps running: at first found some traces of Indians,
but did not see them.

And walked about eighty miles, partly along the river, partly because
of gaps, because there are many the bank of the river, which, when
low river, remain divided about him and made ponds; but when it grows,
the whole campaign is a sea of ??water, because they incorporate with
him.

These eighty leagues recognized that the mother of the river was not so deep that could navigate
for him the ship without manifest danger of running aground, which
determined by P. Patiño pass in the boats with his brother Fog three
Spanish and thirty-four Indians to record what remaining to achieve
the end of business, leaving in the meantime in the boat to Father
Luke Rodriguez, donated and to the other people to wait.

They came sailing the two boats and walked another three hundred leagues, in which several parties
were Indians of various nations, already confined to Chiriguaná.

Finally came to a nation not known, which seemed good-natured Indians, and were have beautiful faces
and good stature as the white Indian, Spanish appeared, they had brood mares and sheep, whose
wool fabrics make great, the horses were not number. The fertile soil in which crops are the
fruits of the country.

Jumped ashore and gave the natives many donecillos they appreciate
and thus they show much affection, who conceived hopes of reducing
later easily.

But some tuffs and Mocovíes that lay between them soured these hopes, because talking to the
Indians, incited them against us, plotting a treacherous betrayal their lives.

They were there for peace each other, in the case with many strokes as long as was necessary
to rest, when, having gone three of our Indians to cut firewood,
they attacked the Toba and Mocovíes treacherous with the Indians of
that nation, killed them both with arrows and the other badly wounded,
so he died a few days away.

The others retired to the boats that cover the Father sent some cow hides resist.

Came along to ours over 600 infidels, to the boats by shooting a storm
of arrows so thick, that looked like a swarm of locusts, but none
were harmed, because they were resistant to the skins, giving off
the arrows, and even though it has that P. Patiño was twice found
in the bow to the shooting, although all parts were falling arrows,
none touched him.

Seeing this attempted to withdraw from the furies of those barbarians, whose treachery undid
so far and hopes dashed able to penetrate the Chaco, where it was expected, as I said, reduce
many nations.

They returned, for no other fruit, with much work retracing the path of four leagues which until
then had sailed.

But back to the Reduction of San Esteban, the same year of 1721, there
were in it many families.

Kindled by this time a smallpox pestecilla, that died after two.

The others charged so scared to death that threatened them smallpox, the same day that those two
were killed, left to neglect our own and everyone fled least eighteen
adults and twenty boys.

Then it warned Fr. Joaquin Lorenzo Fanlo Yegros and mounted their horses in monitoring, and
went to reach for a few hills to Salta, but still much the thickness forest, and roughness
of the mountains, were removed, and followed on foot, with incredible
fatigue, because they fled down the right path, but always obliquely,
because they said so they could not go fever, tired of the bush and
turns.

Such is its enormity.

Parents were powerless before poderles to catch, and turning to his
people to care for those who had been sick, they sent after the fugitives
to two Indians carried with them to stop because of the eighteen adults
were killed fourteen, whom attended with great love, without fear
of contagion, and all other ill.

The two Indians found some miles
away to the fugitives, and even if they did, only they could be reduced
to come down to where they were the Parents.

They sought to roll back the reduction, but then managed only hope they finished the fever again.
Therefore, leaving them there to Parents became people to take care of those who remained,
most patients, of whom died soon fourteen adults, whom attended with great zeal and charity, to
give burial by their own hands.

The fugitives returned after some time his people, by the inquiries of our own, they always have
to work here, gloriously, the innate barbarism of all these nations,
as known by the referral.

At present this town is in extreme danger of destruction because
Mocovíes and Tovas, so far have been bridled by the value of the governor
of the province of Tucumán, main promoter of this reduction is coming
back to raise his head, and having slain the soldiers of Fort St.
Joseph and had the audacity to lay siege to Valbuena, it is feared
give in this town of San Esteban and destroy you for being helpless,
well why not Jesuit lost hope of doing much fruit in the Chaco, fulfilling
the prophecy of San Francisco Solano first apostle, who preached the
gospel to the Lules, and who no tradition in the land, who, having
predicted the ruin of the city of ETEC, which more than thirty years
has happened, also predicted that these Indians would become the Chaco.

Our
Lord wants to fulfill this prophecy as soon as possible</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>