<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04261</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>300142</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22488</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Pasado lo sobredicho, cuentan que fueron hechos grandes sacrificios en Pachacama por Tupac
Inca Yupanqui, y grandes fiestas; las cuales pasadas, dió la vuelta al Cuzco por un camino
que se le hizo, que va á salir al valle de Xauxa, que atraviesa por la nevada sierra de Pariacaca,
que no es poco de ver y notar su grandeza, y cuán grandes escaleras tiene, y hoy dia se ven
por entre aquellas nieves, para la poder pasar. Y visitando las provincias de la serranía,
y proveyendo y ordenando lo que más convenia para la buena gobernacion, allegó al Cuzco, á
donde fué recebido con grandes fiestas y bailes, y se hicieron en el templo grandes sacrificios
por sus victorias.

La provincia de Chincha fué en lo pasado gran cosa en este reino del Perú, y muy poblada de
gente, tanto, que ántes deste tiempo habian con sus capitanes salido y allegado al Collao,
donde, con grandes despojos que hobieron, dieron la vuelta á su provincia, donde estuvieron
y fueron siempre estimados de los comarcanos, y temidos. El Inca padre de Tupac Inca, se dice
que envió desde los Soras un capitan con gente de guerra, llamado Capac Inca, á que procurase
atraer á los de Chincha al señorío suyo; mas, aunque fué y lo procuró, fué poca parte, porque
se pusieron en arma, y de tal manera se querian defender, quel orejon, lo mejor que pudo, se
volvió; y estuvieron sin ver capitan del Inca ninguno hasta que Tupac Inca los sojuzgó, á lo
quellos mesmos cuentan; porque yo no sé en esto más de lo que ellos mismos cuentan.

Volviendo al propósito, como Tupac Inca hobiese llegado al Cuzco, como se ha escripto, despues
de se haber holgado y dádose á sus pasatiempos los dias que le pareció, mandó de nuevo hacer
llamamiento de gente, con intencion de acabar de señorear los indios de Los Llanos. Su mandado
se cumplió, y prestamente parecieron en el Cuzco los capitanes de las provincias con la gente
de guerra que habian de traer, y despues de puesto en órden lo de la ciudad y lo que más el
rey habia de proveer, salió del Cuzco y abajó á Los Llanos por el camino de Guaytaray. Sabiendo
de su ida, muchos le aguardaban con intencion de le tomar por Señor, y muchos con voluntad
de le dar guerra y procurar de conservar [se] en la libertad que tenian. En los valles de los
Nazcas habia copia de gente y apercibidos de guerra.

Llegado Tupac Inca, hobo embajadas y pláticas entre unos y otros, y aunque hubo algunas porfías
y guerrilla, se contentaron con lo que el Inca dellos quiso por cimiento (así): que se hiciesen
casas fuertes y que hobiese mitimaes, y pagar lo que de tributo les pusieron. Y de aquí fué
el Inca al valle de Ica, á donde halló resistencia más que en lo de la Nazca; mas, su prudencia
bastó [á] hacer, sin guerra, de los enemigos amigos, y se allanaron como los pasados. En Chincha
estaban aguardando si el Inca iba á su valle, puestos más de treinta mill hombres á punto de
guerra, y esperaban favores de los vecinos. Tupac Inca, como lo supo, les envió mensajeros,
con grandes presentes para los señores y para los capitanes y principales, diciendo á los embajadores
que de su parte les hiciesen grandes ofrecimientos, y quél no queria guerra con ellos, sino
paz y hermandad, y otras cosas desta suerte. Los de Chincha oyeron lo que el Inca decia, y
recibiéronle sus presentes, y fueron para él algunos principales con lo que habia en el valle,
y hablaron con él y trataron el amistad, de tal manera, que se asentó la paz, y los de Chincha
dejaron las armas y recibieron á Tupac Inca, que luego movió para Chincha. Esto cuentan los
mesmos indios de Chincha y los orejones del Cuzco; otros indios de otras provincias he oido
que lo cuentan de otra manera, porque dicen que hobo grande guerra; más yo creo que sin ella
quedó por Señor de Chincha.

Llegado el Inca á aquel valle, como tan grande y hermoso lo vió, se alegró mucho. Loaba las
costumbres de los naturales, y con palabras amorosas les rogaba que tomasen de las del Cuzco
las que viesen que les cuadraban, y ellos le contentaron y obedecieron en todo; y dado asiento
en lo que se habia de hacer, partió para Ica, de donde fue á lo que llaman del Guarco, porque
supo questaban aguardándole de guerra; y así era la verdad, porque los naturales de aquellos
valles, teniendo en poco á sus vecinos porque así se habian amilanado y, sin ver porqué, dado
la posesion de sus tierras á rey estraño, y con mucho ánimo se juntaron, habiendo hecho casas
fuertes y pucaraes en la parte perteneciente para ello, cerca de la mar, en donde pusieron
sus mujeres, y hijos. Y andando[188] el Inca con su gente en órden, allegó á donde estaban
sus enemigos, y les envió sus embajadas con grandes partidos, y algunas veces con amenazas
y fieros; mas, no quisieron pasar por la ley de sus comarcanos, que era reconoscer á extranjeros,
y entre unos y otros, al uso destas partes, se trabó la guerra y pasaron grandes cosas entre
ellos. Y como viniese el verano y hiciesen grandes calores, adolesció la gente del Inca, que
fué causa que le convino retirar; y así, con la más cordura que pudo, lo hizo; y los del Guarco
salieron por su valle, y cogieron sus mantenimientos y comidas, y tornaron á sembrar los campos,
y hacian armas, y aparejábanse para, si del Cuzco viniesen contra ellos, que los hallasen apercebidos.

Tupac Inca revolvió sobre el Cuzco; y como los hombres sean de tan poca constancia, como vieron
que los del Guarco se quedaron con lo que intentaron, comenzó á haber novedades entre algunos
dellos, y se rebelaron algunos y apartaron del servicio del Inca.--Estos eran naturales de
los valles de la mesma costa.--Todo fué á oido del rey, y lo que quedaba de aquel verano, entendió
en hacer llamamiento de gente y en mandar salir orejones para que fuesen por todas partes del
reino á visitar las provincias, y determinó de ganar el señorio del Guarco, aunque sobre ello
se le recreciese notorio daño. Y como viniese el otoño y fuese pasado el calor del estío, con
la más gente que pudo juntar, abajó á Los Llanos y envió sus embajadores á los valles dellos,
afeándolos su poca firmeza en presumir de se levantar contra él, y amonestóles que estuviesen
firmes en su amistad, donde nó, certificóles que la guerra les haria cruel. Y como llegase
al principio del valle del Guarco, en las haldas de una sierra, mandó á sus gentes fundar una
ciudad á la cual puso por nombre Cuzco, como á su principal asiento, y las calles y collados
y plazas tuvieron el nombre que las verdaderas. Dijo, que hasta quel Guarco fuese ganado y
los naturales sujetos suyos, habia de permanecer la nueva poblacion, y que en ella siempre
habia de haber gente de guarnicion; y luego que se hobo hecho lo que en aquello se ordenó,
movió con su gente á donde estaban los enemigos, y los cercó, y tan firmes estuvieron en su
propósito, que jamás querian venir á partido ninguno, y tuvieron su guerra, que fué tan larga,
que dicen que duró tres años, los veranos de los cuales el Inca se iba al Cuzco, dejando gente
de guarnicion en el nuevo Cuzco que habia hecho, para que siempre estuviese contra los enemigos.

Y así, los unos por ser señores, y los otros por no ser siervos, procuraban de salir con su
intencion; pero al fin, al cabo de los tres años, los del Guarco fueron enflaqueciendo, y el
Inca, que lo conoció, les envió de nuevo embajadores que les dijiesen que fuesen todos amigos
y compañeros, quel no queria sino casar sus hijos con sus hijas, y por el consiguiente, sustener
en todo confederacion con gran igualdad; y otras cosas dichas con engaño, paresciéndole á Tupac
Inca que merescian grand pena por haberle dado tanto trabajo; y los del Guarco, paresciéndoles
que ya no podrian sustentarse muchos dias, y que con las condiciones hechas por el Inca sería
mejor gozar de tranquilidad y sosiego, concedieron en lo que el rey Inca queria; que no debieran,
porque dejando el fuerte, fueron los más principales á le hacer reverencia, y sin más pensar,
mandó á sus gentes que los matasen á todos, y ellos con gran crueldad lo pusieron por obra,
y mataron á todos los principales y hombres más honrados dellos que allí estaban, y en los
que no lo eran, tambien se ejecutó la sentencia; y mataron tantos como hoy dia lo cuentan los
descendientes dellos y los grandes montones de huesos que hay son testigos; y creemos, que
lo que sobre esto se cuenta es lo que veis escripto.

Hecho esto, mando hacer el rey Inca una agraciada fortaleza tal y de tal manera que yo conté
en la Primera parte[189]. Asentado el valle y puestos mitimaes y gobernador, habiendo oido
las embajadas que le vinieron de los Yuncas y de muchos serranos, mandó ruinar el nuevo Cuzco
que se habia hecho, y con toda su gente dió la vuelta para la ciudad del Cuzco, donde fué recebido
con gran alegria, y se hicieron grandes sacrificios con alabanza suya en el templo y oráculos,
y por el consiguiente se alegró el pueblo con fiestas y borracheras y táquis solenes.

Como Tupac Inca hobiese llegado al Cuzco con tan grandes victorias como se ha escripto, estuvo
algunos dias holgándose en sus banquetes y borracheras con sus mujeres y mancebas, que eran
muchas, y con sus hijos, entre los cuales se criaba Guayna Capac, el que habia de ser rey,
y salia muy esforzado y brioso. Pasadas las fiestas, el gran Tupac Inca pensó de dar vista
al Collao y señorear la tierra que más pudiese de adelante; y para hacerlo, mandó que se apercebiesen
en todas partes gentes, y se hiciesen muchos toldos para dormir en los lugares desiertos. Y
comenzaron á venir con sus capitanes, y alojábanse á la redonda del Cuzco, sin entrar en la
ciudad otros que los que la ley no proibia, y á los unos y á los otros proveian cumplidamente
de todo lo necesario, teniendo en ello cuenta grande los gobernadores y proveedores de la mesma
ciudad. Y como se hobiesen juntado todos los que habian de ir á la guerra, se hicieron sacrificios
á sus dioses, conforme á su ceguedad, poniendo á los adivinos que supiesen de los oráculos
el fin de la guerra; y hecho un convite general y muy espléndido, salió del Cuzco Tupac Inca,
dejando en la ciudad su lugarteniente y su hijo mayor Guayna Capac, y con grand repuesto[190]
y majestad, caminó por lo de Collasuyo, visitando sus guarniciones y tambos reales, y holgóse
por los pueblos de los Canas y Canches.

Entrando en lo de Collao, anduvo hasta Chucuito, donde los señores de la tierra se juntaron
á le hacer fiesta; y habia con su buena órden todo recaudo y abasto de mantenimientos, sin
que faltase á más de trescientas mill personas que iban en sus reales. Algunos señores del
Collao se ofrecieron de ir por sus personas con el mesmo Inca, y con los que señaló, entró
en el palude de Titicaca, y loó á los que entendian en las obras de los edificios que su padre
mandó hacer, cuán bien lo habian hecho. En el templo hizo grandes sacrificios, y dió al ídolo
y sacerdotes dones ricos, conforme á tan gran señor como él era. Volvió á su gente y caminó
por toda la provincia del Collao hasta salir della; envió sus mensajeros á todas las naciones
de los Charcas, Carangas y más gentes que hay en aquellas tierras. Déllas, unos le acudian
á servir y otros á le dar guerra, mas, aunque se la dieron, su potencia era tanta, que bastó
á los sojuzgar, usando con los vencidos de gran clemencia, y con los que se venian, de mucho
amor. En Paria mandó hacer edificios grandes, y lo mesmo en otras partes. Y cierto debieron
pasar á Tupac Inca cosas grandes, muchas de las cuales priva el olvido, por la falta que tienen
de letras, y yo pongo sumariamente algo de lo mucho que sabemos, por lo que oimos y vemos,
los que acá estamos, que pasó.

Yendo victorioso adelante de los Charcas, atravesó muchas tierras é provincias y grandes despoblados
de nieve, hasta que llegó á lo que llamamos Chile, y señoreó y conquistó todas aquellas tierras,
en las cuales dicen que llegaron al rio de Maule. En lo de Chile hizo algunos edificios, y
tributáronle de aquellas comarcas mucho oro en tejuelos. Dejó gobernadores y mitimaes, y puesto
en órden lo que habia ganado, volvió al Cuzco.

Hácia la parte de Levante envió orejones avisados, en hábito de mercaderes, para que mirasen
las tierras que hobiese y qué gentes las mandaban; y ordenadas estas otras cosas, volvió al
Cuzco; de donde afirman que tornó á salir á cabo de algunos dias, y con la gente que convino
llevar, entró en los Andes, y pasó grand trabajo por la espesura de la montaña, y conquistó
algunos pueblos de aquella region, y mandó sembrar muchas sementeras de coca, y que la llevasen
al Cuzco, donde él dió la vuelta.

Y dicen que pasados pocos dias, le dió cierto mal que le causó la muerte, y que encomendando
á su hijo la gobernacion del reino y á sus mujeres é hijos, y diciendo otras cosas, murió.
Y se hicieron grandes lloros y tan notable sentimiento desde Quito hasta Chile, ques extraña
cosa de oir á los indios lo que sobre ello cuentan.

Adonde, ni en qué lugar está enterrado no lo dicen. Cuentan que se mataron grand número de
mujeres y servidores y pajes para meter con él, con tanto tesoro y pedrería, que debió montar
más de un millon; y seria poco, pues los señores particulares se enterraban algunos con más
de cient mill castellanos. Sin la gente tanta que metieron en su sepultura, se ahorcaron y
enterraron muchas mujeres y hombres en partes diversas del reino, y en todas partes se hicieron
lloros por un año entero y se tresquilaron las más de las mujeres, poniéndose todas sogas de
esparto; y acabado el año, se vinieron á hacer sus honras. Y lo que dicen que usaban hacer
no lo quiero poner, porque son gentilidades; y los chripstianos questaban en el Cuzco el año
de mill y quinientos y cincuenta, acuérdense de lo que vieron que se hizo por las honras y
cabo de año de Paulo Inca, con se haber vuelto chripstiano, y sacarán lo que seria en tiempo
del reinado de los reyes pasados, ántes que perdiesen su señorío.

CAP. LXI.--De cómo reinó en el Cuzco Guayna Capac que fué el dozeno rey Inca.

Muerto que fué el gran rey Tupac Inca Yupanqui, se entendió en hacer sus obsequias y entierro
al uso de sus mayores, con gran pompa. Y cuentan los orejones, que de secreto tramaban entre
algunos de cobrar la libertad pasada y eximir de sí el mando de los Incas, y que de hecho salieran
con lo que intentaban, si no fuera por la buena maña que se dieron los gobernadores del Inca
con la gente de los mitimaes y capitanes, que pudieron sustentar en tiempo tan revuelto y que
no tenia rey, lo quel pasado les habia encargado. Guayna Capac no descuidó ni dejó de conocer
que le convenia mostrar valor para no perder lo que su padre con tanto trabajo ganó. Luego
se entró á hacer el ayuno, y el que gobernaba la ciudad le fué fiel y leal. No dejó de haber
alguna turbacion entre los mesmos incas, porque algunos hijos de Tupac Inca, habidos en otras
mujeres que la Coya, quisieron ponerse á pretender[191] la dignidad real, mas el pueblo, que
vian estaba con Guayna Capac, no lo consintió, mas estorbó el castigo que se hizo. Acabado
el ayuno, Guayna Capac salió con la borla muy galano y aderezado, y hizo las cirimonias usadas
por sus pasados, con el fin de las cuales el nombre de rey le pusieron, y así, á grandes voces
decian[192]: Guayna Capac Inca Zapalla tucuillacta uya; que quiere decir; "Guayna Capac solo
es rey; á él oyan todos los pueblos."

Era Guayna Capac, segun dicen muchos indios que le vieron y conocieron, de no muy grand cuerpo,
pero doblado y bien hecho; de buen rostro y muy grave; de pocas palabras, de muchos hechos;
era justiciero y castigaba sin templanza. Queria ser tan temido, que de noche le soñaran los
indios. Comia como ellos usan, y así vivia vicioso de mujeres, si así se le puede decir; oía
á los que le hablaban bien, y creíase muy de ligero: privaron con él mucho los aduladores y
lisonjeros, que entre ellos no faltaban, ni hoy deja de haber; y daba oidos á mentiras, que
fué causa que muchos murieron sin culpa. A los mancebos que tentados de la carne dormian con
sus mujeres ó mancebas, ó con las que estaban en el templo del sol, luego los mandaba matar
á ellos, y á ellas castigo igual. A los que él castigó por alborotos y motines, privó de las
haciendas, dándolas á otros; por otras causas, era el castigo en las personas solamente.--Mucho
desto disimulaba su padre, especial lo de las mujeres, que cuando se tomaba alguno con ellas,
decia que eran mancebos.--Su madre de Guayna Capac, señora principal, mujer y hermana que fué
de Tupac Inca Yupanqui, llamada Mama Ocllo, dicen que fué de mucha prudencia, y que avisó á
su hijo de muchas cosas que ella vió hacer á Tupac Inca, y que le queria tanto, que le rogó
no se fuese á Quito ni á Chile, hasta que ella fuese muerta; y así, cuentan que por le hacer
placer y obedecer á su mandado, estuvo en el Cuzco sin salir hasta que ella murió y fué enterrada
con grand pompa, metiéndose en su sepultura muchos tesoros y ropa fina y de sus mujeres y servidores.
Los más tesoros de los Incas muertos y heredades, que llaman chácaras, todo estaba entero desde
el primero, sin que ninguno osase gastarlo ni tocarlo, porque entre ellos no tenian guerras
ni necesidades que el dinero hobiese de las remediar; por donde creemos que hay grandes tesoros
en las entrañas de la tierra perdidos; y así estarán para siempre, si de ventura, alguno, edificando
ó haciendo otra cosa, no topare con algo de lo mucho que hay.

CAP. LXII.--Cómo Guayna Capac salió del Cuzco y lo que hizo.

Guayna Capac habia mandado parescer delante de sí á los principales señores de los naturales
de las provincias, y estando su Córte llena dellos, tomó por mujer á su hermana Chimbo Ocllo,
y por ello se hicieron grandes fiestas, dejando los lloros que por la muerte de Tupac Inca
se hacian. Y acabadas, mandó que se saliesen con él hasta cincuenta mill hombres de guerra,
con los cuales queria ir acompañado para ir á visitar las provincias de su reino. Como lo mandó,
se puso por obra, y salió del Cuzco con más pompa y autoridad que su padre; porque las andas
serian tan ricas, á lo que afirman los que llevaron el rey en sus hombros, que no tuvieran
precio las piedras preciosas tan grandes y muchas que iban en ellas, sin el oro de que heran
hechas. Y fué por las provincias de Xaquixaguana y Andaguaylas, y allegó á los Soras y Lucanas[193],
donde envió embajadas á muchas partes de los llanos y sierras, y tuvo respuesta dellos y de
otras, con grandes presentes y ofrecimientos.

Volvió desde aquellos lugares al Cuzco, donde estuvo entendiendo en hacer grandes sacrificios
al sol y á los que más tenian por dioses, para que le fuesen favorables en la jornada que queria
hacer, y dió grandes dones á los ídolos de los guacas; y supo de los adivinos, por los dichos
de los demonios, ó porque ellos lo inventaron, que le habia de suceder prósperamente en las
jornadas que hacer queria, y que volveria al Cuzco con grande honra y provecho. Esto acabado,
de muchas partes vinieron gentes con sus armas y capitanes, por su mandado, y alojados, de
la ciudad eran proveidos.

En el edificio de la fortaleza se entendia, sin dejar de labrar dia ninguno los para ello señalados.
En la plaza del Cuzco se puso la grand maroma de oro, y se hicieron grandes bailes y borracheras,
y, junto á la piedra de la guerra, se nombraron capitanes y mandones, conforme á su costumbre;
y ordenándoles, hizo un parlamento Guayna Capac, bien ordenado y dicho con palabras vehementes,
sobre que le fuesen leales así los que iban con él, como los que quedaban. Respondieron que
de su servicio no se partirian, el cual dicho loó y dió esperanzas de les hacer mercedes largas.
Y estando aparejado lo que para la jornada era menester, salió del Cuzco con toda la gente
de guerra que se habia juntado, y por un camino grande, tan soberbio como hoy dia paresce,
pues todos los de acá lo vemos y andamos por él, anduvo hácia el Collao, mostrando por las
provincias donde pasaba tener en poco los grandes servicios que le hacian; porque dicen que
decia que á los Incas todo se les debia. Entendia en saber lo que le daban de tributo, y la
posibilidad de la provincia; recogió muchas mujeres, las más hermosas que se podian hallar;
dellas tomaba para sí, y otras daba á sus capitanes y privados; las demás eran puestas en el
templo del sol y allí guardadas.

Entrando en el Collao, le trajeron cuenta de las grandes manadas que tenia de ganados, y cuántas
mill cargas de lana fina se llevaban por año á los que hacian la ropa para su casa y servicio.
En la isla de Titicaca entró y mandó hacer grandes sacrificios. En Chuquiabo[194], mandó que
estuviesen indios estantes con sus veedores á sacar metal de oro con la órden y regimiento
que se ha escripto. Pasando adelante, mandó que los Charcas y otras naciones hasta los Chichas,
sacasen cantidad grande de pastas de plata, que se llevasen al Cuzco por su cuenta, sin que
nada faltase; trasportó algunos mitimaes de una parte en otra, aunque habia dias que estaban
alojados; mandaba que todos trabajasen y ninguno holgase, porque decia que la tierra donde
habia holgazanes, no pensaban otra cosa sinó cómo buscar escándalos y corromper la honestidad
de las mujeres. Por donde pasaba, mandaba edificar tambos y plazas, dando con su mano la traza;
repartió los términos á muchas provincias y límite conocido, para que, por aventajallo, no
viniesen á las manos. Su gente de guerra, aunque era tanta, iba tan corregida, que no salia
de los reales un paso; por donde pasaban, los naturales proveian de lo necesario tan cumplidamente,
que era más lo que sobraba que lo que se gastaba. En algunos lugares edificaron baños, y en
otros cotos, y por los desiertos se hicieron grandes casas. Por todas partes quel Inca pasaba,
dejaba hechas tales cosas, que es admiracion contarlas. Al que erraba castigaba sin dejar pasar
por alto nada, y gratificaba á quien bien le servia.

Ordenado estas cosas y otras, pasó de las provincias subjetas agora á la Villa de la Plata,
y por lo de Tucuman[195] envió capitanes con gente de guerra á los Chiriguanaes; mas no les
fue bien, porque volvieron huyendo. Por otra parte, hácia la mar del Sur, envió más gente con
otros capitanes, á que señoreasen los valles y pueblos que del todo su padre no pudo conquistar.
El fué caminando con toda su gente hácia Chile, acabando de domar, por donde pasaba, las gentes
que habia. Pasó gran trabajo por los despoblados, y fué mucha la nieve que sobre ellos cayó;
llevaban toldos con que se guarescer y muchos yanaconas y mujeres de servicio. Por todas estas
nieves se iba haciendo el camino, ó ya estaba hecho, y bien limpio, y postas puestas por él.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04763</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>159319</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20957</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

After the aforesaid, have great sacrifices that were made in Pachacama by Tupac Inca Yupanqui,
and large celebrations, which last, he turned back to Cuzco on a path that was done, what
you will get the Xauxa Valley, which runs through the snowy mountains of Pariacaca, which is something
to see and feel his greatness, and how large steps are, and today are and among those snows,
to get through. And visiting the provinces of the highland and providing and rearranging the
most convenient for good governance, who is close to Cuzco, to where he was received with
great feasts and dances, and made great sacrifices in the temple for their victories.

Chincha province in the past was much in this kingdom of Peru, and most populated People, therefore,
that before this one time with their masters had left and joined himself to the Collao, where,
with great spoil that hobieron, turned back to his province, where they were and were always
estimated their neighbors, and feared. The father of Tupac Inca Inca, is said Soras sent from
a captain with warriors, called Capac Inca, to obtain Chincha attract the lordship of his own:
but, although he was and what he tried, was low partly because got a weapon, and so it wanted
to defend, quel orejon, the best he could, returned, and were not seeing any captain until Tupac
Inca Inca subjugated, to what T hose same tale, for I do not know about this more than they
themselves.

Returning to the purpose, as Tupac Inca reached the Cuzco hobiese, as eScript, after to be loose
and have given to their hobbies seemed like days, sent it back to People call, with the intention
of ending the Lady Indians of Los Llanos. His command was met, and appeared in Cuzco speedily
masters of the provinces with people of war who were to bring, and put in order after the city
and what more King had to provide, out of Cuzco and down to the plains by way of Guaytaray. Knowing
its way, many were waiting for him with the intention of taking him as Lord, and many willing
to give him war and try to keep [it] in the freedom they had. In the valleys of the Nazca people
had back and ready against war.

Tupac Inca arrived, hobo embassies and talks between them, and although there were some stubbornness
and guerrillas, were content with what the Inca Dellos wanted by the foundation (and) that
hiciesen fortified houses and hobiese mitimaes, and pay tribute to what they put. And here was
the Inca to the valley of Ica, where he found more resistance in the Nazca, but, wisdom enough [to]
do, without war, enemies friends, and were broken as the last. In Chincha waiting if the Inca
were going to the valley, made more than thirty thousand men on the point of war, and hoped
to curry favor with the neighbors. Tupac Inca, as he knew, he sent messengers, with great presents for
the lords and masters and principals, said the ambassadors that of his party's hiciesen great
offers, and chelate did not want war with them, but peace and brotherhood, and other things
to this pass. The Chincha heard what the Inca he said, and received him his present, and were
for him some principal with what was in the valley and talked to him and sought the friendship
so that peace was settled, and Chincha weapons and were left to Tupac Inca, then moved to Chincha.
This counted mesmos Chincha Indians of Cuzco and the dried, other Indians from other provinces
have heard have it otherwise, because they say large hobo war more I believe that without it
was for Lord of Chincha.

Inca come to this valley, so great and beautiful saw it, was delighted. He praised the customs
of the natives, and with loving words I begged them to take those of Cuzco which would see them
add up, and they obeyed him and contented throughout, and given seat when it had to do, went
to Ica, where he was to what they call the Guarco, because questa knew war and turned around,
and it was true, because the natives of those valleys, taking little by their neighbors because
they had so unnerved and do not see why, given possession of their lands to stranger king, and
gathered a lot of courage, having made houses pucaraes strong in the part belonging to it,
near the sea, where they put their wives and children. And walking [188] the Inca with their
people in order, who is close to where they were their enemies, and sent their embassies to
big games, and sometimes threats and fierce, but did not want to go through the law of their neighbors,
who was foreign to Acknowledge, and with each other, the use of these parts, locked the war
and spent great things from them. And come the summer and hiciesen great heat, the people of
the Inca adolesció that was because he agreed to withdraw, and so, with more sanity as he could,
did, and those of Guarco out of its valley, and took their maintenance and meals, and turned to
sow the fields, and they made weapons and aparejábanse for, if the
Cuzco should come against them, found them apercebidos.

Tupac Inca Cuzco stirred about, and as men are of so little evidence, they saw than the Guarco
were left with what they tried, he began to have news from some of them, and rebelled and departed
from the service some of the Inca .-- These were natural valleys up the same coast .-- All the
king went to hearing, and what remained of that summer, he understood to make calls and send
people out to apricots were all over the kingdom to visit the provinces, and determined to win
the dominion of Guarco, though about it ingrowth was evident harm. As autumn came and went past
the heat of summer, with The more people who might join, down to the Plains and sent their ambassadors
to the valleys of them, afeándolos his unsteadiness in presuming he is up against, and they
were amonestóles firm in their friendship, where not, certificóles that the war would make cruel.
And how to get at first Guarco Valley, in Halden saw, he commanded his people to found a city
??to which his name Cuzco, as his chief seat, and the streets and hills and squares were the
real name. He said that even cattle would quel Guarco the native subjects of his, had to remain
the new settlement, and that it always People had to be quartered, and then hobo who did what
on what was ordered, moved with his people to where they were the enemy, and besieged it, and
so firm were in purpose, never wanted to come to any party, and had his war, which was so long,
saying that lasted three years, the summers of which the Inca went to Cuzco, leaving people quartered
in the new Cuzco he had done, that was always against the enemy.

And so, one to be gentlemen, and the other for not being slaves, tried to leave with his intention,
but finally, after three years, the Guarco were emaciated, and Inca, who met him, I again sent
ambassadors to them that they were all friends dijiesen and colleagues, quel did not want to marry
their sons but his daughters, and the resulting, sustener confederation all very equal, and other
things such deception, Paresce to Tupac Merescian grand Inca punishment for having given so much
work, and the Guarco, Paresce could no longer sustain many days, and that conditions would be
made by the Inca better to enjoy peace and quiet, gave what the Inca king wanted, who should not,
since leaving the fort, were the key to reverence him, and without thinking, commanded his people
that kill them all, and they put him with great cruelty at the hands, and slew all the major
and most honest men them who were there, and in they were not, also be carried out the sentence,
and killed as many as today, we have the descendants Dell and large piles of bones that there
are witnesses, and we believe that what about this account is what you see eScript.

This done, he ordered the Inca king and a graceful strength that so I told in Part [189]. Settled
the valley and put mitimaes and governor, having heard embassies which came from the Yuncas
and many mountain, commanded want to ruin the new Cuzco had been done, and all the people turned
around for the city of Cuzco, where he was received with great joy, and made great sacrifices to praise
him in the temple and oracles and therefore he was glad the town with parties and drinking and
táquis Solenoid.

As Tupac Inca reached the Cuzco hobiese with such great victories as has eScript, was some days
rejoiced at their feasts and drinking with their wives and concubines, who were many, and
their children, including growing up Huayna Capac, who was to be king and came out very courageous
and spirited. After the holidays, the great Tupac Inca thought of giving sight Collao and rule the earth
that could front more, and to do so, he issued apercebiesen people everywhere, and many tents
hiciesen sleeping in desert places. Y began to come with their masters, and to the round alojábanse
Cuzco, without entering the city ??other than the law does not proibia, and to each other and
to dutifully provided everything you need, taking into account this great governors and providers
MESMA city. And as hobiesen together all those who had to go to war, is made sacrifices their gods,
according to his blindness, making wizards, who knew of the oracles the end of the war, and
made a general and very splendid treat, Tupac left Cuzco Inca in the city leaving his lieutenant
and his eldest son Huayna Capac, and spare grand [190] and majesty, so Collasuyo walked, visiting
the seals and real drums, and rejoice by the peoples of the Canas and Canches.

Entering in the Collao, walked up Chucuito, where the lords of the earth together him to make
merry, and had its good order all collection and supply of maintenance without who miss more
than three hundred mill people who were on their real. Some lords Collao offered to go for
their people with the same saddle Inca, and with that said, came In malaria Titicaca, and
Loo to those who understood the works of the buildings that his father commanded to do, how well
they had done. In the temple made great sacrifices, and gave the idol priests and rich gifts,
according to so great a lord as he was. He returned to his people and walked throughout the
province to leave della Collao, sent his messengers to all nations of Charcas, Carangas and more
people who are in those lands. Dellas, flocked around him to serve and others to you make
war, but though it was given, his power was so great that enough to the subjugation, using the
conquered of great mercy, and with which it came, much love. In Paria sent to large buildings,
and do the same elsewhere. And some had Inca Tupac go to great things, many of which deprives
the forgetfulness, the need to have letters, and I summarily put something of how much we know
from what we hear and see, that here we are, what happened.

Going ahead of the Charcas victorious, went through many lands and depopulated provinces and large snow,
until he came to what we call Chile, and lorded over and conquered all the lands, in which they
say they came to the river Maule. As of Chile made some buildings and tributáronle of regions
much gold in ingots. Governors and mitimaes left, and since in order you had won, he returned to
Cuzco.

Towards the Levante sent apricots warned, in the dress of merchants, who would look for hobiese
lands and what the people sent, and ordered these other things, returned to Cuzco, in which
contend that turned to go out after a few days, and with people who agreed lead, went into
the Andes, and spent the grand work of the mountain wilderness, and conquered some villages in
that region, and sent many crops of coca plant, and which led Cuzco,
where he turned around.

And they say past few days, gave him some evil that caused his death, and commending his son
the government of the kingdom and their wives and children, and saying
other things, he died.

And there were great tears and feeling so remarkable from Quito to Chile, strange forests
thing to hear what the Indians on that count.

Where or in what place he is buried not say. That have killed large number of women and servers
and pages to get to him with so much treasure and jewels, which had mounted more than one million,
and would be little, because individual lords were buried some of them over a hundred miles
from Castile. Without so much that people got into his grave and hanged buried many women
and men in different parts of the kingdom, and everywhere were crying for an entire year and
is shorn of most of the women, putting all ropes esparto, and finish the year, came to make
their reputations. And what they say they used to I do not want to because they are nations,
and the Christians Quest in Cuzco year of fifteen hundred and fifty,
remember what they saw was made by the honors and After years of Inca
Paulo, with it having become Christians, and bring forth what would
in time the reign of former kings, rather than lose their sovereignty.

CAP. LXI .-- Of how he reigned at Cuzco Huayna Capac who was the Inca king dozen.

Dead king was the great Inca Tupac Yupanqui, is understood to make their funeral rites and burial
the use of their elders, with great pomp. And have the apricots, which secretly plotted between
freedom to collect some past and hold it the command of the Incas, and in fact leave with what
they intended, if not for the very quick, which gave the governors of the Inca with people
of mitimaes and captains, they could sustain such a troubled time and had no king, they had
charged last nickel. Huayna Capac not neglected or failed to meet that he must show courage to
keep it that his father worked so hard won. Then it came to making the fast, and the city will
ruling was faithful and loyal. Have not stopped some confusion among the Incas mesmos, because
some children of Tupac Inca, have occurred in other Coya women, wanted to pretend to be [191]
the kingship, but the people who Vian was with Huayna Capac, not consent, but interfered with
the punishment that was done. Finish fasting, Huayna Capac went with tassel very gallant and
dressed, and made the cirimonias used by their past, to which the
name of king wore, and so loud voices they said [192]: Inca Huayna
Capac Zapalla tucuillacta Uya, which means, "Huayna Capac only is
king Øyan unto him all peoples.

"

Huayna Capac was, as they say many Indians saw him and knew of no very great body but bent and
well done, good and very serious face, a few words, many facts was righteous and punished without
restraint. I wanted to be as feared, that night I dreamed of Indians. Ate as they use, and
so lived cycle of women, if you can tell, hear to those who spoke well, and believed very light:
long deprived him of flatterers and flattering, that among them there were plenty, and today
there is no longer, and gave ear to lies, was the reason that many died without guilt. For
the young men who slept meat tempted to their wives or concubines, or with which they were in
the temple of the sun, then sent them to kill to them, and to punish them equally. For those who
punished him by riots and mutinies, deprived of estates, giving them to others, from other causes,
was punishment .-- Many people only desto conceal his father, especially the women, that when
he took one with them, young men said they were .-- His mother of Huayna Capac, leading lady,
wife and sister who was Inca Tupac Yupanqui, called Mama Ocllo say that was of great prudence,
and warned her son that she saw many things to do to Tupac Inca, and loved him so much that
he begged not to go to Quito and to Chile, until she was dead, and so, do you have that pleasure
and obey his command, was at Cuzco without leave until she died and was buried with grand pomp, getting
in his grave many treasures and fine clothes and their wives and servants. The treasures of the
Incas more deaths and estates, which called Chaco, everything was entirely from the first,
and none dared to spend and do not touch because they did not have wars between and needs the money
hobiese of remedy, for where we believe there are great treasures in the bowels of the earth lost, and
so will be forever, if perchance, one, building or doing something
else, do not bump into something much there.

CAP. LXII .-- How Huayna Capac left Cuzco and what he did.

Huayna Capac had ordered Paresce before him to the chief lords of natural provinces, and while
his court full of them, he married his sister Chimbo Ocllo and therefore were big parties, leaving
the crying for the death of Tupac Inca were done. And finished, he ordered him to go aside up
to fifty thousand men of war with whom I wanted to go together to visit the provinces of his
kingdom. As commanded, stood by the work, and left Cuzco with more pomp and authority than his
father, for the litter would be so rich, to the assertions of those who carried the king on his shoulders,
had not price of the precious stones so large and many who were in them, without the gold that
Heran made.

And it was through the provinces of Xaquixaguana and Andaguaylas, and associates of the Soras
and Lucanas [193] where embassies sent to many parts of the plains and mountains, and was answered
Dell and others, with great presents and offerings.

He returned from those places to Cuzco, where he was understood to make big sacrifices the sun
and those who had more gods, which were favorable to the day I wanted do, and gave great gifts
to the idols of the buried treasures, and knew of the liars, by the
said of demons, or because they invented it, it had to happen prosperously
in days I wanted to do, and would return to Cuzco with great honor
and profit.

This finish in many parts of people came with their guns and captains, by his order, and housed in the
city were provided.

In the building of the fortress was understood, while the styling for this day none reported. In
the plaza of Cuzco was the grand chain of gold, and there was great dancing and drinking; and,
next to the stone of the war, were named captains and bossy, as his custom; and ordering, Huayna
Capac had a parliament, well ordered and said with vehement words, on it were loyal and those
who were with him, as those who remained. Responded that of service not be leaving, which
gave the loo and I hope to make large grants. And being rigged for the day what was needed,
left Cuzco with everyone of war who had gathered, and a big road, so proud as today Paresce,
all here because of what we see and walk by him, walked towards the Collao, showing the provinces
have passed in just the great services rendered him, for they say that It said that the Incas
everything they owe. Understood to know what gave him tribute, and possibility of the province
collected many women, the most beautiful that could be found; Dellas
took for himself, and others gave to his captains and private, the
others were placed on the temple of the sun and stored there.

Entering the Collao, brought him realize that he had large herds of cattle, and how many loads
of fine wool mill were taking a year to those that made the clothes for your home and service.
On the island of Titicaca came in and ordered great sacrifices. In Chuquiabo [194], ordered Indians
were shelves with their suppliers to take gold metal with the order and regiment has been eScript.
Going forward, he ordered the Charcas and other nations to the Chichas bring forth out large
amount of silver pastes, which are taken to Cuzco on your own, without nothing missing; transport
some mitimaes of a party to another, although there were days that were accommodated; ordered
that all work and no loose, because they said the land where there were lazy, did not think anything
but how to find scandals and corrupt honesty women. He went, ordered to build inns and places,
giving his hand the trace; terms distributed to many provinces and known limit, so that, for
aventajallo not should come to blows. His warriors, though much, was so adjusted, that did not come
out the real one step, as they went, the natives provided what is necessary so dutifully, that
was what was left to what was spent. In some places built bathing and other reserves, and the
deserts were great houses. Inca quel everywhere wrong, he had done such things, it is admiration
count.

When they wandered punished without missing ignore anything and pander to those who served
him well.

Sort these things and went from the provinces subjective agora to the Villa de la Plata, and at Tucuman
[195] sent people to war captains to the Chiriguanos, but do not was good, because turned and fled.
Moreover, towards the South Sea, sent more people other captains, to that dominated the valleys
and villages of all his father could not conquer. He was walking with all his people towards Chile,
putting an end to tame, he went, people he had. He spent much work
for the wilds and the snow was a lot of them fell; awnings had to
be guarescer and many yanaconas and women of service. For all these
snow was becoming the way, or was done, and very clean, and posts
made by him</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>