<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>206938</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22162</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> ¿La luz hermosa que reverbera en el horizonte es algo más que
una vibración de la materia? Ese pájaro que hiende los aires y se precipita en el agua para
atrapar un desdichado pez y devorarlo, ¿qué misterio guarda dentro de su organismo? ¿Yo mismo
soy otra cosa más que una expresión individual de la fuerza que anima a todos los seres del
Universo?

Pero cuando estos pensamientos, horribles siempre, le apretaban como las cuerdas de un potro,
se le hacían irresistibles, era cuando le acometían al tiempo de ejercer alguna función de
su sagrado ministerio. Si al celebrar el santo sacrificio de la misa o dar la absolución a
un penitente cruzaba por su espíritu una de estas ideas negras, sentía la misma impresión que
si le atenazasen el cerebro con un hierro candente, le asaltaba una congoja que le dejaba paralizado.
Pensaba morirse. Lo deseaba ardientemente por librarse de aquel suplicio.

Un día le avisaron para llevar el Viático a un caserío próximo a la villa. Como era preciso
caminar algún tiempo a campo traviesa, fue sin campanilla ni convocar a los fieles. Salió solo
con el sacristán, la bolsa de los corporales colgada al cuello y en ella la Sagrada Forma.
El camino ceñía a trechos la orilla de la mar. Fascinado como siempre por la inmensidad del
océano, distrajo su atención del misterio inefable que llevaba sobre su pecho, dejó de balbucir
oraciones y entregó su pensamiento a las mismas meditaciones que noche y día le embargaban
hacía tiempo. Los rayos del sol desparramados sobre los cristales del agua le impulsaron a
considerar la acción suprema, omnipotente de este astro sobre la vida terrestre. Él es quien
la ha creado, quien la sostiene, quien la renueva. La flor le debe su perfume, la fiera su
agilidad y su instinto sanguinario, nuestra alma sus impresiones más dulces o terribles. El
sol es el padre de todo, del amor y del odio. Consideró después que la vida no es más que un
dinamismo inmenso en cuyo seno se trasforman las fuerzas formidables de la física y de la química.
Todos los seres de la tierra, hombres, animales, plantas, están íntimamente ligados. La vida
de todos ellos es una misma, y esta vida universal no es otra cosa que un incesante cambio
de materias. Un movimiento universal arrastra a los átomos, como a los mundos. Mil ondulaciones
se entrecruzan en la atmósfera, mil fuerzas se combinan, el calor y la luz, la afinidad y el
magnetismo se unen en los misterios del mundo vegetal y mineral. Todos los seres están constituidos
de las mismas moléculas, que pasan sucesiva e indiferentemente de uno a otro, de modo que nada
les pertenece en propiedad. Nuestro cuerpo se renueva de tal modo que al cabo de cierto tiempo
no poseemos ya un solo gramo del cuerpo material que poseíamos antes. Este movimiento de renovación
se opera en cada uno de los animales, en cada una de las plantas. Los millones de seres que
habitan la superficie del globo viven en mutuo cambio de organismos. La molécula de oxígeno
que ahora respiro fue ayer respirada por uno de estos árboles que bordan el camino. La molécula
de carbono que arde en uno de estos montoncitos de hoja seca que sirven para abonar la tierra,
quizá haya ardido ayer en los pulmones de un héroe. Quizá en una de esas conchas de ostras
que yacen adheridas a estas peñas se esconda el fósforo que formaba las fibras más preciosas
del cerebro de Jesucristo...

Sintió dentro de su ser algo que se desgarra y cae. Había olvidado por completo que llevaba
consigo el cuerpo divino del Redentor. Le pareció una cosa tan extraña, tan fuera de la realidad
eterna que veía y palpaba, que imaginó estar soñando. Y sin saber de qué antro oscuro de su
ser venían, le acometieron unas ganas feroces, impías, de soltar la carcajada. ¿Qué comedia
era aquélla? Un poco de harina amasada y tostada ayer por el ama de D. Miguel se trasformó
por arte mágico en la persona de Jesucristo, un ser que desapareció de entre los vivos hace
diez y nueve siglos. ¿Esas leyes soberanas, sublimes de la Naturaleza, quedarán violadas porque
unos cuantos insectos de este microscópico planeta reunidos en concilio lo decreten? Separó
los ojos del mar y los fijó en el sacristán, que corría delante silbando a su perro, que se
escapaba detrás de unas gallinas. ¡Qué reverencia la de aquel hombre, llevando a su lado al
Dios de los cielos, al Creador de todas las cosas! Y la carcajada subía del pecho cada vez
con más ímpetu, llegaba a la garganta, tocaba en los labios, estaba a punto de estallar. Un
extraño temblor le hizo dar diente con diente; sintió la frente bañada por un sudor frío; se
le turbó repentinamente la vista, y cayó al suelo sin conocimiento. Cuando lo recobró, estaba
en brazos del sacristán y dos o tres labriegos que por allí andaban. Le habían bañado la cara
con agua fría, le abrieron la sotana y le quitaron el alzacuello. Uno le echaba el humo del
cigarro a la nariz. La bolsa de los corporales con el cuerpo del divino Redentor yacía sobre
la paredilla de un prado. El P. Gil se apresuró a recogerla, se la colgó de nuevo al cuello,
y después de orar un instante hincado de rodillas, siguió su camino sin separar los ojos del suelo.

IX

Su confesor, hasta que le retiraron las licencias, había sido D. Miguel. Se confesaban mutuamente,
como acontece entre los clérigos. Con él fue con quien comunicó primero sus dudas. El viejo
cabecilla quedó más sorprendido que escandalizado de ellas. Le parecían cosa tan insustancial
que no merecía la pena de fijar mucho tiempo la atención. Los dogmas eran para él como las
leyes físicas de la gravedad, la impenetrabilidad, etc. Se contaba con ellos sin pensar en
su existencia. Todo el drama conmovedor de la pasión y muerte de Jesús lo miraba el párroco
de Peñascosa en el fondo como una especie de romanticismo que sirve de acompañamiento obligado
a la verdadera religión. Ésta consistía en la misa, los responsos, el rezo del día, el rosario,
la abstinencia de carne en los días de vigilia, y sobre todo en los derechos parroquiales,
que tal vez juzgaba simultáneos con el acto de la Creación. No se paraba, pues, en analizar
y desvanecer las dudas de su excusador. «Anda adelante.--No hagas caso.--¡Pataratadas!--Déjate
estar.--¡Otra te pego!--¿Cómo no había de resucitar al tercero día, majadero? ¿No ves que lo
dice San Juan y San Mateo y San Marcos?» Éstos eran los consuelos que ordinariamente le prodigaba.

Nuestro sacerdote unas veces se entristecía con ellos, pero otras se confortaba pensando que
no debía de estar tan condenado y maldito cuando D. Miguel tomaba sus terribles dudas con tanta
calma. Cuando a éste le retiraron las licencias no tuvo más remedio que buscar otro confesor.
Convencido de la hostilidad con que le miraban D. Narciso, D. Melchor y D. Joaquín, no quiso
desahogar con ninguno de ellos su conciencia, aunque bien sabía que en el tribunal de la penitencia
nada tienen que hacer las simpatías o las antipatías. Fue a dar con un joven capellán, más
joven aún que él, recién llegado del seminario. Era hijo de un carpintero de la villa, tan
tímido y encogido que apenas sabía saludar, feliz de verse elevado sobre su antigua condición,
tributando un respeto sin límites a todas las grandezas del cielo y a todas las pequeñeces
de la tierra. Éste quedó vivamente impresionado con la confesión del P. Gil, y desde luego
trató de convencerle de que todo aquello venía del demonio y que no había otro remedio más
que ponerle la cruz y darse buenas disciplinas, rezar y ayunar mucho. Por espíritu de humildad
y obediencia, el excusador hizo lo que su confesor le mandaba, secretamente persuadido, sin
embargo, de que no adelantaría nada. Ya antes había intentado estos medios, sin resultado.
Las dudas seguían atormentándole; se le ofrecían cada vez más crueles, más imponentes. El tímido
capellán pasaba un rato muy amargo cada vez que le confesaba; temblaba y se azoraba como si
le sucediese una desgracia: tanto padecía y tales temores le asaltaban, no se sabe de qué,
que poco a poco fue excusándose de oírle en confesión y concluyó por negarse en absoluto.

Entonces se le ocurrió ir a ver a D. Restituto, párroco de una de las aldeas inmediatas a Peñascosa,
hombre que pasaba entre sus compañeros por avisado, prudente y aficionado a los libros. Decíase
que tenía una gran biblioteca y que en su juventud había hecho en Lancia ejercicios brillantísimos
a una de las prebendas de la catedral, y que no se la dieron porque el obispo la tenía reservada
para un sobrino. Don Restituto, herido por la injusticia se había retirado a aquel curato rural,
y nunca más quiso salir de él para intentar nueva contienda. Si continuó dedicado al estudio
de la teología o pagó en ella el desaire que había recibido, no se sabe con certeza. Gustábale,
sí, cuando alguna fiesta o funeral le reunía con sus compañeros, mostrar erudición y excederles
en ingenio y sutileza para defender cualquier proposición; pero los curas de las parroquias
inmediatas todos eran moralistas, esto es, ninguno había estudiado la carrera lata de teología
más que él. Pocas gracias que los arrollase en las disputas de sobremesa. Por lo demás, D.
Restituto llevaba tanta labranza y estaba tan interesado en ella, que no debía de tener mucho
tiempo, ni humor tampoco, para profundizar en la Dogmática ni en la Patrología.

Nuestro acongojado presbítero salió una tarde, después de comer, y encaminó sus pasos hacia
la aldea donde moraba el teólogo. Le conocía bastante, pero no le trataba con intimidad. Estaba
apartada la aldea como media legua. El camino era vario y pintoresco: callejas estrechas con
altos setos de zarzal, trozos de bosque, vereditas entre maizales y senderos al través de los
prados. A la entrada de una garganta, sobre una vega de maíz y teniendo detrás algunas praderas
deliciosas, estaba asentado el principal caserío de la parroquia. La iglesia y la casa rectoral
estaban un buen trecho más allá, en una angostura sombría y húmeda. Todo dormía en el silencio
más completo cuando el joven sacerdote llegó. Las gallinas picoteaban en la calle delante de
la casa; un gato rabón se lavaba la cara sentado sobre la paredilla de la huerta, y un mastín
desorejado dormía de bruces sobre la tabla del hórreo vecino de la casa. Este mastín fue el
encargado de romper la paz de aquel paraje, alzándose iracundo contra el advenedizo, ladrando
con un grito ronco, apagado, testimonio de su decrepitud. El P. Gil detuvo el paso, y comenzó
a decir en tono dulce y persuasivo:

--¡Toma, toma! ¡Quis, quis!

¡Que si quieres! El mastín, viendo al recién llegado achicarse, se creció horriblemente. ¡Guau,
guau! gritó, buscando el registro más feroz y amenazador que pudo hallar en su pecho. Al mismo
tiempo clavaba una mirada de exterminio en el presbítero y avanzaba, aunque con cierta cautela,
hacia él. Éste, aterrado por aquellos ladridos salvajes, dio tres o cuatro pasos atrás y extendió
el brazo con el paraguas, que traía para quitarse el sol, hacia adelante. «¡Paraguas! El recurso
de los cobardes,» debió pensar el mastín. Y se encrespó de tal modo ante aquel ultraje, que
no lo hubiera pasado bien el clérigo a no salir a la puerta una vieja chillando:

--¡Cuco! ¡Cuco! ¡Aquí, Cuco! ¡Fuera, Cuco! ¡Maldito perro! ¡Aquí!... ¡Aquí! ¡Ven aquí!

El perro vaciló un instante, dejó de ladrar y mostró bastante claramente la resolución de volverse
otra vez a dormir como si no hubiera pasado nada; pero la vieja no se dio por satisfecha; exigía
un acto de sumisión.

--¡Aquí, Cuco! ¡Aquí, ahora mismo!

El Cuco bajó la cabeza humildemente y emprendió hacia ella una marcha lenta, penosísima, como
si el camino estuviera erizado de peligros.

--¡Aquí! ¡Venga usted aquí!

«Me trata de usted, ¡malísimo!» se dijo el perro, a quien no hacían efecto las pompas y vanidades.
Y avanzó con mayores precauciones aún, asegurando bien la pezuña a cada paso que daba, meneando
el rabo de un modo vertiginoso.

--¡Aquí! ¡Aquí!--seguía gritando la vieja.

Por fin, a una velocidad máxima de seis pasos por minuto, llegó el Cuco a su destino. La vieja
le cogió por la parte de oreja que le quedaba y dio tres o cuatro tirones con fuerza. El perro
lanzó un aullido de dolor. Luego le cogió por la otra, y otros tantos tirones. Mayor y más
triste aullido aún. Cumplidos sus deberes con la justicia de la tierra, el mastín se retrajo
de nuevo hacia la tabla del hórreo, no sin lanzar por lo bajo algunas imprecaciones y blasfemias.
Esta escena se repetía unas cuantas veces al día, siempre que alguna persona sospechosa, como
ahora, llegaba con propósitos hostiles a la rectoral. El Cuco deploraba en su fuero interno
que no le hubieran rapado mejor las orejas.

--Buenas tardes, D. Gil--dijo la vieja, cambiando súbito la expresión colérica por otra sonriente,
melosísima, dando muestras de que le conocía.

El P. Gil, a quien no sucedía otro tanto, respondió muy cortésmente y preguntó por D. Restituto.

--El señor cura debe de estar hacia el establo. Pase usted, D. Gil. Iré a llamarlo.

--No hay necesidad: yo mismo iré a buscarlo. ¿El establo está aquí?...

--Sí, señor; aquí detrás de la casa.

Dio la vuelta a toda ella el sacerdote, subió algunos pasos por una calleja sucia, y se encontró
con una misérrima fábrica hecha de piedras del río sin labrar apenas, con una puerta desvencijada.
Estaba cerrada, y a nadie vio por allí delante. Iba a dejar aquel sitio y volverse a la casa,
cuando detrás del establo oyó ruido de voces. Fuese hacia allá, y halló, en efecto, a don Restituto,
sorprendiéndose no poco del traje y la situación en que se le apareció.

El anciano cura vestía unos calzones anchos de pana, remendados, como los que gastan los paisanos
por aquella tierra; traía en los pies almadreñas con escarpines de paño burdo, chaqueta lustrosa
por el uso, y camisa de lienzo hilado por el ama, sin alzacuello ni cosa que lo valga. Era
el traje de un labrador, sin quitar ni poner nada. Pero lo que hacía verdaderamente peregrino
y estrafalario el atavío es que en la cabeza traía un bonete viejo y grasiento.

El P. Gil quedó asombrado de aquella figura, y más asombrado, cuando advirtió la ocupación
a que el párroco se entregaba. Estaba, con una rodilla hincada en tierra, desollando un becerro.
Le ayudaba en la operación el criado. Tenían al animal extendido entre los dos, la mayor parte
de él en carne viva ya. Volvió la cabeza D. Restituto al sentir pasos, y hallándose con su
joven compañero, se puso en pie y vino hacia él con las manos ensangrentadas empuñando un enorme
cuchillo.

--¿Qué milagro es éste, amigo? ¡El futuro cura de Peñascosa se digna hacernos una visita!...
Mira, no te doy la mano, porque ya ves cómo la tengo. Bien de salud, ¿verdad?... Por aquí tampoco
hay novedad.

D. Restituto trataba de tú, familiarmente, a todos los clérigos más jóvenes que él desde la
primera entrevista. Cuando Gil le hubo explicado el motivo de su viaje, mostró cierta extrañeza,
pero se apresuró a responderle:

--Bueno, bueno. Yo voy a concluir en seguida. Vete a casa, y espérame.

Pero el joven manifestó deseos de ir a la iglesia.

--¿A la iglesia?--dijo sorprendido. Entre ellos era costumbre confesarse en casa.--Está bien.
No hay inconveniente. Pide al ama la llave, y espérame allí. No tardaré.

¡Pluguiera a Dios que hubiese tardado más! Y sobre todo, pluguiérale que hubiera tenido tiempo
a lavarse bien. Porque el teólogo despedía de sí un vaho de matadero que derribaba. Mientras
duró la confesión, y duró bastante, el P. Gil apenas pudo pensar en otra cosa. Sentíase asfixiado
por aquel olor nauseabundo; acudíanle unas congojas y sudores que estuvieron a punto varias
veces de privarle del sentido. Don Restituto sintió verdadera satisfacción en poder sacar a
relucir su antigua batería de proposiciones teológicas. A cada duda que su atribulado penitente
le ofrecía, contestaba victoriosamente con un texto latino. Como el veterano descuelga con
gozo sus armas a la señal de guerra, así el viejo opositor a la lectoralía de Lancia descolgó
de su memoria los textos enmohecidos ya de Perronne y de Balmes. ¿Cómo dudar de la inmortalidad
del alma, cuando ésta es una cosa simple, y las cosas simples no pueden descomponerse? ¿Quién
se atreve a imaginar que la Iglesia católica puede algún día perecer, cuando están ahí sangrando
las palabras de Jesucristo: «Las puertas del infierno no prevalecerán (non pr?valebunt?)» ¿Cómo
se ha de dar más crédito a la palabra de los hombres que a la de Dios? Pues qué, ¿la Divina
Sabiduría no ha dicho: «Yo para esto nací y para esto vine al mundo, para dar testimonio a
la verdad?» Y este testimonio ¿no está bien claro y bien patente en las obras visibles que
exceden al poder natural, por ejemplo, en la curación de los enfermos, en la resurrección de
los muertos y en otros admirables milagros llevados a cabo por Nuestro Señor Jesucristo y por
los Santos Apóstoles?

El P. Gil recibió la absolución, prometiendo no ser más demente ni idiota; así juzgaba don
Restituto al que dudaba de las verdades reveladas por angélico ministerio. Poco después de
besar aquella mano no bien purgada de la sangre del becerro, y cuando se hubo levantado para
rezar ante un altar la penitencia, nuestro presbítero se sintió indispuesto. Tuvo que salir
inmediatamente de la iglesia, acometido de violentas náuseas. En el pórtico devolvió toda la
comida. Llevole a casa el cura, y quiso curarle con una taza de salvia, remedio supremo que
empleaba contra todas las dolencias que afligen al género humano; pero su joven compañero,
que sabía a qué atenerse sobre su enfermedad, rehusó obstinadamente toda medicación. El párroco
entonces pasó a mostrarle la huerta, en la cual tenía cifrado tanto orgullo como en la profundidad
de sus conocimientos teológicos. Estaba llena de árboles frutales y legumbres. No se veía una
flor ni un arbusto de adorno. Desde allí pasaron a un vasto prado, donde tenía unos cuantos
operarios alzando pared. D. Restituto comenzó a darles instrucciones, aprobó algunas cosas,
reprobó otras, olvidándose por completo de su huésped. Uno de los operarios le participó que
el molino había parado porque el hijo de Cosme había desviado el agua más arriba para secar
el cauce del riachuelo y pescar las anguilas. D. Restituto se enfureció y anunció su propósito
de demandar a Cosme y pedirle indemnización de daños y perjuicios. De él no se burlaba nadie;
estaba resuelto a hacer que se respetase su propiedad. Desde allí se corrieron a los maizales,
y el párroco mostró a su compañero con extremado gozo el estado magnífico de las plantas. El
agua había venido muy a tiempo, pero más que al agua se debía a la gran cantidad de abono que
había echado.

--Tú dirás: ¿dónde podrá hacer D. Restituto tanto estiércol para una tierra como ésta, de quince
días de bueyes? Voy a explicártelo. Yo, aunque tengo nueve cabezas de ganado, no podría abonar
ni la mitad de la tierra que llevo. ¡Aquí del intelectus! En todas las parroquias, como tú
sabes bien, hay una porción de pobretes, a los cuales no es posible sacarles un cuarto ni por
bautizos ni por matrimonios ni por nada. Pues bien, a estas calamidades vivientes les obligo
a echar de vez en cuando delante de sus casas (vulgo pocilgas) una buena cantidad de hoja seca
o tojo. Con el agua y el paso de los transeúntes y el estiércol de las reses que cruzan se
convierte al cabo de algún tiempo en abono. Cuando ya está bien podrido me lo traen y voy formando
montón hasta que llega el tiempo de distribuirlo por la tierra. ¿Qué tal?

Desde allí saltaron a una heredad de prado. D. Restituto, en cuanto se vio en ella, dejó escapar
una risita aguda y burlona, que hizo levantar la cabeza a su joven compañero y mirarle con
curiosidad.

--Este es el prado del molino de abajo... el prado del molino de abajo, ya sabrás... ¿Cómo?
¿no sabes la historia de este prado? Pues ha corrido mucho por la villa... Pertenecía a los
mansos de la parroquia, y había quedado trasconejado cuando la venta de todos ellos. Yo lo
llevaba, y nadie en la parroquia se atrevía a denunciarlo. Pero había aquí un tabernero rico
llamado Lino (que ya reventó, a Dios gracias, el año pasado), y este Lino le tenía muchas ganas
al prado. Al fin dio el soplo en la administración, guardando la mano, porque no quería ponerse
mal conmigo, y lo sacaron a subasta. Dos días antes de hacerse, vino por acá el muy hipócrita
y me dijo: «Señor cura, voy a hacer postura al prado del molino de abajo, pero si usted lo
quiere me quedo en casa.» El tunante trataba de sonsacarme la cantidad que yo pensaba ofrecer.
«No, no lo quiero; puedes rematarlo cuando gustes,» le contesté. El hombre, viendo que yo no
iba al remate, y sabiendo que ningún vecino estaba en situación de tirarle, se las prometía
muy felices. Y mandó a Lancia a un primo hermano suyo. Pero a éste le fui a tropezar camino
de Peñascosa, y le hablé muy al caso, representándole el pecado en que incurría rematando bienes
de la Iglesia, le prometí darle en arriendo el prado, y le puse cuarenta duros en la mano.
¿Qué había de hacer el hombre? Fue a Lancia, lo remató y me lo traspasó a mí acto continuo...
¡Vaya una risa que se armó en el pueblo, amigo! Lino enfermó de rabia, y en cuanto se le presentó
ocasión, que fue al cabo de dos meses, viniendo de una romería, le pegó una puñalada a su primo...
¡Pero, anda, que buenos cuartos le costó la tal puñaladita! No lo hizo con diez mil reales.

Como ya el sol declinaba, después de haberle enseñado un lagar, que acababa de construir para
la sidra, D. Restituto llevó de nuevo a su penitente a casa y le convidó a chocolate. Pero
el excusador no se sentía aún bien. Además tenía prisa. Rehusó todo convite y emprendió el
camino de Peñascosa. El cura le acompañó un buen trecho.

Fuera ya de sus fincas y comprendiendo por el continente reflexivo del excusador de Peñascosa
que su ánimo seguía embargado por pensamientos serios, D. Restituto quiso volver a la carga,
aunque le pareciese sobradamente demostrado que todas las dudas de su compañero no eran más
que bombas de jabón, las cuales deshace con un soplo cualquiera que haya saludado siquiera
la Sagrada Teología.

--Debes fijarte, querido--le decía con protección ilimitada,--que las verdades de la fe no
son contrarias a la razón, sino que están sobre ella. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09332</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>113929</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19714</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Is the beautiful light that reverberates on the horizon is more
than a vibration of matter? That bird that cleaves the air and plunges into the water catch
and devour a hapless fish, what mystery stored inside your body? How do I treat I am nothing
more than an individual expression of the force that animates all beings Universe?

But when these thoughts, always horrible, I squeezed as the strings of a colt made it irresistible
when he was rushing to time exercise any function of their sacred ministry. If we celebrate
the Holy Sacrifice of the Mass or give absolution crossed a penitent spirit of these dark
thoughts, I felt the same impression if you gripped the brain with a hot iron, he assaulted a
heartbreak that left him paralyzed. I thought dying. I longed to get rid of that ordeal.

One day he was told to bring Viaticum to a village near the town. As needed some time walking
across the fields, was no bell and summon the faithful. Left alone with the clerk, the body bag
slung over her neck and the Sacred. The road stretches clung to the edge of the sea. As always
fascinated by the immensity of ocean, distracted his attention from the ineffable mystery that
wore on his chest, stopped stammer prayers and gave his thoughts to the same meditations that night
and day was upon him long time. The sun's rays scattered on the glass of water compelled him
to action considered supreme, omnipotent in this star on Earth life. It is he who has created
the observer, who renewed. The flower owes its perfume, its fierce agility and bloodthirsty
instinct, our sweetest soul impressions or terrible. The Sun is the father of all, love and
hate. Then considered that life is more than a immense dynamism within which transform the
formidable forces of physics and chemistry. All beings on earth, humans, animals, plants, are
closely linked. Life of these is a single, universal life and this is not nothing but a constant change
materials. A universal movement drags the atoms, as the worlds. Thousand ripples intersect in
the atmosphere, a thousand forces combine, heat and light, the affinity and magnetism join
the mysteries of the vegetable and mineral. All beings are made of the same molecules, which pass
successively and regardless of each other, so nothing property belongs to them. Our body is
renewed so that after a certain time and we have not an ounce of body material that we had before.
This renewal movement operating in each of the animals in each of the plants. The millions who
inhabit the surface of the globe live in mutual exchange of organisms. The oxygen molecule now
breathed breath was yesterday one of the trees lining the road. The molecule carbon burning in one
of these piles of dried leaves used to fertilize the soil, may have burned yesterday in the
lungs of a hero. Perhaps one of those oyster shells lying attached to these rocks to hide the
match that was most precious fibers the brain of Jesus Christ ...

He felt within himself something that tears and falls. I had completely forgotten that led
him the divine body of the Redeemer. It seemed a thing so strange, so out of touch eternal saw
and touched, she imagined must be dreaming.

And without knowing what his dark hole be coming, we undertook a fierce desire, wicked, laugh.
What comedy was it? A little flour mixed and toast yesterday's housekeeper D. Miguel was transformed
if by magic in the person of Jesus Christ, a being who disappeared from among the living does
nineteen centuries. "These sovereign laws, sublime nature, be raped because few insects in
this microscopic world council meeting in the decree? Separated eyes from the sea and set
in the sexton, who ran before whistling to his dog, which escaped after some chickens. What
reverence of the man, leading his side to God of heaven, the Creator of all things! And the laughter
rose from the chest when with more energy, reaching to the throat, he played on his lips, was
about to explode. A tremor caused him to miss teeth chattering, and he felt his forehead bathed
in a cold sweat, is troubled him suddenly in sight, and fell unconscious. When he recovered,
was sexton's arms and two or three peasants who roamed around. She had bathed her face with
cold water, opened his robe and removed his collar. One of them threw smoke cigar nose. The
body bag with the body lying on the divine Redeemer the boundary wall of a meadow. Fr Gil was
quick to pick her up, slung it back to the neck, and after a moment to pray on his knees, and
went on without removing your eyes from the ground.

IX

Her confessor, until he withdrew the licenses had been D. Miguel.
Mutually confessed, as happens among the clergy.

With whom he was first informed his doubts.

The old leader was more surprised than shocked them. Thing seemed as insubstantial not worth much
time fixing the attention. The dogmas were to him as physical laws of gravity, the inscrutability,
etc. We were relying on them without thinking its existence. All the moving drama of passion
and death of Jesus looked at the pastor of rocks in the background as a kind of romanticism
that serves as accompaniment required to the true religion. This was the Mass, the responses,
the prayer of the day, the rosary, Abstinence from meat on days of wakefulness, especially
in parochial rights, maybe judged simultaneous with the act of creation. There he stood, then,
to analyze and dispel the doubts of his excuse. "Go ahead .-- .-- Ignore Patarata! - Be be .--
Another hit you! - How not had to rise the third day, fool? Can not you see what says San
Juan and San Mateo and San Marcos? "These were the consolations usually lavished on him.

Our priest was sad at times with them, but others are comforted thinking should not be so condemned
and cursed when D. Miguel took the terrible doubt so calm. When he
withdrew the licenses had no choice but to seek another confessor.

Convinced of the hostility with which he watched D. Narciso, D. Melchior and D. Joaquin declined
with any of them vent their conscience, but knew that the tribunal of Penance have nothing to do
likes and dislikes. He went to a young chaplain, more he still young, fresh from the seminary.
He was the son of a carpenter in the village, so timid and shrunken who could barely say hello,
happy to be elevated above its former condition, pay an unlimited respect for all the grandeur of heaven
and all the little things land. This was vividly impressed with the confession of P. Gil,
and of course tried to convince him that everything came from the devil and that there was
no other choice but to put the cross and be good subjects, to pray and fast a lot. In a spirit
of humility and obedience, the toilet did as his confessor he sent secretly persuaded, without
But that would not advance anything. Even before the media had tried, without success. Doubts
were tormenting him, offered him more and more cruel, more imposing. The timid chaplain spent
a little bitter every time I confessed, shivering and bewildered as if calamity befalls him, both
suffering and such fears assailed him, who knows what, little by little was apologizing to
hear him in confession and concluded by refusing at all.

Then he thought of going to see D. Restituto, pastor of one of the villages Peñascosa immediate,
man walking between his companions advised, prudent and bookish. Was said I had a great library
and that in his youth had done most brilliant exercises Lancia one
of the perks of the cathedral, and that did not receive one because
the bishop had reserved for a nephew.

Don Restituto, hurt by the injustice he had retired to rural parish, and never wanted to leave him to
try new contest. If continued toward the study of theology or she paid in the slight he had received,
it is not known with certainty. He liked, yes, when a party or funeral he met with his companions,
show scholarship and to exceed in wit and subtlety to defend any proposition, but the priests of
the parishes immediate all were moralists, that is, none had studied theology can race more than
him. Few thank the landslide in disputes desktop. Moreover, D. Restituto farm was so far and
was so interested in it, I should not have much time or humor, either, to deepen the dogmatic or
the Patrologia.

Our anguished priest came one evening after dinner, and directed his steps towards the village
where dwelt the theologian. I knew a lot, but not dealt with privacy. Was remote village half
a league. The road was varied and picturesque with narrow streets high hedges of bramble, pieces
of wood, vereditas between the cornfields and trails through meadows.

At the entrance to a gorge, on a plain of corn and taking back some grassland delicious, was
seated the main village of the parish. The church and rectory were a good distance away, in a narrow
dark and wet. All slept in silence most complete when the young priest arrived. Chickens pecked
in the street in front of the house, a Manx cat was washing his face sitting on the boundary
wall of the garden, and a mastiff earless slept face down on the table in the house nearby barn.
The mastiff was responsible for breaking the peace of that place, rising angrily against the upstart,
barking with a hoarse shout, off, witness his decrepitude. Fr Gil stood still, and began to say
sweet tone and persuasive

- Take, take! Quis, quis!

That if you want! The mastiff, watching the newcomer shrink, it grew horribly. Wow, Wow! he shouted,
looking fierce and menacing record he could find in his chest.

At the same time extermination riveting look at the priest and went,
though cautious, to him.

That, terrified by those wild barking, swam three or four steps back and spread the arm with the
umbrella, which brought to remove the sun, forward. "Umbrellas! The appeal of cowards, "he must
have thought the mastiff. And so bristled at this outrage, which I had not had a good cleric not
to leave the door an old screaming:

- Cuckoo! Cuckoo! Here, Cuckoo! Outside, Cuckoo! Damn dog! Here! ... Here! Come here!

The dog hesitated for a moment, stopped barking and was quite clearly
the decision to become back to sleep as if nothing had happened, but
the old woman was satisfied; required an act of submission.

- Here,
Cuckoo!

Here, now!

El Cuco humbly bowed his head toward her and began a slow, excruciating,
as if the path was fraught with danger.

- Here!

Come here!

"I is you, awful!"

Is said the dog, who did not effect the pomps and vanities.

And he advanced with even greater caution, lock the hoof at each step he took, shook the tail of a
rapid mode.

- Here! Here! - Was shouting the old.

Finally, at a maximum speed of six steps per minute, arrived at their destination Cuco. The old
caught him by the left ear and gave him three or four pulls hard. The dog a howl of pain.
Then he took the other, and many other tugs. More and more still sad howl. Fulfilled his duties
with the law of the land, shrank mastiff back to the table in the barn, but not releasing it under
some curses and blasphemies. This scene was repeated a few times a day, provided that any person
suspected as now arrived for purposes hostile to the rectory. El Cuco deplored in their hearts
that had not shaved best ears.

- Afternoon, D. Gil - said the old, angry expression suddenly changing
the other smiling melosísima, showing who knew him.

Fr Gil, who was not happening as much, answered very politely and
asked D. Restituto.

- The priest must be toward the barn.

Come in, D. Gil. I'll call him.

- No need: I will fetch it myself. "The barn is here? ...

- Yes, sir, here behind the house.

He turned it all the priest, went a few steps in a dirty alley, and found a miserable factory made
of uncut stones from the river only, with a rickety door. It was locked, and nobody was there before.
Going to leave that place and come back to home behind the barn when he heard the sound of
voices. He went thither, and found, in fact, Don Restituto, not a little surprised the suit and
the situation in which he appeared.

The old priest was wearing corduroy trousers wide, patched, as they spend the peasants through the
land, wore on her feet clogs with socks of coarse cloth, shiny coat through use, and spinning
linen shirt he loves, without collar or anything like it. Was the costume of a peasant, without
removing it or put anything. But what really made pilgrim and outlandish attire is that the old
head and wore a greasy cap.

Fr Gil was shocked by that figure, and more astonished, when he warned
the occupation that the pastor was delivered.

I was, kneeling on one knee on the ground, skinning a calf. He helped in the operation servant.
The animal had spread between the two, most raw it now. He turned his head D. Restituto steps, feeling,
and being with young fellow stood up and came toward him with bloody
hands clutching a huge knife.

- What miracle is this, man?

The future priest Peñascosa deigns to visit us!

... Look, do not shake hands, because you see how I have it.

Good health, right? ... Not here no novelty.

D. Restituto was you, familiar to all young clerics he from first interview. When Gil had explained
the reason for his trip, showed some surprise, but was quick to respond:

- Well, well. I will close immediately. Go home, and wait.

But the young man expressed a desire to go to church.

- To the church? - Said in surprise. Among them was customary confession at home .-- All right.
No problem. Calls to love the key, and wait there. It will not take.

Would to God that had taken more! And above all, would have had time pluguiérale to wash. For the
theologian dismissed him a whiff of cutting down slaughterhouse. While confession lasted, and lasted
a long time, Fr Gil could hardly think of anything else. He felt suffocated for that foul smell;
acudíanle some worries and sweats that were about several to deprive of sense sometimes. Don
Restituto felt great satisfaction in order to get shine your old battery theological propositions.
Each question his troubled penitent offered him, he answered triumphantly with a Latin text.
As the veteran off-hook with joy their weapons to the signal of war, the old opponent of the
Lancia picked lectoralía of memory texts already Perronne rusty and
Balmes.

How can one doubt of immortality the soul, when it is something simple, and simple things
can not be broken? Who dare to imagine that the Catholic Church may someday die, when there
bleeding Christ's words: "The gates of hell shall not prevail (non pr?valebunt?)" How be given
more credence to the word of men than of God? What! Divine Wisdom has said: "For this I was
born and for this I came into the world, to testify to the truth? "And this testimony is not
is clear and well illustrated in the works visible exceed the natural power, for example, in
healing the sick, the resurrection of the dead and other wonderful miracles performed by Our
Lord Jesus Christ and the Apostles?

Fr Gil received absolution, promising not to be insane or an idiot, so don judged Restituto who
doubted the truths revealed by angelic ministry. Shortly after kissing the hand not well purged
from the blood of the bullock, and when he had risen to praying before an altar of repentance,
our priest fell ill. Had to leave immediately from the church, seized with violent nausea. On
the back porch all food. The priest brought him home, and tried to cure him with a cup of sage,
the supreme remedy used against all the ailments that afflict mankind, but his young companion,
I knew what to expect about your condition, obstinately refused all medication. The pastor then
went on to show the garden, in which encryption was so proud and in depth of theological knowledge.
It was full of fruit trees and vegetables. There was not a flower or ornamental shrub. From
there they went to a vast lawn, where he had a few raising operators wall. D. Restituto began
giving instructions, adopted a number of things failed other, forgetting
all about his guest.

One of the workers took him to the mill had stopped because the son of Cosimo had deviated above
the water to dry the bed of the creek and catch eels. D. Restituto was furious and announced plans
Cosme to sue and ask for damages and losses. Of it is not mocked; was determined to make his
property was respected. From there he ran into the cornfields, and the pastor was a fellow with
extreme joy the great state of plants. The water had come just in time, but most of the water
was due to the large quantity of fertilizer had missed.

- You say: where you can make D. Restituto much manure to a land like this, fifteen days of oxen? I'll
tell you. I, though I have nine heads of cattle, could not pay even
half of the land that I have.

Here's intelectus! In every parish, as you You know, there are a lot of wretches, to whom it is
not possible for them out one quarter or baptisms or marriage or anything. However, these
calamities forced them living to take from time to time outside their
homes (commonly pens) a good amount of dry leaf or gorse.

With water and the passage of pedestrians and cattle manure is crossing becomes after some
time pass. When it is well rotted and I'll bring me forming lot until the time comes to distribute
the land. What?

From there they jumped to an inheritance of meadow. D. Restituto, as it was, let out a sharp, mocking
laugh, he did raise his head to his young companion and look at him curiosity.

- This is the meadow below the mill ... the meadow below the mill, you already know ... How?
Do not you know the history of this field? Well, much has run the town ... Belonged to the meek
of the parish, and had been trasconejado when selling them. I had, and nobody in the parish
dared to denounce him. But here was a rich landlord called Lino (already busted, thank God,
last year), and that he was eager Lino the meadow. At the end gave the breath in the administration,
keeping the hand, not wanting to be wrong with me, and brought it to auction. Two days before done,
came here the very hypocritical and I said, 'Father, I do stand in the meadow below the mill,
but if you I want to stay home. "The rascal probe for the amount I planned to offer. "No, I do
not want, you can top it when you like," I replied. The man, seeing that I went to auction, and knowing
that any neighbor was in a position to throw, they were promised very happy. Lancia Y sent to his
cousin.

But this road trip we went to of rocks, and spoke highly relevant, represents sin incurred goods
topping of the Church, I promised him rent the pasture and put him forty dollars in hand.
What was the man do? It was a Lancia, finished him off and handed it to me to me in the next
breath ... What a laugh that was assembled in the town, buddy!

Lino ill with rabies, and as was presented occasion that was after two months, coming from a
pilgrimage, he stuck a knife to his cousin ... But, go, good rooms that cost him so puñaladita!
He did not do ten thousand.

As the sun went down, after having taught a winery, he had built for
cider, D. Restituto led back to his penitent home and invited him
to chocolate.

But the toilet was still not good. Also in a hurry. Refused all treat and started Peñascosa
way. The priest accompanied him some distance.

Out and understanding
their properties and the continent reflective Peñascosa toilets that
his heart was seized with serious thoughts, D. Restituto wanted to
return to the load though he seemed well established that all doubts
of his companion were only that pumps soap, which breaks with a blow
anyone who has even hailed Sacred Theology.

- You look out, dear
- he said with unlimited protection, - the truths of faith are contrary
to reason, but above it</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>