<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document00354</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>90548</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>791</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El cura de la villa, continuando su errada doctrina, recibió de D. Jacinto Rodriguez
una barra de plata, cuyo valor ascendia á cerca de 2,000 pesos, y una mancerina de oro que
le remitió de las robadas, para que celebrase los sufragios á los europeos asesinados en el
tumulto, contentándose con enterrarlos á todos juntos en un hoyo, y aplicarles algunas misas.
Ninguno de estos ni otros superiores eclesiásticos hizo la menor demostracion para impedir
á los indios violentasen las iglesias: todos consintieron en ello, poseidos del espanto, y
lo que cansó mayor dolor, fué ver que, despues de polutas las iglesias, permitiesen celebrar
el santo y tremendo sacrificio de la misa, enterrando el cura, en el lugar que se hallaba violado,
los cadáveres de los vecinos que morian de enfermedad.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03249</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>16418</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>705</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> The priest of the village, continuing wrong doctrine, received from D. Jacinto Rodriguez
a bar of silver, whose value amounted to about 2,000 pesos, and a gold mancerina he sent the
stolen, that held the vote to the Europeans killed in the tumult, content to bury them all
together in a hole, and apply some mass. None of these or other ecclesiastical superiors made
the slightest demonstration to prevent the Indians broke into the churches, all consented
to it, possessed of fear, and so tired sore, was to see that after the churches polluted,
it can host the holy and tremendous sacrifice of the Mass, the priest buried in the place that
was violated, The bodies of the residents who died of disease.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>