<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05554</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>27276</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22982</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Ciertamente
las obras a que se refieren estas observaciones atinadísimas, dicen poco al puro sentimiento
estético, porque están basadas en la imitación, y sus autores, aunque más o menos hábiles,
carecieron de espíritu propio: mas en cambio, se puede afirmar que por su misma simplicidad
y candor satisfacían perfectamente al fervor religioso que las inspiraba. Las composiciones
de estas pinturas no eran verdaderos cuadros hechos sólo para ornato y gala permanente de habitaciones,
sino pequeños oratorios portátiles, dípticos o trípticos, tablas encharneladas, como se les
nombra en el lenguaje de la época, y estaban todas fundadas en asuntos devotos. Los reyes,
capitanes y grandes señores las llevaban a las guerras, y en sus viajes sufriendo las consiguientes
vicisitudes: lo que hoy estaba en un campamento, mañana se veía en un castillo, y de la ignorancia
o cultura del vencedor dependería siempre su suerte. Este linaje de pinturas debió de generalizarse
extraordinariamente.

En las cámaras y tarbeas de los palacios, alcázares y casas que Isabel I tenía en Aranjuez,
Granada, Sevilla, Toledo, Toro, Tordesillas, Segovia y Medina del Campo, hubo, según consta
del inventario formado a su muerte, al pie de cuatrocientos sesenta cuadros, casi todos de
devoción; y doña Juana la Loca dejó treinta y seis, sobre los que heredó de su madre. La prueba
de que no sólo los monarcas poseían obras de esta índole, está en que muchas de ellas les eran
regaladas, y sus autores debían de ser bien pagados cuando se sabe que Fernando V mandó dar
a Michel Flamenco, pintor que fue de la reina nuestra señora que haya santa gloria, la suma
de 116.666 maravedises, por todo el tiempo que había servido a la reina desde principios del
año 1492 hasta que S. A. finó[6].

[imagen: GALERÍA NACIONAL DE LONDRES

CRISTO ATADO A LA COLUMNA

Fotog. Braun, Clement y Cª]

Carlos I llegó a tener más de seiscientos cuadros: conocido su poder, fácil es colegir los
tesoros que acumularía en los palacios de los Países Bajos, de Italia y de España; sólo su
tía doña Margarita de Austria, le legó más de cien pinturas: ni Francisco I de Francia, ni
Enrique VIII de Inglaterra, llegaron a poseer riqueza parecida. Mas este tesoro ya no se componía
exclusivamente de obras religiosas. El Renacimiento estaba en su apogeo; las auras paganas
despertando el amor a la Naturaleza habían ingerido al arte savia nueva, y a los artistas creyentes
que representaron con placido y sincero misticismo los relatos de los evangelistas, habían
sucedido otros que, inspirándose en los cantos de los poetas gentiles, ponían su genio al servicio
del sensualismo clásico, fingiendo en sus obras, con maravillosa potencia imaginativa, fábulas
eróticas, hazañas de héroes, pasiones de dioses, desnudeces de mujeres, pero estos pintores,
al poner el entendimiento y la mano en la tragedia del Calvario ni aun con la grandiosidad
de la composición y la pompa del color, lograban suplir aquella honda y sincera emoción que
agitó el alma de los fundadores de las escuelas primitivas. El Renacimiento fundado en el estudio
de la antigüedad, fue revolución provechosísima al arte, porque le enseñó a amar la belleza
sin cuidarse de su origen: pero haciendo que prevaleciese la fantasía sobre la piedad, le robó
en general y en particular a la pintura ese algo misterioso e ingenuo independiente de toda
condición externa que seduce y cautiva aun a los adoradores de la forma.

La pintura que durante más de dos siglos había tenido su exclusivo asiento en las iglesias,
se enseñoreó también de los alcázares, varió de índole y hasta cuando decoró templos, los adornó
como si fueran palacios.

No lo permite la extensión de este modesto trabajo, pero conviene fijarse en la acogida que
aquí tuvieron las obras del Renacimiento para observar luego cómo varió su carácter y se modificaron
sus tendencias.

Carlos I debió de ser gran admirador de sus creaciones, aun de aquellas donde más resplandecía
la libre sensualidad del paganismo, pues si bien es cierto que al retirarse a Yuste llevó consigo
gran número de cuadros de devoción, años atrás, según refiere Jusepe Martínez, había mandado
pintar a Ticiano, además de un retrato, unos cuadros de unas poesías, que a no ser tan humanas,
las tuviera por divinas, ¡lastima grande para nuestra religión!

Felipe II, que cuando escribía al mismo Ticiano le llamaba amado nuestro, le encargaba para
sus palacios cuadros como los de Antiope, Venus y Adonis, y Diana y Calixto, de lo cual se
infiere que no era mojigato en materia de arte; y Felipe III y Felipe IV, siguieron reuniendo
obras análogas en Madrid y el Pardo.

Durante este largo período, que abarca todo el siglo XVI, domina ya en España el gusto italiano
en lo referente a los elementos de expresión que animan la obra pictórica: los más ilustres
holandeses, Antonio Moro por ejemplo, sólo son buscados y seguidos como retratistas. En Valencia,
pintan Juan de Juanes y Ribalta; en Andalucía, Luis de Vargas, Alejo Fernández y el divino
Morales. Tomamos de Italia, la escrupulosidad en el estudio de los miembros del cuerpo, la
manera de concebir y disponer el cuadro, el manejo de la luz, los contrastes y armonías del
color, hasta los estilos y procedimientos de la ejecución, pero la tendencia del Renacimiento
a que el arte fuese, ante todo, realización de belleza, ya nacida de los ideales de la mente,
ya contemplada en las obras de la Naturaleza, el criterio amplio y libre hasta la audacia que
florentinos, romanos y venecianos desplegaron en sus frescos y sus lienzos, halló pocos prosélitos
en España.

Los monarcas, a quienes la Iglesia no entorpecía sus gustos personales por pecaminosos que
fuesen, seguían adornando los palacios y casas de recreo con profanidades y mitologías: algunos
grandes señores, hacían lo propio, según se desprende de lo que refieren varios escritores
de aquel tiempo[7]; mas para la mayoría de la nación, el arte fue un mero auxiliar del sentimiento
religioso.

Inútil es que haya quien se obstine en negarlo alegando que además de cuadros devotos, también
se pintaban muchos de otros asuntos. Para persuadirse de lo infundado de esta afirmación, basta
considerar que entre los miles de lienzos del siglo XVII, que se conservan en España, son poquísimos
los que representan episodios históricos o escenas de costumbres, y en cambio es incalculable
el número de los inspirados en el Viejo o el Nuevo Testamento, y en las vidas de los santos:
hasta los floreros se solían disponer de modo que sirvieran de marco a alguna imagen sagrada:
retratos se hicieron en abundancia, pues siempre sobra lo que radica en la vanidad humana,
y no escasean los bodegones, porque muchos artistas tomaban este género por vía de estudio:
de lo que apenas hay rastro, es de la pintura que pudiéramos decir doméstica y familiar. Conocemos
la vida de aquel siglo, por los viajes de los extranjeros, que solían exagerar o mentir; por
los documentos de los archivos, que hablan con seca y desabrida elocuencia; por el teatro,
en que la imaginación es señora; por la novela picaresca, que sólo resucita tipos de una clase
social; por los escritores, que siempre con sentido especialmente devoto, se complacían en
censurar las costumbres, describiéndolas de paso; pero los pinceles tercos en esquivar toda
representación de cosa vulgar y profana, nos dejaron poquísimos datos referentes a la manera
de vivir, los trabajos, oficios, diversiones, casas, habitaciones, muebles y ropas de aquellos
caballeros y soldados, clérigos y estudiantes, mercaderes y mendigos, damas y aventureras,
cómicas y beatas, dueñas y criadas, cuyo abigarrado conjunto conocemos sólo moralmente, gracias
a Cervantes y Quevedo, Tirso y Lope, Zabaleta y Salas Barbadillo, porque los pintores limitados
a la representación convencional de lo sagrado despreciaban lo profano.

Indudablemente sentían amor intenso a la belleza real, lo que se prueba observando cómo daban
a las figuras santas tal aspecto de verdad, que lo que perdían en alteza, lo ganaban en verosimilitud,
mas no era posible que nada de lo que les rodeaba a diario les pareciese objeto digno de emplear
en ello su observación y sus pinceles, cuando la voz de la Iglesia, tan temida y respetada
entonces, les decía que la vida terrena y transitoria, es cosa baja y despreciable en comparación
de la celestial eterna. Tal es, en mi humilde entender, la causa, de que la pintura española
de aquella época no sirva, como sirve la de los países del Norte, para completar el estadio
de la Patria, reflejando las costumbres que es un modo de reflejar el alma de la nacionalidad.

En Italia, tampoco logró la pintura de costumbres gran importancia, porque allí el arte, gracias
a la cultura del Papado, adquirió carácter eminentemente monumental: mas a falta y con ventaja
de no poder representar escenas humanas y vulgares dispusieron los artistas del campo hermoso
e ilimitado de la Mitología, donde no hay belleza que no se contenga, pues en sus admirables
fábulas, los dioses pecando por amor se igualan a los hombres, y los hombres llegando a héroes
por el esfuerzo, casi se confunden con los dioses.

Pero el fundamento de las fábulas mitológicas, en cuanto ofrecen asunto para las artes, es
el desnudo, y en España, para los que regían las conciencias, desnudez y deshonestidad eran
una misma cosa. Quien desee convencerse de ello lea unos cuantos libros de aquellos grandes
escritores místicos que para hacer codiciable la gloria y posible la salvación, presentaban
no sólo la belleza, sino aun la mera forma corporal, como cebo y acicate del pecado. El autor,
por cierto admirable prosista cuyo nombre ha sido olvidado injustamente en las historias de
nuestra literatura, que con más claridad y energía supo expresar esta hostilidad al desnudo,
aunque exagerando como era natural sus peligros, fue el carmelita Fray José de Jesús María.--«El
sentido de la vista--dice--es más eficaz que el del oído, y sus objetos arrebatan el animo
con mayor violencia; y así es más vehemente la moción que despierta la deshonestidad con las
pinturas lascivas, que con las palabras; y tienen menos reparo las especies y memorias que
entran por los ojos que las que se perciben por los oídos; porque las palabras pintan una cosa
ausente o ya pasada, pero las pinturas la figuran presente... Y así los pintores cuando hacen
figuras fabulosas y lascivas cooperan con el demonio, granjeándole tributarios y aumentando
el reino del infierno. Esta introducción pestilencial y venenosa fue obra y traza del demonio
particularmente en estos reinos porque (como queda referido), por vengarse en la tierra, de
la cristiandad, de haberle destruido los templos y los ídolos donde era adorado en las Indias,
introdujo en Europa las figuras deshonestas de mujeres desnudas»[8].

Poniendo en duda o atenuando la fuerza de esta manera de pensar, se dirá que después de escritos
tales párrafos, acaso en aquellos mismos años, los monarcas adornaban sus palacios con obras
de Veronés y de Ticiano, tales que según la intransigencia de los místicos podían calificarse
de pecaminosas, y aun que el mismo Velázquez trajo varias de Italia para Felipe IV; mas esos
lienzos no eran imitados por nuestros pintores.

Los tratadistas de las bellas artes participaban de las mismas ideas; pues si bien los del
siglo XVI, unos como Francisco de Holanda, se postraban ante el genio de los italianos, y otros,
como don Felipe de Guevara, preferían a todo los restos del arte pagano, en cambio los del
siglo XVII sin dejar de entusiasmarse con Rafael y el Vinci, declaran categóricamente que el
objeto principal de la pintura es la glorificación de la fe. Carducho, entre otras afirmaciones
parecidas aceptando la opinión de un monje griego llamado Ignacio, dice que los pintores son
ministros del Verbo, atributo suficiente de apóstoles; y apoyándose en San Gregorio, San Juan
Damasceno y el venerable Beda, añade que el Espíritu Santo socorrió la flaqueza humana con
el milagroso medio de la pintura y que las pinturas de las imágenes son como historia y escritura
para los que ignoran.

Pacheco, movido por igual fervor, escribe que el fin de la pintura será mediante la imitación
representar la cosa con la valentía y propiedad posible... y estando en gracia alcanzar la
bienaventuranza, porque el cristiano criado para cosas santas, no se contenta en sus operaciones
con mirar tan bajamente... de modo que la pintura que tenía por fin parecerse sólo a lo imitado
ahora como acto de virtud, toma nueva y rica sobreveste, y demás de asemejarse, se levanta
a un fin supremo, mirando a la eterna gloria.

Menéndez Pelayo, que ha tratado magistralmente cuanto se refiere a nuestros escritores didácticos
de bellas artes, dice, después de copiar más extensamente aquellos párrafos: «Este profundo
sentido religioso, o más bien ascético que hace de Pacheco en la teoría un predecesor del espiritualismo
de Owerbeck, le mueve a quitar todo valor propio a la pintura considerándola sólo como una
manera de oratoria que se encamina a persuadir al pueblo... y llévalo a abrazar alguna cosa
conveniente a la religión».

D. Juan de Butrón[9], en un libro de insufrible culteranismo sienta también el principio de
que el gusto de una pintura, si con cordura lo recibiésemos, debía levantarnos al conocimiento
del amor de Dios y enseñarnos el principio de que procedemos.

Aun el preceptista de aquel tiempo menos especulativo y más practico, que fue Jusepe Martínez[10],
gran admirador de los italianos, aconseja al pintor católico que la elección de las pinturas
que se deben hacer para ser veneradas no sean hechas con extravagantes posturas y movimientos
extraordinarios, que mueven más a indecencia que a veneración; y en otro lugar añade que en
las pinturas religiosas antes se atienda a la devoción y decoro que a lo imitado: llegando
a decir que el fin de estas profesiones de escultura y pintura no se ha introducido para otra
cosa sino para adoración y veneración a sus santos; por cuyo medio Su Divina Majestad ha obrado
infinitos milagros.

Tal era el concepto que de la pintura tenían los escritores sagrados y los tratadistas especiales.
Estas doctrinas arraigaron con tal fuerza que un siglo más tarde todavía se revelan en rasgos
de superstición y fanatismo. Hombre tan serio como Palomino habla de un religioso de una santa
cartuja a quien hubieron de quitar de la celda una imagen de María Santísima, de suma perfección,
porque su mucha hermosura le provocaba a deshonestidad; y el P. Interian de Ayala exclama indignado:
«Porque ¿a qué viene el pintar a la Virgen, maestra y dechado de todas las vírgenes, descubierta
la cabeza? ¿A qué el cabello rubio esparcido y tendido por el blanco cuello? ¿A qué sin tapar
decentemente aquellos pechos que mamó el Criador del mundo? ¿A qué, finalmente el pintar sus
pies o totalmente desnudos o cubiertos con poca decencia?»[11]. De modo que hasta la Concepción
de Murillo, acaso la expresión más poética del arte católico, vino a ser sospechosa.

A propio intento me he detenido algo en lo que precede, aunque sin insistir lo que la materia
permite, porque tales ideas fueron la causa de que la pintura de aquel tiempo, exceptuando
el retrato, esté limitada al género religioso. Sin incurrir en el absurdo de rechazar esta
fase del espíritu nacional, séame permitido lamentar que su exclusivismo nos privara de otras
manifestaciones artísticas.

Pero si en lo que se refiere a la elección de asuntos, venció el amor a lo sobrenatural, en
lo tocante a la manera de tratarlos y a la representación de la figura humana, prevaleció un
sentido esencialmente realista. La pintura de entonces, no crea más que Cristos, Vírgenes y
Santos, pero no les da forma con rasgos de perfección soñada, sino mediante la más brava imitación
del modelo; su belleza no es un engendro de la mente, no nacen de la corta idea rafaelesca,
sino de la propia naturaleza humana. Los tipos de apóstoles, mártires y ermitaños, están tomados
del campo y de la hampa o son soldados viejos de Flandes y de Italia: el artista sin cuidarse
de ennoblecerlos ni siquiera limpiarlos, los coloca en los altares y allí son reverenciados
y adorados: persuaden al animo y seducen a la imaginación meridional porque tienen vida: la
pintura española esta creada.

III

JUVENTUD DE VELÁZQUEZ.

Don Diego Rodríguez de Silva y Velázquez nació en Sevilla, según tradición falta de pruebas,
en la calle de Gorgoja: fue su padre Juan Rodríguez de Silva, oriundo de Portugal, pero nacido
y avecindado en Sevilla, y su madre D.ª Jerónima Velázquez[12]: se le bautizó en la parroquia
de San Pedro el 6 de Junio de 1599.

De la infancia del gran pintor nada se sabe: es de suponer que estudiase algunos años con cualquier
profesor de humanidades de los muchos que por aquel tiempo había en Sevilla, mas no debió de
ser muy largo este aprendizaje literario. Cean Bermúdez dice: que notando sus padres una inclinación
decidida en el muchacho a la pintura, porque siempre estaba dibujando en los libros y cartapacios,
tuvieron por más acertado ponerle en la escuela de Francisco de Herrera El viejo, tan conocido
por su facilidad en pintar como por la aspereza de su genio. Era éste de condición tan desabrida
y dura que su hija por no aguantarle se metió monja y su hijo le robó y huyó a Italia. Sus
cuadros reflejaban su carácter: pintaba con extraordinario vigor, sin imitar a los que habiendo
estado en Italia volvían entusiasmados con la gracia y la elegancia de las escuelas romana
y florentina. Si esta intransigencia era resultado de ideales artísticos más o menos combatidos
o mera consecuencia de su carácter, nadie puede saberlo: lo cierto es que los discípulos le
sufrían de mala gana y paraban poco a su lado. El hombre debía de hacer intolerable al maestro.
Velázquez, acaso por deseo propio o, pensando mejor, por iniciativa de sus padres, pues aún
no había cumplido catorce años, abandonó el taller de Herrera y pasó al de Francisco Pacheco.
La figura de éste es interesantísima, tanto por el propio valer, cuanto por la influencia que
ejerció en el porvenir de Velázquez. No se sabe de cierto si nació en Sevilla ni si viajó por
Italia: de lo que no cabe duda es de que fue hombre de singular cultura y gran prestigio; pintor,
preceptista y poeta. Si no hubiese escrito más que versos nadie se acordaría de él porque los
hacía dañados de conceptismo, desaliñados y fríos, sin conseguir acercarse a sus modelos Herrera
y Rioja; y de Góngora que fue su amigo sólo se asimiló lo censurable. Como pintor rindió culto
al gusto italiano y aunque nada suyo se conserva de mérito sobresaliente, fue muy apreciado
en su tiempo, influyendo tal vez en esta estimación antes las prendas personales que las facultades
artísticas: sus cuadros son más correctos pero tan fríos como sus sonetos. Trató al Greco en
Toledo año de 1612 sin asimilarse ninguna de sus buenas cualidades. Ha pasado a la posteridad,
gracias a lo que escribió. Compuso en prosa entreverada de versos la Apacible conversación
entre un tomista y un congregado, acerca del misterio de la Purísima Concepción, nuestra señora,
y un opúsculo En defensa del compatronato de Santa Teresa, en el cual alegó razones contra
la opinión de Quevedo que, como es sabido, defendía el patronato exclusivo de Santiago. Pero
compuso dos obras porque merece ser más estimado. La primera es el[13] Arte de la pintura,
su antigüedad y grandezas. En lo que se refiere a las relaciones del arte con la religión esta
fundada en la doctrina y consejos de los amigos jesuitas que le ayudaron en su trabajo, y en
lo que toca a la practica es un reflejo de las ideas de los tratadistas neoplatónicos de Florencia.
El Libro de descripción de verdaderos retratos es una colección de ellos, hechos a dos lápices,
en que figuran desde el Rey Felipe II hasta artífices que entonces gozaban popularidad y hoy
están olvidados: los más del natural, otros valiéndose de copias, todos interesantísimos ya
por la calidad de las personas ya por la excelencia de la mano, y algunos tan sobria y magistralmente
trabajados que antes que de Pacheco pudieran ser de Velázquez.

No faltó, sin embargo, en Sevilla por aquellos años poeta que viendo un Cristo crucificado,
de Pacheco, en que la ejecución quedaba muy por bajo del pensamiento, dijese:

      ¿Quién os puso así Señor
    tan descarnado y tan seco?
    Vos me diréis que el amor,
    mas yo digo que Pacheco.

A pesar de lo cual, la personalidad artística y social del maestro debió de merecer tal respeto
a sus conciudadanos que llegó a ser alcalde y veedor del oficio de pintores, y el Santo Oficio
teniendo atención a su cordura y prudencia le encargó que tuviese particular cuidado de mirar
y visitar las pinturas de cosas sagradas que estuviesen en sitios públicos, dándole para ello
comisión, cual se requiere de derecho.

No sin fundamento llama Palomino a la casa de Francisco Pacheco cárcel dorada del arte, pues
fueron sus amigos y en distintas épocas debieron de leer o presentar allí sus obras muchos
hombres ilustres. Fernando de Herrera, Pablo de Céspedes, el licenciado Roelas, Martínez Montañez,
Juan de Malara, Baltasar del Alcázar, los Carducho, Góngora, Jauregui, Alonso Cano, Quevedo,
Rodrigo Caro, autor de la soberbia elegía a las ruinas de Itálica, y tal vez Miguel de Cervantes.

La atmósfera intelectual creada por tales artistas y poetas, de los cuales unos eran ya muertos
y otros aún vivían, fue el ambiente que comenzó a respirar Diego Velázquez, quien casi niño
salió de poder de Herrera, adusto y regañón, original e intransigente, que dibujaba con cañas
quemadas y pintaba con enormes brochas, y fue a parar a la escuela de un hombre bondadoso,
apacible, imitador de los italianos, cuya morada debía de ser academia donde prevalecía el
gusto clásico, fruto de la más pulcra ilustración, pero al fin clasicismo de reflejo.

Aquí comienza a despuntar el genio de Velázquez, porque aun viviendo rodeado de gentes que
por su educación y tendencia, sobre todo por las corrientes del tiempo, eran entusiastas de
todo espiritualismo, aunque allí dominaban en la doctrina y practica del arte, la devoción
a la antigua española y el renacimiento a la italiana, él lejos de doblegarse fácilmente a
la opinión ajena empezó a trabajar, inspirándose únicamente de lo que la Naturaleza ponía ante
sus ojos, obstinándose en dominar la forma, comprendiendo que las cosas en apariencia más bajas,
viles y groseras están preñadas de belleza para quien sabe estudiarlas. Mientras su maestro
escribía que la pintura es loable porque puede servir a la gloria de la religión y al fomento
de la piedad, cuanto los pintores más insignes competían en la representación de apariciones
milagrosas y prodigios inspirados en la fe; él hacía estudios de animales, aves, pescaderías
y bodegones con perfecta imitación del natural. Pacheco lo refiere diciendo, que cuando era
muchacho, «tenía cohechado un aldeanillo, aprendiz que le servía de modelo en diversas acciones
y posturas, ya llorando, ya riendo sin dificultad alguna. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04109</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>89010</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20942</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Certainly works
referred to these observations atinadísimas say little to pure feeling aesthetic, because they
are based on imitation, and its authors, although more or less able, lacked the spirit of
its own: but instead, we can say that by its very simplicity and candor perfectly satisfied
that inspire religious fervor. Compositions These paintings were not real pictures made just
for ornamental and permanent gala Room but small portable oratories, diptychs or triptychs, encharneladas
tables, as they named in the language of the time, and they were all based on issues devotees.
Kings captains and nobles took them to war, and its consequent suffering Travel affairs: what
was at camp today, tomorrow could be seen in a castle, and ignorance or culture of winning depend always
his luck. This line of paints due to generalized dramatically.

For cameras and Tarbes of palaces, castles and houses that Elizabeth
I had in Aranjuez Granada, Seville, Toledo, Toro, Tordesillas, Segovia,
Medina del Campo, was, as stated inventory made after his death, at
the foot of four hundred sixty paintings, almost all of devotion,
and Juana la Loca left thirty-six, on which he inherited from his
mother.

Test that not only kings possessed such works, is that many of them they were gifted, and their
perpetrators should be well paid when we know that Fernando V sent to Michel Flemish painter
who was Our Lady Queen there blessed glory, the sum maravedises of 116,666, around the time
he had served the queen from the early SA 1492, until the fine [6].

[Image: NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON

CHRIST BOUND TO COLUMN

FRAME. Braun, Clement & C ª]

Charles I had more than six hundred paintings, known his power, it
is easy to deduce the treasures that accumulate in the palaces of
the Netherlands, Italy and Spain, only her Aunt Dona Margarita of
Austria, bequeathed more than one hundred paintings, and Francis I
of France, or Henry VIII of England, came to possess similar wealth.

But this treasure is no longer composed exclusively religious works. The Renaissance was in
full swing, the pagan auras awakening the love of Nature had eaten the new blood art, artists
and believers lazy and accounting with accounts of mysticism sincere evangelists had happened
others, inspired by the songs of the heathen poets, put his genius to of classic sensuality, pretending
in his works, with great imaginative power, fables erotic exploits of heroes, gods passions,
female nudity, but these painters, understanding and putting his hand in the tragedy of Calvary or
even to the greatness composition and pageantry of color, were able to fill that deep and
sincere emotion stirred the souls of the founders of the early schools. The Renaissance was founded
in the study of old, was revolution provechosísima art, because he taught her to love beauty heedless
of its origin: but making the fantasy prevail on piety, robbed in general and in particular
to painting naive that something mysterious and independent of any external condition that
seduces and captivates even the worshipers of the form.

The painting for over two centuries had been its sole seat in the churches, have dominion also
from the palaces, varied in nature and even when decorated temples, adorned like palaces.

Do not allow the extension of this modest work, but should look at
the welcome Here were the works of the Renaissance to see later how
his character changed and modified trends.

Carlos I must have been a great admirer of his creations, even those
where more shining free sensuality of paganism, because if it is true
that led him to retire to Yuste large number of devotional paintings,
years ago, as reported by Jusepe Martinez had sent Titian painting,
and a portrait, a few pictures of some poems, which, if not as human
take them by divine big shame for our religion!

Felipe II, when he wrote the same name Titian loved us, we charge
for Tables palaces such as Antiope, Venus and Adonis, and Diana and
Callisto, from which it inferred that it was not prudish in matters
of art, and Philip III and Philip IV, continued to meet similar works
in Madrid and the Pardo.

During this long period, which spans the sixteenth century in Spain dominates Italian taste in
relation to the expression elements that animate the paintings, the most illustrious Dutch, Antonio
Moro, for example, are only sought and followed as portrait painters.

In Valencia, Juan de Juanes paint and Ribalta, in Andalusia, Luis de Vargas, Alejandro Fernández
and the divine Morales. We in Italy, conscientiousness in the study of members of the body,
how to design and arrange the table, the use of light, contrasts and harmonies color, to the
styles and methods of execution, but the trend of the Renaissance
to art was, above all, performance of beauty, and born of the ideals
of the mind already provided in the works of nature, the broad and
open to the boldness Florentine, Roman and Venetian frescoes and deployed
his canvases found few converts in Spain.

The monarchs, whom the Church would not interfere your personal tastes sinful were, still adorning
the palaces and pleasure houses with profanity and mythology: Some lords, did the same, as
follows from what several writers refer at that time [7], but for most of the nation, the
art was a mere auxiliary of feeling religious.

Needless there who persists in denying the grounds that in addition to pictures devotees also
they painted a lot of other issues. To be persuaded of how unfounded this claim, just consider
that among the thousands of paintings of the seventeenth century, preserved in Spain, there are very
few they represent historical episodes or scenes of customs, and
instead is incalculable the number of those inspired by the Old or
New Testament, and the lives of the saints: to the vases were usually
arranged so that as a framework to some sacred image: Pictures were
made in abundance, as always well what lies in human vanity, and no
shortage of still lifes, because many artists taking the genre by
way of study: than just a trace, paint is domestic and family could
say.

Know the life of this century, foreign trips, which tended to exaggerate or lie, for files
documents that speak eloquently to dry and bland, for the theater, that lady's imagination is,
for the picaresque novel, which only raises rates class social, for writers, who always felt
particularly devout, were pleased censor customs, describing the way, but the stubborn brushes on
avoiding any representation of vulgar and profane, left us very few
data on how to live, work, crafts, entertainment, houses, rooms, furniture
and clothes of those knights and soldiers, clerics and students, merchants
and beggars, women, and adventurous comic and devout, matrons and
maids, whose patchwork know only morally, thanks Cervantes and Quevedo,
Tirso and Lope, Zabaleta and Salas Barbadillo, because the limited
painters conventional representation of the sacred profane contempt.

Undoubtedly felt intense love for real beauty, which gave proof watching to the holy figures that aspect
of truth, which they lost in HH, it gained in credibility, but it was not possible that nothing
around them every day they thought the subject worthy of use in this observation and his brushes,
when the voice of the Church, so feared and respected then told that life on earth and transitory,
is low and despicable thing compared of the eternal heaven. This is, in my humble opinion,
the cause of Spanish painting of that time is not used, how it serves the Northern countries
to complete the stadium of the country, reflecting the customs which is a way of reflecting the soul
of nationality.

In Italy, also failed to custom paint great importance, because there the art, thanks the culture
of the papacy, it became eminently monumental: but in the absence and with advantage can not
represent human and vulgar scenes arranged beautiful countryside artists Mythology and unlimited,
where there is no beauty that is not contained, as in his admirable myths, the gods of love
are equated sinning men, and men coming to Heroes for the effort, almost be mistaken for gods.

But
the foundation of the fables and myths, as the case for the arts offer is nude, and Spain,
for which governed the consciences, nudity and dishonesty were same thing. Anyone wishing to be
convinced of this read a few books of those great mystical writers desirable to glory and salvation
possible, had not only beauty, but even the mere bodily form like
a bait and spur of sin.

The author, indeed admirable prose writer whose name has been unjustly forgotten stories our
literature, that with more clarity and energy capable of expressing this hostility to the naked but he
naturally exaggerating its dangers, was the Carmelite Fray Jose de Jesus Maria .-- "The eyesight
- he says - is more effective than ear, and its objects snatched the mood more violence, and
so the motion is more intense awakening with dishonesty lewd pictures than with words, and species
are under repair and reports catch the eye than they are perceived by the ears, because the
words paint a thing absent or already passed, but the paintings are present ... And so the
painters when they fabulous figures and lascivious cooperate with
the devil, winning and increasing tax the kingdom of hell.

This introduction was pestilential, poisonous devil's work and trace particularly in these realms
because (as has been said), to take revenge on the land, Christianity, of having destroyed the
temples and idols which were worshiped in India, introduced in Europe Dishonest figures of naked
women [8].

Questioning or diminishing the strength of this way of thinking, it
is said that after writing such paragraphs, perhaps in those same
years, the monarchs decorated their palaces with works Veronese and
Titian, such that as the intransigence of the mystics could be classified
of sinful, and even that it brought several of Italy Velázquez Felipe
IV, but these paintings were imitated by our painters.

Writers on the arts participated in the same ideas, because although the sixteenth century,
some as Francisco de Hollanda, fell before the genius of the Italians, and others as Don Felipe
de Guevara, preferred to all the remnants of pagan art, instead of the seventeenth century, while
Rafael enthuse and Vinci, declared categorically that main subject of the painting is the glorification
of the faith. Carducho, among other claims seems to accept the opinion of a Greek monk named
Ignacio, says that the painters are ministers of the Word, sufficient attribute apostles, and building
on San Gregorio, San Juan Damascus and the Venerable Bede, says that the Holy Spirit succor
the human weakness the miraculous through the paint and paints the images are like history and
writing for those who are ignorant.

Pacheco, driven by equal fervor, writes that the purpose of painting is through imitation represent
the thing with the courage and property as possible ... and being in grace reach bliss, because
the Christian servant for holy things, not content in their operations to look so lowly ... so
that the painting was intended to resemble the imitated only now as an act of virtue, making
new and rich surcoat, and others resemble, rises for one ultimate purpose, looking to the eternal
glory.

Menéndez Pelayo, who has dealt brilliantly as it relates to our educational writers fine arts,
he says, after most widely copied those paragraphs: "This deep religious sense, or rather ascetic
Pacheco makes the theory a predecessor of spiritualism of Owerbeck, moves him to remove all
the paint eigenvalue considering it only as a way of speaking that
is aimed at persuading the people ... and take it to embrace something
convenient religion.

"

D. Juan de Butrón [9], in a book of insufferable culteranismo feel also the principle of the
taste of a painting, if wisely what we might receive, should rise to knowledge the love of God
and teach the principle that we proceed.

Although the precept that time less speculative and more practical, which was Jusepe Martínez
[10] great admirer of the Italian Catholic who advises the painter paints the choice of to
be made to be venerated not made extravagant postures and movements extraordinary, moving more to
worship indecency, and added elsewhere that religious paintings before
attending to the devotion and decorum that the imitated: reaching
to say to these professions of sculpture and painting has been introduced
to other nothing but to worship and veneration of their saints through
whom His Divine Majesty has acted endless miracles.

This was the concept of the sacred writers were painting and special writers. These doctrines rooted
so hard that a century later still reveal traits of superstition and fanaticism. Palomino Men's
as serious as speaking of a religious holy Charterhouse who had to be removed from the cell
image of Mary, of great perfection, for her great beauty caused him
to dishonesty and P. Ayala Interian exclaims indignantly: "Because
what's all the painting of the Virgin, teacher and model of all virgins,
outdoor head?

What blond hair spread out and lying on the white collar? What uncovered decently those breasts that
nursed the Creator of the world? What, finally paint their feet or totally naked or covered
with little decency? "[11]. So until the Conception Murillo, perhaps the most poetic expression of Catholic
art, became suspicious.

A proper attempt something I have stopped the above, but without insisting
that the matter allows, because such ideas were the cause of that
painting of that time, except the portrait, is limited to the religious
genre.

Without incurring the absurdity of rejecting this phase of the national spirit, let me lament
that their exclusivity would deprive us of other artistic.

But if in regard to the choice of issues, won the love of the supernatural, regarding how to treat
them as representing the human figure, the prevailing one essentially realistic sense. The painting
then creates only Christs and Virgins Santos, but does not give a perfect dream with features,
but by imitation bravest model, its beauty is not an offspring of the mind, not born of the
idea Raphaelesque short, but human nature itself. The types of apostles, martyrs and hermits,
are taken field and the underworld, or are old soldiers of Flanders and Italy: the artist without
caring to ennoble even clean them, put them on the altar and there are revered and adored: persuaded
to encourage and entice the imagination because they have southern
life: Spanish painting is created.

III

YOUTH OF VELAZQUEZ.

Don Diego Rodriguez de Silva y Velázquez was born in Seville, according to tradition, lack of
evidence Borers in the street: it was his father Juan Rodríguez de Silva, a native of Portugal,
but born and resident in Seville, and his mother Ms Jerónima Velázquez [12] was baptized in the
parish St. Peter's June 6, 1599.

Of the great painter's childhood nothing is known: presumably to study a few years with any
professor of humanities at the many who at that time had at Seville, but should not have this
very long literary apprenticeship. Cean Bermudez says, noting that his parents an inclination
the boy decided to painting, because I was always drawing in books
and pamphlets had put more successful in school by Francisco de Herrera
the old, well known for ease in painting as by the harshness of his
genius.

This was so bland condition and hard to put up his daughter for not got nun and her son stole
and fled to Italy. Its paintings reflected his character painted with extraordinary force, to
imitate those who, having Italy became excited state with the grace and elegance of Roman schools
and Florence. If this intransigence was the result of artistic ideals fought more or less or simply
the consequence of his character, nobody can know: the truth is that the disciples suffered
unwillingly and stopped short at his side. The man was intolerable to the teacher. Velázquez, perhaps
by choice or second thoughts on the initiative of their parents, because even had not reached
fourteen years, left the blacksmith's shop and went to Francisco Pacheco. The latter figure
is interesting, both for the self-worth, but because of the influence exercised in the future
of Velázquez.

It is not known for certain whether he was born in Seville, or if
he traveled Italy: what is certain is that he was a man of outstanding
culture and great prestige, painter preceptist and poet.

If I had not written more than verses one would remember him because
concept was damaged, disheveled and cool, without getting closer to
their models Herrera and Rioja, and his friend Góngora was assimilated
only objectionable thing.

Worshiped as a painter Italian-style and although nothing remains of his outstanding merit,
was greatly appreciated in his time, perhaps influencing this estimate before personal garments
powers art: his paintings are more accurate but as cold as his sonnets. Greco tried to Toledo
likened year 1612 without any of their good qualities.

Has passed to posterity because of what he wrote. He wrote in prose interspersed with verses the conversation
Peaceful between Thomistic and gathered, about the mystery of the Immaculate Conception, Our
Lady, and a pamphlet in defense of compatronato of Santa Teresa, which argued against Quevedo's opinion,
as is known, defended the exclusive patronage of Santiago. But composed two works because it deserves
to be estimated. The first is [13] Art painting its antiquity and greatness. In regard to the
relationship between art and religion is founded on the doctrine and guidance from the Jesuit friends
who helped him in his work, and it touches into practice is a reflection of the ideas of the
Neoplatonic writers of Florence. Book Description The true portraits is a collection of them, made
two pencils, they are from King Felipe II to artists who enjoyed popularity then and now are
forgotten: the most natural of others using copies, all interesting and the quality of the people
and for the excellence of the hand, and some very sober and masterly that worked before may
be of Velázquez Pacheco.

There was no shortage, however, in Seville during those years watching a poet who crucified Christ
Pacheco, where the performance was well under the thought, say:

Who put you well Lord so stark and so dry? You tell me that love I say we Pacheco.

In spite of this, the artistic and social merit of the teacher must have such respect their fellow
citizens who became mayor and overseer of the profession of painters, and the Holy Office having
regard to their wisdom and prudence had instructed him to look particularly carefully and visit
the sacred paintings of things that were in public places, giving to this committee, which is required
of law.

Not without reason called the Palomino to the house of Francisco Pacheco art golden prison
because were his friends and at different times due to read or present his or her work many illustrious
men. Fernando de Herrera, Pablo de Céspedes, Mr. Roelas, Martínez Montañez Juan de Malara,
Baltasar del Alcázar, the Carducho, Gongora, Jauregui, Alonso Cano, Quevedo, Rodrigo Caro, author
of the superb elegy to the ruins of Italica, and perhaps Miguel de Cervantes.

The intellectual atmosphere created by such artists and poets, of which some were already dead
and others still living, was the atmosphere that he breathed Diego Velázquez, who almost child Herrera
came to power, grim and scolding, original and uncompromising, he drew with canes burned and painted
with large brushes, and went to school a good man, peaceful, imitator of the Italians, whose
dwelling had to be prevailed academy where classical taste, the fruit of the neatest illustration,
but the classical order of reflection.

Here begins to emerge Velazquez's genius, because even people who live surrounded by by education
and a tendency, especially by the currents of the time, were keen
all spiritualism, although there ruled in doctrine and practice of
art, devotion the former Spanish and the Italian Renaissance, far
from bowing he easily the opinions of others began to work, keeping
only what Nature put before his eyes, stubbornly clinging to master
the form, realizing that things apparently lower, mean and rude are
pregnant beauty for those who can study them.

      While his teacher wrote
    that the painting is commendable
    because it can serve the glory
    of religion and the promotion of piety, the most celebrated painters
competed in the representation of appearances miracles and wonders,
inspired by faith, he did studies on animals, birds, fish and still
lifes in perfect imitation of nature.

Pacheco refers you saying that when he was boy, "had bribed a aldeanillo, trainee model that served
in various operations and postures, and weeping, and laughing without any difficulty.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>