<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05803</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>173543</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18501</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> ¡Con él! ¡Un sacerdote que entra de noche en los portales a cuchichear
con mujeres hermosas y elegantes! ¡Puf! Sería vergüenza el hacerlo. Obdulia estaba bien segura
de que la mujer que hablaba con su confesor era linda. Esta seguridad la torturaba. Por supuesto
que, si tenía el atrevimiento de venir a hablarle, le daría un desaire de los gordos, le volvería
la espalda. Y confesaría otra vez con D. Narciso. Y diría a sus amigas en qué situación le
había visto con una señora desconocida y elegante. Porque no cabía duda de que vestía con elegancia,
bien lo había reparado. Aquel abrigo largo no estaba hecho en Peñascosa. ¿Quién sería? Alguna
de Lancia, seguro, que vendría a hacerle una visita. Y ¿por qué se viene de lejos a visitar
a un sacerdote no siendo su madre, o su hermana o su deuda? ¿No sabe esa señora que la fama
de los sacerdotes es muy delicada y cualquier cosa la quiebra? El cerebro de la joven no cesaba
de dar vueltas y más vueltas a estas ideas y a otras análogas, mientras su cuerpo permanecía
inmóvil, abatido, clavando los ojos obstinadamente en las manos de D.ª Marciala, que no dejaba
un momento su calceta. Sentíase enferma, deseaba irse; pero una vaga esperanza, que no podía
definir, la retenía a su pesar.

Mientras tanto el P. Norberto estaba sorprendido y confuso por las inusitadas atenciones de
que era objeto por parte de Cándida. El pobre no estaba acostumbrado a que se las prodigasen.
El bello sexo de Peñascosa le profesaba cierto desdén compasivo. Teníasele por un sacerdote
virtuoso, pero de muy cortos alcances. Sus mismos compañeros, cuando hablaban de él, lo hacían
sin dejar de los labios una sonrisa medio protectora, medio burlona. Para las damas, la virtud
del P. Norberto no tenía poesía, carecía de ese encanto especial que en otros sacerdotes la
hace contagiosa, era una virtud pedestre, que no se traducía en conceptos delicados y sublimes
como en el P. Narciso, el P. Gil y otros. Así que rara era la joven que se confesaba con él,
ni menos la que apeteciese su conversación o tuviese gusto en envolverle entre nubes de incienso,
como hacía Cándida en aquel momento. Su misma inclinación a rescatar las mujerzuelas perdidas,
por más que se respetase, no le hacía simpático a las señoritas. Verdad que él se pasaba admirablemente
sin esta simpatía y no le quitaba de engordar cada día más y pasar la vida riendo. Las lisonjas
que le estaba vertiendo al oído con voz insinuante su nueva hija de confesión, en vez de agradarle,
le turbaban, le molestaban visiblemente. Fue una de las pocas veces en que pudo vérsele serio.
Hacía rechinar la silla, cambiando de postura a cada instante, y restallaba los nudillos de
las manos de un modo formidable, tosía, se ponía colorado, y de vez en cuando dejaba escapar
de la garganta un leve bufido con que su modestia alarmada protestaba. Por último, solicitado
vivamente por la dulce perspectiva del tresillo, aprovechó una pausa de la doncella para levantarse
y decir torciendo un poco las caderas a guisa de saludo:

--Con permiso de usted, señorita.

En cuanto salió de aquella situación angustiosa, su faz sanguínea se dilató y volvió a aparecer
en ella la sonrisa de benevolencia universal que le servía de principal ornamento. Su llegada
al grupo donde estaban Consejero, D. Martín, Osuna y otro caballero militar de Lancia fue acogida
con alegría.

--Te presento--dijo D. Martín a su amigo forastero, bajando la voz y echando una mirada recelosa
alrededor para cerciorarse de que no le oía su mujer,--al padre Norberto, un cura que te podrá
informar de todos los chamizos de la población, si deseas conocer alguno.

--¡Oh, oh! ¡D. Martín, por Dios!

--¡Atrévase usted a decir que no los conoce!

--Hombre, sí... de algunos sé... Por desgracia, necesito entrar en ellos alguna vez...

--Este señor se dedica a las jóvenes extraviadas--continuó D. Martín, dirigiéndose a su compañero,
que sonreía lleno de asombro.

--¡Jesús! Considere, D. Martín, que este señor no me conoce...

--Pues para que le conozca a usted hablo.

D.ª Eloisa, de lejos, echaba miradas de terror a su marido, observando la confusión de D. Norberto
y la risa de los otros.

--Bueno--prosiguió el señor de las Casas, haciéndose prudente y conciliador,--yo no diré, D.
Norberto, que usted vaya con mala idea a esas casas de perdición; pero lo que sostendré siempre
es que les está usted prestando un gran servicio: está usted haciendo su agosto.

--¿Cómo, cómo?--preguntó asustado el clérigo.

--Pues muy sencillo; ayudando a que se eleve el precio de la mercancía. Recuerde el ejemplo
de Carmen la zapatillera...

Ésta era una muchacha a quien el P. Norberto había conseguido sacar de una casa de prostitución
y llevar a un convento. Al cabo de algún tiempo se salió y volvió a la mala vida. Tornó D.
Norberto a persuadirla al arrepentimiento, y otra vez ella se vino del asilo y se entregó al vicio.

--¿Y qué tiene que ver?...

--Voy a explicárselo, padre, voy a explicárselo... Atiendan ustedes... Cuando usted catequizó
a Carmen, no me negará que la mercancía estaba bastante depreciada ya...

--¡Yo no sé! ¡Qué cosas tiene usted, D. Martín!--exclamó el clérigo azorado.

--Me consta, padre, me consta. Pues bien, después que estuvo un año por allá y engordó un poco
en el convento y volvió rodeada de cierta aureola de honradez, el precio se elevó notablemente.
Vuelve usted a llevársela cuando ya estaba un poco estropeadilla y la demanda había mermado
hasta un punto que hacía temer por la bucólica, y ahora que viene otra vez gordita y santificada,
se cotiza de nuevo como en sus mejores tiempos.

--¡Jesús! ¡Jesús! ¡Vaya todo por Dios!--exclamó el clérigo tapándose los oídos, pero sin enfadarse.--No
sea usted tan malo, D. Martín.

D.ª Eloisa, que bien advertía lo que estaba pasando, se levantó al fin de la silla y vino hacia
ellos, preguntando con mal humor:

--¿No juegan hoy al tresillo?

--Vamos allá, vamos allá--respondió su marido, sofocando la risa que le fluía del cuerpo, como
a los demás.

Sentáronse Consejero, D. Norberto y él a la mesa, y no tardaron en abstraerse de todos los
ruidos mundanales bajo la influencia fascinadora de la espada, la mala y el basto. Poco después
Consejero rechinaba los dientes y se tiraba cruelmente del bigote, encontrándose dos veces
seguidas con el tres de bastos, su enemigo personal. Hacía ya muchos años que se tenían declarada
una guerra a muerte. Cada vez que le venía a las manos, Consejero se crispaba, juraba sordamente
como un carretero. El tres de bastos, malintencionado y socarrón como ningún otro naipe, gozaba
al parecer con verle irritado, y se colaba bonitamente siempre que podía en el montoncillo
que le repartían. No sólo en la tertulia, sino en toda la villa era conocida esta antipatía.
Algunos, con ciertas precauciones por supuesto, porque D. Romualdo se disparaba fácilmente,
le embromaban con ella. En cierta ocasión, pescando con caña detrás de la iglesia, sacó en
el anzuelo un naipe que resultó ser el tres de bastos. No le cupo duda de que lo habían tirado
allí con intención, pero no dijo palabra para que no se rieran.

Mientras tanto Osuna había ido a frotarse un poco contra D.ª Eloisa. Entre todas las damas
que asistían a aquella tertulia no había más que dos gordas, D.ª Teodora y D.ª Eloisa. Estaba
también en buenas carnes D.ª Rita, pero era blanda, amarilla. Las demás «escocia pura,» como
él llamaba a las flacas, aludiendo al bacalao. Así que no tenía fin el desprecio que nuestro
jorobado profesaba a aquella sociedad degenerada y exhausta de tejido adiposo. Sólo iba por
allí a buscar a su hija, o cuando materialmente no sabía dónde refugiarse. D.ª Eloisa miraba
con benevolencia (como lo miraba todo la buena señora) aquella pasión que el monstruo parecía
sentir hacia ella. Cuando se le acercaba demasiado, separábase dulcemente, sin extinguirse
por eso su sonrisa bondadosa. En cambio D.ª Teodora le tenía un gran miedo, verdadero terror.
Lo mismo era aproximarse Osuna, que ya estaba la casta jamona sofocada, inquieta, un color
se le iba y otro se le venía. Pero era tal la vergüenza que sentía, que no hubiera declarado
a su mismo padre las insinuaciones del sucio contrahecho. ¡Qué diferencia entre este indecente
y el sereno, majestuoso y romántico D. Juan Casanova! Ni con D. Peregrín podía comparársele,
con ser éste, en concepto de la madura doncella, un sujeto mucho más voluptuoso y terrestre.

D. Peregrín había llegado, según costumbre, de los últimos. Y si la tertulia no advirtió en
la mayor estridencia de sus bufidos nasales, en su parpadear infinitamente más solemne y en
la grave manera de poner una pierna sobre otra y echarse hacia atrás que algo importante, importantísimo,
tenía que comunicar, fue que no quiso advertirlo. Aguardó pacientemente, como todos los hombres
seguros del éxito, a que hubiese una pausa, y cuando llegó, profirió con su voz gangosa, penetrante,
encarándose con el ama de la casa:

--¿A que no sabe usted a quién acabo de ver entrar en casa de su hermano, en compañía del excusador?

A Obdulia le dio un salto tan recio el corazón, que pensó caer al suelo. Los demás, incluso
D.ª Eloisa, alzaron la cabeza con curiosidad.

--¿Quién era?

--Su cuñada Joaquina--gritó más que dijo el ex-gobernador interino de Tarragona, como si anunciara
el juicio final.

Profundo estupor en toda la tertulia.

--¡Mi cuñada!--exclamó.

--Su misma cuñada--confirmó D. Peregrín con trompeteo horrísono.

--¡No puede ser!--dijo D.ª Eloisa.

--¡No puede ser!--exclamó su marido, suspendiendo el juego.

--¡No puede ser!--repitió D.ª Serafina Barrado.

El ex-gobernador de Tarragona dejó escapar por la nariz algunos resoplidos fragorosos, como
una locomotora que desaloja el vapor sobrante, y repuso:

--¿Creen ustedes, señores, que no tengo ojos en la cara?

Esta pregunta trascendental, acompañada del adecuado fruncimiento de cejas, produjo bastante
impresión entre los interruptores.

--Bien pudo usted haberse equivocado--dijo el inválido.

--¡Es tan fácil!--exclamó D.ª Eloisa.

--La he visto como les veo a ustedes ahora, a tres pasos de distancia. Venía yo de hablar con
el sacristán para la cuestión del aniversario de mi señor padre, cuando al embocar la calle
del Cuadrante veo al P. Gil con una señora que me pareció forastera. Quise saber quién era,
y me detuve un poco cerca del farol, ocultándome detrás del quicio de una puerta. Era Joaquinita,
sin duda alguna. Esperé un poco y los seguí con la vista hasta que entraron en casa de Montesinos.

--Pero ¿usted la conoce bien?--preguntó el P. Narciso.

--Lo mismo que a usted.

--Peregrín, debes tener presente que no le has hecho más que una visita en Madrid, y por la
noche, según me has dicho--apuntó tímidamente D. Juan.

El ex-gobernador arrojó a su hermano una mirada de indecible desprecio.

--Juan, no metas la pata.

--Peregrín, no sé por qué...

--¡Juan!...

--¡Peregrín!...

--¡Que no la metas! ¡Que no la metas! A esa señora la he visto después de visitarla otra porción
de veces en la calle, y la he saludado. Por lo tanto, me veo en la triste necesidad de manifestarte
que lo que acabas de decir es una impertinencia. Cuando he asegurado que conocía a esa señora,
es porque la conocía. Yo no hablo nunca a humo de pajas. Si fuera un hombre ligero y sin fundamento,
no hubiera podido ocupar las posiciones que he ocupado. Sírvate de gobierno.

--Ahora que me acuerdo--dijo Cándida,--hoy he visto apearse de la diligencia a una señora rubia
con un traje muy elegante.

D. Peregrín alzó los hombros con un gesto de profundo desdén, como si quisiera decir: «¿A qué
viene usted en mi apoyo para contrarrestar los absurdos de este necio?»

Aquel dato y aquel gesto concluyeron de aniquilar a D. Juan, cuyo rostro expresó el abatimiento.
Pero D.ª Teodora, con sus grandes ojos serenos, le clavó una mirada tan afectuosa que las facciones
del caballero, contraídas por la pesadumbre, se fueron dilatando gradualmente, y una plácida
sonrisa melancólica concluyó por esfumarse en sus labios. La frente de D. Peregrín, en cambio,
quedó surcada instantáneamente por una porción de arrugas. La innegable superioridad que tenía
sobre su hermano, ¿de qué le servía? Cuanto mejor la demostraba delante de la fresca jamona,
tanto más se inclinaba ésta a favor de él. Razón tenía el juez de primera instancia de Tarragona
cuando le decía que la mujer era un tejido de contradicciones.

Obdulia sintió que una alegría intensa, infinita, le entraba a chorros dentro del alma. Su
cuerpo, enervado, incapaz de movimiento, adquirió súbito la ligereza de un pájaro. Quería salir
prontamente de aquella estancia y surcar los aires y cantar su gozo. Cualquiera podría observar
el cambio operado en ella. Al mutismo obstinado en que yacía sucedió una locuacidad extrema,
una charla animada, insustancial, entreverada de carcajadas extrañas en que se placía, desahogando
la emoción que la embargaba, estirando sus nervios encogidos. Ni sabía bien lo que estaba diciendo,
ni D.ª Filomena, con quien platicaba, se enteraba tampoco, atenta a contemplar la faz inteligente
del P. Narciso y gozar del brillo de sus humoradas. Al poco rato sintió la garganta seca y
calor inusitado en las mejillas. El caballero de Lancia, que allí estaba, hizo la observación,
que se apresuró a comunicar a Osuna, de que su hija tenía los ojos muy negros y brillantes,
y que le sentaban muy bien las rosetas encarnadas que el calor le había sacado en el rostro.

La noticia había producido sensación en todos. Pocos eran los que conocían allí a la esposa
de Montesinos, aunque nadie ignoraba los incidentes del drama conyugal que había retraído al
mayorazgo a Peñascosa. Pero lo que en los extraños era pura curiosidad, en la buena de doña
Eloisa se ofreció, como es lógico, con la apariencia de viva y honda emoción. Quiso desde luego
salir a saber lo que pasaba en casa de su hermano, quiso después que fuese su marido, quiso
enviar un criado. A todo se opuso D. Martín que, viendo las cosas con más frialdad, comprendía
que cualquier paso de éstos en aquel instante era inoportuno. La conversación se animó extremadamente,
hasta el punto de que los tresillistas suspendieron el juego y tomaron parte en ella. Los comentarios
que se hicieron, infinitos. Se forjaron mil hipótesis sobre el caso. Unos opinaban que la esposa,
arrepentida, venía a pedir perdón a su marido, otros que hacía el viaje tan sólo para reclamar
de él alimentos, otros que su intento era entablar la demanda para formalizar el divorcio,
otros que el marido la había llamado, no pudiendo desterrar de su corazón el amor que la profesaba
(la mayoría del elemento femenino se inclinaba a esta suposición), otros que el P. Gil, motu
proprio, había escrito a D.ª Joaquinita y había preparado la escena, a fin de que D. Álvaro
la perdonase, otros que había persuadido a éste a que la llamase a Peñascosa. Ni faltaba tampoco
quien supusiera que D. Álvaro y su esposa hacía tiempo que mantenían correspondencia, y que
era ella quien resistía venir a visitarle hasta la hora presente.

--De todos modos, lo que no ofrece duda es que el P. Gil tiene una intervención muy principal
en el asunto, y a él le pertenece la gloria de la reconciliación--dijo gravemente D. Narciso.

--Si la hay--repuso Consejero.

--La habrá--replicó el capellán.--La habrá, y aquí D. Martín tendrá quizá el gusto pronto de
ver un sobrinito que le distraerá con sus travesuras y sus gracias.

D. Martín, a quien su alma de héroe no le quitaba de tener muchísimas ganas a la herencia del
cuñado, cuya salud era endeble, arrugó las narices y murmuró groseramente:

--Me tiene sin cuidado.

--No lo creo; no puedo creerlo, D. Martín. A usted no puede menos de alegrarle que la noble
casa de Montesinos no se extinga, que haya quien lleve honrosamente este apellido... Luego
ha de parecer bien aquella casa tan grande con unos cuantos chicos que la alegren con sus risas
y sus gritos. La obra del padre Gil es de las más meritorias que ha llevado a cabo, y eso que
las ha hecho muy buenas.

Obdulia le clavó una mirada colérica; pero templándose súbito, repuso con sonrisa inocente:

--Usted no tiene nada que envidiarle, don Narciso. ¿Quién no recuerda en la villa los muchos
matrimonios que por su mediación están hoy bien avenidos? Sin ir más lejos, todo el mundo sabe
que D. Feliciano quería muy poco a D.ª Nieves... y ya ve usted, hoy están como dos pichones.

Este D. Feliciano era el marido que, según se decía en secreto, había roto una pierna al P.
Narciso arrojándole por las escaleras.

Los circunstantes se miraron con inquietud. Hubo un silencio embarazoso. Consejero soltó la
carcajada, y exclamó, poniendo una carta sobre la mesa, como si se refiriese al juego:

--¡Anda, vuelva usted por otra!

Todos comprendieron que se dirigía al padre Narciso, y esto aumentó la inquietud. El clérigo
se puso colorado y murmuró:

--Gracias, gracias. Todos tenemos obligación...

--Usted va más allá de la obligación, padre... Muchas veces lo que usted hace es pura devoción--replicó
la hija de Osuna con encantadora sencillez.

--¡Arrea!--volvió a exclamar Consejero, con la vista fija en las cartas.

--¿Qué es eso, D. Romualdo?--preguntó riendo D. Norberto.--¿Le ha tocado el tres de bastos?

--Sí, señor; pero me consuela que hay palos para todos.

--Pues yo no tengo ninguno--replicó el cándido presbítero.

--¡Otro los recibirá!

--Hacemos todos lo que podemos; pero no cabe duda que unos pueden más que otros. El P. Gil
es un santo, es un apóstol de los primeros tiempos de la Iglesia. Ninguno de nosotros tiene
la presunción de competir con él en celo ni en sabiduría--manifestó D. Joaquín, viniendo en
socorro de su amigo, con una risita venenosa que haría saltar una piedra.

--En sabiduría puede que tenga usted razón, D. Joaquín--replicó vivamente Obdulia;--pero en
celo, me parece que está usted en un error. Es usted demasiado modesto... No es por adularle,
pero tratándose de celo, yo creo que es usted tan celoso como el primero, ¿verdad, doña Serafina?

Un gruñido de todo punto extraño se escapó en aquel momento de la garganta de Consejero, al
cual siguió inmediatamente un violento golpe de tos que le dejó sin respiración por algunos
segundos. D. Joaquín también sintió cierto picor en la garganta, que le obligó a toser volviendo
la cabeza. D.ª Serafina no contestó a la pregunta, porque se distrajo hablando con D.ª Eloisa.

La conversación cambió de rumbo, como si tácitamente todos convinieran en que aquél era peligroso.
Poco después cesó de ser general, y volvieron a formarse los grupitos de costumbre. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>49394</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>16391</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> With him! A priest comes by night in doorways whispering with beautiful
women and elegant! Ugh! Would be ashamed to do so. Obdulia was quite sure a woman talking to her
confessor was cute. This assurance was torturing. Of course that if he had the audacity to come
to talk, give him a cold shoulder from the fat, I would back. And confess again with D. Narciso.
And tell his friends in what situation you had seen a lady unknown and elegant. Because there
was no doubt who was dressed elegantly While he had repaired. Long coat that was not done in Peñascosa.
Who would? Some Lancia, sure, that would pay him a visit. And why do you come from afar to visit
a priest, not his mother or his sister or his debt? Do not you know that lady that fame Priests
are very delicate and anything bankruptcy? The brain of the young did not stop spinning and
turning these ideas and the like, while his body remained motionless, dejected, staring stubbornly
at the hands of Ms Marciala, leaving no a time when his sock. He felt ill, wanted to leave but
a vague hope that he could not define the retained despite himself.

Meanwhile Fr Norberto was surprised and confused by the unusual attention
of it was subjected by Candida.

The poor man was not accustomed to being the lavish. The fair sex of her professed disdain
Peñascosa compassionate. Teníasele by a priest virtuous, but very short-sighted. His own companions,
when they talked about it, they did while the protective lips half smiling, half-mocking. For
the ladies, virtue Fr Norberto was not poetry, it lacked the charm that other priests becomes
contagious, was a pedestrian under that did not translate into delicate and sublime concepts as
in P. Narciso, P. Gil et al. So rare was the girl who confessed to him not least that felt
like it had the taste in conversation or envelop in clouds of incense, Candida as he did at that
time. His own inclination to rescue the lost sluts, much they respected, was not sympathetic
to the ladies. Truth that he spent admirably Without this sympathy and did not detract from fat each
day and spend my life laughing. Flattery he was pouring his ear with his new daughter insinuating
voice of confession, instead of pleasing, troubled him, annoyed him visibly. It was one of the few times
he could seriously seen lounging. It was grinding the seat, changing position every minute, and
Knuckles crackled hands in a formidable, coughed, blushed, and occasionally let out of the throat with
a slight snort alarmed protested his modesty. Finally, as requested strongly by the sweet prospect
of sitting, took a break from the maiden to rise and say a little twisting hips by way of greeting:

-
With your permission, Miss.

As distressing situation that left his face and dilated blood reappeared in it the universal benevolent
smile which was his principal ornament.

Arrival the group where they were Counsellor, D. Martin, Osuna and
another military gentleman was greeted Lancia with joy.

- I present
- said D. Stranger to his friend Martin, lowering his voice and glancing
suspiciously around to make sure his wife could not hear him - the
father Norbert, a priest who will be able report all the huts of the
people, if you want to know any.

- Oh, oh! D. Martin, by God!

-
Dare you to say they do not know!

- Well, yes ... some know ... Unfortunately,
I need to enter them once ...

- This man is dedicated to the lost
youth - continued D. Martin, addressing his companion, smiling in
amazement.

- Jesus!

Consider, D. Martin, who this gentleman does not know me ...

- But that knows you talk.

Ms Eloisa, by far, cast glances of terror to her husband, noting the confusion of D. Norberto and
the laughter of others.

- Well - continued Mr. de las Casas, becoming cautious and conciliatory,
- I will not tell, D. Norbert, you go with bad idea to these houses
of iniquity, but what always argue is that it is you provide a great
service: you're making a killing.

- How, how? - Scared the cleric
asked.

- Very simple, helping to raise the price of the commodity.

Recall the example Carmen the zapatillera ...

This was a girl whom
Fr Norberto had managed to get a house of prostitution and lead to
a convent.

After some time he went out and returned to the bad life.

D. became Norberto to persuade her to repent, and again she came and gave asylum to vice.

- And what does that matter? ...

- I'll explain, Father, I will explain ... Meet you ... When you catechized Carmen, I do not deny that
the merchandise was quite undervalued and ...

- I do not know!

What things have you, D. Martin! - Said the cleric embarrassed.

- I know, father, I know.

Well, after he spent a year there and a bit fatter in the convent
and became surrounded by an aura of honesty, the price rose significantly.

You take it back when I was a bit estropeadilla and demand had diminished to a point raised
fears for the bucolic, and now it comes again chubby and sanctified
is quoted again as in their heyday.

- Jesus!

Jesus! Go all for God - said the priest covered their ears, but not angry .-- you will be very
bad, D. Martin.

Ms Eloisa, it warned that what was happening, finally rose from his
chair and came toward them, asking in a bad mood:

- Do not play today
ombre?

- Here we go, here we go - her husband said, stifling laughter
that flowed from the body, such as others.

They sat Adviser, D. Norbert and he was at table, and soon block out
all worldly sounds fascinating under the influence of the sword, the
bad and the rough.

Shortly after Councillor gnashed his teeth and mustache pulled cruelly, being twice followed with
three clubs, his personal enemy. Many years ago that had declared a war to death. Every time I
came to the hands, twitched Chief, swore silently like a trooper. The three of clubs, malicious
and cunning as any other card, enjoyed apparently irritated him, and whenever he could sneak nicely
in the pile he distributed.

Not only in the party, but in the whole village was known this antipathy. Some, with certain precautions,
of course, because D. Romualdo easy shooting I teased her.

On one occasion, angling behind the church, pulled in hook a card that turned out to be the three
of clubs.

He had no doubt that he had thrown there on purpose, but said nothing
so as not to laugh.

Osuna meantime had gone to rub a little against Ms Eloisa. Among all the ladies attending that
gathering there were only two fat, Ms Teodora and Ms Eloisa. Was also good meat Ms Rita, but it
was soft, yellow. Other "pure Scotland," as he called the skinny, referring to cod. So there
was no end to our contempt Hunchback professed that degenerate society and exhausted from adipose
tissue. Just going by there to find his daughter, or materially did not know where to shelter. Ms
Eloisa looked sympathetic (as I watched all the good lady) the passion that the monster seemed
feel to it. When you are too close, gently parted without extinction so his kindly smile.
Ms Teodora Instead you had a great fear, real fear. The same approach was Osuna, who was already
suffocating caste buxom, restless, color it was and another was coming. But such was the shame
he felt, had not declared to his own father's dirty insinuations misshapen. What is the difference
between this indecent and serene, majestic and romantic D. Juan Casanova! D. Ni Peregrin could
compare with, to be the latter, by way of the mature girl, a subject
much more voluptuous and land.

D. Pilgrims had arrived, as usual, in the past. And if the gathering is not warned most strident
of nasal snorts, as infinitely more solemn blink and the serious way to put a leg over the other
and lean back to something important, important, had to communicate was that he did not want
to notice. He waited patiently, like all men sure of success, to have a break, and when he arrived,
he uttered with his shrill voice, piercing, turning to the lady of the house:

- Do not you know whom I have just seen entering the house of his brother, accompanied by excused?

A
Obdulia he jumped so hard the heart that thought hit the ground. Other, including Ms Eloisa,
looked up curiously.

- Who was that?

- Your sister Joaquina - cried more that said former acting governor of Tarragona, as announced
Judgement Day.

Deep stupor throughout the party.

- My sister! - Exclaimed.

- His own sister - confirmed D. Peregrin with trumpeting horrid.

- There can be - said Ms Eloisa.

- There can be - said her husband,
suspending the game.

- There can be - repeated Ms Serafina Barrado.

The ex-governor of Tarragona let out through the nose some deafening
snorts as an engine that displaces the excess steam, and said:

-
Do you think, gentlemen, I have no eyes in his head?

This momentous question, accompanied by the appropriate frown, produced
enough impression among the switches.

- Well you could have been
mistaken - said the invalid.

- It's so easy! - Said Ms Eloisa.

-
I've seen as you see them now, three steps away.

I came to talk to the clerk to the issue of the anniversary of my
father, when the hole street Quadrant I to P. Gil with a lady who
seemed a stranger.

I wanted to know who he was, and I paused a little near the lantern,
hiding behind a doorway.

It was Joaquin, no doubt. I waited a bit and followed with his eyes until he entered the house
of Montesinos.

- But you know well? - Asked P. Narciso.

- The same as you.

- Peregrin, please note that you have not done more than a visit to Madrid, and the night, as
I've said - she said timidly D. Juan.

The ex-governor threw his brother a look of unutterable contempt.

- John, do not put the leg.

- Peregrin I do not know why ...

- John! ...

- Peregrin! ...

- Do not the goal!

Not the goals! A lady that I saw after visiting another portion times in the street, and I welcomed.
Therefore, I feel the sad need to show yourself what you just said is an impertinence. When assured
that I knew this lady, is because the know. I never talk to smoke with straw. If I were a man
light and baseless could not occupy the positions I have occupied. Sírvate of government.

- Now I remember - Candida said, - today I have seen alighting from the coach to a blond lady with
a very elegant dress.

D. Peregrin shrugged with a gesture of disdain, as if to say: 'What
you come in my support to counter the absurdities of this fool?

"

That data and concluded that gesture to annihilate D. John, whose face expressed dejection. But
Ms Theodora, with her large calm eyes, he plunged a look so warm that the factions knight, contracted
with grief, went gradually dilating, and a placid concluded by a melancholy smile on his lips
disappear. The head of D. Peregrin, however, was instantly crossed by a portion of wrinkles.
The undeniable superiority was about his brother, what he used? The better showing in front of the
fresh ham, the more it was inclined to favor.

Right the trial judge Tarragona when he said that the woman was a tissue of contradictions.

Obdulia
felt an intense joy, infinite, we fell in streams within the soul. His body, enervated, unable
to move, suddenly became the lightness of a bird. I wanted to go promptly in this room and ride
the air and sing their joy. Anyone could see the change in her. The obstinate silence followed
by a loquacious lying extreme a chat, pointless, interspersed with laughter that was happy strange,
venting the emotion that seized, stretching his cramped nerves. Neither knew what he was saying, or
Ms Philomena, who was talking, he learned not attentive to see the face smart Fr Narciso and enjoy
the brilliance of his jokes. Soon throat felt dry and unusual warmth in her cheeks. The Lancia
Knight, who was there remarked, he hastened to inform Osuna, that his daughter's eyes were black
and shiny and to sit very well embodied rosettes that had taken heat in the face.

The news had been feeling at all. There were few who knew where his wife Montesinos, although
everyone knew the incidents of marital drama that he had withdrawn the Peñascosa entailed estate.
But what was just curious strangers, the good Dona Eloisa offered, of course, with the appearance
of deep and profound emotion. Intended course to find out what happened at his brother, later sought
to be her husband, wanted send a servant. A whole opposed D. Martin, seeing things more coldly,
comprised any step of these at the moment was inopportune. The conversation was extremely animated,
to the point that ombre suspended the game and took part in it. Comments that were made infinite. Thousand
scenarios were forged on the case. Some felt that the wife sorry, came to apologize to her husband, others
who made the trip just to claim of food, others that his intent was to formalize sue for divorce,
others had called her husband, unable to banish from his heart the love that the professed (Most
of the female element was inclined to this assumption), other than P. Gil, motu own, had written
to Ms Joaquin and had prepared the scene, so that D. Álvaro forgive her, others who had persuaded
him to that calling Peñascosa. Missing or not who assumed that D. Alvaro and his wife had long
corresponded, and it was she who refused to come to visit him until the present time.

- Anyway, what is beyond doubt is that the P. Gil has a very major intervention in the case
because he owns the glory of Reconciliation - said gravely D. Narciso.

-
If so - said Director.

- The will - said the chaplain .-- The will,
and here D. Maybe Martin will soon taste see a nephew who will distract
you with their antics and their thanks.

D. Martin, who his hero's soul did not detract from having a great
desire to inherit the brother, whose health was feeble, wrinkled his
nose and muttered rudely:

- I do not care.

- I do not think I can
not believe it, D. Martin.

You can not fail to cheer the noble Montesinos home is not extinct, that anyone honorably carry
this name ... Then has to look good that big house with a few guys
who rejoice with laughter and shouts.

The work of Father Gil is the most meritorious that has taken place, and why has made very good.

Obdulia
stabbed an angry look, but tempered suddenly said with a smile innocent

- You have nothing to envy, Don Narciso. Who does not remember the town's many marriages through
it are now well-matched? Without going any further, everyone knows that D. Feliciano wanted
very little to Ms. Nieves ... and as you see today are like two chicks.

This D. Feliciano was the husband who was said in secret, had broken
a leg P. Narciso throwing down the stairs.

Bystanders looked uneasily. There was an awkward silence. Counselor dropped the laughter, and exclaimed,
putting a letter on the table, as referring to the game:

- Come on, you return the other!

Everyone understood that the father was going Narciso, and this increased
concern.

The cleric blushed and whispered:

- Thank you.

We all have an obligation ...

- You go beyond the obligation, father ... Often what you do is pure
devotion - said Osuna's daughter with charming simplicity.

- Yoho
- she cried Director, staring at cards.

- What is it, D. Romualdo?
- Asked laughing D. Norberto .-- Have you played the three of clubs?

-
Yes, sir, but I take comfort that there are clubs for everyone.

-
Well, I have none - replied the priest candid.

- Another will receive!

-
We do all we can, but there is no doubt that some are stronger than
others.

Fr Gil is a saint, an apostle of the early days of the Church. None of us has the presumption of competing
with him in zeal or wisdom - expressed D. Joaquin, coming in aid
of his friend, with a chuckle poison that would jump a stone.

- In
wisdom you may have reason, D. Joaquin - Obdulia strongly replied,
- but zeal, I think you are wrong.

You're too modest ... There is flatter, but in the case of jealousy,
I think you're as jealous as the first, right, Dona Serafina?

A grunt escaped all strange point at the time of the throat of Director,
to which was immediately followed by a violent fit of coughing that
left him breathless by some seconds.

D. Joaquin also felt some itching in the throat, forcing him to cough
back head.

Ms Serafina did not answer the question, because I was distracted talking to Ms Eloisa.

The conversation veered, as if tacitly all agreed that this was dangerous. Soon after he ceased
to be general, and returned to form the usual cliques

.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>