<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03750</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>331936</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21524</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> En esa tosca llave mohosa se había posado su blanca mano. Quiso abrir, y luego se contuvo,
temeroso de borrar las trazas de aquella mano. Pero su brazo se extendió otra vez, y la puerta
gimió sobre sus goznes. Su temblor aumentó. Allí, en la capilla la veía delante de él, arrodillada,
la cabeza baja, las manos juntas, vuelta hacia el altar, cubierta con un vestido color de fuego...

Vérod cayó de rodillas, rompiendo a llorar. Y en medio de su llanto oyó claramente la voz que
le decía: «Perdona...»

Al día siguiente le llamó el juez. Era la primera vez que se encontraba ante el magistrado
desde el día en que éste, después de triunfar sobre sus argumentos, le había dicho que creyera
en el suicidio. La confusión del joven era extrema, pues no sabía qué podían querer de él todavía.

--Necesitaba, ante todo--le dijo Ferpierre,--reconocer mi error y decir a usted que tenía razón.
Ha sido providencial que usted insistiera en la acusación, a despecho de la evidencia, porque
sin la insistencia de usted, sin la confianza de que le vi animado, yo habría probablemente
dejado de mano las indagaciones ulteriores que me han conducido al descubrimiento de la verdad.
Sin duda a estas horas usted sabe ya lo que ha pasado; pero yo he querido confirmarle personalmente
que su amiga ha sido asesinada. La Natzichet ha confesado su delito, y el Príncipe, que se
había callado en la esperanza de poder salvarla, ha confirmado su confesión.

Roberto Vérod permanecía mudo y confuso.

--¿Está usted contento ahora?

El joven no contestó.

--Ha prestado usted un servicio a la justicia. Sin usted, el asesinato habría quedado impune,
o lo que es peor, un inocente habría pagado la culpa ajena. Había un culpable y el instinto
que se lo advertía a usted no le engañaba: la única diferencia es que las acusaciones de usted
contra el Príncipe han resultado infundadas.

Ferpierre se calló otra vez un momento para dar a Vérod tiempo para decir algo, y luego, como
éste siguiera silencioso, continuó:

--El Príncipe no podía querer la muerte de la Condesa cuando volvía a amarla, con un amor vehemente
y tímido a la vez, que obligaba, a un rebelde como él, a desistir de su propaganda revolucionaria,
a renegar de su pasado, de su fe política, de sus cómplices. Y eso era porque sabía que usted
estimaba y había obtenido el afecto de la Condesa, aquel afecto antes desdeñado por él. ¡Así
razona el corazón humano!... Entonces su cómplice le vio perdido, no solamente para el partido
sino aun para ella misma, porque le amaba y sufría al pensar en que era de otra, al verse confidente
de aquel amor resucitado. Y fue en busca de la rival, a imponerla que le dejara, y tuvo con
ella una tempestuosa explicación que terminó con el delito. Todo lo ha confesado.

Hubo una nueva pausa del juez, a la que Vérod opuso todavía silencio.

--¿Está usted contento?--le preguntó el juez.

--¿Por qué me lo pregunta usted?

Y los dos hombres se miraron fijamente.

--Debería usted estar contento, me parece, de haber vengado la memoria de su amiga, confundiendo
a la reo y obteniendo el triunfo de la verdad y de la justicia.

Ambos volvieron a mirarse en silencio.

--¿Y usted no está contento?...--dijo por fin Vérod.

En la pregunta del juez había visto una especie de incitación, casi una provocación a decir
por entero su secreto pensamiento, como si su pensamiento secreto fuera el mismo del juez.

--Yo no tengo pasiones que satisfacer--respondió éste.--Un solo amor me guía: el amor de la
justicia...

--Si se ha hecho justicia...

--¿Lo duda usted?

--A mí no me tocar dudar...

--¿Quiere usted decir, entonces, que yo debo dudar? ¿Y por qué?... Usted ha denunciado un crimen:
el crimen está probado. Usted no ha sabido decir cuál de los dos posibles autores del delito
fuese realmente culpable, toda vez que ambos eran capaces de delinquir: ¡la culpable se acusa
a sí misma!... ¿Querría usted decir quizás que la sola confesión no basta? ¡Yo lo sé! Pero
eso es cuando no está comprobada. Un loco puede declararse autor de un delito, mas no podrá
dar las razones de su acto, ni explicar sus circunstancias. Pero aquí ¿no está explicado todo?
¿La declaración del otro no la confirma?... ¿O niega usted fe a esta prueba?

--Sí--prorrumpió Vérod, cuyas dudas habían ido creciendo hasta manifestarse con precisión,
robustecidas por las curiosas preguntas del juez.--Sí; le niego fe, como usted también se la
niega, porque esa declaración no es desinteresada, desde que el que la dio tenía en mira su
propia libertad; porque no solamente un loco puede declararse autor de un delito que no ha
cometido, sino también aquel que quiere sacrificarse...

--¿Entonces, usted sostiene?...

--Sostengo--añadió el joven rápidamente, como si quisiera no darse el tiempo de pensar en lo
que decía, y para hablar se venciera a sí mismo:--sostengo que esa mujer se sacrifica por amor,
por celo sectario; que el asesino aprovecha de su sacrificio para asegurarse la impunidad.
Digo que el asesino es él, que no puede ser otro que él...

Sí; Vérod tenía que decir eso. La voz del perdón se callaba; esa voz jamás había hablado. Aquello
había sido un sueño, una alucinación. La verdad era otra: el ser amado yacía bajo tierra, las
manchas de su sangre no se habían borrado aún; la sangre pedía venganza, y él debía obtenerla.

--¿Por qué no lo dijo usted antes? ¿Por qué vaciló al principio?

--Porque aún no sabía, porque no había reflexionado lo bastante; porque usted no creía en el
delito y todas mis fuerzas se concretaban a negar el suicidio.

--¿De modo que no sólo ese hombre habría matado, sino que llevaría su infamia hasta dejar condenar
a una inocente?

--¿Se asombra usted? ¿No es natural que ese individuo esté lleno de júbilo?

--¡Esa idea es horrible! Comprendo que el odio lo ciegue a usted, pero yo no soy ciego. Ese
hombre no es tan perverso como usted cree: en su vida hay actos de valor, y su actitud en presencia
del cadáver y en los primeros días de la prisión no ha sido de júbilo.

--En los primeros días... ¿Y en los demás?

Al oír aquella pregunta, el juez reflexionó un momento antes de contestar.

Era verdad. Cuando la nihilista confesó, él había prestado crédito inmediato a su confesión;
pero la duda comenzaba ya a asaltarlo de nuevo. Si la joven se sacrificaba, ¿qué valor debía
acordar a su confesión y a la confirmación de ésta por el Príncipe?... No obstante, él había
interrogado de nuevo a uno y a otro, separadamente y juntos, y ambos se habían mantenido firmes
en sus declaraciones.

En el careo les había descubierto algunas contradicciones: mientras la Natzichet aseguraba
que en el punto culminante de su explicación con la Condesa, oyendo la voz conturbada del Príncipe
que llamaba, había disparado el tiro, temerosa de que al aparecer él ya no se le hubiera presentado
otra oportunidad de deshacerse de su rival, el Príncipe afirmaba, por el contrario, haber acudido
al oír el tiro desde lejos. Puestos nuevamente el uno frente al otro, la Natzichet se había
corregido, declarando que creyó oír su voz, pero sin duda en su sobreexcitación se había engañado.
Otros pequeños pormenores habían afirmado a Ferpierre en la sospecha de que, como en los anteriores
interrogatorios, en ese también la joven tomaba en cierto modo la iniciativa de la explicación
del drama, e incitaba al Príncipe a seguirla; pero, con todo, estaba decidido a enviarla ante
los jueces para que el debate público acabara de arrojar la luz sobre aquel misterio.

Antes, sin embargo, había querido llamar a Vérod para ver si también él dudaba, para discutir
con él sus nuevas sospechas.

--En los primeros días estaba oprimido por el dolor--contestó, después de haber examinado todo
aquello mentalmente una vez más;--pero después se vio que la prisión le hacía sufrir.

--¿Ve usted?--exclamó Vérod.--Al principio comprendió el error de su crimen; más tarde, vio
que su libertad era segura. ¡El medio ha sido demasiado fácil!

Así había pensado también Ferpierre. Aquel hombre, en quien se sucedían repentinamente diversas
impulsiones, que no era totalmente incapaz de practicar el bien, pero que obedecía con mayor
prontitud a las insinuaciones del mal, había estado, sin duda, próximo a confesar; pero la
disposición de su espíritu había cambiado de un momento a otro, y entonces, ansioso de libertad,
no había tenido escrúpulo para aferrarse a la tabla de salvación.

--Si él es tan infame, ¿quiere decir que la Natzichet posee un corazón heroico?

--¿Qué le impide a usted admitirlo?

Lejos de negarlo, el magistrado había reconocido expresamente que por el ardor de su fe, por
la tenacidad de sus sentimientos, la joven era capaz del heroísmo.

--Pero ¿cómo sorprenderla? ¡Su explicación del delito era completa! Tenía dos razones para
cometerlo: el amor y el fanatismo.

--¿Uno y otro no debían aconsejarla que salvara al hombre amado y al correligionario?

También eso era cierto. Si el Príncipe había muerto a la Condesa, la joven debía intentar salvarle,
tanto por amor al hombre, como por amor al partido.

--Bien; pero ¿y la prueba?

--¡Ah! ¡la prueba! ¡Hay que encontrarla todavía!

--Pues entonces, y mientras encontramos esa prueba, tanta razón tiene usted de insistir en
su sospecha, como yo en volver a mi primera opinión.

--¿Por qué?

--¡Porque sí! ¡Yo vuelvo a creer que la Condesa se ha matado!

--¿Después que ellos admiten la existencia del delito?

--¿Y cómo la admiten? ¡Usted no sabe cómo, en qué circunstancias se ha declarado culpable la
Natzichet! ¡Confesó cuando yo la dije que el Príncipe había confesado! ¡Le vio perdido y quiso
salvarle!

--¿Y eso no le demuestra a usted de una manera luminosa que él, sólo él es el asesino?

--¡Pero él nada ha confesado! ¡Yo fui quien dije eso, como recurso desesperado!

--¡Y no ve usted que dijo la verdad!--arguyó Vérod.--¡Si esa mujer hubiera sabido que Zakunine
era inocente, se habría reído al oírle a usted! ¡No lo habría creído! ¡Habría descubierto el
ardid! ¿Cómo podría creer que su amigo había confesado una culpa jamás cometida por él? Si
esa mujer creyó lo que usted la dijo, ello significa que usted dijo inconscientemente la verdad.
¡Y ha querido salvarle, porque le ha visto realmente perdido!

Ferpierre no contestó.

Estaba maravillado de no haberse hecho aún esa obvia observación entre tantas otras. Y sentía
todo el peso de la clarísima observación, y veía, además, que si ésta correspondía a la verdad,
él se había extraviado por un falso camino.

--¡Hipótesis o presunción como todas las demás!--exclamó bruscamente, deseoso de negar, por
medio de la confusión, la importancia que en su interior atribuía a las palabras del joven.
Lo único que hacemos es pasar de una hipótesis a otra, ¡Si la Condesa no se ha matado, ha sido
asesinada; si no ha sido asesinada, se ha dado la muerte por su mano! El delito es obra de
la nihilista, si no ha sido cometido por Zakunine; ¡si la nihilista es inocente, Zakunine es
el reo! ¡El apasionamiento de usted no constituye una prueba! ¡Mientras no me traiga usted
una prueba más válida de sus apasionadas afirmaciones, por muy severos que queramos ser con
los acusados, no podremos hacer otra cosa que absolverlos a ambos, por falta de indicios!

Y casi bruscamente, le dijo que podía retirarse.

Cuando se quedó solo dio orden de que no se dejara entrar a nadie más. La gravedad de sus pensamientos
en ese instante y la irritación que sentía contra sí mismo, no le permitían ocuparle de otro
asunto.

La observación que le había hecho Vérod era justísima: ¿Cómo negar su valor? Si tantas dudas
había concebido ya él mismo sobre la confesión de la Natzichet, ¿cómo no admitir aquélla? Era
la más considerable de todas. ¿Así, pues, la pasión del joven servía de algo, mientras que
la sangre fría que él estaba obligado a mostrar de nada servía, puesto que el joven era quien
veía con mayor claridad?

Cierto; sin el ardid que había empleado con la nihilista, el Príncipe y ella misma habrían
continuado negando, escudándose con la verosimilitud del suicidio. Era también evidente que
de los dos, el más cuidadoso de la salvación común había sido, desde los primeros días, la
Natzichet. En todos los interrogatorios se había esforzado visiblemente por empujar al Príncipe
a la defensa. Había reconocido ser su querida y le había exigido que confirmara esta declaración,
deseosa de impedir que se descubriera la resurrección de su amor por la Condesa, resurrección
que podía hacer sospechar que la causa del delito fueran los celos. Después, creyendo que Zakunine
se había confesado celoso y reo, había inventado su propia intervención entre los dos actores
del drama. ¿El silencio y la tristeza de Zakunine, no podían ser, no eran, el remordimiento
del culpable? Como quiera que fuese, el Príncipe se había mostrado, durante los primeros días,
tal vez en fuerza de tanto dolor, indiferente a su suerte.

Todo esto hacía pensar a Ferpierre que en realidad había cometido un error al emplear su ardid
contra la joven: más bien debía haber dicho al Príncipe que la Natzichet se confesaba culpable.
Y debía haberlo dicho cuando Zakunine estaba aún bajo el peso del dolor; entonces, probablemente,
no habría tolerado que otra persona sufriera por él, y habría confesado la verdad.

¡La verdad!... Si esta era la verdad verdadera, ¿cómo saberlo? Puesto que la Natzichet quería
salvar al Príncipe, ¿no habría hecho, después de que éste se hubiese confesado en realidad
culpable, lo mismo que hizo al oír el relato capcioso del juez? ¡Y entonces, acusándose uno
y otro, la confesión habría sido mayor! O ¡quién sabe si el careo habría sido fructuoso!

Pero ya los careos eran inútiles. Decidido a aprovechar de la generosidad de la joven, Zakunine
la reconocía culpable, y desde que ella insistía en su confesión, ¿cómo desmentirlos?

Ferpierre pensó en volver a llamar a la Natzichet y decirla: «¿Usted cree haberle salvado?
¡Lejos de eso, le ha perdido usted! ¿Por qué ha confesado usted? ¿Porque yo la dije que él
mismo me había confesado haber muerto a la Condesa? Pues bien: ¡eso no es cierto; él no ha
confesado nada! Yo he dicho una mentira. Pero ahora veo que ésta que yo creía mentira, es verdad,
y usted misma, sin quererlo, o mejor dicho, queriendo lo contrario, me lo ha probado. Si hubiera
sido mentira, usted se habría reído al oiría. Y, en cambio, ha temblado usted por él, y ha
tratado de salvarle, aunque en vano...»

Pero Ferpierre se detuvo bruscamente, previendo que la joven no se habría quedado sin contestar:
«No me reí de la mentira, porque en vez de risa tenía que causarme pena. Creyendo que usted
me decía la verdad, pensó que Zakunine se acusaba por salvarme, y como él es inocente y yo
soy la culpable, no me reí, sino que temblé y dije a usted la verdad...»

¿Qué contestar a eso? ¿Y cómo probarla que mentía?... ¿Y si no mentía? ¿Si era realmente culpable?
¿Si su conducta no era la de una heroína salvadora, sino la de una reo confesa? ¿Cuál era la
razón para no creerla verdaderamente culpable? ¿Era posible que con tanta habilidad hubiera
construido y descripto con tantos colores un falso desenlace del drama; que hubiera sabido
relatar un cúmulo de mentiras con voz tan turbada, con expresión tan sincera?

Entonces Ferpierre volvía a medir las probabilidades, a ahondar las presunciones, a rehacer
la tarea de todos aquellos días, deteniéndose ya en una, ya en otra hipótesis, reconociendo
una vez más las inextricables dificultades del caso.

¿Debía renunciar positivamente a toda investigación ulterior? ¿Había que perder en realidad
la esperanza de obtener una prueba incontrovertible? ¿Y cómo concluir el largo y ya vano sumario?
¿Rechazando la acusación, afirmando que la Condesa se había matado, y que la Natzichet se acusaba
solamente por el temor de ver condenado al Príncipe, aunque era tan inocente como él, y que
por esta razón las versiones de uno y otra no habían estado de acuerdo?... ¿O volviendo a la
hipótesis, ya excluida como la más improbable, de que ambos fuesen culpables, de que la Natzichet
hubiera ayudado a su amante a ejecutar el asesinato con el robo por móvil, y tratado después
de salvarle, acusándose?

Cada una de estas conclusiones repugnaba al magistrado; pero éste necesitaba decidirse por
alguna, y ya pensaba en hacer una última tentativa cerca de los dos rusos, cuando, no obstante
las órdenes que había dado, oyó llamar a la puerta. El ujier, pidiendo disculpa por la contravención,
le entregó un pliego del procurador general: dos palabras subrayadas en un ángulo del sobre,
indicaban que la comunicación era urgente.

Ferpierre rompió distraídamente el sobre, pues nada le parecía urgente si no era salir de una
situación tan ambigua. Dentro había dos papeles: un telegrama y una nota del procurador general.
Este le escribía:

«Transmito a usted inmediatamente el despacho que se acaba de recibir del cónsul helvético
en Edimburgo. Ahora podremos, por fin, saber con precisión algo sobre el misterio de Ouchy.»

Y con mano que la ansiedad hacía temblar, Ferpierre abrió la otra hoja, que decía:

«Sor Ana Brighton vive en Stonehaven, Condado de Kincardine, Escocia. Ya se ha acordado lo
necesario con la magistratura inglesa para recibir su declaración.»

Ya la curiosidad pública se había despertado, más ansiosa que nunca, al saberse que la instrucción
no estaba cerrada aún como se decía primero; que el magistrado desconfiaba de la confesión
de Alejandra Natzichet, y que todo volvía a quedar sujeto a nuevas dudas en el momento en que
el misterio parecía descubierto. Las discusiones recrudecían, apasionadas e inútiles, entre
los que sostenían la sinceridad de los nihilistas, los que veían en su conducta una nueva prueba
de la culpabilidad del Príncipe y los que volvían con mayor confianza a la versión del suicidio,
imputando a los métodos inquisitoriales del magistrado la confesión arrancada a una inocente.
Pero los más reconocían que la justicia se encontraba en presencia de uno de aquellos casos
dudosos de cuya solución hay que desesperar hasta que alguna circunstancia inesperada viene
a aclararlos, y que con mayor frecuencia permanecen irresolutos para siempre.

La noticia de que por fin se había encontrado a Ana, llevó la curiosa expectación al grado
de la fiebre. Su declaración, la última carta que le había dirigido la Condesa, pocas horas
antes de su muerte, lo iban a explicar todo.

No era general, sin embargo, esta confianza, y el mismo Ferpierre, después de su primer movimiento
de estupor y de placer al recibir comunicación del telegrama, temía no poder salir aún de la
duda. Si la muerta hubiera confesado que iba a suicidarse, si había enviado a la hermana su
último adiós, ésta, al recibir la carta, al leer aquel anuncio, ¿no habría debido acudir, o
por lo menos contestar, o tratar de conseguir otras noticias, de saber si Florencia había puesto
en ejecución su funesto propósito? Y puesto que todos los periódicos del mundo habían hablado
de la catástrofe, de la acusación, de los arrestos y del sumario, ¿no era para la religiosa
un deber de conciencia enviar la carta a la justicia? Esta nada había recibido; por consiguiente,
la carta no anunciaba el suicidio.

Natural era, pues, considerar como singularmente empeorada la condición de los acusados. Si
faltaba en la carta una explícita alusión al desesperado propósito de su autora, tenía que
parecer menos probable que nunca el que, una hora después, ésta se hubiera matado; pero ¿a
cuál de los dos acusados se debía imputar el delito? ¿Se podía abrigar la esperanza de que
la Condesa hubiera expresado en la carta el temor suscitado en ella por la amenazadora actitud
de uno u otra? ¿No era más probable que la carta no fuese explícita en sentido alguno, y que,
aun confirmando la angustia que embargaba a la infeliz, no anunciara la intención de ésta de
morir? En tal caso, la ambigüedad iba a subsistir.

Una primera noticia, dada por los diarios ingleses que anunciaban el descubrimiento del paradero
de sor Ana Brighton, destruyó las dudas del magistrado. La religiosa, decían esas hojas, estaba
atacada de una grave parálisis, había perdido el uso del cuerpo y de la palabra.

Un telegrama de Londres para el Journal de Genève precisó, al día siguiente, que la enfermedad
databa de un mes, y que el ataque apoplético, según la declaración de la prima de sor Ana,
su única parienta, la había sobrevenido al leer una noticia funesta.

Y cuando una semana después, recibió Ferpierre con la confirmación de estos rumores el expediente
formado por el magistrado escocés, vio que una vez más se había equivocado en sus previsiones.
Sor Ana no había podido contestar a la Condesa ni iluminar a la justicia porque al leer la
carta de su antigua alumna predilecta había caído como muerta.

Aquella carta, hallada a su lado y unida al informe junto con otras que no tenían importancia,
decía:

«Sor Ana, ruegue usted por mí. Ruegue usted mucho, con todo el fervor de su buena alma, porque
tengo necesidad de mucho perdón.

»Esta es la última carta mía que usted recibe. Si un día sabe usted lo que he hecho, recuerde
usted el nombre que siempre desde la primera vez que gocé de sus caricias quiso darme: recuerde
usted que me ha llamado hija suya y como a tal me ha amado: para su hija siempre será usted
indulgente.

»Dios lee en mi corazón. A usted no puedo ni quiero decir qué tempestad me destroza. ¡Bendita
usted que no conoce el error! ¿Para qué hablarle de aquello con que yo lucho? Piense usted
solamente esto: que si he pecado mucho, ahora quiero huir de otras culpas. Me encuentro reducida
a una condición tal, que todo es para mí culpa y error. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05419</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>88412</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19601</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> In the rusty key crude had settled her white hand. Wanted to open, then held, afraid to erase
the traces of his hand. But his arm is extended again, and the door groaned on its hinges. Her
trembling increased. There, in the chapel he saw before him, kneeling, head bowed, hands together,
turned toward the altar, covered with a dress the color of fire ...

Candle plant fell to his knees, breaking to mourn.

And amid their cries distinctly heard the voice would say, "Sorry ..."

The next day I called the judge. It was the first time was before
the judge from the day he, after triumphing over their arguments,
he had said he believed suicide.

The young man was extreme confusion, not knowing what they could want from him yet.

- I needed first and foremost - Ferpierre said - to acknowledge my error and tell you he was
right. It was providential that you insisted on the prosecution, in spite of the evidence, because
without the insistence of you without the confidence that saw him animated, I would probably Hand made
further investigations which have led me to discover the truth. No doubt this time you already
know what happened, but I wanted to personally confirm that your
friend has been murdered.

The Natzichet has confessed his crime, and Principe, was silent in
the hope to save her, has confirmed his confession.

Roberto candle plant remained silent and confused.

- Are you happy now?

The young man replied.

- Have you provided a service to justice. Without you, the murder would have gone unpunished, or worse,
an innocent man would have paid the fault of others. There was a guilty and instinct I noticed that
you do not deceive: the only difference is that the charges you against the Prince have proved
unfounded.

Ferpierre again paused a moment to give candle plant time to say something, and then as he continued
silent, he continued:

- Prince could not desire the death of the Countess when he came to
love with a passionate love and shy at once, compelling, a rebel like
him to abandon his revolutionary propaganda, to renounce their past,
their political faith, their accomplices.

And that was because I knew you estimated and obtained the affection
of the Countess, that affection before he disdained.

So reasons the human heart ... Then he saw his partner lost, not
only for the match but even for herself, because she loved him and
suffered at the thought that there was another, to be confident that
love is risen.

It was in search of the rival, to let him enforce it, and they had
she ended a stormy explanation to the crime.

Everything he confessed.

There was a pause of the judge, which opposed candle plant still silent.

-
Are you happy? - Asked the judge.

- Why do you ask?

And the two men stared.

- Should you be happy, I think, had avenged his friend's memory, confusing
the inmate and obtaining the triumph of truth and justice.

Both turned to look in silence.

- And you are not happy ?...-- candle
plant said finally.

In the judge's question had been a sort of incitement, almost a provocation to say entirely his
secret thoughts, as if their secret thought was the same judge.

- I have no passion to meet - he answered .-- One Love guides me: the love of justice ...

- If you have done justice ...

- Do you doubt?

- I do not doubt ... play

- Are you saying then that I should doubt? So why ... You have reported a crime: the crime is
proved. You have not been able to tell which of two possible perpetrators of the crime were truly
guilty, given that both were capable of committing a crime: the guilty are accused itself!
... Would you perhaps say that the confession alone is not enough?

I know! But That is when it is not proven. A fool can declare an offender, but can not give reasons
for its action, or explain your circumstances. But here Is not it explained everything? "The
declaration confirms the other not? ... Or do you deny faith to the test?

- Yes - broke candle plant, whose doubts had grown to express precisely Weird being strengthened
by the judge's questions .-- Yes, you deny faith, as you are also
the denied, because that statement is not disinterested, since he
had that look in your own freedom, because only a madman can not declare
an offender who has not committed, but who wants to sacrifice ...

-
So, you argue?

...

- I argue - added the young man quickly, as if to not take the time
to think about what he said, and was beat to talk to himself - argue
that this woman is sacrificed for love sectarian zeal, that the murderer
takes advantage of his sacrifice to ensure impunity.

I say the murderer is he who can not be other than him ...

Yes, candle plant had to say that. The silent voice of forgiveness,
that voice had never spoken.

What had been a dream, a hallucination.

The truth was otherwise: the beloved lay underground, his blood stains
had not been cleared yet, the requested blood revenge, and he should
get it.

- Why do not you said before?

Why hesitated at first?

- Why did not yet know, because I had not thought enough, because you do not believe in crime
and they identified all my strength to deny suicide.

- "So not only would have killed this man, but to let his infamy would condemn an innocent?

-
Are you surprised? Is not it natural that this man is full of joy?

- That idea is horrible! I understand what blind hate you, but I'm not blind. This Man is not as evil
as you believe: in life there are acts of courage, and his attitude in the presence the body
and in the early days of the prison has not been a joy.

- In the early days ... What about others?

Upon hearing that question, the judge thought for a moment before answering.

It was true.

When the nihilistic confessed, he had given immediate credit to his confession; but doubt was
beginning to assault him again. If the girl was sacrificed, what
value should agree to his confession and confirmation of it by Prince?

... However, he had again questioned one and another, separately and together, and both had
remained firm in their statements.

In the confrontation they had found some contradictions: while assuring Natzichet that at the
height of his explanation with the countess, hearing the voice of Prince troubled I called,
had fired the shot, afraid to show him and he had not been submitted another opportunity to get
rid of his rival, Prince said, however, have gone when he heard the
shooting from afar.

Again placed facing each other, had Natzichet corrected, stating
that he thought he heard her voice, but certainly in his excitement
he was mistaken.

Other small details Ferpierre had affirmed the suspicion that, as
in previous interrogation, in that the girl also somewhat took the
initiative of the explanation the drama, and urged the Prince to follow,
but, nevertheless, was determined to send to judges to the public
debate had just shed light on the mystery.

Before that, however, had wanted to call candle plant to see if he too doubted, to discuss
with him his new suspicion.

- In the early days were oppressed by the pain - he replied, after examining all mentally that again,
- but then saw that the prison made him suffer.

- Do you see? - Said candle plant .-- At first realized the error
of his crime, and later saw that their freedom was safe.

The media has been too easy!

So also thought Ferpierre.

One man, who suddenly happened several drives, which was not totally
incapable of doing good, but that was due more advances rapidly to
evil, had been, without doubt, next to confess, but the available
had changed his mind at any moment, and then yearns for freedom, had
no qualms about holding on to the raft.

- If he is so outrageous,
does it mean that the hero has a heart Natzichet?

- What prevents
you admit it?

Far from denying it, the judge had expressly recognized by the ardor of their faith, the tenacity
of her feelings, she was capable of heroism.

- But how to surprise?

His explanation of the crime was complete!

He had two reasons for commit: love and fanaticism.

- Does one and one should not advise that could save the man she loved and the fellow?

This was also true. If the Prince had died at the Countess, she was trying to save, much love for
humanity, for love of the game.

- Well, but what about the test?

- Ah! Test! We must find it yet!

- Well then, while we found that test, so why do you insist on his suspicion, as I return to
my first opinion.

- Why?

- Because! I come to believe that the Countess had been killed!

- After they admit the existence of the crime?

- And how do you support? You do not know how, under what circumstances has pleaded guilty Natzichet!
He confessed when I told her that the Prince had confessed!

I was lost and wanted save!

- And that does not show you in a lighthearted manner that he, only he is the murderer?

- But he has admitted nothing!

It was I who said that, as of desperation!

- And do not you see that telling the truth! - Argued candle plant .-- If I had known this
woman Zakunine was innocent, he would have laughed to hear you! I would not have believed it! Would
have discovered trick! How could he believe that his friend had ever confessed a sin committed by
him? If this woman believed what you said, this means that subconsciously you said the truth.
And he wanted to save him, because he has been really lost!

Ferpierre not answer.

I was astonished at not having done so obvious observation that among
many others.

And I felt full weight of the clearest observation, and saw further that if it was for the truth
he had been misled by a false path.

- Hypothesis or presumption as all the others! - Suddenly exclaimed,
eager to deny, Amid the confusion, the importance attached inside
the words of the young.

All we do is to move from one scenario to another, if the Countess has not been killed, has been
murdered, and if you have not been killed, death has come into their own hands! The crime
is the work of the nihilist, if not committed by Zakunine, if the nihilist is innocent, is
Zakunine the offender! The passion of you not a test!

Until you bring me a valid proof of their passionate statements, we want to be very severe with
defendants, we can not do otherwise than acquit them both, for lack of evidence!

And almost abruptly, he said he could retire.

When he was alone gave the order to not let anyone else. The gravity of his thoughts at that time
and the annoyance felt against himself, not allowed to deal with another matter.

The observation he had made candle plant was very just: How to deny
its value?

If so many questions had conceived and himself on the confession of Natzichet, why not admit it?
Was the most significant of all. So, then, the passion of the young serving of something, whereas
cold blood he was obliged to show it was no use, since the young man who see more clearly?

Certainly, without the artifice he had employed with the nihilistic, the Prince and she would
continued to deny, hide behind the likelihood of suicide. It was also clear that of the two,
the most careful of salvation had been common since the early days, Natzichet. In all interviews
had struggled visibly to push Prince to defense.

There were acknowledged to be his mistress and he was required to confirm this statement, eager
to prevent the discovery of the resurrection of his love for the Countess, resurrection could
be suspected that the cause of the crime were jealousy.

Then, believing Zakunine jealous and had pleaded guilty, had invented their own involvement
between the two actors the drama. Is the silence and sadness Zakunine could not be, was not, remorse
the culprit? Whatever it was, the Prince had shown during the first days perhaps in so much pain
force, indifferent to their fate.

All this made Ferpierre think they really had made a mistake when using your scheme against the young
man should have said rather that the Natzichet Prince pleaded guilty. And he should have said
when Zakunine was still under the weight of pain, then probably would
not have tolerated someone else suffer for it, and have confessed
the truth.

The truth! ... If this was the real truth, how do you know? Since I wanted Natzichet save the Prince,
would not have done, after it had actually confessed guilty, as he did when he heard the judge's
cunning story?

And then, accusing a and another, the confession would have been higher! Or who knows if the
confrontation would have been fruitful!

But the confrontations were useless. Determined to take advantage of the generosity of the
young Zakunine recognized her guilty, and since she insisted in his confession, how belie?

Ferpierre thought to recall the Natzichet and say: 'Do you believe you have saved? Far from
that, I lost you! Why did you confess?

Why I told him myself had confessed he had killed the Countess? Well, that's not true, he has not
confessed to anything! I have told a lie. But now I see I thought this lie is true, and yourself,
without meaning, or rather, wanting the opposite, I have tried it. If there been lying, you would
have laughed to hear it. And instead, you trembled for him, and has tried to save him, but
in vain ... "

But Ferpierre stopped abruptly, anticipating that she would not have gone unanswered: "I laughed
at the lie, because instead of laughing had to cause me grief. Believing that you I told the
truth, accusing Zakunine thought for saving me, and as he is innocent and I I'm the culprit,
I laughed, but trembled and told you the truth ... "

What answer that? And how to test it lying? ... What if I lied? If he was really guilty? If
their conduct was not of a hero saving, but a confessed offender?

What was the reason not to believe really guilty? Could have been so ably built and described with
so many colors a false outcome of the drama, which had known tell a heap of lies in a voice
so distraught, his face so sincere?

Then again Ferpierre measure likely to deepen the assumptions, to rebuild the task of all those days,
stopping and in one, and in another scenario, recognizing once again the intractable difficulties
of the case.

Should he resign positively to any further investigation?

Should we actually lose hoping to get irrefutable proof? And how long complete the vain and
file? "Rejecting the allegation, stating that the Countess had been killed, and that the accused
is Natzichet only by the fear of seeing sentenced the prince, although he was as innocent
as he, and For this reason, versions of one and the other had not agreed? ... Or back to the
hypotheses, and excluded the most unlikely, that both were guilty, that Natzichet had helped her
lover to execute the murder to the theft by phone, and treated after to save him, accusing?

Each of these conclusions repugnant to the magistrate, but it needed
to be decided by some, and thought to make one last attempt about
two Russians, when, despite had given orders, he heard knocking on
the door.

The usher, apologizing for the offense, gave a statement of the attorney general, two underlined
words in a corner of the envelope indicated that communication was urgent.

Ferpierre idly broke the envelope, because nothing seemed urgent if not leave a situation as ambiguous.
Inside were two roles: a telegram and a note from the attorney general. This he wrote:

"I transmit to you immediately at the office that just received from the Swiss Consul in Edinburgh.
Now we finally know precisely something about the mystery of Ouchy. "

And hand that shook anxiety, Ferpierre opened another sheet, which
read:

"Sister Anne lives in Stonehaven Brighton, County of Kincardine,
Scotland.

Already been agreed as necessary with the British judiciary to get a statement. "

And public curiosity had been aroused, the more anxious than ever, knowing that the instruction
was not closed yet as stated first, that the judge mistrusted confession
Alejandra Natzichet, and that everything was to be bound by new doubts
in the moment the mystery seemed to open.

The discussions raged, passionate and useless, among those who believed the sincerity of the
nihilists, those who saw in his conduct a new test Prince of guilt and with greater confidence
returning to the suicide, inquisitorial methods accusing the magistrate of an innocent confession
extracted.

But others recognized that justice was in the presence of one of those cases doubtful whose solution
must not despair until some unforeseen circumstance comes clarify them, and that most often
remain unresolved forever.
The news that had finally found Ana, took a curious anticipation
to the extent of fever. His statement, the last letter addressed to
him by the Countess, a few hours before his death, he would explain
everything.

It was not general, however, this trust, and the same
Ferpierre, after the first move of amazement and pleasure to receive
communication of the telegram, he feared not even get out of doubt.
If the dead had confessed that he would kill himself, if he sent his
sister last goodbye, this, on receiving the letter, to read that ad,
would not come due, or at least answer, or seek other news, you know
if Florence had put running their fatal purpose? And since all the
world's newspapers had talked the catastrophe, for the prosecution,
arrests and summary, was not for religious a duty of conscience to
send the letter to Justice? This all had received, therefore The letter
did not announce the suicide.

Nature was thus seen as uniquely worsened
the condition of the accused. If missing in the letter an explicit
reference to the desperate purpose of its author, had to seem less
likely than ever that an hour later, it had been killed, but at what
which of the two defendants should be liable for the crime? Could
one hope that Countess had charted the fear aroused in her by the
threatening attitude one or the other? Was not it more likely that
the letter was not explicit in any sense, and that while confirming
the anguish felt by the unfortunate, it announced it intended to die?
In this case, the ambiguity would survive.

A top story, given by
the British newspapers that announced the discovery of the whereabouts
Sister Ana Brighton, destroyed the judge's questions. The nun, said
those sheets was attack of severe paralysis, had lost the use of body
and speech.

A telegram from London to the Journal de Geneve said
the next day, the disease dating a month, and that the stroke, according
to the statement of the premium of Sister Anne his only relative,
had occurred when reading a dismal news.

And when a week later, he
Ferpierre with confirmation of these rumors the record formed by the
Scottish judge, was that once again he was wrong in their forecasts.
Sister Anne was not able to answer the Condesa or enlighten justice
because reading the letter from his former favorite pupil had fallen
as dead.

This letter, found by his side and attached to the report
along with others that did not matter, said:

"Sister Anne, you pray
for me. Pray you very much, with all the fervor of his good soul,
because I have need of much forgiveness.

"This is my last letter
you receive. If one day you know what I did, remember you name ever
since the first time I enjoyed his touch wanted me: remember you called
me his daughter and as such has loved me, for you will always be his
daughter indulgent.

"God reads in my heart. You mean I can not do
storm destroys me. Blessed you do not know the error! Why speak of
that which I fight? Think only this, that I have sinned, I want to
run away from other faults. I am Guests to a condition such that everything
is my fault and error</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>