<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>124895</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21679</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> No puedo, no... Mi conciencia se subleva...

--Déjese de sublevaciones, que no somos aquí de tropa. O usted se lleva la pesetilla, o me
enfado, como Dios es mi padre. D. Frasquito, no haga papeles, que es usted más mendigo que
el inventor del hambre. ¿O es que necesita más dinero, porque le debe más a la Bernarda? En
este caso, no puedo dárselo, porque no lo tengo... Pero no sea usted lila, D. Frasquito, ni
se haga de mieles, que esa lagartona de la Bernarda se lo comerá vivo, si no le acusa las cuarenta.
A un parroquiano como usted, de la aristocracia, no se le niega el hospedaje porque deba, un
suponer, tres noches, cuatro noches... Plántese el buen Frasquito, con cien mil pares, y verá
cómo la Bernarda agacha las orejas... Le da usted sus cuatro reales a cuenta, y... échese a
dormir tranquilo en el camastro».

O no se convencía Ponte, o convencido de lo buena que sería para él la posesión de la peseta,
le repugnaba el acto material de extender la mano y recibir la limosna. Benina reforzó su argumentación
diciéndole: «Y puesto que es el niño tan vergonzoso, y no se atreve con su patrona, ni aun
dándole a cuenta la cantidá, yo le hablaré a Bernarda, yo le diré que no le riña, ni le apure...
Vamos, tome lo que le doy, y no me fría más la sangre, Sr. D. Frasquito».

Y sin darle tiempo a formular nuevas protestas y negativas, le cogió la mano, le puso en ella
la moneda, cerrole el puño a la fuerza, y se alejó corriendo. Ponte no hizo ademán de devolverle
el dinero, ni de arrojarlo. Quedose parado y mudo; contempló a la Benina como a visión que
se desvanece en un rayo de luz, y conservando en su mano izquierda la peseta, con la derecha
sacó el pañuelo y se limpió los ojos, que le lloraban horrorosamente. Lloraba de irritación
oftálmica senil, y también de alegría, de admiración, de gratitud.

Aún tardó Benina más de una hora en llegar a la calle Imperial, porque antes pasó por la de
la Ruda a hacer sus compras. Estas hubieron de ser al fiado, pues se le había concluido el
dinero. Recaló en su casa después de las dos, hora no intempestiva ciertamente: otros días
había entrado más tarde, sin que la señora por ello se enfadara. Dependía el ser bien o mal
recibida de la racha de humor con que a Doña Paca cogía en el momento de entrar. Aquella tarde,
por desgracia, la pobre señora rondeña se hallaba en una de sus más violentas crisis de irritabilidad
nerviosa. Su genio tenía erupciones repentinas, a veces determinadas por cualquier contrariedad
insignificante, a veces por misterios del organismo difíciles de apreciar. Ello es que antes
de que Benina traspasara la puerta, Doña Francisca le echó esta rociada: «¿Te parece que son
éstas horas de venir? Tengo yo que hablar con D. Romualdo, para que me diga la hora a que sales
de su casa... Apuesto a que te descuelgas ahora con la mentira de que fuiste a ver a la niña,
y que has tenido que darle de comer... ¿Piensas que soy idiota, y que doy crédito a tus embustes?
Cállate la boca... No te pido explicaciones, ni las necesito, ni las creo; ya sabes que no
creo nada de lo que me dices, embustera, enredadora».

Conocedora del carácter de la señora, Benina sabía que el peor sistema contra sus arrebatos
de furor era contradecirla, darle explicaciones, sincerarse y defenderse. Doña Paca no admitía
razonamientos, por juiciosos que fuesen. Cuanto más lógicas y justas eran las aclaraciones
del contrario, más se enfurruñaba ella. No pocas veces Benina, inocente, tuvo que declararse
culpable de las faltas que la señora le imputaba, porque, haciéndolo así, se calmaba más pronto.

«¿Ves cómo tengo razón?--proseguía la señora, que cuando se ponía en tal estado, era de lo
más insoportable que imaginarse puede--. Te callas... quien calla, otorga. Luego es cierto
lo que yo digo; yo siempre estoy al tanto... Resulta lo que pensé: que no has subido a casa
de Obdulia, ni ese es el camino. Sabe Dios dónde habrás estado de pingo. Pero no te dé cuidado,
que yo lo averiguaré... ¡Tenerme aquí sola, muerta de hambre!... ¡Vaya una mañana que me has
hecho pasar! He perdido la cuenta de los que han venido a cobrar piquillos de las tiendas,
cantidades que no se han pagado ya por tu desarreglo... Porque la verdad, yo no sé dónde echas
tú el dinero... Responde, mujer... defiéndete siquiera, que si a todo das la callada por respuesta,
me parecerá que aún te digo poco».

Benina repitió con humildad lo dicho anteriormente: que había concluido tarde en casa de D.
Romualdo; que D. Carlos Trujillo la entretuvo la mar de tiempo; que había ido después a la
calle de la Cabeza...

«Sabe Dios, sabe Dios lo que habrás hecho tú, correntona, y en qué sitios habrás estado...
A ver, a ver si hueles a vino».

Oliéndole el aliento, rompió en exclamaciones de asco y horror: «Quita, quítate allá, borracha.
Apestas a aguardiente.

--No lo he catado, señora; me lo puede creer».

Insistía Doña Paca, que en aquellas crisis convertía en realidades sus sospechas, y con su
terquedad forjaba su convicción.

«Me lo puede creer--repitió Benina--. No he tomado más que un vasito de vino con que me obsequió
el Sr. de Ponte.

--Ya me está dando a mí mala espina ese señor de Ponte, que es un viejo verde muy zorro y muy
tuno. Tal para cual, pues también tú las matas callando... No pienses que me engañas, hipócrita...
Al cabo de la vejez, te da por la disolución, y andas de picos pardos. ¡Qué cosas se ven, Señor,
y a qué desarreglos arrastra el maldito vicio!... Te callas: luego es cierto. No; si aunque
lo negaras no me convencerías, porque cuando yo digo una cosa, es porque la sé... Tengo yo
un ojo...».

Sin dar tiempo a que la delincuente se explicara, salió por este otro registro:

«¿Y qué me cuentas, mujer? ¿Qué recibimiento te hizo mi pariente D. Carlos? ¿Qué tal? ¿Está
bueno? ¿No revienta todavía? No necesitas decirme nada, porque, como si hubiera estado yo escondidita
detrás de una cortina, sé todo lo que hablasteis... ¿A que no me equivoco? Pues te dijo que
lo que a mí me pasa es por mi maldita costumbre de no llevar cuentas. No hay quien le apee
de esa necedad. Cada loco con su tema; la locura de mi pariente es arreglarlo todo con números...
Con ellos se ha enriquecido, robando a la Hacienda y a los parroquianos; con ellos quiere al
fin de la vida salvar su alma, y a los pobres nos recomienda la medicina de los números, que
a él no le salva ni a nosotros nos sirve para nada. ¿Con que acierto? ¿Fue esto lo que te dijo?

--Sí, señora. Parece que lo estaba usted oyendo.

--Y después de machacar con esa monserga del Debe y Haber, te habrá dado una limosna para mí...
Ignora que mi dignidad se subleva al recibirla. Le estoy viendo abrir las gavetas como quien
quiere y no quiere, coger el taleguito en que tiene los billetes, ocultándolo para que no lo
vieras tú; le veo sobar el saquito, guardarlo cuidadosamente; le veo echar la llave... Y el
muy cochino se descuelga con una porquería. No puedo precisar la cantidad que te habrá dado
para mí, porque es tan difícil anticiparse a los cálculos de la avaricia; pero desde luego
te aseguro, sin temor de equivocarme, que no ha llegado a los cuarenta duros».

La cara que puso Benina al oír esto no puede describirse. La señora, que atentamente la observaba,
palideció, y dijo después de breve pausa:

«Es verdad: me he corrido mucho. Cuarenta, no; pero, aun con lo cicatero y mezquino que es
el hombre, no habrá bajado de los veinticinco duros. Menos que eso no lo admito, Nina; no puedo
admitirlo.

--Señora, usted está delirando--replicó la otra, plantándose con firmeza en la realidad--.
El Sr. D. Carlos no me ha dado nada, lo que se llama nada. Para el mes que viene empezará a
darle a usted una paga de dos duros mensuales.

--Embustera, trapalona... ¿Crees que me embaucas a mí con tus enredos? Vaya, vaya, no quiero
incomodarme... Me tiene peor cuenta, y no estoy yo para coger berrinches... Comprendido, Nina,
comprendido. Allá te entenderás con tu conciencia. Yo me lavo las manos, y dejo a Dios que
te dé tu merecido.

--¿Qué, señora?

--Hazte ahora la simple y la gatita Marirramos. ¿Pero no ves que yo te calo al instante y adivino
tus infundios? Vamos, mujer, confiésalo; no trates de añadir a la infamia el engaño.

--¿Qué, señora?

--Pues que has tenido una mala tentación... Confiésamelo, y te perdono... ¿No quieres declararlo?
Pues peor para ti y para tu conciencia, porque te sacaré los colores a la cara. ¿Quieres verlo?
Pues los veinticinco duros que te dio para mí D. Carlos, se los has dado a ese Frasquito Ponte
para que pague sus deudas, y vaya a comer de fonda, y se compre corbatas, pomada y un bastoncito
nuevo... Ya ves, ya ves, bribonaza, cómo todo te lo adivino, y conmigo no te valen ocultaciones.
Si sé yo más que tú. Ahora te ha dado por proteger a ese Tenorio fiambre, y le quieres más
que a mí, y a él le atiendes y a mí no, y de él te da lástima, y a mí, que tanto te quiero,
que me parta un rayo».

Rompió a llorar la señora, y Benina que ya sentía ganas de contestar a tanta impertinencia
dándole azotes como a un niño mañoso, al ver las lágrimas se compadeció. Ya sabía que el llanto
era la terminación de la crisis de cólera, la sedación del acceso, mejor dicho, y cuando tal
sucedía, lo mejor era soltar la risa, llevando la disputa al terreno de las burlas sabrosas.

«Pues sí, señora Doña Francisca--le dijo abrazándola--. ¿Creía usted que habiéndome salido
ese novio tan hechicero y tan saleroso, le había de dejar yo en necesidad, sin darle para el pelo?

--No creas que me engatusas con tus bromitas, trapalona, zalamera...--decía la señora, ya desarmada
y vencida--. Yo te aseguro que no me importa nada lo que has hecho, porque el dinero de Trujillete
yo no lo había de tomar... Preferiría morirme de hambre, a manchar mis manos con él... Dáselo,
dáselo a quien quieras, ingratona, y déjame a mí en paz; déjame que me muera olvidada de ti
y de todo el mundo.

--Ni usted ni yo nos moriremos tan pronto, porque aún hemos de dar mucha guerra--le dijo la
criada, disponiéndose con gran diligencia a darle de comer.

--Veremos qué porquerías me traes hoy... Enséñame la cesta... Pero, hija, ¿no te da vergüenza
de traerle a tu ama estas piltrafas asquerosas?... ¿Y qué más? coliflor... Ya me tienes apestada
con tus coliflores, que me dan flato, y las estoy repitiendo tres días... En fin, ¿a qué estamos
en el mundo más que a padecer? Dame pronto estos comistrajos... ¿Y huevos no has traído? Ya
sabes que no los paso, como no sean bien frescos.

--Comerá usted lo que le den, sin refunfuños, que el poner tantos peros a la comida que Dios
da, es ofenderle y agraviarle.

--Bueno, hija, lo que tú quieras. Comeremos lo que haya, y daremos gracias a Dios. Pero come
tú también, que me da pena verte tan ajetreada, desviviéndote por los demás, y olvidada de
ti misma y del alivio de tu cuerpo. Siéntate conmigo, y cuéntame lo que has hecho hoy».

A media tarde, comían las dos, sentaditas a la mesa de la cocina. Doña Paca, suspirando con
toda su alma, entre un bocado y otro, expresó en esta forma las ideas que bullían en su mente:

«Dime, Nina, entre tantas cosas raras, incomprensibles, qué hay en el mundo, ¿no habría un
medio, una forma... no sé cómo decirlo, un sortilegio por el cual nosotras pudiéramos pasar
de la escasez a la abundancia; por el cual todo eso que en el mundo está de más en tantas manos
avarientas, viniese a las nuestras que nada poseen?

--¿Qué dice la señora? ¿Que si podría suceder que en un abrir y cerrar de ojos pasáramos de
pobres a ricas, y viéramos, un suponer, nuestra casa llena de dinero, y de cuanto Dios crió?

--Eso quiero decir. Si son verdad los milagros, ¿por qué no sucede uno para nosotras, que bien
merecido nos lo tenemos?

--¿Y quién dice que no suceda, que no tengamos esa ocurrencia?--respondió Benina, en cuya mente
surgió de improviso, con poderoso relieve y extraordinaria plasticidad, el conjuro que Almudena
le había enseñado, para pedir y obtener todos los bienes de la tierra.

XX

De tal modo se posesionaron de su espíritu la idea y las imágenes expresadas por el ciego africano,
que a punto estuvo de contarle a su ama el maravilloso método de conjurar y hacer venir al
Rey de baixo terra. Pero recelando que aquel secreto sería menos eficaz cuanto más se divulgara,
contúvose en su locuacidad, y tan sólo dijo que bien podría suceder que de la noche a la mañana
se les metiera por las puertas la fortuna. Al acostarse junto a Doña Paca, pues dormían en
la misma alcoba, pensó que todo aquello de Almudena era una papa, y tomarlo en serio la mayor
de las necedades. Quiso dormirse, mas no pudo; volvió su espíritu a dar agasajo a la idea,
creyéndola de posible realización, Y si esfuerzos hacía por desecharla, con mayor tenacidad
la pícara idea se le metía en el cerebro.

«¿Qué se pierde por probarlo?--se decía, arropándose en la cama--. Podrá no ser verdad... ¿Pero
y si lo fuese? ¡Cuántas mentiras hubo que luego se volvieron verdades como puños!... Pues lo
que es yo, no me quedo sin probarlo, y mañana mismo, con el primer dinero que saque, compro
el candil de barro, sin hablar. El cuento es que no sé cómo puede tratarse un artículo sin
hablar... En fin, me haré la sordomuda... Luego buscaré el palitroque, también sin hablar...
Falta que el moro me enseñe la oración, y que yo la aprenda sin que se me escape un verbo...».

Después de un breve sueño, despertó creyendo firmemente que en la salita próxima había unas
esportonas o seretas muy grandes, muy grandes, llenas de diamantes, rubiles, perlas y zafiros...
En la obscuridad de las habitaciones nada podía ver; pero de que aquellas riquezas estaban
allí no tenía la menor duda. Cogió la caja de fósforos, dispuesta a encender, para recrear
su vista en el tesoro; mas por no despertar a Doña Paca, cuyo sueño era muy ligero, dejó para
la mañana el examen de tantas maravillas... Pasado un rato, no tardó en reírse de su ilusión,
diciéndose: «¡Pues no soy poco lila!... Es todavía pronto para que traigan eso...». Al amanecer,
despertose al ladrido de dos perrazos blancos que salían de debajo de las camas; sintió la
campanilla de la puerta; echose al suelo, y en camisa corrió a abrir, segura de que llamaba
algún ayudante o gentilhombre del Rey de luenga barba y vestido verde... Pero no era nadie;
no había ser viviente en la puerta.

Arreglose para salir, disponiendo el desayuno de la señora, y dando el primer barrido a la
casa, y a las siete salía ya con su cesta al brazo por la calle Imperial. Como no tenía un
céntimo ni de dónde le viniera, encaminose a San Sebastián, pensando por el camino en D. Romualdo
y su familia, pues de tanto hablar de aquellos señores, y de tanto comentarlos y describirlos,
había llegado a creer en su existencia. «¡Vaya que soy gilí!--se decía--. Invento yo al tal
D. Romualdo, y ahora se me antoja que es persona efetiva y que puede socorrerme. No hay más
D. Romualdo que el pordioseo bendito, y a eso voy, y veremos si cae algo, con permiso de la
Caporala». El día era bueno; al entrar, díjole Pulido que había funeral de primera, y boda
en la sacristía. La novia era sobrina de un ministro pleniputenciano, y el novio... cosa de
periódicos. Ocupó Benina su puesto, y se estrenó con dos céntimos que le dio una señora. Sus
compañeras trataron de hacerla cantar el para qué la había llamado D. Carlos; pero sólo contestó
con evasivas y medias palabras. Suponiendo la Casiana que el señor de Trujillo había tratado
con señá Benina el darle los restos de comida de su casa, la trató con miramiento, sin duda
por llamarse a la parte.

Al fin los del funeral no repartieron cosa mayor; y si los del bodorrio se corrieron algo más,
acudió tanta pobretería de otros cuadrantes, y se armó tal barullo y confusión, que unos cogieron
por cinco, y otros se quedaron in albis. Al ver salir a la novia, tan emperifollada, y a las
señoras y caballeros de su compañía, cayeron sobre ellos como nube de langosta, y al padrino
le estrujaron el gabán, y hasta le chafaron el sombrero. Trabajo le costó al buen señor sacudirse
la terrible plaga, y no tuvo más remedio que arrojar un puñado de calderilla en medio del patio.
Los más ágiles hicieron su agosto; los más torpes gatearon inútilmente. La Caporala y Eliseo
trataban de poner orden, y cuando los novios y todo el acompañamiento se metieron en los coches,
quedó en las inmediaciones de la iglesia la turbamulta mísera, gruñendo y pataleando. Se dispersaba,
y otra vez se reunía con remolinos zumbadores. Era como un motín, vencido por su propio cansancio.
Los últimos disparos eran: «Tú cogiste más... me han quitado lo mío... aquí no hay decencia...
cuánto pillo...». La Burlada, que era de las que más habían apandado, echaba sapos y culebras
de su boca, concitando los ánimos de toda la cuadrilla contra la Caporala y Eliseo. Por fin,
intervino la policía, amenazándoles con recogerles si no callaban, y esto fue como la palabra
de Dios. Los intrusos se largaron; los de casa se metieron en el pasadizo. Benina sacó de toda
la campaña del día, comprendido funeral y boda, 22 céntimos, y Almudena, 17. De Casiana y Eliseo
se dijo que habían sacado peseta y media cada uno.

Al retirarse juntos el ciego marroquí y Benina, lamentándose de su mala sombra, fueron a parar,
como la otra vez, a la plaza del Progreso, y se sentaron al pie de la estatua para deliberar
acerca de las dificultades y ahogos de aquel día. No sabía ya Benina a qué santo encomendarse:
con la limosna de la jornada no tenía ni para empezar, porque érale forzoso pagar algunas deudillas
en los establecimientos de la calle de la Ruda, a fin de sostener el crédito y poder trampear
unos días más. Díjole Almudena que él se hallaba en absoluta imposibilidad de favorecerla;
lo más que podía hacer era entregarle las perras de la mañana, y por la noche lo que sacar
pudiera en el resto del día, pidiendo en su puesto de costumbre, calle del Duque de Alba, junto
al cuartel de la Guardia Civil. Rechazó la anciana esta generosidad, porque también él necesitaba
vivir y alimentarse, a lo que repuso el marroquí que con un café con pan migao, en la Cruz
del Rastro, tenía bastante para tirar hasta la noche. Resistiéndose a admitir la oferta, planteó
Benina la cuestión de conjurar al Rey de baixo terra, mostrando una confianza y fe que fácilmente
se explican por la grande necesidad en que estaba. Lo desconocido y misterioso busca sus prosélitos
en el reino de la desesperación, habitado por las almas que en ninguna parte hallan consuelo.

«Ahora mismo--dijo la pobre mujer--, quiero comprar las cosas. Hoy es viernes, y mañana sábado
hacemos la prueba.

--Compriar ti cosas, sin hablar...

--Claro, sin decir una palabra. ¿Qué se pierde por hacer la prueba? Y dime otra cosa: ¿ha de
ser precisamente a media noche?».

Contestó el ciego que sí, repitiendo las reglas y condiciones imprescindibles para la eficacia
del conjuro, y Benina trató de fijarlo todo en su memoria.

«Ya sé--le dijo al fin--, que estarás todo el día en la fuentecilla del Duque de Alba--. Si
se me olvida algo, iré a preguntártelo, y a que me enseñes la oración. Eso sí que me ha de
costar trabajo aprenderlo, sobre todo si no me lo pones en lengua cristiana, que lo que es
en la tuya, hijo de mi alma, no sé cómo voy a componerme para no equivocarme.

--Si quivoquiar ti, Rey no vinier».

Desalentada con estas dificultades, separose Benina de su amigo, por la prisa que tenía de
reunir algunas perras con que completar lo que para las obligaciones de aquel día necesitaba,
y no pudiendo esperar ya cosa alguna del crédito, se puso a pedir en la esquina de la calle
de San Millán, junto a la puerta del café de los Naranjeros, importunando a los transeúntes
con el relato de sus desdichas: que acababa de salir del hospital, que su marido se había caído
de un andamio, que no había comido en tres semanas, y otras cosas que partían los corazones.
Algo iba pescando la infeliz, y hubiera cogido algo más, si no se pareciese por allí un maldito
guindilla que la conminó con llevarla a los sótanos de la prevención de la Latina, si no se
largaba con viento fresco. Ocupose luego en comprar los adminículos para el conjuro, empresa
harto engorrosa, porque todo había de hacerse por señas, y se fue a su casa pensando que sería
gran dificultad efectuar allí la endiablada hechicería sin que se enterase la señora. Contra
esto no había más recurso que figurar que D. Romualdo se había puesto muy malito, y salir de
noche a velarle, yéndose a casa de Almudena... Pero la presencia de la Petra podría ser obstáculo:
al peligro de que un testigo incrédulo imposibilitara la cosa, se añadía el inconveniente grave
de que, en caso de éxito feliz, la borrachona quisiera apropiarse todos o una parte de los
tesoros donados por el Rey... Por cierto que mejor que en piedras preciosas, sería que lo trajesen
todo en moneda corriente, o en fajos de billetes de Banco, bien sujetos con una goma, como
ella los había visto en las casas de cambio. Porque... no era floja pejiguera tener que ir
a las platerías a proponer la venta de tantas perlas, zafiros y diamantes... En fin, que lo
trajeran como les diese la gana: no era cosa de poner reparos, ni exigir muchos perendengues.

Halló a Doña Paca de mal temple, porque se había parecido en la casa, muy de mañana, un dependiente
de la tienda, y habíala insultado con expresiones brutales y soeces. La pobre señora lloraba
y se tiraba de los pelos, suplicando a su fiel amiga que arase la tierra en busca de los pocos
duros que hacían falta, para tirárselos al rostro al bestia del tendero, y Benina se devanaba
los sesos por encontrar la solución del terrible conflicto.

«Mujer, por piedad, discurre, inventa algo--le decía la señora, hecha un mar de lágrimas--.
Para las ocasiones son los amigos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05976</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>21069</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19869</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> I can not, no ... My conscience revolts ...

- Let the riots, that we are here troops. Or you take away the pesetilla, or me anger, as God
is my father. D. Bottle, do paperwork, you're more beggar the inventor of hunger. Or do you
need more money, because it has more to Bernard? In this case, I can not give it, because I
have not ... But do not be lilac, D. Bottle or is made of honey, which the Lizard of Bernarda eat it
alive, if not charged forty. For a customer like you, of the aristocracy, not denied housing
because they need a pose, three nights, four nights ... Frasquito Plántese good, with a hundred
thousand pairs, and will Bernarda how bends the ears ... It gives you four real account, y.
.. to pour sleep peacefully on the bed.

"

O Ponte was not convinced, or convinced of how good it would be for him the possession of the
peseta he hated the physical act of reaching out and receiving alms. Strengthened his argument Benina
saying: "And since the child is so shy, and does not dare to her
employer, even giving account of the singing, I will speak to Bernard,
I would say that does not fight, nor rush ... Come on, take what you
give, and no more cold blood me, Mr. D. Bottle.

"

And without giving him time to make further protests and negative, took her hand, put it currency,
cerrole force fist and ran away. Ponte made no move to return money, or throw. He remained standing
and silent, watched as the vision Benina vanishes in a flash of light, and keeping in his left
hand the peseta, with the right took out his handkerchief and wiped
his eyes, he cried horribly.

Cried irritation senile eye, and also of joy, admiration and gratitude.

Benina still took over an hour to reach the Imperial Street, passed because before that of
The Ruda to do their shopping. These had to be on credit, because he had concluded money. Ended
up in his house after two hours is certainly not untimely: other days had come later, but this
is the angry lady. Depended on being right or wrong received from the streak of humor that Doña Paca
picked up at the time of entry. That afternoon, Unfortunately, poor Mrs. Ronda was one of its most
violent irritability crisis nervous. His genius was sudden eruptions, sometimes determined by
any setback small, sometimes by mysteries of the body difficult to appreciate. This is that
before of Benin through the door, threw the Dona Francisca dash: "Do you think they are these hours
to come? I have to talk to D. Romualdo, to tell me when to salt your home ... I bet you now you
pick up the lie that you went to see the child, and you had to feed him ... Do you think I'm an idiot,
and I believe your lies? Shut your mouth ... I do not ask explanations, neither need, nor
I, you know that believe anything you say, liar, tangled '.

Aware of the nature of the lady knew that the worst Benina system against outbursts of anger
was contradicting explanations to give, open up and defend themselves. Doña Paca not admit reasoning,
and thoughtful they were. The more logical and fair were the clarification
the contrary, she sulked more.

Not infrequently Benina, innocent, had to file guilty of the offenses alleged against the
lady, because doing so would calm down soon.

"See how I have right? - Continued the lady, who when put in such a state, was of the more unbearable
than you can imagine -. You shut ... by silence, grants. Then it is true what I say, I am always
aware ... It is what I thought: you have not gone home Obdulia, and that's the path. God knows
where you've been ping. But do not care, I'll find out ... Keep me here alone, dying of hunger!
... What a morning I've actually happen! I've lost count of those who have come for the shops peppers,
amounts that have not already paid your disorder ... Because the
truth, I do not know where You put you the money ... Responds, women
... even defend yourself, that if everything you give no answer, I
seem to still tell you little.

"

Benina humbly repeated the above: that it had completed later at the
home of D. Romualdo, that D. Carlos Trujillo, entertained the sea
of ??time that had gone after the Calle de la Cabeza ...

"God knows,
God knows what you've done, correntona, and what sites you've been
... Let's see, to see if you smell a wine.

"

Smelling breath, broke into shouts of disgust and horror: "Remove, take off there, drunk. You reek
of brandy.

- I have not tasted, ma'am, I can believe. "

Doña Paca insisted that in those crisis situations became his suspicions, and his stubbornness forged
his conviction.

"I can believe it - repeated Benina -. I have not taken more than a glass of wine that gave me Mr.
de Ponte.

- I 'is giving me a bad feeling that M. de Ponte, who is an old fox
and green and very rascal.

Kind, as the plants you too silent ... Do not think you fool me,
hypocrite ... After aging, it gives you the solution, and litter of
brown peaks.

What things come, Lord, and what derangement drag the damn service! ... You shut up, then it
is true. No, if even I deny not convince me, because when I tell you one thing, it's because I know ...
I have I ...». eye

Without giving time for the offender to explain, came by the following record:

"And you tell me, woman? What made you welcome my relative D. Carlos? What? Is good? Do not burst
yet? No need to say anything because, as if it had been me your secret
behind a curtain, I know all that talk ... Do not I right?

Well I'm telling you what happens to me is my damn habit of not keeping
accounts.

No one will PASA of that folly. To each his own theme, the folly of my relative is to fix everything
with numbers ... Has enriched them, robbing the Treasury and the parishioners, and with them
wants to life to save his soul, and the poor, we recommend the medicine of the numbers that
it does not save him or us any good. With what success? Was this what you said?

- Yes, ma'am. Looks like you were hearing.

- And after crush with that gibberish of debit and credit, has given you a handout for me ... Ignore
my dignity rises up to receive it.

I see him as he opened the drawers wants and does not want to take the taleguito in having
the bills, hiding to avoid being you could see, I see him rubbing the pouch, store carefully, I
see you turn the key ... And very dirty off-hook with a crap.

I can not specify the amount he has given you for me, because it is so difficult to anticipate
the calculations of avarice, but of course I assure you, without fear of contradiction, that
has not reached the forty dollars. "

The look on his face Benina hearing this can not be described. The lady, carefully watched, pale,
and said after a brief pause:

"It's true: I've run a lot.

Forty, no, but even so stingy and mean it man, there will be dropped from twenty-five dollars. Less
than that will not admit it, Nina, I can not admit.

- Madam, you are delusional - said the other firmly planted in reality -. Mr. D. Carlos has not given
me anything, which is called nothing. To begin next month give you an allowance of two dollars
per month.

- Liar, swindling ... Do you think me fool me with your clutter? Well, well, I do not bother me ...
I have worsening account, and I am not to take tantrums ... Understood, Nina, understood.
There you will understand with your conscience. I wash my hands and leave it to God give you
your due.

- What, ma'am?

- Join now simple and Marirramos kitten. Can not you see me immediately
and I guess calo your fabrications?

Come on, woman, confess, do not try to add to infamy deception.

- What, ma'am?

- Well, you've had a bad temptation ... Confiésamelo, and I forgive you ... Do not want to declare?
For the worse for you and your conscience, because you bring out the colors in the face. Want
to see?

For twenty-five drives that you gave to me D. Carlos, you have given to this Frasquito Ponte
to pay their debts, and go to lunch, catering, and buy shirts, ointment,
and a stick again ... You see, you see, bribonaza, how everything
you guessed it, and me not worth your concealment.

If I know more than you. Now you have been given to protect the deli Tenorio, and I want more
than me, and he now serves me no, and you feel sorry for him and me, how much you want, damned me.
"

Mrs. broke to mourn, and Benin and answer felt like such impertinence
giving lashes like a crafty child, seeing the compassion tears.

I knew that crying was the completion of the cholera crisis, sedation of access, rather, that
such happened, it was best to let the laughter, bringing the dispute
into the realm of delicious mockery.

"Yes, Mrs. Dona Francisca - said hugging -.

Did you think when they had gone that boyfriend as sorcerer and as salt shakers had to leave
me in need, without giving hair?

- Do not think you fooled me with your little jokes, swindling, flattering ...-- said the lady,
and unarmed and defeated -. I assure you I do not care what you did, because the money Trujillete
I had to take ... I'd rather die of hunger or stain my hands with
him ... Give, give it to whoever you want, ingratona, and leave me
alone, let me die I missed you and around the world.

- Neither you
nor I will die so soon, because we still give a lot of war - he said
maid, preparing with great care to feed.

- We'll see what crap you
bring me today ... Show me the basket ... But, daughter, do not you
ashamed to bring to your loved these filthy scraps?

... What else? Cauliflower ... I have already plague-stricken with your cauliflowers, they
give me fart, and I am repeating three days ... In short, what we
in the world than to suffer?

Dame soon these comistrajos ... What brought you eggs? And know that not happened, and not very
fresh.

- Eat what you give without grumbling, that putting so many objections to the food that God da,
is offended and aggrieved.

- Well, my dear, whatever you want. Eat what you have, and give thanks to God. But like You too, I'm
sorry to see you so busy, desviviéndote for others, and forgotten yourself and your body relief.
Sit with me, and tell me what you did today. "

In the afternoon, ate two, sit-to kitchen table. Doña Paca, sighing all his soul, between bites
another, expressed in this way the ideas bubbling in his mind:

"Tell me, Nina, among so many strange things, incomprehensible, what's in the world, what would
be a medium, a form ... I do not know how to say, a spell by which
we could spend from scarcity to abundance, by which all that the world
has a place in many hands greedy, come to ours who have nothing?

-
What does the lady?

What if it could happen in the blink of an eye go from poor to rich, and saw a mean, our house
full of money, and everything God created?

- That I mean. If miracles are true, why is not the case one for us, that it We deserved what
we got?

- Who says it does not happen, we do not have this outcome? - Said Benin, in whose mind emerged
suddenly, with strong relief and extraordinary plasticity, the spell Almudena had taught him to
seek and obtain all the goods of the earth.

XX

Thereby took possession of his mind the idea and images expressed by the blind African that point
was to tell her mistress the wonderful method of plotting and to bring the King baixo terra.
But fearing that the secret would be less effective the more you disclose, contúvose in his
loquacity, and only said it could be that of the overnight tuck them through the gates of fortune.
At bedtime with Doña Paca, for sleeping in the same room, thought
everything was a potato Almudena, and take it more seriously of nonsense.

He wanted to sleep, but could not, he turned his mind to give entertainment to the idea, thinking
it might be carrying, and if efforts made by waste more tenaciously the mischievous idea he
got into the brain.

"What is lost by trying it? - It was said, wrapping up in bed -. May not be true ... But and
if it were? There were many lies then truths became fists! ... For what that's me, I'm out
to try, and tomorrow, with the first money I take, buy the lamp of clay, without speaking.
The story is that I do not know how to treat an item without talk ... Anyway, I'll make the
deaf ... Then look for the stick, even without speaking ... I need to teach the Muslim prayer,
and I learn it without a verb ...». escape me

After a brief sleep, woke up believing strongly in the parlor next had a Seret large basket or
very large, very large, filled with diamonds, Rubilar, pearls and sapphires ... In the dark
room could see nothing, but that those riches were there was no doubt.

He took the box of matches ready to light, to recreate your eyes on the treasure, but not wake
Doña Paca, whose sleep was very light, left to morning the examination of so many wonders ... After
a while, soon to laugh at his enthusiasm, saying: "Well, I'm not little purple! ... It is too
early to bring this ...». At dawn, awoke to the barking of two white big dog came out from under
the bed, felt the doorbell, he fell to the ground and ran in his shirt open, secure calling a gentleman
of the King assistant or a long beard and dressed in green ... But there was nobody; there was no
living thing on the door.

Arreglose to leave, having breakfast the lady, and taking the first scan to home, and at seven and left
with his basket on his arm and Imperial Street. As he had no cent or where he came, he went to San
Sebastian, thinking down the road in D. Romualdo and his family, since both speak of those gentlemen,
and both comment and describe them had come to believe in its existence. "I'm gill Go! - They
said -. I to this invention D. Romualdo, and now it seems to me that is a person EFET and can
help me. There is no D. Romualdo the begging blessed, and that I, and see if you drop something,
with permission Caporal. " The day was good to get him, and said Pulido was the first funeral
and wedding in the sacristy. The bride was the niece of a minister pleniputenciano, and the groom
... thing newspapers.

Benina took his place, and was released with two cents who gave a lady. Its companions tried to
sing it for what he had called D. Carlos, but only answered with evasions and half-words. Casiana
Assuming that Mr. Trujillo had tried Sena Benina with the leftover food to give your home, treated
her with courtesy, no doubt by calling the party.

At last thing the funeral was not subdivided further, and if the bodorrio were run something
else, went so pobretería other quadrants, and there was such a din and confusion, which took
about five, and others stayed in albis. Seeing out the bride, so dolled up, and Ladies and gentlemen
of his company, fell upon them like a cloud of locusts, and the sponsor I squeezed his coat, and
he even muss his hat. Labour cost the good lord shake the terrible plague, and had no choice
but to throw a handful of pennies in the yard. The more agile made a killing, the most awkward crawled
avail. The Caporale and Elisha trying to impose order, and when the bride and groom and all the support
they got in the car was near the church miserable mob, grunting and kicking. Dispersed, and again met
with swirls buzzers. It was like a riot, defeated by his own fatigue.

The last shot was, "You fucked more ... I have removed mine ... here there is no decency ... how
rogue ...».

Mockery, that was the most they swipe, missed toads and snakes of
his mouth, attracting the minds of all the crew against Caporale and
Elisha.

Finally, Police intervened, threatening to pick you up if not silent, and this was like the
word of God.

The intruders made off, the house got into the passage. Benina took all Day campaign, including
funeral and wedding, 22 cents, and Almudena, 17.

Casiano and Elisha were said to have taken peseta and a half each.

When he retired Moroccan together blind and Benin, lamenting his evil shadow, ended, as before,
to the Plaza del Progreso, and sat at the foot of the statue to deliberate
about the challenges and drowning that day.

He no longer knew which saint entrusted Benina: with the alms of
the day did not have to start because Eral forced to pay some deudillas
establishments in the Rue de la Rue, to sustain the credit and power
trick few more days.

Almudena said to him that he was in absolute inability to promote it; the most he could do
was give the dogs in the morning and at night so take could the rest of the day, asking in its
usual place, street of the Duke of Alba, along the Civil Guard barracks. He rejected the old
woman's generosity, for he too needed live and feed, to which said the Moroccan coffee with
a bread crumb on the Cross Rastro, had enough to pull up the night. Loath to accept the offer,
raised Benina avert the issue of the King of baixo terra, showing trust and faith that easily
be explained by the great need it was. The mysterious stranger and seeks his proselytes in the
realm of despair, inhabited by the souls who find solace anywhere.

"Right now - said the poor woman - I want to buy things. Today is Friday, and Saturday morning
do the test.

- Compressed you things, let alone ...

- Of course, without saying a word. What is lost by doing the test? And tell me another thing:
Why has be precisely at midnight? ".

The blind man answered yes, saying the rules and conditions necessary for effective spell,
and tried to fix Benina everything in your memory.

"I know - he said at last - that'll be all day in the fountain of the Duke of Alba -. If I forget something,
I'll be asking you, as I teach prayer. Now that I must be hard to learn, especially if I put
it in Christian language, what is in yours, son of my soul, I do not know how to compose myself
for not wrong.

- If you quivoquiar, King not vinyl. "
Discouraged with these difficulties, separose Benina of your friend,
I had to hurry gather some bitches to complete what the obligations
of that day needed, can not expect anything and credit, began to ask
at the corner of the street San Millán, next to the door of the cafe
of the Naranjeros, pestering passers with the story of their misfortunes:
they had just left the hospital, her husband had fallen a scaffold,
which had not eaten in three weeks, and other things that left their
hearts. Something was fishing the unhappy, and had caught something
else, if not look like a fucking there chilli that enjoined to take
her to the basement of the prevention of America, if not Long cool
wind. Ocupose then buy the gadgets for the spell, company sick cumbersome,
because everything had to be made by signs, and went home thinking
it would be great difficulty making the devilish sorcery there but
found out the lady. Against this had not recourse but to include that
D. Romualdo had been very ill, and leave velarle night, going home
Almudena ... But the presence of Petra could be an obstacle: the danger
that a witness preclude incredulous thing, added the serious drawback
that, if successful happy, the drunks would appropriate all or part
of treasures donated by the King ... Certainly better than precious
stones, which would bring him everything in common, or in bundles
of bank notes, secured with a rubber band, as she had seen in the
exchange houses. Because ... was not having to go loose pejiguera
the silverware to propose the sale of many pearls, sapphires and diamonds
... Finally, it bring as give them the win: it was a matter of cavil
or require many perendengues.

Dona Paca found in an ill temper, because
it had seemed at home in the morning, a clerk Store and insulted Tell
them brutal and vulgar expressions. The poor lady was crying and hair
pulling, pleading with his faithful friend plowing the land in search
of the few drives that were needed to tirárselos to face the beast
of a shopkeeper and racked Benina brains to find the solution to the
terrible conflict.

"Woman, by compassion, runs, invents something
- I said the lady, a sea of ??tears -. For chances are friends</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>