<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04313</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>14539</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21288</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Apenas si la
humanidad ha nacido. Yo he leído en un libro muy docto esta sentencia, que no olvidaré nunca.
«La humanidad, en su vida colectiva, no ha nacido aún.»

Todo este largo pasado que llevamos ya, el vivir en la primavera del año máximo y el columbrar
un extenso porvenir, esplendoroso y fecundo, no debe, sin embargo, alegrarnos en demasía, ni
menos ensoberbecernos. Comparados nuestros veinte millones de años ya cumplidos, más otros
veinte millones que por lo menos durará aún la primavera de este planeta, con otras primaveras
y años máximos de otros planetas y de otros más grandes sistemas solares, tal vez parezca más
breve dicha primavera que la ordinaria y menuda del año vulgar, que sólo dura tres meses.

Cavilando yo días pasados sobre este asunto, y hallándome en el campo, en soledad amena, en
hondo valle circundado de rocas escarpadas, donde había silencio, frescura y mil plantas, hierbas
y flores, tuve despierto un sueño, que parecía visión espiritual o intuición pura de algo real,
aunque para mí materialmente imperceptible.

Dentro de la superficie de un kilómetro cuadrado entendí que había ciertas emanaciones sutiles
de cierto fluido mil veces más tenue que el aire; fluido que penetraba el aire todo, infundiéndose
en los vacíos e intersticios que dejan sus moléculas. Este fluido, que el hombre no verá, ni
pesará, ni sentirá jamás con sus sentidos, no se eleva más allá de un kilómetro. Tenemos, pues,
un kilómetro cúbico lleno de este fluido tenue, desleído en el aire como perfumes o efluvios.
Figureme, pues, mi kilómetro cúbico como un mundo aparte, y vi que estaba poblado de un linaje
de silfos tan diminutos, que, si por descuido se tragase cualquiera de ellos la más ruin molécula
de aire, dicha molécula se le atragantaría y quizás le ahogaría como a cualquiera de nosotros
un hueso de melocotón. Mi linaje de silfos respira, pues, el fluido tenue de que he hablado.
Con las moléculas del aire hacen los silfos mil primores, y hasta juegan cuando son muchachos,
disparándolas por medio de enormes cerbatanas.

Fuera del kilómetro cúbico está para mis silfos lo infinito, desconocido e insondable. Viven
en una hora; pero su inteligencia es tan rápida y tan sutil, que en esta hora tienen tiempo
de sobra para instruirse, enamorarse, propagarse, seguir una carrera, elevarse a las más altas
posiciones, legar un nombre ilustre a su legítima prole, y hasta cansarse de la vida y apelar
al suicidio. Un minuto para cualquiera de ellos es mucho más que un año para cualquiera de
nosotros. Sus poetas componen versos desesperados y desengañados a los quince minutos de nacer,
y sus sabios inventan los más profundos y alambicados sistemas de filosofía a los treinta minutos.

La voz de mis silfos es tan delgada, que sólo el fluido susodicho puede trasmitirla en ondas
sonoras. Sus palabras van tan prontas, que en un segundo refiere un silfo una historia que
el más conciso de nosotros tardaría tres o cuatro horas en contar. Todo lo que entre nosotros
es extenso, es intenso entre los silfos. En las veinticuatro horas de cualquier día se extiende
la historia de los silfos, y es tan fecunda en revoluciones, cambios, guerras y progresos,
como la nuestra en los mil ochocientos setenta y pico de años que median desde la Era cristiana
hasta el momento en que escribo.

Mis silfos tienen figura humana. Yo entiendo que toda alma, todo pensamiento que informa un
cuerpo, grande o chico, le da esta figura, por ser la más hermosa.

La hermosura de mis silfos es tal, que si lográsemos fabricar un microscopio bastante poderoso
para llegar a verlos, envidiaríamos a los varones y nos enamoraríamos desesperadamente de las
hembras.

Están muy adelantados en civilización. Han tenido muchos profetas y fundadores de religiones;
pero ya va pasando entre ellos la edad de la fe, y rayando la aurora de la edad de la razón.

Sus conocimientos históricos, sin mezcla de fábula, aquello que la crítica más severa da por
cierto, no pasa de noventa días, lo cual, equivale a más de tres mil sucesivas generaciones.
Y como un minuto para ellos viene a equivaler a un año para nosotros, puede afirmarse que ellos
hacen subir la antigüedad de su civilización a más de 129.600 años. Más allá, yendo contra
la corriente de los tiempos, los silfos no ven claro; pero, si entre ellos hay un Darwin o
un Haeckel, sin duda colocará la aparición de la primera monera del mundo silfídico a una distancia
proporcionalmente mucho mayor.

El concepto que forman del Universo es muy distinto del que formamos nosotros. Y no porque
su razón no concuerde con la nuestra, sino porque son otros los datos de sus sentidos. No llegan
con la vista al sol, ni a la luna, ni a las estrellas, por donde los torrentes de luz ardorosa
que lanza sobre ellos el primero, y la luz tibia y plateada en que los baña la luna, proceden
para ellos de un manantial oculto. Así es que forman mil hipótesis para explicarlo. Claro está
que hay largos períodos históricos de una luz, y largos períodos históricos de otra.

En su mundo hay seres animados, de proporciones tan gigantescas, que nosotros ni siquiera las
concebimos. Una avispa para ellos es más que lo que sería para nosotros el Nevado de Sorata,
si arrancándose él mismo de cuajo, animándose y echando alas, se pusiese a volar y se nos mostrase
por el aire. Por fortuna, la excesiva pequeñez de los silfos y su agilidad portentosa los salvan
de tales monstruos.

Claro está que lo infinito es siempre lo infinito, así en la mente de un silfo como en la mente
de un hombre. En este punto, si nos contraemos a la especulación racional, nuestros conceptos
son iguales; pero en contar, en extenderse a mayor número, en notar mayor cantidad, los silfos
nos ganan; penetran con sus sentidos, y ven y perciben abismos de extensión, de tiempo, de
volumen y de duraciones en lo infinitamente pequeño, por donde lo mediano, lo mezquino para
nosotros, su universo de un kilómetro cúbico, es más ingente para ellos que toda la inmensidad
de los cielos para nosotros. Y no dejan por eso de poner más allá de su universo lo infinito
inexplorado.

Andan todos ellos muy soberbios con su cultura y con sus progresos, que juzgan sin límites.
Así como cuentan ya un pasado larguísimo, esperan un porvenir más largo aún. Y es lo cierto
que no se equivocan. Ellos nacieron con esta última primavera y acabarán al fin del próximo
otoño. Ahora, que es verano, están en todo el auge de su grandeza. Lo mismo nos sucede a nosotros.

¿Quién sabe si habrá seres, en comparación de los cuales seamos nosotros lo que para nosotros
son mis silfos? Y si alguno de estos seres llega a averiguar que existimos, como yo he llegado
a averiguar que existen silfos tales, ¿no se reirá, o nos compadecerá, al ver que esperamos
aún tan largo porvenir? Los millones de años que llevamos de vida y los que esperamos vivir
aún, serán para él una primavera. Acaso, cuando vuelva él de veranear o de bañarse en algunos
baños de su mundo, encuentre ya el nuestro desolado y hecho ruinas, y extinguida, nuestra efímera
raza. Pero no tendrá razón. Lo importante es la inteligencia, la cual no se mide por varas,
ni por kilómetros, ni por diámetros terrestres. Su actividad, cuando es fecunda, puede condensar
en un minuto más hechos, más ideas, más creaciones, más gloria y más infierno, que otra inteligencia
reacia, perezosa y torpe, durante siglos de siglos.

Última moralidad. Todo es relativo, como decía D. Hermógenes. No hay menos ni más. En el tiempo
que he tardado yo en escribir este artículo para cumplir mi imprudente promesa, un hombre de
ingenio fecundo hubiera sido capaz de escribir la historia de toda la raza humana; y, en menos
tiempo, mis silfos son capaces de realizar lo más importante de su propia historia. No lo daré
por muy seguro, porque no he llegado a enterarme bien y no gusto de fantasear, pero es posible
que mientras yo he estado afanadísimo componiendo todas estas candideces e inocentadas, a fin
de salir del paso, mis silfos hayan fundado nuevos imperios, creado constituciones, inventado
filosofías y máquinas, y erigido monumentos, en su sentir, imperecederos.

Tal consideración me avergüenza y humilla, en vez de llenarme de vanidad; y, aunque no sea
de silfos, sino de hombres como yo, el público que ha de leerme, todavía le presento con grandísima
desconfianza este escrito, que no he tenido reposo, ni humor, ni tiempo para hacer más breve.

LA CORDOBESA

El editor de esta obra tuvo la bondad de encomendarme, un siglo ha, uno de sus artículos; y
yo, como es natural, elegí la cordobesa, por ser la provincia de Córdoba donde he nacido y
me he criado.

Mi extremada desidia me ha impedido hasta ahora cumplir mi palabra de escribirle. Tal vez para
cohonestar esta falta me presentaba yo un sinnúmero de dificultades y objeciones, por cuyo
medio trataba de condenar el pensamiento del editor, a fin de justificar mi tardanza en contribuir
a su realización con mi trabajo.

¿Qué diferencia esencial, ni siquiera qué diferencia accidental notable, puede haber o hay
pongo por caso, entre la cordobesa, la jaenense o la sevillana? Allá en lo antiguo quizás la
hubiese, porque no eran tan fáciles las comunicaciones, y era más fácil el vivir aislado y
sedentario; pero en el día, en que, no ya los hombres y mujeres de contiguas provincias, sino
los de remotas naciones, longincuos países y apartadísimos reinos, se ven y visitan con frecuencia,
¿cómo ha de persistir esa variedad y distinción de tipos, dando ocasión a que se describan
mujeres que por sus costumbres, creencias, modos de sentir y de pensar, fisonomía, continente
y traje, se diferencien hasta el punto de que las pinturas o descripciones que de ellas se
hagan, varíen por el asunto, y no sólo por el estilo del que pinta o describe? Además, me decía
yo, aunque el sello de casta y el de nacionalidad sean indelebles, sin que acierte a borrarlos
o a confundirlos la continua convivencia y el íntimo comercio espiritual, en esta época en
que tanto se escribe, se lee y se viaja, en este siglo del vapor y la electricidad, del ferro-carril
y del telégrafo, todavía no logro persuadirme de que haya también un sello de provincialidad,
como hay sello de nación, de tribu o de casta. Lo peculiar y lo castizo, en lo que tienen de
exclusivas estas calidades, provienen de divisiones que hizo la naturaleza misma, y no de las
divisiones administrativas o políticas, esto es, artificiales, como son las divisiones por
provincias. Malagueñas o sevillanas habrá, sin duda, de casta y suelo más homogéneos con los
de ciertas cordobesas, que los de muchas cordobesas entre sí. Una mujer de Cuevas de San Marcos,
por ejemplo, debe parecerse más a otra de Rute, que una de Rute a otra de Belalcázar, y más
se parecerá la de Casariche a la de Benamejí, que la de Benamejí a la de Almodóvar.

Harto se me alcanzaba que entre la gallega y la mujer de Cataluña, y entre la manchega y la
vizcaína habían de mediar radicales diferencias; pero esto de que cada provincia, fuese la
que fuese, había de tener un tipo especial, se me hacía difícil de creer. Sólo salvaba yo la
monotonía de este libro y cifraba su variedad en el ingenio diverso de cada escritor, en el
sesgo que atinase a dar al asunto, y en lo singular de su estilo, pensamientos y sentimientos.

Nunca pensé que el editor desease que escribiésemos una reseña erudita, una serie de vidas
de todas las mujeres célebres de cada provincia. Esto sería quizás, no sólo ameno, sino ejemplar
y didáctico; pero no se trataba de esto, ni yo me hubiese comprometido a escribir mi artículo,
si de esto se tratase. No era obra histórica, ni biográfica, la que se trazaba y proyectaba,
sino cuadro de costumbres y pintura al vivo o retrato fiel de lo que hoy se nota en cada provincia
en los usos, cultura, ideas, y demás prendas, condiciones y actos de las mujeres. Y siendo
la cosa así, repito que no me percataba yo de nada o de casi nada que impidiese la monotonía
de la obra por el objeto, aunque por el sujeto, o mejor diré por los sujetos, viniese a ser
un jardín de flores, como la capa del estudiante, merced a la diversidad de estilos y a la
idiosincracia de cada escritor que en ella pusiese mano.

Así, sobre poco más o menos, andaba yo cavilando, cuando deberes de familia me llevaron al
riñón de la provincia de Córdoba; a una dichosa comarca donde el color local provincial está
difundido a manos llenas por la Naturaleza pródiga e inexhausta en sus varias creaciones. Y
estando este color, este sello, este tipo en todo, ¿cómo, me dije yo, no ha de estarlo en la
mujer, la cual es blanda cera para recibir impresiones, y duro bronce para conservarlas sin
que se desvanezcan?

Más de cinco meses pasé en mi lugar, y en este tiempo mudé por completo de parecer, respecto
al libro del Sr. Guijarro. No me quedaba excusa para no escribir el artículo. Estaba persuadido
de que si la cordobesa que yo pintase no era un tipo sui generis, era porque yo no sabía pintar
lo que estaba viendo de un modo claro. Me decidí, pues, desde entonces a hacer esta pintura,
confesando con ingenuidad que, si no sale original y nueva, la culpa será mía y no del modelo.

Una cosa me turba aún y dificulta mi propósito. Al ver y tratar a la cordobesa del día, acuden
a mi imaginación las ya casi borradas especies que desde mi niñez y primera juventud, harto
lejanas por desgracia, dormían o estaban sepultadas en mi mente, de la cordobesa del primer
tercio de este siglo. La disparidad entre el recuerdo y la impresión presente me confunden
un poco. El tipo cordobés femenino no ha desaparecido, pero ha habido cambio, si bien el cambio
no ha sido de lo castizo a lo exótico. El cambio ha sido por interior desenvolvimiento de la
propia esencia de la mujer cordobesa, la cual, como todas las esencias inmortales, permanece
en su fundamento sustancial, si bien adquiere nuevas formas y nuevos accidentes. La cordobesa
de este momento histórico no es la cordobesa del momento histórico anterior; pero es siempre
la cordobesa, y siempre sigue realizando su esencia, como cada hija de vecina, exteriorizando
la idea típica suya propia, y presentando diverso aspecto, en cada una de las diversas evoluciones
con que la exterioriza.

Veo que me encumbro demasiado, y voy a descender y a hablar con más llaneza, dejando los raptos
filosóficos para mejor ocasión.

Hoy se me presenta la cordobesa a la vista tal como es, mientras que la memoria me la retrae
tal como era treinta o cuarenta años ha. De aquí se origina cierta confusión, algo como una
antinomía; pero, si bien se estudia la antinomía, se resolverá con poco trabajo en una síntesis
suprema. Esta síntesis, si acertase yo a crearla, sería un artículo primoroso. Es más: sin
esta síntesis no es posible el artículo, porque yo no voy a pintar a la cordobesa muerta, parada,
estacionaria, inerte, fósil, sino a la cordobesa viva, en movimiento, en desarrollo, en progreso;
desenvolviéndose, no con prestado impulso, sino según las leyes propias de su gran ser y de
su rico y generoso organismo.

Para adquirir el concepto total de la cordobesa es menester estudiarla en sus diferentes clases
y estados: desde la gran señora hasta la mujer del rudo ganapán, desde la niña hasta la anciana,
desde la hija de familia hasta la madre o la abuela; y verla y visitarla, ya en la antigua
y espléndida capital del Califato; ya en la Sierra, al Norte del Guadalquivir, abundante en
minas y en dehesas selváticas y esquivas; ya en la campiña ubérrima, donde hay lugares populosos
y hasta lindas ciudades, y donde la riqueza, el bienestar y la cultura son mayores. Pero si
fuésemos analizando y examinando por separado todas estas cosas, no tendría fin ni término
nuestro artículo; y así conviene tocar sólo puntos capitales, y resumir y cifrar en dos o tres
tipos todo lo que hay en la cordobesa de más característico y propio.

Claro está que en la provincia de Córdoba hay damas ricas, que han estado o están en Madrid,
que tal vez han ido a Baden o a Biarritz algún verano; que hablan francés, que han paseado
en el bosque de Boulogne, que conocen acaso varias cortes extranjeras, que leen las novelas
de Jorge Sand y los versos de Lamartine en la misma lengua en que se escribieron, y que se
visten con Worth, con Laferrière, con la Honorina o con la Isolina. En todas estas damas subsiste
aún la esencia de la mujer cordobesa; pero sería menester ahondar y penetrar demasiado para
descubrir esa esencia al través de tantos aditamentos extraños y de tantas exterioridades postizas.
Busquemos, pues, a la genuina cordobesa donde no tengamos necesidad de profundizar o de eliminar
para hallarla: busquémosla en la lugareña, ya sea rica, ya pobre; ya señora, ya criada.

La lugareña es en extremo hacendosa. Por pobre que sea, tiene la casa saltando de limpia. Los
suelos, de losa de mármol, de ladrillo o de yeso cuajado, parecen bruñidos a fuerza de aljofifa.
Si el ama de la casa goza de algún bienestar, resplandecen en dos o tres chineros el cristal
y la vajilla; y en hileras simétricas adornan las paredes de la cocina peroles, cacerolas y
otros trastos de azófar o de cobre, donde puede uno verse la cara como en un espejo.

La cordobesa es todo vigilancia, aseo, cuidado y esmerada economía. Nunca abandona las llaves
de la despensa, de las alacenas, arcas y armarios. En la anaquelería o vasares de la despensa
suele conservar, con próvida y rica profusión, un tesoro de comestibles, los cuales dan testimonio,
ya de la prosperidad de la casa; ya de lo fértil de las fincas del dueño, si son productos
indígenas y, como suele decirse, de la propia crianza y labranza; ya de la habilidad y primor
de la señora, cuyo trabajo ha aumentado el valor de la primera materia con alguna preparación
o condimento. Allí tiene nueces, castañas, almendras, batatas, cirolitas imperiales envueltas
en papel para que se pasen, guindas en aguardiente, orejones y otras mil chucherías. Los pimientos
picantes, las guindillas y cornetas y los ajos, cuelgan en ristras al lado del bacalao, en
la parte menos pulcra. En la parte más pulcra suele haber azúcar, café, salvia, tila, manzanilla,
y hasta té a veces, que antes sólo en la botica se hallaba. Del techo cuelgan egregios y gigantescos
jamones; y, alternando con esta bucólica manifestación del reino animal, dulces andregüelas
invernizas, uvas, granadas y otras frutas. En hondas orzas vidriadas conserva la señora lomo
de cerdo en adobo, cubierto de manteca; pajarillas, esto es, asaduras, riñones y bazo del mismo
cuadrúpedo; y hasta morrillas, alcauciles, setas y espárragos trigueros y amargueros; todo
ello tan bien dispuesto, que basta calentarlo en un santiamén para dar una opípara comida a
cualquier huésped que llegue de improviso.

La matanza se hace una vez al año en cada casa medianamente acomodada; y en aquella faena suele
lucir la señora su actividad y tino. Se levanta antes que raye la aurora, y rodeada de sus
siervas dirige, cuando no hace ella misma, la serie de importantes operaciones. Ya sazona la
masa de las morcillas, echando en ella, con rociadas magistrales y en la conveniente proporción,
sal, orégano, comino, pimiento y otras especias; ya fabrica los chorizos, longanizas, salchichas
y demás embuchados.

La mayor parte de esto se suspende del humero en cañas o barras largas de hierro, lo cual presta
a la cocina un delicioso carácter de suculenta abundancia. Casi siempre se reciben en invierno
las visitas en torno del hogar, donde arde un monte de encina o de olivo y pasta de orujo,
bajo la amplia campana de la chimenea. Entonces, si el que llega mojado de la lluvia o transido
de frío, ya de la calle, ya del campo, alza los ojos al cielo para darle gracias por hallarse
tan bien, se halla mucho mejor y tiene que reiterar las gracias, al descubrir aquella densa
constelación de chorizos y de morcillas, cuyo aroma trasciende y desciende a las narices, penetra
en el estómago y despierta o resucita el apetito. ¡Cuántas veces le he saciado yo, estando
de tertulia, por la noche, en torno de uno de estos hogares hospitalarios! Tal vez la misma
señora, tal vez alguna criada gallarda y ágil, descolgaba con regia generosidad una o dos morcillas,
y las asaba en parrillas sobre el rescoldo. Comidas luego con blanco pan, con un traguito de
vino de la tierra, que es el vino mejor del mundo, y en sabrosa y festiva conversación, sabían
estas morcillas a gloria.

Es injusta la fama cuando asegura que se come mal por allí. En mi provincia hay un sibaritismo
rústico que encanta. Bien sabe mi paisana estimar, buscar y servir en su mesa las mejores frutas,
empezando por la que se cría en su heredad, mil veces más grata al paladar y más lisonjera
para el amor propio que la tan celebrada del cercado ajeno. Ni carece tampoco, en la estación
oportuna, de cerezas garrafales de Carcabuey, de peras de Priego, de melones de Montalvan,
de melocotones de Alcaudete, de higos de Montilla, de naranjas de Palma del Río, y aun de aquellas
únicas ciruelas, que se dan sólo en las laderas del castillo de Cabra; ciruelas, dulces como
la miel, que huelen mejor que las rosas. En cuanto a las uvas, no hay que decir que son mejores
ni peores en ninguna parte, porque son excelentes en todas: y las hay lairenes, pedrojiménez,
negras, albillas, dombuenas de corazón de cabrito, moscateles, baladíes, y de otros mil linajes
o vidueños.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04591</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>824</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19253</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Just if mankind
is born. I have read in a very learned book this sentence, I will never forget. "Mankind, in
its collective life, not yet born."

All this long history that we already living in the spring of maximum and descry a long future,
glorious and fruitful, must not, however, rejoice too much, or less hubris. Compared our twenty
millions of years already served, plus twenty million at least last spring still on this planet,
with other springs and peak years of other planets and solar systems larger ones, may seem more
brief this spring that the ordinary and vulgar fine year, which only
lasted three months.

I spent days pondering on the subject, and found myself in the field, in pleasant solitude in deep
valley surrounded by steep rocks, where there was quiet, cool and
a thousand plants, herbs and flowers, had awakened a dream that seemed
pure spiritual vision and intuition to something real, but for me
physically imperceptible.

Within the area of ??one square kilometer understood that there were some subtle emanations of
certain fluid thousand times fainter than the air flow that penetrated the air around, infusing
in the gaps and interstices that allow molecules. This fluid, that man does not see, neither
weighed, and never feel with your senses, does not rise beyond a mile. We therefore a cubic kilometer
of this fluid filled thin, diluted in the air as perfumes or fragrances. Figureme, then, my world
as a cubic kilometer apart, and saw that it was populated by a lineage of sylphs so tiny that
if you accidentally swallow any one of the meanest molecule air, this molecule and perhaps you
will drown or choke as any of us a peach pit. My lineage sylphs breathe, therefore tenuous fluid
which I spoke.

With air molecules do sylphs thousand beauties, and even play when they are young, huge disparity
through blowguns.

Outside cubic kilometer is for my sylph infinite, unknown and unfathomable. Living in one hour,
but his mind is so fast and so subtle that at this time have time plenty of room for instruction,
love, spread, careers, rising to the highest positions, leave an illustrious name to its legitimate
offspring, and even tired of life and appeal suicide. One minute
for any of them is much more than a year for any us.

Their poets composed verses desperate and disillusioned at fifteen minutes after birth, and
his wise invent the deepest and most convoluted systems of philosophy at thirty minutes.

The voice of my sylph is so thin that only the fluid can be transmitted in waves above sound. His
words are so early in a second story concerns a sylph who the most concise of us take three
or four hours to count. Everything between us is extensive, it is intense among the sylph. In four
hours of any day is extended History of the Sylphs, and is so rich
in revolutions, changes, wars and progress, like ours in the 1870-odd
years that separate from the Christian Era until the time of writing.

Sylphs have my human figure. I understand that every soul, every thought that informs a body, big
or small, gives this figure as the most beautiful.

The beauty of my sylph is such that if we could make a very powerful microscope to get to see
them, men envy and we desperately fall in love with the females.

They are very advanced in civilization. They have had many prophets and founders of religions;
but passes including age of faith, and scratching the dawn of the age of reason.

His knowledge of history, without any mixture of fable, what gives severe criticism by Indeed,
nothing more than ninety days, which amounts to over three thousand generations. And like a minute
for them is to be equivalent to a year for us, we can say that they
make up the age of their civilization over 129,600 years.

Beyond that, going against current time, the Sylphs are not clear, but if among them are a
Darwin or a Haeckel undoubtedly place the appearance of the first world monera sylph at a distance
proportionately much larger.

The concept of the universe are very different from that formed us. And not because his reason
is inconsistent with ours, but because there are other data from
their senses.

Fail with the view to the sun or the moon or the stars, where the streams of burning light Throwing
on them first, and warm, silvery light that bathes the moon, come for them from a hidden spring.
So are a thousand scenarios to explain. Course there are long historical periods of light and other
long historical periods.

In his world there are living beings, of such gigantic proportions that we do not even conceive.
A wasp is cheaper for them than it would be for us the Nevado de Sorata, if pulling himself from
rennet, cheering and throwing wings, to receive a fly and show us through the air. Fortunately,
the excessive smallness of the Sylphs and agility portentous save them of these monsters.

It
is clear that the infinite is always infinite, so in the mind of a sylph and mind of a man.
At this point, if we incur a rational speculation, our concepts are equal, but to count on extended
to greater numbers, to notice much, Sylphs beat us, penetrate your senses and see and perceive
depths extension of time, volume and duration in the infinitely small,
where the median, the mean for us, the universe of a cubic kilometer
is more daunting for them the whole vastness of the heavens to us.

And do not stop putting so beyond its infinite universe unexplored.

Walk all very proud with their culture and their progress, they judge without limits. Just as
there is already a very long last, expect even longer future. And
it is certain not wrong.

They were born this past spring and will finish at the end of next fall. Now, it's summer, are
around the height of its grandeur. The same thing happens to us.

Who knows if there will be things in which we compare what we think we are my sylph? If any
of these beings come to find out that we exist, as I have come to find out that there sylphs
such, do not laugh, or pity us, seeing hope yet so long future? The millions of years we have been
living and those who hope to live Moreover, it will be for a spring. Perhaps, when you return
the Summer or bathing in some bathrooms of their world, find and made our own desolate ruins and
extinct, our ephemeral race. But it will be right. What is important is intelligence, which is not measured
by rods, not for miles, nor Earth diameters.

Its activity, when fertilized, can condense in a minute more facts, more ideas, more creations,
more glory and more hell, that other intelligence reluctant, lazy and stupid, for ever and ever.

Last
morality. Everything is relative, as I said D. Hermogenes. No less no more. In time I've taken
me to write this article to fulfill my rash promise, a man fertile ingenuity had been able to
write the history of the entire human race, and in less time, my sylph are able to do the most
important of his own history. Do not give for sure, because I've come to learn well and do not
like to fantasize, but it is possible while I've been writing all these candideces afanadísimo
and innocent, so muddle through, my sylph have founded new empires,
created constitutions, invented philosophies and machinery, and erected
monuments in their feelings, evergreen.

Such consideration I am ashamed and humiliated, rather than full of
vanity, and, although not of Sylphs, but men like me, the audience
has to read to me, he still presented with the greatest distrust of
this writing, I have not had sleep or mood, or time to do more soon.

THE CORDOVA

The editor of this work was kind enough to entrust a century been one of his articles, and I naturally
chose the Cordoba, as the province of Cordoba, where I was born and I grew up.

My extreme laziness has prevented me until now to keep my word to
write.

Perhaps to palliate this lack me I had a number of difficulties and objections, which was
half thinking of condemning the editor, to help justify my tardiness in to fruition with my
work.

What essential difference, or even accidental notable difference can be or is say, between Cordoba,
the jaenense or Seville? Back in the old maybe any, because communications were so easy, and
it was easier to live isolated and sedentary, but on the day that, not men and women in adjoining
provinces, but those remote nations apartadísimos faraway countries and kingdoms, and visitors
are often How to persist the variety and distinction of types, giving occasion for describing women
who by their customs, beliefs, ways of feeling and thinking, appearance, continent and costume,
differentiate to the point that the paintings or descriptions of them make, vary by subject,
not just by the style of painting or describe? Also, I said I, though the stamp of caste and nationality
are indelible, not who hits delete or confuse the continued existence and the inner spiritual
commerce at this time both are written, read and travel, in this age of steam and electricity,
railroad and telegraph, still not persuaded that there is also a mark of provincialism, as no
seal of nation, tribe or caste. The peculiar and castizo, as have the These unique qualities,
from divisions that made the nature, and not the administrative or political divisions, ie artificial,
as are the divisions provinces. Malaga or Seville will, no doubt, caste and more homogeneous soil
with certain Cordoba, Cordoba than those of many together. A woman of Cuevas de San Marcos,
for example, should be more like another of Rute, Rute a Belalcázar
to another, and more will resemble that of the Benamejí Casariche,
Benamejí than that of Almodóvar.

Tired as I know that between the Galician and Catalan woman, and between La Mancha and Bilbao
had to mediate radical differences, but that of each province, was the it was, he would have
a special type, I was hard to believe.

I just saved monotony of this book and encrypting the variety in the diverse talent of every
writer in the bias that manages to give the matter, and the singularity of his style, thoughts and
feelings.

I never thought that the editor wishes we wrote a scholarly review, a number of lives of all the famous
women of each province. This would perhaps be not only entertaining, but exemplary and didactic,
but it was not, nor have I committed to writing my article, if this is it. It was historical
work, or biographical, which was traced and planned, but box and painting the living habits
or accurate picture of what today is reflected in every province in land use, culture, ideas,
and other items, conditions and actions of women.

And being the thing, I repeat that I did not see me for nothing or almost nothing to stop
the monotony of the work on the subject, although the subject, or I should say by the subjects
came to be a flower garden, and the layer of the student, through the diversity of styles and
idiosyncrasies of each writer that she put an hand.

Thus, on more or less, walked me wondering, when family duties took
me to kidney in the province of Cordoba, to a happy region where the
local color is provincial released by the handful of lavish nature
and inexhaustible in their various creations.

Y being this color, this stamp, this type throughout, how, I said to myself, not to be so in
women, which is soft wax for impressions, and hard to preserve bronze without they fade?

More than five months I went in my place, and this time apparently moved completely respect the
book of Mr. Pebble. I had no excuse for not writing the article.

He was convinced that if I paint Cordoba was not a type sui generis, it was because I did not
know painting what I was seeing a clear way. I decided, therefore, since to do this painting,
ingenuously confessed that, if it does not original and new, the fault is mine and not the
model.

One thing still troubles me and makes my purpose. To see and treat the Cordoba of the day, come
my imagination the species nearly wiped from my childhood and early youth, tired far unfortunately,
slept or were buried in my mind, the first in Cordoba third of this century. The disparity between
the memory and print this confused me a little. Cordoba female type has not disappeared, but
there has been change, but change it has not been castizo to the exotic. The change has been
for development of the interior very essence of women in Cordoba, which, like all essences immortal
remains in substantial foundation, while taking on new forms and
new accidents.

The Cordoba of this historic moment is not the previous historical moment in Cordoba, but is always
of Cordoba, and always continues to make its essence as each neighbor's
daughter, externalizing the typical idea their own, and presenting
different aspect in each of the various developments with the exteriorized.

I

see that elevates me too, and I'm going to go down and speak with more frankness, leaving kidnapping
philosophy for another time.

Today I get the Cordoba in the light as it is, while memory retracts me as it was thirty or
forty years ago. Of confusion arises here, something like a antinomy, but while studying the antinomy
is resolved with little work on a synthesis supreme. This short, if you were right I to create would
be a neat article. Moreover, no this synthesis is not possible the article because I'm not
going to paint the Cordoba dead stop stationary, inert, fossil, but
the Cordoba living, moving, developing, in progress; unfolding, not
given impulse, but by the laws of their own great being and its rich
and generous body.

To purchase the whole concept of Cordoba is necessary to study in different classes and states:
from the great lady to the porter rude woman from the girl to the elderly, from the daughter's
family to the mother or grandmother, and see and visit, and in the former and splendid capital of
the Caliphate, and in the Sierra, north of the Guadalquivir, abundant mines and wild meadows
and elusive, and the bountiful countryside where there are populated places and from the beautiful
cities, where wealth, welfare and culture are higher. But if we were analyzing and examining all
of these things separately, it would end or our article, and so should
touch only capital items, and encrypt and summarize in two or three
types everything in Córdoba most characteristic and proper.

Of course, in the province of Cordoba is rich ladies who have been or are in Madrid, that may
have gone to Baden or Biarritz a summer speaking French, who have walked in the forest of
Boulogne, who know perhaps several foreign courts, who read the novels George Sand and Lamartine
in the same language they were written, and that Worth dress with Laferrière, with or with
Isolina Honorine. In all of these women remains remains the essence of women in Cordoba, but it would
be necessary to deepen and penetrate too discover that essence through so many attachments to strangers
and so many false externalities.

Seek, therefore, to Cordoba where we have no genuine need for further or eliminate to find it:
let us look at the villager, whether rich and poor, and lady and maid.

The villager is extremely hardworking. However poor, must clean the house jumping. The floors,
marble tile, brick or plaster studded seem burnished by dint of mopping.

If the mistress of the house has a well, shine in two or three glass china cabinets and dishes,
and in symmetrical rows adorn the walls of the kitchen pots, pans and Other dishes of brass or
copper, where can one see the face in a mirror.

The Cordoba is all surveillance, hygiene, care and careful economy. Never leave keys the pantry,
cupboards, chests and cabinets. On the shelf units or shelves of the pantry usually maintained
as provident and rich profusion, a treasure of foodstuffs, which account, and prosperity of the
house, and of fertile farms of the owner, if they are products Indians and, as they say, one's upbringing
and tillage, and the skill and elegance the lady, whose work has increased the value of the
first subject with some preparation or condiment. There has walnuts, chestnuts, almonds, sweet potatoes,
wrapped imperial cirolitas paper for the writing, brandied cherries, apricots and a thousand other trinkets.
Peppers spicy hot peppers and garlic and horns, hung on strings next to the cod the less neat.
In part there is usually neater sugar, coffee, sage, linden, chamomile, and even tea sometimes,
just before the pharmacy was. Hanging from the ceiling and giant egregious hams, and, alternating
with the pastoral statement of the animal kingdom, sweet andregüelas wintry, grapes, pomegranates
and other fruits. Preserved in deep glazed crocks back Mrs. marinated pork, covered with butter,
birds, ie, offal, kidney and spleen of the same quadruped, and even
rubble, artichokes, mushrooms and asparagus and amargueros, all it
so well prepared, it is enough heat in a hurry to give a hearty meal
any guest who comes unexpectedly.

The killing is done once a year in each house well-off, and in that task usually look lady its
activity and skill. He rises before dawn to scratch, and surrounded by her servants runs, she does,
the series of major operations. Seasons and mass of the black pudding, pouring on her, sprayed master
and the appropriate proportion salt, oregano, cumin, pepper and other
spices, and manufactures sausages, sausages, sausages and other sausage.

Most

of this is suspended from the humerus in long rods or bars of iron, which provides to cook a delicious
abundance of succulent character. Are almost always in winter visits around the home, where a
mountain of burning oak or olive pulp and pomace under the broad hood of the fireplace. So
if you get wet from the rain and transfixed cold, and the street, and the field, raised his eyes
to heaven to be giving thanks for as well, is much better and have to reiterate the thanks, to
discover that dense constellation of sausages and black pudding, which transcends and aroma
to the nose down, penetrates in the stomach and awakens or revives the appetite. Many times I have
satisfied myself, being talk shows at night, around one of these homes hospital! Maybe the
same lady, perhaps a servant bold and agile, with kingly generosity took down one or two sausages,
and roasted on grills on the embers. After meals with white bread with a sip of local wine, which is
the world's best wine, and delicious and festive conversation, they knew these puddings to glory.

It
is unfair to fame when he says he eats bad over there. In my province there is a sybaritic rustic
love.

Well you know my countrywoman estimate, look at your table and serve the best fruit starting with
the one raised in his heritage, a thousand times more pleasant to the palate and more flattering
for self-love that held the fence as others. Nor does either, at station timely blunders Carcabuey
cherry, pear of Priego, melon Montalvan Alcaudete peaches, figs Montilla, oranges Palma del Rio,
and even those only plums, which are given only on the slopes of Cabra Castle, plums, sweet
and Honey, you smell better than roses. As for the grapes, not to say they are better or worse anywhere,
they are excellent in all: and there lairenes, pedrojiménez, black Albillo, dombuenas kid at
heart, muscat, trivial, and a thousand other lineages or vintages.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>