<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04335</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>70625</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21115</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Al salir de Jupiter, atravesaron un espacio de cerca
de cien millones de leguas, y costearon el planeta Marte, el qual, como todos saben, es cinco
veces mas pequeno que nuestro globulo; y vieron dos lunas que sirven a este planeta, y no han
podido descubrir nuestros astronomos. Bien se que el abate Ximenez escribira con mucho donayre
contra la existencia de dichas lunas, mas yo apelo a los que discurren por analogia; todos
excelentes filosofos que saben muy bien que no le seria posible a Marte vivir sin dos lunas
a lo menos, estando tan distante del sol. Sea como fuere, a nuestros caminantes les parecio
cosa tan chica, que se temieron no hallar posada comoda, y pasaron adelante como hacen dos
caminantes quando topan con una mala venta en despoblado, y siguen hasta el pueblo inmediato.
Pero luego se arrepintieron el Sirio y su companero, que anduvieron un largo espacio sin hallar
albergue. Al cabo columbraron una lucecilla, que era la tierra, y que parecio muy mezquina
cosa a gentes que venian de Jupiter. No obstante, rezelando arrepentirse otra vez, se determinaron
a desembarcar en ella. Pasaron a la cola del cometa, y hallando una aurora boreal a mano, se
metieron dentro, y aportaron en tierra a la orilla septentrional del mar Baltico, a cinco de
Julio de mil setecientos treinta y siete.

CAPITULO IV.

Que da cuenta de lo que les sucedio en el globo de la tierra.

Habiendo descansado un poco, se almorzaron dos montanas que les guisaron sus criados con mucho
aseo. Quisieron luego reconocer el mezquino pais donde se hallaban, y se dirigieron de Norte
a Sur. Cada paso ordinario del Sirio y su familia era de unos treinta mil pies de rey: seguiale
de lejos el enano de Saturno, que perdia el aliento, porque tenia que dar doce pasos mientras
alargaba el otro la pierna, casi como un perrillo faldero que sigue, si se me permite la comparacion,
a un capitan de guardias del rey de Prusia.

Como andaban de priesa estos extrangeros, dieron la vuelta al globo en treinta y seis horas:
verdad es que el sol, o por mejor decir la tierra, hace el mismo viage en un dia; pero hemos
de reparar que es cosa mas facil girar sobre su exe que anclar a pie. Volvieron al cabo al
sitio donde etaban primero, habiendo visto la balsa, casi imperceptible para ellos, que llaman
el Mediterraneo, y el otro estanque chico que con nombre de grande Oceano rodea nuestra madriguera;
al enano le daba el agua a media pierna, y apenas si se habia mojado el otro los talones. Fueron
y vinieron arriba y abaxo, haciendo quanto podian por averiguar si estaba o no habitado este
globo: baxaronse, acostaronse, tentaron por todas partes; pero eran tan desproporcionados sus
ojos y manos con los mezquinos seres que andan arrastrando aca baxo, que no tuvieron la mas
leve sensacion por donde pudiesen caer en sospecha de que existimos nosotros y nuestros hermanos
los demas moradores de este globo.

El enano, que a veces fallaba con alguna precipitacion, decidio luego que no habia vivientes
en la tierra, y su razon primera fue que no habia visto ninguno. Micromegas le dio a entender
con mucha urbanidad, que no era fundada la consequeencia; porque, le dixo, con vuestros ojos
tan chicos no veis ciertas estrellas de quinquagesima magnitud, que distingo yo con mucha claridad.
?Colegis por eso que no haya tales estrellas? Si lo he tentado todo, dixo el enano. ?Y si no
habeis sentido lo que hay? dixo el otro. Si esta tan mal compaginado este globo, replico el
enano; si es tan irregular, y de una configuracion que parece tan ridicula, que todo el se
me figura un caos. ?No veis esos arroyuelos, que ninguno corre derecho; esos estanques que
ni son redondos, ni quadrados, ni ovalados, ni de figura regular ninguna; todos esos granillos
puntiagudos de que esta erizado, y se me han entrado en los pies? (y queria hablar de las montanas).
?No notais la forma de todo el globo, aplastado por los polos, y girando en torno del sol con
tan desconcertada direccion, que por necesidad los climas de ambos polos han de estar incultos?
Lo que me fuerza a creer de veras que no hay vivientes en el, es que ninguno que tuviese razon
querria habitarle. ?Que importa? dixo Micromegas, acaso no tienen sentido comun los habitantes,
pero al cabo no es de presumir que se haya hecho esto sin algun fin. Decis que aqui todo os
parece irregular, porque esta todo tirado a cordel en Jupiter y Saturno. Pues por esa misma
razon acaso hay aqui algo de confusion. ?No os he dicho ya que siempre habia notado variedad
en mis viages? Replico el Saturnino a estas razones, y no se hubiera concluido la disputa,
si en el calor de ella no hubiese roto Micromegas el hilo de su collar de diamantes, y caidose
estos; que eran unos brillantes muy lindos, aunque pequenitos y desiguales, que los mas gruesos
pesaban quatrocientas libras, y cincuenta los mas menudos. Cogio el enano algunos, y arrimandoselos
a los ojos vio que del modo que estaban abrillantados, eran microscopios excelentes: cogio
pues un microscopio chico de ciento y sesenta pies de diametro, y se le aplico a un ojo, mientras
que se servia Micromegas de otro de dos mil y quinientos pies. Al principio no vieron nada
con ellos, puesto que eran aventajados; fue preciso ponerse en la posicion que se requeria.
Al cabo vio el morador de Saturno una cosa imperceptible que se meneaba entre dos aguas en
el mar Baltico, y era una ballena: pusola bonitamente encima del dedo, y colocandola en la
una del pulgar, se la enseno al Sirio, que por la segunda vez se echo a reir de la enorme pequenez
de los moradores de nuestro globo. Convencido el Saturnino de que estaba habitado nuestro mundo,
se imagino luego que solo por ballenas lo estaba; y como era gran discurridor, quiso adivinar
de donde venia el movimiento a un atomo tan ruin, y si tenia ideas, voluntad y libre albedrio.
Micromegas no sabia que pensar; mas habiendo examinado con mucha paciencia el animal, saco
de su examen que no podia residir un alma en cuerpo tan chico. Inclinabanse pues nuestros dos
caminantes a creer que no hay razon en nuestra habitacion, quando, con el auxilio del microscopio,
distinguieron otro bulto mas grueso que una ballena, que en el mar Baltico andaba fluctuando.
Ya sabemos que hacia aquella epoca volvia del circulo polar una bandada de filosofos, que habian
ido a hacer observaciones en que nadie hasta entonces habia pensado. Traxeron los papeles publicos
que habia zozobrado su embarcacion en las costas de Botnia, y que les habia costado mucho trabajo
el salir a salvamento; pero nunca se sabe en este mundo lo que hay por debaxo de cuerda. Yo
voy a contar con ingenuidad el suceso, sin quitar ni anadir nada: esfuerzo que de parte de
un historiador es sobremanera meritorio.

CAPITULO V.

Experiencias y raciocinios de ambos caminantes.

Tendio Micromegas con mucho tiento la mano al sitio donde se via el objeto, y alargando y encogiendo
los dedos de miedo de equivocarse, y abriendolos luego y cerrandolos, agarro con mucha mana
el navio donde iban estos senores, y se le puso sobre la una, sin apretarle mucho, por no estruxarle.
Hete aqui un animal muy distinto del otro, dixo el enano de Saturno; y el Sirio puso el pretenso
animal en la palma de la mano. Los pasageros y marineros de la tripulacioon, que se creian
arrebatados por un huracan, y que pensaban haber barado en un baxio, estan todos en movimiento;
cogen los marineros toneles de vino, los tiran a la mano de Micromegas, y ellos se tiran despues;
agarran los geometras de sus quartos de circulo, sus sectores, y sus muchachas laponas, y se
apean en los dedos del Sirio: por fin tanto se afanaron, que sintio que se meneaba una cosa
que le escarabajeaba en los dedos, y era un garrote con un hierro a la punta que le clavaban
hasta un pie en el dedo indice: esta picazon le hizo creer que habia salido algo del cuerpo
del animalejo que en la mano tenia; mas no pudo sospechar al principio otra cosa, pues su microscopio,
que apenas bastaba para distinguir un navio de una ballena, no podia hacer visible un entecillo
tan imperceptible como un hombre. No quiero zaherir aqui la vanidad de ninguno; pero ruego
a la gente vanagloriosa que paren la consideracion en este lugar, y contemplen que suponiendo
la estatura ordinaria de un hombre de cinco pies de rey, no hacemos mas bulto en la tierra
que el que en una bola de diez pies de circunferencia hiciera un animal que tuviese un seiscientos
mil avos de pulgada de alto. Figuremonos una substancia que pudiera llevar el globo terraquueeo
en la mano, y que tuviese organos analogos a los nuestros, y es cosa muy factible que haya
muchas de estas substancias; y colijamos que es lo que de las funciones de guerra, en que hemos
ganado dos o tres lugarejos que luego ha sido fuerza restituir, pensarian.

No me queda duda de que si algun capitan de granaderos leyere esta obra, haga a su tropa que
se ponga gorras dos pies mas altas; pero le advierto que, por mas que haga, siempre seran el
y sus soldados unos infinitamente pequenos.

iQue maravillosa mana hubo de necesitar nuestro filosofo de Sirio para atinar a columbrar los
atomos de que acabo de hablar! Quando Leuwenhoek y Hartsoeker vieron, o creyeron que vian,
por la vez primera, la simiente de que somos formados, no fue, ni con mucho, tan asombroso
su descubrimiento. iQue gusto el de Micromegas quando vio estas maquinillas menearse, quando
examino sus movimientos todos, y siguio todas sus operaciones! iComo clamaba! icon que jubilo
alargo a su companero de viage uno de sus microscopios! Viendolos estoy, decian ambos juntos;
contemplad como se cargan, como se baxan y se alzan. Asi decian, y les temblaban las manos
de gozo de ver objetos tan nuevos, y de temor de perderlos de vista. Pasando el Saturnino de
un extremo de confianza al opuesto de credulidad, se figuro que los estaba viendo ocupados
en la propagacion. Ha, dixo el Saturnino, cogida tengo la naturaleza "con las manos en la masa."
Enganabanle empero las apariencias, y asi sucede muy frequeentemente, quando uno usa y quando
no usa microscopios.

CAPITULO VI.

De lo que les acontecio con unos hombres.

Muy mejor observador Micromegas que su enano, vio claramente que se hablaban los atomos, y
se lo hizo notar a su companero, el qual con la vergueenza de haberse enganado acerca del articulo
de la generacion, no quiso creer que semejante especie de bichos se pudieran comunicar ideas.
Tenia el don de lenguas no menos que el Sirio; y no oyendo hablar a nuestros atomos, suponia
que no hablaban: y luego ?como habian de tener los organos de la voz unos entes tan imperceptibles,
ni que se habian de decir? Para hablar es indispensable pensar; y si pensaban, tenian algo
que equivalia al alma: y atribuir una cosa equivalente al alma a especie tan ruin, se le hacia
mucho disparate. Dixole el Sirio: ?Pues no creiais, poco hace, que se estaban enamorando? ?pensais
que enamora nadie sin pensar, y sin hablar palabra, o a lo menos sin darse a entender? ?o suponeis
que es cosa mas facil hacer un chiquillo que un silogismo? A mi uno y otro me parecen impenetrables
misterios. No me atrevo ya, dixo el enano, a creer ni a negar cosa ninguna; procuremos examinar
estos insectos, y discurriremos luego. iQue me place! respondio Micromegas; y sacando unas
tixeras, se corto las unas, y con lo que corto de la una de su dedo pulgar hizo al punto una
especie de bocina grande, como un embudo inmenso, y puso el canon al oido: la circunferencia
del embudo cogia el navio y toda su tripulacion, y la mas debil voz se introducia en las fibras
circulares de la una, de suerte que, merced de su industria, el filosofo de alla arriba oyo
perfectamente el zumbido de nuestros insectos de aca abaxo, y en pocas horas logro distinguir
las palabras, y entender al cabo el frances. Lo mismo hizo el enano, aunque no con tanta facilidad.
Crecia por puntos el asombro de los dos viageros, al oir unos aradores hablar con bastante
razon, y les parecia inexplicable este juego de la naturaleza. Bien se discurre que se morian
el enano y el Sirio de deseos de entablar conversacion con los atomos; mas se temia el enano
que su tenante voz, y mas aun la de Micromegas, atronara a los aradores sin que la oyesen.
Trataron, pues de disminuir su fuerza, y para ello se pusieron en la boca unos mondadientes
muy menudos, cuya punta muy afilada iba a parar junto al navio. Puso el Sirio al enano sobre
sus rodillas, y encima de una una el navio con la tripulacion; baxo la cabeza y hablo muy quedo,
y despues de todas estas precauciones y otras muchas mas, dixo lo siguiente: Invisibles insectos
que la diestra del Criador se plugo en producir en el abismo de los infinitamente pequenos,
yo le bendigo porque se digno manifestarme impenetrables secretos. Acaso nadie se dignara de
miraros en mi corte, pero yo a nadie desprecio, y os brindo con mi proteccion.

Si ha habido asombros en el mundo, ninguno ha llegado al de los que estas razones oyeron decir,
sin poder atinar de donde salian. Rezo el capellan las preces de conjuros, votaron y renegaron
los marineros, y fraguaron un sistema los filosofos del navio; pero, por mas sistemas que imaginaron,
no les fue posible atinar quien era el que les hablaba. Entonces les conto en breves palabras
el enano de Saturno, que tenia menos recia la voz que Micromegas, con que gente estaban hablando,
y su viage de Saturno: les informo de quien era el senor Micromegas, y habiendose compadecido
de que fueran tan chicos, les pregunto si habian vivido siempre en un estado tan rayano de
la nada, y que era lo que hacian en un globo que al parecer era peculio de ballenas; si eran
dichosos, si tenian alma, si multiplicaban, y otras mil preguntas de este jaez.

Enojado de que dudasen si tenia alma, un raciocinador de la banda, mas osado que los demas,
observo al interlocutor con unas pinulas adaptadas a un quarto de circulo, midio dos triangulos,
y al tercero le dixo asi: ?Con que creeis, senor caballero, que porque teneis dos mil varas
de pies a cabeza, sois algun?... iDos mil varas! exclamo el enano, pues no se equivoca ni en
una pulgada. iCon que me ha medido este atomo! icon que es geometra, y sabe mi tamano; y yo
que no le puedo ver sin auxilio de un microscopio, no se aun el suyo! Si, que os he medido,
dixo el fisico, y tambien medire al gigante companero vuestro. Admitiose la propuesta, y se
acosto Su Excelencia por el suelo, porque estando en pie su cabeza era muy mas alta que las
nubes; y nuestros filosofos le plantaron un arbol muy grande en cierto sitio que Torres o Quevedo
hubiera nombrado por su nombre, pero que yo no me atrevo a mentar, por el mucho respeto que
tengo a las damas; y luego por una serie de triangulos, conexos unos con otros, coligieron
que la persona que median era un mancebito de ciento y veinte mil pies de rey.

Prorumpio entonces Micromegas en estas razones: Ya veo que nunca se han de juzgar las cosas
por su aparente magnitud. O Dios, que diste la inteligencia a unas substancias que tan despreciables
parecen, lo infinitamente pequeno no cuesta mas a tu omnipotencia que lo infinitamente grande;
y si es dable que haya otros seres mas chicos que estos, acaso tendran una inteligencia superior
a la de aquellos inmensos animales que he visto en el cielo, y que con un pie cubririan el
globo entero donde ahora me encuentro.

Respondiole uno de los filosofos que bien podia creer, sin que le quedase duda, que habia seres
inteligentes mucho mas chicos que el hombre, y le conto, no las fabulas que nos ha dexado Virgilio
sobre las abejas, sino lo que Swammerdam ha descubierto, y lo que ha disecado Reaumur. Instruyole
luego de que hay animales que son, con respecto a las abejas, lo que son las abejas con respecto
al hombre, y lo que era el Sirio propio con respecto a aquellos animales tan corpulentos de
que hablaba, y lo que son estos grandes animales con respecto a otras substancias ante las
quales parecen imperceptibles atomos. Poco a poco fue haciendose interesante la conversacion,
y dixo asi Micromegas.

CAPITULO VII.

Conversacion con los hombres.

O atomos inteligentes, en quien se plugo el eterno Ser en manifestar su arte y su potencia,
sin duda que en vuestro globo disfrutais contentos purisimos; pues teniendo tan poca materia
y pareciendo todos espiritu, debeis emplear vuestra vida en amar y pensar, que es la verdadera
vida de los espiritus. En parte ninguna he visto la verdadera felicidad, mas estoy cierto de
que esta es su mansion. Encogieronse de hombros al oir este razonamiento los filosofos todos;
y mas ingenuo uno de ellos confeso sinceramente que, exceptuando un cortisimo numero de moradores
poquisimo apreciados, todo lo demas es una cafila de locos, de perversos y desdichados. Mas
materia tenemos, dixo, de la que es menester para obrar mal, si procede el mal de la materia,
y mas inteligencia, si proviene de la inteligencia. ?Sabeis por exemplo que a la hora esta
cien mil locos de nuestra especie, que llevan sombreros, estan matando a otros cien mil animales
cubiertos de un turbante, o muriendo a sus manos, y que asi es estilo en toda la tierra, de
tiempo inmemorial aca? Horrorizose el Sirio, y pregunto el motivo de tan horribles contiendas
entre animalejos tan ruines. Tratase, dixo el filosofo, de unos pedacillos de tierra tamanos
como vuestro pie, y no porque ni uno de los millones de hombres que pierden la vida solicite
un terron siquiera de dicho pedazo; que se trata de saber si ha de pertenecer a cierto hombre
que llaman Sultan, o a otro que apellidan Cesar, no se por que. Ninguno de los dos ha visto
ni vera nunca el rinconcillo de tierra que esta en litigio; ni menos casi ninguno de los animales
que reciprocamente se asesinan ha visto tampoco al animal por quien asesina.

iDesventurados! exclamo indignado el Sirio: ?como es posible imaginar tan furioso frenesi?
Arranques me vienen de dar tres pasos, y con tres patadas estruxar todo ese hormiguero de ridiculos
asesinos. No os tomeis ese trabajo, le respondieron, que sobrado se afanan ellos en labrar
su ruina. Sabed que dentro de diez anos no quedara en vida el diezmo de estos miserables; y
que, aun sin sacar la espada, casi todos se los lleva la hambre, la fatiga, o la destemplanza,
aparte de que no son ellos los que merecen castigo, sino los ociosos despiadados, que metidos
en su gabinete mandan, mientras digieren la comida, degollar un millon de hombres, y dan luego
solemnes acciones de gracias a Dios. Sentiase el caminante movido a piedad del mezquino linage
humano, en el qual tantas contradicciones descubria. Siendo vosotros, dixo a estos senores,
del corto numero de sabios que sin duda a nadie matan por dinero, os ruego que me digais quales
son vuestras ocupaciones. Disecamos moscas, respondio el filosofo, medimos lineas, combinamos
numeros, estamos conformes acerca de dos o tres puntos que entendemos, y divididos sobre dos
o tres mil que no entendemos. Ocurrioles al Sirio y al Saturnino hacer preguntas a los atomos
pensadores, para saber sobre que estaban acordes. ?Que distancia hay, dixo este, desde la estrella
de la Canicula hasta la grande de Geminis? Respondieronle todos juntos: Treinta y dos grados
y medio.--?Quanto dista de aqui la luna?--Sesenta semi-diametros de la tierra.--?Quanto pesa
vuestro ayre? Creia haberlos cogido; pero todos le dixeron que pesaba novecientas veces menos
que el mismo volumen del agua mas ligera, y diez y nueve mil veces menos que el oro. Atonito
el enanillo de Saturno con sus respuestas, estaba tentado a creer que eran magicos aquellos
mismos a quienes un quarto de hora antes les habia negado la inteligencia.

Dixoles finalmente Micromegas: Una vez que tan puntualmente sabeis lo que hay fuera de vosotros,
sin duda que mejor todavia sabreis lo que hay dentro: decidme pues que cosa es vuestra alma,
y como se forman vuestras ideas. Los filosofos hablaron todos a la par, como antes, pero todos
fueron de distinto parecer. Cito el mas anciano a Aristoteles, otro pronuncio el nombre de
Descartes, este el de Malebranche, aquel el de Leibnitz, y el de Locke otro. El anciano peripatetico
dixo con toda confianza: El alma es una entelechia, una razon en virtud de la qual tiene la
potencia de ser lo que es; asi lo dice expresamente Aristoteles, pag. 633 de la edicion del
Louvre: Entelexeia esti, etc. No entiendo el griego, dixo el gigante. Ni yo tampoco, respondio
el arador filosofico. ?Pues a que citais, replico el Sirio, a ese Aristoteles en griego? Porque
lo que uno no entiende, repuso el sabio, lo ha de citar en lengua que no sabe.

Tomo el hilo el cartesiano, y dixo: Es el alma un espiritu puro que en el vientre de su madre
ha recibido todas las ideas metafisicas, y que asi que sale de el se ve precisada a ir a la
escuela, y aprender de nuevo lo que tan bien sabia y que nunca volvera a saber. Pues estas
medrado, respondio el animal de ocho leguas, con que supiera tanto tu alma quando estabas en
el vientre de tu madre, si habia de ser tan ignorante quando fueras tu hombre con barba. ?Y
que entiendes por espiritu? ?Que es lo que me preguntais? dixo el discurridor, no tengo idea
ninguna de el: dicen que lo que no es materia.--?Y sabes lo que es materia? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03439</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>195303</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19538</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Leaving Jupiter, passed through a space of about a hundred
million miles, and cost the planet Mars, the qual, as everyone knows, is five times smaller than
our globule, and they saw two moons that serve this planet, and have not our astronomers have
discovered. While the abbot was written in much Donayre Ximenez against the existence of these
moons, but I appeal to those run by analogy, all great philosophers who know very well that
it will be possible to live without two moons Mars at least, being so far from the sun. Anyway,
they seemed to our travelers thing girl, who feared not finding a comfortable inn, and went
forward as do two Quando walkers encounter poor sales in the wilderness, and continue to the
next village. But then he repented the Syrian and his partner, who walked a long period without
finding hostel. After a little light descry, which was the land, which seemed very mean thing to
people who had come from Jupiter. However, rezelando repent again, were determined to land
on it. They went into the comet's tail, and finding an aurora borealis by hand, went inside and brought
ashore to the north shore of the Baltic Sea, five of July 1737.

CHAPTER IV.

That accounts of what happened on the globe of the earth.

Having rested a bit, had lunch two mountains that are then cooked his servants with much toilet.
Wanted to recognize the wretched country then where they were, and headed north to south. Each
step ordinary Sirius and his family was about thirty thousand feet of the king, followed him
by far the dwarf of Saturn, who lost his breath, because I had to take twelve steps while the other leg
stretched out, almost like a lapdog that is, if you will excuse the
comparison, a captain of the guards of the king of Prussia.

As they went in a hurry these foreigners, were seen around the globe in thirty-six hours: truth
is that the sun, or rather the earth, makes the same journey in one day, but we to repair something
that is easier to turn on its exe to anchor foot. They returned after the etab first place, having
seen the raft, almost imperceptible to them, they call the Mediterranean, and another pool boy with
big name around our den Oceano; the dwarf gave him water to half a leg, and barely had wet the
other heels. Were and came up and abaxo, making quanto could be determined whether or not it
was inhabited this Balloon baxaronse, acostaronse, tempted by all parties, but was so disproportionate
their eyes and hands with the petty things that go dragging Baxo here, who had no more slight feeling
for where they might fall under suspicion of us and our brothers
the other inhabitants of this globe.

The dwarf, sometimes with some precipitation failed, he decided then that there was no living
on earth, and his first reason was that there had been none. Micromegas given to understand with great
civility, which was not founded consequeencia because, he said to him, with your eyes so kids
do not see some stars of Quinquagesima magnitude that I can distinguish very clearly. ? Colegis
why there is such a star? If I have tempted all, 'said the dwarf. And if not you have felt
what it is? he said the other. If so bad collated this globe, "replied the dwarf, if it is
so irregular, and a configuration that seems so ridiculous that everyone is I imagine chaos. ?
Not see these streams, which runs any right, these ponds and are round or squares, or oval or any regular
figure, all these bumps pointed that this bristling, and I have entered on your feet? (And wanted
to talk about the mountains). ? Do not you notice the way around the globe, flattened at the poles,
and spinning around the sun so confused direction, which by necessity climates of both poles have
to be uneducated? What forces me to believe that there is really living in, is that no one who
had reason floor would want. ? Who cares? Micromegas he said, may not have common sense people,
but after it is presumed that this has been done without any purpose. You say that you all
here appears irregular because everything is thrown into the line in Jupiter and Saturn. Well,
for the same reason is perhaps some confusion here. ? No I said that I had always noticed
variety in my journeys? Replied the Saturnino these reasons, and not completed the dispute, if
the heat she had not broken the thread of his Micromegas diamond necklace, and caidose these, that
they were very nice bright, though tiny and uneven, the thicker weighed four hundred pounds, and fifty
the most petite. Some grabbed the dwarf, and leaning saw the eyes as they were polished, microscopes
were excellent: grabbed as a kid microscope hundred and sixty feet in diameter, and was applied to
one eye, while Micromegas is served another two thousand and five hundred feet. At first they
saw nothing with them, since they were gifted, had to be put in the position that was required.
After the inhabitants of Saturn saw something bobbing imperceptible in midwater the Baltic
Sea, and it was a whale, nicely laid it over your finger and placing it in a thumb, she was
taught to Sirius, the second time he laughed at the huge smallness the inhabitants of our globe. Persuaded
by that Saturnino was inhabited our world he imagined then that it was just for whales, and as it
was great discurridor, tried to guess where the movement came to an atom so mean, and if I had
ideas, will and free will. Micromegas not know what to think, but having examined the animal patiently,
bag of consideration that he could not reside in the body as a soul boy. Inclinabanse for
our two walkers to believe that there is no reason in our room, when, with the aid of a microscope,
package distinguish other thicker than a whale in the Baltic Sea walked fluctuating. We know that
by that time returned from the polar circle, a flock of philosophers, who had gone to make observations
that no one had hitherto thought. They brought the papers public that their boat had capsized off
the coast of Bothnia, and they had a difficult time going out to rescue, but you never know in this
world there is to vnder rope. I I have naively the event, without removing or adding anything, effort
on the part of a historian is exceedingly meritorious.

CHAPTER V.

Experience and reasoning of both walkers.

Micromegas tended with great circumspection hand via the site of the object, and stretching
and shrinking fingers of fear of being wrong, and then opening them and closing them, I take very mana
the ship where they were these gentlemen, and placed on a "not too tight, not estruxarle. Lo here
a very different animal from the other, 'said the dwarf of Saturn and Sirius put the pretense
animal in the palm of the hand. The passengers and sailors tripulacioon, which is believed caught
by a storm, and thought they aground on a Baxi, are all in motion; sailors caught barrels of wine,
toss them at the hand of Micromegas, and after they are thrown; seize the geometries of quarts
circle, their sectors, and Lapp, and alight on the fingers of Sirius: Finally both were busy,
they felt it shaking a thing that beetles in the fingers, and it was a club with an iron tip
nailed him a foot in the index finger: the itching made him believe that the body had become
something The creature that I had on hand, but could not suspect anything at first, as its microscope
barely enough to distinguish a ship of a whale could not make visible a entecillo as inconspicuous
as a man. I do not want censure of any vanity here, but please vainglorious people to stop
the consideration here, and consider that if ordinary height of a man five feet of the king,
but do not lump in the ground than in a ball ten feet in circumference did an animal that
had a hundred avos thousand of an inch high. Let us imagine a substance that could lead the globe
terraquueeo in hand, and had bodies similar to ours, and it is most likely that there many of these
substances, and I gather that is what the functions of war, we have won two or three small
place that has since been restoring force would think.

I have no doubt that if any captain of grenadiers shall read this book, have your troop put hats
two feet higher, but I warn you that, however you do, always will be the and his soldiers about
infinitely small.

iQue wonderful mana you need our philosopher had Sirius for managing to descry the atoms of
which I speak! Quando Hartsoeker Leuwenhoek and saw, or believed that Vian for the first time,
the seed of which we are formed, there was not nearly as amazing discovery. iQue Micromegas
like that of when he saw these razors wiggle, when examine all their movements, and continued
its operations! iCom cried! icon who retired extension cord to his partner of one of its microscopes
journey! I'm watching them, they said both together; behold as loaded as baxan and rise. So
they said, and they shook hands the joy of seeing objects as new, and the fear of losing sight.
Saturnino passing of a trust to the opposite end of credulity, it figures that he was busy
watching in the propagation. Ha, he said the Saturnino, I have caught nature "red-handed." However
Enganabanle appearances, and so very frequeentemente happens, when one uses and when do not use
microscopes.

CHAPTER VI.

From what I happened to men.

Very best observer Micromegas his dwarf, he saw clearly that the atoms were spoken, and it pointed
out to his partner, which with the embarrassment of having deceived about the article the generation,
unwilling to believe that such kind of bugs could communicate ideas. He had the gift of tongues
is not less than Sirius, and not hearing about our atoms, supposed who did not speak: then? as
the organs were to have a voice as subtle bodies, or that they had to say? To talk is essential to
consider and if thought, had something which was equivalent to the soul: and attribute something equivalent
to a kind soul so base, is to much nonsense. The Syrian told him:? For You thought not, little does,
which were falling in love? ? Do you think to love one without thinking, without saying a word,
or at least not make themselves understood? , Or suppose it is easiest thing to a child a
syllogism? My one and one I seem impenetrable mysteries. I dare ya, 'said the dwarf, to believe
or deny any thing, try to look these insects, and runs later. iQue my place! Micromegas answered,
and drawing a tixeras, trim her nails, and short of what one of her thumb made the point a kind
of big horn, like a huge funnel, and put the fee at an ear, the circumference funnel took the
ship and all its crew, and the weakest voice in the fibers were introduced circular one, so that,
through their industry, the philosopher of heard up there well the buzz of our insects abaxo here,
and within hours was able to distinguish words, and understanding after the French. So did
the dwarf, but not so easily. Spot grew the astonishment of the two travelers, on hearing about
quite a few mites reason, and this game seemed inexplicable nature. Well it goes that he was
dying the dwarf and Syrian desire to engage in conversation with the atoms, but the dwarf
is feared his thunderous voice, and even more of Micromegas, thundered to the mites without
being overheard. They tried, as to diminish its force, and it got a toothpick in his mouth very
tiny, very sharp as he was going to stop next to the ship. He put the dwarf on the Syrian his knees
and one on top of a ship with the crew; Baxo head and spoke very quietly, and after all these precautions
and many more, said the following: Invisible bugs the right hand of the Creator is pleased
to produce in the abyss of the infinitely small, I manifest myself worthy bless because impenetrable
secrets. Perhaps no one is worthy of yourselves in my court, but
I despise anyone, and I give you my protection.

If there has been amazing in the world, none has reached the that this was heard to say, unable to hit
upon which he left. The chaplain pray the prayers of spells, and disowned voted sailors, and
forged a philosophers of the ship, but for most envisioned systems, were unable to hit upon who was
speaking to them. And he told them in brief the dwarf of Saturn, which was less Micromegas is
stronger voice with which people were talking, and his journey to Saturn: I inform the gentleman
who was Micromegas, and having compassion they were so young, I wonder if they had always lived
in a state as bordering on nothing, and that was what they were doing
in a balloon which appeared to be peculiar to whales, if they were
happy, if they had soul, if multiplied, and a thousand other questions
of this sort.

Dudasen angry that if I had a soul, a reasoning of the band, more daring than others, the participant
observed a finlets adapted to a quarter of a circle, measured with two triangles, and the third
told him so:? With what you believe, sir knight, that because you have two thousand yards from
head to toe, you are some ...? gone a thousand yards! exclaimed the dwarf, it is not wrong
or an inch. iCon I measured the atom! icon that is geometry, and he knows my size and I that
I can not see without the aid of a microscope, not even yours! Yes, that I have measured he
said the physical, and also measure your giant companion. Admitiose the proposal, and Acosto His
Excellency on the ground, because they stood their head was higher than the clouds, and our
philosophers they planted a tree in a very large site or Torres Quevedo been appointed by
name, but I do not dare to lie on the great respect that I have the
ladies, and then by a series of triangles, connected to each other,
guessing that the person was a mancebito mediate hundred and twenty
thousand feet of a king.

Micromegas then burst out in these reasons: I see that you never have to judge things its apparent
magnitude. O God, who gave intelligence to some substances such despicable seem infinitely small
costs no more to your omnipotence that the infinitely large; and if it is possible that other
creatures smaller than them, perhaps will have a higher intelligence
that of those huge animals I've seen in the sky, and with one foot
would cover the entire globe where I am now.

Answered one of the philosophers who could not believe it, but you have any doubt, he had loved much
more intelligent boys than men, and told him not fables that we have forsaken Virgilio on bees,
but what Swammerdam discovered, and what has dissected Reaumur. Instructed him then there are
animals that are about bees, which are the bees with respect man, and what was the Syrian
same with respect to those so stout of animals speaking, and what are these big animals compared
with other substances to the quale seem imperceptible atoms.

Gradually the conversation was becoming interesting, Micromegas and
said so.

CHAPTER VII.

Conversations with men.

O atoms intelligent, in whom it pleased the eternal Being in showing their art and power no doubt
that your globe PLEASURE purest happy, as having so little substance and looking all spirit,
you ought to use your life in love and think that is true life of the spirits. In part I have
seen no real happiness, but I am sure this is his mansion. Encogieronse shoulders to hear
this argument all the philosophers; and more naive one sincerely confessed, except a very few of
residents very little appreciated, everything else is a cafile crazy, perverse and unfortunate.
More material we have, he said, which is necessary to do evil, if evil comes from matter, and
more intelligence, if it comes from intelligence. ? Par example You know that when this one
hundred thousand fools of our species, who wear hats, are killing a hundred thousand other animals
covered with a turban, or dying at their hands, and so is style throughout the land, immemorial
time here? The Syrian terribly shocked, and asked the reason for such horrible strife between
so vile little creatures. It is, he said the philosopher, a few scraps of land sizes as your foot,
not because neither one of the millions who die request even a lump
of that piece, it is to know whether to belong to a certain man Sultan
called or another surname Cesar, do not know why.

Neither has been and never see the little corner of land that is in dispute, nor least almost
none of the animals that has been reciprocally are killed either by the person who kills the animal.

iDesventurados!
Sirius exclaimed indignantly:? as you can imagine so mad frenzy? Starters come to give me
three steps, with three kicks estruxar ridiculous this whole swarm of murderers. You do not
take that job, he responded, which left them till toil ruin. Know that within ten years in life
fails, the tenth of these wretches, and that even without drawing the sword, almost everyone
carries the hunger, fatigue, or the distemper, apart from that it is they who deserve punishment,
but the idle ruthless, which stuck sent in his cabinet, as they digest the food, slaughter a million
men, and are then solemn thanksgiving to God. I felt the walker moved to pity the wretched
lineage human in so many contradictions found qual. As you, he said to these gentlemen, the short
number of scholars who certainly kill anyone for money, I pray you tell me quale are your occupations.
Dissected flies, "replied the philosopher, measured lines, combined numbers, we agree on two
or three points that mean, and divided on two or three thousand who do not understand. It occurred
to Sirius and ask questions Saturnino atoms thinkers, to know about that they were consistent. ? Far
is, he said this, since the star Canicula to the big Geminis? They answered together: Thirty-two
degrees and one-half .--? Quanto far from here the moon? - Sixty semi-diameter of the earth
.--? Quanto weighs your ayre? Taken if any thought, but all they told him that weighed nine hundred
times less the same volume of water lighter, and nineteen thousand times less than gold. Astonished
the little elves urgently Saturn with their answers, I was tempted to believe that those were
magic ones to whom a quarter of an hour before the intelligence had
been denied.

Micromegas finally said to them: Once you know how time what is outside of you no doubt that you
will know better yet what is inside: say they know what is your soul and how are your ideas.
Philosophers spoke all at the same time, as before, but all were of a different opinion. I quote the
most ancient to Aristotle, one pronounce the name of Descartes, that the Malebranche, that
that of Leibnitz, Locke and the other. The old peripatetic he said with confidence: The soul
is a entelechia, a reason under the qual is power being what it is, so what Aristotle says expressly,
pag. 633 of the edition of Louvre: Entelexeia esti, etc. I do not understand the Greek, 'said the
giant. Nor I, "replied the plowman philosophical. ?

Well, that citais, "replied the Syrian, in that Aristotle in Greek? Because what you do not understand,
"said the sage, it must include language that does not know.

I take the Cartesian thread, and said: The soul a pure spirit in the womb has received all the
metaphysical ideas, and so leave the has been refined to go to school and relearn what we knew
so well and never gonna know. For these prospered, the animal responded eight leagues, who could
both remember when I was in your soul the womb of your mother, if
had to be so ignorant Quando were your man with a beard. ? Y you mean
by spirit? ? That's what I ask? he said the discurridor, I have no
idea none of it: they say that it is not subject .--? And you know
what is matter</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>