<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07115</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>2905</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16271</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Habían estado tan
dignas, tan severas, tan naturales, tan sin espantos o alharacas de hembra vulgar que es honrada
o presume de serlo, como si hubieran sido dos duquesas o princesas que hubieran tenido el capricho
de salir de noche a recorrer las calles y se hubiesen visto perseguidas, durante algunos minutos,
por un lacayo mal criado y bastante vano para creerse seductor.

El Conde, a pesar de todo, quizá porque así fuese, quizá porque el amor propio le engañaba,
había creído notar, en gestos imperceptibles, en el ademán, en algo que apenas se había podido
ver y que apenas se podía apreciar ni evaluar sino por un entendimiento tan sutil como el suyo
y tan perito en las aventuras amorosas, que la casada se le había mostrado menos indiferente
y más propicia; que se adivinaba en su cara el contentamiento, la vanidad satisfecha de verse
seguida por un joven tan principal y tan gallardo, y hasta que le miró una o dos veces de soslayo
y con disimulo, con curiosa simpatía.

¿Escribiría, pues, a la casada? Pero ¿qué derecho tenía para ello? ¿Qué le iba a decir? ¿Y
si el marido era celoso y cogía la carta? ¿No se exponía desde el principio a imposibilitar
o dificultar así grandemente para lo futuro el buen éxito de su aventura?

El Conde desistió, por consiguiente, de escribir a la casada.

La soltera le parecía más bonita y más distinguida; pero estaba enojadísimo contra ella. Allí
sí que no se forjaba ilusiones: allí sí que no le cabía la menor duda. Inesita no había hecho
más caso de él que de un perro callejero. No acertando a explicarse aquella serenidad olímpica,
aquel suave endiosamiento, que por extraña contraposición se conciliaba con la humildad y la
modestia, el Conde se daba a sospechar si Inesita sería idiota; pero recordaba sus ojos, su
airoso modo de andar y la expresión inteligente de su hermosa cara, y tenía que confesarse
que, o él no sabía lo que eran mujeres, o Inesita era de lo más discreto que había nacido de madre.

¿Cómo, pues, escribir a Inesita? Esto era más difícil que escribir a doña Beatriz.

No incurramos aquí en la necia hipocresía de suponer, cuando se escribe una historia, que la
sociedad tiene una moral muy superior a la que realmente tiene. Digamos las cosas como son.

Es singular, es poco lógico, es absurdo, pero ocurre lo siguiente. Está tan en los usos y costumbres
que cualquier caballero diga su atrevido pensamiento a una mujer casada, que ésta se ofenderá
rara vez. Por virtuosa que sea, se limitará a rechazar o a desengañar con dulzura al pretendiente.
No se dará por ofendida, cuando en realidad le han propuesto la infracción de una ley moral,
civil y religiosa, su deshonra y la de su casa, y tal vez la vileza de un hurto de bienes materiales,
si llega a tener un hijo. En cambio, apenas habrá soltera, como no esté completamente perdida,
que no se considere injuriada si le piden amor sin presuponer matrimonio de un modo explícito
o implícito; y, en realidad, la falta a que entonces se induciría a la soltera sería mucho
menor que la que se pretendía de la casada. La soltera, libre, no engañaría a su marido, no
faltaría a ninguna promesa, no se expondría a dar a nadie por heredero legítimo a aquel que
no debiese serlo.

Esto es exacto. No hay argumento que pueda valer en contra. Y con todo, apenas habrá seductor,
por brutal, irreverente y desaforado que sea, que ose pretender a una soltera, sin proponer
la buena fin: y apenas hay Tenorio, por enclenque, canijo y fehuelo que Dios o el diablo le
hayan hecho, que no tiente el vado, se declare con desenfadada audacia y se atreva a pretenderlo
todo de una mujer casada.

Nuestro héroe, sin meterse en filosofar sobre lo dicho, lo tenía más que sabido. Así es que,
por esta consideración, aunque no atendiese a otras, hallaba más difícil escribir a Inesita
que a doña Beatriz. Escribir a doña Beatriz, como casada, el uso, la práctica, la jurisprudencia
establecida, lo consentía sin que pasase por injuria. Escribir a Inesita, en cambio, no podía
ser sin menospreciarla y vejarla cruelmente, como el Conde no dijera o diese lugar a que se
sobreentendiera que aspiraba a casarse con ella.

Ahora bien; el Conde ni estaba enamorado, ni pensaba en casarse con nadie, ni mucho menos con
Inesita: sólo aspiraba a pasar el rato; pero el Conde tenía también su moral, y no había rato,
por bueno que fuese, que mereciera que él se rebajase hasta mentir y engañar a una pobre chica,
haciéndola creer que podría casarse con ella.

Así, pues, el Conde desistió de escribir a doña Beatriz por razones de prudencia y estrategia
amatoria, y desistió de escribir a Inesita por más delicadas consideraciones. Mas no por eso
desistió de conocerlas y tratarlas a las dos. Dejémosle cavilando y discurriendo el medio más
atinado de lograrlo, y adelantémonos nosotros, penetrando invisibles en casa de nuestras heroínas
y conociéndolas antes que el Conde.

IV

El crítico más hábil y atinado, quizá, entre cuantos hay en España me ha hecho ya dos o tres
veces, al juzgar otras novelas mías, un favor y un disfavor que no creo merecer; pero si los
merezco, esta vez, lejos de enmendarme, incurro más de lleno que nunca en su censura, que por
otra parte me lisonjea. Supone el crítico que mis personajes todos son yo, con lo cual hace
de mí un Proteo, pues harto diversos caracteres he retratado; y supone además que todos hablan,
como yo en igual situación hablaría, con erudición, discretas sutilezas y espíritu filosófico
impropios de su condición humilde y hasta de su sexo, ya que a menudo mis mujeres se pasan
de listas.

En la presente historia, donde, según el título lo indica, los más importantes personajes,
cada uno por su estilo, van a pasarse de listos, pecaré, sin poderlo remediar, contra lo que
el crítico quiere. La culpa, si la hay, porque me resisto a declararme culpado, está en la
elección del asunto. Ya elegido, no tengo más recurso que hacer a mis héroes, conservando a
cada uno su índole, sus pasiones y su singular fisonomía, todo lo más discretos, sutiles y
listos que yo sepa y pueda, porque tal ha de ser el defecto mayor de todos ellos, y sobre todos
ellos, del protagonista de la historia.

Hago aquí esta declaración para que doña Beatriz, a quien pronto oirán hablar mis lectores,
no los coja desprevenidos. Doña Beatriz era listísima.

No recuerdo en qué libro, tratado o epístola del Antiguo o del Nuevo Testamento, se dice que
el espíritu sopla donde quiere: sentencia con la cual basta y sobra para justificar la verosimilitud
de que el espíritu, ora sea divino, ora sea diabólico, hubiese soplado y penetrado en el ser
de una muchacha de veintidós años, que no tenía más doña Beatriz, nacida y criada en un lugar
de la provincia de Córdoba. Hay también otra sentencia macarrónica, llena de verdad, que reza
de este modo: Quod natura non dat, Salamanca non proestad, de la cual puede inferirse, según
buena lógica, que la madre naturaleza no ha menester de Salamanca, o dígase de hondos estudios
y largo trato de mundo, para hacer muy sutiles y entendidos a aquellos a quienes gusta de favorecer,
aun cuando sean mujeres, y mujeres de lugar.

En este número se contaba doña Beatriz, la cual, sobre su innato despejo, si bien no había
cursado en ninguna universidad, tenía cierto saber adquirido en la conversación frecuente de
su marido don Braulio, quien gozaba fama de sujeto muy ilustrado, aunque sólo tuviese 3.000
pesetas anuales de sueldo.

Doña Beatriz e Inesita, huérfanas de padre y madre desde la niñez, habían estado bajo la tutela
y criadas en casa del cura del pueblo. No eran enteramente pobres. Tenían algunas finquillas,
que venían a producir, bien administradas, unos 4.000 reales de renta para cada una. Con esto
era difícil que en el pueblo, a no infundir una violenta pasión, se casase ninguna de ellas
con los hidalgos o señores ricos; y como ambas eran muchachas finas, señoritas verdaderas,
no era probable que se hubieran querido casar con ningún arriero palurdo o con ningún labrador
rústico e ignorante.

El padre cura receló, aunque tarde, que había educado a sus pupilas mal de puro bien, y que,
de resultas de su esmerada educación, iban a quedarse para vestir imágenes. Por fortuna no
sucedió así. El Administrador de Rentas, don Braulio, trató a doña Beatriz, y la halló tan
bonita y discreta que se enamoró de ella. Ella pensó haber hallado en don Braulio un hombre
que, aunque viejo, podía enamorar por su talento y por otras nobles prendas del alma, y enamorados,
o persuadidos de que lo estaban, se casaron, después de un noviazgo corto.

El cura tutor, que era muy anciano, murió pocos meses después de este casamiento.

Nada absolutamente dejó a sus pupilas.

De una hermana suya, viuda, tenía el cura un sobrino, de edad de veintiocho años, llamado Paco
Ramírez. Este fué el universal heredero de su tío, consistiendo el activo de la herencia en
la casa con los muebles y libros, que valdría todo 40.000 reales, y el pasivo en varias deudas,
que pasaban, también en reales, de 30.000.

Paco Ramírez era un mozo muy guapo, y tan morigerado, económico, activo y fecundo en recursos,
que con 50.000 reales que su padre le había dejado en dinero, empleando en cebada y en trigo,
comprando mosto barato en tiempo de vendimia, haciéndole vino potable en unas cuantas pipas
que tenía, vendiéndole luego por cargas a los arrieros, y, en suma, trapicheando de otras mil
maneras, si bien todas lícitas, no sólo mantenía con holgura a su madre, sino que se vestía
él hasta con majeza y elegancia, al uso del pueblo, e iba, poco a poco, aumentando el capital.

Muchas veces había pensado el cura en que su sobrino podría ser un buen marido para cualquiera
de sus dos pupilas; pero, como no era un buen partido, calló el cura su pensamiento y propósito,
y jamás hizo nada por realizarle.

Paco, Beatriz e Inesita se querían como hermanos. Paco, que tenía seis años más que la mayor
de ellas, y diez más que la segunda, lo cual en la primera edad parece enorme diferencia, les
tenía un cariño que él calificaba de paternal. Ellas eran hijas del caballero más ilustre del
pueblo, por más que hubiesen venido a tanta pobreza, y él, plebeyo, y archiplebeyo por todos
cuatro costados, y con menos bienes de fortuna que las pupilas de su tío, ¿cómo había de atreverse
ni siquiera a imaginar que podría casarse con ninguna de las dos?

Así las cosas, se casó don Braulio con doña Beatriz, y a poco, como ya hemos dicho, murió el
cura, que era excelente sujeto.

Inesita, según era natural, se fue a vivir con su hermana y cuñado; los siguió a Sevilla, y
después los siguió a esta alegre capital de las Españas.

Desde que salieron del lugar dejaron encomendada a Paco la administración de los bienes que
en él tenían, con la seguridad de que nadie había de administrarlos mejor. Paco, en efecto,
respondió a aquella confianza. Así es que en la época en que comienza nuestra historia, cuando
aparecen en el Buen Retiro nuestras dos heroínas, tenían entre ambas algo más de 8.000 reales
al año, que juntos a los 12.000 mal contados de don Braulio, sumaban una taleguita anual muy
corrida y larga de talle.

Aunque hacían vida retirada, como todo está caro, y se trataban bien, y se vestían con cierto
lujo para su clase, renta y sueldo se consumían completamente, y gracias si no se hallaban
a veces en apuros.

Para salir de ellos, vivir con esplendidez y elevarse a mayor posición en la jerarquía social,
se presentaban dos caminos, iluminados por la esperanza, a la aguda consideración de doña Beatriz,
la cual cavilaba mucho sobre estas cosas desde que había salido del lugar, ya casada.

Doña Beatriz tenía el concepto más elevado de la inteligencia y del saber de su marido. Atribuía
su poco éxito en el mundo a descuido, desprecio o desdén que don Braulio tenía de todo lo práctico,
a cierta falta de estímulo que notaba en su alma, y se inclinaba a creer que si ella estimulaba
y aguijoneaba el alma de su marido, apartándola de vagos ensueños y de teóricas distracciones,
que a nada conducían, aun era posible que le viese de Ministro de Hacienda, o por lo menos
de Director de Rentas Estancadas.

El otro punto, que era como cimiento o piedra angular sobre la cual levantaba doña Beatriz
el alcázar de sus esperanzas ambiciosas, era la hermosura, el garbo y la distinción de su hermana
Inesita.

Doña Beatriz, casada ya con un hombre a quien veneraba y quería, y a quien era deudora de haber
salido del lugar, donde se ahogaba, y de espaciarse por grandes ciudades, limitaba su misión
para lograr el engrandecimiento a servir como de espuela a la reacia voluntad de su marido;
pero en Inesita, soltera y libre y llena de atractivos, que ella sabría completar y hacer valer
con su prudencia, veía doña Beatriz un filón intacto aún, un minero riquísimo de todos los
bienes, encumbramientos y prosperidades.

Importa declarar, en honor de doña Beatriz, que al trazar en su imaginación el proceso ascendente
de uno y otro plan de ventura, ora valiéndose de don Braulio, ora de Inesita, jamás se le ocurría
poner en la composición de su cuadro el menor toque pecaminoso. Nada de fullerías. Doña Beatriz
quería jugar limpio. Don Braulio había de ser personaje de primera magnitud sin mancharse las
uñas, e Inesita había de ser condesa, marquesa, y quién sabe si duquesa, sin la menor liviandad
y con todos los requisitos eclesiásticos y civiles.

El orgullo de doña Beatriz, su decoro aristocrático, que le tenía, aunque nacida en pobres
pañales, y sus creencias cristianas, vivas y fervorosas como de persona educada por un sacerdote
de ejemplarísima virtud, repugnaban todo recurso que pudiera mancillar; pero su afán de elevarse
y de elevar a su familia le sugería, a su ver, medios decentes y honrados por donde lograr
riqueza, dignidades y distinciones, con facilidad y sin desdoro ni culpa.

Doña Beatriz no descubría por completo sus planes y sus esperanzas a don Braulio y a Inesita.
Temía asustarlos y que del susto saliesen la contradicción y la oposición. Cauta y astuta,
soñaba con atraer diestramente al uno y a la otra por los caminos que ella juzgaba conducentes
al término a que aspiraba, y ya comprometidos y metidos en él, y cuando fuese muy difícil volver
atrás, declarar ella su propósito y mostrarles el término, si no le veían.

Con Inesita, sobre todo, que era sobrado poética e inexperta, procedía doña Beatriz con superior
cautela y disimulo.

Desde la noche que habían ido al Buen Retiro le había hablado varias veces del gentil caballero
que las había seguido, pero sin descubrir jamás todo su pensamiento.

Doña Beatriz, por las frases que había oído al Conde de Alhedín y a sus compañeros, por el
coche que había visto y por algunas noticias que después había recogido con habilidad, sabía
que el Conde era soltero, muy rico, muy noble, huérfano de padre, y con una madre que no tenía
más voluntad que la suya. Ahora bien; ¿qué imposibilidad habría en que el Conde se enamorase
resueltamente de Inesita y se casase con ella? Más desiguales casamientos se han visto y se
ven todos los días.

Con un poco de fortuna y con la rara discreción de que doña Beatriz se juzgaba dotada, bien
podría casar a Inesita con el Conde. Inesita era, como ya se ha dicho, una criatura adorable.
Hasta su indiferencia, hasta su espíritu, dormido a toda ambición, podría contribuir al triunfo.
Nada suele perjudicar tanto a otras muchachas, en esto de atrapar un buen casamiento, como
el afán cándido y mal encubierto de atraparle.

Así, pues, doña Beatriz dejaba dormir a su hermana y no procuraba despertar su ambición. Aquel
sueño indiferente y sublime era un arma poderosa de que no convenía desprenderse. Ella, sin
decírselo hasta que llegase la ocasión oportuna, guiaría a su hermana sin sacarla del poético
sonambulismo.

Sonámbula y todo, importaba, no obstante, que Inesita por sí misma se moviese; y para ello
doña Beatriz había ya tocado, y aun pensaba tocar, cualquiera otro resorte de su alma menos
el de la ambición y la codicia.

Con estos planes e intenciones, la noche del día en que el Conde supo en el Ministerio de Hacienda
quiénes eran sus desconocidas, hablaban éstas a solas en su pobre casa, mientras aguardaban
a don Braulio, que estaba trabajando en la Secretaría.

--No te entiendo, Inesita--decía doña Beatriz, sentada en una butaca enfrente de su hermana--.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08120</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>148442</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14824</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Been so worthy, so
severe, so natural, so without fear or fuss vulgar female who is honored or presumed to be, as if
they were two duchesses and princesses who have had the whim going out at night to roam the streets
and had been persecuted for a few minutes, by a footman spoiled and vain enough to believe seductive.

The
Count, nevertheless, perhaps because it was so, perhaps because the
self-deceived him, noting he had believed in subtle gestures, the
gesture, something that has barely been see and you could barely see
or evaluate, but by a delicate understanding like yours and so adept
in affairs, that the married woman he had been less indifferent and
more favorable, which could be glimpsed in his face contentment, being
satisfied vanity followed by a young man as principal and so handsome,
and until I looked once or twice sideways and concealment, with a
curious sympathy.

Would you write, then, to the married? But what right had I to do? What could I say? What if the
husband was jealous and took the letter? Do not be exposed from the outset to preclude or hinder
the future and greatly to the success of his adventure?

The count withdrew, therefore, writing to the married.

It seemed the single most beautiful and distinguished, but he was
in high dudgeon against it.

There forged it does not delude itself that there was no doubt about
it.

Ines had no more for him than a junkyard dog. Not conceive explained that serenity Olympic that
gentle godliness, which is reconciled by a strange contrast with the humility and modesty, the
Count was suspecting if Ines would be idiotic, but remember your eyes, graceful gait and intelligent
expression of her beautiful face, and had to confess that either he did not know what they were
women, Ines was most discreet mother was born.

How, then, write to Inesita? This was more difficult than writing to Dona Beatriz.

Incur no hypocrisy here in the foolish imagine, when writing a story that moral society has a
much higher than it actually is. Say things like it is.

Is singular, it is not logical, it is absurd, but the following happens. So it is in the customs
that any gentleman say his bold thinking a married woman, that it offended rarely. For virtuous it
is, is merely rejected or gently disabuse the claimant. Will not be offended, when in fact you
had proposed the infringement of a moral law civil and religious, his disgrace and his home, and perhaps
the vileness of a theft of material goods if you do have a child. Instead, just be single, as
it is not completely lost not considered injured if you are asked to presuppose love without
marriage in an explicit way or implied, and indeed, the lack of which then induce the single
would be much less than that sought in the marriage. The single, free, not deceive her husband,
not fail in any undertaking, not to expose anyone for legitimate heir who ought not to be.

This
is accurate.

There is no argument against it is worth. And yet, just be seductive however brutal, irreverent
and outrageous that is, who dares claim a maiden, without proposing good order, and hardly
any Tenorio, for frail, sickly and fehuelo God or the devil already done so do not tempt the
ford, declares with unabashed boldness and daring to intending all of a married woman.

Our hero, without getting into philosophical about what has been said, I had only known. So,
by this consideration, although not attend to others, was more difficult to write to Inesita
that Dona Beatriz. Write to Dona Beatriz, as married, use, practice, jurisprudence established,
it consented without pass for libel. Write to Ines, however, could not vejarla be without despising
and cruelly, as the Count did not tell or give rise to understanding that aspired to marry
her.

Now, the Count and was in love, or thought of marrying anyone, let alone with Ines: only aspired
to hang, but the Count was also their moral, and there was no time, good it was, that he deserved
to stoop to lie and deceive a poor girl, into believing that he could
marry her.

So write withdrew Count Dona Beatriz for reasons of prudence and strategy amatory, and withdrew
Inesita write more delicate considerations. But why not withdrew to know them and treat them both.
Let him brooding and run the most wise to this, and we fast forward,
penetrating invisible in our heroes home and knowing them before the
Count.

IV

The most able and judicious critic, perhaps, among those who are in Spain I have already done
two or three Sometimes, when judging other novels of mine, a favor and disfavor do not think I
deserve, but if I deserve this time away from mend, incur more fully than ever in its censorship,
which Moreover flatters me. The critic assumes that all my characters are me, which makes
a Proteus me because I had enough different characters portrayed,
and further assumed that everyone talks about, in the same situation
as I speak, with erudition, discreet subtleties and philosophical
spirit someone of his lowly status and even sex, since women often
spend my lists.

In this story, where, as the title indicates, the most important characters each to his own
style, they will play smart, sin, could not help, contrary to the critic wants. The blame,
if any, because I refuse to plead guilty, is in the choice of subject. Already chosen, I have
no recourse but to make my heroes, retaining each of its nature, its passions and its unique features,
all as discreet, subtle and ready know and I can because this has
to be the major defect of these, and all them, the protagonist of
the story.

I make this statement here for Dona Beatriz, who will soon hear about my readers not catch them
off guard. Doña Beatriz was listísima.

I do not remember which book, treatise or letter of the Old or New Testament, is said to the spirit
blows where it pleases with that statement is more than enough to justify the plausibility that
the spirit, whether it be divine, whether it be evil, it would blow being penetrated a girl
of twenty years, he had no Dona Beatriz, born and raised in a the province of Cordoba. There is
also another macaronic sentence full of truth, which reads thus: Quod natura non dat, non proestad Salamanca,
which can be inferred, as Logically, that Mother Nature has no need
of Salamanca, or say to yourself in deep studies and throughout the
world try to make very subtle and understanding to those who like
to promote, even if they are women, and women's place.

This issue had Dona Beatriz, who, on his innate clearance, although there was no studied in
any college, had some knowledge acquired in the common conversation
her husband Don Braulio, who enjoyed a reputation for subject is illustrated,
although only 3,000 had ESP annual salary.

Doña Beatriz and Ines, orphan of father and mother since childhood, had been in care and raised
in the village priest's house. Were not entirely poor. They had some finquillas, who came to
produce, well-managed, real income about 4,000 each. This was difficult for the people, not
to instill a violent passion, to marry any of them with rich gentlemen or lords, and as both girls
were fine, real girls, was not likely to have wanted to marry with
any carrier or no hick farmer rustic and ignorant.

Priest Father suspicion, but later, he had educated his eyes of pure evil good, and that result
of their good education, went to left on the shelf images. Fortunately no happen. Revenue Manager,
Don Braulio, tried to Dona Beatriz, and found that nice and unobtrusive that he loved her. She thought
he had found a man at Don Braulio who, though old, could fall in
love with his talent and other noble garments of the soul, and love,
or convinced that they were, were married after a short courtship.

The priest tutor who was very old, died a few months after this marriage.

Absolutely nothing left to his pupils.

Of a sister, a widow, was the priest's nephew, twenty-eight years old, called Paco Ramírez. This
was the universal heir of his uncle, consisting of the assets of the inheritance the house with
furniture and books, worth around 40,000 real and liabilities in various debts, passing, also
real, 30,000.

Paco Ramírez was a very handsome boy, and so restrained, economical,
active and fruitful in resources, 50,000 reals with his father had
left him money, using barley and wheat buying cheap grape harvest
time, making wine drinking a few pipes I had, then by selling loads
to carriers, and, in short, a thousand other wheeling and dealing
However, while all legitimate, not only held loosely at his mother,
but who dressed majeza it up with elegance, the use of people, and
was gradually increasing the capital.

Often the priest had thought that his nephew might be a good husband
to any its two eyes, but as it was a good game, the priest stopped
his thought and purpose, and never did anything to be done.

Paco, and Ines Beatriz they loved as brothers. Paco, who was six years older than most of them,
and ten more than the second, which at first seems enormous age difference, they had a baby
that he described as paternal. They were daughters of the illustrious gentleman people, even though
they had come to such poverty, and he, a plebeian, and archiplebeyo
all four sides, and under the blessings of fortune that his uncle's
eyes, how had he dared not even imagine that he could marry either?

So, Don Braulio married Dona Beatriz, and soon, as we have said, died priest, who was excellent
subject.

Ines, as was natural, he went to live with his sister and brother, followed in Seville, and
then followed this lively capital of Spain.

Since leaving the place left Paco entrusted to the administration of assets it had, with the
assurance that no one had to manage them better.

Paco, in effect, responded to that trust. So in the time our story begins, when appear in the
Buen Retiro our two heroines, had between them just over 8,000 real year, which together with
the 12,000 counted evil Don Braulio, totaling an annual taleguita
very run and long-waisted.

Even if life were removed, as everything is expensive, and well treated,
and dressed with a certain class for class, income and salary are
completely consumed, and thanks if you were not sometimes in distress.

To get out of them, living lavishly and rise to higher position in the social hierarchy are two
paths, lit by hope, to the acute consideration of Dona Beatriz, which brooded a lot about these
things since he left the place, already married.

Doña Beatriz was the highest form of intelligence and knowledge of her husband. Attributed
their lack of success in the world to neglect, contempt or disdain that Don Braulio was all practical,
a certain lack of stimulus that could see into his soul, and was
inclined to believe that if she encouraged and spurred the soul of
her husband and away from theoretical vague dreams and distractions
that led to nothing, it was still possible to see him as Minister
of Finance, or at least Director of Monopolies.

The other point, it was as the foundation or cornerstone on which stood Beatriz the castle of
his ambitious hopes, was the beauty, the elegance and distinction of his sister Ines.

Doña Beatriz, married and with a man who worshiped and wanted, and
who was indebted to have left the place where he drowned, and spaced
by large cities, limiting its mission to achieve the greatness to
serve as a spur to the reluctant will of her husband; but Inesita,
single and free and full of attractive, she would know and enforce
complete with his wisdom, saw a reef Beatriz still intact, a rich
mining of all property, and prosperity encumbrances.

Import declaration in honor of Dona Beatriz, who draw on their imaginations to the ascending process
of each other plan of happiness, now using Don Braulio, Inesita prays never occurred to him put
in the composition of the least touch his picture sinful. Nothing thief comes. Doña Beatriz I wanted
to play fair.

Don Braulio had to be first-rate character without stain nails, and Ines was to be a countess,
marquise, and who knows if Duchess, without the least levity and all ecclesiastical and civil requirements.

Beatriz's
pride, his aristocratic decorum, which was, though born poor diapers, and their Christian beliefs,
alive and fervent as educated by a priest ejemplarísima of virtue, repelled any remedy that
might tarnish, but his desire to rise and raise your family will
suggest, in his view, decent and honest means by which to achieve
wealth, honors and awards, with ease and without dishonor or guilt.

Doña Beatriz fully discovered their plans and hopes and Inesita Don Braulio. He feared to frighten
and scare saliesen contradiction and opposition. Cautious and cunning, deftly bring the dream of
one and the other in the ways that she deemed conducive at the end
to which he aspired, and already committed and placed in him, and
when was very difficult to return ago, it declared its purpose and
show the term, if not see him.

With Ines, above all, that was about poetry and inexperienced, Beatriz came to top caution and dissimulation.

From
the night they had gone to the Buen Retiro had spoken several times
of the gentle knight that had followed, but never discover all his
thinking.

Doña Beatriz, by the phrases he had heard the Earl of Alhedín and his companions, by the car he
had seen and some news that after he had collected with skill, know the Count was single, very
rich, very noble, no father, and a mother who had no will but yours. Now, what is impossible
that the Count would fall in love Inesita resolutely and marry her?

More mixed marriages have been and see every day.

With a little luck and with rare discretion of Dona Beatriz was deemed gifted, well Inesita could
marry the Count. Ines was, as mentioned above, an adorable creature. Until his indifference
to its spirit, slept all ambition, could contribute to winning.

Nothing will damage both the other girls in this to catch a good marriage, as the naive and ill-disguised
effort to catch him.

Thus, Beatriz from sleeping with his sister and did not seek to awaken
their ambition.

That indifferent and sublime dream was a powerful weapon which should not be detached. She,
tell until a suitable opportunity came, would lead to her sister without removing the poetic
sleepwalking.

Sleepwalking and everything mattered, however, that Ines should move itself, and for this Dona
Beatriz had already played, and even thought to touch, any other
spring of your soul less the ambition and greed.

With these plans and intentions, the evening of the Earl heard at
the Ministry of Finance who their unknown, they talked alone in his
poor house, while waiting Don Braulio, who was working in the Secretariat.

-
I do not understand, Ines - Beatriz said, sitting in an armchair in
front of his sister -</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>