<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document08913</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>398179</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19732</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Todos los años se repetía, y no había nadie entre los invitados que no
la esperase. Pero había que repetir la frase sacramental, las excusas de rúbrica, y mientras
todos aseguraban que no tenían sed y preguntaban con enfado a los dueños de la casa por qué
se molestaban, la lengua, seca por el calor, parecía pegarse al paladar, y los ojos se iban
tras las tazas de filete dorado que contenían el humeante chocolate, las anchas copas azules,
sobre las cuales erguían los sorbetes sus torcidas monteras rojas o amarillas, y las maqueadas
bandejas cubiertas de dulces. Había que resignarse y no hacer un desaire a los señores de la
casa. Y a los pocos minutos ya estaban amigablemente en torno de la mesa, con el mantel cubierto
de migajas de bizcocho, las jícaras de chocolate vacías y clavando barquillos en las entrañas
de los sorbetes.

Doña Manuela hablaba con el señor Cuadros, Teresa la había colocado junto a su marido, con
la esperanza de lograr su catequización. Aquella señora, que tanto sabía y tan grande experiencia
había adquirido en las miserias matrimoniales, era su única esperanza.

La viuda hablaba con su antiguo dependiente, sonriendo. ¡Cómo había cambiado aquel hombre!
Doña Manuela, experta conocedora, notaba en él cierto atrevimiento, como el muchacho que se
emancipa de la autoridad maternal y se lanza en plena vida de locuras.

La viuda, siempre sonriente, se asombraba de sus frases de doble sentido, de los guiños picarescos
con que acompañaba sus palabras, y hasta le parecía ¡oh poder de la ilusión! que había en su
persona un perfume extraño que comenzaba a crispar los nervios de doña Manuela, algo del ambiente
de aquella mala piel de la calle del Puerto, que el protector se había traído sin duda a su
hogar honrado.

Mientras tanto, Teresa, sin dejar de atender a los convidados y de abrumarles con obsequios,
no quitaba los ojos de su marido y de la bondadosa amiga. Doña Manuela experimentaba una profunda
conmiseración cada vez que se fijaba en la pobre esposa. ¡Bueno estaba su marido para intentar
conversiones! El señor Cuadros era un hombre perdido para siempre, un hambriento que había
gustado el fruto prohibido, tras muchos años de vida obscura y laboriosa, sin saber lo que
era juventud y trabajando como una bestia de carga. Antes moriría que hallarse saciado. Nada
podría adelantar su esposa alejándolo de Clarita. Los calaveras cincuentones resultan terribles
por su candidez, y aunque los aíslen, son capaces de enamorarse de la criada de la casa.

Doña Manuela afirmábase aún más en esto al notar lo que ocurría en torno de ella. ¿De quién
era aquel pie que debajo de la mesa pisaba el suyo? ¿Qué rodilla era la que tan audazmente
acariciaba su falda de seda? Del señor Cuadros, de aquel honrado padre de familia que contestaba
a sus palabras con melosos gestos y parecía medirla de arriba abajo con sus ojos encandilados.

¡Pobre Teresa! Tal vez se imaginaba que las palabras de doña Manuela conmovían al descarriado,
haciéndole entrar en el camino del arrepentimiento; no adivinaba ni aun remotamente que su
marido, por una aberración extraña, en la que entraba por mucho el amor propio, comenzaba a
entusiasmarse con la belleza algo marchita de la esposa de su antiguo principal.

La viuda sentíase molestada por tales audacias; agitábase nerviosa en su asiento, pero callaba
y seguía sonriendo. Pensaba en que la situación imponía disimulo, y que la amistad del matrimonio
Cuadros le era muy necesaria para salvarla en sus apuros de señora en decadencia, acosada por
las deudas. Además, el porvenir de su hija, de su Amparito, estaba allí, y la viuda lanzaba
una mirada de ansiedad maternal al extremo de la mesa, donde estaba la niña junto a Andresito,
recibiendo con gestos de gatita mimosa los dulces y las palabras de su novio.

Tras media hora de sobremesa, se disolvió la reunión. Los hombres iban en busca de sus sombreros
y las señoras besuqueábanse al despedirse, murmurando todas el mismo saludo:

--Hasta el año que viene. Que Dios nos conserve a todos la salud, para ver la procesión.

Fueron desfilando todas las familias, y al fin quedaron solas las de Pajares, que esperaban
a Juanito o Rafael para que las acompañase a casa.

El señor Cuadros seguía acosando a doña Manuela Ésta se había levantado, huyendo de las audaces
intimidades por debajo de la mesa, pero el bolsista la seguía para continuar su conversación.
Ahora los dos estaban junto a Teresa, y el marido sólo se permitía frases amables y recuerdos
sobre la gran amistad que siempre había unido a las dos familias.

--Los chicos tardarán en venir--dijo don Antonio--. Rafael estará con sus amigos; y en cuanto
a Juanito, le atraen obligaciones ineludibles. Me han dicho que ahora tiene novia y está loco
por ella. ¡La juventud! ¡Oh, qué gran cosa! Ya conozco yo eso, ¿verdad, Teresa?

Y como si presintiese lo que pensaba su mujer y quisiera apaciguarla de antemano, lanzaba a
la obesa señora una mirada de ternura, como un hombre honrado y de costumbres intachables recordando
su tranquila luna de miel.

Doña Manuela estaba admirada. Decididamente, la tal Clarita había cambiado a aquel hombre.
Era un tuno. Y en vez de indignarse por la crueldad con que mentía e intentaba engañar a su
mujer, la viuda comenzaba a encontrarlo simpático, viendo en él como una resurrección de su
segundo marido, de aquel doctor calavera al que tanto había amado.

--Si ustedes quieren, las acompañaremos Andresito y yo.

Doña Manuela, animada por un instinto pudoroso, intentó excusarse.

--Sí; Antonio las acompañará--se apresuró a decir Teresa.

Ya la pobre mujer la rogaba con su mirada que aceptase, como si fuese para ella una esperanza
que su marido prolongase la conversación con la viuda. ¡Quién sabe cuántas cosas podía decir
doña Manuela al marido infiel!

No hubo medio de excusarse. Las de Pajares salieron acompañadas por Andresito y don Antonio,
siguiéndolas con su vista ansiosa la crédula Teresa. ¡Dios mío, que se ablandara el corazón
de aquel hombre, para que no la martirizase escandalizando a la familia y los amigos!

Abajo, en la cerrada tienda, encontraron a don Eugenio, siempre con la gorrita de seda, el
cual acogió con gesto huraño a su antiguo dependiente. Las de Pajares y sus dos acompañantes
siguieron por una acera del Mercado. Delante, las dos niñas con Andresito; Concha malhumorada
y ceñuda porque en todo el día no había visto al elegante Roberto, y Amparo muy satisfecha
de poder lucir un novio, para molestia de su hermana. Detrás, el señor Cuadros dando el brazo
a doña Manuela, apretándola intencionadamente el codo sobre su cadera cada vez que soltaba
una palabrita atrevida y contoneándose como un invencible conquistador.

Fue algo más que acompañar a las de Pajares lo que hicieron el padre y el hijo. Subieron con
ellas, permanecieron de visita más de una hora, cantó Amparito para obsequiar a su futuro suegro,
y cuando salieron a la calle, el padre y el hijo marchaban como compañeros unidos fraternalmente
por una común empresa.

Sólo habían transcurrido algunos meses, pero estaban ya lejanos para Cuadros aquellos tiempos
en que el tendero de costumbres tranquilas y rutinarias se indignaba al saber que su hijo iba
a los bailes y le esperaba tras la puerta empuñando fieramente la vara de medir.

IX

A las cuatro de la tarde entraban las de Pajares en el paseo de la Alameda.

Era domingo, y la animación ruidosa y expansiva de los días festivos inundaba la acera izquierda
del paseo. El tiempo era hermoso: una tarde de verano, con el cielo limpio de nubes, y en lo
más alto, como un jirón de vapor tenue y apenas visible, la luna, esperando pacientemente que
le llegase el turno para brillar. Las largas filas de rosales, los macizos de plantas, toda
esa jardinería mutilada y corregida por las tijeras del hortelano, reverdecía con el soplo
cálido de la tarde y se cubría de flores, uniendo sus simples perfumes a la estela de esencias
que dejaban las señoras tras su paso.

Por el arroyo central daban vueltas y más vueltas, como arcaduces de noria, los carruajes alineados
en interminable rosario. Las torres de los guardas erguían sus caperuzas de barnizadas tejas
por encima de los árboles, y a los dos extremos del paseo, empequeñecidas por la distancia,
destacábanse sobre el verde fondo las monumentales fuentes con sus figuras mitológicas ligeras
de ropa. Era la hora en que el paseo adquiría su aspecto más brillante. A todo galope de los
briosos caballos bajaban carretelas y berlinas, y por las aceras del paseo desfilaban lentamente,
con paso de procesión, las familias endomingadas. Los verdes bancos no tenían ni un asiento
libre. Un zumbido de avispero sonaba en el paseo, tan silencioso y desierto por las mañanas,
y algunas familias ingenuas conversaban a gritos, provocando la sonrisa compasiva de los que
pasaban con la mano en la flamante chistera, saludando con rígidos sombrerazos a cuantas cabezas
asomaban por las ventanillas de los carruajes.

Lo que atraía la atención de todos era el desfile incesante de coches, símbolos de felicidad
y bienestar en un país donde el afán de enriquecerse no tiene más deseo que no ir a pie como
los demás mortales.

Piafaban los caballos con la boca llena de espuma, esparciendo en torno el pajizo olor de las
cuadras, y de vez en cuando un relincho contagiaba a toda la línea de brutos briosos, que parecían
contestar con nerviosos pataleos a este llamamiento de libertad. Los cocheros, enfundados en
sus blancos levitones, exhibían desde lo alto de los pescantes, sus caras afeitadas y carrilludas
de cómicos obesos o párrocos bien conservados, y miraban con cierto desprecio a toda aquella
muchedumbre que les obligaba a pasar unas cuantas horas de tedio. En la larga fila de vehículos
estaba el antiguo faetón, balanceándose sobre sus muelles como una enorme caja fúnebre y encerrando
en su acolchado interior toda una familia, incluso la nodriza; la ligera berlina, con sus ruedas
rojas o amarillas; la carretela, como una góndola, meciéndose a la menor desigualdad del suelo,
y la galerita indígena, transformación elegante de la tartana y símbolo de la pequeña burguesía,
que, detenida en mitad de su metamorfosis social, tiene un pie en el pueblo, de donde procede,
y otro en la aristocracia, hacia donde va.

Parecía existir una barrera invisible e infranqueable entre la gente que paseaba a pie y aquellas
cabezas que asomaban a las ventanillas, contrayéndose con una sonrisa siempre igual cuando
recibían el saludo de las personas conocidas. Grupos de jinetes mezclados con jóvenes oficiales
de caballería caracoleaban por entre los carruajes, tendiéndose algunas veces sobre el cuello
de sus cabalgaduras para hablar al través de una portezuela. Las de Pajares contemplaban con
nostalgia de desterradas el paso de los carruajes. ¡Gran Dios, qué tarde! ¡Se acordarían de
ella toda la vida! Era la primera vez que iban a pie a la Alameda. Las niñas, a pesar de sus
elegantes trajes, creían que todos se fijaban en ellas para sonreír compasivamente, y doña
Manuela marchaba erguida, con altivez dolorosa, poco más o menos como Napoleón en Santa Elena
después de la denota. La viuda presentía su ruina. Ya no eran las deudas y los apuros pecuniarios
las amarguras de la vida; ahora, la fatalidad, según ella decía, complacíase en agobiarla con
nuevos golpes, quitando a la familia los escasos medios que la restaban para sostener su prestigio.

Aquella mañana había sido de prueba para las de Pajares. Nelet el cochero subió muy alarmado
a dar cuenta a sus señoras de que el caballo estaba enfermo. El suceso no era para tomarlo
a risa. No se trataba de un cólico vulgar, y la pobre bestia, sostenedora inconsciente del
prestigio de la familia, revolcábase abajo, en la obscura y húmeda cuadra, quedando panza arriba
y con las patas agitadas por un temblor convulsivo. La situación fue ridícula y conmovedora.
Tantos años de servicios habían establecido cierto afecto entre las señoras y la brava bestia,
que era considerada casi como de la familia. Doña Manuela, recogiéndose la cola de su bata
teatral, bajó a la cuadra, no pasando de la puerta por miedo al caballo, que se revolcaba furioso.

Llamaron al mejor veterinario de la ciudad; pero el caballo no mejoraba, y por la tarde desvaneciéronse
las ilusiones que tenían las niñas de pasear en carruaje. Casi adquirieron la certeza de que
el pobre caballo no saldría de la enfermedad. ¿Qué iban a hacer ellas cuando se vieran confundidas
entre las cursis que paseaban a pie por la Alameda? ¿Qué dirían las amigas al ver que transcurría
el tiempo y la hermosa galerita, de que tan orgullosas estaban, permanecía arrinconada en la
cochera? Porque las dos, aunque su mamá, por no entristecerlas, las ocultaba el estado de la
casa, tenían pleno conocimiento de los apuros de la familia y estaban seguras de la imposibilidad
de reemplazar el viejo pero brioso caballo por otro que valiese tanto como él.

Después de comer, la madre y las hijas sentáronse en el salón, y allí permanecieron más de
una hora, silenciosas, hurañas y malhumoradas. El día era magnífico; pero no, no saldrían:
primero monjas que el mundo se enterase de su decadencia, de sus privaciones tan hábilmente
ocultadas.

Pero las tres no podían resignarse a pasar un día dentro de casa. Además, por los balcones
entraba el sol y soplaba un aire cargado de perfume irritante del verano. Pensaban involuntariamente
en los verdes campos, en el paseo exuberante de gentío, en el placer de andar lentamente bajo
las ladeadas sombrillas, viendo caras nuevas y contestando al saludo de los amigos; y por fin,
la madre y las hijas no pudieron resistir más y comenzaron a vestirse.

--No hay que ser tan escrupulosas--dijo doña Manuela--. Todos nos conocen, y porque un día
nos vean salir a pie no van a imaginarse que nos falta el carruaje. Vamos, niñas, ¡a paseo!

Y salieron de casa con el propósito de ir a cualquier parte menos a la Alameda. Pero el paseo
las atraía; no sabían adonde ir, y al fin, insensiblemente, sin ponerse de acuerdo, encamináronse
allá.

¡Qué tardecita pasaron las de Pajares! Exteriormente fueron las de siempre; las niñas contestaron
con mohines graciosos a los saludos de los amigos, y la mamá, altiva y majestuosa, cobijándolo
todo con su mirada de protección. Pero en su interior ¡cuántos tormentos! Si alguna amiga las
saludaba desde su carruaje con expresión cariñosa, las tres creían adivinar cierto asomo de
lástima, y enrojecían bajo la capa de blanquete que cubría sus mejillas. Si una persona conocida
se detenía a saludarlas, ellas, a tuertas o a derechas, y muchas veces las tres a un tiempo,
se apresuraban a decir que habían salido a pie en vista de la hermosura de la tarde; y seguían
mirando con nostalgia y despecho la larga fila de carruajes, experimentando la misma impresión
de nuestros bíblicos padres ante las puertas del Paraíso cerradas para siempre.

Después, ¡qué recuerdos tan penosos! A las tres las obsesionaba la enfermedad del caballo,
como si éste fuese de la familia. Estaban arrepentidas de haber salido de casa; sentían la
falsa esperanza de los que se interesan por un enfermo y creen que permaneciendo a su lado
aceleran la curación. Saludaban a derecha y a izquierda; deteníanse a estrechar manos, cambiando
palabras sobre el tiempo o sobre los trajes que más lucían en el paseo; pero sus miradas iban
inconscientemente a detenerse en aquellos caballos que pasaban a pocos pasos de ellas; y en
todos, bien fuese por el color, por la cabeza o por la grupa, encontraban cierto parecido con
el otro que ocupaba su memoria.

Tuvieron en aquella tarde encuentros muy penosos. Andresito, el hijo de Cuadros, pasó por entre
las dos filas de carruajes montando el enorme caballote que le había comprado su padre. Buscaba
a la novia para ir escoltándola, luciendo sus habilidades hípicas en torno de su carruaje.
El gesto de inocente sorpresa que hizo al verlas a pie, confundidas entre la cursilería dominguera,
fue una verdadera puñalada para las tres mujeres.

Todo hería su susceptibilidad. Roberto del Campo, que iba con algunos amigos, las saludó con
la más seductora de sus sonrisas; pero ellas creyeron distinguir en sus labios una irónica
expresión. Indudablemente, aquel trasto de Rafaelito había relatado a Roberto lo del caballo.
Estaban seguras de que todo el paseo conocía el desagradable suceso, adivinando lo que vendría
después. Y cegadas por la vanidad herida, recordando sin duda las burlas que ellas habían dirigido
a otras familias, turbábanse por momentos, creyendo ver miles de ojos rijos en ellas y que
las señoras desde los carruajes las sonreían desdeñosamente, como si fuesen criadas disfrazadas.
Hasta llegaron a pensar con escalofríos de terror si a su s espaldas las señalarían irrisoriamente
con el dedo. Y siempre el maldito caballo ocupando su pensamiento, viéndolo con los ojos de
la imaginación tal como estaba en su cuadra al salir ellas de paseo, panza arriba, estirando
convulsivamente las patas. Las tres llevaban dentro de sí, como implacable enemigo, su propio
pensamiento, que las hacía ver la burla y la lástima en todas partes, y hasta creyeron algunas
veces que personas conocidas fingían distracción por no saludarlas.

--Vámonos, niñas--dijo la mamá con una expresión en que vibraban el dolor y la cólera--; vamos
a casa a ver cómo está «aquello». Hoy el paseo está muy cursi.

Las niñas apoyaron a la mamá con gesto de aprobación. Era verdad, muy cursi; y las tres emprendieron
una retirada desastrosa, anonadadas, vencidas, como si acabasen de sostener una batalla con
la consideración pública, quedando derrotadas y maltrechas. Al subir la rampa del puente del
Real tuvieron que apartarse del borde de la acera, limpiándose con los pañuelos de blonda el
polvo que levantaban las ruedas de un carruajillo descubierto que corría con velocidad insolente,
arrollándolo todo.

Era la última sorpresa. El señor Cuadros, tirando de las riendas para refrenar su veloz caballo
y agitando el látigo, las saludaba desde lo alto de aquella cáscara de nuez montada sobre ruedas.

A su lado iba Teresa, desbordando sus carnes blanduchas sobre el banquillo de terciopelo azul,
moviendo con cierta incomodidad su cabeza, como si le molestase la capota, recargada de rosas
y follaje, regalo de su marido.

--Hasta la noche.... Adiós, niñas. Esta noche iré a ver a ustedes.

Y Teresa enviaba una sonrisa sin expresión a su antigua señora, como suplicando que no abandonase
la tarea de catequizar a su esposo.

¡Buena estaba doña Manuela para tales indicaciones! Sabía lo que significaban las asiduas visitas,
unas veces por la tarde y otras por la noche, que la hacía aquel cincuentón; pero no pensaba
ahora en eso. El encuentro había acabado de trastornarla. Sus antiguos criados en carruaje,
ensuciándola con el polvo de las ruedas, y ella, la hija de un millonario, la viuda del doctor
Pajares, a pie y humillada por unas gentes a las que siempre había tratado con cierto desprecio.
Jamás había imaginado que pudiera ocurrir aquello. Agobiada por las deudas, esperaba la caída,
pero no tan honda y lastimosa para su dignidad.

Esto era demasiado fuerte para poder resistirlo. Y la pobre mujer, toda susceptibilidad y orgullo,
sintió que algo caliente se agolpaba a sus ojos, y hubo de hacer esfuerzos para no llorar.
Su paso acelerado era una verdadera fuga. Huían del paseo, de aquel lujo que algunos días antes
era su elemento y ahora les parecía un verdadero insulto.

Cuando entraron en la plazuela donde vivían, la vista de su casa, que con el portalón entornado,
los balcones cerrados y la fachada obscurecida por la última luz de la tarde tenía cierto aspecto
fúnebre, hizo revivir en la memoria de las tres el recuerdo del caballo.

--¡Dios mío! ¿Cómo estará el pobre Brillante? </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04591</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>82769</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17488</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Repeated every year, and there was nobody among the guests who do not the
wait. But had to repeat the sacramental phrase, excuses for heading, and while all claimed that
they were thirsty and asked angrily to homeowners why bother, tongue, dry heat, seemed to stick
to the palate, and eyes were after the gold fillet cups containing the steaming chocolate,
wide glasses blue on which stood their twisted monteras sorbet red or yellow, and lacquer covered
trays of sweets. Had to resign and do a rebuff to the lords home. And a few minutes they were
friends around the table, covered with cloth biscuit crumbs, empty gourds chocolate wafers and
nailing in the bowels of sorbets.

Doña Manuela spoke with Mr. Cuadros, Teresa had placed beside her
husband, the hope of achieving their catechism.

This lady, who knew so much and so great experience had acquired in marital misery, their
only hope.

The widow spoke with his former clerk, smiling. How the man had changed! Doña Manuela, knowledgeable
expert, noted in him a certain audacity, as the boy who emancipated from maternal authority
and launch into life full of crazy.

The widow, always smiling, amazed at his words with double meanings, of roguish winks which accompanied
his words, and even seemed oh power of illusion! was in his person a strange perfume beginning to
fray the nerves of Dona Manuela, some of the environment of that bad skin of the street from
the Port, that the guard had no doubt brought to his home honest.

Meanwhile, Teresa, while addressing the guests and overwhelm them with gifts, not take his eyes
off her husband and caring friend. Doña Manuela felt a deep pity every time you noticed the
poor wife. Well her husband was trying to conversions! Mr. Cuadros was a man lost forever,
he had a hungry like the forbidden fruit, after years of obscure and laborious life, not knowing
what Young was working as a beast of burden. Prior to die than to be satisfied. Nothing could advance
his wife away from Clarita.

The skulls are terrible fifties for his candor, and although isolated, are capable of falling
in love with the maid of the house.

Doña Manuela We stated further in this to notice what was happening
around her.

Who was one foot under the table, stepped on yours? What was that knee so boldly stroking her
silk skirt? Mr. Cuadros, to this honest family man who answered his honeyed words and gestures
seemed to measure up and down with their eyes dazzled.

Poor Teresa! Perhaps he imagined that the words of Dona Manuela unmoved by wayward making it into
the path of repentance, not even remotely guessed that his husband, by a strange aberration, which
came through a lot of pride, began to excited about something fading beauty of the wife of his
former principal.

The widow he felt disturbed by such audacity; agitábase nervously
in his seat, but was silent and still smiling.

I thought that the situation imposed hiatus, and that the friendship of marriage Pictures it was
very necessary to save their lady troubles in decline, beset by debts.

In addition, the future of his daughter, his Amparito, was there,
and the widow throwing a look of maternal anxiety at the end of the
table, where the child was with Andresito getting cuddly kitten with
gestures of sweets and the words of her boyfriend.

After half an hour of desktops, the meeting broke up. The men went in search of their hats and ladies
besuqueábanse to leave, muttering all the same greeting:

- Until next year. May God preserve us all health, to see the procession.

Were

parading all families, and finally left alone the Pajares, waiting Juanito or Raphael to accompany
them home.

Mr. Cuadros was harassing Dona Manuela It was up, running away from the bold intimidated by
the table below, but followed her stockbroker to continue their conversation. Now the two were next
to Teresa, and the husband was allowed only pleasantries and memories
on the great friendship that had always united the two families.

-
The boys take to come - said Don Antonio -.

Rafael will be with his friends, and as Juanito, you attract mandatory obligations. I am told
that now has a girlfriend and is mad for her. Youth! Oh, what a great thing! I already know
that, right, Teresa?

And as if sensing what he thought his wife and wanted to appease in
advance, throwing a the obese lady a look of tenderness, as an honest
man and of moral probity remembering its quiet honeymoon.

Doña Manuela was amazed. Decidedly, this Clarita had changed the man. He was a rascal. And instead
of outraged by the cruelty with which he lied and tried to deceive his woman, the widow began
to find sympathetic, seeing it as a resurrection of second husband,
the doctor that the skull had so loved.

- If you want, and I will
accompany Andresito.

Doña Manuela, animated by an instinct bashful, tried to excuse.

- Yes, the accompanying Antonio - Teresa said quickly.

And the poor woman begging with her eyes to accept, as if for her hope her husband prolonged
conversation with the widow. Who knows what could I say Dona Manuela's husband cheating!

There was no way to apologize.

The left Pajares Andresito and accompanied by Don Antonio following them with his eyes anxiously
Teresa gullible. My God, to soften the hearts the man, lest the shocking martyr himself to the family
and friends!

Down in the closed shop, they found Don Eugenio, always with the beanie silk, sullenly which welcomed
his former clerk. The Bird and his two companions followed by a sidewalk market. Before the two
girls with Andresito, Concha moody and scowling all day because he
had not seen the elegant Robert, and very satisfied Amparo able to
showcase a boyfriend, to the annoyance of his sister.

Behind Mr. Tables giving arm Dona Manuela, intentionally squeezing
your elbow on your hip every time you let go daring and swagger a
little word as an invincible conqueror.

It was more than accompany the Pajares what did the father and son. They came up with they remained
for over an hour visit, he sang Amparito to give to his future father, they took to the streets,
the father and son marched fraternally united as partners by a common enterprise.

Only a few months had passed, but were already far away for those times tables the shopkeeper of
quiet habits and routine was indignant to learn that his son was
to dances and I was waiting behind the door clutching the measuring
stick fiercely.

IX

At four p.m. Pajares entered the Paseo de la Alameda.

It was Sunday, and noisy and expansive entertainment holidays filled the left hand side the
ride. The weather was beautiful: a summer afternoon, the sky cloudless, and what higher, as
a thin wisp of steam and barely visible, the moon, waiting patiently it is the turn to shine.
The long rows of roses, the clumps of plants, all that gardening mutilated and corrected by the
scissors in the manger, was green with the breath warm in the afternoon
and was covered with flowers, perfumes simple joining the wake of
essences Ladies who left in its wake.

For the central stream and whirled round like the wheel arcaduces,
carriages lined in an endless rosary.

The towers of the guards raised their caps painted tiles above the trees, and the two ends of
the promenade, dwarfed by distance, stood out on the monumental fountains green background with light
mythological figures clothes. It was the time the trip took on its most brilliant. A gallop
of barouches down spirited horses and saloons, and on the sidewalks of the parade walk slowly procession
to pass, families Sunday best. The green banks did not have a seat free. Beehive buzzing sounded
on the trip, so silent and deserted in the morning and some families naive talking loudly, causing
the compassionate smile that went hand in the brand new hat, waving a few heads rigid sombrerazos peered
through the windows of the carriages.

What attracted the attention of all was the endless parade of cars, symbols of happiness and welfare
in a country where the desire to get rich has no desire not to go on foot other mortals.

Horses pawing with his mouth full of foam, spreading around the smell of straw blocks, and occasionally
a whinny infusing the spirited gross line, which seemed answered with a nervous kicking this
call for freedom. The drivers, dressed in their white frocks, displayed at the top of the gallows,
their faces shaved and carrilludas obese or pastors comedians well preserved, and looked with
contempt to all that crowd were forced to spend a few hours of tedium. In the long line of vehicles
was the old phaeton, rocking on its springs as a big box and enclosing funeral in its interior
padding whole family, including the nurse, the lightweight saloon with its wheels red or yellow,
the reel, like a gondola, swaying to the lower land inequality, and indigenous galerita, graceful
transformation of the trap and a symbol of the petty bourgeoisie that stopped in the middle of
social metamorphosis, has one foot in the village, where applicable, and another in the aristocracy,
where it goes.

There seemed to be invisible and impassable barrier between people walking on foot and those
heads sticking out the windows, contracting with a smile always the same when received the
greetings of the people I know. Groups of riders mixed with young officers snails cavalry
between the carriages, lying sometimes on the neck of their horses to talk through a door. Pajares
those contemplated with banished nostalgia over the carriages. Great God, how late! Would remember
her life! It was the first time they went on foot to the Alameda. The girls, despite their elegant
suits, believed that all were set in them to smile sympathetically, and Dona Manuela walked
upright, proudly painful, more or less like Napoleon on St. Helena
after denoted. The widow sensed his ruin.

They were not distressed debt and monetary the bitterness of life, but now, fate, as she said, pleased
to overwhelm her with the beating, depriving the family of limited means to sustain that detracted
from his reputation.

That morning had been tested for Pajares. Nelet the driver went very alarmed to account to their
wives that the horse was sick. The event was not to take to laugh. It was not vulgar colic,
and the poor beast, unconscious sustaining prestige of the family, revolcábase down in the dark and
wet block, being belly up and paws stirred by a convulsive shudder.

The situation was ridiculous and touching. Many years of service had established some affection
between the ladies and the brave beast it was considered almost like family. Doña Manuela,
recording the train of her gown theater down the block, not passing the door for fear the horse,
which rolled furious.

Called the best veterinarian in the city, but the horse did not improve, and in the afternoon
desvaneciéronse the illusions that had the girls to ride in a carriage. Acquired almost certain
that the poor horse would not leave the disease.

What would they do when they see them confused between the corny who walked on foot along
the Alameda? What would her friends to see it passed time and the
beautiful galerita, of how proud they were, remained wedged in the
garage?

Because the two, although his mother, not to grieve, the hidden status house, were fully aware
of the plight of the family and were confident of the impossibility to replace the old but fiery
horse with one that were worth as much as him.

After eating, the mother and daughter sat down in the lounge, where they remained over an hour,
silent, sullen and moody. The day was gorgeous, but no, they would not leave: nuns that the
world first to know of their decline, their hardships so ably hidden.

But the three could not resign himself to spending the day indoors. In addition, the balconies
the sun came and blew an irritant perfume-laden air of summer. Involuntarily thought in the green
fields, in the exuberant crowd stroll in the pleasure of walking
slowly under the tilted umbrellas, seeing new faces and responding
to the greeting of friends, and finally mothers and daughters could
not resist any longer and began to dress.

- Do not be so scrupulous
- said Dona Manuela -.

We all know, and because one day walk out to see us not going to imagine that we lack the
carriage. Come on girls, to walk!

And they went home with the intention to go anywhere but to the Alameda. But the tour be turned on,
do not know where to go, and at last, insensibly, without agreeing, on they went there.

What Pajares spent the late afternoon! Were always outside, the girls answered Funny grimaces
with the greetings of friends, and mom, proud and majestic, sheltering
him all with their eyes for protection.

But inside many torments! If any friend of waving from his carriage with loving expression, the
three believed guess some semblance of pity, and reddened under Blanquete layer covering her cheeks.
If a known person stopped to greet them, them, one-eyed or right-and often all three at a
time rushed to say they'd walk out in view of the beauty of the evening, and continued looking with
nostalgia and spite the long line of carriages, experiencing the
same impression of our biblical fathers before the closed gates of
Paradise forever.

Then why such painful memories! All three of them obsessed with horse sickness, as if he were
family. He was sorry for having left home, felt the false hope for those who are interested in
a patient and believe that by remaining at his side accelerate healing. Saluted right and left; deteníanse
to shake hands, changing words about the weather or the outfits they wore on the ride over,
but his eyes were unconsciously to dwell on those horses who spent a few steps from them, and in
everyone, whether from the color, the head or rump, were somewhat similar to the other who was in
his memory.

That evening meetings were very painful. Andresito, the son of Paintings, went through the two
rows of mounting the huge big horse carriages that had bought his father. Sought the bride to
be escorted, wearing their skills around his horse carriage.

The innocent gesture of surprise that made to see them walk, confused between dominguera kitsch,
was a real stab to the three women.

Everything hurt their susceptibility. Roberto del Campo, who was with some friends, greeted
the most seductive of smiles, but they believed his lips distinguish ironic expression. Undoubtedly,
that junk Rafaelito Roberto had related to the horse. Were sure that all knew the ride unpleasant
event, guessing what was coming later. And blinded by wounded vanity, no doubt recalling the taunts
that they had conducted other families, turbábanse at times, thinking
she saw thousands of eyes on them and Rijos Ladies from the carriages
of smiling contemptuously, as if they were reared in disguise.

They even thinking shiver of terror if your s behind the laughably would point finger. And always
the damn horse was in his thoughts, seeing through the eyes of imagination
as it was on your block to ride them out, belly up, stretching legs
convulsively.

The three bear within them, as implacable enemy, his own thought, which made them see the mockery
and pity everywhere, and even believed some times known people pretended not to greet distraction.

-
Come on, girls - said the mother with an expression that vibrated
the pain and anger -, we home to see how it is "that."

Today the ride is very cheesy.

The girls supported the mother in a gesture of approval.

It was really, really cheesy, and the three set a disastrous withdrawal, overwhelmed, overcome, as
if it had to sustain a battle with public consideration, being beaten and battered. Going up
the ramp bridge Real had to depart from the curb, wiping with the lace scarves dust raised
by wheels of a carruajillo discovered running speed insolent over all in.

It was the last surprise. Mr. Cuadros, pulling the reins to restrain his swift horse and waving
his whip, the waving from the top of that nutshell wheels.

At his side was Teresa, overflowing their flesh flabby on the bench blue velvet moving his head
uneasily, as if the hood bothered you, loaded with roses and foliage,
gift from her husband.

- Until the night .... Goodbye, girls.

Tonight I'll see you.

And Teresa sent a smile with no expression to his old lady, and pleading
not to leave the task of religious instruction to her husband.

Dona Manuela was good for such information! He knew what he meant
the assiduous visits sometimes in the evening and others at night,
which made one fifty, but did not think that now. The meeting had
just upset her. His former coach bred, soiled by the dust of the wheels,
and she, the daughter of a millionaire, the widow of Dr. Pajares,
ski and humiliated by some people whom he had always treated with
contempt. I had never imagined what might happen. Burdened by debt,
waiting for the fall but not so deep and hurt to their dignity.

This
was too strong to resist. And the poor woman, all susceptibility and
pride felt something warm running together in their eyes, and had
to make efforts not to mourn. Its fast pace was a real leak. Fleeing
the ride, the one luxury that some days before was her element and
now seemed an insult.

When they entered the square where they lived,
the sight of his house, the gate ajar, enclosed balconies and facade
obscured by the last light of evening had a certain aspect funeral,
revived the memory of the three memories of the horse.

- God! How
will the poor Brilliant</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>