<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07190</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>125535</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22469</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> A poco de la toma de la capital de esta
rica provincia, esto es, el 15 de Junio, entraba Bolivar en ella precedido de las mas calurosas
y expresivas muestras de aprecio y entusiasmo de los pueblos del transito. De aqui se traslado
a Guayaquil, donde las aclamaciones de jubilo se reprodujeron, pasando despues a Cuenca, desde
cuyo punto puso a disposicion del gobierno del Peru una division de 4.000 colombianos.

San Martin corrio a encontrar a Bolivar, y el 25 de Julio se abrazaban en Guayaquil estos dos
valientes guerreros, que habiendo partido desde ambos extremos del Nuevo Mundo, iban a conferenciar
acerca de la independencia de su pais bajo el ardiente sol del Ecuador. Tres dias pasaron reunidos
estos dos heroes americanos, sin que un solo momento se les viese al uno sin el otro; pero
el resultado de sus conferencias quedo envuelto en la noche del misterio. Solo se sabe que
aunque en las entrevistas reino la mas atenta cordialidad entre ellos, su separacion, sin embargo,
no fue de aquellas en que la amistad deja ver la efusion del entusiasmo o la ternura de un
vivo afecto. Entre las ideas politicas de estos dos hombres eminentes se alzaba tal vez una
gran valla.

Los realistas ocupaban por entonces, no solo todo el Alto Peru, sino tambien la mayor parte
del Bajo, y se encontraban muy animados y llenos de esperanza a causa de sus recientes triunfos.
Los patriotas poseian unicamente a Lima y los paises situados en la costa del Norte; ademas
se hallaban separados en diferentes partidos politicos, que minaban por su base la fuerza de
la causa comun del Sud de America, y sus recursos metalicos no eran sobrados, antes por el
contrario, andaban escasos. Tal era la situacion del Peru desde fines de 1822 a mediados de 1823.

El 8 de Abril de este ano el Congreso de Colombia se reunia otra vez, y el 4 de Julio autorizaba
al Libertador para que pasase a llevar sus auxilios al Peru, acto el mas notable de aquella
legislatura. Ya conocemos la entrevista que luego tuvieron el llamado dictador de aquel pais
y el ilustre caraqueno. En el trascurso del mismo ano Montilla preparaba en la ciudad de Hacha
una expedicion contra Maracaibo, combinandose al efecto con las fuerzas navales que mandaba
el coronel jefe de la escuadra Jose Padilla, quien juzgo posible la arriesgada empresa de forzar
la barra, operacion que se ofrecio a cumplir y que cumplio el 8 de Mayo con solo la perdida
del bergantin General Bolivar, al mando y de la propiedad del capitan de navio Nicolas Joly.

Una vez libre de cruzar las aguas del lago, en las cuales llego a ensenorearse, a fines de
Junio, y mientras el general Francisco Esteban Gomez, por enfermedad de Montilla, se dirigia
contra Maracaibo, Morales reforzaba su escuadrilla con dos goletas que el capitan Laborde traia
de Curazao. Reunida la flotilla espanola en Zaparas, fondeaba el 22 de Julio entre Maracaibo
y el islote de Capitan-Chico. Los independientes hacian lo propio en Altagracia y Punta de
Piedras. Ambos combatientes, a vista uno del otro, esperaban el viento para acometerse, cuando
habiendolo tenido favorable los patriotas, abordaron el 24, tres horas despues del medio dia,
al enemigo, y trabando un renidisimo combate quedo vencedor Padilla. Los realistas tuvieron
800 bajas entre muertos y heridos, mas 420 prisioneros entre oficiales, clase de tropa y marineria.
Los patriotas contaron 44 muertos entre oficiales y tropa y 119 heridos.

Las armas republicanas, favorecidas por su valor y la buena causa, marchaban sembrando por
su camino los laureles de la victoria y anadiendo cada dia una piedra mas al colosal edificio
de su independencia. Alli donde se presentaban, desalentados por sus esteriles esfuerzos los
antiguos dominadores de Venezuela, cedian el campo a los ya aguerridos soldados de la libertad.
El 3 de Agosto capitulo Morales bajo las mas generosas condiciones de los republicanos, que
haciendolo asi se coronaban de gloria; y doce dias despues se hacia a la vela aquel memorable
general con rumbo a la isla de Cuba. En el resto del ano Coro y Puerto Cabello, ultimos baluartes
de la dominacion espanola en Venezuela, cayeron tambien en manos de los valientes y benemeritos
hijos del Nuevo Mundo, cuya heroica sangre venia derramandose hacia tantos anos, y por fin,
al despedirse el de 1823, podian exclamar, enarbolando el pabellon de Colombia: "Ya somos libres."

CAPITULO XI

Bolivar en Lima.--El espiritu publico en el Peru.--Perdidas. --Disolucion del Congreso.--El
Libertador organiza una gran expedicion.--Paso de los desfiladeros de los Andes.--Victoria
de los colombianos en Junin.--Retirada de las tropas espanolas.--Descanso. --Combinaciones
estrategicas.--Bolivar se dirije al Alto Peru.--Batalla de Ayacucho.--Capitulaciones.--Entrada
de Bolivar en Lima.--Convocatoria para la reunion de un Congreso.--Su reunion y sus actos.--Republica
Bolivar.--Rendicion del Callao.--Emancipacion de la America del Sud realizada.--Consideraciones.--Principia
a turbarse el orden entre los venezolanos.--Deposicion decretada contra Paez.--Sublevacion
de Valencia. --Los partidos.--Asamblea provocada por los federalistas de Caracas. --Bolivar
se dirije a Venezuela.--Proclama dada en Maracaibo. --Acontecimientos del Peru.

El 1 deg. de Setiembre de 1825 habia hecho el libertador su entrada en Lima, donde fue investido
del poder dictatorial, con autorizacion de disponer libremente de todos los recursos del pais;
pero en vista de la oposicion de algunos partidos politicos, y comprendiendo que con los elementos
disolventes que minaban su noble empresa no seria posible llegar al termino que se habia propuesto,
se retiro a Trujillo. Abandonada asi la capital, pronto se vio ocupada por las tropas realistas
al mando del general Canterac.

A principios de 1824 el estado de la causa de la independencia era lastimoso en el Peru y marchaba
desalentadamente a la ruina. Perdidas el 5 de Febrero las fortalezas del Callao, se disolvio
el Congreso, depositando en Bolivar la esperanza de su salvacion. El ilustre jefe colombiano,
aun cuando no fuera por su ardiente amor hacia la causa de la libertad de la America del Sud,
no podia mirar con indiferencia los peligros que vendrian a amenazar la obra por el realizada
hasta alli si las armas espanolas llegasen a entronizarse en el Peru; y cuando recibio la triste
noticia de los ultimos desastres se hallaba en la provincia de Huamalies organizando tropas
y esperando refuerzos de su republica para continuar las operaciones de su cuenta y riesgo,
pudiendo oponer de alli a poco a las desgracias ocurridas un ejercito de 4.000 patriotas del
pais y 6.000 colombianos.

Cruzo entonces los desfiladeros de los Andes, mientras Canterac guarnecia los de Jauja y situaba
sus puestos avanzados en Casas, y marcho decididamente sobre Pasco. El general espanol, que
ignoraba la direccion seguida por su contrario, se encamino hacia este mismo punto con objeto
de practicar un reconocimiento. Aqui supo que el 5 de Agosto habia pasado Bolivar tomando por
la derecha de la laguna de Junin, y retrocedio en el acto para estorbar que las fuerzas enemigas
vinieran a situarse a su espalda. Al practicar este movimiento, y a los tres dias de haberlo
emprendido, Canterac fue alcanzado por Bolivar y los realistas sufrieron una gran derrota en
Junin o Pampa de los Reyes.

Los vencedores siguieron en persecucion de Canterac que, sucesivamente y en buen orden, fue
retirandose a Tarma, Jauja, Huancayo y Huamanga, llegando por fin a Cuzco con una perdida de
mas de 2.000 hombres. El ejercito libertador no paso de Huamanga sino despues de haber descansado
alli por espacio de un mes, en cuyo tiempo, segun lo dispuso su jefe, el general Sucre debia
dirigirse sobre Challuanca para amenazar la retaguardia del enemigo, en tanto que el practicaba
un reconocimiento hacia el Apurimac, operacion en la cual vino a sorprenderles el invierno
y se suspendieron las que despues de esta debian verificarse. Entonces Bolivar, movido por
causas poderosas, se separo de su ejercito, dejandole en cuarteles de invierno, y se dirigio
al Alto Peru con el fin de preparar los medios necesarios para cerrar la campana y al propio
tiempo organizar un buen gobierno en aquel pais.

Mas tarde, el 9 de Diciembre, los tropas de Sucre se coronaban de laureles en Ayacucho, alcanzando
una decisiva victoria sobre las armas espanolas, mandadas por Laserna, virey entonces del Peru.
A cerca de 9.500 hombres ascendian las fuerzas del virey, mientras que no llegaban a 6.000
las comandadas por el general republicano; pero bien combinado y habilmente dirigido el plan
de batalla, los realistas fueron deshechos completamente, quedando en poder de Sucre, ademas
de Laserna, 15 generales, 16 coroneles, 68 tenientes coroneles, 484 oficiales, 3.200 soldados,
cabos y sargentos, 11 piezas de artilleria, gran numero de fusiles, municiones y en fin, todos
los pertrechos de guerra pertenecientes al enemigo, que habia sido puesto en el caso de rendirse
por capitulacion.

En esta memorable jornada, la mas brillante de las que tuvieron lugar en la America del Sud,
junto al jefe que la alcanzo se distinguieron heroicamente Jose Maria Cordoba, el ingles Miller
y el general Lamar. Segun las bases de la capitulacion los espanoles se obligaban a entregar
los paises aun dominados por ellos en el Alto y Bajo Peru y los vencedores a respetar las vidas
y haciendas de los vencidos y de sus partidarios, costeando ademas el viaje a la peninsula
a los individuos del ejercito que asi lo solicitasen. La batalla de Ayacucho inmortalizo el
nombre del valiente hijo de Cumana, tan buen patriota como virtuoso ciudadano, tan habil como
noble general.

Al siguiente dia de esta batalla Bolivar entraba en Lima y expedia un decreto por el cual convocaba
un Congreso para el 10 de Febrero del proximo ano. Llegada esta fecha y reunido ya, los primeros
actos de este cuerpo se encaminaron a manifestar de una manera solemne su gratitud hacia los
libertadores del pais, ordenando se abriese una medalla en honor del Libertador y que en la
plaza principal de Lima se le erigiese una estatua. Ademas hizole presente de dos millones
de pesos, para que uno lo distribuyese entre los generales y demas clases de ejercito, reservandose
el otro para si, lo cual rehuso dignamente; y al mismo tiempo distinguio al general Sucre con
el titulo de mariscal de Ayacucho. Despues confirio a Bolivar el poder ejecutivo, y este pidio
permiso a Colombia para poder aceptarlo, pues, segun sus palabras en esta ocasion, reconocia
monstruosa aquella autoridad e impropia de el.

Bajo la denominacion de Republica Bolivar (mas tarde Bolivia), se constituyeron por medio de
una Asamblea general, declarando en independencia, las provincias del Alto Peru a 10 de Julio
del mismo ano 1825 y confiaron al Libertador la autoridad ejecutiva por todo el tiempo de su
permanencia en el territorio del Estado, y Sucre quedo encargado del mando inmediato de los
departamentos en que aquel habia sido dividido. A los tres meses no cabales, esto es, el 6
de Octubre, despues de haber encargado al Libertador que formase una Constitucion politica
para el pais, se disolvio la Asamblea, aplazando la reunion del cuerpo constituyente, reunion
que debia realizarse el 25 de Mayo del siguiente ano.

A pesar de los esfuerzos hechos por los partidarios de la independencia, el general Rodil,
refugiado en el Callao, sostuvo durante mas de un ano esta plaza, rendida por fin el 23 de
Enero de 1826, dia en que el Peru, a consecuencia de este acontecimiento quedaba totalmente
emancipado de Espana y la America del Sud veia terminarse la sangrienta y larga lucha comenzada
y llevada a feliz termino por los valientes hijos de Venezuela, bajo la gloriosa direccion
del celeberrimo Bolivar.

Pero el pueblo colombiano, como sucede con todos los pueblos colocados en analogas circunstancias,
si bien cediendo a un natural impulso, habia desplegado todas sus fuerzas para sacudir el yugo
de la esclavitud, no bien dispuesto aun a recibir la nueva forma de gobierno, poco ilustrado
para conocer los medios de aprovecharse de la libertad que habia conquistado, y no comprendiendo
el valor de los deberes que adquiria al adquirir nuevos derechos, pronto se vio envuelto en
las discordias civiles por no prestarse de buen grado a ellos. Resistiendose los caraquenos
a la tercera invitacion hecha por Paez, que queria dar cumplimiento al decreto sobre la organizacion
de milicias, se vio este jefe obligado a hacer algunas prisiones, y con tal motivo Caracas
presento 17 dias antes a la toma del Callao la imagen de una espantosa revolucion.

So color de haber sido hollados los derechos del pueblo en la manera de dar cumplimiento a
los decretos del gobierno, la Camara de los representantes fulmino contra Paez una acusacion,
que en 30 de Marzo admitio el Senado, suspendiendole de su empleo y citandole a dar cuenta
de su conducta. No solo desobedecio esta orden trasmitida por medio del poder ejecutivo, sino
que por disposicion de la Asamblea municipal de Valencia, en cuya ciudad se hallaba Paez entonces,
el 30 de Abril reasumio el mando de que el Senado le habia separado, dando lugar este hecho
a que todos los pueblos se creyeran autorizados a desconocer el legitimo gobierno, y pronto
se vio la Republica envuelta en las discordias civiles.

Dos fueron los bandos que se alzaron: uno federal y otro central, siendo los partidarios del
primero de los sistemas quienes marchaban a su fin con mayor unidad, con mas perfecta armonia.
Los federalistas de Caracas concitaron a Paez para que convocara y presidiera una Asamblea
general con objeto de fijar el destino politico de Venezuela en aquellas circunstancias; y
verificada la reunion el 7 de Noviembre, despues de mediar violentas discusiones y una incalificable
votacion, Paez quedo autorizado; conforme a los poderes de que la Asamblea le habia investido,
dio un decreto senalando el 10 de Diciembre para la reunion de los colegios electorales y para
la instalacion del Cuerpo constituyente en Valencia fijo igual dia de Enero de 1827.

Bolivar, noticioso de los escandalos promovidos en Venezuela, partio de Lima el 4 de Setiembre
y cuarenta dias mas tarde entraba en Santa Fe de Bogota, siendo recibido con generales muestras
de afecto. El 25 de Noviembre se dirigio a Venezuela y durante su travesia hasta Cucuta fue
reuniendo tropas para presentarse con imponente actitud. El 16 del siguiente mes dio una proclama
desde Maracaibo en que, ofreciendo acelerar la gran Convencion nacional para que legalmente
tuviera el pueblo leyes fundamentales, decia: solo el (el pueblo) conoce su bien y es dueno
de su suerte, y no un poderoso, ni un partido, ni una sola fraccion del mismo pueblo. El Libertador,
al cual volvian algunos de los extraviados patricios, llego por Coro a Puerto-Cabello el ultimo
dia del ano, epoca en que Paez se encontraba en Valencia.

Los acontecimientos del Peru mientras el trascurso del ano que asi espiraba fueron: la reunion
del Congreso constituyente de Bolivia, que con lijeras variantes acepto el proyecto que le
habia enviado Bolivar, acompanado del reconocimiento de aquella republica por el Consejo de
gobierno del Peru; el nombramiento del general Sucre como Presidente vitalicio del Estado,
dignidad que solo admitio por dos anos; la declaracion de nulidad en los poderes otorgados
por los colegios de algunas provincias a sus representantes, hecha por el Consejo de gobierno
peruano en su primer Congreso constitucional; la disolucion de este; la reunion del colegio
electoral de la provincia de Lima, en virtud de decreto de la autoridad competente, el 16 de
Agosto; la aceptacion que el mismo hizo de la Constitucion boliviana como Codigo fundamental
del Peru, y el nombramiento de Bolivar para Presidente perpetuo de la Republica, actos sancionados
por el Consejo de gobierno, en vista de la unanimidad conque los colegios electorales habian
procedido en todos sus acuerdos.

CAPITULO XII

Disposiciones conciliatorias.--Bolivar y Paez se reconcilian.--Error politico.--Reclamaciones
de Nueva-Granada y del Peru.--Dimision del Libertador ante el quinto Congreso reunido en Bogota.--No
es admitida su dimision.--Se levantan facciones en Venezuela.--El Congreso Constituyente del
Peru.--Agitaciones politicas y desunion de Colombia. --Fracasa la Convencion de Ocana.--Acta
del 15 de Junio de 1828. --Conjuracion a mano armada.--Peligro del Libertador.--Acto de justicia
contra los conspiradores.--Nueva convocacion a un Congreso Constituyente.--Trabajos de zapa
de los descontentos.--Manifiesto de Bolivar.--Consecuencias del manifiesto.--Es llamado el
Libertador por algunos miembros del Congreso de Colombia.--Sancion del Codigo politico.--Cesacion
de la dictadura y de la representacion de la Colombia.--Viaje de Bolivar a Cartagena.--Decretos
de Paez.--Instalacion del Congreso en Valencia.--Nueva Constitucion de Venezuela.--Fallecimiento
del Libertador.

El ano 1827 era inaugurado por el Libertador de una manera politica y conciliatoria. El primer
dia de aquel desde Puerto Cabello publico un decreto de amnistia, confirmando a Paez la autoridad
de jefe civil y militar que al principio de la revolucion le habia sido conferido por los concejos
municipales. Este dicto al siguiente otro decreto por el cual reconocia y mandaba reconocer
a Bolivar como Presidente de la Republica, anulando al propio tiempo todas sus anteriores resoluciones,
inclusa la de reunion de un Congreso. El 4, a las dos de la tarde, ambos jefes se habian visto
y abrazado al pie del cerro de Naguanagua, entrando luego juntos en Valencia entre las aclamaciones
entusiastas del pueblo; y el 10 del mismo mes todo Caracas se deshacia en expresiones de la
mas grande admiracion al acoger en su recinto a su ilustre hijo, el Libertador de la America
del Sud.

El excesivo amor de este grande hombre por la causa que tan constante y noblemente habia defendido,
el vivo deseo que le agitaba de consolidar su grande obra, le hizo cometer un error, perdonable
bajo este punto de vista. Pero ?quien que sintiese como el sentia, quien que como el se viese
rodeado de tan rebeldes circunstancias cuando apenas lucia la primer aurora de la libertad
de su patria, quien que como el la encontrase amenazada de ser envuelta entre las sombras de
una devastadora tempestad en el momento mismo de nacer, no hubiera tratado de evitar a toda
costa las tristes consecuencias que resultarian de la desunion entre los elementos politicos
que debian formar entonces su mas firme apoyo? Esto fue sin duda lo que le hizo halagar a los
disidentes, lo que le obligo a apagar su desenfrenada ambicion y deseo de mando, produciendo
entre sus amigos el descontento y la envidia. iAmigos!...iQue lastimoso abuso se ha hecho de
esta bella frase, empleandola sin razon en vez de adeptos al tratarse de aquellos hombres que,
como Bolivar, llegan a tener entre sus manos los destinos de una nacion!

En la Nueva-Granada, lo mismo que en el Peru, muchos militares dirigian representaciones al
gobierno reprobando las reformas introducidas en la primitiva ley del Estado; y despues de
tantos y tan inmensos sacrificios, despues de tanta y tan preciosa sangre vertida en aras de
la patria, mezquinos intereses, miras egoistas de dominio, envidias y rencores mal comprimidos,
encienden los animos y los concitan a la guerra mas inicua que la humanidad conoce entre la
iniquidad misma de la guerra, a la que el genio del mal despierta y mantiene en el corazon
de los que debiera unir el vinculo fraternal de las costumbres, del idioma, del pais y la familia.
Asi, pues, por desgracia, al triunfo de la independencia sucedia la discordia civil en la America
del Sud, enconada y sobreexcitada por medidas cuyo espiritu, cuyo fin no era otro que el de
la conciliacion, el bienestar y la fuerza. Pero el hombre propone y Dios dispone.

Ante el quinto Congreso, reunido en Bogota, dimitio Bolivar su cargo de Presidente, y despues
de largos y acalorados debates, por 50 contra 24 votos no fue atendido. Esta dimision la hizo
desde su pueblo natal; en vista de la negativa, el 10 de Setiembre paso a Bogota, jurando nuevamente
ante el Congreso, al efecto reunido en sesion extraordinaria, sostener y defender como hasta
alli la Constitucion de la Republica. En Venezuela mientras tanto se habian levantado facciones
que, como la de Cisneros en Caracas, llevaban la devastacion a todas partes.

El Congreso constituyente del Peru se habia reunido, con antelacion a los hechos ultimamente
citados, el 1 deg. de Mayo, y declaro que la Constitucion jurada en 9 de Diciembre del ano
anterior era nula y sin ningun efecto, por haber sido sancionada de un modo ilegal y atentatoria
a la soberania del pueblo; restableciendo provisionalmente en su fuerza y vigor, con supresion
de algunos capitulos, interin el Cuerpo Legislativo se ocupaba de formar otra nueva, la admitida
y votada en 1823. Don Jose de Lamar, gran mariscal, y Don Manuel Salazar y Barquijano fueron
elegidos, el primero como Presidente y el segundo como Vice-Presidente de la Republica. Tales
fueron los hechos mas notables o importantes de la America del Sud en este ano.

En el siguiente de 1828 dos eran los grandes partidos que se agitaban en el seno de la Colombia.
Los que aspiraban con la mejor buena fe del mundo a hacer alteraciones liberales en la ley
fundamental,--cuyo medio, a los ojos de sus emulos, era el mas a proposito para derrocar al
Libertador, asi como tambien para los que deseaban dividir el territorio colombiano en tres
distintos estados independientes entre si,--formaban el primero de estos partidos. En el segundo
estaban afiliados la mayor parte de los generales, jefes y oficiales venezolanos, mas todos
los extranjeros que subsistian al servicio de la Colombia y los deudos y amigos de Bolivar,
que se esforzaban en sostener la integridad de la republica creada por la union de Venezuela,
Quito y la Nueva-Granada. Esta era precisamente la division intentada por los de la faccion
contraria.

Despues de haber fracasado la Convencion nacional reunida en Ocana el 9 de Abril, a causa de
lo encontrado de las opiniones y principios politicos alli representados, una junta de personas
notables, formada en Bogota, suscribia el 13 de Junio una acta en la cual hacian solemne protesta
contra toda reforma que emanase de la Convencion, depositando el cargo supremo de la Republica
y su entera confianza en el general Bolivar, ejemplo que luego fue imitado y seguido en toda
su latitud por los demas pueblos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04814</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>9392</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20236</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Shortly after taking the capital of this
rich province, ie June 15, Bolivar entered it preceded the warmest and expressive tokens of appreciation
and enthusiasm of the people of transit. From here he moved Guayaquil, where the shouts of joy
were reproduced from then to Cuenca, from which point put at the disposal of the government of
Peru is a division of 4,000 Colombians.

San Martin ran to find Bolivar, and July 25 in Guayaquil embraced two brave warriors, having started
from both ends of the New World, were to confer about the independence of his country under the burning
sun of Ecuador. Three days passed together these two American heroes, not a single moment
they saw one without the other, but the outcome of his talks remained shrouded in mystery
night. Only known that Interviews though the most attentive kingdom cordiality between them, their
separation, however, were not those that the friendship reveals the outpouring of enthusiasm
or the tenderness of a Live affection. Among the political ideas of these two eminent men stood
perhaps a high fence.

The royalists occupied at the time, not only all of Upper Peru, but also most Lower, and were
very encouraged and hopeful because of his recent triumphs. The Patriots possessed only in Lima
and the countries located on the northern coast; also were separated in different political
parties, which undermined its force base the common cause of South
America, and metal resources were not over, before the contrast, were
short.

Such was the situation of Peru from late 1822 to mid-1823.

On 8 April this year, Colombia's Congress met again, and authorized on July 4 the freedom to
pass to get their aid to Peru, the most notable event of that legislature. We know that after
the interview had called dictator of that country and the illustrious Caracas. In the course
of the same year the city was preparing Montilla Axe an expedition against Maracaibo, combined with
the effect commanded naval forces Colonel squad leader Jose Padilla, who can judge the risky
venture of force bar, an operation which was offered to fulfill and
accomplish his May 8 with only the loss General Bolivar's brig, commanded
and owned by Captain Nicolas Joly.

Once free to cross the lake, where I get to lord it in late June, and while General Francisco Esteban
Gomez, sick of Montilla, was headed against Maracaibo, Morales strengthened their squad with
two schooners that was bringing Captain Laborde Curacao. Gathered in Zapara Spanish fleet,
anchored on July 22 between Maracaibo and the island of Captain-Chico. The independents were doing
so in Altagracia Punta Piedras. Both fighters, in sight of each other, waiting for the wind to
be undertaken when patriots when they had been favorable, boarded the 24, three hours after
noon, the enemy and fight renidisimo'm locking a winner Padilla. The royalists had 800 casualties in
dead and wounded, 420 prisoners from more official kind of army and
navy.

The Patriots were 44 officers and men killed and 119 wounded.

Weapons Republican, favored for their courage and good cause, marching seeding for the way the
laurels of victory and adding one each day over the colossal stone building independence. Where
there had discouraged by their fruitless efforts the former rulers of Venezuela, ceded the
field to the brave and freedom fighters. On August 3 chapter Morales under the most generous
terms of the Republicans who doing so will be crowning glory and twelve days after the candle is
to that memorable general due to the island of Cuba. In the rest of the year Coro and Puerto Cabello,
the last bastion of Spanish domination in Venezuela, also fell into the hands of the brave
and meritorious children of the New World, whose heroic came spilling
blood for so many years, and finally to leave the 1823, could exclaim,
waving the flag of Colombia: "We are already free."

CHAPTER XI

Bolivar in Lima .-- The public spirit in Peru .-- Lost. - Dissolution of Congress .-- The Libertador
organized a major expedition .-- Passage of the gorges of the Andes .-- Victoria Junin Colombians in
the Troops .-- .-- Break Spanish. - Combinations Bolivar .-- strategic directs the High Battle of Ayacucho
Peru .-- .-- .-- Entry Capitulaciones Bolivar in Lima .-- Call for a reunion of Congress .--
The .-- reunion and actions Republic Surrender of Callao Bolivar .-- .-- Emancipation of South
America made Considerations .-- .-- Principia to disturbed the order
among Venezuelans decreed against Paez Deposition .-- .-- Revolt of
Valencia. - Assembly .-- parties caused by the Federalists of Caracas.
- Bolivar is heading to Venezuela .-- Proclamation given in Maracaibo.
- Events of Peru.

The 1 deg. September, 1825 had made its entry into the liberator Lima, where he was sworn in dictatorial
power, with authorization to dispose of all resources of the country; but given the opposition of some
political parties, and realizing that the elements solvents that undermined its noble undertaking
would not be possible to reach the end which had proposed Trujillo
retired.

Thus abandoning the capital, was soon occupied by the royal troops Canterac under General.

In early 1824 the state of the cause of independence was pitiful in Peru and marched despondently
to ruin. Missed the February 5 strengths of Callao, was dissolved Congress, putting in Bolivar
hope of their salvation. The illustrious leader Colombian even if it were not for their ardent
love for the cause of freedom of South America, I could not watch with indifference the dangers
that would come to threaten the work done by the up there if the arms enthrone Spanish arrived
in Peru, and when he received the sad news was the latest disaster in the province of organizing
troops Huamalies and waiting for reinforcements from their republic to continue operations at
its own risk may oppose in a little to the misfortunes that occurred
an army of 4,000 patriots country and 6,000 Colombians.

Then crossed the passes of the Andes, while those of Jauja Canterac garrisoned and placed their
outposts in Houses, and marched resolutely on Pasco. The Spanish general, who know the direction
followed by its opposite, is heading the same point in order recognition practice. Here he learned
that on August 5 had been taking for Bolivar the right of Lake Junin, and fell in the act to
hinder the enemy forces came to be at your back. By practicing this movement, and have three
days undertaken, Canterac was hit by Bolivar and the royalists suffered
a major defeat in Or Pampa Junin de los Reyes.

The winners Canterac followed in pursuit of that, on and in good order, was retiring to Tarma, Jauja,
Huancayo and Huamanga, and arrived at Cuzco with a loss more than 2,000 men. The liberating
army Huamanga not pass until after he had rested there for about a month, at which time, as he
had his boss, General Sucre was to Challuanca go on to threaten the enemy's rear, while he
practiced a recognition of the Apurimac, operation in which the winter came to surprise suspended
and that after this debian verified. Bolivar then moved by powerful causes, he separated from
his army, leaving him in winter quarters, and headed the Alto Peru in order to prepare the necessary
means to close the hood and at the same time to organize good governance
in that country.

Later, on December 9, the troops were crowned with laurel Sucre in Ayacucho, reaching a decisive
victory over Spanish arms, commanded by Laserna, then viceroy of Peru. A nearly 9,500 men ascended
the viceroy's forces, while not arriving at 6,000 the general command of the republic, but well
combined and skillfully directed the plan battle, the royalists were completely undone, remained
in the hands of Sucre, in addition de Laserna, 15 generals, 16 colonels, 68 lieutenant colonels,
484 officers, 3,200 soldiers, corporals and sergeants, 11 pieces of artillery, a large number of
rifles, ammunition and finally, all the military equipment belonging
to the enemy, who had been placed in the case of surrender by capitulation.

On

this memorable day, the brightest of which took place in South America, with the head that reached
heroically distinguished Jose Maria Cordoba, English Miller and Gen. Lamar. According to the foundations
of the Spanish capitulation was forced to surrender countries still dominated by them in the
Upper and Lower Peru and the victors to spare the lives and property of the vanquished and their
supporters, paying also travel to the peninsula Army individuals who request them. The immortalized
the Battle of Ayacucho name of the brave son of Cumana, as good a patriot as a virtuous citizen,
as skilled as noble general.

The next day the battle Bolivar Lima and expedia entered a decree which summoned a congress on 10 February
next year. After that date, and already met the first acts of this body were directed to express
in a solemn manner his gratitude to the liberators of the country, ordered it opened a medal
in honor of the Liberator and the Lima's main square was erected a statue. You made the present
of two million pesos, for one it circulated among the generals and other military classes,
reserving the other for himself, which he refused with dignity, and distinguished himself while General
Sucre the title of Marshal of Ayacucho. After Bolivar conferred on the executive, and he asked
Colombia permission to accept it, because, according to his words on this occasion, he recognized
monstrous that the authority and improper.

Republic under the name of Bolivar (Bolivia later), constituted by a General Assembly, declaring
independence in the provinces of Upper Peru to July 10 the same year 1825 and entrusted the executive
authority Libertador around the time of stay in the territory of the State, and Sucre is charged
with the immediate command of the that departments that had been divided. Three months is not
complete, that is, 6 October, after having instructed the Liberator, which formed a political
constitution for the country, disbanded the Assembly, postponing the constitutional body reunion,
reunion which was to be held on May 25 of next year.

Despite the efforts made by supporters of independence, General Rodil, refugee in Callao, held
for over a year this place, finally surrendered on 23 January 1826, the day that Peru, as
a result of this event was totally emancipated from Spain and South America saw the completion
of the long and bloody struggle started and carried to a successful conclusion by the brave sons
of Venezuela, under the direction glorious the celebrated Bolivar.

But the Colombian people, like all people placed in analogous circumstances While yielding to a natural
impulse, had displayed all his strength to throw off the yoke of slavery, not even willing to
receive the new form of government, unenlightened to find ways to take advantage of the freedom
they had conquered, and not understanding the value of the duties to acquire new rights acquired,
soon became involved in civil strife not willingly given them. Resisting the Caracas the third
invitation made by Paez, who wanted to implement the decree on the organization militia, was
the chief forced to do some prisons, and on that occasion Caracas presented 17 days prior to the seizure
of Callao the image of a terrible revolution.

Pretext of having been trampled people's rights in the way of implementing government decrees,
the House of Representatives Paez fulminated against an accusation, March 30 in the Senate admitted,
suspended from his job and to realize quoting of their behavior. Disobeyed the order not only
transmitted by the executive, but that provision of the Municipal Assembly of Valencia, whose
city was Paez then April 30, retook the Senate that he had separated, resulting in the fact to believe
all people are entitled to ignore the legitimate government, and soon Republic was embroiled
in civil strife.

There were two sides who were raised: one federal and one central, with supporters first system
who marched to an end with more unity, more perfect harmony. The Federalists stirred Paez Caracas
to convene and chair an Assembly general in order to determine the political destiny of Venezuela
in the circumstances, and verified the reunion on November 7, after violent debates and an
unspeakable vote, Paez is authorized, pursuant to the powers that the Assembly had invested, pointing
issued a decree on December 10 for the reunion of polling stations and the installation of fixed
Valencia constituent body as day of January 1827.

Bolivar, news of the scandals promoted in Venezuela, departed from Lima on September 4 and forty
days later went into Santa Fe de Bogota, and was received with general samples affection. On November
25, headed to Venezuela and during his journey to Cucuta was massing troops to perform with
impressive attitude. On 16 the following month gave a proclamation from Maracaibo that, offering
high speed National Convention to legally people had the basic laws, he said: only the (people)
know her well and is owner their fate, not a powerful nor a party, not a single fraction from
the same village. The Liberator which returned some of the patricians lost, I arrive at Puerto-Cabello
Choir last day of the year, a time when Paez was in Valencia.

The events of Peru as the course of the year that were expiring so: the reunion Bolivia's Constituent
Congress, which accepted the draft Thin variants that Bolivar had sent, accompanied by the
recognition of that republic by the Council Peru's government, the appointment of General Sucre
as Life President of the State dignity that only admitted for two years, the declaration of
nullity of the powers conferred by schools in some provinces to their representatives, made
by the Governing Council Peruvian Congress in its first constitutional dissolution of this, the
school reunion election in the province of Lima, by decree of the competent authority, 16 August,
the acceptance that it made the Bolivian Constitution as fundamental Code Peru, and Bolivar's
appointment to president in perpetuity of the Republic, acts punishable by the Governing Council,
in view of unanimity had simply to have polling stations proceeded in all its agreements.

CHAPTER XII

Conciliatory provisions .-- Bolivar and Paez reconcile political failure .-- .-- Claims New-Granada
and Peru .-- Resignation of the Liberator to the fifth Congress meeting in Bogota .-- No his resignation
is accepted .-- factions are raised in Venezuela .-- The Constituent Congress Peru .-- political
unrest and disunity of Colombia. - Fail the Convention of Ocana Act .-- June 15, 1828. - Conspiracy
to armed .-- .-- Hazard Libertador Justice Act against the conspirators .-- New convening a Constituent
Congress .-- spade work of the discontented .-- Bolivar Manifesto .-- .-- Consequences of the
manifest is called the Libertador by some members of Congress of Colombia .-- .-- Punishment
of the Political Code Cessation of the dictatorship and the representation of Colombia .-- Journey
to Cartagena Bolivar .-- Decrees Paez .-- Congress in Valencia Installing New Constitution of Venezuela
.-- Death .-- del Libertador.

The year 1827 was opened by the Libertador in a manner and conciliatory policy. The first that
day from Puerto Cabello published an amnesty decree, confirming the authority Paez of civil and military
chief at the beginning of the revolution had been given by councils municipal. This dictated the following
other decree by which he recognized and sent acknowledge Bolivar as President of the Republic,
at the same time canceling all its previous resolutions, including that of reunion of a Congress. 4, at
two in the afternoon, both leaders had been and embraced at the foot of the hill Naguanagua, and
fit together in Valencia amid the acclamations enthusiastic people, and 10 of the same month across
Caracas melted in terms of greatest admiration to host on its campus to its illustrious son,
the liberator of America del Sud

The excessive love of this great man for the cause he had so nobly defended constant, strong desire
to consolidate it shook his great work, I made a mistake, excusable this point of view. But? Who
felt that felt like, who he saw that as as rebels surrounded circumstances when looked just the
first dawn of freedom of his country, who found that as the threat of being wrapped in the
shadows of a devastating storm at the moment of birth, had not tried to avoid at all coast of
the sad consequences that would result from disunion among the political elements which were
to be so strongly supported? This was no doubt what he did flatter the dissidents, which forced
him to put his unbridled ambition and desire to control, producing among his friends discontent
and envy. iAmigos! ... iQue pitiful abuse has been made This beautiful phrase, used without
reason rather than to be followers of those men who and Bolivar, come to have in their hands
the destiny of a nation!

In New Granada, as well as in Peru, many representations they directed the military failing
government reforms in the primitive law of the State, and, after so many great sacrifices,
after so much bloodshed and so precious for the sake of country, narrow interests, selfish view
domain, envy and resentment wrong tablets Tempers flare and ranks first in the most unjust war
the human race is between iniquity of the war itself, which the genius of evil awakens and
keeps the heart than you should join the fraternal bond of custom, language, country and family.
So, unfortunately, the triumph of independence was followed by the civil strife in America del Sud,
bitter and overwrought by measures whose spirit, whose purpose was none other than conciliation,
the welfare and strength. But man proposes and God disposes.

To the fifth congress, held in Bogota, Bolivar resigned his position as President, and then lengthy
and heated debate, by 50 votes to 24, went unheeded. This resignation was made from his hometown,
in view of the refusal, on 10 September step Bogota, vowing again before the Congress, meeting in extraordinary
session effect, and to uphold and defend there the Constitution of the Republic. In Venezuela
meanwhile had risen factions that, like Cisneros in Caracas, brought devastation everywhere.

The Constituent Congress of Peru had been met, prior to the events lately cited by 1 deg. May,
and declare that the Constitution sworn in on December 9th of the year was above zero and
with no effect, being punished by illegal and threatening the sovereignty of the people provisionally
restoring force and effect with suppression some chapters, meantime the Legislature was concerned
with forming a new one, that permitted and voted in 1823. Don Jose de Lamar, Grand Marshall, and
Don Manuel Salazar and were Barquijano elected, the first and the second as President and Vice-President
of the Republic. Such were the most notable or important in South America this year.

In 1828, following two major parties were stirred in the heart of Colombia. Those who aspired to
the best of faith in the world to make liberal changes in the law fundamental - which means,
in the eyes of his rivals, was the most on purpose to overthrow the Libertador, as well as
for those who wanted to divide the territory into three Colombian different states independent
of each other - were the first of these games. In the second Most were members of the generals,
commanders and Venezuelan officials, but all foreigners who remained in the service of Colombia
and the relatives and friends of Bolivar, that strove to uphold the integrity of the republic
created by the union of Venezuela, Quito and New Grenada. This was precisely the division attempted
by the faction contrary.

After having failed the National Convention held in Ocana on April 9 due to the findings of opinions
and political principles represented there, a gathering of people notables, formed in Bogota, signed
on June 13 an act in which they made solemn protest against any reform emanating from the Convention,
depositing the highest office of the Republic and his entire confidence in Gen. Bolivar, example
was later imitated and followed throughout latitude for the other races.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>