<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document01321</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>22728</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>728</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Le parecía que estaba viéndola, tan arrogantona y tan... y luego
con su blandura de entraña... Pero Dios no había querido que las cosas pasaran de allí; y hoy
un hijo y mañana otro, le había llevado los tres que había ido teniendo, y por último a ella,
que valía un Potosí de oro puro, y con ella, la luz y la alegría de la casona, que fenecería
«mañana u el otru» con el pobre don Celso, que ya había estado a punto de morir. Y en feneciendo
este último Ruiz de Bejos, y en cerrándose la casona o pasando a dueños desconocidos, ¿qué
sería de Tablanca ni qué vivir el suyo, sin aquel arrimo, tan viejo en el valle como el mismo
río que le atravesaba? Por eso se alegraba él tanto de mi venida. Bien podía ser permisión
de Dios. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01142</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>25318</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>660</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> It seemed I was seeing, so arrogantona and so ... and then involved
with their softness ... But God had not wanted things happen from there, and today a son, and
tomorrow another, had been the three who had been taking, and finally it worth a Potosi pure
gold, and with it the light and joy of the house, which fenecería "Tomorrow or the otru" with
the poor Don Celso, who had been about to die. And deceased Ruiz de Bejos latter, and in closing
the house or moving to unknown owners, what Tablanca would not live for his, no one came over
in the valley as old as the same river that crossed? So he was glad both of my coming. Permission
might well be of God.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>