<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document00011</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>34179</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16592</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Los ferrocarriles
y caminos, la navegacion de los lagos, las escuelas populares, los colegios, museos y bibliotecas,
los institutos de caridad, beneficencia, crédito y economía, y cuantos pueden distinguir á
una sociedad civilizada, son atendidos con gran solicitud por las autoridades y los ciudadanos,
y no hay progreso que no encuentre acogida simpática entre los Vaudenses, dignos émulos de
los Ginebrinos.

La historia de Vaud tiene mucha analogía con la de Ginebra: la misma sucesion de conquistas
y dominaciones bajo los Romanos, los Bárbaros, los Francos y Burguiñones, los condes de Saboya,
los obispos y condes del país, y los Franceses desde 1798 hasta 1814. Sinembargo, Vaud estuvo
sometido en los últimos siglos (de 1536 á 1798) á la dominacion de Berna, que no llegó á pesar
sobre Ginebra. La revolucion francesa independizó al país de Vaud respecto de Berna, haciéndolo
figurar en diversas combinaciones de Napoleon. Así, de 1798 á 1803 fué primero República lemánica;
despues hizo parte de la República rodánica (bajo la proteccion francesa), y al cabo fué Canton
independiente confederado á Suiza. Su constitucion con este carácter data de 1803, ratificada
luego por los tratados de 1815. Por lo demas, los Vaudenses han sido poco belicosos, como lo
indica la ausencia de fortificaciones en sus principales ciudades, excepto en Losana (donde
las han demolido) y en la pequeña ciudad interior de Romont.

La poblacion vaudense está muy esparcida en los campos y en pequeñas ciudades, aldeas y distritos,
circunstancia que explica bien el esmero con que están cultivadas todas las campiñas, graciosamente
salpicadas de casas de labor y alegres quintas.

El Canton está dividido en 19 circúitos político-judiciales, 60 círculos electorales con jueces
de paz, y 388 distritos ó comunes con municipalidad, aparte de las aldeas que, por su pequeñez,
carecen de personalidad política. Así, el término proporcional es de unos 500 habitantes por
distrito.

Los centros político-sociales mas importantes del Canton son diez, de los cuales siete corresponden
á la hoya del Ródano y tres á la del Aar ó el Rin. Los primeros son:

Losana, ciudad algo industrial, que cuenta cerca de 20,500 habitantes.

Vevey, centro muy fabril y comercial, con 5,500.

Morges, ciudad comercial, con 3,500.

Bex, situada en el valle del Ródano y notable por sus salinas, con 3,200.

Nyon, con 2,600, y Rolle con 1,400 en la ribera del Leman.

Villa-nueva, con 1,300, puerto importante del extremo oriental del lago y punto de escala para
el comercio que toma la via que conduce de Ginebra á Milan por el Simplon.

En las comarcas interiores solo tienen importancia algunas pequeñas ciudades: Iverdun, con
3,800 habitantes, situada en el extremo meridional del lago de Neuchâtel, notable como punto
de escala comercial y de la navegacion por vapor; Moudon, con 2,450 vecinos, una de las mas
antiguas ciudades de Suiza, y Romont, plaza fortificada (con 1,250) muy frecuentada por los
agricultores á causa de sus férias de ganado y caballos.

       *       *       *       *       *

El canton de Vaud estuvo en 1814 á punto de perder su autonomía, y para salvarla hubo de hacer
el sacrificio de algunas libertades.

Hasta 1830 conservó su primera constitucion cantonal, pero la impulsion dada al movimiento
liberal en Europa por la revolucion francesa de julio, provocó en Vaud una reforma democrática
exigida por el pueblo en masa. Con todo, la reforma de 1831 pareció mas tarde insuficiente,
y en 1845 una nueva revolucion hizo surgir la constitucion vigente hoy que es completamente
democrático-republicana[15].

[15] En 1861 se ha votado una importante reforma constitucional mas avanzada aún en el sentido
democrático.

Conforme á ella todos los hijos ó vecinos permanentes del Estado, de edad de 23 años, son ciudadanos
y ejercen la soberanía en comicios ó asambleas, ó eligiendo sus representantes. El pueblo se
ha reservado el poder constituyente y solo delega la autoridad legislativa, ejecutiva y judicial,
en los negocios generales. En los distritos que tienen ménos de 600 habitantes, ejerce el poder
administrativo y legislativo propio un Gran-Consejo, enteramente patriarcal y democrático,
que se compone de todos los jefes de familia mayores de 25 años. En los distritos de mayor
poblacion, la autoridad legislativa es confiada á un Consejo comunal de eleccion popular, compuesto
de 25 á 100 vecinos; y la administracion y policía están a cargo de una municipalidad presidida
por un sindico.

Los circúitos en que se divide el Estado son administrados por prefectos. El poder legislativo
cantonal reside en un Gran Consejo, compuesto de 195 miembros elegidos popularmente por los
círculos, el cual se reune en Losana dos veces por año en sesiones ordinarias, sin derecho
á remuneracion. Los poderes de los representantes duran cuatro años. El Gran Consejo nombra
los diputados á las Cámaras de la Confederacion y los altos funcionarios, entre estos los 9
miembros del Consejo de Estado, que ejerce el poder ejecutivo por períodos de seis años. Esos
9 consejeros deben salir del seno del Gran Consejo, y ellos nombran anualmente de entre sí
el presidente ó jefe del gobierno. El órden judicial está bajo la dependencia del cuerpo legislativo.
El Estado atiende á todas sus necesidades con un presupuesto anual de unos 550,000 pesos.

En Vaud están abolidas desde hace algunos años las penas de muerte, trabajos forzados en presidio,
vergüenza pública y confiscacion. El sistema penitenciario es enteramente análogo al de Ginebra,
y el bello panóptico de Losana es el primero que se ha fundado en Europa. Los vaudenses y demas
residentes gozan de la mas amplia libertad de religion, publicidad, instruccion, locomocion,
asociacion, etc. Excepto las vias de comunicacion y la enseñanza pública gratúita, que el Estado
sostiene, las manifestaciones de la actividad social pertenecen á la iniciativa privada. Es
tan grande el interes que allí se tiene por el progreso de la instruccion pública que casi
no hay una ciudad que no tenga su biblioteca bien surtida, su museo y muchos institutos y colecciones
importantes. Hay en el Estado cerca de 800 escuelas primarias, 10 colegios comunales y 22 escuelas
secundarias, unas clásicas y otras politécnicas. Allí se mira con particular atencion la ciencia
económica, y no ha muchos meses[16] que Losana reunió un congreso y un concurso de economistas
europeos para combinar el mejor sistema de impuestos. Es muy pequeña en el Estado la minoría
de los individuos que carecen de alguna instruccion.

[16] En 1861.

       *       *       *       *       *

De las localidades de Vaud en que tocamos, tres nos llamaron particularmente la atencion y
á ellas reduciré algunas rápidas observaciones.

Vevey, donde desembarcamos al atravesar el Leman desde Boveret, es una ciudad tan graciosa
por su estructura, su admirable situacion y sus bellos paisajes de las cercanías, como interesante
por su movimiento social. Arrancando desde la ribera misma del lago, en cuyas ondas baña sus
pequeños muelles, sus elegantes quintas, terrazas y jardines y los muros de muchas de sus casas,
se extiende primero sobre un terreno llano de poca extension y luego trepa por en medio de
viñedos y huertos hasta la colina que la domina, la cual sirve de asiento á la catedral de
San-Quintin y varias obras de un antiguo castillo, limitados por una gran terraza que sombrean
frondosos olmos y castaños. Al pié de los muros que sostienen la ciudad del lado del lago se
balancean en las ondas numerosos barquichuelos barnizados con vivos colores, y de todas partes
se levantan mil rumores llenos de poéticas armonías. El hotel mismo de las «Tres-Coronas» en
que nos alojamos, extiende sus terrazas elegantes hasta el lago, repletas de flores y arbustos,
entre otros el naranjo, el jazmin y el habano de hojas lanceoladas, plantas que crecen al aire
libre y en plena tierra, como en los climas meridionales.

Vevey, rodeada de ondulosas colinas y lindas laderas, y en cuyas cercanías son numerosos los
bellos puntos de vista y agradables paseos, ofrece uno de los mas encantadores panoramas que
se pueden imaginar, sobre todo si se la contempla desde la terraza ó la encumbrada torre de
San-Quintin, monumento gótico de estilo muy sencillo y severo. Al pié se desarrolla la ciudad
como un jardin de los mas variados contornos y colores; despues se extiende el vasto lago,
tranquilo y murmurante, lleno de luz y poesía y surcado por numerosos vapores, buques de vela
y barcas y faluchos de remos, y limitado en su márgen meridional por la barrera abrupta, rocallosa
y severa por su sombría vegetacion, que forman las montañas de Saboya ó de la antigua provincia
de Chablais. En la ribera misma, al pié de esas montañas, se ven las pequeñas localidades de
Meillerie y San-Gingolfo (donde comienza la nueva frontera de Francia), puertos dominados por
los contrafuertes y las altas cimas del Diente-de-Oche y Chaumeny. Mas léjos se levanta el
magnífico grupo nevado del Diente-del-Mediodía y detras y al S. E., en un inmenso horizonte
de colosos de granito, las inextricables y estupendas montañas que forman las cadenas del Monte-Blanco
y el San-Bernardo. Nada mas majestuoso en su género que esas montañas empinadas casi verticalmente
sobre el lago, cubiertas de bosques seculares y sombríos, con algunas praderas naturales en
las estrechas faldas, salpicadas de numerosísimos chalets ó casas de pastores que de léjos
parecen microscópicas moradas de animales alpestres.

Si se torna la mirada á derecha é izquierda, sobre la costa misma de Vevey, se ve donde quiera
un enjambre pintoresco de casas de campo y viñedos entrecortados por cercas de palos, y sostenidos
en anchos anfiteatros de muchos escalones por pretiles ó muros de construccion sólida y sencilla
que impiden los derrumbes del terreno. Aquello es una inmensa ola de sarmientos que las brisas
encrespan, y cuyo verde claro hace el mas gracioso juego con el azul turquí resplandeciente
del lago y las lejanas tintas oscuras de las montañas. Es imposible no sentirse profundamente
seducido por los encantos de ese incomparable panorama, lleno de risueña poesía, de promesas
de amor y dulce movilidad en su conjunto y sus pormenores. No es, pues, extraño que Vevey sea
en Europa una de las residencias predilectas de los extranjeros que viajan en solicitud no
de los placeres del juego, las vanidades del lujo y las emociones violentas, sino de la calma
de la naturaleza, la dulzura del clima y los goces moderados y delicados. Baste decir que Vevey
ha sido visitada con delicia por Voltaire y J. J. Rousseau, Byron y Víctor Hugo y mil viajeros
eminentes.

       *       *       *       *       *

Aquella ciudad sorprende bajo el punto de vista social, no solo al hijo de las comarcas solitarias
ó salvajes de Colombia sino tambien á los habitantes de las capitales europeas. En Europa,
en lo general, una localidad de 5,000 habilantes es un átomo; y sinembargo, son muchas las
ciudades de 25 á 30,000 vecinos que carecen de verdadera cultura. En Suiza, donde, á excepcion
de las montañas, todo es pequeño, gracioso y esmerado, las pequeñeces valen mucho y los pormenores
son todo. Es ciertamente admirable hallar en la modesta ciudad de Vevey, de poco mas de 5,500
habitantes, un gran número de institutos y todas las comodidades de la vida, que regularmente
no se encuentran sino en las grandes ciudades muy avanzadas en civilizacion. Si las condiciones
físicas del país han favorecido ese desarrollo, no puede negarse que la libertad individual
y colectiva, la bondad de las instituciones y el espíritu de independeneia y dignidad que engendra
el calvinismo, aliado á las generosas cualidades de la raza francesa, son las causas principales.

En efecto, Vevey contiene, entre otras cosas interesantes: dos bibliotecas, la una religiosa
y popular y la otra de la ciudad, con 13,000 volúmenes; un número muy considerable de colegios,
escuelas, hospitales, hospicios y otros institutos de enseñanza y beneficencia; varios pequeños
museos ó colecciones científicas, literarias y artísticas; tres círculos, con gabinetes de
lectura; muy buenos edificios para todos los servicios públicos; excelente alumbrado de gas,
muelles y mercados; centenares de talleres y pequeñas fábricas, y una multitud de sociedades
que atienden á los intereses literarios, religiosos, económicos, etc. Son muy notables entre
ellas las de mosqueteros, arcabuceros y carabineros, que se ejercitan en el tiro,--instituciones
esencialmente nacionales y muy interesantes por su carácter político-social en Suiza, donde
cada ciudadano es un soldado en reserva y las montañas hacen vivir al cazador.

Vevey no solo es un centro de primer órden en el Estado, en la produccion y exportacion de
vinos (blancos y muy suaves, del género Champaña), sino que es notable por la explotacion de
mármoles y otros objetos minerales, la fabricacion de relojes, joyas y máquinas, el comercio
de maderas y la cria de gusanos de seda. Asi, aunque por su poblacion es la segunda ciudad
vaudense, es la primera por su industria y comercio.

Entre las asociaciones libres de Vevey hay una que, ademas de ser curiosa por las tradiciones
y costumbres que mantiene, da la medida del interes que allí se toma por la agricultura, y
de la fecundidad del espíritu de asociacion: hablo de la Abadía de los Viñadores, congregacion
muy antigua de los cultivadores de viñas y propietarios mas interesados en ellas. Teniendo
por divisa las palabras Ora y trabaja, su objeto no es otro que el de favorecer la prosperidad
de las viñas y sus cultivadores. Así, todos los años envia comisionados á recorrer minuciosamente
los viñedos del distrito, y en virtud de sus informes la congregacion discierne premios á los
cultivadores que mas se distinguen y toma las medidas necesarias para mejorar el cultivo, ensanchar
el comercio de vinos veveisinos y extirpar toda enfermedad ó mal que pueda atacar á los viñedos.
No es ménos curiosa la Fiesta de los viñadores, que estos celebran cinco ó seis veces en cada
siglo, en las épocas de grandes cosechas,--fiesta que, según nos contaron, ofrece las mas singulares
escenas de costumbres, y tiene cierto carácter pagano que la hace muy original en la época
presente.

El sol de la tarde brillaba con melancólica hermosura sobre las crestas de las montañas jurásicas
y el lago y las campiñas riberanas, cuando nos embarcamos en el vapor Aigle y nos dirigimos
hácia el puerto de Ouchy, costeando la ribera setentrional. Las brisas rizaban las ondas del
lago, resplandeciente y lleno de murmullos deliciosos, como agitaban las guirnaldas de tupidos
sarmientos en los viñedos de la costa; y en el fondo de ellos, á 100 metros de distancia, vimos
destacarse cinco ó seis pueblecitos ó aldeas llenos de gracia en sus pormenores, y como descendiendo
de sus suaves colinas en pintoresco desórden, para bañar en el lago los festones y las terrazas
de sus alegres casitas. Cada uno de esos pueblecitos parece el original de uno de esos pesebres
ó nacimientos tan populares en las sociedades españolas en el mes de Navidad.

Ouchy, pequeño caserío de la ribera, sombreado por hermosas arboledas y rodeado de quintas
elegantes, jardines y parques, es el puerto de Losana. Allí mismo, ó á muy corta distancia,
existió la antigua Lausanium, destruida en el año de 563 por el choque violento de las aguas
del lago, producido por la caída de una montaña en la ribera opuesta. Los habitantes, aterrados,
buscaron el sitio mas alto de la comarca vecina y en él fundaron á Losana, con increíble capricho,
á tres kilómetros de distancia de Ouchy. Un ómnibus nos condujo inmediatamente á esa ciudad,
por un amplio camino, que en realidad es una inmensa calle orillada por quintas suntuosas y
terrazas, parques de espeso follaje y jardines cargados de perfumes.

La ciudad, cortada en el fondo por dos arroyos que se juntan en profundas ramblas, demora sobre
tres colinas y sus faldas interiores y estrechos vallecitos intermedios. Así sus formas son
tan irregulares y complicadas que llegan hasta la extravagancia. Sus calles, casi todas estrechas,
oscuras, tortuosas y muy pendientes, forman un laberinto de cuestas que obligan á subir ó bajar
en todo caso. No ha mucho la comunicacion entre las calles de las tres colinas era muy lenta
y penosa; pero luego el magnífico puente Pichard (que reposa sobre una doble arcada y mide
180 metros de longitud, de una colina á otra), algunas calles que faldean esas colinas y los
hermosos caminos de ruedas y paseos exteriores, han mejorado mucho la ciudad y facilitado el
movimiento de las gentes y de los carruajes.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07508</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>479835</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15040</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Railroads and roads,
the navigation of the lakes, popular schools, colleges, museums and libraries charitable institutes,
charities, credit and economy, and few can distinguish a civilized society, are treated with
great care by the authorities and citizens and no progress can not find sympathetic reception among
Vaudenses, worthy rivals of the Genevans.

The history of Vaud has much analogy to Geneva: the same succession of conquests and domination
under the Romans, Barbarians, and Burguiñones Franks, the counts of Savoy, Bishops and earls of
the country and the French from 1798 to 1814. HOWEVER, Vaud was subject in recent centuries (from
1536 to 1798) to the domination of Berne, who weighed on Geneva. The French Revolution to the
country of Vaud independence for Berne, making appear in various combinations of Napoleon. Thus,
from 1798 to 1803 was the first Republic of Geneva; later became part of the Republic Rodan (under
French protection), and Canton was held Confederate independent Switzerland. Its constitution with
this character dates from 1803, ratified then by the treaties of 1815. For the rest, the Vaudenses
have been very bellicose, as indicates the absence of fortifications in its major cities, except
in Lausanne (where they have been demolished) and the small inland town of Romont.

Vaudense population is very scattered in fields and small towns, villages and districts, circumstance
that explains well the dedication with which they are cultivated all the fields, graciously dotted
with farmhouses and villas happy.

The Canton is divided into 19 political-judicial circuits, 60 electoral circles judges peace, and
388 common or municipal districts, apart from the villages, by their smallness, lack of political
personality.

Thus, the proportional term is about 500 inhabitants per district.

The socio-political centers of Canton most important are ten, of which
seven correspond to the valley of the Rhone and three to the Aare
or the Rhine The first are:

Lausanne, rather industrial city, which
has about 20.500 inhabitants.

Vevey, very industrial and commercial center, with 5.500.

Morges, commercial city, with 3.500.

Bex, located in the Rhone Valley and noted for its salt mines, with 3.200.

Nyon, with 2.600 and 1.400 Rolle on the banks of Lake Geneva.

Villanueva, with 1.300, major port in the eastern end of the lake
and stopping point for trade that takes the road from Geneva to Milan
by the Simplon.

       

In the inland areas are important only some small towns: Iverdun with
3.800 inhabitants, situated at the southern end of Lake Neuchâtel,
notable as a commercial scale and steam navigation, Moudon, with 2.450
residents, one of the most ancient cities of Switzerland and Romont,
fortified (with 1,250) is frequented by farmers of their annual cattle
and horses.

* * * * *

The canton of Vaud in 1814 was about to lose its autonomy and had
to do to save the sacrifice of some freedoms.

Until 1830 cantonal retained its first constitution, but given the movement's drive liberal in Europe
by the French revolution of July resulted in Vaud democratic reform required by the people en
masse. However, the reform of 1831 later seemed insufficient and in 1845 a new revolution gave rise
to the constitution that is completely relevant today Democratic-Republican [15].

[15] In 1861 was voted a major constitutional reform even more advanced in the sense democratic.

According
to her all the children or permanent residents of the State, age 23, are citizens and exercise sovereignty
in elections or assemblies, or by choosing their representatives. The people has reserved the constitutional
power and only delegated legislative authority, executive and judicial
general business.

In districts with fewer than 600 people exercise power own administrative and legislative Grand-Council,
entirely patriarchal and democratic consisting of all heads of household over 25 years. In
most districts population, the legislative authority is entrusted to a popular election Communal
Council composed 25 to 100 neighbors, and the administration and enforcement are chaired by
a municipality by a trustee.

Circuits that divide the state are administered by prefects. Legislative power cantonal resides
in a grand council, composed of 195 members popularly elected by the circles, which meets in Lausanne
twice a year in ordinary sessions without the right remuneration.

The credentials of representatives last four years. The Great Council appointed Members of the Houses
of the Confederation and senior officials, among them the 9 Members of the Council of State, which
exercises executive power for six years. These 9 directors must leave within the Grand Council,
and they appoint annually from among themselves the president or head of government. The court
order is under the jurisdiction of the legislature. The State attends to all your needs with an
annual budget of about 550.000 pesos.

In Vaud are abolished in recent years the death penalty, forced labor in prison, public embarrassment
and confiscation. The prison system is entirely analogous to Geneva and the beautiful Losana Panopticon
is the first to be founded in Europe. The vaudenses and other Residents enjoy the full freedom of
religion, advertising, instruction, locomotion association, etc. Except for the roads and free
public education that the State holds, the manifestations of social activity belong to the private
sector.

Is so great was the interest that there is progress in public education
almost there is a city that has its well-stocked library, museum and
many colleges and libraries important.

       There are about 800 state elementary schools, 10 community colleges
and 22 schools secondary, some classical and other polytechnics.

There is viewed with particular attention science economic, and not many months [16] that
met Lausanne congress and a competition economist to combine the
best European tax system.

It's very small minority in the State of individuals without any instruction.

[16] in 1861.

* * * * *

Vaud localities we play, three of us and drew particular attention them to reduce some quick observations.

Vevey,
which disembarked to cross the Leman from Boveret, is a city so funny its structure, its admirable
situation and beautiful scenery nearby, and interesting by social movement. Starting from the
bank of the lake, whose waves bathes small springs, elegant villas, terraces and gardens and
walls of many of their homes, first extends on a plain low extension and then climbs amid vineyards
and orchards to the hill that dominates, which serves as a seat at the Cathedral Saint-Quentin
and various works of an ancient castle, limited by a large terrace
shaded leafy elm and chestnut trees.

At the foot of the walls that hold the city side of the lake bob in the waves many little boats
painted in bright colors, and everywhere rise a thousand rumors full of poetic harmony. The
hotel itself of the "Three-Crowns" in we stayed, extends its elegant terraces to the lake,
filled with flowers and shrubs, including orange, jasmine and the cigar of lanceolate leaves,
plants that grow in the air Free and open ground, and in southern climates.

Vevey, surrounded by beautiful rolling hills and slopes, and near which there are many beautiful views
and pleasant walks, offers one of the most enchanting panoramas you can imagine, especially if
it is seen from the terrace or the soaring tower Saint-Quentin, a gothic monument of simple
and severe style. When walking the city develops like a garden of the most varied contours and
colors, then stretches the vast lake Whispering quiet, full of light and poetry, and crossed
by numerous steamers, sailing vessels feluccas and boats and oars, and limited in its southern
margin by the barrier abrupt rocky and severe for its dark vegetation, which form the mountains of Savoy
or in the former province the Alps. In the same bank at the foot of these mountains, are the small
towns And San-Gingolfo Meillerie (which begins the new frontier of France), dominated by ports
buttresses and the high peaks of the Oche-Tooth and Chaumeny. Farther rises Tooth magnificent
snowy group-of-Midi and back and the SE, in a vast horizon colossi
of granite, the inextricable and stunning mountains that form the
chain of Mont Blanc and the Saint-Bernard.

Nothing is more majestic in its genre that these almost vertically steep mountains on the lake,
covered with ancient forests and gloomy, with few natural grasslands in narrow skirts, interspersed
with numerous villas or houses of shepherds from afar microscopic animals seem alpine dwellings.

If
it gets the look right and left, on the coast itself in Vevey, is everywhere a swarm picturesque
cottages and vineyards interspersed with fences of sticks, and sustained in broad arenas of
many steps for railings or walls simple and robust construction preventing the collapse of the
land. That is a huge wave of shoots the breeze Curling, whose green makes the most funny game
with bright turquoise the lake and distant mountains dark ink. It is impossible not to feel deeply
seduced by the charms of the incomparable panorama, full of smiling poetry, promises sweet
love and mobility as a whole and its details. It is not therefore surprising that it Vevey in
Europe one of the favorite residences of foreigners who travel in order not the pleasures of gambling,
luxury vanities and violent emotions, but calm of nature, mild climate and moderate pleasures
and delicate.

       Suffice to say, Vevey has been viewed with delight by Voltaire and
JJ Rousseau, Byron and Victor Hugo and a thousand travelers eminent.

* * * * *

Surprising that city under the social point of view, not only the lonely son of the regions wild or
Colombia but also to the inhabitants of the European capitals. In Europe, in general, a town
of 5.000 habilantes is an atom, and HOWEVER, many cities, 25 to 30.000 residents who lack true
culture. In Switzerland, where, except the mountains, everything is small, funny and attentive,
the little things and details are worth much are everything. It is certainly remarkable to
find in the modest town of Vevey, a little more than 5.500 inhabitants, a large number of institutes
and all the comforts of life, which regularly are not in big cities
but very advanced civilization.

If conditions country's physical development have favored that can not be denied that individual
freedom and collectively, the goodness of the institutions and the spirit of dignity and engendering
independeneia Calvinism, allied to the generous qualities of the French race, are the main causes.

Indeed,
Vevey contains, among other interesting things: two libraries, a religious and popular and
one of the city, with 13,000 volumes, a considerable number of schools, schools, hospitals,
hospices and other educational institutions and charities, several small museums or scientific
collections, literature and art, three circles, with cabinets reading, very good building for
all public services, excellent gas lighting, docks and markets, hundreds of workshops and small
factories, and a multitude of companies serving literary interests, religious, economic. Very
notable among including those of musketeers, musketeers and police,
who train in the shot, - institutions essentially national and interesting
for their political-social in Switzerland, where Every citizen is
a soldier in reserve and the mountains make their living by hunting.

Vevey is not only a first-order center in the state, in the production and export of wine (white
and very soft, gender champagne), but is notable for the exploitation of marbles and other
objects minerals, manufacture of watches, jewelry, machinery, trade
timber and the rearing of silkworms.

So, although its population is the second city vaudense, is the first in its industry and commerce.

Among
the free associations of Vevey is one which, besides being curious traditions and customs
that maintains a measure of the interest therein is taken by agriculture and fecundity of the
spirit of partnership I speak of the Abbey of the tenants, Congregation very old vineyard
growers and owners more interested in them. Taking Pray for currency words and works, his object
is not other than to promote prosperity of the vineyards and growers. So, every year send commissioners
to go carefully vineyards in the district, and by virtue of their reports to the congregation
discerning awards most distinguished cultivators and takes steps to improve the crop, expand veveisinos
wine trade and remove any disease or illness that can attack the vines. No less curious is the Feast
of the tenants, that they held five or six times each century, in times of great vintages, -
party, as we were told, offers the most unique genre scenes, and has some pagan character that makes
it very original at the time present.

The afternoon sun shone on the melancholy beauty of mountain peaks Jurassic and the lake and riparian
meadows, when we embarked on the steamer and headed Aigle towards the port of Ouchy, coasting
along the shore setentrional. Breezes curling waves lake, bright and full of delicious murmurs,
like agitated dense wreaths vines in the vineyards of the coast and in the bottom of them, at
100 feet away, saw stand five or six towns or villages full of grace in detail, and as descending
of rolling hills in picturesque disorder, to bathe in the lake the scallops and terraces their cheerful
houses. Each of these villages seems the original of one of those cribs birth or as popular in
the Spanish companies in the month of Christmas.

Ouchy, a small village on the banks, shaded by beautiful trees and surrounded by villas elegant
gardens and parks, is the port of Lausanne. There, or at very close range There was the old
Lausanium destroyed in the year 563 by the violent impact of water Lake, produced by the collapse
of a mountain on the opposite bank. The residents, terrified, sought the highest place of the neighboring
county and he founded to Lausanne, with incredible fad, to three miles away from Ouchy. A bus took
us immediately to that city, by a wide road, which is actually a huge street edged by sumptuous
villas terraces, parks and gardens of thick foliage laden with perfumes.

The city, cut into the bottom of two streams that come together in deep gullies, delay on three
hills and inland slopes and narrow valleys in between. So forms are so irregular and complicated
that reach the extravagance. Its streets, almost all narrow dark, winding and very steep, forming
a maze of hills that require up or down in any case. It has not much communication between the
streets of the three hills was very slow and painful, but then the magnificent bridge Pichard
(which sits on a double arch and measures 180 meters long, one hill to another), some streets
that skirted these hills and beautiful walking paths and outdoor wheels, the city has greatly
improved and facilitated movement of people and carriages.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>