<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document00354</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>10101</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>823</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>
Tal vez hubiera tenido que ceder su intrépido defensor Segurola, sino hubiese aparecido Reseguin,
que venia á socorrerle con 5,000 hombres, llenos de entusiasmo por un triunfo que acababan
de reportar en Yaco.

Tantos trabajos habian postrado á este incansable oficial, que por primera vez desde su salida
de Montevideo, se veia forzado á interrumpir sus tareas. Aun no habia convalecido de una grave
enfermedad que le habia asaltado, cuando llega á la Paz la noticia de una fuerza que Tupac-Catari
organizaba en las Peñas. Débil, y extenuado por sus padecimientos, Reseguin halla en su alma
vigor bastante para reanimar sus fuerzas abatidas. Empuña su espada, alcanza á los rebeldes,
los derrota, y cual otro Mariscal de Sajonia en la batalla de Fontenoi, entra al pueblo de
las Peñas, cargado en hombros de sus soldados.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09333</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>892647</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>792</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Maybe
it would have had to give his fearless advocate Segurola, but had appeared Reseguin, who came to
his assistance with 5.000 men, full of enthusiasm for a victory that ended reporting in Yaco.

Many
jobs had ridden to this indefatigable officer, who for the first
time since his exit Montevideo, was forced to interrupt their work.

Although there was no recovering from a serious disease that he had assaulted, when it comes to
the news of a peace force that Tupac-Catari organized in the Rocks. Weak and exhausted by his
sufferings, is in his soul Reseguin force enough to revive their forces shot down. He wields his
sword, reaches to the rebels, The defeat, which another Marshal of Saxony at the battle of Fontenoi,
enters the village Peñas, loaded on the shoulders of its soldiers.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>