<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>688020</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16339</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Siguió ella adelante en su relato, no queriendo insistir contra esta muralla inconmovible.

--Mi padre también fué italiano de origen, pero por su nacimiento era austriaco... Además,
le inspiraban un entusiasmo ciego los Imperios germánicos. Era de los que abominan de su origen
y ven todas las virtudes en los pueblos del Norte.

Inventor de maravillosos negocios, financiero proyectista de empresas colosales, había pasado
su existencia asediando á los directores de los grandes establecimientos bancarios y haciendo
antesala en los ministerios. Eternamente en vísperas de combinaciones sorprendentes que debían
proporcionarle docenas de millones, vivía en una pobreza lujosa, yendo de hotel en hotel, siempre
los mejores, con su mujer y su hija única.

--Tú ignoras esa vida, Ulises; tú procedes de una familia tranquila y con dinero. Los tuyos
no han conocido la existencia de aparato en los «Palace», ni tampoco los apuros para liquidar
la nueva cuenta del mes, logrando que la incorporen á las de los meses anteriores un crédito
sin límites.

Ella había visto de niña llorar á su madre en el lujoso departamento del hotel, mientras hablaba
el padre con aspecto de iluminado, anunciando para la semana próxima una ganancia de un millón.
La esposa, convencida por la facundia de su grande hombre, acababa secando sus lágrimas, empolvando
su rostro y adornándose con sus perlas y sus blondas de problemático valor. Luego descendía
al magnífico hall, lleno de perfumes, de susurros de conversaciones y gemidos discretos de
violines, para tomar el té con sus amistades del hotel, formidables millonarias de los dos
hemisferios, que sospechaban vagamente la existencia de una enfermedad llamada pobreza, pero
eran incapaces de concebir que pudiese atacar á las personas de su mundo.

Mientras tanto, la niña jugaba en el jardín del «Palace» con otras niñas vestidas y adornadas
como muñecas lujosas y frágiles, cada una de las cuales pesaba varios millones.

--Yo he sido compañera de infancia--continuó Freya--de mujeres que son célebres por su riqueza
en Nueva York, en París, en Londres... Me he tuteado con grandes millonarias que hoy son, por
sus casamientos, duquesas y hasta princesas de sangre real. Muchas han pasado junto á mí sin
reconocerme, y yo no he dicho nada, sabiendo que la igualdad de la niñez no es mas que un vago
recuerdo...

Así había llegado á ser mujer. Varios negocios casuales del padre les permitían continuar esta
existencia de pobreza brillante y costosa. El proyectista consideraba necesario tal aparato
para sus futuros negocios. La vida en los hoteles más caros, el automóvil por meses, los trajes
de grandes costureros para la mujer y la niña, los veraneos en las playas de moda, el patinaje
invernal en Suiza, eran para él una especie de uniforme de respetabilidad que le mantenía en
el mundo de los poderosos, permitiéndole entrar en todas partes.

--Esta existencia me moldeó para siempre y ha influido en el resto de mi vida. El deshonor,
la muerte, todo lo creo preferible á la miseria... Yo, que no temo los peligros, me siento
cobarde al pensar en la pobreza.

Moría la madre, crédula y sensual, fatigada de esperar una fortuna sólida que no llegaba nunca.
Ella seguía con su padre, siendo la señorita que vive entre hombres, de hotel en hotel, algo
masculina en sus ademanes; la virgen á medias, que lo sabe todo, no se asusta de nada, guarda
ferozmente la integridad de su sexo, calculando lo que puede valer, y adora la riqueza como
la divinidad más poderosa de la tierra.

Al morir el padre, viéndose sin otra fortuna que sus trajes y unas cuantas joyas artísticas
de escaso precio, decidía fríamente su destino.

--En nuestro mundo no hay más virtud que la del dinero. Las muchachas del populacho se dan
con menos facilidad que una señorita habituada al lujo, teniendo por única fortuna el conocimiento
del piano, del baile y de unos cuantos idiomas... Entregamos nuestro cuerpo como si cumpliésemos
una función material, sin rubor y sin pena. Es un simple negocio. Lo único importante es conservar
la antigua vida con todas sus comodidades... no descender.

Pasó con precipitación sobre los recuerdos de este período de su existencia. Un conocido de
su padre, viejo negociante de Viena, había sido el primero. Luego sintió el aletazo romántico,
al que no escapan las hembras más frías y positivas. Había creído enamorarse de un oficial
holandés, un Apolo rubio que patinaba con ella en Saint-Moritz. Este había sido su único esposo.
Al fin le aburría la modorra colonial de Batavia, y tornaba á Europa, rompiendo su matrimonio,
para reanudar la existencia en los grandes hoteles, pasando de las estaciones invernales á
las playas de lujo.

¡Ay, el dinero!... En ningún plano social se podía reconocer su poderío como en el que ella
habitaba. Encontró en los «Palace» mujeres de ademanes soldadescos y manos groseras, fumando
á todas horas, con los pies en el respaldo de una silla, mostrando la superficie posterior
de sus muslos en alto y el triángulo blanco de sus enaguas tendidas sobre el asiento. Eran
semejantes á las rameras de los grandes puertos que esperan á la puerta de sus tugurios. ¿Cómo
las dejaban vivir allí?... Sin embargo, los hombres se inclinaban ante ellas como esclavos
ó las perseguían suplicantes. Hablaban con unción de los millones heredados de sus padres,
de sus formidables riquezas de origen industrial, que les habían permitido comprar un marido
noble, entregándose luego á sus gustos de maritornes andariegas.

--No he tenido suerte... Soy demasiado altiva para triunfar. Los hombres me encuentran de mal
carácter, discutidora y nerviosa. Tal vez he nacido para ser una madre de familia... ¡Quién
sabe si hubiese sido otra de vivir en tu país!

Su veneración religiosa por el dinero tomó al decir esto un acento de odio. Las jóvenes pobres
y bien educadas, si sentían miedo á la miseria, no tenían otro recurso que la prostitución.
Les faltaba la dote, requisito indispensable en muchos pueblos civilizados para ser mujer honrada
y constituir un hogar.

¡Maldita pobreza!... Había pesado sobre su vida como una fatalidad. Los hombres que se mostraban
buenos al principio se envenenaban después, volviéndose egoístas é ingratos. El doctor Talberg,
á la vuelta de América, la había abandonado para casarse con una joven fea y rica, hija de
un negociante, senador de Hamburgo. Otros habían explotado igualmente su juventud, tomando
su parte de alegría y de belleza para unirse luego con mujeres que sólo tenían el atractivo
de una gran fortuna.

Ella había acabado por odiarlos á todos, deseando su exterminio, exasperándose al pensar que
los necesitaba para vivir y nunca podría libertarse de esta esclavitud. Para ser independiente,
se había dedicado al teatro.

--He bailado, he cantado; pero mis éxitos fueron siempre femeniles. Los hombres venían detrás
de mí, deseando á la hembra y riéndose de la artista. Además, ¡la vida de los bastidores!...
¡El mercado de blancas con un nombre en el cartel!... ¡Qué explotación!...

El deseo de emanciparse la había arrastrado hacia su amiga la doctora, aceptando sus proposiciones.
Le pareció más honorífico servir á un gran Estado, ser un funcionario secreto, laborando en
la sombra por su grandeza. Además, le sedujo al principio lo novelesco del trabajo, las aventuras
de las misiones arriesgadas, la orgullosa consideración de que con sus espionajes tejía la
trama del porvenir, preparando la historia futura.

También aquí había tropezado desde los primeros pasos con la esclavitud sexual. Su belleza
era un instrumento para sondear las conciencias, una llave para abrir secretos; y esta servidumbre
resultaba peor que las anteriores, por ser irredimible. Había conseguido apartarse con facilidad
de su vida de viajera amorosa y de mujer de teatro; pero el que entraba en el «servicio secreto»
ya no podía salir de él. Se aprendían demasiadas cosas, se llegaba lentamente á la comprensión
de importantes misterios. El agente quedaba prisionero de sus funciones: era un emparedado,
y con cada acto nuevo añadía una nueva piedra al muro que le separaba de la libertad.

--Tú sabes el resto de mi vida--continuó--. La obligación de obedecer á la doctora, de seducir
á los hombres para arrancarles sus secretos, me hizo odiarlos con una agresividad mortal...
Pero llegaste tú, ¡tú, que eres bueno y generoso, que me buscaste con una simplicidad entusiasta,
lo mismo que un adolescente, haciéndome retroceder en mi existencia, como si aún estuviese
en los diez y ocho años y me viera cortejada por primera vez!... Además, tú no eres egoísta.
Te das con noble entusiasmo. Creo que, de conocernos en la primera juventud, no me habrías
abandonado para ser rico casándote con otra... Me resistí á ser tuya porque te amaba y no quería
hacerte daño... Después, el mandato de mis superiores y mi pasión me hicieron olvidar estos
escrúpulos... Me entregué; fuí la «mujer fatal» de siempre: te traje desgracia... ¡Ulises!
¡amor mío!... Olvidemos: de nada sirve recordar el pasado. Conozco bien tu alma, y al verme
en peligro acudo á ella. ¡Sálvame! ¡llévame contigo!...

Como estaba de pie frente á él, le bastó levantar las manos para colocarlas sobre sus hombros,
iniciando el principio de un abrazo.

Ferragut permaneció insensible á la caricia. Su inmovilidad repelía estas súplicas. Freya había
rodado mucho por el mundo, á través de vergonzosas aventuras, y sabría librarse por su propio
esfuerzo, sin necesidad de complicarle nuevamente en sus enredos. La historia que acababa de
relatar no era para él mas que un tejido de engaños.

--¡Todo falso!--dijo con voz sorda--. No te creo, no te creeré nunca... Cada vez que nos vemos
me cuentas una nueva historia... ¿Quién eres? ¿Cuándo dirás la verdad, toda la verdad de una
vez?... ¡Embustera!

Ella, insensible á los insultos, siguió hablando de su porvenir angustiosamente, como si se
viese rodeada de misteriosos peligros.

--¿Dónde iré si tú me abandonas?... Si me quedo en España, continúo bajo la dominación de la
doctora. No puedo volver á los Imperios donde pasé mi vida; todos los caminos están cerrados,
y en aquellas tierras renacería mi esclavitud... Tampoco puedo ir á Francia ó Inglaterra: tengo
miedo á mi pasado. Cualquiera de mis hazañas anteriores bastaría para que me fusilasen: no
merezco menos... Además, me inspira temor la venganza de los míos. Conozco los procedimientos
del «servicio» cuando necesita deshacerse de un agente incómodo que está en tierra enemiga.
El mismo lo denuncia: comete voluntariamente una torpeza, hace que se extravíen unos documentos,
envía una carta comprometedora con falsa dirección, para que caiga en manos de las autoridades
del país. ¿Qué haré si tú no me socorres?... ¿Dónde podré rufugiarme?...

Ulises se decidió á contestar, apiadado de su desesperación. El mundo es grande: podía ir á
vivir en una república de América.

Ella no aceptó el consejo. Había pensado lo mismo; pero le daba miedo el porvenir incierto.

--Soy pobre: apenas tengo con qué pagar mi viaje... El «servicio» retribuye bien al principio.
Después, como nos tiene seguros á causa de nuestro pasado, sólo da lo necesario para vivir
con cierto desahogo. ¿Qué voy á, hacer en aquellas tierras?... ¿Debo pasar el resto de mi existencia
vendiéndome á cambio del pan?... No quiero: ¡antes morir!

La desesperada afirmación de su pobreza hizo sonreír burlonamente á Ferragut. Miró el collar
de perlas eternamente acostado en la admirable almohadilla de su pecho, las gruesas esmeraldas
de sus orejas, los brillantes que chisporroteaban fríamente en sus manos. Ella adivinó su pensamiento,
y la idea de vender estas joyas le produjo una inquietud mayor que los terrores que le infundía
el porvenir.

--Tú no sabes lo que esto representa para mí--añadió--. Es mi uniforme, mi blasón, el salvoconducto
que me permite sostenerme en el mundo de mi juventud. Las mujeres que vamos solas por la tierra
necesitamos las alhajas para seguir nuestro camino sin obstáculos. Los gerentes del hotel se
humanizan y sonríen ante su brillo. Quien las posee no inspira desconfianza, aunque tarde en
pagar la cuenta de la semana... Los empleados de las fronteras se muestran galantes: no hay
pasaporte más poderoso. Las señoras altivas se ablandan con su centelleo á la hora del té en
los halls donde una no conoce á nadie... ¡Lo que yo he sufrido para conseguirlas!... Arrostraría
el hambre antes de venderlas. Con ellas se es alguien: puede una persona no tener una moneda
en el bolsillo y entrar donde entran los más ricos, viviendo como ellos...

No aceptaba el consejo. Era como si á un guerrero hambriento le propusiesen entregar sus armas
en país enemigo á cambio de pan. Una vez la necesidad satisfecha, quedaría prisionero; se vería
envilecido, igualándose con los miserables que horas antes recibían sus golpes. Ella arrostraba
todos los peligros y sufrimientos antes que despojarse del casco y el escudo, símbolos de su
estirpe superior. El traje de más de un año, las botinas fatigadas, la ropa interior con desgarrones
mal compuestos, no le entristecían en los momentos difíciles. Lo importante era poseer un sombrero
de moda y conservar el gabán de pieles, el collar de perlas, las esmeraldas, los brillantes,
toda la armadura honorífica y gloriosa, dentro de la cual quería morir.

Su mirada pareció apiadarse de la ignorancia del marino, que se atrevía á proponerle tales
absurdos.

--Es imposible, Ulises... Llévame contigo. En el mar es donde puedo vivir más segura. Los submarinos
no me dan miedo. Las gentes se los imaginan numerosos y apretados como las piedras de un pavimento,
pero sólo un buque entre mil recibe sus ataques... Además, contigo no temo nada: si nuestro
destino es perecer en el mar, moriríamos juntos.

Se hizo insinuante y seductora, avanzando las manos sobre los hombros de él, tirando de su
cuello con un apasionamiento que equivalía á un abrazo. Su boca, al hablar, se aproximó á la
del marino. Los labios se arquearon iniciando la redonda caricia de un beso.

--¿Tan mal vivirías con Freya?... ¿No te acuerdas ya de nuestro pasado?... ¿Es que ahora soy otra?

Ulises se acordaba, efectivamente, del pasado, y empezó á reconocer que este recuerdo era demasiado
vivo. Llegaron hasta él, como lejanas melodías voluptuosas y medio olvidadas, las ráfagas de
una carne bien oliente, despertando su memoria sexual. El contacto de las ocultas redondeces,
tibias y firmes, que se apretaban contra su pecho sin perder la turgente dureza, evocó en la
imaginación de Ferragut una serie vertiginosa de escenas de amor. La castidad observada en
los últimos tiempos á causa de sus dolorosas preocupaciones le atormentó ahora como un suplicio.

Ella, que seguía esta revolución con ojos astutos, adivinándola en las contracciones de su
rostro, sonrió triunfadora, pegando su boca á la de él. Estaba segura de su poder... Y reprodujo
el beso del Acuario, aquel beso que estremecía la espalda del marino, haciéndole vacilar sobre
sus piernas.

Pero cuando se entregaba con más abandono á esta succión dominadora, se sintió repelida, disparada
por un manotón brutal, semejante al puñetazo que la había lanzado sobre los almohadones al
principio de la entrevista.

Alguien se había interpuesto entre los dos, á pesar de que estaban abrazados estrechamente.

El capitán, que empezaba á perder la conciencia de sus actos, lo mismo que un náufrago, descendiendo
y descendiendo á través de las capas vibrantes de un placer sin límites, vió de pronto la cara
de Esteban difunto, con los ojos vidriosos fijos en él. Más allá vió igualmente una imagen
de triste esfumamiento: Cinta que lloraba, como si sus lágrimas fuesen las únicas que podían
caer sobre el cadáver desgarrado del hijo.

--¡Ah, no!... ¡no!

El mismo quedó sorprendido de su voz. Fué un rugido de bestia herida, un aullar seco de desesperado
que se retuerce en el tormento.

Freya, tambaleándose bajo el rudo empujón, intentó aproximarse otra vez á él, enlazarse de
nuevo en sus brazos, repetir su beso imperioso.

--¡Amor mío!... ¡amor mío!...

No pudo seguir. La tremenda mano volvió á repelerla, pero tan violentamente, que fué á dar
de cabeza contra los cojines del diván.

Tembló la puerta con un rudo tirón que hizo abrir sus dos hojas á la vez, sacando el pestillo
de la cerradura.

La mujer, tenaz en sus deseos, se levantó prontamente, sin reparar en el dolor de la caída.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05479</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>2204</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>14518</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

She went on in his story, not wanting to insist against the unyielding wall.

- My father was born Italian but was Austrian by birth ... In addition, blind enthusiasm inspired
him Germanic Empires.

Was among those who abhor its origin and see all the virtues in the people of the North.

Inventor of wonderful business, financial planner colossal companies had spent its existence to
plague the directors of large banking institutions and making precursor in the ministries. Forever
on the verge of striking combinations to be provide tens of millions,
luxurious living in poverty, going from hotel to hotel, if the best,
with his wife and only child.

- You ignore that life, Ulysses, you
come from a quiet family and money.

Yours have not known the existence of device in the "Palace", nor the rush to settle the new
account of the month, making the incorporation to the previous months credit without limits.

She
had seen a child mourn his mother's apartment in the luxurious hotel, talking the father-like
glow, announcing next week a gain of one million.

The wife, convinced by the eloquence of a great man, had dried her tears, powdering his face adorned
with pearls and lace their problematical value. Then down the great hall, full of perfumes, whispers
and moans discrete talks Violins, for tea with friends in the hotel, millionaire formidable of the
two hemispheres, which vaguely suspected the existence of a disease called poverty, but were
unable to conceive that could attack people in their world.

Meanwhile, the child played in the garden of the "Palace" with other girls dressed and adorned
as luxurious and fragile wrists, each of which weighed several million.

- I have been a childhood companion - continued Freya - of women who
are famous for their wealth New York, Paris, London ... I have familiarly
with big millionaire today are, their marriages, duchesses and princesses
of royal blood to.

Many have passed by me without recognize, and I have not said anything, knowing that the equality
of children is nothing more than a vague remember ...

This had come to be women. Several of the parent business casual is allowed to continue existence
of poverty shiny and expensive.

The designer considered necessary such apparatus for their future business. Life in the more expensive
hotels, car for months, costumes large sewing for women and girls, the summers on the beaches
of fashion, skating winter in Switzerland, were for him a kind of uniform of respectability that
kept him the world of the powerful, allowing you to enter everywhere.

- The existence forever shaped me and influenced the rest of my life.

Dishonor, death, all I think preferable to the misery ... I fear no danger, I feel cowardly
to think of poverty.

The mother died, credulous and sensual, tired of waiting for a solid fortune never came. She remained
with her father, being the lady who lives among men, from hotel to hotel, something male in
his manner, the mean virgin, who knows everything, is not afraid of anything, save fiercely integrity
of their sex, calculating what it may be, and love of wealth as the most powerful god of the
earth.

The death of the father, seeing no other fortune than his clothes
and a few artistic gems low price, coldly decided his fate.

- In
our world there is more virtue than the money.

The girls are given the populace less easily than a young lady accustomed to luxury, having
knowledge of only fortune the piano, dancing and a few languages ??... We deliver our body as if cumpliésemos
a material function, without shame and without regret. It's a simple business. The only important
thing is to keep the old life with all its amenities ... relegation.

Hastily passed on memories of this period of its existence. A known his father, an old merchant
of Vienna, had been the first. Then gives flight felt romantic, that females can not escape colder
and positive. He had believed in love with an officer Dutch, a blond Apolo skated with her
in Saint-Moritz. This had been her only husband. At last I was bored the Batavian colonial slumber,
and around Europe, breaking her marriage to resume life in the big hotels, from winter resorts
to luxury beaches.

Oh, money! ... In any social background could recognize their power and in which she lived.
Found in the "Palace" women of rude hand gestures and soldierly, smoking at all hours, his feet
on the back of a chair, showing the rear surface of her thighs up and the white triangle of
her petticoats lying on the seat. Were similar to the whores of the major ports waiting at
the door of their slums. How let them live there? ... However, the men bowed before them as slaves
or the chase pleading. They spoke with reverence of millions inherited from their parents,
riches of its formidable industrial origin, which had enabled them to buy a husband noble,
pass on to their tastes andariegas Maritornes.

- I have not had any luck ... I'm too proud to succeed. Men find me bad character, argumentative,
nervous. Perhaps I was born to be a mother ... Who know if it was another to live in your country!

His
religious veneration for the money it took to say in a tone of hatred.

Poor girls and well educated, if they were afraid to misery, they had no other recourse than prostitution.
They lacked the dowry, a prerequisite in many civilized women to be honored and build a home.

Poverty
Damn! ... There was heavy on his life as a fatality. The men who showed poisoned good at first then
becoming selfish and ungrateful.

Dr. Talberg, Back from America, had abandoned her to marry a rich ugly girl, daughter a businessman,
Senator of Hamburg. Others had also exploited his youth, taking their share of joy and beauty for
women who join after the appeal had only to a large fortune.

She had ended up hating them all, wanting to exterminate them, exasperated at the thought that
I needed to live and would never be freed from this bondage.

To be independent, had been devoted to the theater.

- I danced, I sang, but my successes were always feminine.

The men were behind me, looking at the female and laughing at the artist. In addition, the life
of the racks! ... The target market with a name in the lineup! ... What exploitation! ...

The desire to free themselves had dragged her friend the doctor, accepting his proposals. It seemed
more honorable to serve a great state, be an official secret, working in the shadow of his
greatness. In addition, he won over the principle of working the romance, adventure risky missions,
a proud account of his espionage wove the plot the future, preparing future history.

Here, too, had encountered since the first steps to sexual slavery. Her beauty was a tool to
probe the conscience, a key to unlock secrets, and this easement was worse than previous ones, being
irredeemable. Had gotten away with ease of his life loving woman traveling theater, but entering
the "secret service" I could not leave it. Too many things were learned, is slowly coming to an
understanding important mysteries. The officer was a prisoner of its functions: it was a sandwich,
and with each new act added a new stone wall that separated him from freedom.

- You know the rest of my life - continued -. The obligation to obey the doctor, to seduce to men
to wrest their secret, it made me hate them with a deadly aggression ... But you came, you
who are kind and generous, I searched with a simplicity enthusiastic the same as a teenager, making
back in my life, as if he were still in eighteen years and I saw first courted! ... In addition,
you are not selfish. You see with noble enthusiasm. I think we met in early youth, I would have
left to be rich marrying another ... I refused to be yours because you loved and would not
hurt ... After the mandate of my superiors and my passion made me forget these scruples ... I surrendered,
I was the 'femme fatale' as always: I brought disgrace ... Ulysses! My love ... Forget: there
is no point reminiscing. Know well thy soul, and to me Endangered go there. Save me! Take
me with you! ...

As he stood before him, was enough to raise their hands to put them on his shoulders, starting
the beginning of a hug.

Ferragut remained insensible to the touch. His immobility repelled these appeals. Freya had lot
of running around the world through outrageous adventures, and know books on their own effort,
no need to complicate their tangled again.

The story that had just report was not for him but a tissue of deceit.

- All wrong! - Said dully -.

I do not believe, do not believe ever ... Each time we meet I tell a new story ... Who are
you? When you say the truth, the whole truth of a time?

... Liar!

She, insensible to the insults, speaking of his future remained painfully, as if saw surrounded
by mysterious dangers.

- Where to go if you leave me? ... If I stay in Spain, continued under the domination of doctor.
I can not return to the Empires where I spent my life, all roads are closed and those lands reborn
my slavery ... I can not go to France or England, I have fear of my past. Any of my previous achievements
would be enough to shoot me: no deserve less ... In addition, it
inspires me fear the vengeance of mine.

I know the procedures the 'service' when you need to get rid of an agent who is uncomfortable
in enemy territory.

He himself complaint: voluntarily committed a blunder, makes some
documents are lost, sends a compromising letter with false address,
to fall into the hands of the authorities the country.

What if you do not I help? ... Where can I elite group? ...

Ulysses was decided to reply, pity on his despair. The world is big: I could go to live in a republic
of America.

She did not accept the advice. I had thought the same, but was afraid of the future uncertain.

-
I'm poor, I have little money to pay my trip ... The "service" pays well at first. Then, as we have insurance
because of our past, gives only enough to live with some relief. What am I going to, do in those
lands?

... Should I spend the rest of my life sold in exchange of bread? ... I do not want: rather die!

The desperate assertion of poverty Ferragut smiled mockingly. He looked at the collar Pearl eternally
admirable pad lying on his chest, the thick emerald their ears, coldly brilliant crackled in
his hands. She guessed his thoughts, and the idea of ??selling these gems he produced a major
concern to the terrors that inspired him the future.

- You do not know what this means to me - he said -. It is my uniform, my shield, the pass I
can hold on in the world of my youth. Women who own the land we jewelry
need to continue on unimpeded.

Hotel managers humanize and smile at his brilliance. The possessor does not inspire confidence,
although late in the bill of the week ... Employees borders gallant display: no passport more powerful.
Haughty ladies soften its sparkle at the hour of tea halls where one does not know anyone ... What
I have suffered to get them! ... Arrostraría hunger before selling them. With them is one: can
a person does not have a coin in your pocket and go where they enter the richest, living as they ...

Not
accept the advice. It was as if a hungry soldier offered him their weapons in enemy territory in exchange
for bread. Once satisfied the need, would be prisoner would degraded, equaling the miserable
hours before receiving their shots.

Her face all the dangers and sufferings rather than shed the helmet and shield as symbols
of their superior stock.

The suit over a year, the booties fatigued underwear with tears poorly made, not saddened in difficult
times. The important thing was to have a hat fashion and keep the fur coat, collar of pearls, emeralds,
diamonds, whole armor honorable and glorious, in which he wanted to die.

His eyes seemed to take pity on the ignorance of the ocean, who dared to propose such absurd.

-
It is impossible, Ulises ... Take me with you. In the sea where I can live more safely. Submarines
I'm not afraid.

People imagine they are numerous and tight as paving stones, but
only a ship in a thousand get their attacks ... In addition, you fear
nothing: if our fate is to perish at sea, we would die together.

It was insinuating, seductive, moving his hands on his shoulders, pulling her neck with a passion
that amounted to an embrace. Her mouth spoke, approached the the ocean. Bow lips caress round
initiating a kiss.

- So bad you would live with Freya? ... Do not you remember because of our past? ... Is it
that now I am another?

Ulises remember, indeed, the past, and began to recognize that this
memory was too vivo.

They came to him as distant melodies and voluptuous half-forgotten, bursts of good-smelling meat,
arousing their sexual memory. The contact of the hidden curves, warm and firm, which is pressed
against your chest without losing the turgid hardness, evoked in
Ferragut imagination of a dizzying array of love scenes.

Chastity observed recent times on account of his painful worries
tormented him now as a punishment.

She, who was this revolution with cunning eyes, guessing its contractions face, winning smile,
pressing her face to his. I was sure of his power ... And reproduced Aquarium kiss, that kiss
that shook the back of the ocean, causing hesitation on her legs.

But when he handed over to the suction dominating abandonment, was
repelled, shot manotón by a brutal, like the punch that was thrown
onto the cushions to beginning of the interview.

Someone had come between the two, notwithstanding they were embraced
closely.

The captain, who began to lose consciousness of their actions, as well as a castaway, descending
and down through the layers to vibrant an unalloyed pleasure, suddenly
saw your face Stephen deceased, with glazed eyes fixed on him.

Beyond just saw a picture sad Vanish: Tape weeping as if her tears
were the only ones that could fall on the torn corpse of the child.

-
Ah, no! ... No!

The same was stunned by her voice. It was a wounded
beast roar, a howl of despair dry writhing in torment. 

Freya, staggering
under the rough push, he again tried to approach it, link to back
in his arms, repeating his urgent kiss.

- My love! ... My love ...

Could
not continue. The tremendous hand returned to repel it, but so violently,
that came to give head against the cushions of the couch.

Shook the
door with a rude jerk that it opened its two sheets at once, making
the latch lock.

The woman, tenacious in their desires, got up quickly,
regardless of the pain of the fall</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>