<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10900</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>494154</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24943</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Murió el año de 715; no se sabe el día, pero se cree fué su muerte á los últimos de Noviembre,
en edad de 40 años y 21 de religión, en que había entrado á 1.º de Octubre de 1694.

CAPÍTULO XVIII

Fúndase una Reducción nueva y el P. Juan Bautista de Zea emprende la Misión de los Zamucos.

Ya es tiempo de que volvamos á atar el hilo de la historia, interrumpida con esta larga, bien
que útil digresión, y en primer lugar á dar una vista á la Reducción de San Juan Bautista,
para pasar después á hablar por extenso de las trabajosísimas Misiones que en estos años emprendió
á gloria de Dios y bien de las almas, el Apostólico P. Juan Bautista de Zea.

Ya dijimos en el capítulo XVI cómo para suplir la falta de sujetos se habían extinguido dos
pueblos, y el uno de la advocación de San Juan Bautista; mas por este tiempo se volvió á fundar
otro con la misma advocación.

Habíanse, pues, agregado á San Joseph buen número de Morotocos y Quíes, y para mantener tanta
gente era el terruño algo estéril, y cortas las cosechas; por lo cual era necesario dividir
aquel pueblo y buscar en otra parte lugar para fundar en él otro nuevo.

Trece leguas de San Joseph, hacia Levante, había una campaña llamada el Naranjal, estéril,
no tanto por infelicidad de la tierra, cuanto por no haber quien la cultivase.

De común consentimiento escogieron, entre los otros, este paraje los neófitos, y tomó luego
habitación en él la gente de cuatro naciones y de otros tantos idiomas, Boros, Penotos, Taus
y Morotocos, poniendo por nombre á aquel pueblo San Juan Bautista; y para esto se atendió tanto
á que tuviesen cómodamente con qué pasar la vida, cuanto á que en bárbaros nuevos en la fe,
viniendo muchos en número y envejecidos en los vicios, es cosa de increíble trabajo quitarles
las malas costumbres, hacerlos olvidar las antiguas supersticiones y reducirlos á la estrechez
de la ley y vida cristiana; y como decía graciosamente un Misionero, son ellos tan niños, sin
uso de razón que para criarlos con vida de hombres racionales, es necesario estar en continuo
ejercicio de todas las virtudes, en especial de la paciencia, del celo, agrado y de aquella
que todo lo obra, la caridad, sufriéndoles infinitas impertinencias y necedades, acomodándose
á su modo y transformándose en cada uno de ellos para ganarlos y conducirlos todos á Dios.

Encargóse este nuevo pueblo al P. Juan Bautista Xandra, sardo de nación, el cual procuró, con
todo el fervor de su espíritu, que la gente fabricase sus Ranchos y labrase la tierra, de suerte
que volviendo de allí á poco el Padre Zea de los Zamucos, con no tan buen suceso como esperaba,
se consoló no poco con lo que vió en el nuevo pueblo de San Juan, y tomó ánimo para arriesgar
de nuevo la vida en la empresa de los Zamucos.

Esta conversión de Zamucos es aquella obra que emprendo ahora escribir, en que por haber sido
la última de este obrero evangélico; así como el sol en su horizonte, cuanto más precipitado
corre al ocaso, tanto se muestra más luminoso y bello, así este sol apostólico echó el resto
de su incomparable caridad cuando más cercano á su muerte; y aunque consumido, no menos de
los años que de los trabajos, tuvo tantas fuerzas y aliento, que pudo llegar á plantar triunfante
la bandera de Cristo en país inaccesible, no tanto por la barbaridad de sus moradores, cuanto
por su sitio natural; bien que después, por los inescrutables juicios de Dios, cometida á otros
aquella grande obra, se frustraron por algún tiempo tantas fatigas, y las esperanzas concebidas
de penetrar por aquí á las vastísimas provincias del Chaco.

Fortalecido, pues, su espíritu con largas oraciones y súplicas á Dios Nuestro Señor para la
feliz conducta de aquel negocio, se puso en camino para los Zamucos por Julio de 1716, acompañado
de cien neófitos, y á pocas leguas se le opuso el infierno con horribles tempestades en el
aire, torbellinos de agua y viento, crecientes de ríos y otras mil incomodidades; de manera
que en andar cosa de catorce leguas, gastó diecinueve días, mas no sin algún fruto; porque
dando una ligera corrida á registrar algunas Rancherías de los Tapuyquias, ya asoladas, halló
allí treinta almas que perseveraban aún en las tinieblas del gentilismo; y ganadas para Cristo,
las despachó al pueblo de San Joseph.

Alegre con esta ganancia impensada, pasó adelante, y á pocas leguas encontró con un bosque
de diez leguas de largo, horrible á la vista, y tan difícil de penetrar por él, que nunca le
había visto semejante en todas sus correrías.

Lo que aquí hizo y padeció, con ningunas palabras lo podré mejor referir que con las que el
mismo P. Zea se lo escribió al P. Vice-Provincial Luis de la Roca:

«Los indios (dice) no obstante que desconfiaban llegar al cabo, comenzaron á trabajar y á desmontar
la espesura; mas á la mitad de ella desmayaron totalmente y se resolvieron á dejarla, y tuve
por milagro el poder detenerlos; y para animarlos á llevar al cabo lo comenzado, me puse yo
á la frente con una hacha en la mano, á veces con el azadón y otras llevándoles agua para refrigerarlos
de los incendios del ardientísimo sol que hacía, y de esta manera, con el favor de Dios, en
diecinueve días de trabajo, se acabó de romper el bosque.

»Mas lo que se hacía insufrible era el no tener de día ni de noche treguas de las sangrientas
molestias de infinitos mosquitos y tábanos de varias especies, molestísimos, cuyos aguijones
nos desfiguraron sobremanera y nos duraron por mucho tiempo las señales.

»Puse por nombre á este bosque el Purgatorio, para que quien los años siguientes viniere á
este país en busca de almas, sepa cuánto le han de costar.»

Hasta aquí el P. Zea.

Abierto finalmente el camino salieron á campaña rasa, donde no hallaron cosa de comer el Padre
ni sus compañeros para repararse de los trabajos pasados, porque no había en aquel lugar ninguna
caza ni laguna de pescado, ó alguna colmena, como hay por otras partes.

Sólo había gran copia de agua estantía en las lagunas, y algunas raíces duras y tan amargas
como la hiel, y de éstas no en mucha abundancia; por esta causa perdió las esperanzas de llegar
al término de su viaje, porque fuera de lo dicho, habían también con los trabajos caído enfermos
no pocos de los neófitos, y los demás apenas se podían tener por la falta de alimento.

Con todo eso pasó adelante, á dos jornadas distante de la última Ranchería de los Cucarates,
le suplicaron algunos Orerobates y Morotocos torciese algún tanto el camino y fuese á tres
Rancherías de su nación á reducir á aquellos sus paisanos al conocimiento del Dios verdadero.

Condescendió con ellos de buena gana el santo varón, y dando orden al resto de su comitiva
que le esperasen junto á los Cucarates con solos algunos pocos dió la vuelta hacia las dichas
Rancherías, y en menos de dos días entró en aquellas tierras donde no halló ni aun una sola
alma, porque la carestía había obligado á los paisanos á esparcirse por los bosques en busca
de comidas; por tanto, fueron tras ellos los cristianos sin perder tiempo; mas los infieles,
juzgándolos, ó enemigos ó indios Chiquitos, de quien se temen en gran manera, huyeron, hasta
que desengañados, por haberse dado á conocer los nuestros, se pararon.

Pero fué en vano hablarlos de que se hiciesen cristianos, porque no venían bien en abandonar
su nativo suelo y tomar casa en otro paraje, y de otra manera no podían ser doctrinados en
las cosas de la fe y admitidos al santo bautismo; por cuya razón, viendo el P. Zea que no era
aún llegado el tiempo para su conversión, dió la vuelta en busca de sus compañeros; mas no
le salieron en vano sus fatigas, porque corriendo por algunas Rancherías ya desiertas, halló
allí poco más de setenta almas que redujo con facilidad á la fe, y dejándolas al cuidado de
algunos de sus neófitos que las guiasen y condujesen hasta San Joseph, alegrísimo el siervo
de Dios de haber en tres días sacado de las garras del demonio tantos infieles, llegó junto
á la última Ranchería de los Cucarates, donde le esperaban sus compañeros, á los cuales el
espíritu maligno había puesto en el corazón tal desesperación del éxito feliz de aquella empresa,
que por más que los animó no pudo jamás conseguir con ellos que pasasen adelante; y ¿qué podría
hacer él solo si faltaba por romper otro bosque semejante al pasado?

Detenerse aquí, y con el ayuda de otros infieles penetrar á los Zamucos era imposible, porque
todos, al ver á los Chiquitos, se habían retirado muy adentro.

Por tanto, con increíble sentimiento y dolor de su corazón, se vió obligado á volver atrás
y diferir la empresa hasta el año siguiente:

Mas el celo de las almas y de la mayor gloria de Dios, que estimulaban al Apostólico Padre
á proseguir lo comenzado, no le dejaron esperar á que abriese el tiempo, y aunque de las continuas
lluvias que caían estaban anegadas las campañas, resolvió exponerse segunda vez á los riesgos
y peligros pasados.

Cuáles y cuántos fuesen, no lo refiere el Padre por extenso, pero sí explica lo bastante para
comprender el valor y aliento que tenía en los negocios del servicio de Dios.

«Lo mismo (dice) era tratar de esta Misión que tocar al arma el infierno para deshacerla, romper
el aire con furiosas tempestades y mover en la tierra persecución aún más terrible; porque
unos me persuadían á que era temerario atrevimiento esta empresa y que no había de salirme
bien con los esfuerzos humanos. Otros, con más errado juicio, decían que se perdía inútilmente
el tiempo y el trabajo en la conversión de pocos cuando había cerca tantos países donde á menos
costa se ganaría para Dios muy grande multitud de almas.»

Así nos pinta, como en bosquejo, los esfuerzos de los hombres y de los demonios para apartarle
de sus intentos; mas todo se desvaneció, porque cuando Dios le llamaba, ni persuasión de razones,
ni terror de peligros, ni embarazos que se le atravesasen, eran poderosos para apartarle de
sus intentos.

Llamó, pues, un día á doce de los más fervorosos cristianos, y de igual ánimo en los peligros,
y con gran copia de razones les exhortó á que quisiesen ser sus compañeros en aquella empresa,
diciéndoles que en el cielo les daría Dios el galardón de lo que por su amor padeciesen; que
debían procurar el bien de los otros y moverse á compasión de tantas almas oprimidas de la
tiranía del demonio, de quien ellos, por la misericordia divina, habían sacudido el yugo; que
no se espantasen de los trabajos y riesgos que se les ofrecían porque corría por cuenta del
cielo el librarlos de ellos; fuera de que él sería el primero en exponerse á los peligros y
ellos en su seguimiento vendrían pisando sus huellas; él tantearía primero los vados de los
ríos, se arrojaría por los pantanos, echaría mano del hacha, y si osasen acometerlos los bárbaros,
él se ofrecería á servirles de escudo.

Esto y más les dijo este generosísimo propagador de la ley de Dios, con grande energía de espíritu,
porque de suyo era elocuentísimo. Y á la verdad era necesaria tal eficacia en sus palabras
para que sus indios perseverasen y pudiesen sufrir tantos trabajos.

Persuadióles lo que quería, y con estos pocos compañeros, en el mayor rigor del tiempo, por
Febrero del año siguiente, pasó á reconocer el bosque que faltaba por abrir para entrar en
los Zamucos; y pareciéndole cobardía el no poner luego manos á la obra para allanar aquella
dificultad, cogiendo una hacha y otras á su imitación los neófitos, comenzó á hacer el camino.

«Por espacio de quince días (dice él mismo en una carta) desde el amanecer hasta puesto el
sol, trabajé en desmontar parte de aquella selva, las más de las veces con el agua hasta la
cintura, á pie descalzo por entre aquellos espinares, perdiendo á cada paso el camino, porque
la violencia del agua nos llevaba de una parte á otra.»

Trabajando con este tesón llegaron hasta la mitad del bosque, donde conoció el santo varón
que de aquella manera no tanto se habían de sufrir trabajos y vencer dificultades, cuando contrastar
poco menos que un imposible; pues fuera del riesgo que había, de que creciendo un poco más
el agua quedasen todos anegados, no tenían un palmo de tierra donde reposar de noche, y la
molestia y enfado de los mosquitos era más insufrible que estar debajo del agua; por esto se
vió precisado á volver atrás hasta que se serenase el tiempo y tomasen nuevo vigor y aliento
sus compañeros, aunque el Venerable Padre, á quien los consuelos del cielo infundían tanto
ánimo y valor en tantas angustias, que el celo de las almas le hacía casi insensibles todos
los trabajos.

Llegaron todos sanos y salvos el Sábado Santo á la Reducción de San Juan Bautista, habiendo
gastado más de cuarenta días en el viaje.

Al siguiente día de Pascua de Resurrección trató el P. Zea de ajustar las paces y reducir al
conocimiento de Dios los Carerás, para limpiar de esta manera el camino de peligros y encuentros
con aquellos caribes, que causaban no poco terror á los pasajeros y servían de embarazo á la
dilatación de la santa fe.

Son estos Carerás de la misma lengua y nación que los Morotocos, con los cuales poco antes
habían roto la paz por litigios y contiendas que tenían entre sí, y se habían seguido, de ambas
partes, muchas muertes y ruinas, hasta que cansados de pelear y hacer guerra los Carerás enviaron
mensajeros á los Morotocos para volver á su antigua amistad; pero contra todo el derecho de
las gentes, dieron éstos inhumanamente la muerte á dichos mensajeros.

Irritó tanto esta alevosía á los Carerás, que se conjuraron para destruir á los Morotocos,
sin dar cuartel á ninguno de ellos; antes bien, haciendo pedazos á cualquiera que caía en sus
manos, y celebrando con sus carnes banquetes de cruelísima alegría.

A domesticar, pues, estas fieras y reducirlas al rebaño de Cristo se partieron ciento y sesenta
indios cristianos del pueblo de San Joseph, y entrando en su Ranchería, procuraron introducir
tratados de paz; mas los Carerás, sin querer dar oídos á estas pláticas, se pusieron luego
en arma, y del primer golpe mataron un indio cristiano é hirieron á otros dos.

Los neófitos, entonces, ofendidos, dieron sobre ellos, disparándoles una tempestad de flechas,
de que muchos quedaron muertos: irritados, los que pudieron, escaparon, y sólo se recogieron
dieciséis de la chusma, que traídos á San Joseph, se redujeron á nuestra santa fe.

Los fugitivos, en varias ocasiones, quisieron matar al P. Zea; mas Dios, que le guardaba, le
libró siempre, de varias maneras, de su furor y crueldad.

Mientras sucedía lo referido con los Carerás, se estaba disponiendo el infatigable Misionero
para llevar al cabo y conseguir el fin glorioso de tan trabajosa empresa; para la cual, escogiendo
segunda vez algunos cristianos de más valor y fuerzas, partió á fines de Mayo de 717, y llegando
al lugar de sus sudores, se puso luego con mayor brío á cortar árboles y á allanar la tierra,
facilitando este trabajo y fatiga la esperanza de feliz suceso.

Parecía casi imposible quitar aquel embarazo; pero nada le es inaccesible, nada duro de vencer,
á quien ha ofrecido su espíritu á Dios, y á los prójimos su vida en obsequio de la caridad.

Al cabo de veinte días se llegó á abrir del todo aquel impenetrable bosque, y á los 12 de Julio
llegó á la primera Ranchería de los Zamucos.

Estos, á quienes había llegado antes la fama de su venida, le festejaron con demostraciones
de extraordinaria alegría; cercáronle todos en rueda, y los varones todos, uno por uno, le
fueron besando la mano; querían hacer lo mismo las mujeres; mas el santo varón que se deshacía
todo en lágrimas de consuelo, les dió á besar la imagen de la Virgen santísima, que traía en
la mano.

Cumplimentaron después á los neófitos, abrazándoles en señal de paz y de amor, y les alojaron
en sus casas, dándoles parte de la pobreza y escasez del país.

El día siguiente juntó el pueblo en la plaza, les dió razón y juntamente una breve noticia
de Dios, de su santa ley, y los preguntó si querían que los Misioneros viniesen á predicarles
allí la fe de Jesucristo, y enseñarles el camino del cielo.

Respondieron ellos que había mucho tiempo que lo deseaban, y el no ser ya cristianos era porque
no tenían quién les explicase los misterios de la fe que habían de creer, ni los mandamientos
que debían observar.

--Pues si es así--añadió el Padre, bañado en alegría--es necesario levantar primero iglesia
á vuestro criador y señor, y que os juntéis todos en un pueblo.

A esta propuesta se levantaron dos caciques principales, diciendo que lo harían de buena voluntad,
mas no allí, sino en mejor sitio, y que juntarían luego al punto toda la gente del contorno
para fundar una reducción numerosa.

Entre tanto hizo el P. Zea enarbolar una cruz en un alto, y puestos todos de rodillas delante
de ella, la adoraron; y entonadas las letanías de la Virgen, puso aquel pueblo debajo del patrocinio
y tutela de nuestro Padre San Ignacio, cuya advocación le dió.

Hubiérase quedado allí de buena gana para dar calor á la buena voluntad de los Zamucos si hubiera
llevado consigo los ornamentos sagrados y el altar portátil, aunque le fuese forzoso sufrir
muchas incomodidades, y no tener otra cosa para comer que agua y algunas raíces de yerbas silvestres;
por esta causa se hubo de despedir de ellos y volverse por entonces con igual sentimiento y
dolor del que se partía y de los que se quedaban.

A la vuelta tuvo ocasión oportuna de ganar para Cristo á cien indios de varias naciones Zinotecas,
Japorotecas y Cucarates que se trajo consigo á la Reducción de San Juan Bautista, en donde
mientras se estaba disponiendo de nuevo para volver á sus Zamucos, recibió orden de nuestro
Padre General Miguel Ángel Tamburini, de que tomase á su cargo el gobierno de provincia; á
que obedeció prontamente, no sin incomparable dolor de su corazón.

Y porque con esta ocasión murió al bien público de estas misiones, dejando después de dos años
poco menos, la vida en el empleo de Provincial, haremos aquí una breve relación de los méritos
que partiéndose de aquí llevó consigo al Paraguay, para ejemplo de los súbditos, y después
al cielo, para recibir la corona debida á los operarios apostólicos.

Fué el P. Juan Bautista de Zea, natural de Goaze, lugar de Castilla la Vieja, en donde nació
á 18 de Marzo de 1654.

Aquí aprendió los primeros rudimentos de la gramática, aunque por la calidad del lugar y de
los maestros, aprovechó más en la devoción que en las letras, creciendo no menos en la virtud
que en los años.

Para estudiar las ciencias mayores pasó á la Universidad de Valladolid, donde dió buenas muestras
de ingenio en las ciencias especulativas, pero mucho más en la de los santos.

Sobresalía en él una modestia virginal, una inocencia de costumbres tan cristianas como amables,
un desprecio grande de las cosas del mundo, y un no gustar de otra cosa que de Dios y de su alma.

Poco era menester para que quien estaba tan despegado de los afectos de la carne y sangre se
rindiese á la voluntad divina que le llamaba á la Compañía, en que á 13 de Agosto de 1671 le
recibió el doctísimo P. Diego de la Fuente Hurtado, el cual descubriendo con luz soberana,
y anteviendo los fines á que Dios tenía destinado al nuevo Jesuita, pronosticó de él cosas
grandes en el servicio de Dios y aumento de la santa Iglesia, y de allí adelante le amó siempre
y le veneró como á santo.

Apenas el hermano Zea se vistió la sotana de la Compañía, cuando haciéndose cargo de las nuevas
obligaciones que con ella había contraído, procuró dar á ellas entero cumplimiento; y como
si empezara de nuevo el camino de la virtud, se miraba en las virtudes de sus connovicios,
observando cuanto en ellos era digno de ser imitado para copiar en sí mismo la perfección de todos.

Dándosele para leer y considerar nuestras reglas, se las puso delante como modelo, á que se
arregló perfectamente en lo interior y exterior.

Tuvo muy poco en qué vencerse para entregar del todo su corazón á Dios, no queriendo ni amando,
ni pensando en otro bien que en Su Majestad; y testifica sujeto que le conoció estudiando la
filosofía, que habiéndole dado los Superiores el cuidado del reloj de casa, se estaba sólo
en un aposento bien incómodo sin salir de él sino obligado de las funciones escolásticas ó
domésticas.

Aquí todo el tiempo que le sobraba de las tareas del estudio lo daba á Dios, y rarísima vez
á los hombres, porque usaba muy poco de su conversación, y esto solamente cuando lo pedía la
obligación.

Pasó después á estudiar la teología á Salamanca, y á este tiempo corrió la noticia por las
provincias de España de haber llegado á Cádiz los PP. Cristóbal de Grijalva y Tomás Dombidas,
procuradores del Paraguay, y poniéndose á considerar sobre la conversión de los idólatras y
el extremo desamparo en que están innumerables pueblos del Occidente, dilatado campo en que
ofrece copiosísima mies á muchos operarios Evangélicos, si hubiese muchos que despreciando
las comodidades propias atendiesen á la eterna salvación de las almas; se le encendió el corazón
en deseos de ser uno de los escogidos á quien tocase la suerte de ser señalado para la Misión
de la dilatadísima provincia del Paraguay; por tanto puso luego todo empeño en alcanzar licencia
de sus Superiores, los cuales sintieron mucho su petición, porque por una parte no querían
privarse de él, y por otra no querían oponerse á la voluntad de Dios, conocida claramente en
su vocación, prevaleció finalmente la América, y la abandonada gentilidad del Paraguay: por
lo cual, nuestro Zea, contento y alegrísimo se partió de su provincia de Castilla, á quien
como hijo profesó siempre tiernísimo afecto; y sus condiscípulos le siguieron con el corazón,
conservando su dulcísima memoria; singularmente se esmeró en esto su maestro en la filosofía
el P. Baltasar Rubio, confesor que fué de la serenísima reina de España doña María Luisa de
Saboya; éste le siguió con el afecto; con sus oraciones y con sus cartas pues cuando se ofrecía
ocasión siempre le escribía, por tener del P. Zea subido concepto, como en ellas lo manifestaba.

Ordenóse de sacerdote antes de embarcarse para esta provincia, á que pasó el año de 1681 y
apenas se dieron á la vela en Cádiz, cuando se le ofreció ocasión en qué dar muestras del espíritu
y virtudes, de las cuales iba abundantemente prevenido para aquel viaje.

Cayeron enfermos casi todos sus compañeros, que llegaban á sesenta, porque se marearon con
extraordinaria inapetencia y fastidio de la comida; á que se siguieron otras enfermedades,
de que murieron ocho de los Jesuitas, como dije en la vida del P. Caballero, que pasó también
á Indias en esta ocasión.

El P. Zea era entonces todo para todos, sirviéndoles no solamente de enfermero, sino de cocinero,
aunque sin experiencia en tales oficios; mas la caridad, que es maestra muy ingeniosa, le enseñó
estos y otros oficios para servir á sus hermanos.

Convalecidos éstos, empleó todos sus pensamientos y celo en la chusma de los grumetes del navío,
tomando á su cargo el cuidado espiritual de ellos con las pláticas, exhortaciones, confesiones
y todos los otros ejercicios conducentes al aprovechamiento de las almas, no dejando, entre
tanto, obra ninguna, por vil y repugnante que fuese, que no la ejecutase en servicio de ellos,
por ganarlos para Dios, y de mejor gana y más alegremente hacía aquellas que eran de mayor
trabajo y desprecio.

Con este porte tan santo procedió toda la navegación, que duró tres meses, con aprovechamiento
maravilloso de muchos, á quien redujo á bien vivir, ya valiéndose de las verdades eternas,
ya poniéndoles á la vista tantos peligros y tempestades del mar, que aun á los más perdidos
suelen obligar á cuidar de la conciencia y del alma, que antes tenían en tal olvido ó parecía
no tenerla.

Lo que obró después que llegó á las Indias y en qué oficios se empleó en el largo curso de
su vida, no lo he podido averiguar, por la distancia de los lugares donde vivió y trabajó,
y por haber muerto muchos de la Compañía que le trataron familiarmente. Pero sé que por el
aprecio que desde el principio hicieron de él los Superiores, poco después que llegó de España
le hicieron ministro del Colegio Máximo de Córdoba, donde se cría la religiosa juventud de
toda esta provincia.

Después fué Superior de las Misiones del Uruguay, Visitador de la de los Chiquitos, Vice-Rector
del Colegio de Córdoba, y estuvo también señalado Rector del Colegio de las Corrientes, á que
por motivos que tuvo propuso; y últimamente fué Provincial de esta provincia, oficio en que
le cogió la muerte al año y medio de su gobierno.

Ahora sólo diré brevemente alguna cosa de sus virtudes, reservando para mejor ocasión el dar
por extenso relación completa de sus muchas empresas y acciones heroicas. Y en primer lugar
diré de su pobreza religiosa.

Fué siempre pobrísimo en su vestido, tanto, que por los muchos remiendos que tenía, decía con
gracia un Misionero, que había en él más accidentes que substancia; él mismo lo remendaba por
sus manos; jamás mudó otro, hasta que el primero, por no poder ya subsistir, se le caía á pedazos.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02451</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>250414</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>22616</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

He died in 715, do not know the day, but it is believed his death was the last of November, at
age 40 and 21 of religion, which had come to 1. st October 1694.

CHAPTER XVIII

Founding a new and Fr Reduction Juan Bautista de Zea undertakes the mission of Zamucos.

It is time we return to tie the threads of the story, interrupted
this long, well than useful digression, and first to give a view to
the reduction of San Juan Bautista, then move on to talk at length
about the trabajosísimas Missions undertaken in recent years to the
glory of God and the good of souls, the Apostolic P. Juan Bautista
de Zea.

We said in Chapter XVI how to address the lack of subjects had been
extinguished two peoples, and one dedicated to San Juan Bautista,
but by this time returned to start another with the same dedication.

Habíanse therefore added to St. Joseph and number of Morotocos Quies,
and to maintain as much people was the homeland a bit sterile, and
short crops, and it was therefore necessary to divide that town and
look elsewhere to fund it rather than a new one.

Thirteen miles from St. Joseph, towards the East, had a campaign called the Naranjal, sterile
not so much unhappiness in the land, as by not having those who cultivate it.

Chosen by common consent, among others, this site newbies, and then took room at the people
of four nations and many languages, Boros, Penot, Taus and Morotocos, using his name to that
town San Juan Bautista, and this is covered both to which they had comfortably with what life
pass, the new barbarians to that in faith, coming many in number and aging in vice, a thing of
incredible work remove bad habits, make them forget the old superstitions and reduce them to
narrow of law and Christian life as a missionary graciously said, they are so young, without
use of reason to bring them alive rational men, need to be continuous exercise of all virtues,
especially patience, zeal, delight and that that everything works,
love, suffering and endless impertinent nonsense, settling his own
way and becoming each of them to win and lead all to God.

New village Encargóse P. Juan Bautista Xandra, Sardinian nation, which sought, with all the fervor
of his spirit, that the people made their huts and till the ground, so that back in a little
of Father Zea Zamucos, with not so good success as expected, not
a little consoled himself with what he saw in the new town of San
Juan, and took courage to risk new life in the company of Zamucos.

This conversion is the work Zamucos business I now write, that having been the last of this gospel
worker, and the sun on the horizon, the more precipitate runs at sunset, so is more bright
and beautiful, and the sun threw the rest apostolic its incomparable charity when closest to death,
and although used, at least the years of work, had so much strength and encouragement, he could
get to grow successful the banner of Christ in inaccessible country, not so much by the barbarity
of its inhabitants, the by its natural place, rather than later, by the inscrutable judgments of
God, committed to other that great work, got frustrated so many hardships
for some time, and the hopes here to penetrate the vast provinces
of Chaco.

Strengthened, then, his spirit with long prayers and supplications to God our Lord for happy
conduct of that business, he set out for Zamucos in July of 1716, accompanied hundred neophytes,
and a few leagues opposed him hell with horrible storms in air, water and wind swirling, rising
rivers and a thousand other discomforts, so that thing walk fourteen leagues, spent nineteen
days, but not without some fruit, for giving a slight run to record some of the Tapuyquias Rancherías,
already ravaged, found there thirty souls who persevered even in
the darkness of heathenism, and won to Christ dispatched to the town
of San Joseph.

Happy with this unexpected win, went ahead and found a few leagues
with a forest ten leagues long, horrible in sight, and so difficult
to penetrate it, he never had been similar in all their wanderings.

What we did and suffered, with no words as best I can refer you to the same P. Zea wrote it to P. Vice-Provincial
Luis de la Roca:

"The Indians (says) get suspicious, however, that after all, began to work and to remove the thickness,
but half of it to completely fainted and resolved to leave, and I miraculously the power to
stop them, and to encourage them to take after it started, I stood
his forehead with an ax in his hand, sometimes with the hoe and other
carrying water to cool them ardientísimo fire of sun that made, and
so, by the grace of God, nineteen days of work, ended up breaking
the forest.

"But what became unbearable was not having the day or night of the
bloody truce endless hassles of mosquitoes and flies of several species,
molestísimos, whose stings us and we greatly disfigured last long
signals.

"I put his name Purgatory to this forest, that whosoever cometh unto
the coming years this country in search of souls, know how much it
must cost.

"

So much for the P. Zea.

Finally opened the way out to open field, where they found something to eat Father nor his companions
to repair the past work, because there was in that place no hunting or fishing pond, or a hive,
as there are other parties.

Only water was great copy estantía in the gaps, and some as tough and bitter roots as gall,
and they are not in great abundance, for this cause lost hope of
reaching at the end of your trip, because outside it said, had also
fallen ill work not a few of the converts, and others could hardly
be for lack of food.

With all of that step forward, two days distant from the last Rancheria of Cucarates, begged
some Morotocos Orerobates and twist some both the road and went to three Settlements of their
nation to reduce to those his countrymen to the knowledge of the true God.

Condescended to them willingly accept the holy man, and gave orders
to the rest of his entourage to wait for him beside the Cucarates
with only a few turned around to the said Ranches, and in less than
two days came in those lands where no one even found soul, because
the famine had forced the villagers to spread through the woods in
search food, so Christians were behind them without wasting time,
but the infidels, judging, or enemies or Chiquitos Indians, who were
greatly afraid and fled, until disappointed that, having been given
to know us, they stopped.

But it was in vain to speak them to become Christians, as they are not good to leave his native
land and take home in another place, and otherwise could not be indoctrinated in things of
faith and admitted to holy baptism, for which reason, seeing the P. Zea was not even when the
time for conversion, went around in search of his companions, but not I went in vain their
toil, for running some Rancherías and deserted, found there slightly more than seventy souls
who easily reduced to the faith, and leaving care some of their neophytes that would lead and
guide him to St. Joseph, the servant alegrísimo of God be in three days out of the clutches
of the demon many unbelievers, came together to the last Rancheria of Cucarates, where they waited
for his companions, to whom the evil spirit had such despair in the heart of the success of that
happy company which encouraged more than ever could not get them
to go ahead with them, and what could do it only if it will break
another forest similar to the past?

Stop here, and with the help of other infidels to enter the Zamucos was impossible because
all, to see the little ones, had retreated deep inside.

Thus, with incredible feeling and pain in his heart, he was obliged to go back and defer the company
until the following year:

But the zeal for souls and the greater
glory of God, which stimulated the Apostolic Father to continue what
was begun, was not allowed to expect that time opened, and although
the continuous rain that fell were flooded campaigns, decided to expose
a second time to the risks and dangers past.

Which and how many were, not referred to the Father in full, but enough to explain understand the
value and encouragement they had in the business of serving God.

"The same (says) this mission was to try to touch the gun hell to undo, break the air with furious
storms and move on the earth even more terrible persecution, because about persuaded me that it
was foolhardy to dare this company and that there was to get out
well with human effort.

Other, more flawed trial, said he was lost in vain the time and effort in converting a few when
there were nearly as many countries where less God coast to win great multitude of souls. "

So we painted, as an outline of the efforts of men and demons to remove
him of their attempts, but all vanished, because when God called him,
or persuasions of reasons, terror and danger, and he went through
pregnancies, were powerful to take away from their attempts.

Called, then, one day to twelve of the most fervent Christians, and of one mind on the dangers,
and great abundance of reasons to which he exhorted them to be his companions in the venture,
saying that in heaven God would give them the reward of what they should suffer for their love,
that should seek the good of others and move to compassion of so many souls of the oppressed
tyranny of the devil, whom they, by divine mercy, had shaken off the yoke that do not be frightened
of work and risks that were offered because he ran on behalf of sky rid of them, outside of
which he would be the first to be exposed to danger and They come treading in following in his footsteps,
he first probe for the fords of rivers, the marshes yield, would
throw hand ax, and if you dare to attack them barbarians he would
offer to serve as a shield.

This and more I said this very generous propagator of the law of God,
with great energy of mind because his was eloquent.

And indeed it was necessary so effectively in his words to persevere and his Indians could
suffer so many hardships.

Persuadióles what I wanted, and with these few peers in the strictest
of time, February the following year, went to reconnoitre the forest
that remained to be open to enter the Zamucos, and seeming cowardice
not to put then to work to pave this difficulty taking a hatchet to
his imitation and other neophytes, he began to make the journey.

"For about fifteen days (he says in a letter) from dawn to put the Sun, worked on removing some
of that jungle, most of the time with water to waist, to walk barefoot
among those thorny, losing at every step along the way, because Water
violence would take us back and forth.

"

Working with this determination came to the middle of the forest, where he met the holy man
that in that way not so much work had to suffer and overcome difficulties when comparing little
less than an impossibility because of the risk out there, that grow a little water are all flooded,
they had an inch of land to settle overnight, and nuisance and annoyance of mosquitoes was unbearable
to be under water by this found it necessary to go back until it calms the time and to take
new strength and encouragement peers, although the Venerable Father, whom the consolations
of heaven instilled both spirit and courage in so many anxieties,
and zeal for souls made him almost insensitive all jobs.

They all arrived safely on Holy Saturday to the Reduction of San Juan Bautista, having spent
more than forty days in the journey.

The day after Easter tried Fr Zea adjusting to peace and reduce Carer
knowledge of God, thus cleaning the path of danger and meetings with
those Caribbean, causing no little terror to passengers and provided
a pregnancy to the expansion of the holy faith.

Are these career of the same language and nation that Morotocos, with whom shortly before Peace had
been broken by disputes and feuds that had each other, and were followed, both parties, many
deaths and ruined, until tired of fighting and sent to war Carer
messengers to the Morotocos to return to his old friend, but against
every right people gave them to death inhumanely these messengers.

So angry this treacherous to the Carer, who plotted to destroy the
Morotocos, without giving quarter to none, but rather, making pieces
to anyone who came his hands, and celebrating with joy most cruel
meat banquet.

A tame, then, these beasts and reduce the flock of Christ hundred and sixty left Christian
Indian village of St. Joseph, and entering its Rancheria, sought
to introduce peace treaties, but the Carer, without wanting to give
ear to these talks, then got a weapon, and the first strike killed
a Christian Indian and wounded another two.

Neophytes, then offended, gave about them, shooting a storm of arrows
that many were killed: irritability, they could, escaped, and only
collected Sixteen of the mob, which brought to St. Joseph, fell to
our holy faith.

The fugitives, on several occasions, tried to kill P. Zea, but God, who kept him always fought,
in many ways, his rage and cruelty.

As was true Carer referred to, was having the indefatigable missionary to carry out and achieve
the glorious end of such laborious undertaking, for which, by choosing
second time some Christians more courage and strength, started in
late May of 717, and reaching the place of his sweats, then put more
verve to cut trees and to pave the earth, facilitating this work and
fatigue in the hope of good success.

It seemed almost impossible to remove this pregnancy, but nothing is inaccessible, nothing hard
to beat, whom he has offered his spirit to God and his neighbor his
life for the sake of charity.

Twenty days after it was open to anyone in the impenetrable forest, and to the July 12 arrived
at the first Rancheria of Zamucos.

These, whom fame had preceded his coming, we celebrated with demonstrations of extraordinary joy
cercáronle all in a circle, and men all, one by one, we were kissing
his hand, wanted to do the same for women, but the holy man crumbled
all in tears of relief and gave them to kiss the image of the Blessed
Virgin, who brought in hand.

Completed after the neophytes, embracing in peace and love, and I
stayed in their homes, giving them part of the poverty and the country.

The

next day the people gathered in the square, right, and together they gave a brief report of God,
his holy law, and asked if they wanted should come and preach the Missionary Hence the faith
of Jesus Christ and teach the way to heaven.

They answered that he had long wished, and not being Christian and it was because I had no one explain
the mysteries of the faith they had to believe, or the commandments to be observed.

- Well if so - said the Father, bathed in joy - you need to first raise church to your Creator
and Lord, and that you keep company all in one village.

That proposal was raised two principal chiefs, saying they would of goodwill but not there, but in
a better place, and that would gather at once to all the people of the neighborhood to found
a large reduction.

Meanwhile made P. Zea fly a cross on a high, and put all kneel before
it, worship it, and chanted the Litany of the Virgin, placed under
the patronage that people and protection of our Father St. Ignatius,
which gave invocation.

One would have gladly stayed there for warmth to the good will of the Zamucos if there brought
with them the sacred vestments and altar laptop, but he was forced to suffer many inconveniences,
and having nothing else to eat but water and some wild grass roots;
from this cause was to dismiss them and turn then to the same feeling
and pain that started and those who stayed.

On the return was timely opportunity to win for Christ to one hundred Indians of various nations
Zinotecas, Japorotecas and Cucarates that brought to the Reduction
of San Juan Bautista, where as he was preparing again to return to
their Zamucos, received orders to our General Michelangelo Tamburini
father, that he take charge of the provincial government, to they
promptly obeyed, not without pain in his heart incomparable.

And this time he died because the public good of these missions, leaving after two years slightly
less, life in the provincial employment, we here a brief account of the merits starting from
here took with him to Paraguay, for example of the subjects, and
then the sky to receive the crown due to the apostolic workers.

Father was Juan Bautista de Zea, a native of Goaz, instead of Old Castile, where he was born to March
18, 1654.

Here he learned the rudiments of grammar, but by the quality of place and teachers, took over
in devotion in the letters, not least in growing under that year.

To study more science went to the University of Valladolid, where he gave good examples ingenuity
in the speculative sciences, but much more on the saints.

He excelled in maiden modesty, innocence of manners as Christian and kind, great contempt of
worldly things, and not like anything other than God and his soul.

There was little need for one who was so detached from the affections
of flesh and blood surrender to the will of God calling him to the
Company, in which to August 13, 1671 will P. was the most learned
Diego Hurtado de la Fuente, who discovered light sovereign and foreseeing
the end to which God had designed the new Jesuit, it predicted things
great in the service of God and increase the holy Church, and from
then on he always loved and was venerated as a saint.

Zea brother just donned the robes of the Company, when taking over new obligations that she
had contracted, he tried to give them full compliance, and as if I started again the path
of virtue, he looked in the virtues of their connovicios, As observed
in them worthy of emulation to copy itself to the perfection of all.

Bragging to read and consider our rules, they are put forward as a
model, to which perfectly arranged in the interior and exterior.

Had very little to overcome to deliver the all his heart to God, not wanting or loving, or thinking
of other good that Her Majesty and subject testifies he met while studying the philosophy,
having given the Supreme clock care home, was only rather uncomfortable in a room without
leaving it but forced or scholastic functions domestic.

Here all the time that he had plenty of work study God gave it, and very rarely to men, because they
used very little of their conversation, and then only when requested by the obligation.

Then he went to study theology at Salamanca, and at this time the news spread by provinces of
Spain have arrived at Cadiz PP. Cristóbal de Grijalva and Thomas Dombaas, Prosecutors in Paraguay,
and to consider putting on the conversion of idolaters and the extreme distress in which are
innumerable peoples of the West, where extensive field offers copious harvest operators to many
Evangelicals, if there are many who disregard the amenities to attend to the eternal salvation
of souls is kindled the heart the desire to be one of the elect whom he touched the good fortune
to be appointed for the Mission the very extensive province of Paraguay,
and therefore made every effort to reach then leave of his superiors,
who felt much his request, because one part would not deprived of
it, and otherwise would not oppose the will of God, clearly known
their vocation, the American finally prevailed, and the abandoned
paganism of Paraguay by thus, our Zea, happy and alegrísimo broke
his province of Castile, to whom as a child always professed most
tender affection, and his classmates followed him to the heart, retaining
its sweet memory; singularly took pains to master this, your philosophy
Fr Baltasar Rubio, who was confessor of the Most Serene Queen of Spain,
Dona Maria Luisa Savoy, he followed him with affection, with their
prayers and their letters because when offered always hand wrote,
having the P. Zea uploaded concept, as I stated them.

Ordenóse a priest before embarking for the province, he spent the
year 1681 and were just sailed in Cadiz, when occasion offered which
demonstrate the spirit and virtues, of which plenty was prevented
for that trip.

Fell ill almost all his companions, who came to sixty, it is dizzy with extraordinary loss of
appetite and food boredom, to be followed by other diseases, that
killed eight of the Jesuits, as I said in the life of P. Caballero,
who also spent Indians on this occasion.

Fr Zea was time for everyone, serving not only as a nurse, but a cook,
but no experience in such trades, but the charity which is very clever
teacher, taught him these and other offices to serve his brethren.

Convalesced them, used all his thoughts and zeal in the mob of apprentices of the ship, taking
responsibility for the spiritual care of them with the talks, calls, confessions and all other
exercises leading to the advantage of souls, leaving between therefore no work, were vile
and disgusting it was, who did not run on their service, to win them
for God, and better and more happily did win those who were most work
and contempt.

With this size so holy proceeded all the navigation, which lasted three months, taking advantage
many wonderful, whom reduced to living well, and drawing on the eternal truths and putting them
in sight so many dangers and storms at sea, which even the most lost
often obliged to care for the conscience and soul, who had previously
appeared in such neglect or not having it.

What worked after he came to the Indies and in what trades are employed in the long course
his life, I have not been able to ascertain, by the distance of the places where he lived and
worked and having killed many of the Company who treated him familiarly. But I know that by
the I appreciate that from the beginning made him superiors soon
after he arrived from Spain made him minister of the Colegio Máximo
de Cordoba, where they breed the religious youth throughout the province.

After

he was Superior of the Missions of Uruguay, Visitor of the Chiquitos, Vice-Rector College of Córdoba,
and was also designated the Rector of Corrientes, to which for reasons that had proposed, and
recently was Provincial of the province, letter by Death took him a year and a half of his
government.

Now I'll just say briefly something of their virtues, reserving for another day to give in full
respect of all his many enterprises and heroic deeds.

And first tell your religious poverty.

He was always very poor in their dress, so much that by the many patches
that had, say with grace a missionary, he was in more accidents than
substance, he himself mended by their hands never moved another, until
the first, and can not survive, was falling to pieces</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>