<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04030</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>3715</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>694</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Antes se ahorcan que fugarse al bosque...

Podía echarse de ver por esto poco que algo se le alcanzaba a don Cándido Gamboa de achaque
de etnología africana. Ya se ve, el tráfico constante en esclavos por muchos años, la posesión
de dos o tres centenas de éstos, le habían enseñado que según su raza eran más sumisos o levantiscos,
más o menos a propósito para llevar hasta la muerte el pesado yugo de la esclavitud. Sucedía,
sin embargo, que otra cosa le había enseñado a Moya su larga experiencia en el manejo de negros
suyos y ajenos, y todo su ser se sublevaba cuando oía decir que los había buenos y malos, y
que algunos no se huían jamás sin causa poderosa, más bien se quitaban la vida. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document04505</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>211354</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>649</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Before hanging themselves to escape to the forest ...

Lie could see
so little that something is reached Don Candido ailment Gamboa African
ethnology.

Already seen, the constant traffic in slaves for many years, holding two or three hundred of
these, he had been taught by race were more submissive or rebellious, more or less calculated
to lead to death on the heavy yoke of slavery. Happened, however, that nothing had taught him to Moya
long experience in handling black own and others, and his whole being revolted when she heard
that there were good and bad, and that some are not without cause powerful ever fled rather took
their own lives.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>