<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05171</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>1048</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>823</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Ni faltan arriates todo alrededor, en que las flores también abundan; y
para más primor y amparo de las flores, hay encañados vistosos, donde forman las cañas mil
dibujos y laberintos, rematando en triángulos y en otras figuras matemáticas. Las puntas superiores
de las cañas, con que se entretejen aquellas rejas o verjas, suelen tener por adorno sendos
cascarones de huevo o lindos y esmaltados calabacines. Las abejas y las avispas zumban y animan
el patio durante el día. El ruiseñor le da música por la noche.

En el invierno, la cordobesa tiene buen cuidado de que plantas de hoja perenne hermoseen su
habitación. Canarios o jilgueros recuerdan la primavera con sus trinos; y si el amo de casa
es cazador, no faltan perdices y codornices cantoras en sus jaulas, y las escopetas y trofeos
de caza adornan las paredes. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document07947</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>663739</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>775</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Missing or flowerbeds all around, where the flowers are also abundant, and
for more delicacy and under the flowers are gorgeous gorges, where they form a thousand reeds
drawings and mazes, ending in triangles and other mathematical figures. The upper points of the rods,
which are interwoven with those fences or gates, usually take two separate ornament eggshells
or cute and glazed zucchini. Bees and wasps buzz and encourage the playground during the day. The
Nightingale gives music at night.

In the winter, Córdoba takes good care of evergreens beautify your room. Canaries or finches
remember the spring with their songs, and if the householder is a hunter, partridges and quails
are not lacking songbirds in their cages, and guns and trophies Hunting
adorn the walls</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>