<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document00858</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>74480</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>746</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Nunca he dormido tan bien como la primera noche que pasé en aquella modesta alcoba. A pesar
de haber dejado abierta la ventana, pues lo permitía la temperatura, no sufrí ruido molesto
de ninguna especie. Al contrario, creo que me arrulló suavemente el constante y sonoro toque
de campanas.

Desperté temprano, como es mi costumbre, y desde el lecho empecé a admirar de nuevo el grato
aspecto de mi balcón florido: las hortensias, con sus esferas de azul y rosa; las azáleas y
geránios, con sus variados tonos de rojo y blanco; mas ¿qué era esa flor maravillosa, en el
centro de todas, en la cual no había yo reparado la víspera?

Salté del lecho, y ví con sorpresa que no era flor alguna, sino un pájaro que se posaba en
el barandal del balcón. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02807</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>55943</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>701</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

I've never slept so well like the first night I spent in that modest bedroom. Despite have left
open the window, because it allowed the temperature, did not suffer noise nuisance of any kind.
On the contrary, I think I rocked gently tap the steady and sound bells.

I awoke early, as is my habit, and from the bed started to admire again pleased aspect of my
balcony flower: hydrangea, with its fields of blue and pink azaleas and geraniums, with their
various shades of red and white, but what was that wondrous flower, the center of all, which
I had not noticed the day before?

I jumped out of bed, and saw with surprise that it was not a flower,
but a bird perched on the railing of the balcony</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>