<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document06464</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>98976</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>18654</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Porque no veo remedio á ella,
le respondió. He sido el vecino mas pudiente de la aldea de Derlback, cerca de Babilonia, y
con ayuda de mi muger hacia los mejores requesones del imperio, que gustaban infinito á la
reyna Astarte y al célebre ministro Zadig. Habla suministrado para entrámbas casas seiscientos
requesones: fuí un dia á Babilonia á que me pagaran, y supe que aquella misma noche se habian
desaparecido Zadig y la reyna. Fuí corriendo á casa del señor Zadig, á quien nunca habia visto,
y encontré á los alguaciles del gran Desterham, que con un papel del rey en la mano robaban
con mucho órden y sosiego toda la casa. Púseme en volandas en la cocina de la reyna; algunos
de los gentiles-hombres de beca me dixéron que habia muerto, otros que estaba presa, y otros
afirmáron que se habia escapado; pero todos estaviéron contestes en que no se me pagarian mis
requesones. Fuíme con mi muger á casa del señor Orcan, que era uno de mis parroquianos; le
pedímos su amparo en nuestra cuita, y se le otorgó á mi muger, y á mí no. Era mi muger mas
blanca que los requesones que fuéron el orígen de mi desventura, y no brilla mas la púrpura
de Tyro que el color que su blancura animaba: por eso se la guardó Orcan, y me echó de su casa.
Escribí á mi esposa desesperado una carta, y respondió al portador: Sí, ya, ya sé quien me
escribe, ya me han hablado de él; dicen que hace requesones excelentes: que me trayga, y que
se los paguen.

Quise acudir á la justicia en mi desdicha. Quedábanme seis onzas de oro: fué menester dar dos
al jurisperito que consulté, otras dos al procurador que se encargó de mi asunto, y dos al
escribiente del primer juez. Hecho esto, aun no se habia empezado mi pleyto, y ya llevaba mas
dinero gastado que lo que mis requesones y mi muger de añadidura valian. Volvíme al pueblo
con ánimo de vender mi casa por recobrar á mi muger. Valia esta unas sesenta onzas de oro;
pero me vían pobre, y con premura de vender. El primero á quien me dirigí me ofreció treinta,
el segundo veinte, y el tercero diez; y la iba á dar por este precio, segun estaba ciego. Vino
á la sazon á Babilonia un príncipe de Hircania, asolando todo el pais por donde pasaba, el
qual saqueó mi casa, y despues le puso fuego. Habiendo perdido de esta manera dinero, muger
y casa, me retiré al pais donde me veis, procurando ganar mi vida con la pesca. Los peces hacen
burla de mí lo mismo que los hombres: no saco ningunos, y me muero de hambre; y sin vos, consolador
augusto, iba á tirarme al rio.

No contó su historia el pescador sin hacer muchas pausas, y á cada una le decia Zadig, arrebatado
y fuera de sí: ¿Con que nada sabeis de la suerte de la reyna? No, señor, respondia el pescador;
lo que sé, es que ni la reyna ni Zadig me han pagado mis requesones, que me han robado á mi
muger, y que estoy desesperado. Yo espero, dixo Zadig, que no habeis de perder todo vuestro
dinero. He oido hablar de ese Zadig, como de un hombre honrado; y si vuelve á Babilonia, mas
de lo que os debe os dará; mas por lo que hace á vuestra muger, que no es tan honrada, aconsejoos
que no hagais diligencias por volver con ella. Tomad mi consejo, id á Babilonia, adonde ántes
que vos llegaré yo, porque vais á pié y yo voy á caballo; veos con el ilustre Cador, decidle
que habeis encontrado á su amigo, y esperadme en su casa: id en paz, que acaso no seréis siempre
desdichado.

Poderoso Orosmades, siguió, de mí os habeis valido para consolar á este hombre: ¿de quién os
valdréis para darme á mí consuelo? Así decia dando al pescador la mitad de todo el dinero que
traía de Arabia; y el pescador atónito y confuso besaba las plantas del amigo de Cador, y le
apellidaba su ángel tutelar.

Zadig no cesaba de preguntarle noticias, y de verter llanto. ¿Cómo, señor, exclamó el pescador,
tambien sois desdichado siendo benéfico? Cien veces mas infeliz que tú, respondió Zadig. ¿Cómo
puede ser, decia el buen hombre, que sea el que da mas digno de lástima que el que recibe?
Porque tu mayor desgracia, replicó Zadig, era la necesidad, y la mia pende del coraron. ¿Os
ha robado Orcan á vuestra muger? dixo el pescador. Esta pregunta traxo á la memoria á Zadig
todas sus aventuras, y le hizo repasar la lista de todos sus infortunios, empezando por la
perra de la reyna hasta su arribo á casa del bandolero Arbogad. Ha, dixo al pescador, Orcan
es digno de castigo; pero por lo comun esos son los hombres que estan en privanza del destino.
Sea como fuere, vete á casa del señor Cador, y espérame. Separáronse con esto: el pescador
se fúe dando gracias á su estrella, y Zadig maldiciendo sin cesar la suya.

CAPITULO XVIII.

El basilisco.

Llegó Zadig á un hermoso prado, donde vió una muchedumbre de mugeres que andaban buscando solícitas
cosa que parecia que habian perdido. Acercóse á una de ellas, y le preguntó si queria que las
ayudara á buscar lo que querían hallar. Dios nos libre, respondió la Syria; lo que nosotras
buscamos solo las mugeres pueden tocarlo. Raro es eso, dixo Zadig: ¿me haréis el favor de decirme
qué cosa es esa que solo las mugeres pueden tocarla? Un basilisco, respondió ella. ¡Un basilisco,
señora! ¿y por qué motivo buscais un basilisco? Para nuestro señor y dueño Ogul, cuyo palacio
estais viendo á orillas del rio, y al cabo de este prado, que somos sus mas humildes esclavas.
El señor Ogul está malo, y le ha recetado su médico que coma un basilisco hervido en agua de
rosas; y como es animal muy raro, y que solo de las mugeres se dexa coger, ha prometido el
señor Ogul que escogerá por su querida esposa á la que le lleve un basilisco: con que así dexádmele
buscar; que ya veis lo mucho que yo perderia, si una de mis compañeras ántes que yo le topara.

Dexó Zadig á esta Syria y á todas las demas que buscaran su basilisco, y siguió su camino por
la pradera. Al llegar á la orilla de un arroyuelo, encontró á otra dama acostada sobre los
céspedes, que no buscaba nada. Parecia magestuosa su estatura, aunque tenia cubierto el rostro
de un velo. Estaba inclinada la cabeza al anoyo; exhalaba de rato en rato hondos sollozos,
y tenia en la mano una varita con la qual estaba esciibiendo letras en una fina arena que entre
los céspedes y el arrojo mediaba. Quiso ver Zadig qué era lo que escribia: arrimóse, y vió
una Z, luego una A, y se maravilló: despues leyó una D, y le dió un vuelco el corazon; mas
nunca fué tanto su pasmo, como quando leyó las dos postreras letras de su nombre. Permaneció
inmoble un rato; rompiendo al fin el silencio, con voz mal segura, dixo: Generosa dama, perdonad
á un extrangero desventurado, que á preguntar se atreve ¿por qué extraño acaso encuentro aquí
el nombre de Zadig, por vuestra divina mano escrito? Al oir esta voz y estas palabras, alzó
con trémula mano su velo la dama, mitó á Zadig, dió un grito de temura, de asombro y de alborozo,
y rindiéndose á los diversos afectos que de consuno embatian su alma, cayó desmayada en sus
brazos. Era Astarte, era la reyna de Babilonia, la misma que idolatraba Zadig, y de cuyo amor
le acusaba su conciencia; aquella cuya suerte tantas lágrimas le habia costado. Estuvo un rato
privado del uso de sus sentidos; y quando cluvó sus miradas en los ojos de Astarte que lentamente
se abrian de nuevo entre desmayados, confusos y amorosos: ¡O potencias inmortales! exclamó,
¿me restitais á mi Astarte? ¿en qué tiempo, en qué sitio, en qué estado torno á verla? Hincóse
de rodillas ante Astarte, inclinando su fiente baxo del polvo de sus pies. Alzale la reyna
de Babilonia, y le sienta cabe sí en la orilla del arroyo, enxugando una y mil veces sus ojos
que siempre en frescas lágrimas se bañaban. Veinte veces añudaba ci hilo de razones que interrumpian
sus gemidos; hacíale preguntas acerca del acaso que los habia reunido, y no daba lugar á que
respondiese con preguntas nuevas; empezaba á contar sus desventuras, y queria saber las de
Zadig. Habiendo finalmente ámbos sosegado un poco el alboroto de su pecho, dixo en breves palabras
Zadig por qué acaso se encontraba en esta pradera. ¿Pero como os hallo, o reyna respetable
y desdichada, en este desviado sitio, vestida de esclava, y acompañada de otras esclavas que
buscan un basilisco, para hervirle, en virtud de una receta de médico, en agua de rosas?

Miéntras que andan buscando su basilisco, voy á informaros, dixo la hermosa Astarte, de todo
lo que he padecido, y que perdono al cielo una vez que vuelvo á veros. Ya sabeis que el rey
mi esposo llevó á mal que fuéseis el mas amable de todos los hombres, y acaso por este motivo
tomó una noche la determinacion de mandaros ahorcar, y darme un tósigo; y tambien sabeis que
los cielos compasivos dispusiéron que me avisara mi enano mudo de las órdenes de su sublime
magestad. Apénas os hubo precisado el fiel Cador á obedecerme y partiros, se atrevió á penetrar
por una puerta excusada en mi quarto á media noche, me sacó de palacio, y me llevó al templo
de Orosmades, donde me encerró su hermano el mago dentro de una estatua colosal cuya basa se
apoya en los cimientos del templo, y la cabeza toca con la bóveda. Aquí quedé como enterrada,
puesto que el mago que me servia cuidó de que nada me faltase. Al rayar el dia, entró en mi
quarto el boticario de su magestad con una pócima de beleño, opio, cicuta, eléboro negro, y
anapelo; y otro oficial se encaminó á vuestra casa con un cordon de seda azul; nias no halláron
á nadie. Por engañar mas al rey, le hizo Cador una falsa denuncia contra nosotros dos, fingiendo
que llevábais vos el camino de la India, y yo el de Menfis; y enviáron gente en nuestro seguimiento.

No me conocian los mensageros que fuéron en busca riña, porque casi nunca habia mostrado mi
semblante, como no fuese á vos, delante de mi marido y por órden suya. Ibanme persiguiendo
por las señas que de mi persona les habian dado; y se encontráron á la raya de Egipto con otra
de mi estatura misma, y que acaso era mas hermosa. Estaba bañada en llanto, y andaba desatentada,
de suerte que no dudáron de que era la reyna de Babilonia, y la conduxéron á Moabdar. Enojóse
violentamente el rey por la equivocacion; mas habiendo luego contemplado mas atentamente á
esta muger, vió que era muy hermosa, y se consoló. Llamábase Misuf, nombre que, segun despues
me han dicho, significa en egipcíaco la bella antojadiza, y lo era efectivamente; pero no iban
en zaga sus artes á sus antojos, tanto que habiendo gustado á Moabdar, le cautivó de manera
que la declaró su legítima esposa. Manifestóse entónces su índole sin rebozo, entregándose
sin freno á todas las extravagancias de su imaginacion. Quiso precisar al sumo mago, viejo
y gotoso, á que baylase en su presencia; y habiéndose negado este, le persiguió de muerte.
A su caballerizo mayor le mandó hacer una tarta de dulce; y puesto que representó que no era
repostero, todo fué en balde: tuvo que hacer la tarta, y le despidió porque estaba muy tostada.
El cargo de caballerizo mayor se le dió á su enano, y á un page le hizo fiscal del consejo:
de esta suerte gobernó á Babilonia. Llorábame todo el mundo; y el rey, que hasta que habia
mandado ahorcaros y darme veneno habia sido bastante bueno, dexó que sus virtudes corriesen
naufragio en su amor á la bella antojadiza. El dia del fuego sagrado vino al templo, y le ví
implorar á los Dioses por Misuf, postrado ante la estatua donde estaba yo metida. Alzando entónces
la voz, le dixe: "Los Dioses desechan las súplicas de un rey convertido en tirano, y que ha
querido quitar la vida á una muger de juicio, por casarse con una loca." Pusiéron estas palabras
en tamaña confusion á Moabdar, que se le fué la cabeza. Con el oráculo que habia yo pronunciado,
y con la tiranía de Misuf sobraba para que perdiera la razon; y con efecto en pocos dias se
volvió loco.

Esta locura, que se atribuyó á castigo del cielo, fué la señal de rebelion: amotinóse el pueblo,
y tomó armas; Babilonia, donde reynaba tanto tiempo hacia una muelle ociosidad, se convirtió
en teatro de una horrorosa guerra civil. Sacáronme del hueco de mi estatua; pusiéronme al frente
de un partido, y fué Cador corriendo á Menfis, para traeros á Babilonia. Noticioso de tan fatales
nuevas acudió el príncipe de Hircania con su exército á formar tercer partido en la Caldea,
y vino á embestir al rey que le salió al encuentro con su desatinada egipcíaca. Murió Moabdar,
traspasado de mil heridas, y cayó Misuf en poder del vencedor. Quiso mi desventura que yo tambien
fuera cogida por una partida de guerrilla hircana, que me conduxo á presencia del príncipe,
al mismo tiempo que le llevaban á Misuf. Sin duda sabréis con satisfaccion que me tuvo este
por mas hermosa que la egipcia, pero no será de ménos sentimiento para vos qué os diga que
me destinó para su serrallo, diciéndome sin andarse con rodeos, que luego que concluyese una
expedicion militar para la qual iba á partirse, vendria á mí. Figúraos qual fué mi quebranto:
rotos los vínculos que con Moabdar me estrechaban, podia ser de Zadig, y caía en los hierros
de un bárbaro. Respondíle con toda la altivez que me inspiraban mi alta gerarquía y mis afectos,
habiendo oido decir toda mi vida que las personas de mi dignidad las habian dotado los cielos
de tal grandeza, que con una palabra y un mirar de ojos confundian en el polvo de la nada á
quantos temerarios eran osados á apartarse un punto del mas reverente acatamiento. Hablé como
reyna, pero fuí tratada como una moza de cántaro: el Hircano, sin dignarse siquiera de responderme,
le dixo á su eunuco negro que yo era mal hablada, pero que le parecia linda. Mandóle que me
cuidase y me diera el trato que á las que estaban en su privanza, para que me volviesen los
colores, y fuese mas digna de sus caricias el dia que le pareciese oportuno honrarme con ellas.
Díxele que me mataria, y me respondió riéndose que ninguna se mataba por esas cosas, y que
estaba acostumbrado á semejantes melindres, y se fué dexándome como un xilguero en jaula. ¡Qué
situacion para la primera reyiia del universo, y mas para un corazon que era de Zadig!

El qual se hincó de rodillas al oir estas razones, regando con sus lágrimas las plantas de
Astarte. Alzóle esta cariñosamente, y prosiguió diciendo: Víame en poder de un bárbaro, y en
competencia con una loca con quien estaba encerrada. Contóme Misuf su aventura de Egipto; y
por la pintura que de vos hizo, por el tiempo, por el dromedario en que ibais montado, y por
las demas circunstancias vine en conocimiento de que era Zadig quien habia peleado en su defensa;
y no dudando de que estuviérais en Menfis, me determiné á refugiarme en esta ciudad. Bella
Misuf, le dixe, vos sois mucho mas donosa que yo, y divertiréis mas bien al príncipe de Hircania:
procuradme medio para escapar; reynaréis vos sola, y me haréis feliz, librándoos de una rival.
Misuf me ayudó á efectuar mi fuga, y me partí secretamente con una esclava egipcia.

Ya tocaba con la Arabia, quando me robó un bandolero muy nombrado, llamado Arbogad, el qual
me vendió á unos mercaderes que me traxéron á este palacio, donde reside el señor Ogul, que
me compró sin saber quien yo fuese. Es este un gloton, que solo piensa en atracarse bien, y
cree que le ha echado Dios al mundo para disfrutar de una bueua mesa. Está tan excesivamente
gordo, que á cada instante parece que va á reventar. Su médico poco influxo tiene con él quando
hace buena digestion, pero le manda despóticamente quando tiene ahitera; y ahora le ha hecho
creer que le habia de sanar con un basilisco hervido en agua de rosas. Ha prometido dar su
mano á la esclava que le traxere un basilisco, y ya veis que yo las dexo que se merezcan tan
alta honra, no habiendo nunca tenido ménos ganas de topar el tal basilisco que desde que han
querido los cielos que volviese á veros.

Dixéronse entónces Astarte y Zadig quanto á los mas generosos y apasionados pechos pudiéron
inspirar afectos tanto tiempo contrarestados, y tanto amor, y tanta desdicha; y los genios
que al amor presiden lleváron las razones de ámbos á la esfera de Vénus.

Tornáronse á la quinta de Ogul las mugeres sin haber hallado nada. Zadig se presentó á él,
y le habló así: Descienda del cielo la inmortal Hygia para dilatar vuestros años. Yo soy médico;
he venido habiendo oido hablar de vuestra dolencia, y os traygo un basilisco hervido en agua
de rosas; no porque aspire á casarme con vos, que solo os pido la libertad de una esclava jóven
de Babilonia, que os vendiéron pocos dias hace; y me allano á permanecer esclavo en su lugar,
si no tengo la dicha de sanar al magnifico señor Ogul.

Fué admitida la propuesta, y se partió Astarte para Babilonia en compañía del criado de Zadig,
prometiéndole que le despacharia sin tardanza un mensagero, para informarle de quanto hubiese
sucedido. No ménos que su reconocimiento fuéron amorosos sus vales: porque, como está escrito
en el gran libro del Zenda, las dos épocas mas solemnes de la vida son el instante en que nos
volvemos á ver, y aquel en que nos separamos. Queria Zadig á la reyna tanto como se lo juraba,
y la reyna queria á Zadig mas de lo que decia.

Zadig habló de esta suerte á Ogul: Señor, mi basilisco no se come, que toda su virtud se os
ha de introducir por los poros; yo le he puesto dentro de una odre bien henchida de viento,
y cubierta de un cuero muy fino; es menester que empujeis hácia mí dicha odre en el ayre con
toda vuestra fuerza, y que yo os la tire muchas veces; y con pocos dias de dieta y de este
exercicio veréis la eficacia de mi arte. Al primer dia se hubo de ahogar Ogul, y creyó que
iba á exhalar el alma; al segundo se cansó ménos, y durmió mas bien: por fin á los ocho dias
recobró toda la fuerza, la salud, la ligereza, y el buen humor de sus mas floridos años. Zadig
le dixo: Habeis jugado á la pelota, y no os habeis hartado: sabed que no hay tal basilisco
en el mundo; que un hombre sobrio y que hace exercicio siempre vive sano, y que tan imaginado
es el arte de amalgamar la gula con la salud como la piedra filosofal, la astrología judiciaria,
y la teología de los magos.

Conociendo el primer médico de Ogul quan peligroso para la medicina era semejante hombre, se
coligó con el boticario del gremio para enviarle á buscar basiliscos al otro mundo: de suerte
que habiendo sido castigado siempre por sus buenas acciones, iba á morir por haber dado la
salud á un señor gloton. Convidáronle á un espléndido banquete, donde le debian dar veneno
al segundo servicio; pero estando en el primero, recibió un parte de la hermosa reyna, y se
levantó de la mesa, partiéndose sin tardanza. El que es amado de una hermosa, dice el gran
Zoroastro, de todo sale bien en este mundo.

CAPITULO XIX.

Las justas.

Fué recibida la reyna en Babilonia con aquel júbilo con que se recibe siempre una princesa
hermosa y desdichada. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09591</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>704438</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17460</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Because I see no remedy for it,
answered. I have been the more affluent neighboring village Derlback, near Babylon; with the
help of my wife to the best curds of the empire, who liked to infinity to queen Astarte and
the famous minister Zadig. Speech delivered to both of hundred houses curd: I went one day to
Babylon to pay me, and I knew that night it had Zadig and queen disappeared. I ran to the house
of Mr. Zadig, whom I had never seen and found great Desterham sheriffs, with a role of the king
in his hand stole very orderly and calm throughout the house. I went down in a twinkling in
the kitchen of the Queen, some of scholarship gentlemen told me that had died, others were imprisoned,
and others said that he had escaped, but all estava answer that I can not pay my curds. We went
with my wife to the house of Mr. Orcan, who was one of my parishioners, he ask for his protection
in our grief, and given to my wife, and me not. It was my wife more white curds that were
the source of my misery, and do not even shine purple Tyro that encouraged having white color,
so he put it Orcan, and gave me his home. I wrote to my wife desperate letter, and responded
to the bearer: Yeah, yeah, I know who I writes, I have talked about it, they say that makes curds
excellent: I am bringing, and they are paid.

I wanted to go to court in my misery.

Quedábanme six ounces of gold was necessary to give two the legal expert I consulted, two to
the attorney who handled my case, and two to scribe the first judge. This done, had not yet
started my pleyto, and I had been more spent money than my curds and my wife were worth the bargain.
I returned to the people with the intention of selling my house for my wife to recover. Valia
is about sixty ounces of gold; but I Vian poor, and in haste to sell. The first to whom I
spoke gave me thirty the second twenty, and the third ten, and was going to take for this price,
according was blind. Wine At the time, a prince of Babylon to Hircania, ravaging the whole country
through which he passed, the qual ransacked my house, and then put fire. Having thus lost
money, wife and home, I retired to the country where you see me, trying to earn my living by
fishing. The fish do teasing me just as the men drew no, and I'm starving, and without you, dildo
August, was about to jump into the River.

No fisherman told his story without many pauses, and to every one was telling Zadig, robbed and out
of it: With what you know nothing of the fate of the Queen? No, sir, "replied the fisherman; I
know, is that neither the queen nor Zadig has paid me my curds that I have stolen my wife,
and I'm desperate. I hope, 'said Zadig, that you have not lost all your money. I've heard of
that Zadig, as an honest man and if he returns to Babylon, but what should I give you, but for
what you do to your wife, who is not honest, aconsejoos prevent you from doing errands to get back
to it. Take my advice, go to Babylon, where before I'll get to you because you are going to walk
and I am going to horse veos the illustrious Cador, tell that you have found his friend, and
wait for me at home: go in peace, that maybe you will not be provided unhappy.

Orosmades powerful, followed me to comfort you have earned this man: who you valdréis to give
me comfort? So said the fisherman giving half of all money brought from Arabia, and the fisherman
kissed the stunned and confused's Friend Cador plants, and we last name his guardian angel.

Zadig
news did not stop to ask, and shed tears.

What, sir, "said the fisherman, You are also unhappy to be beneficial? Hundred times more unhappy
than you, "replied Zadig. How may be, he said the good man, that is the one who gives more to
be pitied than to receive? Because your great misfortune, "replied Zadig, was the need, and
mine depends on the coraron. Would you Orcan stolen to your wife? 'said the fisherman. This
question he brought to mind Zadig all his adventures, and made him go through the list of all
their woes, starting with queen bitch until arrival at the house of the bandit Arboga. Ha,
'said the fisherman, Orcan is worthy of punishment, but these are usually men who are in Privanza
destination. Anyway, go to the house of Mr. Cador, and wait. Separáronse with this: the fisherman
it was giving thanks to his star, and constantly cursing Zadig yours.

CHAPTER XVIII.

The basilisk.

Zadig came to a beautiful meadow, where he saw a crowd of wives who were looking for caring
thing that had seemed lost. He approached one of them, and asked if I wanted that help them find
what they wanted to find. God forbid, said the Syria, what we we can touch only the women. Rare is
it, 'said Zadig: do me please tell me what it is that the women can only touch it? A basilisk,
"she said. A basilisk lady! Why what are you looking for a basilisk? For our lord and master Ogul,
whose palace are watching the banks of the river, and within this field, who are his most humble
slaves. Mr. Ogul is bad, and your doctor has prescribed a basilisk eat boiled in water roses,
and as is very rare animal, and that only the women are catching dexamethasone, has promised Mr. Ogul
to choose for his beloved wife to bring him a basilisk that well
dexádmele look, that you see how much I would lose if one of my colleagues
before I could Topara.

I leave this Zadig to Syria and to all others who seek their basilisk, and continued on his way
the prairie. On reaching the bank of a creek, he found another lady lying on lawns, not looking
for anything. It seemed majestic stature, although he had covered his face a veil. Head was tilted
to Anoy; exhaled from time to time deep sobs and held in his hand a wand with the qual was
esciibiendo letters in a fine sand between lawns and courage mediated. Zadig wanted to see
what he wrote: arrimóse, and saw a Z, then an A, and wondered: then read a D, and gave her heart
skip a beat, but never was both his astonishment, as the two rearward Quando read letters in his
name. Remained motionless for a while, finally breaking the silence, unsure, voice, said: "Generous
Lady, forgive to a hapless foreigner who dares to ask why anything strange encounter here the
name of Zadig, by thy divine hand writing? On hearing this voice and these words, lifted with trembling
hand the lady her veil, myth Zadig, uttered a cry of Temur, wonder and joy, and surrendering
to the various emotions that together embatian his soul fainted in arms. Was Astarte, was the
queen of Babylon, the same as Zadig idolized, and whose love his conscience accused him, those
whose fate had cost so many tears. He spent some time deprived of the use of their senses, and when
their eyes Cluver's eyes slowly Astarte opened again between faint, confused, loving, O immortal
powers! exclaimed, "Restitais me to my Astarte? What time, what site, around to see what state?
Hincóse knees before Astarte, bowing his fiente Baxo dust of your feet. Lift it up the Queen
of Babylon, and I feel it themselves on the banks of the stream, a thousand times enxugar eyes
always bathed in fresh tears. Twenty times ci knotted thread of reasons that blocked her moans; doeth
questions about anything that had gathered, and did not rise to that respond to new questions,
beginning to tell their misfortunes, and wanted to know those Zadig. Having finally both a
little calm the tumult of his breast, he said in brief Perhaps why Zadig was in this meadow. But as
I am, or respectable queen and unfortunate, in this deviant site, dressed in a slave and other
slaves who accompanied looking for a basilisk, for boiling, under a doctor's prescription, in
rose water?

While they are looking for their basilisk, I shall inform you, 'said the fair Astarte, all I
have suffered, and forgive the sky once you get to see you. You know that the king My husband
took it amiss that you were the kindest of all men, and perhaps for this reason took a night
to send you the determination to hang, and give me a tósigo, and also know that compassionate
heaven disposed to let me know my dwarf silent orders of his sublime Majesty. No sooner had I pointed
the faithful Cador to obey and depart, she dared to penetrate by a side door in my fourth at
midnight, I pulled out of the palace, and took me to temple of Orosmades, where I locked her
brother magician into a colossal statue which is based rests on the foundation of the temple,
and the head touches the roof. This was like buried as the magician who served me made sure
that I shall not want. At break of day, entered my quarto of His Majesty the chemist with a
potion of henbane, opium, hemlock, black hellebore, and anapelo, and another officer went to your
house with a blue silk cord; Nias found no to anyone. For more deceive the king, Cador him a false
complaint against two of us, pretending you wore you the way to India,
and mine in Memphis, and sent people in our trackers.

I knew the messengers who were looking fight, because it seldom had shown me face, unless it was
to you, before my husband and by his order. Chasing Ibanme by signs that they had given me, and found
the line of Egypt with other my height itself, and that perhaps was more beautiful. I was in
tears, and walked heedless, so that they did not doubt that she was the queen of Babylon,
and to Moabdar conduxéron. Wroth King violently by mistake, but after having covered more closely
to this woman, saw that it was very beautiful, and was comforted. Missouf was called, a name which,
according to later I am told, means the beautiful Egyptian, capricious, and it was indeed,
but were not in behind their gear to their cravings, while having to Moabdar liked him so
captivated who declared his lawful wife. Manifestóse then frankly its kind, giving unchecked
to all the extravagances of his imagination. Wished to stress the high magician, old and gout,
to which Bayle in his presence, and having refused this, he was haunted by death. In the Horse
I ordered a sweet cake, and since it was not represented baker, all was in vain: he had to make
the cake, and let him go because he was so toast. The office of the Horse was given to his
dwarf, and a page to him tax advice: ruled in this way to Babylon. Llorábame around the world,
and the king, until he had sent me hang and poison had been pretty good, I leave that his virtues
runners to shipwreck on his love of beautiful fanciful. The day of the sacred fire came to the
temple, and I saw him implore the gods for Missouf, prostrate before the statue where I was stuck.
Then raising voice, I said to him: "The Gods dismiss the pleas of a king became a tyrant, and
has wanted to take the life of a woman on trial for marrying a crazy woman. "put these words Moabdar
on such a confusion to which he was the head. In oracle I had pronounced and the tyranny of Missouf
had plenty to lose his reason, and with effect in a few days went crazy.

This madness, which was attributed to punishment from heaven, was the signal for rebellion: amotinóse
the people and took weapons, Babylon, where queen into a pier as long idleness, became theater
of a horrific civil war. They pulled me out of the hole of my statue; They put forward of a party,
and Cador was running to Memphis, to bring him to Babylon. News of such fatal New Prince of Hircania
came with his army to form third party in Chaldea and came to attack the king met him with
his blundering Egyptian. Moabdar died, pierced by a thousand cuts, and fell in the hands of the
victor Missouf. It was my misfortune that I also was caught by a band of guerrillas Hyrcanus, Condux
me into the presence of the prince, at the same time it took to Missouf. Surely ye shall know
that I had the satisfaction for more beautiful than the Egyptian, but shall not be less feeling
for what you say you I devoted to his harem, saying without beating about the bush, then to
conclude a military expedition to qual was scheduled to leave, would come to me. Imagine qual
was my grief: Broken links with Moabdar shook me, could be Zadig, and fell in the irons of a
barbarian. I replied with all the pride that my high large hierarchy inspired me and my affections,
having heard that all my life that people of my dignity of the heavens had endowed of such greatness,
with a word and a look of eyes mingled in the dust of the blue to quanta were reckless daring
to depart from a point in the most reverent obedience. Spoke as Queen, but I was treated like
a maid of pitcher: the Hyrcanus, without even deigning to answer, he said to his black eunuch
that I was swearing, but he seemed nice. Ordered him to me take care and give me the treatment to those
who were in his favor, that I became the colors, and were more worthy of his touch on the day
it seemed appropriate to honor them. Dixel would kill me, and I replied laughing that none
were killed by these things and was used to such niceties, and went as a xilguero dexándome cage.
What situation for the first reyiia of the universe, and more for a heart that was Zadig!

And
he knelt down to hear these reasons, watering with tears plants Astarte. Alzola this affectionately,
and went on to say: Viamed in the hands of a barbarian, and competition
with a crazy who was locked.

Contour Missouf his adventure in Egypt, and for painting that you did, by time, by the dromedary
in ye were mounted, and the other circumstances came to the attention of Zadig was who had fought
in their defense; and no doubt you were in Memphis, I determined to take refuge in this city.
Bella Missouf, I said to him, "you are much more comely than I, and looking for fun rather Hyrcanian
Prince: procuradme means of escape; reynaréis you alone, and you will make me happy, librándoos of
a rival. Missouf helped me to make my flight, and I departed secretly with an Egyptian slave.

Already
played with Saudi, when a robber stole my very name, called Arboga, the qual I sold to some merchants
that they brought me to this palace, where he lives, Mr. Ogul, which I bought without knowing
who I was. This is a glutton, who thinks only of binge well, and
believes that God has put the world to enjoy a bueu table.

He is so excessively fat, which every moment seems he is going to burst. Your doctor is with
him little influx Quando makes good digestion, but when they have high-handedly sends ahitera
and now has made believe that he had to heal with a basilisk boiled in rose water. Has promised
to give hand to the slave that traxere a basilisk, and you see me I leave they deserve the very
high honors, having never been less willing to bump the basilisk that since they have heaven wanted
to come back to see you.

Astarte and Zadig Dixéronse quanto then the most generous and passionate breasts could countered
inspire affection so long and so much love and so much misery, and geniuses that love led preside
reasons of both in the sphere of Venus.

He turned about a fifth of the women Ogul without having found anything.

Zadig was introduced to him, and said to him: the sky Descend the immortal Hygia to dilate
your years. I am a doctor; I've been having heard of your illness, and I am bringing a basilisk
in boiling water Rose, not because I aspire to marry you, I ask only the freedom of a young
slave Babylon, which I sold a few days ago, and I acquiesced to remain a slave in his place, if
I have the joy of healing the magnificent Mr. Ogul.

The proposal was accepted, and went to Babylon, Astarte in the company of Zadig's servant, promising
that he would ship out immediately a messenger to inform had quanto happened. No less than his
recognition were loving their vouchers, because, as written in the great book of Zenda, the two
most solemn times of life is the moment we meet again, and that we parted. Zadig to the Queen
wanted as much as he swore, and Zadig loved the queen more than what he said.

Zadig spoke in this way to Ogul, Lord, my basilisk not eat, that all virtue is you must enter
through the pores, I've put in a good swollen wineskin wind and covered with a fine leather,
it is necessary that such wineskin empujeis towards me in the air with all your strength, and
that I will throw it often, and with a few days and this Diet Exercicio will see the effectiveness
of my art. The first day it was to drown Ogul, and believed that was about to breathe the
soul, the latter is less tired and slept most good: at last the eight days regained all the
strength, health, lightness, and good humor of his most florid years. Zadig said to him: Have
you played at the ball, and you have not had enough: know that there is no basilisk in the
world, that a sober man and always makes Exercicio healthy lives, and how imagined amalgamation
is the art of gluttony with health as the Sorcerer's Stone, judicial astrology, and theology of
the Magi.

Knowing the quan Ogul first doctor of medicine was dangerous for such a man, collide with the
apothecary to send for guild basilisks to the other world: so that having been punished for
their good deeds always, was to die for having given health to a man gluttonous. Convidáronle
to a feast, where he ought to poison the second service, but still in the first, received a
part of the beautiful queen, and rose from the table, splitting without delay. He who is loved
by a beautiful, says the great Zoroaster, everything goes well in
this world.

CHAPTER XIX.
The fair.

Received the Queen was in Babylon with that joy with which
we always welcome a princess beautiful and unhappy</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>