<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09383</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>609370</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>24313</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Daba su sangre por que el mundo entero fuese libre y
desapareciesen todas las monarquías.

--Me bato por Francia, porque es el país de la gran Revolución. Su historia anterior no me
importa: para reyes ya tenemos los nuestros. Pero á partir del 14 de Julio, lo que es de Francia
lo considero mío y de todos los hombres.

Se detuvo unos segundos, buscando una afirmación más concreta:

--Me bato, capitán, por Dantón y por Hoche.

Vió Ferragut en su imaginación las melenas blancas de Michelet y el tupé romántico de Lamartine
sobre un doble pedestal de volúmenes que contenían la historia-poema de la Revolución.

--También me bato por Francia--dijo finalmente--porque es la patria de Víctor Hugo.

Ulises presintió que este republicano de veinte años debía guardar en su mochila un cuaderno,
escrito con lápiz, lleno de versos.

El sudamericano, habituado á las disputas de sus dos compañeros, se miraba las uñas negras
con la melancólica desesperación de un profeta que contempla su patria en ruinas. Blanes, hijo
de burgués, le admiraba por su origen. El día de la movilización había ido en París á inscribirse
como voluntario montando un automóvil de cincuenta caballos. El y su chófer se alistaban juntos.
Luego hacía donación de su lujoso vehículo.

Había deseado ser soldado porque todos los jóvenes de su club partían á la guerra. Además,
le halagaba que su última amante le dedicase unas lágrimas de admiración y asombro viéndole
con uniforme. Sentía la necesidad de conmover á todas las damas que habían bailado el tango
con él hasta la semana anterior. Por otra parte, los millones de su abuelo «el gallego», algo
roídos por su padre el criollo, se estaban deshaciendo entre sus manos.

--Esto dura demasiado, capitán.

Al principio había creído en una guerra de seis meses. Las balas le importaban poco; lo terrible
era el piojo, el no mudarse la ropa, el verse privado del baño diario. ¡Si él hubiese adivinado!...

Y resumía su entusiasmo con esta afirmación:

--Me bato por Francia porque es un país chic. Sólo en París se visten bien las mujeres. Esos
alemanes, por mucho que hagan, serán siempre unos ordinarios.

No necesitaba añadir más: todo quedaba dicho.

Los tres recordaron los meses de infierno sufridos recientemente en los Dardanelos, en un espacio
de seis kilómetros conquistado á la bayoneta. Una lluvia de proyectiles caía incesantemente
sobre ellos. Había que vivir debajo de la tierra como topos, y aun así, les alcanzaba el estallido
de los grandes obuses.

En esta lengua de tierra frente á Troya, por la que se había deslizado la historia remota de
la humanidad, las palas, al abrir las trincheras, tropezaban con los más raros hallazgos. Un
día, Blanes y sus compañeros habían sacado á luz jarros, estatuillas y platos que tenían treinta
siglos. Otra vez cortaron blanduras repulsivas que exhalaban un hedor insufrible. Estaban abriendo
trincheras en un pedazo de terreno que había servido de cementerio á los turcos. Los vientres
hinchados se partían bajo las palas, derramando los zumos de su putrefacción. La necesidad
de resguardarse había obligado á los legionarios á vivir con el rostro al nivel de los cadáveres
que asomaban en el corte vertical de la tierra removida.

--Los muertos estaban como las trufas en un pastel--dijo el sudamericano--. Yo tuve que permanecer
un día entero tocando con mi nariz los intestinos de un turco muerto dos semanas antes... No,
la guerra no es chic, capitán, por más que hablen de heroísmos y cosas sublimes en periódicos
y libros.

Quiso ver Ulises otra vez á «los tres mosqueteros» antes de partir de Salónica, pero el batallón
había levantando su campo, situándose á muchos kilómetros al interior, frente á las primeras
líneas búlgaras. El entusiasta Blanes disparaba ya su fusil contra los asesinos de Roger de Flor.

A mediados de Noviembre llegó el Mare nostrum á Marsella. Su capitán experimentaba siempre
cierta admiración al doblar el cabo Croissette, viendo cómo se abría ante la proa una vasta
curva marítima. En el centro de ella, una colina abrupta y desnuda avanzaba hacia el mar, sosteniendo
en su cumbre la basílica y la torre cuadrada de Nuestra Señora de la Guardia.

Marsella era la metrópoli del Mediterráneo, el puerto terminal para todos los navegantes del
mare nostrum. En su bahía, de cortas olas, se alzaban varias islas amarillentas, con franjas
de espuma, y sobre una de ellas las torres robustas del novelesco castillo de If.

Todos, desde Ferragut á los últimos marineros, contemplaban como algo propio la ciudad que
iba asomando en el fondo de la bahía, sus bosques de mástiles y su amontonamiento de edificios
grises, sobre los cuales brillaban las cúpulas bizantinas de la nueva catedral. En torno de
Marsella se abría un hemiciclo de alturas desnudas y secas, coloreadas alegremente por el sol
de Provenza. Los pueblos y caseríos moteaban de blanco estas pendientes, así como las bastidas,
«villas» de placer de los mercaderes de la ciudad. Más allá de dicho semicírculo, el horizonte
estaba cerrado por un anfiteatro de ásperas y sombrías montañas.

En los viajes anteriores, la vista de la gigantesca Virgen dorada, que brilla como una lanza
de fuego en lo alto de Nuestra Señora de la Guardia, esparcía el regocijo sobre el puente del
buque.

--¡Marsella, Tòni!--decía el capitán alegremente--. Te convido á una bouillabaisse en casa
de Pascal.

Y Tòni contraía el peludo rostro con sonrisa de gula viendo por anticipado el restorán famoso
del puerto, sus salones crepusculares oliendo á marisco y á salsas picantes, y sobre la mesa
el hondo plato de pescado con un caldo suculento teñido de azafrán.

Pero ahora Ulises había perdido su vigorosa alegría de vivir. Contemplaba la ciudad con ojos
amorosos pero tristes. Se veía desembarcando la última vez, enfermo, sin voluntad, anonadado
por la trágica desaparición de su hijo.

El Mare nostrum llegó á la boca del puerto viejo, teniendo á su derecha las baterías del Faro.
Este puerto viejo era el recuerdo más interesante de la antigua Marsella. Penetraba como un
cuchillo acuático en las entrañas del caserío; la ciudad se extendía por sus muelles. Era una
plaza enorme de agua á la que afluían todas las calles; pero su área resultaba insignificante
para el tráfico marítimo, y ocho puertos nuevos venían á cubrir toda la ribera Norte de la bahía.

Una escollera interminable, una muralla más larga que la ciudad, se extendía paralelamente
á la costa, y en el espacio entre la orilla y este obstáculo, que obligaba á espumear y rugir
á las olas, se extendían los ocho amplios puertos, comunicándose entre sí desde el llamado
de la Joliette, que era el de acceso, hasta el lejano de la Estaca. Todavía este último se
prolongaba tierra adentro por el gran canal subterráneo que pone en comunicación á la ciudad
con el Ródano.

Ferragut había visto ancladas en esta sucesión de abrigos las marinas de toda la tierra y aun
de todas las épocas. Junto á los trasatlánticos enormes balanceaban sus vergas las vetustas
tartanas y algunos barcos griegos, pesados y de formas arcaicas, que hacían recordar las flotas
descritas en la Ilíada.

En sus muelles circulaban todos los hombres mediterráneos: helenos del continente y de las
islas; levantinos de la costa de Asia; españoles, italianos, argelinos, marroquíes, egipcios.
Muchos guardaban sus trajes originales, y á esta variada indumentaria se unía la diversidad
de lenguas, algunas de ellas misteriosas y casi perdidas. Como atraídos por la confusión oral,
los mismos franceses olvidaban su idioma, hablando el dialecto marsellés, que conserva rastros
indelebles de su origen griego.

Atravesó Mare nostrum el antepuerto, la dársena de la Joliette, la del Lazareto, deslizándose
lentamente por los pasos de comunicación, entre grupos de transeúntes y de carros que esperaban
el restablecimiento de los puentes giratorios de acero abiertos ante su proa. Luego fué á anclarse
en la dársena de Arenc, cerca de los docks.

Cuando Ferragut pudo desembarcar, se dió cuenta de la gran transformación sufrida por este
puerto con motivo de la guerra.

El tráfico de los tiempos de paz no existía. Los géneros no eran de una variedad infinita,
como otras veces. En los muelles sólo se apilaban cargamentos, monótonos y uniformes, de víveres
ó de material de guerra.

Habían desaparecido también las legiones de descargadores. Todos estaban en las trincheras.
Las orillas eran barridas ahora por mujeres, y las descargas las efectuaban destacamentos de
tiradores senegaleses. Se estremecían de frío en los días asoleados del invierno y se encorvaban
como moribundos bajo la lluvia ó el soplo del mistral. Trabajaban con el gorro rojo calado
sobre las orejas, y al menor alto en sus faenas se apresuraban á meter las manos en los bolsillos
del capote. Estos negros formaban grupos vociferantes en torno de un fardo ó una pieza que
cuatro hombres hubiesen movido en tiempo ordinario, y el paso de una mujer ó de un vehículo
les hacía descuidar el trabajo, volviendo sus caras de diablos con una curiosidad infantil.

La descarga amontonaba en las principales dársenas los mismos artículos: trigo, mucho trigo,
y azufre y salitre para la composición de materias explosivas. En otros muelles se alineaban
á miles los pares de ruedas grises, sostén de cañones y furgones; las cajas enormes como viviendas
que contenían aeroplanos; las piezas de acero que sirven de andamiaje á la artillería gruesa;
cajones de fusiles y cartuchos; enormes paquetes de conservas alimenticias y de materias sanitarias;
todo el avituallamiento del ejército que peleaba en el extremo remoto del Mediterráneo.

Varios pelotones de hombres precedidos y seguidos de bayonetas marchaban de un puerto á otro
con rítmico paso. Eran prisioneros alemanes, sonrosados y alegres á pesar de la cautividad,
vistiendo aún sus uniformes de color verde col, con un gorro redondo sobre la esquilada cabeza.
Iban á trabajar en el interior de los buques, cargando ó descargando el material que debía
servir para el exterminio de sus compatriotas y sus amigos.

En las dársenas, los vapores se mostraban extraordinariamente agrandados. A su llegada sólo
alzaban sobre el muelle unos cuantos metros de borda; pero ahora que su cargamento estaba apilado
en tierra, parecían altísimas fortalezas. Dos tercios del casco ocultos siempre en el mar quedaban
al descubierto, mostrando el vivo rojo de su panza. Sólo su quilla se mantenía en el agua.
El tercio superior, lo que quedaba visible sobre la línea de flotación en tiempo ordinario,
era ahora una simple cornisa negra que remataba el extenso muro purpúreo. Los palos y chimeneas,
achicados por esta transformación, parecían corresponder á otro buque más pequeño.

Todos estos vapores mercantes y pacíficos llevaban un cañón en la popa para librarse de los
corsarios submarinos. Inglaterra y Francia habían movilizado sus tramps, sus barcos vagabundos,
y empezaban á darles medios de defensa. Algunos no habían podido montar el cañón sobre una
cureña fija, y llevaban una pieza de artillería terrestre, asomando su boca entre las ruedas
clavadas en la cubierta.

El capitán, en todos sus paseos, se sentía atraído por la famosa Cannebière, vía succionante
que aspira la actividad entera de Marsella.

Algunos días, un viento fresco y violento arremolinaba en ella el polvo y los papeles. Los
camareros de los cafés trincaban los grandes toldos como si fuesen el velamen de un buque.
Se aproximaba el mistral, y cada dueño de establecimiento ordenaba la maniobra para hacer frente
al helado huracán que vuelca mesas, arrebata asientos y se lleva todo lo que no está asegurado
con marinos amarres.

Creyó ver Ferragut en la famosa avenida marsellesa una antesala de Salónica. Los mismos tipos
del ejército de Oriente circulaban por sus aceras: ingleses vestidos de kaki, canadienses y
australianos con sombreros de ala levantada; indostánicos enormes y esbeltos, de tez cobriza
y espesa barba en forma de abanico; tiradores senegaleses, de un negro charolado; tiradores
anamitas, de cara redonda y amarillenta, con ojos en triángulo. Pasaban incesantemente camiones
obscuros guiados por soldados, automóviles llenos de oficiales, recuas de mulas procedentes
de España que iban á ser embarcadas para Oriente, y esparcían detrás de su vivo trote un olor
punzante y bravío de cuadra.

El puerto viejo atraía á Ferragut por su antigüedad, casi tan remota como las primeras navegaciones
mediterráneas. En esta plaza de agua metida entre casas habían anclado sus pobres naves los
primeros fenicios, viéndose sucedidos por los emigrantes de Focea en Asia Menor, marineros
griegos que huían de la invasión de los persas. Las colinas calcáreas y desnudas inmediatas
al puerto se cubrían de viviendas, y así nació Marsalia, que había de ser siglos adelante la
señora del Mediterráneo.

Sus navegantes atrevidos bajaban á lo largo de la costa española, fundando ciudades que eran
focos de civilización para los rudos íberos, así como Marsalia lo fué para los belicosos galos.

Ferragut, al pasar ante el palacio de la Bolsa, lanzaba una mirada á las estatuas de los dos
grandes navegantes marselleses Eutymenes y Pyteas. Eran los abuelos más remotos de la navegación
mediterránea, los primeros capitanes conocidos por la Historia que habían transpuesto las columnas
de Hércules, lanzándose á través del Atlántico misterioso. Uno había explorado las costas del
Senegal; el otro subía más allá de Irlanda y las Orcadas.

La antigua ciudad griega se había visto suplantada por otras durante largos siglos. Venecia,
Génova y Barcelona la tenían en humilde dependencia. Pero cuando caían éstas y le llegaba á
ella su hora de prosperidad, esta prosperidad iba acompañada de todas las ventajas de la época
presente. Se había inventado la máquina de vapor, y los buques podían salvar fácilmente el
obstáculo del estrecho de Gades, sin tener que aguardar semanas á que amainase la violencia
de la corriente enviada por el Atlántico. Había nacido el industrialismo, y las fábricas del
interior lanzaban por el ferrocarril, recientemente instalado, un oleaje de productos que las
flotas iban transportando á todos los puebles del Mediterráneo. Finalmente, al ser abierto
el istmo de Suez, se desdoblaba la ciudad de un modo prodigioso, pasando á ser un puerto mundial,
poniéndose en contacto con la tierra entera, multiplicando sus dársenas, gigantescos apriscos
adonde venían á aglomerarse como rebaños los buques de todos los pabellones.

El puerto viejo, encajonado en plena ciudad, cambiaba de aspecto según las horas y el estado
de la atmósfera. En las mañanas serenas era de un verde amarillento y olía ligeramente á agua
descompuesta: agua orgánica, agua animal. Los puestos de ostras y erizos establecidos en sus
muelles parecían rociados con esta agua impregnada de mariscos.

Los días de fuerte viento todo él se tornaba de un verde terroso y opaco, formando olas cortas
y continuas, con una leve espuma amarillenta. Los buques empezaban á bailar, chirriando bajo
el tirón de bus amarras. Entre sus cascos y la superficie vertical de los muelles se formaban
montones de basura inquieta, mordida abajo por los peces y picoteada arriba por las gaviotas.

En la boca, cerca de los fuertes venerables de San Juan y San Nicolás, el transbordador levantaba
sus dos pilastras de celosía de acero y el puente recto que las une, formando una portada triunfal.

Los barcos armados que vigilaban las aguas limítrofes venían á descansar en esta dársena histórica
rodeada de cafés, tiendas, almacenes, cúpulas y campanarios.

Ferragut veía los rápidos torpederos, de paredes delgadísimas, danzando á la más leve ondulación
sobre sus amarras de acero retorcido. Examinaba los «chaluteros», embarcaciones militares improvisadas,
vaporcitos robustos y cortos, construídos para la pesca, que llevaban en la proa un cañón de
tiro rápido. Todos estos buques menores, pintados de un gris metálico para confundirse con
el color del agua, entraban en el puerto y salían como centinelas que se reemplazan.

Montaban la guardia en alta mar, más allá de las islas rocosas y desiertas que cierran la bahía
de Marsella, aproximándose á los buques para reconocer su nacionalidad, corriendo á todo vapor,
con sus melenas de humo horizontales, hacia el punto donde esperaban sorprender el periscopio
del enemigo oculto entre dos aguas. No había mal tiempo que les adormeciese ó les asustase...
En plena tormenta se mantenían á la vista de la costa, saltando de ola en ola, con su fragilidad
de barcos construídos para ser flechas; y únicamente cuando otros compañeros venían á sustituirles
regresaban al puerto viejo, para descansar unas horas á la entrada de la Cannebière.

Las callejuelas de la orilla derecha atraían á Ferragut. Eran la Marsella antigua, en la que
aún subsisten algunos palacios ruinosos de los mercaderes y armadores de otros siglos. En estas
vías estrechas, pendientes é inmundas, vivía la prostitución pintarrajeada y triste de toda
ciudad marítima.

Se aglomeraban en dicho barrio los guerreros de las diferentes Áfricas francesas, impulsados
por su ardor de raza y por el deseo de desquitarse con grandes hartazgos de la carestía de
los países musulmanes, donde la mujer vive en celoso encierro. En todas las esquinas había
grupos de infantería marroquí recién desembarcada ó convaleciente de sus heridas, soldados
jóvenes con gorros rojos y largos capotes de amarillo mostaza. Los zuavos de Argel conversaban
con ellos en un español salpicado de árabe y de francés. Negros adolescentes que servían de
fogoneros en los buques avanzaban por las empinadas callejuelas con ojos de inquietante resplandor,
como si preparasen un rapto en masa. Se perdían bajo las puertas, con una tiesura sacerdotal,
los graves jinetes moriscos, arrastrando el albo alquicel anudado á la cabeza como una bola
de nítida blancura, ó el manto purpúreo de aguda capucha, que les daba el aspecto de barbudos
frailes rojos.

Entre la salida del hospital y el nuevo combate que les esperaba en las trincheras del Norte,
estos guerreros venidos de lejanos países de sol para pelear y morir buscaban el poderoso consuelo
de la mujer. Sus brazos impacientes se llevaban con un tirón de fiera las hembras esqueléticas
y macabras y las que aparecían hinchadas por una falsa robustez, producto de malos humores.
Algunas tenían la desproporción embrionaria de los fetos, con enormes cabezas sirviendo de
remate á cuerpos raquíticos. Otras avanzaban sus míseros troncos descarnados sobre unas piernas
anchas y redondas de paquidermo. Los soldados faltos de dinero miraban con envidia y hambre
á las mujeres estacionadas en las puertas: criaturas de lujo é ilusión, con faldellines orinados
llenos de lentejuelas, altas botas y medias amarillas.

El capitán iba por las cumbres de estas calles, deteniéndose para apreciar el rudo contraste
entre ellas y su vista terminal. Casi todas descendían hasta el puerto viejo, con un reguero
de aguas sucias por mitad del arroyo que saltaba de piedra en piedra. Eran obscuras como tubos
de telescopio, y al extremo de sus zanjas malolientes, ocupadas por el deforme mujerío, se
abría un amplio desgarrón de luz y de azul. Se veían blancos veleros anclados al final de la
pendiente, un pedazo de lámina acuática y las casas del muelle opuesto, empequeñecidas por
la distancia. En otras aparecía como último plano la montaña de Nuestra Señora de la Guardia,
con su basílica puntiaguda y la brillante estatua final, semejante á una llama de oro inmóvil
y tortuosa. Algunas veces, un torpedero, al entrar en el puerto viejo, se deslizaba por la
boca de una de estas callejuelas sombrías como si pasase por la lente de un anteojo.

Al sentirse fatigado el marino por el mal olor y la miseria viciosa de los barrios viejos,
volvía al centro de la ciudad, paseando bajo los árboles de las avenidas de Meilhan ó entre
los puestos de flores del Coso Belzunce.

Un anochecer, cuando esperaba el tranvía en la Cannebière rodeado de otras personas, volvió
la cabeza con el presentimiento de que alguien le estaba contemplando á sus espaldas.

Efectivamente, vió á un hombre detrás de él en el borde de la acera, un señor elegantemente
vestido, completamente afeitado, que parecía por su aspecto un inglés cuidadoso de su persona.
Este gentleman acababa de detenerse á impulsos de la sorpresa, como si hubiese reconocido á
Ferragut.

Se cruzaron las miradas de los dos, sin que esto despertase eco alguno en la memoria del capitán...
No podía recordar á este hombre. Casi estaba seguro de no haberlo visto nunca. Su rostro afeitado,
sus ojos de un gris metálico, su tiesura elegante, no decían nada á su memoria. Tal vez el
desconocido sufría una equivocación.

Así debía ser, á juzgar por la prontitud con que separó su mirada de la de Ferragut, alejándose
apresuradamente.

El capitán no dió importancia á este encuentro. Lo había olvidado ya al subir al tranvía, pero
minutos después resurgió en su memoria, bajo una nueva luz. El rostro del inglés se presentaba
en su imaginación con un relieve distinto al de la realidad. Lo veía más claramente que al
resplandor algo mortecino de los reverberos de la Cannebière... Pasaba con indiferencia sobre
sus rasgos fisonómicos: en realidad, los había contemplado por primera vez. ¡Pero los ojos!...
El conocía perfectamente aquellos ojos: se habían cruzado muchas veces con los suyos. ¿Dónde?...
¿Cuándo?...

Le acompañó hasta su buque el recuerdo de este hombre como una obsesión, sin lograr que su
memoria diese una respuesta á sus preguntas. Luego, al verse en la cámara de popa con Tòni
y el tercer oficial, volvió á olvidarlo.

En los días sucesivos, al bajar á tierra, su memoria experimentaba invariablemente el mismo
fenómeno. Iba el capitán por la ciudad, sin acordarse de aquel individuo, pero al entrar en
la Cannebière surgía inmediatamente en su cerebro dicho recuerdo, seguido de una ansiedad inexplicable.

«¿Dónde estará ahora mi inglés?--pensaba--. ¿Dónde le he visto antes?... ¡Porque es indudable
que nos conocemos!»

Miraba curiosamente, á partir de este instante, á todos los transeúntes, y á veces apresuraba
el paso para examinar á algunos que se le asemejaban por la espalda. Una tarde creyó reconocerlo
en un carruaje de alquiler cuyo caballo marchaba á vivo trote por la avenida del Prado; pero
cuando quiso seguirle, el vehículo había desaparecido en una calle inmediata.

Transcurrieron los días, y el capitán olvidó definitivamente este encuentro. Otros asuntos
más reales é inmediatos le preocupaban. Su buque estaba listo; iban á enviarle á Inglaterra
para cargar municiones destinadas al ejército de Oriente.

La mañana de su partida bajó á tierra sin deseos de llegar al centro de la ciudad.

En una calle de los docks había una barbería frecuentada por los capitanes españoles. La charla
pintoresca del barbero, nacido en Cartagena, las láminas de colores fijas en la pared representando
corridas de toros, los periódicos de Madrid olvidados en los divanes de hule y una guitarra
en un rincón, hacían de esta tienda un pedazo de España para los vagabundos del Mediterráneo.

Ferragut, antes de partir, quiso entregar sus barbas al tijereteo del verboso maestro. Cuando,
pasada una hora, pudo salir de la barbería, arrancándose á las interminables despedidas del
dueño, siguió una amplia calle entre dos filas de docks, solitaria y silenciosa.

Las puertas corredizas de acero estaban cerradas y selladas. Los almacenes, vacíos y sonoros
como naves de catedral, exhalaban aún los fuertes olores de los géneros que habían guardado
en tiempo de paz: vainilla, canela, rollos de cuero, nitratos y fosfatos para abonos químicos.

No vió en toda la calle mas que un hombre que venía hacia él dando la espalda á la dársena.
Entre las dos largas paredes de ladrillos surgía el muelle en el fondo, con montañas de mercancías,
escuadras de cargadores negros, vagones y carros. Más allá estaban los cascos de los buques,
sustentando un bosque de palos y chimeneas, y en último término la muralla amarilla del malecón
exterior y el cielo recién lavado por la lluvia, con un rebaño de nubecillas blancas y plácidas
como sedosos carneros.

El hombre que volvía del puerto y caminaba con los ojos fijos en Ferragut se detuvo de pronto,
y girando sobre sus talones volvió hacia el muelle... Este movimiento despertó la curiosidad
del capitán, aguzando sus sentidos. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document01154</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>430394</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21354</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> He gave his blood for the whole world was free and disappear
all monarchies.

- Me bato by France, because it is the country of the great Revolution. His past history did not
matter: for kings and we have ours.

But as of July 14, which is from France I consider myself and all
men.

He paused a few seconds, looking for a more specific statement:

- Beat me, captain, Danton and Hoche.

Ferragut saw in his mind the white mane of Michelet and Lamartine romantic toupee on a double
pedestal of volumes containing the history-poem of the Revolution.

- Beat me also for France - he finally said - it is the home of Victor Hugo.

Republican Ulysses sensed that twenty years had to keep a notebook in his backpack, written
in pencil, full of verses.

The South American, accustomed to the disputes of his two companions, his fingernails black with
the melancholy despair of a prophet who contemplates his homeland
in ruins.

Blanes, son of bourgeois admired him for his origin.

The day of mobilization had been in Paris to sign volunteer riding a car fifty horses. He and his
driver got ready together. Then he would grant his luxury vehicle.

He had wanted to be a soldier because all the youth of his club left for the war. In addition,
he was flattered that he devoted his last lover tears of admiration
and awe seeing uniform.

I felt the need to move to all the ladies who had danced the tango
with him until last week.

Moreover, the millions of his grandfather 'Galician', something gnawed by his father Creole, were
falling apart in your hands.

- It takes too long, Captain.

At first he had believed in a six-month war. The bullets he cared little, how terrible Scale was,
not moving the clothes, deprived of the daily bath. If he had guessed it ...

And he summed up his enthusiasm with this statement:

- Me bato by France because it is a country chic.

Only in Paris are well dressed women. These German, however much they do, will always be a regular.

No
need to add more, everything was said.

The three recalled the months of hell suffered recently in the Dardanelles,
in an area won six miles with the bayonet.

A rain of bullets fell incessantly on them. Had to live underground like moles, and even then, they
reached the outbreak of large shells.

In this tongue of land before Troy, which had slipped remote history humanity, shovels, opening
the trenches, faced with the most rare finds. A day, Blanes and his companions had brought
to light vases, figurines and dishes that they had thirty centuries. Repulsive softness cut again exhaling
a stench unbearable. Were opening trenches on a piece of land that
had served as a cemetery to the Turks.

Bellies swollen split apart under the blades, juices spilling its putrefaction. The need the
guard had forced the Legion to live with his face to the level of the bodies poking at the coalface
of disturbed soil.

- The dead were like truffles on a cake - said the South American -. I had to stay a whole day
with my nose touching the guts of a Turk died two weeks before ... No, war is not chic, captain,
though talk of heroism and sublime things in newspapers and books.

Ulysses wanted to see again to the "three musketeers" before from Thessaloniki, but the battalion
had raised their field, located many miles inland, opposite the first
Bulgarian lines.

Blanes enthusiast and fired his rifle against the murderers of Roger de Flor.

In mid-November came the Mare Nostrum Marseille.

Its captain always experienced some admiration to round the Cape Croisette, watching the bow
opened to a vast Maritime curve.

In the center of it, a steep hill and moved towards the sea naked, holding at its peak the basilica
and the square tower of Our Lady of the Guard.

Marseille was the metropolis of the Mediterranean, the port terminal for all boaters mare nostrum.
In the bay, from short waves rose several islands yellowish stripes foam, and one novel robust
towers Chateau d'If.

Everyone from Ferragut to the last sailors, looked like something out of city was hovering at
the bottom of the bay, its forests of masts and buildings crowding gray, over which shone the
Byzantine domes of the new cathedral. Around Marseille Chamber opened a dry bare heights, colored
brightly by the sun Provence. The towns and villages dotting these
slopes white and fortified towns, "Villas" of delight from the merchants
of the city.

Beyond the semicircle, the horizon was enclosed by an amphitheater of rough, dark mountains.

In
previous trips, the sight of the giant Virgin golden, shining like a spear of fire on top of
Our Lady of the Guard, spreading the joy on the bridge ship.

- Marseille, Toni! - Said the captain merrily -. Invites you to a home bouillabaisse Pascal.

And
Toni contracted the hairy face of gluttony smile seeing in advance
the famous restaurant port, halls smelling of twilight to seafood
and spicy sauces, and on the table the deep dish of fish with a delicious
broth tinged with saffron.

But now Odysseus had lost his vigorous joy of life. Eyes gazed upon the city loving but sad. Was
seen disembarking the last time, ill, without a will, stunned by
the tragic death of his son.

The Mare Nostrum came to the mouth of the old port, taking his right batteries Faro. The old
port was the most interesting memories of the former Marseille. Penetrated as a Water Knife in
the bowels of the settlement, the city extended their docks. Was a square to the huge water that
flowed all the streets, but their area was negligible for maritime
traffic, and eight new ports coming to cover the entire northern shore
of the bay.

An endless rubble, a wall longer than the city, stretched parallel to the sea, and space between the
bank and this obstacle, which required to froth and roar to the waves,
extending the eight large ports, communicating with each other from
the so-called de la Joliette, which was accessible to as far Stake.

Latter still dragged inland by the great underground channel which connects to the city the
Rhone.

Ferragut had been anchored in this series of coats of marine and even the whole earth of all ages.
Beside huge ocean liners the venerable swinging their dicks tartans
and some Greek ships, heavy and archaic forms, which were reminiscent
of the fleet described in the Iliad.

In its Circular Quay all Mediterranean men: mainland Greeks and islands Levantine coast of Asia,
Spanish, Italians, Algerians, Moroccans, Egyptians. Many kept their original costumes, and
clothing to the wide diversity joined language, some mysterious and almost lost. Attracted by the
confusion as oral, the French themselves forgot their language, speaking the dialect of Marseille,
which preserves traces Indelible Greek origin.

Mare nostrum crossed the outer harbor, the docks of Joliette, that of Lazareto, sliding slowly
through the steps of communication between groups of pedestrians and cars waiting restoration
of open steel swing bridges to its bow. Then went to anchor Arenc in the dock, near the docks.

When Ferragut could land, he realized the great transformation experienced by this port during the war.

The
traffic there was peacetime. Gender were not an infinite variety,
as usual.

At the docks just piled cargoes, monotonous and uniform, food or war material.

Gone were also the legions of downloaders. All were in the trenches. The banks were swept now by
women, and downloads the effected detachments Senegalese sharpshooters. Shivered with cold
in winter and sunny days hunched as dying in the rain or the breath
of the mistral.

Working with the red cap draft on the ears, and lower high in their tasks were rushing to put
their hands in their pockets cape. These black vocal groups formed around a bundle or a piece four
men had moved in ordinary time, and the passage of a woman or of a vehicle I was neglecting work,
turning their faces to hell with a childlike curiosity.

The download crowded into the main docks for the same items: wheat, much wheat and sulfur and saltpeter
for the composition of explosive materials.

In other halls were lined to thousands of pairs of gray wheels, hold guns and trucks, the big
boxes as houses containing planes, the steel parts that serve as scaffolding to the heavy artillery;
crates of rifles and cartridges, huge packages of canned food and sanitary materials; all
the equipment of the army that fought at the remote end of the Mediterranean.

Several platoons of men preceded and followed by bayonets marched from one port to another with
rhythmic step.

German prisoners were smiling and happy in spite of the captive still wearing their uniforms
of green cabbage, with a round hat on his head sheared. Iban to work inside the vessels, loading
or unloading the material to be used for the extermination of his countrymen and friends.

In the docks, the vapors showed extremely enlarged.

On arrival only stood on the dock a few feet of rail, but now that its cargo was stacked on land,
seemed like enormous strengths. Two thirds of the town hidden in the sea were always exposed,
showing the red piping on its belly. Only her keel was kept in water. The top third, which was
visible above the waterline in Ordinary Time was now a simple cornice crowned the long black
wall purple. Sticks and fireplaces, dwarfed by this transformation, seemed to belong to another
smaller vessel.

All these peaceful merchant steamers and carried a gun in the stern
to get rid of underwater pirates.

England and France had mobilized their tramps, vagabonds their boats, and began to give them means
of defense. Some were unable to mount the gun on a fixed carriage, and wore a piece of land
artillery, his mouth hovering between wheels nailed to the deck.

The captain, in all his walks, he was attracted by the famous Cannebière, via sucking that sucks
the whole activity of Marseille.

Some days, a fresh wind in her violent swirling dust and papers. The waiters in the cafes lashed
the big awning as if they were the sails of a ship. Mistral was approaching, and every owner of
established order to meet the maneuver the ice storm that turns tables, grabs seats and takes everything
that is not insured with marine mooring.

Ferragut thought he saw on the famous Marseilles an anteroom of Thessaloniki. The same types
East Army circulated by their sidewalks, khaki-clad British, Canadian and Australians raised
brimmed hats, large and slender Asian Indian, copper-skinned and beard in a fan; shooters Senegalese,
a black patent leather handles Annamese, round face and yellow, with triangle eyes. Trucks
constantly passing dark guided by soldiers, cars full of officers, mule trains from of Spain
that was to be shipped to the East, and live scattered trotting behind her smell sharp and brave
block.

The old port Ferragut attracted by its antiquity, almost as remote as the first navigation Mediterranean.
In this place of water sandwiched between their poor houses were anchored ships as early Phoenicians,
looking succeeded by migrants from Asia Minor Focea, sailors Greeks
fleeing the Persian invasion.

The bare limestone hills and immediate the port is covered with houses, and thus was born Marsalia,
which was to be centuries later the Lady of the Mediterranean.

His daring sailors down along the Spanish coast, and founded cities
that were centers of civilization to the rude Iberians and Marsalia
it was for the warlike Gauls.

Ferragut, going to the palace of the bag, threw a glance at the statues of the two Eutymenes great
navigators and Pyteas Marseille.

They were the remotest grandparents navigation Mediterranean, the first masters known from history
that it had transposed the columns Hercules, rushing across the Atlantic
mysterious.

One had explored the coasts of Senegal, the other was up more than Ireland and the Orkneys.

The ancient Greek city had been supplanted by others for many centuries. Venice Genoa and Barcelona
were in humble dependence. But when they fell and we will send it's time to prosperity, that prosperity
was accompanied by all the advantages of the time present. He had invented the steam engine,
and ships could easily save Gades Strait obstacle without having to wait weeks to 'sit violence
stream sent across the Atlantic.

He was born on industrialism, and factories thrown inside the rail, recently installed, a wave
of products that fleets were transported to all the peoples of the Mediterranean. Finally, to be
opened the Isthmus of Suez, the city unfolded a prodigious way, becoming an international port,
by contacting the whole earth, multiplying its docks, giant folds where flocks came to agglomerate
as ships of all flags.

The old port, boxed in the city, changing their appearance according
to the hours and the state atmosphere.

In the morning calm was a yellowish green and smelled faintly of water decomposed organic water,
water animal. The oysters and sea urchins positions established in Spring seemed sprinkled with
this water infused seafood.

The days of strong wind, all he was becoming an earthy green and opaque, forming short waves
and continuous, with a slightly yellowish foam. Ships began to dance, creaking under bus pull
straps. Among their helmets and the vertical surface of the springs are formed piles of garbage
restless fish bite down and pecked up by the seagulls.

In the mouth, near the strong venerable St. John and St. Nicholas, the shuttle lifted the two
pillars of steel truss and the bridge that links straight, forming a home triumph.

Armed boats patrolled the surrounding waters came to rest in this historic dock surrounded by
cafes, shops, warehouses, domes and bell towers.

Ferragut saw the fast torpedo boats, wafer-thin walls, dancing at the slightest ripple on their
moorings of twisted steel. Examined the "chaluteros' makeshift military vessels, steamers robust and
short, built for fishing in the bow carrying a gun snap shot. All of these smaller vessels, painted
a metallic gray to blend with the color of water, entered the harbor and out like sentinels
are replaced.

Standing guard on the high seas, beyond the rocky, deserted islands that enclose the bay Marseille,
approaching vessels to recognize their nationality, running at full steam smoke in their hair horizontal
to the point where they hoped to catch the periscope the hidden enemy
between two stools.

There was bad weather that scares them or they fall asleep ... Kept in a storm in sight of the
coast, jumping from wave to wave, with its fragile Boat built to be arrows, and only when other
colleagues were coming to replace them returning to the old port, to rest a few hours at the entrance
of the Cannebière.

The streets of the right bank appealed to Ferragut. Marseille were the former, which there
are still some ruined palaces of the merchants and owners of other centuries. In these narrow
roads, slopes and unclean living prostitution and sad daubed all maritime city.

Jammed in the neighborhood the warriors of the different French Africa,
driven by race and burning desire to get even with the big crunch
surfeits Muslim countries where women live in seclusion jealous.

On every corner there Moroccan infantry groups recently landed or convalescing from his wounds,
soldiers young people with red hats and long coats of yellow mustard. The Zouaves from Algiers
talking with them in a Spanish peppered with Arabic and French.

Black teenagers who served stokers on the ship moves through the steep streets with haunting
eyes glow as prepare a mass kidnapping.

Were lost under the doors, with a stiffness priestly Moors serious riders, dragging the white
alquicel tied at the head like a ball of crisp white, or the purple robe of acute hood, which
gave them the aspect of bearded Red Friars.

Between hospital discharge and the new battle awaiting them in the trenches of the North these warriors
come from distant countries to fight and die sun looking for the strong consolation of women. His
arms had been impatient with a fierce tug of skeletal females and macabre and they appeared
swollen by a false strength, due to bad moods.

Some had the disproportion embryonic fetuses with huge heads serving emaciated bodies to finish.
Other advancing his poor emaciated logs on legs pachyderm wide and
round.

The cash-strapped soldiers looked on with envy and hunger to the women stationed at the gates:
creatures of luxury and excitement, with kilts urinated full of sequins, high boots and yellow
stockings.

The captain was on the summits of these streets, stopping to appreciate the harsh contrast between
them and terminal view. Almost all came down to the old port, with a trail sewage stream in half
jumping from stone to stone.

It was dark as pipes telescope, and the end of their stinking trenches occupied by the deformed
Mujeri is opened a wide rift in light blue. White sailboats were anchored at the end of slope,
a piece of sheet water and the houses opposite the pier, dwarfed
by distance.

In other appeared as the background the mountain of Our Lady of the Guard Basilica with its
sharp and brilliant final statue, resembling a golden flame still and tortuous. Sometimes,
a shortstop, to enter the old port, slipped by mouth of one of these
dark lanes as if it were to the lens of a telescope.

Feeling fatigued the ocean by the smell and squalor of the old districts vicious, returned to
the city center, walking under the trees of the avenues of Meilhan or between flower stalls of Coso
Belz.

One evening, while waiting for the tram at the Cannebière surrounded by other people, again
head with the feeling that someone was looking behind him.

Indeed, he saw a man behind him on the curb, an elegant lady dressed,
clean-shaven, appeared to an Englishman in appearance careful of his
person.

This gentleman had stopped impelled by surprise, as if he had recognized Ferragut.

They exchanged glances of the two, but it awakened no echo in the memory of Captain ... I could
not remember this man. I was almost sure of not having ever seen.

His face shave its metallic-gray eyes, his elegant stiffness, said nothing to his memory. Perhaps
the suffered an unknown error.

This was to be, judging by how quickly separated his gaze from Ferragut, away hastily.

The captain did not give importance to this meeting.

I had forgotten to get on the tram, but minutes later resurfaced in his memory, a new light.
The face of English is presented in his imagination with a relief different from reality. He saw more
clearly that somewhat dim glow of the lamps of the Cannebière ... Passed with indifference their
facial features, in fact, had seen for the first time. But the eyes! ... He knew perfectly those
eyes had met many times with his family. Where? ... When? ...

Accompanied him to his ship the memory of this man as an obsession, unable to make their memory
of a reply to your questions. Then, when viewed in the camera with Toni Stern and the third
officer, returned to forget.

In the following days to go ashore,
its invariably experienced the same memory phenomenon. He was the
captain of the city, forgetting that individual, but on entering the
Cannebière immediately arose in his brain that memory, followed by
an inexplicable anxiety.

"Where is now my English? - Thought -. Where
you've seen before? ... Because there is no doubt we know! "

He looked
curiously from this moment, to all the passersby, and sometimes rushed
step to examine some who resembled him in the back. One evening she
thought she recognized hire a coach whose horse was going to live
trot Prado Avenue, but when he wanted to keep the vehicle on a street
was gone immediately.

The days passed and finally the captain missed
the meeting. Other matters more real and immediate was concerned.
His ship was ready, would be sent to England to carry ammunition for
the army of the East.

The morning of his departure down to the ground
not wanting to get to downtown.

In a street of the docks had a barber
shop frequented by the Spanish captains. Chat quaint barber, born
in Cartagena, the color plates fixed on the wall representing bullfights,
Madrid newspapers left in the rubber couches and a guitar in a corner
of this store did a bit of Spain for the homeless in the Mediterranean.

Ferragut,
before leaving, wanted to give their beards to clipping the master
verbose. When one hour, could leave the barbershop, pulling to the
endless bounces owner, followed by a wide street between two rows
of docks, solitary and silent.

Steel sliding doors were locked and
sealed. Warehouses, empty sound cathedral-like ships, even the strong
odors exhaled from the genres that had kept peacetime: vanilla, cinnamon,
rolls of leather, nitrates and phosphates for chemical fertilizers.
Did not see across the street but a man coming toward him with his
back to the dock. Between the two long walls of bricks came the pier
in the background, with mountains of goods, squares of black boots,
wagons and carts. Beyond were the hulls of ships, sustaining a forest
of poles and chimneys, and ultimately the yellow wall pier the sky
outside and freshly washed by rain, with a herd of placid white puffs
as silky rams.

The man who returned to the harbor and walked with
his eyes fixed on Ferragut stopped suddenly, turning on his heel and
returned to the dock ... This move aroused the curiosity Captain,
sharpening your senses</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>