<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09874</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>231967</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>15040</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Con ochenta
y dos años cumplidos el 3 de Febrero, San Blas bendito, un día después de la Candelaria, ¿para
qué quería vivir más ni qué se le había perdido por acá? Un hombre que sirvió al Rey doce años;
que durante cuarenta y cinco había picado miles de miles de toneladas de piedra en esas carreteras
de Dios, y que siempre fue bien mirado y puntoso, nada tenía que hacer ya, más que encomendarse
al sepulturero para que le pusiera mucha tierra, mucha tierra encima, y apisonara bien. En
cuantito que colocara a las dos criaturas, se acostaría para no levantarse hasta el día del
Juicio por la tarde... ¡y se levantaría el último! Traspasada de pena Benina al oír la referencia
de tanto infortunio, cuya sinceridad no podía poner en duda, dijo al anciano que la llevara
a donde estaba la niña enferma, y pronto fue conducida a un cuarto lóbrego, en la planta baja
de la casa grande de corredor, donde juntos vivían, por el pago de tres pesetas al mes, media
docena de pordioseros con sus respectivas proles. La mayor parte de estos hallábanse a la sazón
en Madrid, buscando la santa perra. Sólo vio Benina una vieja, petiseca y dormilona, que parecía
alcoholizada, y una mujer panzuda, tumefacta, de piel vinosa y tirante, como la de un corambre
repleto, con la cara erisipelada, mal envuelta en trapos de distintos colores. En el suelo,
sobre un colchón flaco, cubierto de pedazos de bayeta amarilla y de jirones de mantas morellanas,
yacía la niña enferma, como de seis años, el rostro lívido, los puños cerrados en la boca.
«Lo que tiene esta criatura es hambre--dijo Benina, que habiéndola tocado en la frente y manos,
la encontró fría como el mármol.

--Puede que así sea, porque cosa caliente no ha entrado en nuestros cuerpos desde ayer».

No necesitó más la bondadosa anciana, para que se le desbordase la piedad, que caudalosa inundaba
su alma; y llevando a la realidad sus intenciones con la presteza que era en ella característica,
fue al instante a la tienda de comestibles, que en el ángulo de aquel edificio existe, y compró
lo necesario para poner un puchero inmediatamente, tomando además huevos, carbón, bacalao...
pues ella no hacía nunca las cosas a medias. A la hora, ya estaban remediados aquellos infelices,
y otros que se agregaron, inducidos del olor que por toda la parte baja de la colmena prontamente
se difundió. Y el Señor hubo de recompensar su caridad, deparándole, entre los mendigos que
al festín acudieron, un lisiado sin piernas, que andaba con los brazos, el cual le dio por
fin noticias verídicas del extraviado Almudena.

Dormía el moro en las casas de Ulpiano, y el día se lo pasaba rezando de firme, y tocando en
un guitarrillo de dos cuerdas que de Madrid había traído, todo ello sin moverse de un apartado
muladar, que cae debajo de la estación de las Pulgas, por la parte que mira hacia la puente
segoviana. Allá se fue Benina despacito, porque el sujeto que la guiaba era de lenta andadura,
como quien anda con las nalgas encuadernadas en suela, apoyándose en las manos, y estas en
dos zoquetes de palo. Por el camino, el hombre de medio cuerpo arriba aventuró algunas indicaciones
críticas acerca del moro, y de su conducta un tanto estrafalaria. Creía él que Almudena era
en su tierra clérigo, quiere decirse, presbítero del Zancarrón, y en aquellos días hacía las
penitencias de la Cuaresma majometana, que consisten en dar zapatetas en el aire, comer sólo
pan y agua, y mojarse las palmas de la mano con saliva. «Lo que canta con la cítara ronca,
debe de ser cosa de funerales de allá, porque suena triste, y dan ganas de llorar oyéndolo.
En fin, señora, allí le tiene usted tumbado sobre la alfombra de picos, y tan quieto que parece
que lo han vuelto de piedra».

Distinguió, en efecto, Benina la inmóvil figura del ciego, en un vertedero de escorias, cascote
y basuras, que hay entre la vía y el camino de las Cambroneras, en medio de una aridez absoluta,
pues ni árbol ni mata, ni ninguna especie vegetal crecen allí. Siguió adelante el despernado,
y Benina, con su cesta al brazo, subió gateando por la escombrera, no sin trabajo, pues aquel
material suelto de que formado estaba el talud, se escurría fácilmente. Antes de que ganar
pudiera la altura en que el africano se encontraba, anunció a gritos su llegada, diciéndole:
«¡Pero, hijo, vaya un sitio que has ido a escoger para ponerte al sol! ¿Es que quieres secarte,
y volverte cuero para tambores?... ¡Eh... Almudena, que soy yo, que soy yo la que sube por
estas escaleras alfombradas!... Chico, ¿pero qué?... ¿Estás tonto, estás dormido?».

El marroquí no se movía, la cara vuelta hacia el sol, como un pedazo de carne que se quisiera
tostar. Tirole la anciana una, dos, tres piedrecillas, hasta que consiguió acertarle. Almudena
se movió con estremecimiento; y poniéndose de rodillas, exclamó: «B'nina, tú B'nina.

--Sí, hijo mío: aquí tienes a esta pobre vieja, que viene a verte al yermo donde moras. ¡Pues
no te ha dado mala ventolera! ¡Y que no me ha costado poco trabajo encontrarte!

--¡B'nina!--repitió el ciego con emoción infantil, que se revelaba en un raudal de lágrimas,
y en el temblor de manos y pies--. Tú vinir cielo.

--No, hijo, no--replicó la buena mujer, llegando por fin junto a él, y dándole palmetazos en
el hombro--. No vengo del cielo, sino que subo de la tierra por estos maldecidos peñascales.
¡Vaya una idea que te ha dado, pobre morito! Dime: ¿y es tu tierra así?».

No contestó Mordejai a esta pregunta; callaron ambos. El ciego la palpaba con su mano trémula,
como queriendo verla por el tacto.

«He venido--dijo al fin la mendiga--porque me pensé, un suponer, que estarías muerto de hambre.

--Mí no comier...

--¿Haces penitencia? Podías haberte puesto en mejor sitio...

--Este micor... monte bunito.

--¡Vaya un monte! ¿Y cómo llamas a esto?

--Monte Sinaí... Mí estar Sinaí.

--Donde tú estás es en Babia.

--Tú vinir con ángeles, B'nina... tú vinir con fuego.

--No, hijo: no traigo fuego ni hace falta, que bastante achicharradito estás aquí. Te estás
quedando más seco que un bacalao.

--Micor... mí quierer seco... y arder como paixa.

--En paja te convertirías si yo te dejara. Pero no te dejo, y ahora vas a comer y beber de
lo que traigo en mi cesta.

--Mí no comier... mí ser squieleto».

Sin esperar a más razones, Almudena extendió las manos, palpando en el suelo. Buscaba su guitarro,
que Benina vio y cogió, rasgueando sus dos cuerdas destempladas.

«¡Dami, dami!--le dijo el ciego impaciente, tocado de inspiración».

Y agarrando el instrumento, pulsó las cuerdas, y de ellas sacó sonidos tristes, broncos, sin
armónica concordancia entre sí. Y luego rompió a cantar en lengua arábiga una extraña melopea,
acompañándose con sonidos secos y acompasados que de las dos cuerdas sacaba. Oyó Benina este
canticio con cierto recogimiento, pues aunque nada sacó en limpio de la letra gutural y por
extremo áspera, ni en la cadencia del son encontró semejanza con los estilos de acá, ello es
que la tal música resultaba de una melancolía intensa. Movía el ciego sin cesar su cabeza,
cual si quisiera dirigir las palabras de su canto a diferentes partes del cielo, y ponía en
algunas endechas una vehemencia y un ardor que denotaban el entusiasmo de que estaba poseído.

«Bueno, hijo, bueno--le dijo la anciana cuando terminó de cantar--. Me gusta mucho tu música...
Pero ¿el estómago no te dice que a él no le catequizas con esas coplas, y que le gustan más
las buenas magras?

--Comier tú... mí cantar... Comier yo con alegría de ser tú migo.

--¿Te alimentas con tenerme aquí? ¡Bonita substancia!

--Mí quierer ti...

--Sí, hijo, quiéreme; pero haz cuenta de que soy tu madre, y que vengo a cuidar de ti.

--Tú ser bunita.

--¡Mia que yo bonita... con más años que San Isidro, y esta miseria y esta facha!».

No menos inspirado hablando que cantando, Almudena le dijo: «Tú ser com la zucena, branca...
Com palmera del D'sierto cintura tuya... rosas y casmines boca tuya... la estrella de la tarde
ojitas tuyas.

--¡María Santísima! Todavía no me había yo enterado de lo bonita que soy.

--Donzellas tudas, invidia de ti tenier ellas... Hiciéronte manos Dios con regocijación. Loan
ti ángeles con cítara.

--¡San Antonio bendito!... Si quieres que te crea todas esas cosas, me has de hacer un favor:
comer lo que te traigo. Después que tengas llena la barriga hablaremos, pues ahora no estás
en tus cabales».

Diciéndolo, iba sacando de la cesta pan, tortilla, carne fiambre y una botella de vino. Enumeraba
las provisiones, creyendo que así le despertaría el apetito, y como argumento final le dijo:
«Si te empeñas en no comer, me enfado, y no vuelvo más a verte. Despídete de mi boca de rosas,
y de mis ojitos como las estrellas del cielo... Y luego has de hacer todo lo que yo te mande:
volverte a Madrid, y vivir en tu casita como antes vivías.

--Si tú casar migo, sí... Si no casar, no.

--¿Comes o no comes? Porque yo no he venido aquí a perder el tiempo echándote sermones--declaró
Benina desplegando toda la energía de su acento--. Si te empeñas en ayunar, me voy ahora mismo.

--Comier tú...

--Los dos. He venido a verte, y a que almorcemos juntos.

--¿Casar tú migo?

--¡Ay qué pesado el hombre! Pareces un chiquillo. Me veré obligada a darte un par de mojicones...
Ha, morito, come y aliméntate, que ya se tratará lo del casorio. ¿Piensas que voy yo a tomar
un marido seco al sol, y que se va quedando como un pergamino?».

Con estas y otras razones logró convencerle, y al fin el desdichado dejó de hacer ascos a la
comida. Empezando con repulgos, acabó por devorar con voracidad. Pero no abandonaba su tema,
y entre bocado y bocado, decía: «Casar yo tigo... dirnos terra mía... Yo casar por arreligión
tuya si quierer tú... Tú casar por arreligión mía, si quierer ella... Mí ser d'Israel... Bautisma
jacieron mí señoritas confirencia... Poner mí nombre Joseph Marien Almudena...

--José María de la Almudena. Si eres cristiano, no me hables a mí de otras arreligiones malas.

--No haber más que un Dios, uno solo, sólo Él--exclamó el ciego, poseído de exaltación mística--.
Él melecina a los quebrantados de corazón... Él contar número estrellas, y a tudas ellas por
nombre llama. Adoran Adonai el animal y tuda cuatropea, y el pájaro de ala... ¡Alleluyah!...

--Hombre, sí, cantemos ahora las aleluyas para que no nos haga daño la comida.

--Voz de Adonai sobre las aguas, sobre aguas mochas. La voz de Adonai con forza, la voz de
Adonai con jermosura. La voz de Adonai quiebra los alarzes del Lebanón y Tsión como fijos de
unicornios... La voz de Adonai corta llamas de fuego, face temblar D'sierto; fará temblar Adonai
D'sierto de Kader... La voz de Adonai face adoloriar ciervas... En palacio suyo tudas decir
grolia. Adonai por el diluvio se asentó... Adonai bendecir su puelbro con paz...».

Aún prosiguió recitando oraciones hebraicas en castellano del siglo XV, que en la memoria desde
la infancia conservaba, y Benina le oía con respeto, aguardando que terminase para traerle
a la realidad y sujetarle a la vida común. Discutieron un rato sobre la conveniencia de tornar
a la posada de Santa Casilda; mas no parecía él dispuesto a complacerla en extremo tan importante,
mientras no le diese ella palabra formal de aceptar su negra mano. Trató de explicar la atracción
que, en el estado de su espíritu, sobre él ejercían los áridos peñascales y escombreras en
que a la sazón se encontraba. Realmente, ni él sabía explicárselo, ni Benina entenderlo; pero
el observador atento bien puede entrever en aquella singular querencia un caso de atavismo
o de retroacción instintiva hacia la antigüedad, buscando la semejanza geográfica con las soledades
pedregosas en que se inició la vida de la raza... ¿Es esto un desatino? Quizás no.

XXIX

Con todo su ingenio y travesura no pudo la anciana convencer al marroquí de la oportunidad
de volverse al Madrid alto. «Y no sé--le dijo echando mano de todos los argumentos--, no sé
cómo vas a arreglarte para vivir en este monte de tus penitencias. Porque tú no pides; aquí
nadie ha de traerte el garbanzo, como no sea yo; y yo, si ahora tengo algún dinero, pronto
me quedaré sin una mota, y tendré que volver a pedirlo con vergüenza. ¿Esperas tú que aquí
te caiga el maná?

--Cader sí manjá--replicó Almudena con profunda convicción.

--Fíate de eso... Pero dime otra cosa, hijito: ¿habrá por aquí dinero enterrado?

--Haber mocha, mocha.

--Pues, hijo, a ver si lo sacas, que en este caso no perderías el tiempo. Pero ¡quia! no creo
yo las papas que tú cuentas, ni las hechicerías que te has traído de tu tierra de infieles...
No, no: aquí no hay salvación para el pobre; y eso de sacar tesoros, o de que le traigan a
uno las carretadas de piedras preciosas, me parece a mí que es conversación.

--Si tú casar migo, mí encuentrar tesoro mocha.

--Bueno, bueno... Pues ponte a trabajar para la averiguación de dónde está la tinaja llena
de dinero. Yo vendré a sacarla, y como sea verdad, a casarnos tocan».

Diciéndolo, recogía en su cesta los restos de comida para marcharse. Almudena se opuso a que
se fuese tan pronto; pero ella insistía en retirarse, con la firmeza que gastaba en toda ocasión:
«¡Pues estaría bueno que me quedara yo aquí, puesta al sol y al aire como un pellejo en secadero
de curtidores! Y dime, Almudenita: ¿me vas tú a mantener aquí? ¿Y a mi señora, quién le mantiene
el pico?».

Esta referencia a la casa de la señora despertó en Mordejai el recuerdo del galán bunito; y
como se excitara más de la cuenta con tal motivo, apresurose Benina a calmarle con la noticia
de que Ponte se había marchado ya a sus palacios aristocráticos, y de que ni ella ni su ama
Doña Francisca querían trato ni roce con aquel viejo camastrón, que les había dado un mal pago,
despidiéndose a la francesa, y quedándoles a deber el pupilaje. Tragose el africano esta bola
con infantil candor; y haciendo prometer y jurar a su amiga que a verle volvería diariamente
mientras él continuase en aquella obligación de sus acerbas penitencias, la dejó marchar. Fuese
Benina por arriba, prefiriendo subir hacia la estación, como salida más cómoda y practicable.

De vuelta a casa, lo primero que su señora le preguntó fue si sabía cuándo regresaba de Guadalajara
D. Romualdo, a lo que respondió ella que no se tenían aún noticias seguras del regreso del
señor. Nada ocurrió aquel día digno de notarse, sino que Ponte mejoraba rápidamente, poniéndose
muy gozoso con la visita de Obdulia, que estuvo cuatro horas platicando con él y con su mamá
de cosas elegantes, y de sucesos rondeños anteriores en cuarenta años a la época presente.
Debe hacerse notar también que a Benina se le iba mermando el dinero, pues comió allí la niña,
y fue preciso añadir merluza al ordinario condumio, y además dátiles y pastas para postres.
Con el gasto de aquellos días, con las prodigalidades caritativas en las Cambroneras, los duros
que restaron del préstamo de la Pitusa, después de saldados débitos apremiantes, se iban reduciendo
por horas, hasta quedar en uno solo, o poco más, el día de la tercera escapatoria al arrabal
del Puente de Toledo.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10379</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>137060</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>13926</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Eighty and two
years old on February 3, San Blas blessed, a day after the Candelaria, why what I wanted to live
or what had been lost here? A man who served the King twelve years that for forty-five had been
stung thousands of thousands of tons of stone on these roads of God, and that was always well regarded
and puntoso, had nothing to do and, more to entrust the gravedigger who put a lot of land, much
land over, and pack it. In quantitative placed the two creatures, would lie not rise until
the day of Judgement in the afternoon ... And rise last! Pierced with grief upon hearing the
reference Benina so much misfortune, whose sincerity could not put into question, said the old man
to take her to where the child was ill, and soon was conducted to a room dark, on the ground
floor Large house corridor, where they lived together, for the payment of three pesetas a month,
average dozen beggars with their offspring. Most of these complained bitterly at the time in
Madrid, looking for the holy bitch. Benina saw only an old, petiseca and sleepy, it seemed drunk,
and a potbellied female, swollen, vinous, tight skin, like a corambre filled with the face Erysipelas,
poorly wrapped in cloths of different colors. On the ground, on a thin mattress covered with pieces
of yellow cloth and tattered blankets Morella, lay the sick girl, about six years, the pale
face, clenched fists in the mouth. "What has this creature is hungry - Benina said, who, having touched
on the forehead and hands, found it cold as marble.

- Maybe so, because hot thing has not come into our bodies from yesterday.

"

No longer needed a kind old lady, that it overwhelms the piety, which flooded mighty your soul and
bringing to reality his intentions with the speed that was her property, was at once to the grocery
store in the corner of that building there, and bought you need to get a pot immediately, also
taking eggs, coal, cod ... because she never did things by halves. At the time, and were remedied
those unhappy and others were added, the smell induced across the bottom of the hive soon spread.
And the Lord had to reward his charity, department, among the beggars attended the banquet,
a cripple with no legs, walking with arms, that he gave him true news of the lost order Almudena.

Moor
slept in the homes of Ulpian, and he spent the day praying hard,
and playing a guitar with two strings that Madrid had brought all
this without leaving a section dunghill, which falls below the flea
season, at the bridge looking towards Segovia.

There he was Benina slowly, because the person who guided journey was slow, as one who walks
with the buttocks bound in soil, on hands, and these in two billets of wood. By the way, the man
from the waist upwards ventured some indications criticism of the Moor, and somewhat bizarre
behavior. He thought that was Almudena cleric in the land, wants to say, priest of Zancarrón,
and in those days was the majometana penance of Lent, which consists of giving heels in the
air, eat only bread and water, and moisten palms with saliva. "What the harp sings hoarse should be
a matter of funerals there, because it sounds sad and mourn feel like hearing it. In short,
madam, there you have it lying on the carpet of peaks, and so still it seems who have turned
to stone. "

Distinguished, in fact, Benina the motionless figure of the blind, in a landfill, slag, rubble
and garbage, which is between the road and the path of Cambroneras amid absolute aridity, for neither
tree nor bush, nor any plant species growing there.

He went on the despernado, and Benin, with his basket on his arm, crawling up the heap, not without
difficulty, for he loose material that formed was the slope, slipped easily. Before winning could
the height at which the African was, loudly announced their arrival, saying: "But, son, go to
a site that has been to choose to put the sun! Do you want to dry off, and become leather drums?
... Eh ... Almudena, who am I, who am I going up these carpeted stairs! ... Chico, but what?
... Are you stupid, you asleep? ".

The Moroccan did not move, her face turned toward the sun, like a piece of meat would toasting.
Tirole the old one, two, three stones, until he got hit.

Almudena moved with trepidation, and his knees, cried: "B'nina, you B'nina.

- Yes, my son: here's this poor old woman, who comes to see the wilderness
where you dwell.

Well has not given you bad gust of wind! And that does not cost me a little work to find you!

-
B'nina! - Excitedly repeated the blind child, who was revealed in
a flood of tears, and the shaking of hands and feet -.

You vinir sky.

- No, son, no - said the good woman, and arrived with him, and giving slaps on shoulder -. Not
come from heaven, but I go to these cursed land crags. What an idea that has given you poor
Moor! Tell me, what is your country like that? ".

Mordechai did not answer this question, silenced them.

The blind man felt it with his hand trembling as if seeing it for the touch.

"I came - said the beggar at the end - because I thought, a guess,
you'd be starving.

- Did not eat me ...

- Do you do penance?

You could have put in a better place ...

- This micor ... Mount
Bunite.

- What a mountain!

What do you call this?

- Mount Sinai ... Me to be Sinai.

- Where you are is in the clouds.

-
You vinir with angels, B'nina ... vinir you with fire.

- No, son,
do not bring fire or necessary, that enough achicharradito're here.

You're being drier than a cod.

- Micor ... I want to dry ... and burn like paix.

- In straw you
would become if I let you.

But do not leave, and now you eat and drink I bring in my basket.

-
Did not eat me ... squieleto me to be.

"

Without waiting for more reasons, Almudena spread his hands, touching
the ground.

He sought his guitar, Benin saw and picked up, two-stringed strumming intemperate.

"Dami, dami! - Said the blind impatient, inspiration hit."

And grabbing the instrument, struck the strings, and got them sounds sad, Broncos, without harmonic
coherence between them. And then began to sing in Arabic a strange chant, accompanied with dry
and rhythmic sounds that drew the two strings. Benina heard this Cantici with true devotion,
for though it told him nothing of the lyrics and guttural extremely rough, or the cadence of
similarity are found here styles, it is that such music was an intense melancholy. Constantly
moving the blind head, as if to lead the words of her song to different parts of the sky, and
set in Lays some vehemence and enthusiasm burning denoting that he was possessed.

"Well, son, well - the old woman said when she finished singing -. I really like your music
... But the stomach does not tell you that he does not catechins
with these songs, and that you like best good lean?

- Eat your ...
me singing ... I ate with you the joy of being me.

- Do you feed
it with me here?

Bonita substance!

- Me wants you ...

- Yes, son, love me, but please realize that I
am your mother, and I come to take care of you.

- You be Bunite.

-
Mia I pretty ... more years of San Isidro, and this misery and this
fascist!

".

No less inspired talking than singing, Almudena said, "You be the
zucena com, branca ... D'Com palm desert belt of yours ... casmines
roses and mouth you ... the evening star thine eyes.

- Mary!

I had not yet learned how beautiful I am.

- Donzella tudas, envy of you had them ... Regocijación Hiciéronte
God hands.

Loan you angels with harp.

- San Antonio blessed!

... If you wish to create all those things you must do me a favor eat what you bring. After you
have filled your belly talk, now you're not in your right mind. "

Saying, was taken out of the basket bread, tortillas, canned meat and a bottle of wine. Listing provisions,
believing that this will awaken the appetite, and as the final argument said: "If you insist
on not eating, I get angry, and not be back again to see you. Say goodbye to my mouth of roses
and my eyes as the stars of heaven ... And then you have to do everything that I command you:
Come back to Madrid, and live in your house as soon as you lived.

-
If you marry me, this yes ... If not married, no.

- Do you eat or
not eat?

Because I have not come here to waste time by lying sermons - said
Benina displaying all the energy of her accent -.

If you insist on fasting, I'm going now.

- Eat your ...

- Both.

I come to you, and have lunch together.

- Casar thou me?

- Oh really heavy man! You look like a boy.

I will be forced to give you a couple of punches ... Ha, Moor, eat and feed, which will be discussed
at the wedding. Do you think I'm going to take a husband dry in the sun, which is lagging like
a scroll? ".

With these and other reasons persuaded him, and finally stopped the
unfortunate to be squeamish food.

Beginning with Repulgue, eventually devouring voraciously.

But he did not leave his subject, and in between bites, said: "I tigo Casar ... terra Dirna mine
... I married for arreligión yours if you want ... Arreligión you marry for me, if you want
it ... Me be d'Israel ... Baptism jacieron confirencia me ladies
... Put my name Joseph Marien Almudena ...

- José María de la Almudena.

If you are a Christian, talk to me no other arreligiones bad.

- Not have more than one God, one, only he - said the blind man, possessed of mystic exaltation
-. He melecina to the brokenhearted ... He stars count number, and by them tudas name calling. Adonai
love animals and Tuda cuatropea, and the bird-wing ... Alleluyah! ...

- Well, yes, now let us sing Alleluia to not hurt us food.

- Voice of Adonai on the water, on water mochas. The voice of Adonai with forza, voice Adonai with
jermosura. Adonai's voice breaks the Alarza of Lebanon and as fixed Tsion unicorns ... The voice of
Adonai short flames, face D'desert tremble, tremble Farah Adonai Kader D'desert ... The voice of
Adonai face adoloriar deer ... In his palace that tudas Grolier. Adonai settled by the flood
... Adonai bless her with peace puelbro ...».

Even continued reciting prayers in Hebrew fifteenth century Castilian, which from memory retained children,
and respect Benina heard him, waiting to bring it ended to reality
and subject to the common life.

They talked a while about the desirability of making to the Inn of
Santa Casilda, but he seemed not willing to please extremely important,
while not giving her word to accept his black formal hand.

He tried to explain the attraction that, in the state of his mind, he exerted on the crags
and tailings in arid at that time was. Actually, he knew not explain or understand Benina but
attentive observer may well be a glimpse into this strange fondness a case of atavism or feedback
to the old instinct, seeking the solitude geographical similarity rocky in the beginning of
the life of the race ... Is this nonsense? Maybe not.

XXIX

With all his wit and mischief could not convince the old Moroccan
opportunity Madrid turning to the high.

"I do not know - he said using all the arguments - I do not know how are you going to fix you
to live in this mountain of your penance. Because you do not ask, here one has to bring you the
pea, except to me, and I, if now I have some money soon I'll be without a speck, and I will
have to order it with shame. Do you expect you here dropping your mana?

- Yes manj Cader - Almudena replied with deep conviction.

- Trust that ... But tell me one thing, son: Will there be money buried here?

- Have mocha, mocha.

- Well, son, see if you take it out, which in this case would not
waste time.

But quia! I do not think me that you count potatoes or witchcraft that you've brought your
land of infidels ... No, no: there is no salvation for the poor, and that removing treasures,
or bring it one the truckloads of precious stones, it seems to me that it is conversation.

-
If you marry me, this I find treasures mocha.

- Well, well ... Then get to work for the investigation of where the barrel filled money. I will
come to draw with, and as true, to marry touch. "

Saying, collected in your basket leftovers to go. Almudena opposed it was so soon, but she insisted
on retiring, the firm he spent on all occasions "Then it would be good for me to stay I'm
here, put the sun and the air like a coat in the dryer Tanners! And tell me, Almudenita: are you
going to keep me here? And my wife, who keeps the peak? ".

This reference to the home of Mrs. Mordechai awakened the memory of the gallant Bunite, and as
excite more than usual on this occasion, hastened to soothe Benina the news that Ponte had
already left their aristocratic palaces, and that neither she nor her mistress Dona Francisca wanted
to try and brush with sly old man who had given them a poorly paid, farewell to the French, and the
boarding was a duty. The African Tragose this ball with childlike innocence, and promise and
swear by her friend that day to see him again While he continued
in that obligation of its bitter penance, let him go. Was Benina above,
preferring to go to the station, as output more comfortable and practical.

Back
home, the first thing his wife was asked if he knew when he returned
from Guadalajara D. Romualdo, to which she replied that no news had
yet to secure the return of sir. Nothing occurred worthy of note that
day, but quickly improved Ponte, putting very joyful with the visit
of Obdulia, which spent four hours talking with him and his mom of
fancy things, and Ronda events forty years earlier in the present
era. It should be noted also that he was undermining Benina money
because the child ate there, and it was necessary to add stuffing
hake regular, plus dates and pastries for dessert. With the expense
of those days, with the prodigality charitable Cambroneras, harsh
which subtracted from the loan Pitusa after pressing debts paid off,
they would reduce for hours to get into one, or so, the day of the
third escape from the suburbs Toledo Bridge</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>