<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05189</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>661225</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>699</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Merced a esta fuerza ha podido reunir su inmenso
capital. Al tender la vista por esta distinguida asamblea, observo con júbilo que todos los
que la componen han sido dotados también de una buena parte de esta fuerza nativa o acumulada
por la herencia. Por ello les felicito con toda mi alma. Lo esencial en este mundo que habitamos
es nacer aptos para la lucha. Para no ser aplastados es menester aplastar. Y yo me felicito,
repito, de encontrarme entre los elegidos de los dioses, aquellos que su providencia ha marcado
con el sello de la felicidad....

--Oye, chica--dijo Pepa Frías acercando su boca al oído de Clementina:--esto parece el brindis
de Mefistófeles.

Clementina sonrió ligeramente.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08737</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>272725</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>657</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Thanks to this force was able to meet its huge capital.
By reaching this distinguished assembly view, I note with joy that all that it consists were
also fitted with a good part of this force or total native by heredity. Therefore, I congratulate
you with all my heart. The essential thing in this world we inhabit is suitable for birth control.
To avoid being crushed is necessary to crush. And I congratulate I repeat, to be among the chosen
of the gods, those whose providence has marked with the seal of happiness ....

- Hey, girl - Pepa Frias said bringing his mouth to ear Clementina - this seems a toast Mephistopheles.

Clementina
smiled faintly.
</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>