<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03526</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>576727</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>720</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Las culebras del monte cantaban con una voz extraña en
este silencio. Cantaban, sí señor. No había quien se lo discutiese al Lobato; lo había oído
mil veces, y dudar de esto era llamarle embustero, exponiéndose a sentir el peso de sus manazas.
Y así como cantaban los reptiles, hablaban los toros; sólo que él no había llegado a penetrar
todos los misterios de su idioma. Eran a modo de cristianos, aunque andaban a cuatro patas
y tenían cuernos. Había que verlos despertar cuando surgía la aurora. Saltaban gozosos como
niños; jugueteaban acometiéndose de mentirijillas y cruzando sus cuernos; intentaban montarse
unos a otros, con una alegría ruidosa, como si saludasen la presencia del sol, que es la gloria
de Dios. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document05406</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>110098</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>645</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Snakes of the mountain with a strange voice singing in this
silence. Singing, yes sir. There was no one discussed it at Lobato, I had heard thousand times,
and doubt this call was a liar, exposing them to feel the weight of his paws. And as they sang the
reptiles, spoken by the bulls, only that he had failed to penetrate all the mysteries of their
language. Were like Christians, but walked on all fours and had horns. Seen them awake when
the dawn came. Joyful leaping as children, toys and cross-believe rushing their horns, trying
to mount each other, with a noisy joy, as if he welcomed the presence of the sun, which is the
glory of God.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>