<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document03472</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>24797</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>736</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Las costumbres
son generalmente libres; las pasiones violentas, sobre todo en Málaga y Valencia; la franqueza
es genial. La mujer carece en lo general de timidez. La vanidad no es rara en todas las clases.

La poblacion del segundo grupo (que comprende mas de la mitad de la total de España en el continente)
es de un tipo generalmente inferior, ó el ménos bello de los del pais. Las fisonomías son severas
y frias, pero sin aspereza, y sus líneas muy pronunciadas. Allí los tipos hermosos no tienen
seduccion sino majestad. Inclinacion general á la holganza, y desaseo en los hábitos. Fuertes
instintos de mendicidad. El sentimiento de la personalidad mucho ménos vigoroso que en los
demas grupos. Tendencia muy notable al misticismo. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00067</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>9562</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>662</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Customs are generally
free, the violent passions, especially in Málaga and Valencia openness is great. Women generally
lacking in shyness. Vanity is not uncommon in all classes.

The population of the second group (comprising more than half the total of Spain on the continent)
is of a type generally lower, or the less beautiful of the country. The faces are severe and
cold, but without harshness, and its very sharp lines. There are beautiful no rates seduction
but majesty. General inclination to leisure, and untidy in habits. Strong instincts of begging.
The feeling of personality much less vigorous than in other groups.
Remarkable tendency to mysticism</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>