<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document09087</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>246279</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>1704</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Esta murmuración contra el cardenal, que subía desde la sacristía hasta el claustro, irritaba
al hermano de Gabriel. El Vara de palo, soldado raso de la Iglesia, no podía escuchar con calma
los ataques a sus superiores. Para él todo eran calumnias. Lo mismo que de don Sebastián, habían
hablado los canónigos de todos los arzobispos anteriores, lo que no impedía que después de
muertos fuesen unos santos. Cuando sorprendía al Tato repitiendo en las Claverías los chismes
de abajo, le amenazaba con toda su autoridad de jefe de la familia.

Esteban se entristecía viendo el estado de salud de su hermano. Alababa la conducta de éste,
siempre prudente, acogiendo con un silencio respetuoso las costumbres de la catedral, sin que
se le escapase una palabra reveladora de su pasado; le enorgullecía la atmósfera de admiración
que rodeaba a su hermano, el afán con que la gente sencilla del claustro escuchaba sus viajes,
pero le apenaba la enfermedad de Gabriel, la certeza de que la muerte había puesto en él su
mano, y únicamente por los cuidados de que le rodeaba iba retardando el momento de la posesión.

Había días en que el silenciario sonreía satisfecho viendo a Gabriel de buen color y oyendo
con menos frecuencia su tos dolorosa.

--Muchacho, eso va bien--decía alegremente.

--Sí--contestaba Gabriel--; pero no te forjes ilusiones. Estoy bien agarrado. Ésa vendrá a
su hora. Tú eres quien la repele. Pero un día podrá más que tú.

La certeza de que la muerte acabaría por vencerlo enardecía a Esteban, haciéndole redoblar
los cuidados. Apelaba a la superalimentación como único remedio, y siempre que se aproximaba
a Gabriel, era con algo en las manos.

--Cómete esto.... Bebe lo que te traigo.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08854</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>15135</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>1852</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

These murmurs against the bishop, that rose from the sacristy up to the cloister, irritated brother
Gabriel. The Wooden Stick, soldier stormed out of the church, he could not listen with peace to
the superior attacks. For him, everything was slander. Same as that of Don Sebastian, they had spoken
with the priests of all the previous archbishops, which did not prevent that after their deaths
they would become saints.

When Tato would be surprised repeating in the priest's office the gossips from below, threatening
him with all his authority of a boss and head of the family. Esteban would be saddened by seeing
his brother's health condition. He would praise his behavior, always prudent, acknowledging with
respectful silence the traditions of the cathedral, without a word escaping that would reveal his
past; the atmosphere of admiration that surrounded his brother made him proud, the eagerness
with which the simple people of the cloister would listen him tell
about his trips, but Gabriel's sickness embarrassed him, the certainty
that death had put its hand on him, and only for the treatments that
surrounded him were slowing down the moment of possession.

There were days in which the Silentiary would smile satisfied as he watched
Gabriel of good color and would listen with less frequency to his
painful cough.

"Boy, that's going
well," he would say cheerfully.

"Yes," Gabriel would answer. But don't
forge dreams.

I have a firm grasp. That will come at its own time.

You are who repeals it. But one day it will come more than you.

The certainty that death would end up beating him would make Esteban fire-up with anger, making
him double the care for his brother. He appealed to super feeding as an only resort, and every time
he would approach Gabriel it was with something in his hands.

"Eat this... Drink what I bring you.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>true</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>