<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05171</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>1048</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>23031</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Ni faltan arriates todo alrededor, en que las flores también abundan; y
para más primor y amparo de las flores, hay encañados vistosos, donde forman las cañas mil
dibujos y laberintos, rematando en triángulos y en otras figuras matemáticas. Las puntas superiores
de las cañas, con que se entretejen aquellas rejas o verjas, suelen tener por adorno sendos
cascarones de huevo o lindos y esmaltados calabacines. Las abejas y las avispas zumban y animan
el patio durante el día. El ruiseñor le da música por la noche.

En el invierno, la cordobesa tiene buen cuidado de que plantas de hoja perenne hermoseen su
habitación. Canarios o jilgueros recuerdan la primavera con sus trinos; y si el amo de casa
es cazador, no faltan perdices y codornices cantoras en sus jaulas, y las escopetas y trofeos
de caza adornan las paredes. En torno del hogar, casi en tertulia con los amos, vienen a colocarse
los galgos y los podencos.

Todavía en las casas aristocráticas de los lugares suele haber uno como bufón o gracioso, que
recuerda, si bien por lo rústico, al lacayo de nuestras antiguas comedias. Este gracioso posee
mil habilidades; caza zorzales con silbato y percha, y jilgueros con liga o red, y pesca anguilas
metiéndose en los charcos y arroyos, y cogiéndolas con la mano. Alguno de estos suele tener
su poco de poeta; da los días a la señora en décimas, y compone coplas en su elogio, y sátiras
contra los rivales o contrarios de sus amos. Acompaña también y entretiene a los niños, y sabe
una multitud de cuentos, que relata con animación y mucha mímica.

La criada de lugar no deja de saber también muchos cuentos, y los cuenta con gracia. Los sabe
de asombros, de encantos y de amores; y todos éstos son serios. Para lo cómico y jocoso atesora
una infinidad de chascarrillos picantes.

Siendo yo pequeñuelo, no me hartaba nunca de oír cuentos que me contaban las criadas de casa.
El más bonito, el que más me deleitaba era el de doña Guiomar, cuyo argumento, en lo esencial,
es el mismo del drama indio de Kalidasa, titulado Sacuntala. Los árabes, sin duda, trajeron
este cuento y otros mil, en la Edad Media, desde el remoto Oriente.

La criada que descuella por lo lista, amena y entretenida, se capta la voluntad y se convierte
siempre en la acompañanta o favorita del ama, o de la niña o señorita soltera. Viene a semejarse
a la confidenta de las tragedias clásicas, y aun puede hacer el papel de Enone. De todos modos
va con su ama a visitas, a misa y a paseo, le lleva y le trae recados, y procura tenerla al
corriente de cuanto pasa en el lugar.

A esto de saber vidas ajenas y de murmurar, menester es confesarlo, hay una deplorable afición
en las hidalgas y ricas labradoras de por allí.

Por lo demás, si hay algo de cierto en el mordaz proverbio que dice: Al andaluz hacedle la
cruz, y al cordobés de manos y pies, bien puede afirmarse que no reza con las mujeres; antes
son víctimas las pobrecitas de lo levantiscos, alborotados y amigos de correrla que son generalmente
los maridos. Ya dice uno que va al campo a ver las viñas o los olivares y a inspeccionar la
poda, la cava u otra labor cualquiera; ya supone otro que va a cazar sub Jove frígido, tenerae
conjugis immemor; ya éste tiene que ir a negocios a la cabeza de partido, o a Córdoba, o a
Madrid por motivos políticos; ya alega aquél que debe ir a Jerez a llevar muestras de vino,
o a alguna feria, a ver si vende o compra ganado: en suma, jamás carece ninguno de pretexto
para estar ausente de su casa la mitad del año. Si el marido es mozo y alegre, suele pasar
meses enteros lejos del techo conyugal. La tierna esposa, entre tanto, queda en la soledad
y en el abandono, y si a menudo se ve asediada por los pretendientes, imita a Penélope y aun
se le adelanta, pues al cabo su marido, ni fue a pasar trabajos y a aventurar la vida en la
guerra de Troya, ni de fijo, salvo raras y laudables excepciones, se muestra más fosco y zahareño
que Ulises con las Circes y Calipsos que en mesones, hosterías, fondas y otras partes se le
aparecen.

Muy de maravillar y muy digna de alabanza es esta fidelidad resignada de la cordobesa. No negaré,
con todo, que a veces agota la cordobesa la resignación y rompe el freno de la paciencia. Entonces
estallan los celos como una tempestad. Me acuerdo de cierta parienta mía que supo que su marido
tenía con todo sigilo a una muchacha en su casa de campo, adonde iba todas las tardes y aun
se quedaba algunas noches, con pretexto de las labores. Apenas lo supo, mandó que pusiesen
las jamugas a la burra, se hizo acompañar en otra burra por su confidenta, y sin que su marido
lo notase, se fue por aquellos vericuetos hasta llegar a la casería. Terrible fue la entrevista
con la pecadora, a quien echó de allí a pescozones.

Debo advertir que en este y otros casos se avivan los celos con poderosas razones económicas.
Tal linaje de mancebas suele ser muy costoso, y remata en la perdición de pingües y desahogados
caudales. No se origina el gasto, ni nace de las galas y dijes, coches y primores que hay que
comprar a la muchacha, ni del boato y pompa con que es menester sostenerla; aunque todo es
relativo y proporcional, y en algo de esto se gasta también. La hetera de lugar es menos exigente,
pedigüeña y antojadiza que las Coras, las Baruccis, las Paivas y otras famosas heteras parisinas:
pero aquéllas son solas, se diría que nacieron como los hongos, y la lugareña tiene un diluvio
de parientes, que se lanza y abate sobre la casa y la hacienda del mantenedor enamorado, como
bandada de langostas hambrientas y voraces. Los primos, los sobrinos, los cuñados, la madre,
las tías, todos, en suma, se creen con derecho a cuanto hay: con derecho al trabajo; y por
consiguiente, con derecho a la asistencia y a la holganza. El aceite sale de tu bodega, no
por panillas, sino por arrobas; las lonjas de tocino vuelan de la despensa; las morcillas transponen;
la manteca se evapora; los jamones se disipan. La parentela entera se alumbra, se calienta,
come, bebe y hasta mora a costa tuya. Si tienes casas, las habitará alguien de la parentela
y no te las pagará; si eres cosechero de vino o aguardiente, menudearán las botas, botijas
y botijuelas, y entrarán vacías y saldrán rebosando.

No se crea, no obstante, que, siendo tan lucrativo este oficio, se dedican muchas mujeres a
él y abaratan el mercado con la competencia. En todo el territorio de Córdoba ha vivido siempre
gente muy hidalga y harto difícil en puntos de honra. Colonia en lo antiguo de verdaderos ciudadanos
romanos, y no de libertos, como otras, mereció y obtuvo el título de patricia; cuando la invasión
mahometana, no vinieron a poblarla rudos y plebeyos berberiscos, sino claros varones de pura
sangre arábiga; los linajes más ilustres de Medina y de la Meca; los descendientes de los ansáres,
tabies y muhadjires. Y por último, habiendo sido mi provincia, durante dos siglos, fronteriza
con el reino de Granada, ha debido tener y ha tenido para custodia y defensa de sus lugares
fuertes, y para tomar el desquite de cualquier ataque, entrando en algarada por los dominios
del alarbe, talando sus mieses y haciendo otras mil insolencias y diabluras, una población
de hombres recios y valerosos,

    Todos hidalgos de honra
    Y enamorados de veras,

como canta el viejo romance. Desde entonces no ha deslucido Córdoba su bien cimentada reputación:
y no por vana jactancia, sino con sobra de motivo, lleva por mote, en torno de los rampantes
leones de su limpio escudo: «Corduba, militiae domus, inclyta fonsque sophiae.» Lucano, Séneca,
Averroes, Ambrosio de Morales, Góngora y mil otros dan testimonio de lo segundo. Acreditan
lo primero, en multitud innumerable, los acérrimos y audaces guerreros que por todos estilos
ha criado Córdoba; ya para pasmo y terror de los enemigos de España, como el Gran Capitán;
ya para perpetua desazón y sobresalto constante de los españoles mansos, como el Tempranillo,
el Guapo Francisco Esteban, el Chato de Benamejí, el Cojo de Encinas-Reales, Navarro el de
Lucena, y Caparrota el de Doña-Mencía.

No es, pues, llano el que haya por allí mucho marido sufrido, mucho padre complaciente, y mucha
interesada y fácil mujer. La que lo es se lo hace pagar caro, no tanto por la rareza, sino
por lo que pierde. Sólo a fuerza de regalos y de espléndida generosidad, y deslumbrando con
su lujo, se hace perdonar en ocasiones sus malos pasos. Aun así, es mirada con desprecio, y
no suelen llamarla con su nombre de pila, sino con un apodo irónico, como, por ejemplo, la
Galga, la Joya, la Guitarrita. Tal vez la designan con el nombre genérico del país de que es
natural, como para designar su origen forastero; y de éstas he conocido yo a la Murciana, a
la Manchega y a la Tarifeña.

Si alguna mocita soltera o alguna casada joven siente veleidades de dejarse seducir y sonsacar,
hay con frecuencia un padre o un marido que la sana y endereza con una buena vara de mimbre.
Ni debe estar muy seguro y descuidado el seductor, por mucho respeto que inspire. No basta
a veces la inocencia, si es que infunde recelos algún galán. Cierto compañero mío de colegio,
en el Sacro Monte, fue, años ha, a curar las almas en un lugar de mi provincia. Era gran teólogo,
recto y virtuoso; pero bien hablado, elegantísimo, peripuesto y agradable; era hombre que en
el siglo XVIII hubiera figurado, en una corte, como el más delicioso abate. Pues bien, en el
pueblo la tomaron con él, y, como vulgarmente se dice, le abroncaron. El brónquis que le dieron
llegó hasta tirarle algunos tiros, pero con pólvora sólo, para asustarle. Él calculó que de
la pólvora, si no surtía efecto, se podría con facilidad pasar a los perdigones, y se largó
con la música y la teología a otra parte menos difícil.

Semejantes extremos son raros, por fortuna. La cordobesa no es coqueta, sino muy prudente y
sigilosa, y a nadie compromete. Aunque sea de la más humilde condición, acostumbra a desahuciar
al paciente enamorado, hablando de su honor, como las damas calderonianas. Cuando esto no basta,
ni chilla, ni alborota, ni escandaliza; pero se defiende cual una Pentesilea; lucha, como el
ángel luchó con Jacob, en las tinieblas de la noche; y robusta, aunque angélica, suele echarle
la zancadilla, derribarle, y hasta darle una soba, todo con muda elocuencia y en silencio maravilloso.
Y no se extrañe esto, porque en la clase de muchachas pobres, y aun en algunas acaudaladas
labradoras, es notable la robustez. Son más duras que el mármol, no sólo de corazón, no sólo
en el centro, sino por toda la perifería. Cierto día hicimos una gira de campo con las más
garridas y principales mozas del lugar. Una de ellas, creyendo el asiento más alto, se sentó
de golpe sobre un montón de tejas. Eran de las macizas y mejores de Lucena. Tres vimos rotas.
Ella nos dijo con encantadora modestia que ya, antes de la caída, lo estaban.

No se entienda, por lo dicho, nada que amengüe o desfigure en lo más mínimo la esbeltez y gentileza
de mis paisanas. Una cosa es la densidad y la firmeza, y otra el desaforado volumen. La moza
que desde niña trabaja, anda mucho y va a la fuente que está en el ejido, volviendo de allí
con el cántaro lleno, apoyado en la cadera, o con la ropa lavada por ella en el arroyo, es
fuerte, pero no gorda. La fuente o el pilar era el término de mi paseo cotidiano, y allí me
sentaba yo en un poyo, bajo un eminente y frondoso álamo negro. Al ver lavar a las chicas,
o llenar los cántaros y subir con ellos tan gallardas, airosas y ligeras, por aquella cuesta
arriba, me trasladaba yo en espíritu a los tiempos patriarcales; y ya me creía testigo de alguna
escena bíblica como la de Rebeca y Eliacer; ya, comparándome con el prudente Rey de Ítaca,
me juzgaba en presencia de la princesa Nausicáa y de sus amables compañeras. Nada de miriñaques
ni ahuecadores en aquellas muchachas. El pobre vestido corto, sobre todo en verano, se ciñe
al cuerpo y se pliega graciosamente, velando y revelando las formas juveniles, como en la estatua
de Diana cazadora.

Por desgracia, las damas del lugar han adoptado, en cuanto cabe, casi todas las modas francesas,
y van perdiendo el estilo propio de vestirse y peinarse. Todas usaron ingentes miriñaques totales,
y ahora usan el miriñaque parcial y pseudo-calípigo que priva. El día menos pensado abandonarán
la mantilla y se pondrán el sombrerito. Todas se peinan, tomando por modelo el figurín, y suelen
llamar a este peinado de cucuné o de remangué, a fin de darle, hasta en el nombre, cierto carácter
extranjero. Las faldas, en vez de llevarlas cortas, las llevan largas, y van barriendo con
la cola el polvo de los caminos. En resolución, es una pena este abandono del traje propio
y adecuado.

A pesar de tales disfraces, la belleza, o al menos la gracia, el garbo y el salero, son prendas
comunes en mis paisanas. Tienen en el andar mucho primor, y más aún si bailan. Los rigodones
y el vals y la polca se van aclimatando; pero el fandango no se desterró todavía. Hasta las
señoritas salen a hacer una mudanza, si las sacan y obligan en cualquiera fiesta campestre,
y se mueven y brincan con gallardía y desenfado, y repiquetean con brío las castañuelas. Mujeres
hay del pueblo que, en esto de bailar y tocar las castañuelas, vencen a la Teletusa, celebrada
por Marcial, en aquel epigrama que principia:

    Edere lascivos ad Bætica crusmata gestus.

Si la mujer casada, como ya queda expuesto, es un modelo de paciencia conyugal, la soltera
es casi siempre un modelo de novias. Puntualmente baja a la reja todas las noches a hablar
con el enamorado, a lo que se llama pelar la pava. En cada calle de cualquier lugar de Andalucía
se ven, de diez a una de la noche, sendos embozados, como cosidos a casi todas las rejas. Tal
vez suspira él y exclama:

--¡Qué mala es usted!

Y ella responde:

--¡Pues no, que usted!...

Y exhala otro suspiro.

Así se pasan horas y horas.

Tiene tal encanto este ejercicio, para el hombre sobre todo, que no pocos noviazgos se prolongan
más que el de Jacob y Raquel, que duró catorce años, sólo por no perder el encanto de pelar
la pava. Las pobres muchachas lo sufren con paciencia, pero languidecen y se ponen ojerosas.

Verdad es que luego, cuando se casan, no sucede, como en otras partes, que la mujer sigue sirviendo,
trabajando y afanando. Aunque sea el novio un miserable jornalero, procura que su novia, no
bien llega a ser su mujer, salga de todo trabajo, no vuelva a escardar ni a coger aceituna,
y sea en su casa como reina y señora. Si está sirviendo, se despide y deja de servir; y ya
no cose, ni lava, ni plancha, ni friega, ni guisa, sino para su marido y para sus hijos. El
hombre, salvo en raras ocasiones, es quien trabaja, busca y granjea o garbea lo necesario para
el sostén de toda la familia.

La cordobesa, sea de la clase que sea, es todo corazón y ternura: pero sin el sentimentalismo
falso y de alquimia que ha venido de extranjis. Nadie (vergüenza es confesarlo) ha pintado
a la cordobesa del pueblo, verdaderamente enamorada y apasionada, como el novelista Mérimée.
Su Carmen es el tipo ideal de la humilde y baja de condición, aunque sublime por el alma. Como
reza el dístico del poeta griego, que sirve de epígrafe a la novela, Carmen sabe morir y amar;
es admirable cuando se entrega por amor y cuando por amor muere; tiene dos horas divinas: una
en la muerte; otra en el tálamo.

De atrás le viene al garbanzo el pico, según el decir vulgar. Desde muy antiguo es la cordobesa
espejo, luz y norte de enamoradas. Sus ojos, como los de Laura, inspiran platónicos y casi
místicos afectos, y hacen que un moro, como Ibn Zeidun, escriba canciones más finas que las
del Petrarca, merced a la princesa Walada, que era asimismo poetisa.

Los amores de dos mujeres cordobesas han tenido un inmenso influjo bienhechor en el mundo:
han contribuido, casi han sido causa de las más preciadas glorias para España, y de acontecimientos
tan providenciales, que sin ellos la actual civilización europea no se explicaría. Sin Zahira,
enamorada de Gústios, no hubiera nacido Mudarra, los siete infantes de Lara no hubieran tenido
vengador; la flor de la caballería castellana hubiera perecido antes de abrir el cáliz; acaso
no hubiéramos poseído al Cid, pues a no inspirarse en la espada de Mudarra y cobrar aliento
con ella, no hubiera muerto al Conde Lozano ni dado principio a tanta hazaña imperecedera.
Si doña Beatriz Enriquez no se enamorara en Córdoba de Colon, consolándole y alentándole, Colon
se hubiera ido de España; hubiera muerto en un hospital de locos; no hubiera descubierto los
nuevos orbes, cuya existencia había columbrado y vaticinado más de mil y cuatrocientos años
antes un inspirado cordobés, y para cuyo descubrimiento le dio ánimo y bríos aquella apasionada
e inmortal cordobesa.

Véase, pues, de cuánto son y han sido capaces mis paisanas. Dios las bendiga a todas.

Imposible parece que, siendo tan buenas, las descuiden y abandonen los pícaros hombres. Además
de las peregrinaciones de que ya hemos hablado, las dejan para irse al casino, donde se pasan
las horas muertas. Razón le sobraba al gran Donoso al tronar tanto contra el casino, en su
elocuente libro sobre el Catolicismo. Es verdad que siempre ha habido casino, sólo que antes,
para los ricos, se llamaba la casilla, y estaba en la botica, y para los pobres, el casino
estaba en la taberna. Pero, en el día, ni las boticas ni las tabernas han acabado, y todo lugar,
por pequeño que sea, pulula, hierve en casinos. Cada bandería, cada matiz político tiene el
suyo. Hay casino conservador, casino radical, casino carlista, casino socialista y casino republicano.
Las infelices mujeres se quedan solas. ¡No sé cómo hay mujer que sea liberal! Todas debieran
ser absolutistas, y muchas lo son en el fondo.

La única compensación que trae a la mujer el liberalismo novísimo es que debilita bastante
la autoridad conyugal y paternal, que antes era terrible y hasta tiránica. A la vara se le
llamaba el gobierno de una casa; pero a la mujer briosa, como lo es la cordobesa, más le duele
cuando la desdeñan que cuando le pegan: más la quebranta un desaire que una paliza.

De todos modos, la mujer cordobesa, como las demás españolas, conserva siempre un manantial
purísimo de consuelo para sus sinsabores y disgustos: este manantial es la religión cristiana.
No hay cordobesa que no sea profundamente religiosa.

Entre los hombres ha cundido la impiedad. El soldado licenciado, de retorno a su casa, ha solido
traer algún ejemplar del Citador; los periódicos se leen, y no todos son piadosos; y por último,
no falta estudiante que vuelve de la universidad inficionado de Krause y hasta de Hegel, y
que echa discursos a los rústicos, a ver si los hace panteistas y egoteistas.

La mujer no entiende, ni quiere entender, tan enrevesados tiquismíquis, y sigue apegada a sus
antiguas creencias. Ellas son el bálsamo para todas las heridas de su corazón: ellas le llenan
de esperanzas inmarcesibles; ellas abren en su ardiente imaginación horizontes infinitos, dorados
por la luz divina de un sol de amor y de gloria.

Hasta para menos elevadas exigencias y para más vulgares satisfacciones es la religión un venero
inagotable. Casi todo honesto mujeril pasatiempo se funda en la religión. Si no fuese por ella,
¿habría romerías tan alegres como la de la Virgen de Araceli y la de la Virgen de la Sierra
de Cabra? ¿Habría Niño Jesús que vestir? ¿Habría procesión que ver? ¿Habría paso de Abraham,
Descendimiento, judíos y romanos, apóstoles y profetas, encolchados, ensabanados y jumeones,
hermanos de cruz, y demás figuras que salen por las calles, en la Semana Santa? Nada de esto
habría. No tendría la mujer jubileos ni novenas, ni oiría sermones, ni adornaría con flores
ningún altar, ni engalanaría ninguna cruz de Mayo, ni se complacería tanto en el mes de María.
Las golondrinas, que ahora son respetadas porque le arrancaron a Cristo con el pico las espinas
de la corona, serían perseguidas y muertas, y no acudirían todos los años a hacer el nido en
el alero del tejado o dentro de la misma casa, ni saludarían al dueño con sus alegres píos
y chirridos. Todo para la mujer estaría muerto y sin significado, faltando la religión. La
pasionaría perdería su valor simbólico; y hasta el amor al novio o al marido o al amante, que
ella combina siempre con el presentimiento de deleites inmortales, y que idealiza, hermosea
y ensalza con mil vagos arreboles de misticismo, se convertiría en cualquiera cosa, bastante
menos poética.

Tal es, en general, la mujer de la provincia de Córdoba. Si entrásemos en pormenores, sería
este escrito interminable. En aquella provincia, como en todas, hay mil grados de cultura y
de riqueza, que hacen variar los tipos. Hay además las diferencias individuales de caracteres
y de prendas del entendimiento.

He omitido un punto muy grave. Voy a tocarle, aunque sea de ligero, antes de terminar el artículo.
Este punto es el filológico: el lenguaje y el estilo de la cordobesa.

La cordobesa, por lo común (y entiéndase que hablo de la jornalera o de la criada, y no de
la dama elegante e instruida), aspira la hache. Tiene además notable propensión a corroborar
las palabras con sílabas fuertes antepuestas. Cuando no se satisface con llamar tunante a cualquiera,
le llama retunante; y no bastándole con Dios, exclama: ¡Redios! En varios pueblos de mi provincia,
así como en muchos de los pueblos de la de Jaén, es frecuentísima cierta interjección inarticulada
que se confunde con un ronquido. La cordobesa, por último, adorna su discurso con mil figuras
e imágenes, le salpimenta de donaires y chistes, y le anima con el gesto y el manoteo.

El adverbio a manta se emplea a cada instante para ponderar o encarecer la abundancia de algo.
Las voces mantés, manteson, mantesada y mantesonada, mantesería y mantesonería, salpican o
llenan tanto todo coloquio como en Málaga la de charran y sus derivados. Más singular es aún
el uso del gerundio en diminutivo, para expresar que se hace algo con suavidad y blandura.
Así, pues, se dice: «Don Fulano se está muriendito. La niña está deseandito casarse, o rabiandito
por novio.»

En la pronunciación dejan un poco que desear las cordobesas. La zeda y la ese se confunden
y unimisman en sus bocas, así como la ele, la ere y la pe. ¿Quién sabe si sería alguna maestra
de miga cordobesa la que dijo a sus discípulas: «Niñas, sordado se escribe con ele y precerto
con pe»? Pero si en la pronunciación hay esta anarquía, en la sintaxis y en la parte léxica,
así las cordobesas como los cordobeses, son abundantes y elegantísimos en ocasiones, y siempre
castizos, fáciles y graciosos. No poca gente de Castilla pudiera ir por allá a aprender a hablar
castellano, ya que no a pronunciarle.

Sin adulación servil aseguro que la cordobesa es, por lo común, discreta, chistosa y aguda.
Su despejo natural suple en ella muy a menudo la falta de estudios y conocimientos. Sus pláticas
son divertidísimas. Es naturalmente facunda y espontánea en lo que dice y piensa. Amiga de
reír y burlar, embroma a los hombres y les suelta mil pullas afiladas y punzantes, pero jamás
se encarniza.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document11070</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>96018</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>21197</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Missing or flowerbeds all around, where the flowers are also abundant, and
for more delicacy and under the flowers are gorgeous gorges, where they form a thousand reeds
drawings and mazes, ending in triangles and other mathematical figures. The upper points of the rods,
which are interwoven with those fences or gates, usually take two separate ornament eggshells
or cute and glazed zucchini. Bees and wasps buzz and encourage the playground during the day. The
Nightingale gives music at night.

In the winter, Córdoba takes good care of evergreens beautify your room. Canaries or finches
remember the spring with their songs, and if the householder is a hunter, partridges and quails
are not lacking songbirds in their cages, and guns and trophies Hunting adorn the walls. Around the
home, almost in conversation with the masters, are to be placed the
hounds and the hounds.

Still in the aristocratic houses of the places there is usually a clown or funny like that remember,
though for the rustic, the lackey of our old comedies. This funny has billion skills and game
thrushes whistle and perch, and goldfinches to link or network, and eel fishing getting into the
ponds and streams, and catching them by hand. Some of these usually his little poet, gives the
days to the lady in tenths, and composed songs in praise and satire
against rivals or opponents of their masters.

Also accompanies and entertains children and know a multitude of stories that relates to animation
and lots of mime.

The maid of place no longer know too many stories, and with grace. The known of amazement, of
charms and love, and they all are serious. For the comic and hilarious treasures spicy countless
jokes.

As I child, will not ever get tired of hearing stories that they told me the house maids. The most
beautiful, the most delighted me was the Dona Guiomar, whose argument, in essence, is the same as
the Indian drama by Kalidasa, entitled Sacuntala. The Arabs undoubtedly brought this story and
another thousand in the Middle Ages, from the remote East.

The maid who excels at list, enjoyable and entertaining, it captures the will and becomes always
the favorite companion or mistress, or unmarried girl or woman.

Comes to resemble the confidante of classical tragedies, and even can play the role of Oenone.
Anyway loves going with his visits to church and walk, takes you and brings messages, and attempts
to have it As current passes in the place.

This to know people's lives and murmuring, must be confessed, is a deplorable taste in the noblemen
and rich styling of there.

Moreover, if there is some truth in the proverb scathing: Do it the Al Andalusia cross, and
Cordoba hands and feet, it can be said to not pray with women before poor things are victims
of unruly, rowdy and friends are usually run it husbands. And from one who goes to the field
to see the vineyards and olive groves and inspect the pruning, digging or other work either,
and is another who goes hunting frigid sub Jove, tenerae conjugis immemorial, and it has to
go to business at the head of the party, or Cordoba, or Madrid for political reasons, and argues
that it should go to Jerez to take samples of wine or a show, to see whether buying or selling
cattle, in short, lacking any excuse ever to be away from home half
the year.

If the husband is handsome and cheerful, often goes months on end away from the conjugal roof. The
tender wife, meanwhile, is in solitude and abandonment, and if is often besieged by suitors, Penelope
and even mimics overtakes him, for after her husband, and he went for work and adventure in life
Trojan War, or fixed, except for rare and laudable exceptions, is more gloomy and Zahareña
Ulysses and Calypso with Circes in inns, lodges, inns and other parties shall be appear.

Very wonderful and very worthy of praise is this fidelity resigned from Cordoba. I will not deny,
however, sometimes exhausted resignation and breaks Cordoba brake
patience.

Then jealousy burst like a tempest. I remember a certain relative of mine who knew that her husband
Stealth was yet a girl in his cottage, where he went every afternoon and even stayed a few nights,
under the pretext of work. Just found out, he ordered verifications the jamugas the donkey, was
accompanied by his donkey in another confidante, and without her husband noticing, it was
for those twists and turns until you reach the farmhouse. Terrible was the interview with the sinner,
who drove out slaps.

I note that in this and other cases are fueling strong economic jealousy. This line of mistresses
often very costly, and ends in the destruction of lucrative and filed flows. No spending originates
or comes from the finery and jewels, cars and workmanship to be buy the girl, or the pomp
and pageantry that is necessary to sustain it, but it is all relative and proportional, and
some of it is spent well. The heterogeneity of place is less demanding beggar and whimsical that Coras,
the Baruccis, the Paiva and other famous Parisian hetairae: but those are single, you'd think
they were born like mushrooms, and the locals have a flood relatives, which is released and
descends upon the house and the estate of the maintainer in love, as Locusts swarm of hungry
and greedy.

Cousins, nephews, brothers, mother, aunts, all, in short, feel entitled to whatever is: with
the right to work, and therefore entitled to the care and leisure. The oil comes out of your cellar,
no for chime, but by the bushel, the slices of bacon flying out of the pantry, the transpose sausages;
butter evaporates, the hams are dissipated. The entire kindred lights, heated, eat, drink and even
dwells at your expense. If you have houses, one of the kindred dwell and do not get the pay,
if you are grower of wine or spirits, often boots, jars and botijuelas, and will enter empty and overflowing.

Do
not believe, however, that since this business so lucrative, many women are engaged He and cheaper
market competition. Throughout the territory of Cordoba has always lived people are very noble
and very difficult at points of honor. Old Colony as true citizens Romans, not freed, like others,
deserved and earned the title of patrician, when the invasion Mohammed, did not come to populate
Berber rude and commoners, but men of pure light Arabian blood, the
most illustrious lineage of Medina and Mecca, the descendants of the
Ansar Tab and muhadjires.

    And finally, having been
    my province, for two centuries, frontier the kingdom of Granada,
had to take and had to defend their custody and places strong, and
to retaliate for any attack, riot by entering domains the Alarba,
cutting their crops and doing other mischief thousand insolence and
a population tough and courageous men,

All gentlemen of honor And
you really love,

as he sings the old romance.

Since then he has tarnished his well-established reputation Córdoba: and not idle boasting, but with
plenty of reason, bears the motto, regarding the rampant lions of his clean coat "Corduba, militiae
domus, inclyta fonsque Sophiaa." Lucan, Seneca, Averroes, Ambrosio de Morales, Gongora and a thousand
others attest to the latter. Accredited first on innumerable multitude, the staunch and courageous
warriors in every way Córdoba has grown; and to wonder and terror of the enemies of Spain as
the Great Captain; and for perpetual anxiety and dread constant gentle Spanish, such as Tempranillo,
Francisco Esteban El Guapo, Benamejí Chat The Cripple of Encinas-Reales, Navarro's Lucena, and
Caparrota the Doña-Mencia.

It is therefore plain that her husband has been there much, much indulgent parent, and many interested
and easy women. Which is what makes him pay dearly, not because of the rarity, but so lost.
Only by dint of superb gifts and generosity, and dazzling with luxury, it is sometimes forgive
its missteps. Still, she is spurned and do not usually call it by its name, but with an ironic
nickname, for example, Galga, La Joya, the guitar. Perhaps designated by the generic name
of the country is natural, and to designate its origin stranger, and I've known them to Murcia,
a the Manchego and Tarifa.

If any young lady or a young married maiden feels vagaries of being seduced and coax, there is often
a father or a husband who straightens healthy and good rattan cane. Neither should be very safe
and neglected seductive inspire much respect. Not enough sometimes innocent, if a lover gives
misgivings. True friend of mine from school, in the Sacro Monte, was, years ago, to heal the
soul into a place of my province. He was a great theologian, straight and virtuous, but well spoken,
elegant, Slick and pleasant man who was the eighteenth century had figured in a court, as the
most delicious abbe. Well, in the people took it with him, and, as they say, you abroncaron.
The brónquis that gave came to shoot some shots, but only with gunpowder, to scare. He estimated
that powder, if it was ineffective, it could easily happen to the shot, and ran away with music
and theology elsewhere less difficult.

Such extremes are rare, fortunately. Cordoba is the flirtatious but very cautious and stealthy,
no one agrees. Even the most humble condition, used to evict the patient in love, talking about
his honor, as the ladies Calderon. When this is not enough or scream, or excited, or shocked, but
he defends which a Penthesilea; struggle, as the angel wrestled with Jacob in the darkness of
night, and robust, even angelic, often throw the trip up, overthrow, and even give you a soba,
all with mute eloquence and quietly beautiful. And do not miss this class because of poor girls, and even
in some affluent styling is remarkable robustness. They are harder than marble, not only of
heart, not just in the center, but the entire periphery. One day we toured the country with
the most graceful and main girls of the place. One of them, believing the highest seat, sat
hit on a pile of tiles. Were of the massive and best of Lucena. Three saw broken. She said with
a charming modesty and, before the fall, they were.

Not understood, so that, Amenga or deface anything at all slenderness and kindness of my countrywomen.
One thing is the density and firmness, and over the outrageous volume. The girl that a child
works, go hard and go to the fountain in the ejido, returning from there with the jug full,
on her hip, or washed her clothes in the stream, is strong but not fat. The source or the
pillar was the end of my daily walk, and there I I sat on a bench under a leafy eminent black
poplar. Seeing the girls washing, or fill the jars and go with them so graceful, airy and
light, for that slope above, I moved my spirit to the patriarchal times, and I thought I saw
some Biblical scenes such as Rebecca and Eliacer, and, comparing with the wise King of Ithaca, I
tried in the presence of Princess Nausicaa and her companions kind. Nothing crinolines or
recessed into those girls. The poor short dress, especially in summer, hews the body and gracefully
folded, watching and revealing the juveniles, as in the statue huntress Diana.

Unfortunately, the ladies have taken place, as soon as possible, almost
all French fashion, and are losing their style of dress and grooming.

All huge crinolines used total and now use the pseudo-partial crinoline depriving callipygian. When
you least expect leave the blanket and put the hat. All comb, taking figurine modeled after, and often
call this hairstyle cucuné or rolled up to give up the name, a character abroad. Skirts, short
rather than take them, take them long, and are sweeping dust tail of the roads. In short, it's a
shame this abandonment of the suit itself and appropriate.

Despite these costumes, beauty, or at least the grace, the elegance and wit, are items common
in my countrywomen.

They go far in the delicacy, and especially if dancing. The rigodones and the waltz and polka will
acclimatizing, but the fandango not banished yet. Until ladies come out to make a move, if taken
out and force in any country fair, and move and jump with panache and ease, and castanets rattle
briskly. Women There's people that in this dance and play castanets, due to Teletusa held by
Martial, in that epigram which begins:

Eder ad Baetica crusmata Gestus lewd.

    

If a married woman, as exposed, is a model of patience married, the unmarried is almost always
a model girlfriends. Down to the gate on time every night to talk with love, on what is called
the turkey skin. In every street anywhere in Andalucía are, from 10:00 to 13:00, two separate muffled,
and sewn into most bars. Such Once he sighs and exclaims:

- Too bad you are!

And she answers:

- No, you! ...

And breathe another sigh.

So spend hours and hours.

This exercise has such charm to the man above all, not just extend dating more than that of
Jacob and Rachel, which lasted fourteen years, not only losing the charm of peel the kettle.
The poor girls suffer with patience, but languish and become haggard.

Truth is that then when they get married, not, as elsewhere, that
women are still serving, service and dedication.

Although the groom is a journeyman miserable, try to find his girlfriend, no property become
his wife, quit all work, no weed again or pick olives and be at home as queen and mistress.
If you are serving, says goodbye and leaves to serve, and as does not sew or clean, or iron,
or scrub, or wise, but for her husband and their children. The man, except in rare cases, the
worker, or Garbee garners looks and what is necessary to the support of the entire family.

The Cordoba, is in the class it is, is all heart and tenderness but
without sentimentality false and alchemy that has come from extranjis.

No one (shame confess) has painted Cordoba to the people, truly in love and passionate, as the
novelist Mérimée. Her Carmen is the ideal kind of humble and low capacity, even sublime soul.
As says the Greek poet's couplet, which serves as epigraph to the novel, Carmen knows dying
and love; is admirable when it is given out of love and when love
dies, you have two hours divine: a in death, and another in the thalamus.

From behind comes the garbanzo the peak, as the vulgar say. Since ancient times is the Cordoba
mirror, northern light and love. Her eyes, like those of Laura, inspired and almost Platonic mystical
feelings, and make a Moor, as Ibn Zeidun, write songs finer than of Petrarch, through Walada
princess, who was also a poet.

The loves of two women have had a huge Cordoba beneficent influence in the world: have contributed
almost have been the cause of the most precious glory for Spain, and events as angels, without
whom the current European civilization is not explained. Without Zahira Gusti love, Mudaliar
had not been born, seven infants of Lara would not have had avenger, the flower of Spanish chivalry
had died before opening the cup, perhaps we had not possessed the
Cid, because not inspired by the sword and collect breath Mudarra
with her had not died or given to Count Lozano feat so enduring principle.

If Dona Beatriz Enriquez fell in love with Columbus in Córdoba, comforting
and encouraging, Colon had gone to Spain, had died in an insane hospital,
I had not discovered new orbs, whose existence was discerned and predicted
more than thousand and four hundred years before an inspired Cordoba,
and the discovery of which gave him the passionate spirit and vigor
Cordoba immortal.

See, then, how are and have been able to my countrywomen. God bless you all.

Unable to appear to be as good, the neglected and abandoned men rogues. Addition The pilgrimage
of which we spoke, the left to go to the casino, where they spend idle time. He had plenty of reason
to the roar of the great Donoso both against the casino, where eloquent book on Catholicism.
It is true that there has always been casino, just before for the rich, is called the box, and was in
the pharmacy, and the poor, the casino was in the tavern. But in the day or the pharmacy or
the pubs are gone, and everywhere however small, swarming, boiled
in casinos.

Each factions, each has the political hue yours. There are conservative casino, casino radical
Carlist casino, casino casino socialist and republican. The poor women are left alone. I do
not know how no woman who is liberal! All should be absolute, and many are in the background.

The
only compensation that the woman brings brand new liberalism is quite
weak marital and paternal authority, which previously was terrible
and even tyrannical.

A rod is the government called a house, but the spirited woman, as is the Cordoba, it hurts
when the disdain that when you're stuck, plus a slight breaks to beat.

Anyway, Cordoba women, like other Spanish, still retains a spring pure comfort for their sorrows
and disappointments: this spring is the Christian religion. Cordoba there is not deeply religious.

Among
men ungodliness has spread. The discharged soldier, returning home, has often bring a copy
of the citing authors, the papers are read, and not all are pious,
and finally, not missing student returning to college Krause infected
and even Hegel, and that addresses the rustic check to see if it makes
pantheistic and egotism.

Women do not understand, nor want to understand, so convoluted picky, and still attached to its old
beliefs.

They are the balm for all wounds of his heart, they will fill imperishable hopes, they open in his
ardent imagination infinite horizons, golden by the divine light of the sun of love and glory.

Even
for less stringent requirements and more vulgar satisfactions is religion a mine inexhaustible.
Almost all honest feminine pastime is based on religion. If it were not for her, Would there
be as happy as the pilgrimage of the Virgen de Araceli and the Virgen de la Sierra Goat? Child
Would Jesus wear? Would procession to do? Would passage of Abraham, Descent, Jews and Romans,
apostles and prophets, encolchados, ensabanados and jumeones, Cross brothers, and other figures
coming out in the streets during Holy Week? None of this would. No woman would jubilees or novenas,
or hear sermons or adorn with flowers no altar, no crosses or engalanaría May, or so happy in the
month of Mary. The swallows, who are now respected because he tore Christ with thorns peak the
crown, would be persecuted and killed, and would not come every year to nest in the eaves
or in the same house, or greet the owner with his gay peeps and squeaks. Especially for women
would be dead and meaningless, that takes religion. The Passiflora lose its symbolic value, and
to love her boyfriend or husband or lover, who she always combined with a presentiment of immortal
joys, and idealized, beautifies and praises with a thousand vague red glow of mysticism, whatever
became quite less poetic.

This is, in general, women in the province of Cordoba. If you go into details, it would this writing
endless.

In that province, as in all, a thousand degrees of culture and wealth, for varying types. There are
also individual differences in character Apparel and understanding.

I missed a very serious point. I'll touch, albeit slightly, before finishing the article. This
point is the philological: the language and style of Cordoba.

The Cordoba, usually (and understood that I speak of the laborer or servant, and not elegant and educated
lady), hache sucks. It also has remarkable propensity to corroborate words with strong syllables
prefixed. When not satisfied with rogue call anyone, retunante called,
and God was not enough, exclaims: Redio!

In several towns in my province and in many towns of Jaen, it is very frequent some inarticulate
interjection which coincides with a snore. The Cordoba, finally, adorns his speech with a
thousand pictures and pictures, he peppered with witticisms and jokes, and encouraged by the
gesture and gesticulation.

The adverb is used to blanket every moment to weigh or abundance of
something expensive.

The voices blankets, manteson, Mantese and mantesonada, mantesería and mantesonería, dot or
fill up all conversation as much of charran Malaga and its derivatives. Is even more unique the
use of the gerund in short, to express something is done smoothly and softness. So you say "Don
Fulano is muriendito. Deseandito The girl is married, or rabiandito by boyfriend. "

In pronunciation leaves a bit to be desired of Cordoba. The Zeda and confused that and unimisman
in their mouths, and the elements, the ere and pe.

Who knows if it would be a teacher Cordoba crumb which told his disciples: "Girls, deaf and
precerto writes ele PE '? But if the pronunciation is this anarchy, the syntax and the lexical well
as the Cordoba Cordoba, are abundant and extremely elegant at times, and always castizos,
easy and funny. No Castilla few people could go there to learn to speak Castilian, as not to
rule.

No servile adulation assure that the Cordoba is usually discreet,
funny and sharp. Its natural clearing supplies in it very often lack
of education and knowledge. His talks are hilarious. Facunda is naturally
and spontaneously in what he says and thinks. Friendly laughing and
teasing, teasing men, and they released a thousand barbs sharp and
pointed, but never rages</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>