<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04261</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>255469</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19163</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Los naturales de Bonbon habian savido, segun estos cuentan, el desbarate de Xauxa, y cómo habian
sido los Guancas[165] vencidos, y sospechando que los vencedores querian pasar adelante, acordaron
de se apercibir, porque no los tomasen descuidados; y poniendo sus mujeres é hijos con la hacienda
que pudieron en una laguna que está cerca dellos[166], aguardaron á lo que sucediese. Los capitanes
del Inca, como hobieron asentado las cosas del valle de Xauxa, salieron y anduvieron hasta
Bonbon, y como se metieron en la laguna, no les pudieron hacer otro mal que comerles los mantenimientos;
y como esto vieron, pasaron adelante y allegaron á lo de Tarama, á donde hallaron á los naturales
puestos en arma, y hobieron batalla en que fueron presos y muertos muchos de los Taramentinos,
y los del Cuzco quedaron por vencedores; y como les dejasen en la voluntad del rey, [que] era
que le sirviesen y tributasen como hacian otras muchas provincias, y que serian bien tratados
y favorecidos, hicieron todo lo que les fué mandado, y envióse al Cuzco relacion de todo lo
que se habia hecho en este pueblo de Tarama.

Cuentan los indios Chancas, que como los indios que salieron de su provincia de Andaguaylas
con el capitan Ancoallo hobiesen hecho grandes hechos en estas guerras, envidiosos dellos y
con rancor que tenian contra el capitan Ancoallo de más atrás, cuando el Cuzco fué cercado,
determinaron de los matar; y así, los mandaron llamar; y como fuesen muchos juntos con su capitan,
entendieron la intencion que tenian, y puestos en arma, se defendieron [de los] del Cuzco,
y aunque murieron algunos, pudieron los otros, con el favor y esfuerzo de Ancoallo, de (así)
salir de allí; el cual se quejaba á sus dioses de la maldad de los orejones, é ingratitud,
afirmando, que, por no los ver más ni seguir, se iria con los suyos en voluntario destierro;
y echando delante las mujeres, caminó y atravesó las provincias de los Chachapoyas y Guánuco,
y pasando por la montaña de los Andes, caminó por aquellas sierras hasta que llegaron, segun
tambien dicen, á una laguna muy grande, que yo creo debe ser lo que cuentan del Dorado, á donde
hicieron sus pueblos y se ha multiplicado mucha gente. Y cuentan los indios grandes cosas de
aquella tierra y del capitan Ancoallo.

Los capitanes del Inca, pasado lo que se ha escripto, dieron la vuelta al valle de Xauxa, donde
ya se habian allegado grandes presentes y muchas mujeres para llevar al Cuzco, y lo mesmo hicieron
los de Tarama. La nueva de todo fué al Cuzco, y como fué sabido por el Inca, holgóse por el
buen suceso de sus capitanes, aunque hizo muestras [de] haberle pesado lo que habian hecho
con Ancoallo. Mas era, segun se cree, industria, porque algunos afirman que por su mandado
lo hicieron sus capitanes. Y como Tupac Uasco y los otros Chancas hobiesen ido á dar guerra
á la provincia del Collao y hobiesen habido victoria de algunos pueblos, recelándose el Inca
que, sabida la nueva de lo que habia pasado con Ancoallo, se volverian contra él y le harian
traicion, les envió mensajeros para que luego viniesen para él, é mandó, so pena de muerte,
que ninguno les avisase de lo pasado.

Los Chancas, como vieron el mandado del Inca, vinieron luego al Cuzco, y como llegaron, el
Inca les habló con gran disimulacion amorosamente, encubriendo la maldad que se usó con el
capitan Ancoallo, y daba por sus palabras muestras de habelle dello pesado. Los Chancas, como
lo entendieron, no dejaron de sentir el afrenta, mas, viendo cuán poca parte eran para satisfacerse,
pasaron por ello, pidiendo licencia á Inca Yupanqui para volver á su provincia; y siéndoles
concedido, se partieron, dándole privilegio al señor principal para que se pudiese sentar en
el duho[167] engastonado en oro, y otras preminencias.

Y entendió el Inca en acrescentar el templo de Curicancha con grandes riquezas, como ya está
escripto. Y como el Cuzco tuviese por todas partes muchas provincias, dió algunas á este templo,
y mandó poner las postas, y que hablasen una lengua todos los súditos suyos, y que fuesen hechos
los caminos reales, y los mitimaes; y otras cosas inventó este rey, de quien dicen que entendia
mucho de las estrellas y que tenia cuenta con el movimiento del sol; y así tomó él por sobrenombre
Inca Yupanqui, que es nombre de cuenta y de mucho entender. Y como se hallase tan poderoso,
no embargante que en el Cuzco habia grandes edificios y casas reales, mandó hacer tres cercados
de muralla excelentísima y dina la obra de memoria, y tal paresce hoy dia, que ninguno la verá
que no alabe el edificio y conozca ser grande el ingenio de los maestros que la inventaron.
Cada cercado destos tiene más de trescientos pasos: al uno llaman Pucamarca, y al otro Hátun
Cancha, y al tercero Cassana[168]; y es de piedra excelente y puesta tan por nivel, que no
hay en cosa desproporcion, y tan bien asentadas las piedras y tan pegadas, que no se divisará
la juntura dellas. Y están tan fuertes y tan enteros los más destos edificios, que si no los
deshacen, como han hecho otros muchos, vivirán muchas edades.

Dentro destas cercas ó murallas habia aposentos como los demás quellos usaban, donde estaban
cantidad de mamaconas y otras muchas mujeres y mancebas de los reyes, y hilaban y tejian de
la su tan fina ropa, y habia muchas piezas de oro y de plata y vasijas destos metales. Muchas
destas piedras vi yo en algunas destas cercas, y me espanté cómo, siendo tan grandes, estaban
tan primamente puestas.--Cuando hacian los bailes y fiestas grandes en el Cuzco, era hecha
mucha de su chicha por las mujeres dichas y bebíanla.--Y como de tantas partes acudiesen al
Cuzco, mandó poner veedores para que no saliese sin su licencia ningun oro ni plata de lo que
entrase, y pusiéronse gobernadores por las mesmas partes del reino, y á todos gobernaba con
gran justicia y órden. Y porque en este tiempo mandó hacer la fortaleza del Cuzco, diré algo
della, pues es tan justo.

La ciudad del Cuzco está edificada en valle, ladera y collados, como se escribe en la primera
parte desta historia[169], y de los mesmos edificios salen unas formas de paredes anchas, en
donde hacen sus sementeras, y por compás salian unas de otras, que parescian cercas, de manera
que todo estaba destos andenes, que hacia más fuerte la ciudad, aunque por natura lo es su
sitio; y así, lo escogieron los Señores della entre tanta tierra. Y como ya se fuese haciendo
poderoso el mando de los reyes, é Inca Yupanqui tuviese los pensamientos tan grandes, no embargante
que tanto por él habia sido ilustrado y enriquecido el templo del sol, llamado Curicancha,
é hobiese hecho otros grandes edificios, determinó que se hiciese otra casa del sol que sobrepujase
el edificio á lo hecho hasta allí, y que en ella se pusiesen todas las cosas que pudiesen haber,
así oro como plata, piedras ricas, ropa fina, armas de todas las que ellos usaban, municion
de guerra, alpargates, rodelas, plumas, cueros de animales y los de aves, coca, sacas de lana,
joyas de mill géneros; en conclusion, habia todo aquello de que ellos podian tener noticia.
Y esta obra se comenzó tan soberbia, que si hasta hoy durara su monarquía, no estuviera acabada.

Mandóse que viniesen de las provincias que señalaron veinte mill hombres, y que los pueblos
le enviasen bastimento necesario, y si alguno adolesciese, entrando en su lugar otro, se volviese
á su naturaleza, aunque estos indios no residian siempre en la obra sino tiempo limitado, y
viniendo otros, salian ellos, por donde sentian poco el trabajo. Los cuatro mill destos quebrantaban
las piedras y sacaban las piedras; los seis mill las andaban trayendo con grandes maromas de
cueros y de cabuya[170]; los otros estaban abriendo la zanja y abriendo los cimientos, yendo
algunos á cortar horcones y vigas para el enmaderamiento. Y para estar á su placer, estas gentes
hicieron su alojamiento cada parcialidad por sí, junto á donde se habia de hacer el edificio.--Hoy
dia parecen las más de las paredes de las casas que tuvieron.--Andaban veedores mirando como
se hacian, y maestros grandes y de mucho primor; y así, en un cerro que está á la parte del
Norte de la ciudad, en lo más alto della, poco más que un tiro de arcabuz, se fabricó esta
fuerza que los naturales llamaron Casa del Sol, y los nuestros nombran la Fortaleza.

Cavóse en peña viva para el fundamento y armar el cimiento, el cual se hizo tan fuerte, que
durará mientras hobiere mundo. Tenia, á mi parecer, de largo trescientos y treinta pasos, y
de ancho doscientos. Tenia muchas cercas tan fuertes, que no ay artillería que baste á romperlas.
La puerta principal era de ver cuán primamente estaba y cuán concertadas las murallas para
una no salir del compás de la otra; y en estas cercas se ven piedras tan grandes y soberbias,
que cansa el juicio considerar cómo se pudieron traer y poner y quién bastó á labrallas, pues
entre ellos se ven tan pocas herramientas. Algunas destas piedras son anchas como doce piés
y más largas que veinte, y otras más gruesas que un buey, y todas asentadas tan delicadamente,
que entre una y otra no podrán meter un real.--Yo fuí á ver este edificio dos veces: la una
fué conmigo Tomas Vázquez, conquistador, y la otra Hernando de Guzman, que se halló en el cerco[171],
y Juan de la Playa[172]; y creed los que esto leyerdes, que no os cuento nada para lo que ví.
Y andándolo notando, ví junto á esta fortaleza una piedra que la medí y tenía doscientos y
setenta palmos de los mios de redondo, y tan alta, que parescia que habia nacido allí, y todos
los indios dicen que se cansó esta piedra en aquel lugar, y que no la pudieron mover más de
allí[173]; y cierto, si en ella misma no se viese haber sido labrada, yo no creyera, aunque
más me lo afirmaran, que fuerza de hombres bastara á la poner allí, adonde estará para testimonio
de lo que fueron los inventores de obra tan grande, pues los españoles lo han ya desbaratado
y parado tal, cual yo no quisiera ver la culpa grande de los que han gobernado en lo haber
permitido, y que una cosa tan insigne se hobiese desbaratado y derribado, sin mirar los tiempos
y sucesos que pueden venir y que fuera mejor tenerla en pié y con guarda[174].

Habia muchos aposentos en esta fuerza, uno encima de otros, pequeños, y otros entre suelos,
grandes; y hacíanse dos cubos, el uno mayor que otro, anchos y tan bien sacados, que no sé
cómo lo encarecer, segun están primos y las piedras tan bien puestas y labradas; y debajo de
tierra dicen que hay mayores edificios. Y cuentan otras cosas, que no escribo, por no las tener
por ciertas. Comenzóse á hacer esta fuerza en tiempo de Inca Yupanqui; labró mucho su hijo
Tupac Inca y Guayna Capac y Guascar, y aunque ahora es cosa de ver, lo era mucho más sin comparacion.
Cuando los españoles entraron en el Cuzco, sacaron los indios de Quizquiz gran tesoro della,
y los españoles aún hallaron[175] alguno, y se cree que hay á la redonda della mayor número
de lo uno y lo otro. Lo que desta fortaleza y la de Guarco ha quedado seria justo mandar conservar[176]
para memoria de la grandeza desta tierra y aun para tener en ellas tales dos fuerzas, pues
á tan poca costa se las hallan hechas. Y con tanto, volveré á la materia.

Como estos indios no tienen letras ni cuentan sus cosas sino por la memoria que dellas queda
de edad en edad y de sus cantares y quipos, digo esto, porque en muchas cosas varían, diciendo
unos uno y otros otro, y no bastara juicio humano á escrebir lo escripto, sino tomara destos
dichos lo que ellos mismos decian ser más cierto, para lo contar. Esto apunto para los españoles
questán en el Perú que presumen de saber muchos secretos destos, que entiendan que supe yo
y entendí lo que ellos piensan que saben y entienden y mucho más, y que de todo convino escribirse
lo que verán, y que pasé el trabajo en ello que ellos mismos saben.

Y así, dicen los orejones, que estando las cosas de Inca Yupanqui en este estado, determinó
de salir del Cuzco con mucha gente de guerra á lo que llaman Collao y sus comarcas; y así,
dejando su gobernador en la ciudad, salió della y anduvo hasta ser llegado al gran pueblo de
Ayavire, adonde dicen que, no queriendo venir los naturales dél en conformidad, tuvo cautela
como, tomándolos descuidados, mató á todos sus vecinos, hombres y mujeres, haciendo lo mesmo
de los de Copacopa[177]; y la destruicion de Ayavire fué tanto, que todos los más perecieron,
que no quedaron sino algunos que despues quedaban asombrados de ver tan grande maldad y como
locos furiosos por las sementeras, llamando á los mayores suyos con grandes aullidos y palabras
temerosas[178]. Y como ya el Inca hobiese caido en la invencion tan galana y provechosa de
poner los mitimaes, como viese las lindas vegas y campañas de Ayavire y el rio tan hermoso
que por junto á él pasa[179], mandó que viniesen de las comarcas la gente que bastase con sus
mujeres á poblarlo; y así fué hecho, y se hicieron para él grandes aposentos y templo del sol,
y muchos depósitos y casa de fundicion; de manera que, poblado de mitimaes, Ayavire quedó más
principal que ántes, y los indios que han quedado de las guerras y crueldad de los españoles,
son todos mitimaes advenedizos y no naturales, por lo que se ha escripto.

Sin esto cuentan más, que habiendo ido por su mando ciertos capitanes con gente bastante á
dar guerra á los de Andesuyo, que son los pueblos y comarcas questan en la montaña, toparon
unas culebras tan grandes como maderos gruesos, las cuales mataban todos los que podian, tanto,
que sin ver otros enemigos, hicieron ellas la guerra de tal arte, que vinieron pocos de los
muchos que entraron; y que recebió enojo grande el Inca con saber tal nueva; y estando con
su congoja, una hechicera le dijo que ella iria y pararia bobas y mansas las culebras susodichas,
que mal á ninguno no hiciesen aunque en ellas mesmas se sentasen. Agradeciendo la obra, si
conformaba con el dicho, le mandó lo pusiese en ejecucion, y lo hizo, al creer dellos y no
al mio, porque parece burla; y encantadas las culebras, dieron en los enemigos, y subjetaron
muchos por guerra y otros por ruego y buenas palabras que con ellos tuvieron.

El Inca salió de Ayavire, dicen que por el camino que llaman Omasuyo, el cual para su persona
real fué hecho ancho y como lo vemos; y caminó por los pueblos de Oruro[180], Asillo, Azángaro,
en donde tuvo algunos recuentros con los naturales; mas, tales palabras les dijo, que con ellas
y con dones que les dió, los atrajo á su amistad y servicio, y dende en adelante usaron de
la pulicía que usaban los demás que tenian amistad y alianza con los Incas, y hicieron sus
pueblos concertados en lo llano de las vegas.

Pasando adelante Inca Yupanqui, cuentan que visito los más pueblos que confinan con la gran
laguna de Titicaca, que con su buena maña los trajo todos á su servicio, poniéndose en cada
pueblo del traje que usaban los naturales, cosa de gran placer para ellos y con que más se
holgaban. Entró en la gran laguna de Titicaca y miró las islas que en ella se hacen, mandando
hacer en la mayor de ellas templo del sol y palacios para él y sus descendientes; y puesta
en su Señorío, y todo lo demás de la gran comarca del Collao, se volvió á la ciudad del Cuzco
con grande triunfo; á donde mandó, luego que en ella entró, hacer grandes fiestas á su usanza,
y vinieron de las más provincias á le hacer reverencia con grandes presentes; y los gobernadores
y delegados suyos tenian gran cuidado de cumplir en todo su mandado.

CAP. LIII.--De cómo Inca Yupanqui salió del Cuzco, y lo que hizo.

Volaba la fama de Inca Yupanqui en tanta manera por la tierra, que en todas partes se trataba
de sus grandes hechos. Muchos, sin ver bandera ni capitan suyo, le vinieron á conocer, ofreciéndosele
por vasallos, afirmando con sus dichos que del cielo habian caido sus pasados, pues sabian
vivir con tanto concierto y honra. Inca Yupanqui, sin perder su gravedad, les respondió mansamente
que no queria hacer agravio á nacion ninguna, sino viniesen á le dar la obediencia, pues el
sol lo queria y mandaba. Y como hobiese tornado á hacer llamamiento de gente, salió con toda
ella á lo que llaman Condesuyo y sujetó á los Yanaguaras y á los Chumbivilcas, y con algunas
provincias desta comarca de Condesuyo tuvo recias batallas; mas, aunque le dieron mucha guerra,
su esfuerzo y saber fué tanto, que con daño y muerte de muchos le dieron la obediencia, tomándolo
por Señor, como lo hacian los demás; y dejando puesta en órden la tierra, y hechos caciques
á los naturales, y mandándoles que no hiciesen agravio ni daño á estos súbditos, se volvió
al Cuzco, poniendo primero gobernadores en las partes principales, para que impusiesen á los
naturales la órden que habian de tener, así para su vivienda, como para le servir y para hacer
sus pueblos juntos, y tener en todo gran concierto, sin que ninguno fuese agraviado, aunque
fuese de los más pobres.

Pasado esto, cuentan más, que reposó pocos dias en el Cuzco, porque quiso ir en persona á los
Andes, á donde habia enviado sus adalides y escuchas para que mirasen la tierra y le avisasen
del arte que estaban los moradores della; y como por su mandado estuviese todo el reino lleno
de depósitos con mantenimientos, mandó que proveyesen el camino quél habia de llevar, é fué
hecho así; y con los capitanes y gente de guerra salió del Cuzco, á donde dejó su gobernador
para la administracion de la justicia, y atravesando las montañas y sierras nevadas, supo de
sus corredores lo de adelante, y de la grande espesura de las montañas, y aunque hallaban de
las culebras tan grandes que se crian en estas espesuras, no hacian daño ninguno, y espantábanse
de ver cuan fieras y monstruosas eran.

Como los naturales de aquellas comarcas supieron la entrada en su tierra del Inca, como ya
muchos dellos por mano de sus capitanes habian sido puestos en su servicio, le vinieron á hacer
la mocha, trayéndole presentes de muchas plumas de aves y coca y de lo más que tenian en su
tierra, y á todos lo agradecia mucho. Los demás indios que habitaban en aquellas montañas,
los que quisieron serle vasallos, enviáronle mensajeros, los que no, desampararon sus pueblos
y metiéronse con sus mujeres en la espesura de la montaña.

Inca Yupanqui tuvo gran noticia que, pasadas algunas jornadas, á la parte de Levante, habia
gran tierra y muy poblada. Con esta nueva, codicioso de descubrirlo, pasó adelante; mas, siendo
avisado como en el Cuzco habia sucedido cierto alboroto, y habiendo allegado é un pueblo que
llaman Marcapata, revolvió con priesa grande al Cuzco, donde estuvo algunos dias.

Pasados estos, dicen los indios, que como la provincia de Collao sea tan grande y en ella hubiese
en aquellos tiempos número grande de gente y señoríos de los naturales muy poderosos, como
supieron que Inca Yupanqui habia entrado en la montaña de los Andes, creyendo que por allí
seria muerto ó que vendria desbaratado, concertáronse todos á una, desde Vilcanota para adelante,
á una parte y á otra, con muy gran secreto, de se rebelar y no estar debajo del señorío de
los Incas, diciendo que era poquedad grande de todos ellos, habiendo sido libres sus padres
y no dejándolos en cautiverio, sujetarse tantas tierras y tan grandes á un Señor solo. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document10957</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>80463</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17650</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

The natives had savido Bonbon, according to this count, the rout of Xauxa, and how had Huancas been
[165] up, and suspecting that the victors wanted to move on, agreed to be summoned, because tomasen
not neglected, and putting their wives and children to the ranch they could in a lake that is near
it [166], waiting for it to happen. Masters the Inca, as things settled hobieron Valley Xauxa came
out and walked up Bonbon, and as they entered the lagoon, they are not doing any further damage
that could eat them the maintenance; and as it were, went ahead and draw nigh to him of Tarama, to where
they found the natives gun positions, and hobieron battle in which they were imprisoned and killed
many of the Taramentinos, Cuzco and the winners were from, and as I dejasen in the king's will,
[that] you serve and pay tribute as did many other provinces, and that would be well treated
and favored, did everything I was commanded, and relationship to Cuzco envióse all had been done
in this town of Tarama.

The Indians Chance, as the Indians who left their province Andaguaylas with Captain Ancoallo
hobiesen great deeds done in these wars, jealous of them and set with rancor against the captain
who had Ancoallo more ago, when the Cuzco was fenced determined to kill them, and thus, was
summoned, and as were many together with his captain understand the intentions they had, and put into
a weapon, fought [the] Cuzco and even killed some, could the other, with the help and effort
Ancoallo of (well) out of there, which complained to their gods from the evil of the apricots,
and ingratitude, stating that, by not more or follow, it would go with his family in voluntary
exile; and throwing women before, walked and walked through the provinces of Chachapoyas and
Huanuco, and through the Andes mountain, walked through those mountains until they came, according
to also say, to a large lagoon, which I think must be what they tell Dorado, whither made their
villages and multiplied many people. And the Indians have great things that land and the captain
Ancoallo.

The captains of the Inca, after what has been eScript, turned the valley Xauxa where already had
great close friend, and many women present to bring to Cuzco, and do the same did Tarama those. The
new all went to Cuzco, and as it was known by the Inca, rejoiced by good fortune of their masters,
though he signs [of] him what they had done heavy with Ancoallo. But it was, it is believed,
industry, because some say that by his command did their masters. And Tupac and other Chancas
UASC hobiesen gone to make war to the province of Collao and hobiesen been no victory of some
people, suspicious of the Inca that new known what had happened to Ancoallo would turn against
him and would do treason, sent messengers to them then they should come to him, and commanded,
on pain of death, none warned of the past.

The Chancas, as were the order of the Inca, then came to Cuzco, and as they arrived, the Inca
with great dissimulation spoke lovingly, concealing the evil that was used to Ancoallo captain,
and gave his words heavy dello Habell samples. The Chancas, as understood, did not fail to feel
the shame, but, seeing how few of them were to be met, passed through it, asking leave to Inca Yupanqui
to return to his province, and being so granted, were split, giving privilege to be principal
lord could sit in the Duho [167] engastonado in gold, and other pre-eminence.

And understood the Inca temple Curicancha acrescentar with great riches, as is already eScript.
And like everywhere Cuzco had many provinces, gave some to this temple and sent to the posts, and
they speak a language all their own Sudit, which were made the highways, and mitimaes, and other
things invented the king, who said he understood Many of the stars and has had the sun's movement,
and so took him by nickname Inca Yupanqui, which is the account name and a lot of understanding. And
as is so powerful Notwithstanding that in Cuzco had large buildings and royal palaces, he ordered
three enclosures of wall Excellency and coordinates the work of memory, and such Paresce today,
so that anyone will not praise the building and learn to be great ingenuity of the teachers who
invented it. Each Near this is more than three hundred steps to a Pucamarca call, and the other
Hatun Court, and the third Cassana [168], and is of excellent and fantastic stone as per level,
not disproportion is a thing, and so well settled and so stuck stones, which can not even
see the joint in them. " They are so strong and so whole the most outstanding buildings, if not
apart, as have many others, will live many ages.

WITH THESE fences or walls within rooms and others had used Quellos, where they were number of
virgins and many women and concubines of the kings, and spun and wove of your so fine clothes,
and had many pieces of gold and silver and vessels these metals. Many I saw stones WITH THESE
WITH THESE some fences, and it frightens me how, being so large, were as first place .-- When
they made the big dances and parties in Cuzco, was made much of its chicha for those women
and bebíanla .-- And as so many parties to come to Cuzco, sent to providers to not come out
without his permission no gold or silver than entered, and stood by the mesmos governors over
the kingdom, and ruled them all with great justice and order. And because this time he ordered
the fortress of Cuzco, say something Dell, as it is right.

The city of Cuzco is built on valley slopes and hills, as written in the first Part of this history
[169], and the buildings mesmos out a thick-walled forms, in where they do their fields, and
Salian beat each other, which parescian fences, so everything was desto platforms, stronger than
towards the city, although it is his nature site, and so I chose the Lords della between so
much land. And as we were doing powerful command of the kings, and Inca Yupanqui had such great
thoughts, not attaching that he had been both enlightened and enriched the temple of the sun, called
Curicancha, é hobiese made other large buildings, determined that they should do another house
of the sun which surpasses the building to what was done there, and that she verifications all things
that might have, gold and silver, precious stones, fine clothing, weapons of all that they used,
ammunition war, sandals, shields, feathers, animal skins and bird, cocaine, bags of wool, mill
jewelry genres, in conclusion, had everything that they could be news. And this work was begun
so proud, that if the monarchy lasted until today, was not finished.

Mandóse that would come from the provinces said twenty thousand men, and that people necessary
provisions to send him, and if any adolescent, taking his place another, became his nature, but these
Indians resided in work but always limited time and coming others, Salian them, where they
felt little work. They broke the four mill desto rocks and stones taken out, the six mill were bringing
the large ropes of Leather and hemp [170], the others were digging the trench and opening the
ground, going some short wooden columns and beams for the woodwork. And to be at his pleasure,
these people made their accommodation each moiety itself beside where he had to make the building
.-- Today day seem most of the walls of the houses had walked about suppliers watching .-- were made,
and great teachers and a lot of delicacy, and so, on a hill which is on the part of North of
the city, on top of it, little more than a musket shot, was produced this natural force that
called Casa del Sol, and our named La Fortaleza.

Cavos in living rock for the foundation and build the foundation, which became so strong that
last as long as hobiere world. Had, in my view, three hundred and thirty feet long, and two
hundred wide. Had many fences so strong that not enough artillery to and to break them. The front
door was to see how premium was and how concerted the walls to one did not leave the bar to
the other, and fencing in these rocks are so large and magnificent, which tires the trial to
consider how they could bring and place and who was enough to labrallas because between them
are so few tools. WITH THESE Some stones are wide and twelve feet and longer than twenty, and
other thicker than an ox, and all so delicately settled, which between them can not get a real
.-- I went to see this building twice: one Tomas Vazquez was with me, conqueror, and other
Hernando de Guzman, who was found in the circle [171] and Juan de la Playa [172], and believe that this
leyerdes, not anything I tell you what I saw. And andándolo noticing, I saw this fortress beside
a stone than average and had two hundred and seventy spans of round mine, and so high that
parescia who was born there, and all Indians say they are tired of this stone in that place, and
could not move more than there [173], and some, if not to find itself being carved, I do not
believe, though more me affirm that enough to force the men to put there, where will be a witness
what were the inventors of great work, as they have already wrecked Spanish and stopped that, which
I did not want to see the great fault of those who have ruled in allowed, and a notable thing
is hobiese disrupted and broken down, without looking at the times and events that may come
and it was better to have it standing and keep [174].

There were many rooms in this force, one above the other, small, and others between soil large,
and hacíanse two buckets, one larger than another, wide and well taken, I do not know how
expensive, according to cousins ??and the stones are so well made and carved, and underneath
ground say there are more buildings. And they have other things that do not write, for not having
as true. Was commenced to make this force in time of Inca Yupanqui, styled much your child
Tupac Inca, Huayna Capac and Huascar, and even now is something to see, it was much more without comparison.
When the Spanish entered Cuzco, the Indians took great treasure della Quizquiz, Spanish and
still found [175] one, and he believes there is more della radius of one or the other. What's
this fortress and has been serious Guarco just send preserving [176] memorial to the greatness of this
land and even to take them two such forces, as so easily to find them is made. And I will
come back to the subject.

As these Indians have no letters or tell her things but memory is Dellas old age and their songs
and quipos, I say this, because many things vary, saying some one and some another, and not
enough human trial to him he could write eScript, but take desto said what they claimed to be more
true, for counting. This points to the Spanish quest in Peru who claim to know many secrets
dest, I understand that I knew and understand what they think they know and understand and much more,
and all agreed that written what they see, and that I spent working
on it than themselves.

And so, say the big ears, that being things Inca Yupanqui in this state, determined out of Cuzco
with many people from war to what he called Collao and its regions, and thus, leaving his governor
in the city, went out of it and walked until he reached the great people of Ayavire, where they
say, not the natives of wanting to come into compliance, had cautiously and, taking them neglected,
killed all his neighbors, men and women, with do the same Copacopa those of [177] and of slaughter
of Ayavire was therefore all the more perished, but were not some who later were astonished to
see so great wickedness as crazy angry about the fields, he called his older with great howling
and words fearful [178]. And as the Inca hobiese fallen into the invention so gallant and
profitable mitimaes put, as he saw the beautiful valleys and Ayavire campaigns and the beautiful
river that passes by him [179], ordered them to come of the districts were enough people with
women to populate it, and so it was done, and it made for great buildings and temples of the
sun, and many tanks and casting house, so that, mitimaes village, was more Ayavire principal
before, and the Indians who have been wars and cruelty of the Spanish
mitimaes are all strangers and unnatural, so has eScript.

Without this feature again, that having gone through his command some people enough to captains
give Andesuyo war against those who are the towns and quests in the mountains, ran Snakes as
big as a thick wood, which killed all they could, therefore, who have not seen other enemies,
the war made them so artfully that came within the many who entered, and I have received great anger
the Inca to know that new, and being with their grief, a sorceress said she would go and stop
silly and tame snakes aforementioned, that they should not do evil to none but them same they
sit down. Appreciating the work, if accordance with that, he sent him to put an execution, and
did, by believing them and set no to me, because it seems fun, and
charmed snakes, were the enemies, and subjective many war and others
for prayer and good words that they had.

The Inca left Ayavire, say by the way they call Omasuyo, which for him width was made real as we
see it, and walked through the towns of Oruro [180], Asillo, Azangaro where he had some encounters
with the natives, but such words were said, that with them and gave them gifts, attracted
to his friendship and service, and from then on used for Pulici wearing
the others who had friendship and alliance with the Incas, and made
their concluded in the plain people of the plains.

Passing on Inca Yupanqui, have to visit the most towns bordering the Great Lake Titicaca, whose
very quick, brought all his service, getting in each suit people who used the natural thing of
great pleasure for them and that most loose. Entered into the great lake of Titicaca and the
islands looked in it are made by sending making them the largest sun temple and palaces for himself
and his descendants, and made in his Lordship, and all the rest of the vast region of Collao,
returned to the city of Cuzco with great triumph, to where he had, after it came in large parties
to make their custom, and most provinces came to him with great reverence,
present, and the governors and his delegates had great care to fulfill
all his orders.

CAP. LIII .-- How the left Cuzco Inca Yupanqui, and what he did.

Flying Inca Yupanqui fame in such a way over land, which was everywhere of his great deeds. Many, seeing
their flag or captain, he came to know and provide him vassals, affirming his sayings that
the sky had fallen their past, they knew live with both concert and honor. Inca Yupanqui, without
losing its gravity, I replied meekly did not want to do wrong to any nation, but they should
come and give him obedience, as the sun wanted and ordered. And hobiese around to make people call,
came out with all to what they call it Condesuyo and subject to the Yanaguaras and to the Chumbivilcas,
and some Desta provinces had stout Condesuyo region of battles, but, although he gave much
war their efforts and knowledge was therefore damage and death that many gave obedience, taking
by Lord, as did the others, and put in order, leaving the earth and made chiefs the natives,
and commanding that they should not insult or damage to these subjects, it became Cuzco, placing
first governors in the main parties, to impose on the the natural order that had to have, and
for housing to serve you and make their people together, and take
every great concert, and no one was injured, although were of the
poorest.

After this, have more, rested a few days in Cuzco, because he wanted to go in person to the Andes,
where they had sent their champions who would look and listen for the land and let you know
Art della they were the inhabitants, and as his orders were filled throughout the kingdom maintenance
of tanks, sent Quél that would provide the road had to carry, E was done so, and with the captains
and warriors left Cuzco, where he left the governor to for the administration of justice, and
through the mountains and snowy mountains, he knew his runners at the front, and the great wilderness
of the mountains, and even were the as large snakes breeding in these
thickets, did not hurt none, espantábanse to see how monstrous beasts
and they were.

As the natives of those districts were able to enter its land of the Inca, as many of them by
the hand of their masters had been put in service, we came to do the mocha, bringing present
in many bird feathers and coca and as they had in their earth, and very grateful to all. Other
Indians who lived in those mountains subjects who wanted to be, They
sent messengers, no, deserted villages and metiéronse with their wives
in the thick of the mountain.

Inca Yupanqui had great news that after a few days, to the Levant, had large and densely populated
land.

With this new, greedy to find out, he went on, but, being advised as in Cuzco had happened a stir,
and having friends and they a people Marcapata call, stirred it with great haste to Cuzco,
where he spent a few days.

After these, the Indians say, that as the province of Collao is so great and she had in those
days large number of people and dominions of the powerful natural as Inca Yupanqui knew they
had entered the mountains of the Andes, believing that there would
be dead or would come undone, concertáronse all at once, from Vilcanota
forward, to one side and to another, with very great secrecy, rebels
and not be under the lordship of the Incas, saying it was all big
smallness, their parents having been free and not leaving them in
captivity, secured much land and so great a Lord alone</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>