<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04113</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>26166</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>21512</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Don Tadeo le tomó mucho cariño: ¡eso
sí! No le hubiese tratado mejor aunque fuera hijo suyo. Lo único que me supo mal, fue lo de
hacerle cura; pero no pude evitarlo. Si al menos fuera un cura como Muñoz Torrero o Venegas,
o Martín Velasco...

--Calle Vd., por Dios, don José. ¿Curas liberales? ¡Son los peores!

Pepe, Leocadia y la madre callaban, sintiendo que se hablara de aquello, porque don José en
tales casos acababa poniéndose de un humor de todos los diablos; pero Millán, que desde tiempo
atrás tenía deseos de saber la historia del caso, fue poco a poco obligando al viejo a que
la contara.

--Ese don Tadeo estaría entregado a gente de iglesia...

--Cabalito: era un sujeto buenísimo, pero de los que se comen los santos, y que hiló el negocio
con gran finura. Tomó cariño a Tirso, eso es indudable. Creo yo que lo primero que se le ocurrió
fue darle carrera, sin fijarse en cuál, hacerle hombre; luego sus ideas, sus relaciones...
Cuando me trasladaron de Granada a Zamora, hizo el viaje con el chico sólo para que yo le viera;
tenía ya doce años; aquello se lo agradecí mucho, porque únicamente le había visto en dos escapadas
cortísimas que hicimos esa y yo desde Valladolid. Quisimos recoger al muchacho entonces, en
Zamora, pero por un lado, ya comprenderás, las consideraciones a lo mucho que debíamos a don
Tadeo... él insistió en que no se le quitáramos; decía que Tirso era tan bueno, que le había
tomado tanto cariño... Además, la situación nuestra no era buena, es decir, nunca lo ha sido,
jamás hemos podido ahorrar nada. Ahora, si no fuese por la jubilación, ignoro cómo viviríamos.
En fin, para concluir, cuando don Tadeo nos escribió que Tirso quería ser cura, ya le había
metido en el Seminario. ¿Qué íbamos a hacer? Aunque tuviera yo más energía que un león... pues:
¡aguantarme! ¡Cualquiera se arrisca a luchar con gente de iglesia!...

Al llegar aquí calló, temeroso de que se le fuera la lengua.

--¿Pero él tenía vocación?

Pepe, que hacía ya rato daba señales de impaciencia, no pudo aguantar más, y rompió diciendo
entre burlón y enojado:

--¡Vocación! ¡Vocación! ¿Quién sabe lo que es eso? Podrá sentirla el hombre harto de vivir
y pensar; pero un chico de diez y seis años, como era Tirso entonces, cuando entró en el Seminario,
¿qué entendería de consagrarse a Dios? ¡Fue una verdadera infamia, un engaño, un robo, un secuestro
ad mayorem Dei gloriam!

--Sí--respondió Millán--como cuando se meten los jesuitas en familia donde hay niña con dinero,
y al poco tiempo cátatela monjita.

--Exactamente lo mismo, chico. Pero es preciso ser justo. En este caso hubo una notable diferencia
a favor de don Tadeo, que era un fanático exageradísimo, y sin embargo, un hombre muy bueno.
Él debió indudablemente encargarse de mi hermano por pagar a papá el favor aquel de la causa
que ya te hemos contado; luego sus ideas, sus amistades con gente de iglesia, la influencia
que sobre él ejercían sus amigotes, su horror a que el muchacho aprendiera lo que se aprende
en los libros contra esa pillería, el no querer enviarle, siendo su ahijado, a un centro de
enseñanza donde los realistas de la provincia no querían enviar a sus hijos, todo esto contribuyó
al pecado. No hubo en él, al principio, maldad de intención: don Tadeo creyó hacer una acción
meritoria, casi una obra de caridad. No se fijó en que robaba un hijo a sus padres; su propósito
fue poner una voluntad al servicia de Dios.

--Vamos, una calamidad hecha hombre.

Doña Manuela callaba porque, aun disgustándole la forma en que su hijo se expresaba, comprendía
que no le faltaba razón: Leocadia, acostumbrada a escenas parecidas, casi no escuchaba, por
tener todo aquello oído hasta la saciedad. Además, lo que absorbía su atención, por el momento,
era andar lista para que Muían no la cogiese un pie entre los suyos debajo de la mesa, excesillo
disculpado por el amor del novio y favorecido por la clásica camilla, con su largo refajo de
bayeta verde que caía hasta tocar en el suelo. Don José estuvo haciendo con la cabeza signos
de asentimiento mientras habló Pepe.

--Tienes razón en todo, hijo mío; don Tadeo quiso hacer un bien y nos fastidió. Porque, la
verdad, quien es de la Iglesia, sólo es de ella. Hay días en que me parece que no tengo tal hijo.

Doña Manuela, sin ser devota, pues el echar criaturas al mundo no la dejó tiempo para ello,
profesaba cierto respeto inexplicable e inconsciente a las cosas y personas sagradas: sobre
todo, desde que su hijo mayor se hizo cura, comenzó a tener una como sombra de veneración indeterminada
y vaga a la clase sacerdotal; así que, cuantas veces asistía a semejantes diálogos, pasaba
un mal rato. Su falta de ilustración y su escaso sentimiento religioso, no podían prestarle
armas para luchar; pero le dolía que siendo Tirso clérigo, y habiendo por el mundo tanta gente
que les guarda consideración, su otro hijo les mirase con tan malos ojos.

--¿Qué edad tiene ahora?--preguntó Millán.

--Echa la cuenta: de los tres hijos que nos quedan, es el mayor; nació el año de 38, tiene
ahora treinta y cuatro; luego va éste (por Pepe), que tiene veinticuatro, y esa (por Leocadia),
que cumplirá pronto diez y nueve.

--Si hubieran vivido los otros, serían siete, y a todos los he criado yo--añadió con cierto
orgullo la madre--menos a Tirso. Ahora, por vez primera, vamos a vivir juntos.

--¡Ojalá vivamos en paz!--dijo Pepe.

--¡Ave-María Purísima! ¡Qué cosas tiene este hermanito que Dios me ha dado!

--Lo digo en serio, y no me importa que lo sepáis. Tengo miedo a la venida de Tirso; la deseo
y la temo.

Don José callaba tristemente; aquello no le agradaba; pero desde que se supo la próxima llegada
a Madrid de su hijo mayor, tenía el alma combatida por los mismos presentimientos que agitaban
a Pepe, y escuchándole hablar, le parecía oírse a sí propio.

--Por nuestra parte--prosiguió Pepe--nadie ha de turbar esta armonía. Aquí, lo has visto desde
que nos conoces, Millán, mis padres viven para ésta y para mí; nosotros para ellos. Estos muebles,
que tienen más años que yo, no han oído nunca una disputa ni la menor falta de respeto. Leocadia
y yo tratamos a los viejecitos con más mimo que chico a juguete nuevo. ¿Sabes por qué? Porque
no nos hemos separado nunca, ni nos hemos acostado una sola noche sin besarnos, ni ha tenido
uno dolor que no lo sea de los demás, ni ha callado ninguno una alegría, ni ha comido nadie
un bollo sin guardar a los otros, ni se ha hecho un traje sin pensar cuánta ropa tenía cada
uno; en una palabra, chico, nuestras ideas, en mí por convicción, en mis padres y en ésta por
bondad, lo han supeditado todo al cariño, atesorándolo día por día y hora por hora, sin mezcla
de egoísmo, sin compartirlo con nadie... (A don José se le humedecían los ojos de gusto.) Y
ahora vendrá Tirso, educado lejos de nosotros, hecho un hombre... y le recibiremos con los
brazos abiertos. Por mi parte, estoy deseando que llegue: a más cuidados tocará papá cuantos
más seamos en casa. Pero... ¡sabe Dios!

--No hay pero que valga; parece que se te queda algo dentro del cuerpo; pues es tan hermano
tuyo como ésta, que yo misma os he parido a todos.

--No entiendes lo que he querido decir, mamá. Para nosotros todas las dichas de la tierra están
dentro de estas paredes; podemos, o procuramos dárnoslas unos a otros. Cuando venga Tirso le
oirás hablar de distinto modo, y verás cómo hay en él alguna aspiración, alguna idea que sobrepuja
al cariño que nos tenga.

--Vaya, ¡ya pareció aquello! las ideas de ahora; calla, hijo, calla.

--Al tiempo, madre, al tiempo.

Habían concluido de cenar. Los ruidos de la calle inmediata iban cesando poco a poco; percibíase
más claro el lejano campaneo de alguna iglesia, que anunciaba la Misa del Gallo; los chicos
de las latas de petróleo seguían pasando de rato en rato por la calle Imperial, y de los otros
pisos de la casa subían, a intervalos desiguales, cantares, villancicos, carcajadas, gritos
y algún maullido de gato que estaba toda la noche oliendo besugo sin comerlo.

--Quitaremos la mesa--dijo doña Manuela, y comenzó por guardar para don José lo poco que quedara
de la perada y del turrón.

--¿Quiere Vd. que le acostemos entre ese y yo?--preguntó Millán al enfermo.--Van a dar las
doce; en vilo le llevaremos a Vd. a la cama.

Como antes hicieron doña Manuela y Leocadia, Pepe y Millán fueron empujando la butaca desde
el comedor al gabinete en cuya alcoba dormía don José; Leocadia se quedó doblando el mantel
y las servilletas. Un momento después, don José se despedía desde dentro diciendo a Millán,
que había vuelto a salir al comedor:

--Si hay noticias, ven mañana, ¿eh? y tráeme algún periódico, que es la única distracción que
tengo.

--Descuide Vd., no faltaré. Adiós, doña Manuela; que pasen ustedes buenas noches, y de hoy
en un año. Adiós, Leo. ¿Quién hace el favor de bajar a abrirme?

La muchacha, que dormitaba en la cocina, acompañó a Millán. Cuando subió de abrirle la puerta
de la calle, estaban los dos hermanos sentados en el comedor junto a doña Manuela.

--Esperemos a que papá se duerma--decía Leocadia--no sea que nos oiga.

Dejaron pasar un rato; Leocadia destrenzó mientras tanto el escaso pelo a su madre, recogiéndoselo
con un par de horquillas, y luego hizo lo mismo con sus largos rizos castaños. Pepe encendió
un pitillo y examinó la lámpara, como quien ha de utilizarla hasta tarde, para que luego no
faltara petróleo.

--Mucho escribes, hermano.

--Yo, cuando quiero a alguien, no soy como tú, que apenas haces caso de Millán. Pues mira:
sus intenciones no pueden ser más claras. Esta noche he dicho yo eso de que bajabas pronto
a abrirme cuando imaginabas que él venía; pero, en fin, allá tú. A mí me parece que no estás
muy expresiva con él.

--¡Tiene gracia! ¿Quieres que me le coma con la vista? ¡Ni que fuera una estampa!

--No vayas a pensar que quiero meterte el novio por los ojos. Lo que te digo es que, aunque
vivieras cien años, no encontrarías uno mejor.

--¿Es príncipe?

--Sí; como tú princesa.

--Pues hijo, tú bien haces el amor a una señorita de coche.

En esto se asomó al gabinete doña Manuela.

--Hijos, ya está medio dormido: vamos a hablar pronto cuatro palabras, que estoy rendida y
quiero también acostarme.

--Pues mira, mamá, lo que hay que hablar es poco; pero no queda más medio que decidir algo.
La botica se lleva un dineral; es necesario gastar menos en todo lo demás. Yo voy a hacer un
trabajo para don Luis, que de fijo me pagará bien; pero con lo que esto produzca no hay que
contar hasta el mes que viene.

--Bueno; lo primero es despedir a la chica: aunque no son más que treinta reales, algo es algo.
Mañana llevará ésta a empeñar la colcha de Filipinas y los candeleritos de plata.

--Lo que debíamos hacer es suprimir parte del gasto diario--dijo Leo.--Que no traigan carne
más que para papá, y con decirle que coma en su cuarto para moverse menos, luego nosotros nos
venimos al comedor, y así no se entera.

--Yo, con tres cajetillas a la semana tengo bastante. Además, don Luis me da algunos puros
y los guardaré para picarlos. ¿Os han dicho algo de la tienda?

--Si--repuso Leocadia--por cada docena de pañuelos pagan, según el dibujo, de veinticuatro
a treinta y seis reales, y tengo yo que poner lo que haga falta.

--En resumen--dijo Pepe haciendo números con un lápiz al margen de La Correspondencia, y murmurando
entre dientes las cifras del cálculo--tenemos veintisiete duros de la paga de papá, con diez
y ocho de mi sueldo, son cuarenta y cinco, y unos ocho o diez que le den a ésta por los bordados...
de cincuenta y tres a cincuenta y cuatro duros al mes: quitando los veinte, lo menos, que hay
que dar a la lonja por los plazos, y el pico que falta del sastre, quedarán unos treinta y
cuatro duros... pongamos a duro diario para el gasto de la casa... la botica es la que nos pierde.

--Pues hijo, de algún lado hay que sacarlo; ni un cuarto se malgasta... ¿Qué haríamos?

--Ahora, acostarnos; cada cual a su cama. Dejadme a mí: creo que don Luis nos ha de sacar de
apuros. Al menos yo he de hacerle un favor que... en fin, ¿quién sabe? Adiós mamá; y tú, fea,
cara de mona, hasta mañana.--Y dando un beso a cada una, las echó suavemente del comedor. Cogió
luego la candileja que había en la cocina, fue con ella a su cuarto, volvió trayendo sobre
un cartapacio grande tintero, plumas, papeles, sobres y tres o cuatro libros, y colocándose
lo mejor que pudo, se sentó ante la camilla.

Hasta cerca de la madrugada estuvo tomando apuntes de varios libros, escribiendo en las cuartillas
párrafos muy cortitos, como extractos, cifras seguidas de referencias y citas. Aquello parecía
trabajo preparado para que lo aprovechara otro. Cuando en el reloj cercano sonaron las tres,
el pobre muchacho tenía ya la cabeza pesada, la vista insegura, y su hermoso busto, inclinado
aún hacia la mesa, aparecía envuelto en una nube de humo que habían dejado en la atmósfera
del cuarto los pitillos consumidos, cuya ceniza, movida por la respiración, revoloteaba sobre
las hojas de los libros. Todavía continuó llenando cuartillas un rato, hasta que, yertos los
pies y ardorosa la frente, recogió los papeles y los guardó en uno de los volúmenes. En seguida
sacó un plieguecillo para una carta, y quedándose un instante como ensimismado, pensó: «La
escribiré, por si no nos vemos mañana.» Luego, al buscar los sobres, como hubiese entre ellos
uno mayor y más pesado, lo abrió, sacando de él dos o tres cartas y un retrato de mujer, el
de la señorita de coche que mentó Leocadia, y contemplándolo un momento, murmuró: «¡Qué bonita
es!» En seguida, sin que ningún ruido le distrajese, entregado con alma y vida a sus ideas,
tomó el plieguecillo y comenzó a escribir:

«Adorada Paz:...»

II

Pepe y Millán se conocieron en 1862, cuando a los catorce o quince años cursaban en el Instituto
del Noviciado primero de latín.

Eran ambos entonces de escaso desarrollo físico, pero inteligentes, guapos, listos sin exceso
de picardía, y avisados sin sobra de malicia. En su organismo endeble de madrileños criados
en casas pobres, prevalecía su entendimiento de niños educados junto a personas mayores que,
sin velar nada, hablan de todo libremente. Pepe era delgado, alto, larguirucho, con el pelo
rubio, rizoso y arremolinado, que dicen ser indicación de genio vivo. El mirar penetrante de
sus ojos parecía, al fijarse en las cosas, querer arrancarlas la enseñanza que de ellas brota;
nunca se le cansaba la boca de preguntas, ni los oídos de respuestas: en cambio, la impaciencia
que demostraba para interrogar se le trocaba en calma para oír. Desde pequeño, una incredulidad
instintiva le hizo regocijarse menos que otros chicos con los cuentos de brujas, y siendo mayorcito,
siempre tuvo en los labios el ¿cómo? y el ¿por qué? A semejanza de los niños que rompen los
juguetes para ver lo que tienen dentro, él, obedeciendo quizá a una predisposición poco vulgar,
pretendía que se le diese explicación de todo; así que, para negarle lo que pedía, era preciso,
al menos, simular un razonamiento, convencerle, con lo cual quedaba tranquilo y obediente.
Su precocidad no era la que consiste en el temprano desarrollo de algunas facultades, sino
en cierta serenidad de juicio que, dominando sobre las impresiones, le impulsaba a rechazar
lo que su entendimiento no alcanzaba. Había que explicárselo todo, y la señal de que lo comprendía
era una docilidad encantadora. Jamás consiguió una criada divertirle con gigantes de los que
tragan carne cruda, hazañas de ladrones ni aventuras maravillosas de princesas encantadas;
pero si escuchaba a sus padres sucesos reales, casos vívidos, algo en que hubiera verdad, entonces,
con los ojitos muy abiertos, como perrillo a quien enseñan golosina, se estaba quieto, esperando
que la relación terminara, para hacer luego preguntas y más preguntas acerca de lo que no podía
entender. Con una sonrisa muy burlona rechazaba lo que repugnaba a sus ideas aniñadas, y a
veces, las frases que se le ocurrían, si no por el propósito, tenían por la entonación algo
de sátira.

Millán era más inocentón, más chico; había menos dificultad para engañarle, y era también de
mayor robustez y dado a juegos más arriscados. La savia de la vida, que el primero tenía como
reconcentrada en el cerebro, había tomado en el segundo forma de energía física. Uno era de
la estirpe de los que piensan, otro de la raza de los que obedecen. Viéndoles jugar juntos,
resultaba Pepe voluntarioso, porque Millán parecía plegarse a sus caprichos; pero, a poco que
se les observase, era fácil notar que la pasividad de éste no era sino el reconocimiento implícito
e instintivo de la superioridad de aquél. Además, Millán tenía buenísima índole y, como complaciéndose
en ello, dejaba ver que, si en cosas de fuerza estaba la ventaja de su parte, en todo lo restante
era de Pepe la primacía. En hacer espadas de palo, cortar tablas, correr al marro, saltar al
paso, trepar por rejas y encaramarse a tapias, no hallaba Millán competidor: para lograr premios,
disculpar travesuras y evitar regaños, tenía Pepe especial ingenio. Sabía esperar para pedir
a tiempo, dejar pasar los primeros instantes de un enfado, no irritar el disgusto con respuestas
y evocar, en ocasión propicia, el recuerdo de lo ofrecido.

Los comienzos de su amistad fueron una especie de pacto contra el latín y contra aquel modo
de enseñar la lengua del Lacio que hacía aborrecibles a Virgilio y a Cicerón. Formaron una
sociedad de socorros mutuos para apuntarse la lección, ahorrarse trabajo al traducir, buscando
juntos los significados en el diccionario y responder, al pasar lista, uno por otro: hasta
llegaron a reunir en común la colección de sellos de franqueo que por entonces hacía todo chiquillo
madrileño. Al principio sólo se veían en el aula o en el claustro del Instituto, que tiene
entrada por la calle de los Reyes; luego se encontraron en el camino al venir de sus casas,
y lo anduvieron juntos, esperándose recíprocamente en la plaza de Santo Domingo, donde llegaban
casi a la misma hora. Millán vivía en la plazuela del Biombo; Pepe en la calle de Botoneras:
aquél venía por la Costanilla de los Ángeles; éste por la calle de las Veneras, y después seguían
juntos hasta el Noviciado, haciendo escala en cuantos escaparates hubiera algo que les llamara
la atención. Las mañanas de invierno compraban buñuelos, las tardes de verano chufas, y en
todo tiempo alfeñique, mojama, garrofa o caramelos de a ochavo; pero su verdadera delicia consistía
en repartirse una cajetilla de pitillos, sin que jamás llegasen a reñir sobre quién gastaba
un cuarto más o menos. Durante el primer curso conservaron el aspecto algo encogido de chicos
criados entre faldas y limpios de lenguaje, no hechos a la libertad de andar solos por la calle;
mas al poco tiempo fueron abriendo oídos a la malicia y teniendo la lengua pronta para la desvergüenza:
entróseles la picardía al pensamiento como ciencia infusa, aprendieron a decir palabrotas,
pegóseles algo de ese impudor que se recoge al paso, y aumentaron su vocabulario con frases
soeces y giros achulados, cuyo sentido acaso no entendían, repitiendo tales cosas por imaginar
que hablando gordo harían viso de hombres bragados. No por esto se malearon, y aquellas obscenidades
y ternos que empleaban entre sí, pero que ante nadie repetían, fueron como un cieno que, si
les ensució la boca, no les llegó a manchar el alma.

Una mañana que faltó a su clase un catedrático, se marcharon con otros chicos a jugar a la
Era del Mico, y esta escapatoria fue para ellos una revelación. De entonces en adelante, cuando
calculaban que podían preguntarles la lección, iban a clase; pero los más de los días, luego
de pasada lista, se escurrían, o pinchándose las encías y manchándose el pañuelo, fingían echar
sangre por las narices para que les dejaran salir, renegando de la declinación y el hipérbaton
latino como de las mayores infamias que inventaron hombres. De esta época data en la historia
de su vida la larga serie de correrías que hicieron por Madrid, evitando siempre ir por calles
céntricas donde pudieran hallarse de manos a boca con quien diera en sus casas noticia del
encuentro. Así llegaron a conocer palmo a palmo cuantos paseos, carreteras y cuestas rodean
a la Corte, yéndose a pies que queréis por esas rondas, como hidalgos de leyenda que marchan
a ver tierras, y por entonces debió ser cuando en casa de Millán el padre de éste, y en la
de Pepe su madre, notaron que los chicos rompían zapatos como si lo hicieran a porfía. El famoso
Marco Polo en lo antiguo, y Livingstone o Stanley en estos tiempos, fueron junto a ellos exploradores
de poco más o menos. ¿Qué mayor expedición que ir desde el Noviciado a la Puerta de Hierro
haciendo escala en el Puente Verde para llamar ¡todas! ¡todas! a las lavanderas del río? ¿Pues
y el viaje a Moratalaz o Amaniel para ver hacer el ejercicio a la tropa? ¿Y el ir a extasiarse
ante los puestos de San Isidro, en vísperas de romería, o marcharse en invierno a ver si se
había helado el Canal del Lozoya? Lo que nunca se les ocurrió fue tomar partido en pedrea de
las Peñuelas, ver ajusticiado en el Campo de Guardias ni tratar con los barquilleros que, al
juego de la cinta, robaban dinero a los provincianos en la Montaña del Príncipe Pío. En cambio,
les divertía mucho ver en Palacio la parada o estarse en Santa Cruz oyendo a los charlatanes
perorar desde el pescante de un simón vendiendo grasa de león para quitar manchas o diciendo
que tenían polvos para matar los insetos solitarios del estómago, que es el intestino donde
se mete la comida. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document00376</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>326037</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>19506</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Don Tadeo it took a lot of love: that
yes! There would have been treated better if only his son. The only thing I felt bad, was it
of cure him, but I could not help. If only he were a priest or as Torrero Muñoz Venegas and
Martin Velasco ...

- Calle you, by God, Don José.

Cures "liberal? They are the worst!

Pepe, Leocadia and her mother were silent, feeling there was talk of that, because Don Jose such
cases, just getting in a mood of all the devils, but Miller, who from time back had a desire
to know the history of the case, was gradually forcing the old to
the count.

- This gift would be delivered Tadeo people from church
...

- Cabalito: it was a terrific subject, but those who eat the
saints, and spun the business with great finesse.

Tirso took a liking to, that's undeniable.

I think the first thing that occurred to him was to give race, without looking at what, to make
man, then his ideas, his relationships ... When I moved from Granada to Zamora, made the trip with
the boy just so I could see; already had twelve years that I thanked him very much, because
he had seen only two escapes cortísimas we did that and I from Valladolid. We wanted to pick up
the boy then, Zamora, but on the one hand, and understand the considerations of how much we had to
don Thaddeus ... he insisted that he was not take off, said Tirso was so good that he had taken
so much love ... In addition, our situation was not good, that is, never has been, We could
never save anything. Now, if it were not for retirement, I do not know how we would live. In
order to conclude, when we wrote that Don Tadeo Tirso wanted to become a priest, had already
put in the seminar. What do we do? Although I had more energy than a lion ... then: Stand it!
Anyone Arrisca to fight with people from church! ...

Coming here was silent, fearful that it was the language.

- But he had a vocation?

Pepe, who had long since showed signs of impatience, could not hold
back and broke it by saying between mocking and angry:

- Vocation!

Vocation! Who knows what that is? May feel tired of living man and thinking, but a boy of
sixteen years, as was Tirso then, when he entered the seminary, Understand how to devote to God? It
was a real shame, deception, robbery, kidnapping mayorem ad Dei gloriam!

- Yes - said Millán - like when you put the Jesuit family where girl with money and soon cátatela
nun.

- Exactly the same, boy. But it must be fair. In this case there was a noticeable difference
in favor of Mr. Thaddeus, who was a fan exageradísimo, and yet a very good man. He should certainly
take care of my brother for the father to pay for one of the causes which we've already had,
then their ideas, their friends from church, the influence exerted on him his cronies, his horror
at the boy to learn what is learned on the books against the rascals, not wanting to send,
with his godson, a center realistic learning where the province would not send their children, all
contributed sin. There was in him, at first, evil intent: Don Tadeo thought to action meritorious,
almost a charity. Did not notice a child who stole his parents, his purpose was a desire to serve
God.

- Let a man made calamity.

Doña Manuela silent because even disliking the way your child was expressed, understood that he
was right: Leocadia, accustomed to similar scenes, hardly heard, for have all heard that ad nauseam.
Also, what absorbed his attention, for the moment walking was not ready for the cogiese Millan
among his foot under the table, excesillo apologized for the love of the bridegroom and favored
by the classic couch with her long underskirt of green baize playing
fell to the ground.

Don Jose was making signs with his head Pepe assent as he spoke.

- You're right about everything, my son, Don Tadeo wanted to do well and we screwed up. Because,
Indeed, who is from the Church, only her. There are days when I do not think I have such a
son.

Doña Manuela, without being pious, as the creatures take the world did not leave time for it,
professed some respect and unconscious inexplicable things and sacred persons, on However, since
his eldest son became a priest, began to have a shadow of worship
as indeterminate and vague to the priestly class, so, how often attended
such talks, he spent a hard time.

Their lack of enlightenment and religious feeling low, they could
not pay arms to fight, but it still hurt Tirso clergyman, and having
so many people around the world consideration save them, his other
son as they looked with disfavor.

- How old are you now? - Said Millán.

-
Check the account: of the three children we have left, is the largest,
was born in 38, has now thirty-four, then going it (by Pepe), who
is twenty, and that (for Leocadia) who will be nineteen soon.

- If
you have lived the other, would be seven, and all I have grown up
- with some added proud mother - least Tirso.

Now, for the first time, we will live together.

- I wish to live in peace! - Pepe said.

- Hail-Mary Immaculate!

What things has this brother that God has given me!

- I mean, I do not care who you know.

I have fear of coming Tirso, the desire and fear.

Don José silent sadly, that did not like, but since he knew the next
arrival Madrid with his eldest son, had fought for the same soul that
stirred misgivings Pepe, and listening to him, he thought to himself
heard.

- For our part - continued Pepe - no one is to disturb this
harmony.

Here, you've seen since we know, Millán, my parents live for this and for me, us to them. These
furniture that are older than me, have never heard a dispute not the slightest disrespect. Leocadia
and I tried to mime that old people over a new toy boy.

Do you know why? Because we have not separated ever, and we slept one night without kissing, or
had a pain that is not the other, neither silent nor joy, nor has anyone eaten a bun without saving
the other, or a suit made without thinking about how many clothes were each one, in a word, boy,
our ideas, in my conviction, my parents and the latter by goodness, I have linked all the love,
treasuring day by day and hour by hour, unmixed selfishness, without sharing it with anyone
... (A Don José is moistened the eyes of taste.) Y now come Tirso, educated away from us, become
a man ... and we welcome them with open arms. For my part, I can not wait: a few more care
will be playing Dad more of us at home. But ... God knows!

- No buts about it, it seems that you have left something inside the body, it is so brother
yours like this that I have kidded myself to everyone.

- You do not understand what I meant, Mom.

For us all the joys of earth are within these walls, we can, or try to give them to us each
other.

When it comes Tirso you will hear in different ways, and see in it any aspiration, any idea which
transcends the affection that we have.

- Wow, that was it! ideas now, hush, child, hush.

- At the time,
mother, at a time.

Dinner had ended. The immediate street noises were gradually ceasing; perceived more clear the distant
chime of a church, which announced the Midnight Mass, the children oil cans still happening
from time to time by Imperial Street, and other floors of the house rose, with uneven intervals,
songs, carols, laughter, screams and a cat that was meowing all night without eating smelling
bream.

- Remove the table - "Dona Manuela, and began to save for Don José
what little was left the perry and nougat.

- Do you want that you
go to bed between that and me? - Miller asked the patient to give
.-- Van twelve in suspense will take for you to bed.

As before Dona Manuela made and Leocadia, Pepe and Miller were pushing the chair from the dining
room cabinet in which he slept Don José; Leocadia folding the cloth fell and napkins. A moment
later, Jose was dismissed from the inside telling the Millán, he was back out to the dining
room

- If there is news, see tomorrow, eh? and bring me a newspaper, which
is the only distraction I have.

- Rest assured you, not fail.

Goodbye, Dona Manuela, who pass you good night, and today in one year. Goodbye, Leo. Who will
you please go down to open up?

The girl, who was sleeping in the kitchen, accompanied Millán.

When you open the door up Street, were the two brothers sitting in
the dining room next to Dona Manuela.

- Let's wait for Dad to sleep
- said Leocadia - lest we hear.

Spend some time left, Leocadia unbraided thinning hair meanwhile her mother, gathering with
a pair of forks, and then did the same with her long brown curls.

Pepe lit a cigarette and looked at the lamp, as having to use it
until late, then have no missing oil.

- Much writing, brother.

-
Yo, when I want someone I'm not like you, if you just Millán.

Well, look: their intentions can not be clearer. Tonight I have said that they lowered your
soon to open up when they imagined that he was coming, but, well, there you are. I think you're
not very expressive with it.

- Funny! You want me to eat it with their eyes? Not to be a stamp!

- Do not think you want to get you the groom from his eyes.

What I say is that although you lived a hundred years, would not
find a better one.

- Is it Prince?

- Yes, as you princess.

- Well,
son, you rather make love to a lady's car.

In this cabinet appeared to Dona Manuela.

- Children, already half asleep, we will talk soon four words, I'm
exhausted and I also sleep.

- Look, Mom, what is that talking is
little, but there is no other means to decide something.

The pharmacy takes a lot of money, you need to spend less on everything else. I'll make a work
for Don Luis, who fixed pay me well, but what it should not occur have until next month.

- Well, the first thing is to fire the girl, but not more than thirty
real, it's something.

Tomorrow will take it to pawn the quilt candeleritos Philippines and silver.

- What you should do is to remove part of daily spending - said Leo .-- Do not bring meat rather
than dad, and tell you to eat in your room to move less, then we come into the room, and so does
not know.

- I, with three packs a week I have enough.

In addition, Don Luis I get some cigars and to keep chopping. Would you have said something
at the store?

- Yes - said Leocadia - per dozen handkerchiefs pay, according to the drawing, twenty-four Thirty-six
reals, and I have to put whatever it takes.

- In summary - Pepe said crunching numbers with a pencil on the margins of correspondence,
and muttering mumble calculation figures - we pay hard twenty-seven
Dad, ten and eight of my salary is forty-five, and eight or ten be
given to it by the embroidery ... of fifty-three to fifty-four dollars
a month, removing the twenty, at least, that there to give the market
over the time, and the lack of tailor peak, will be about thirty four
dollars ... put a hard day for the cost of the house ... the pharmacy
is the one we lost.

- Well, son, that somewhere out there, and fourth
is wasted ... What would we do?

- Now, lie down, each in his own bed.

Leave me to myself, I think that Don Luis has to draw from trouble.

At least I have to ask a favor ... in short, who knows? Goodbye Mom and you, ugly cute face,
until tomorrow .-- And giving a kiss to each, gently threw the room. Took then the limelight
was in the kitchen, went with her to her room, returned with about a large binder ink, pens, paper,
envelopes and three or four books, and placing the best he could, sat at the table.

Until near dawn was taking notes of several books, writing in the
pages very cortitos paragraphs, as extracts, numbers followed by references
and citations.

That seemed paper prepared for that exploited other. As the clock near the stroke of three, the poor
boy's head was already heavy, uncertain view and a beautiful bust, sloping even to the table,
appeared in a cloud of smoke that had been left in the atmosphere Cigarette consumed the room,
whose ash, moved by the breath, hovered over the leaves of books. Still continued to fill pages
for a while, until the stiff Burning feet and forehead, gathered up the papers and put them
in one volume. Immediately took a plieguecillo for a letter, leaving a pensive moment as she
thought, "The write, if not see you tomorrow. "Then, to find the envelopes, and have between
them a larger and heavier, opened it, taking from him two or three letters and a portrait of women,
Mademoiselle de creased Leocadia car, and staring a moment, murmured: "How beautiful is! "Then,
without any noise distracted him, delivered with soul and life to your ideas, plieguecillo seized
and began to write:

Adoro Paz :...»

II

Pepe and Miller met in 1862, when at fourteen or fifteen years were enrolled in the Institute Novitiate
first Latin.

They were both then of little physical, but smart, handsome, ready without excess of mischief,
and without plenty of malice warned. In his feeble body servants Madrid poor homes, the prevailing
understanding of children educated alongside older people, without watching anything, speak
of all free. Pepe was thin, tall, lanky, with hair blond, curly and swirling, who claim to be
an indication of temper. Looking penetrating his eyes seemed to look at things, want to start
teaching them that springs; he was never tired of questions mouth or ears of responses: rather,
impatience showing bartered to interrogate you to listen quietly. Since childhood, unbelief instinctively
rejoice him less than other children with tales of witches, and being grown man, was always on our lips
how? and why? Like children who break toys to see what they have inside, he, following perhaps
a bit vulgar disposition, intended to be given explanation for everything, so, to deny what you
asked, it was necessary, at least simulate an argument, to convince, which was quiet and obedient.
His precocity was not the one consists in the early development of some faculties, but trial
in certain serenity that dominates over impressions, led him to reject what your understanding
is not enough. We had to explain everything, and he understood signal was a charming docility.
Never got a maid with giants amused that swallow raw meat, feats of thieves or enchanted princesses
wonderful adventures; but if you listened to his parents real events, vivid cases, something
that had true then with your eyes wide open, as they teach puppy treat, was still waiting
that the relationship ended, then to questions and more questions about what could not understand.
With a very mocking smile rejected what was repugnant to their childish ideas and Sometimes the
phrase that occurred to him, if not for the purpose, something had by intonation satire.

Miller was more simpleton, smaller, had less difficulty to deceive, and it was also given more
strength and Arriscado games.

The sap of life, as the former had reconcentrated in the brain, had taken in the second form
of physical energy. One was the race of those who think, another race of those who obey. Watching
them play together Pepe was willful, it seemed Miller bend to their whims, but to little are
observed, it was easy to notice that the passivity of this was but the implicit recognition
instinctive superiority of the former. In addition, Miller was very good nature and, as he pleases
it, revealed that, in matters of force was the advantage of you, in everything else Pepe was the lead.
In making wooden swords, cutting boards, run the hammer, jump to step, climb fences and walls to climb,
no competitor was Millán: to make awards condone pranks and avoid scolding, Pepe had special talent.
He knew to wait to ask time, let the first moments of anger, not to irritate the annoyance with
answers and evoke a favorable opportunity, the memory of the offering.

The beginnings of his friendship was a kind of pact against Latin and against this mode to teach
the language of Latium that was abhorrent to Virgil and Cicero.

Formed a mutual aid society to join the lesson, save work to translate, looking together the
meanings in the dictionary and responding, the roll call one by another, until came to gather
together the collection of postage stamps which by then was all boy Madrid. At first only saw
in the classroom or on the faculty of the Institute, which has Street entrance of the Kings,
then found their way to come home, and we walked together, expecting another in the plaza of Santo
Domingo, where he arrived almost at the same time. Millan lived on the square of the Screen;
Pepe on the streets of Buttons: Costanilla that came by the Angels; it down the street from
the scallops, then followed together to the Novitiate, stopping in as many windows had something
they called attention. Winter mornings bought donuts, summer evenings groundnuts, and all-weather
wimp, roe, or carob candies to farthing, but his delight was in sharing a pack of cigarettes, but
never arrived to fight over who spent quarter or so. During the first year kept the boys look
a little cramped raised among skirts and clean language, made no freedom to walk alone down
the street; but soon were opening ears to the malice and having ready for the shameless tongue: mischievousness
entróseles thought as infused knowledge, learned to swear, pegóseles some of that impudence
that is given step, and increase your vocabulary with phrases Achilles turns foul language and
whose meaning may not understand, imagine repeating such things that talking about fat men would
hint of panties. Not for this malearon, and those obscenities and suits that used to each other, but to
anyone they repeated, was like a mud that if I messed up the mouth, did not arrive to stain
the soul.

One morning she missed her class with a professor, went to other guys to play Mico was, and this loophole
was to them a revelation. From then on, when calculated that they could ask the lesson, went
to class, but most of the day, then passing list, slipped, or gum
pricking and staining the tissue, they pretended take bleed from nose
to let them out, denying the decline and hyperbaton Latin and for
older men who invented slander.

Dates from this period in history of his life long series of raids they did in Madrid, and
avoiding going through streets downtown where they could be hand to mouth at home who gave notice
of meeting. So they came to know every inch of few walks, roads and surrounding hills the Court,
leaving a foot you want for these rounds, as gentlemen marching Legend to see land and then had
to be home when Miller's father, and the Pepe's mother noticed that the boys broke shoes as if
they were to stubbornness. The famous Marco Polo in the old, and Livingstone and Stanley these
days, browsers were next to them of more or less. What greater issue to go from the novice to
the Iron Gate stopping at the Green Bridge to call them all! All! the washers of the river?
Why, and the trip to Amaniel Moratalaz or do the exercise for the troops? What about going
to ecstasy to the positions of San Isidro, on the eve of pilgrimage, or go in winter to see
if had frozen the Canal del Lozoya? What never occurred to them was taking sides in stoning
of the Peñuelas, see executed in Camp Guard or deal with the waffle that, game tape and stole money
from the provincials in the Principe Pio Mountains. In contrast, I enjoyed very much to see in the palace
stop or to stand on Santa Cruz listening to quacks rant from the driver's seat of a cab selling
lion to remove grease spots or saying powders having to kill the lone inset stomach, which is
the intestine where gets the food.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>