<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document10715</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>54733</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19003</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> En tales momentos, las mujeres menos agraciadas parecen aéreas
y adorables; los hombres más tímidos se atreven a todo, y sintiendo más se expresan con mayor
elocuencia.

--Isabel, dijo Leonardo, me extraña tu conducta conmigo.

--Califíquela, repuso Isabel sonriendo.

--No me corresponde calificarla, por la sencilla razón de que soy el agraviado.

--¿Eso más? Pues era lo que faltaba.

--¿Te sorprende? ¿Cómo se compagina, si no, nuestra amigable despedida de La Habana (por mi
parte, se entiende), con tu silencio e indiferencia enseguidas...?

--¿Sin motivo que justificara el cambio?

--Sin motivo que lo justificara. Yo al menos no he podido penetrarlo todavía.

--Refresque Vd. la memoria de los hechos.

--Nada, Isabel, no alcanzo, desconozco el motivo.

--¿De verás?

--De veras.

--Entonces he sido una loca, una tonta, he visto visiones.

--Tanto como eso no, Isabel. ¿No te ocurre que hayas podido interpretar mal un acto inocente
mío o de otra persona hacia mí?

--Si no se trata de interpretaciones, señor don Leonardo, se trata de lo que yo vi con mis ojos.

--Sepamos lo que vio mi señora doña Isabel con sus ojos.

--Vi lo que Vd. vio, mejor dicho, lo que le pasó Vd. al estribo del quitrín.

--¿Y ése era motivo suficiente para que tú me perdieras el cariño y estuvieras a punto de olvidarme?

--Lo era y grande, para enojarse cualquier mujer de vergüenza, por mucho que la cegara la pasión.

--Veo claro, Isabel, que en todo ello ha habido una equivocación de tu parte, y que, sin quererlo
has sido injusta conmigo.

--Explíquese Vd., dijo Isabel con aparente ansiedad.

--Te diré en pocas palabras lo que pasó, continuó Leonardo, poniéndose colorado, porque de
hecho pensado iba a mentir. Mientras te decía el último adiós, naturalmente extendí un pie
sobre la acera. Una de las dos mulatas que pasaban tropezó conmigo, y, creyendo que le había
armado una zancadilla, llena de ira me dio un empellón. Tú sabes lo insolente que son esas
mujerzuelas cuando se creen ofendidas.

--Sí, dijo Isabel pensativa. Después de un breve rato añadió: Mas ¿qué motivo le di yo para
que me dijese la palabra indecente que aún me zumba en los oídos?

--Tu exclamación, Isabel, y luego el llamarla Adela, cuando tal vez se llamaba Nicolasa o Rosario
fue sin duda lo que aumentó su cólera.

--Si la llamé por el nombre de Adela, mejor dicho, si en mi exclamación solté ese nombre, fue
porque me figuré que era ella su hermana de Vd. Además de tomarla por el vivo retrato de Adela,
no pude, ni debí imaginar que otra mujer tuviese con Vd. semejantes bromas.

--¡Toma! El cuento es que no hubo broma de su parte.

--Luego ella le conoce a Vd. y le maltrató por... celos.

--La conozco de vista, lo confieso, ya me había llamado la atención su semejanza con mi hermana
Adela; mas no la he dado jamás ocasión a encelarse de mí.

--Quizá le ama a Vd. en secreto.

--No tendría nada de particular, sólo que en mi vida le he dicho «ojos negros tienes».

--Sentiría hacer a Vd. una injusticia, Leonardo. Las apariencias, sin embargo, le condenan.

--No, Isabel, no. Soy inocente. Si te engañase en este momento, si no te dijese toda verdad,
si te pintara una pasión que no sentía, si en consecuencia te hubiese dado justo motivo de
agravio, sería el más malo de los hombres...

--Está bien; doblemos la hoja, le interrumpió Isabel convencida.

--¿Pelillos a la mar?, le preguntó Leonardo con amoroso acento.

--Pelillos a la mar, contestó ella con celestial sonrisa. No habría dicha para mí si me viese
condenada a dudar de la palabra del hombre a quien tenía por amigo y caballero.

--Bien, agregó Leonardo más animado. ¿No crees tú que debíamos sellar esta dulce reconciliación...?

Diciendo esto dejaba correr disimuladamente la mano por el barandal para coger la de Isabel,
que se apoyaba en el mismo. Pero ella, evitando la ocasión, evitó el peligro. Se puso seria
y pasó al lado de su tía, a quien dijo alto que era hora de recogerse. El reloj de Leonardo
marcaba las once de la noche.

Había volado el tiempo. Diego Meneses, no obstante sabedor de que la ocasión la pintan calva,
supo aprovecharla lo que bastaba para hacer a Rosa una formal declaración de amor; habiendo
encontrado el tema o pretexto de la conversación en el regalo del clavel que esa joven hizo
a Leonardo en el jardín. ¡Cándida paloma del vergel de Alquízar! Ella, que no había escuchado
antes un «te amo, Rosa» dicho con intención y con fuego. Ella, que se sentía atraída hacia
aquel joven como la aguja al imán, como la avecica a la serpiente, no pudo desviar la atracción,
deshacer el encanto; no encontró a mano gesto, palabra ni ardid para negar que había sucumbido
y que también amaba a su tentador desde la primer temporada que pasaron juntos en el cafetal
La Luz.

CAPÍTULO II

     Y en los bellos cafetales
      todo es frescura y olores,
      besadas sus blancas flores
      por las brisas tropicales.

         J. PADRÍÑEZ

Como novia de Cupido desde la víspera, Rosa Ilincheta, por el temor pudoroso de encararse con
su cómplice a la clara luz del día, retardó cuanto pudo su salida del tocador. Pero Isabel
tenía obligaciones que llenar y bien temprano apareció en el pórtico del sur de la casa con
la sombrilla en la mano derecha, una cestita calada al brazo izquierdo por el aro, y por todo
abrigo el pañolón de seda bordado de realce.

Asomaba entonces el sol por un ángulo de la casa, alumbrando una parte del jardín y proyectando
la sombra de aquélla y de los árboles, por largo trecho, sobre el espacioso batey de la finca.
Había sido abundante el rocío de la madrugada. Empapado estaba el césped, apagado el polvo
bermejo de los caminos y las hojas de las plantas y las corolas de las flores cuajadas de menudos
aljófares; otros tantos prismas que descomponían la luz del almo sol, al recibirla de soslayo.

Echó Isabel una mirada inquisitiva por todo el país desplegado ante ella, y se aventuró fuera
del pórtico; porque desde allí echó a ver una rosa de Alejandría que acababa de abrirse al
dulce calor solar, en el cuadro del sudeste del jardín. Cortola sin punzarse ni mojarse, y
cuando se adornaba con ella la espléndida trenza de sus cabellos, volvió maquinalmente los
ojos hacia la casa y le pareció que uno de sus huéspedes la observaba desde el postigo de la
ventana del cuarto, en el extremo del pórtico, donde en efecto se habían los dos alojado. Era
Diego Meneses, que por no haber disfrutado de sueño tranquilo, dejó la cama desde el amanecer
y aspiraba el puro ambiente del campo, a la sazón que Isabel apareció en medio de sus gayadas
flores.

De tal modo la turbó este incidente, que por breve rato estuvo indecisa entre si volvía atrás
o seguiría adelante, porque los actos de adornarse el cabello y de mirar para la casa, magüer
que inocentes y casuales, podían interpretarse de diversas maneras, y ella huía tanto de la
frivolidad como de la necia coquetería. Pero tenía que salir y salió con firme paso.

Por el lado del sur, una cerca de piedra separaba el campo del cuadrado en que se comprendía
el variado caserío de la finca. En el centro se alzaba el molino del café, entre los dos pares
de tendales, capaces de contener a un tiempo, secándose, la mitad de la cosecha. Más lejos,
cerrando el gran espacio por la izquierda, se veía el grueso y oscuro brocal del pozo con su
horca y garrucha para la extracción del agua; el palomar después, el corral de las aves y algunos
chiqueros; al fondo y a la derecha, el campanario, o más bien el pilar de madera de cuyo brazo
cubierto con un tejadillo, pendía la campana; los graneros o almacenes, las caballerizas, el
establo de las vacas y las otras dependencias. Los bohíos de los esclavos figuraban una aldea
de regular tamaño.

Ni estaba desprovisto de vegetación el magnífico batey que hemos venido describiendo, pues
muchos árboles, y sin duda los más copudos y corpulentos de toda aquella hacienda, le adornaban
y daban sombra. Entre ellos varios aguacates, mameyes colorados, mangos y caimitos; sobre todo
los primeros, cual las coníferas del continente, parecían escalar el cielo con la cúspide de
sus ramas. Aquéllos más empinados y coposos eran los escogidos por las gallinas de Guinea (Numidas
Meneagris de Cuvier), conocida la hurañía de esas aves exóticas, para sus querencias de noche.
La banda, que bien podía componerse de cien, desde antes de aparecer el sol empezaron a removerse
y a repetir el clamor o cacareo peculiar suyo, en que parece que una dice pascual y la otra
contesta, pascual, hasta que todas despiertan y se preparan para descender de sus elevadísimas
y naturales alcándaras. Ni los pichones ni las gallinas daban aún señales de vida: aquéllos
por no ser madrugadores, éstas por el encierro y la oscuridad de su casa.

Por lo demás, se notaba bastante movimiento en todo el batey. De los esclavos de ambos sexos,
quiénes recogían con sus guatacas o azadones las hojas secas y briznas del suelo; quiénes con
los mismos instrumentos rozaban la yerba de los caminos; quiénes con ambas manos abiertas levantaban
la basura amontonada y la metían en canastas que otros conducían fuera a la cabeza; quiénes
a brazo sacaban agua del profundo pozo y la vertían en una amplia cubeta de piedra al pie del
brocal para que otros, en unos baldes rústicos hechos del pecíolo de la palma, la distribuyesen
en los depósitos de los varios departamentos de la hacienda. A la vera del pozo daba agua y
bañaba los caballos de dos en dos o de tres en tres, el calesero Leocadio. Dentro del molino
resonaba la voz penetrante del negrito, que, sentado al extremo del eje de la rueda vertical,
con que girando en la solera se descascaraba el café, aguijaba sin cesar a la caballería que
servía de motor. Cuatro esclavas, entre tanto, tendían el grano, aún no bien seco; mientras
otros conducían el pilado o descortezado al aventador, cuyas paletas hacían un ruido tremendo
y despertaban los ecos doquiera que la ola sonora encontraba obstáculo elástico en su trayecto.
Y una vez limpio de toda paja o polvo, era llevado a los almacenes para que allí se escogiese
y clasificase por otros esclavos.

Ninguno de los que pasaban al alcance de Isabel dejaba de darla los buenos días y de pedirla
su bendición, doblando la rodilla en señal de sumisión y respeto. Pedro, el Contramayoral,
sin la insignia ominosa de su oficio, yendo de un lado a otro, animaba a sus compañeros al
trabajo y daba la mano en muchos casos, como para imprimir mayor peso a la palabra con la obra.
La subida o aparición de Isabel en los tendales fue la señal para que el negrito del molino
alzase la voz argentinada y aguda con la canción, tan ruda como sencilla, improvisada quizás
la noche anterior, la cual principiaba con esta especie de verso: La niña sen va, y terminaba
con este otro, repetido en coro por todos los demás negros: Probe cravo llorá. Entre la primera
letra y el estribillo o pie insertaba el guía, no obstante que criollo, nacido en el cafetal,
frases en congo puro, a que también contestaba el coro con el obligado: Probe cravo llorá.

Inútil fuera pedir armonía, siquiera música a una canción, ni civilizada ni salvaje del todo;
pero si parecía asaz monótona a oídos delicados, también es verdad que el tono y la letra rebosaban
en melancólico sentimiento. Así lo estimó Isabel, aunque hizo como que no oía ni entendía palabra,
y siguió adelante hasta el pie de los árboles, donde ya bullían y corrían en todas direcciones
las aborotosas gallinas de Guinea. Algunas, las más ariscas, al verla quisieron emprender vuelo,
estallando en el grito nasal, chillón y alto con que suelen dar la voz de alarma a sus compañeras.
Mas conocida la voracidad de esas aves, bastaron a tranquilizarlas y contenerlas unos granos
de maíz que Isabel sacó de la cestita que llevaba al brazo y que tuvo cuidado de arrojarlos
en un punto dado, cerca de sí. La banda en masa se echó sobre el escaso alimento, depuesta
la vigilancia, olvidado el peligro, y sólo ocupada de egullir granos o pedrezuelas. De esta
circunstancia se aprovechó una de las esclavas, a una señal de su señorita, para arrastrarse
por el suelo y pillar dos, sin que lo echaran de ver las otras. Muy gustosa es la carne de
estas aves, tan gustosa como la de la perdiz, razón por qué Isabel se propuso obsequiar a sus
huéspedes con un par de ellas, asadas, en el almuerzo.

A la vista del alimento, arrojado ahora a puñados, acudieron presurosos los pichones. Estos,
menos huraños que las guineas, a las cuales temían, y más capaces de simpatía que ellas, revolotearon
al principio en torno de la joven, luego se posaron en su cabeza, en sus hombros y en el brazo
de la cesta, acabando por arrebatarle el maíz de las manos y aun picarle en la boca. Tales
y tan tiernas demostraciones de inocentes avecicas, por más que repetidas un día con otro,
siempre la enternecían, y jamás, sino en casos extraordinarios, consintió que las matasen fuera
de su vista. Por éste y otros actos parecidos en que se ponía de manifiesto la influencia ejercida
por Isabel sobre cuantos seres se le acercaban, no creían menos sus esclavos sino que Dios
la había dotado de una especie de encanto o poder secreto, el cual no cabía aludir ni repeler.

Seguía Diego Meneses con la vista los pasos de su amiga, y, bien que, a fuer de hombre civilizado,
no estaba dispuesto a conceder nada sobrenatural en ella, sí creía, como los demás, que era
una mujer extraordinaria. Desde su puesto de observación daba cuenta fiel de lo que veía u
oía, a Leonardo, quien continuaba en la cama descansando y gozando de las finísimas sábanas
cargadas de encajes y perfumadas con los pétalos de las rosas de Alejandría, obra toda de las
industriosas manos de Isabel. Decía Meneses a Gamboa, entre otras cosas:

--Es mucha mujer ésa, amigo.

--¿No te lo decía yo?, contestaba éste satisfecho.

--Vale un Perú. No se ven muchas como ella por ahí.

--¿Quieres cambiar? La cambio pelo a pelo por Rosa. Vamos.

--No te burles, compadre, contestaba Diego serio. Que reconozca en Isabel prendas raras, dignas
de encomio, no quiere decir que me guste más que otras mujeres, ni que esté prendado de ella.
Pero la verdad es que cada vez me convenzo más de que tú no te la mereces.

--¡Pues qué! ¿Te figuras que ella es mejor que yo? replicaba Leonardo, herido de la observación
de su amigo. Te equivocas, chico, de medio a medio. Ten presente que Isabel es hija de un antiguo
empleado del gobierno, empleado cesante, un cafetalista arruinado, un pobretón, en suma; mientras
que mis padres tienen potreros, cafetal, ingenio, son hacendados ricos y hacen diferente papel
en La Habana. ¿Está Vd.?

--Estoy, sólo que no me referí a nada de eso cuando te dije que no te merecías esa muchacha.
Hablando en plata, Leonardo, tú no la quieres.

--¿Por qué supones que no la quiero?

--¡Qué! ¿Acaso no tengo ojos? Desde que llegamos vengo observando tus acciones y palabras,
y nada en ti me persuade que amas a Isabel.

--¡Hombre, Diego! Te diré francamente lo que me pasó, dijo Gamboa tras breve rato de silencio.
No siento por Isabel aquella pasión ciega y ardiente que sientes tú, por ejemplo... por Rosa.

--Di mejor, le atajó prontamente Meneses, que la que tú sientes por Cecí...

--¡Calla! exclamó Leonardo alarmado, y medio incorporado en la cama. No se mienta la soga en
casa del ahorcado. Te pueden oír: las paredes oyen. Ese nombre es vedado aquí.

--Poco importa un nombre. Es muy común y no creo que Isabel lo haya oído en su vida.

--Probable es que no, pero por el hilo se saca el ovillo, cuanto más que Isabel no tiene pelo
de tonta.

--Y ahora que viene al caso, ¿cómo te has compuesto respecto a la escena delante de la casa
de las Gámez en el momento de la partida de Isabel?

--Creo que sospecha algo y tengo para mí que sus primas le han contado o escrito sobre eso
algún cuento. Ello es que Isabel se muestra recelosa y al parecer muy sentida conmigo.

--No dudo que las primas hayan despertado sus celos. La cosa fue, no obstante, muy clara para
que se dejase de alarmar Isabel y sospechar lo mismo que tú y yo sabemos. ¡Qué osadía la de
aquella muchacha!

--¿Qué quieres? La cegó el demonio de los celos, comprometiéndome a los ojos de Isabel y de
sus primas. No puedes imaginarte cuánta fue mi vergüenza.

--Lo considero. Yo, en tu lugar, escondo la cara bajo siete estados de tierra. Mas ¿de dónde
sacó Isabel que podía haber sido tu hermana Adela?

--Ahí verás, Diego. Con todo, si bien recuerdas, se parecen mucho a primera vista.

--Ya había hecho yo la misma observación. ¡Qué malo que tu padre tuviese que ver con semejante
parecido!

--¿Quién sabe? A él le gusta la canela tanto como a mí. No tendría nada de extraño que, andando
a salto de mata, como solía cuando mozo, hubiese dado un tropezón... Lo que es de C... está
que se le cae la baba. Me consta.

--Luego no puede ser su padre.

--¡Qué había de serlo! Ni pensarlo. ¡Disparate!

--Pues por ahí se corre que lo es.

--Habladurías de las gentes, Diego. ¿Conciben que estaría enamorado de C... si le ligasen esas
relaciones de parentesco con ella?

--Quizás lo ignore, porque tú dices, fue todo a consecuencia de un tropezón. Quizás también
la cela de ti, sabedor del parentesco que media entre Vds. dos. ¡Cuando el río suena!...

--En este caso el río no lleva agua, ni piedra. Sólo porque da la casualidad que se parecen
mucho C... y Adela se encapricha la gente y habla... Lo que te sé decir es que él me ha hecho
pasar más sustos que pelos tengo en la cabeza. Cuando menos lo espero me doy con él de manos
a boca. Casi, y sin casi, me causa doble inquietud que el músico Pimienta. Lo único que me
tranquiliza por esta parte, es que ella desdeña tanto a los viejos como desprecia a los mulatos.

--No te fíes, sin embargo. Cosa sabida es que hijo de gato ratón caza, y que por donde salta
la madre salta la hija. Mas volviendo a nuestro cuento, el resultado de estas misas es que
tú no estás en el mejor pie con Isabel.

--No. Como te decía, ella sospecha algo, o alguien la ha predispuesto contra mí. Isabel es,
además, muy perra para explicarse con franqueza; yo soy punto menos, de modo que así iremos
pasando hasta que Dios quiera, o ella deponga el orgullo y se reconcilie conmigo.

--Esa misma conformidad tuya, observó Meneses, me confirma en la creencia de que tú no amas
a Isabel.

--O yo no me he sabido explicar, o tú no me entiendes, Diego. No habiendo puntos de comparación
bajo ningún concepto entre las dos mujeres, no puedo querer a la una como quiero a la otra.
La de allá me trae siempre loco, me ha hecho cometer más de una locura y todavía me hará cometer
muchas más. Con todo, no la amo, ni la amaré nunca como amo a la de acá... Aquélla es toda
pasión y fuego, es mi tentadora, un diablito en figura de mujer, la Venus de las mula... ¿Quién
es bastante fuerte para resistírsele? ¿Quién puede acercársele sin quemarse? ¿Quién al verla
no más no siente hervirle la sangre en las venas? ¿Quién la oye decir: te quiero, y no se le
trastorna el cerebro cual si bebiera vino? Ninguna de esas sensaciones es fácil experimentar
al lado de Isabel. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02019</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>227800</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17308</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> At such times, women appear less graceful aerial and lovable, and
men more timid dare all, and feeling more are given more eloquence.

- Isabel, Leonardo said, I am surprised your conduct with me.

- Rate
it, "said Isabel, smiling.

- Not for me to qualify, for the simple
reason that I am the victim.

- That more?

For it was what was missing.

- Are you surprised?

How does it fit, if not, the friendly bounce of Havana (my part, that is), with your silence
and indifference soon ...?

- "No reason to justify the change?

- No reason to justify it.

At least I still have not been able to penetrate.

- Refresh you
memory of events.

- Nothing, Isabel, I fail, I know why.

- Really?

-
Really.

- So I've been a fool, a fool, I have seen visions.

- As
much as it does not, Isabel.

Do not you think that you could misinterpret an innocent act mine
or someone else to me?

- If it is not interpretations, Don Leonardo,
this is what I saw with my eyes.

- Let us know what was my lady Elizabeth
with her eyes.

- I saw what you saw, rather, what happened to you
at the stapes of chitin.

- And that was reason enough for the love
you lost me and were about to forget?

- It was, and large, to anger
any woman of shame, much as the blinding passion.

- I see clear,
Isabel, who have all been a mistake on your part, and that inadvertently
has been unfair to me.

- Explain you, "Isabel said with apparent
anxiety.

- I'll tell you briefly what happened, Leonardo continued,
turning red, because fact was thought to lie.

As I said the last goodbye, naturally stretched a foot on the sidewalk.

One of the two mulatto passing bumped into me, and believing him put together a trip, full of
anger gave me a shove.

You know what are those insolent sluts when creating offense.

- Yes, Isabel said thoughtfully.

After a little while he added: But what gave me reason to I say the
word indecent that I still buzzing in the ears?

- You cry, Isabel,
and then the call Adela, though they may be called Nicole or Rosario
was no doubt which increased his anger.

- If called by the name of
Adela, rather, if I let my exclamation that name, was because I figured
she was his sister, you also take it by the picture of Adela, I could
not, or I should imagine that another woman had with you like jokes.

-
Takes!

The story is that there was no joke on your part.

- Then she knows you and you abused by ... jealousy.

- I know of
view, I confess, I had noticed his resemblance to my sister Adela,
but have given no occasion ever jealous of me.

- Perhaps he loves
you in secret.

- It would be nothing special, except that in my life
I said "you black eyes."

- I would feel an injustice done to you,
Leonardo.

Appearances, however, condemn him.

- No, Elizabeth, no. I am innocent. If you deceive at this time, if you do not tell the whole
truth if you paint a passion that he felt, therefore if you had given just cause of tort, would
be the worst of men ...

- Okay, fold the paper, convinced Isabel interrupted.

- Pelillos to sea?, Leonardo asked with loving accent.

- Pelillos to sea, "she answered with heavenly smile. It would not have said to me if I saw sentenced
to doubt the word of the man who was a friend and gentleman.

- Well, said Leonardo more lively.

Do not you think we should seal this sweet reconciliation ...?

Saying this left hand secretly run by the railing to catch Elizabeth,
leaning on it.

But it, avoiding the time, avoided the danger. Sobered and walked
by her aunt, who said it was high time to pick up.

Leonardo clock marked eleven at night.

Time had flown. Diego Meneses, despite knowing that the time the paint bald He took advantage
of what Rosa was enough to make a formal declaration of love, having
find the theme or pretext of the conversation in the gift of carnations
that this girl did Leonardo in the garden.

Dove Candida Alquízar orchard!

She had not heard before an "I love you, Rosa 'intention and the
fire.

She, who was attracted to the young as the needle to the magnet, as sometimes the snake could
not divert attraction break the enchantment, found no hand gesture,
word or scheme to deny that he had succumbed and also loved his tempting
from the first season they spent together in the coffee Light.

CHAPTER II

And in the beautiful coffee plantations everything is fresh and smells
kissed its white flowers by tropical breezes.

J. PADRÍÑEZ

As a bride of Cupid from the previous day, Rosa Ilincheta, fearing shame of face his accomplice
in the clear light of day, delayed his departure from his best dresser. But Isabel had obligations
to complete and appeared very early in the south porch of the house the umbrella in her right
hand, a basket hit off the left arm through the hoop, and all wrap the silk embroidered shawl
enhancement.

     
      Then the sun peeked from a
      corner of the house, illuminating
      a part of the garden and planning the shadow of it and trees, long
distance, on the spacious farm batey.

         There was plenty of dew in the morning.

Was soaked grass, dust off roads and russet leaves of the plants and the flowers of flowers studded
with tiny seed pearls, as many prisms that decomposed the light of the sun almo, upon receipt
of sideways.

Isabel threw a questioning look across the country spread out before
her, and ventured out the porch, because from there began to see a
rose from Alexandria who had just opened the sweet solar heat in the
southeast of the garden table.

So she cut without punctured or splashing, and when she was adorned with splendid braid her hair
again mechanically the eyes towards the house and thought that one of his guests watched from
the shutter of the bedroom window at the end of the porch, where in fact the two were staying.
Was Diego Meneses, who have not enjoyed peaceful sleep, left the bed since the dawn and breathing
the pure atmosphere of the countryside, at the time that Isabel appeared
in the midst of gayadas flowers.

Thereby the troubled this incident, which for a short time it was uncertain if he returned
back from or go ahead, because the act of adorning the hair and look for the house, Magu to
innocent and accidental, could be interpreted in different ways, and she fled both frivolous
and the foolish vanity. But I had to go and went with firm step.

On the south side, a stone fence separating the field that included square the varied farm village.
In the center stood the coffee mill between the two pairs of awnings,
which can contain a time, drying, half of the harvest.

Further, closing the large space on the left, you could see the thick dark rim of the pot with
gallows and pulley for the extraction of water, the loft after the poultry birds and some pens,
in background at right, the bell, or rather the wooden pillar whose arm covered with an awning,
hung the bell, and the granaries and warehouses, stables, cow barn
and other outbuildings.

The huts of the slaves included a village regular size.

Was devoid of vegetation or the magnificent batey we have been describing, for many trees, and
certainly the most corpulent copudos and all that farm, he adorned and shaded. Including several
avocados, red mamey, mango and star apple trees, especially the first, which the continent conifers,
climbing the sky seemed the height of its branches. Those steeper and flakes were chosen by the
Guinea fowl (Numidians Meneagris Cuvier), knowing the Hurani of these rare birds to their haunts
at night. The band, which might well consist of hundreds, from appearing before the sun began
to stir and repeat the cry, or his peculiar cackle, it seems that
Easter and the other says answers, Easter, until all wake up and prepare
to descend from their very high and natural perches.

Neither the young nor the chickens still gave signs of life: those for not being early risers,
they by the darkness and seclusion of his home.

Otherwise, you could see plenty of movement around the sugar mill. Of the slaves of both sexes,
who picked up their hoes and spades the dried leaves and stalks of the soil who with the same instruments
touched the grass on the roads, who raised both hands open piles of trash and put it in baskets
they lead others to the head, who arm to draw water from deep well and poured into a large stone
basin at the foot of curb for others, in a rustic buckets made of the petiole of the palm,
distribute deposits in the various departments of the estate. At the edge of the well water was
bathing horses in twos or threes, the coachman Leocadio. Inside the mill penetrating voice
sounded bold, who sat at the end of the vertical wheel axle, that
turning the floor was peeling coffee, constantly goad the cavalry
served motor.

Four slaves, meanwhile, tended the grain, not yet dry, while others led the milled or debarked
to fan whose blades made a huge noise and awakened the echoes wherever the sound wave was elastic
obstacle in its path. And once all clean straw or dust, was taken to the store so that there was chosen
and classified by other slaves.

None of those who passed the scope of Isabel left to give it the good morning and ask his blessing,
bending the knee in submission and respect. Peter, the Contramayoral, without the ominous badge
of his office, going from one place to another, encouraging his colleagues to work and gave
her hand in many cases, to give added weight to the word with the work. The rise or the appearance
of Elizabeth in the awnings was the signal for the black mill Argentina raise your voice and
sharp with the song, so rude and simple, perhaps improvised last night, which begins with this
kind of verse: The girl is sin, and ended with this one, repeated in chorus by all the other
blacks: Probe cravo cries. Between the first lyrics and the chorus or foot inserting the guide,
though not native, born on the plantation, congo phrases in pure, also answered the chorus with
the bound: Probe cravo cries.

Was useless to ask harmony, even listening to a song, or any civilized or savage; but seemed
Asaz monotone sensitive ears, it is also true that the tone and the lyrics were full in melancholy
feeling. Isabel felt it, but pretended not to hear or understand speech, and proceeded to the foot
of the trees, which already swarmed and ran in all directions the aborotosas Guinea fowl. Some,
the most surly, wanted to see her take flight exploding in the nasal scream, shrill and high,
which often give the alarm to her companions. More familiar with the voracity of these birds
were enough to reassure and contain a few grains Isabel corn took from the basket, leading to the
arm and took care to throw at a given point near each other. The band mass fell on the little
food, deposed surveillance, forgot the danger, and only occupied
egullir grains or pebbles.

This circumstances took one of the slaves, a sign of his lady, to drag on the ground and pillar
two, without being thrown out of seeing others. Very tasty meat is these birds, as tasty as the partridge,
the reason why Isabel is proposed to give your guests with a couple of them, grilled, lunch.

In view of the food, now thrown in handfuls, came rushing chicks. These, less haggard than guineas,
to which they feared, and more capable of sympathy to them, fluttered at first about the young, then
fell on his head, shoulders and arm basket, running to snatch the corn from the hands and even
bite in the mouth. Such so tender and innocent shows sometimes, even repeated a day with another,
Always tender, and never, but in extraordinary cases, agreed that kill off of sight. For this
and other similar acts that was reflected the influence by Isabel on how things came to him,
not least their slaves but believed that God had endowed with a kind of charm or secret power
which could not refer or repel.

Diego Meneses was still scrutinizing the footsteps of his friend,
and, well, by dint of civilized man was unwilling to concede anything
supernatural in it, did believe, like others, it was an extraordinary
woman.

From his observation post was faithful account of what he saw or heard, Leonardo, who was still
in bed resting and enjoying the fine linens full of lace and scented with rose petals of Alexandria,
all of the work Elizabeth hands industrious. Meneses said Gamboa, among other things:

- It's a lot of women that, friend.

- Did not I tell you?, Answered this content.

- It's worth a Peru. There are many like her out there.

- Would you change? The hair changes hair Rosa. Come on.

- Do not laugh, gossip, Diego answered seriously. Isabel recognize in rare items worthy commendable,
does not mean that I like better than other women, or that is in love with her. But the truth
is that more and more convinced me that you do not deserve it.

- What! Do you imagine that she is better than me?

Leonardo replied, wounded by the observation of his friend.

You're wrong, man, medium to medium.

Keep in mind that Elizabeth is the daughter of a former government employee, former employee, a
ruined coffee, a pauper, in short, while my parents have pastures, coffee-mill, are wealthy landowners
and make different role in Havana. Are you?

- I, only I did not refer to any of that when I said I do not deserve this girl. Bluntly, Leonardo,
you do not want it.

- Why do you suppose I do not love?

- What!

Do not I have eyes? Since we arrived I have been watching your actions and words, and nothing
to persuade me that you love to Isabel.

- Male, Diego! I'll tell you frankly what happened to me, "Gamboa said after a brief period
of silence.

Do not feel sorry for Elizabeth that blind and burning passion you feel, for example ... by Rosa.

-
Di best Meneses promptly stopped him, that you feel by Ceci ...

- Shut up! Leonardo said in alarm, and hereby incorporated in the bed. Not lie in the rope house
of the hanged. You can hear: the walls have ears. That name is banned here.

- Never mind a name. It is very common and do not believe that Isabel has ever heard.

- Probably not, but the thread is pulled the ball, the more it has no hair Isabel dumb.

- And now that is beside the point, how you've made about the scene in front of the house of
Gamez at the time of the departure of Isabel?

- I think I have suspected something and to me that her cousins ??have told or written about
it a story.

It is shown that Elizabeth apparently very suspicious and felt me.

- No doubt that the premiums have aroused his jealousy. The thing was, however, very clear to
alarm to leave Isabel and suspect the same thing you and I know.

The nerve of that girl!

- What?

The blinded the demon of jealousy, engaging in the eyes of Elizabeth and premiums. You can not
imagine how much it was my shame.

- I think.

I, in your place, hiding his face under seven U.S. land.

But where does Isabel took could have been your sister Adela?

-
You will find there, Diego.

However, if I recall, they seem much at first glance.

- I had already made the same observation. Too bad your father had to do with such like!

- Who knows? He likes the cinnamon as much as me. There would be nothing unusual, walking to
mouth, as usual when young, had taken a tumble ... What is C. .. is to him drool. I know.

- Then can not be your father.

- What was to be! Not a chance. Nonsense!

- Then there is out there it is.

- Gossip of the people, Diego. "They understand they would love C. .. if you ligasen these kinship
with her?

- Try to ignore it, because you say, it was all a result of a stumble.

Perhaps the plot for you, knowing of kinship that mediates between Vds. two. Where there's smoke
...!

- In this case the river does not carry water, or stone. Just because he happens to resemble
lot C. .. and Adela becomes infatuated people and talk ... What I can tell you is that he has made
me spend more scares that I have hair on his head. At least I hope I hand him to mouth. Almost,
and hardly I double cause concern that the musician Pepper. The only thing I reassured by this
part, is that it neglects both the old and despises the Cubans.
- Be wary, however. Thing known is that the son of cat mouse game,
and where jumps mother's daughter jumps. But back to our story, the
result is that these masses you are not the best foot with Isabel.

-
No. Like I said, she suspects something, or someone has biased against
me. Isabel is well, bitch to explain frankly, I am a point less, so
in this way we going until God wants, or she lay down their pride
and reconcile with me.

- That same line of yours, noted Meneses,
I confirmed in the belief that you do not love Elizabeth.

- O I have
not been able to explain, or you do not understand me, Diego. Not
having points of comparison under any circumstances between the two
women, I can not love one another as I love. The one of there always
brings me mad, made me make more of a crazy and I still will make
many more. However, not love, or love and love never on this earth
... It is all passion and fire is my temptress, a devil in the shape
of women, the Venus of the mule ... Who is strong enough to refuse?
Who can approach him without getting burned? Who to see no more do
not feel the blood boil in their veins? Who hears: I love you, and
you are not disrupts the brain as if to drink wine? None of these
feelings is easy to experiment by Isabel</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>