<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document04696</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>58016</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22722</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> El alcalde don Roque, que desde tiempo
inmemorial venía asistiendo a la tienda de la Morana en compañía de don Segis el capellán de
las monjas Agustinas y don Benigno el coadjutor de la parroquia, y se bebía en el transcurso
de la noche, de cuatro a ocho vasos de vino de Rueda, según las circunstancias, no pudo sufrir
el hogar doméstico más de tres días y salió también a la calle. Le acompañaba el octogenario
alguacil Marcones con tercerola y sable. El iba armado de revólver y estoque.

Después, y sucesivamente, fueron saliendo y diseminándose por las tertulias nocturnas don Melchor,
Gabino Maza, don Pedro Miranda, Delaunay, don Mateo, y todos los demás. Los indianos tardaron
más tiempo. Lo mismo la tienda de Graells que la de la Morana y el Saloncillo, se transformaban
al llegar la noche en verdaderos arsenales. Cada uno de los que iban llegando dejaba arrimadas
a la pared sus armas y pertrechos de guerra. Al salir tornaban a empuñarlas con un valor impávido,
digno de la sangre cántabra que casi todos llevaban en las venas. Allí el antiguo arcabuz de
chispa alternaba de igual a igual con el moderno rifle americano de doce tiros, el estoque
cilíndrico de hierro con el espadín pavonado que guardan los nuevos bastones, el cachorro tosco
de bronce con el revólver nielado. Y esta misma diversidad de armas mortíferas contribuía poderosamente
a mantener en todos los pechos el espíritu bélico tan necesario en aquella ocasión.

Se habían tomado algunas medidas acertadísimas; de gran utilidad. Hasta las doce de la noche
los serenos tenían orden de no apagar ningún farol. A aquéllos se les había provisto de nuevos
pitos infinitamente más sonoros que los antiguos. Además tenían prevención para vigilar a cualquier
persona desconocida que transitase por las calles. Entre los vecinos se había convenido juiciosamente
no dejar la acera a nadie desde las diez en adelante como no fuese a un amigo. Sabida es de
todos la enorme influencia que tiene en la criminalidad esta costumbre de dejar la acera. Con
tal motivo, encontrándose una noche en la calle de San Florencio don Pedro Miranda y don Feliciano
Gómez, ambos embozados en sus carriks, con los estoques desenvainados, prevenidos para cualquier
evento, don Feliciano le gritó a don Pedro desde lejos:

--¡Eh, amigo, al arroyo!

--Phs, phs; sepárese usted--contesta don Pedro.

--Quien debe apartarse es usted--replica el comerciante.--¡Al arroyo, al arroyo!

--Phs, phs, haga usted el favor de dejar franco el paso--responde el señor Miranda.

Ninguno de los dos se movía de su sitio. Habíanse desembozado y mostraban ya la punta aguzada
de sus floretes.

--Tenga usted la bondad...

--Haga usted el obsequio...

¿Quién sabe la horrible tragedia que hubiera acaecido en Sarrió, si al cabo de un rato bastante
largo de hallarse estos varones así detenidos en su camino, no se hubiesen reconocido?

--¿Sería usted tal vez don Feliciano?...

--¿Sería usted don Pedro?

--¡Don Feliciano!

--¡Don Pedro!

Y se acercaron corriendo y se estrecharon las manos con efusión.

--¡Qué suerte ha tenido usted en que le hubiese reconocido, don Feliciano!--exclamó el señor
Miranda mostrando su ancho estoque de hierro con puño de hueso.

--¡Pues la de usted no ha sido pequeña, don Pedro!--contesta el comerciante esgrimiendo en
el aire una hoja fina y pavonada de Toledo.

Para entrar en la tienda de la Morana era preciso bajar dos escalones. La tienda era una confitería,
aunque no lo pareciese; la única confitería que había entonces en Sarrió. Hoy, si no me engaño,
cuenta ya con tres. Y digo que no lo parecía, porque se vendían cirios de iglesia, pies y manos
y cabezas y troncos de cera para ofertas. Estos objetos poco a poco habían ido llenando todo
su ámbito, pasando de comercio suplementario a principal, en virtud de lo nada golosos que
eran los vecinos de aquella villa. Y éste es uno de los rasgos característicos que reclamo
para ella. En España es muy general que los habitantes de las villas y ciudades pequeñas sean
dados con pasión a los confites. No gozando de los placeres de toda laya con que brindan las
grandes capitales, la sensualidad se escapa por ahí.

Acaso se arguya que en Sarrió las monjas Agustinas también fabricaban dulces; pero debemos
advertir que esta fabricación estaba limitada exclusivamente al rallado de ciruela, membrillo,
pera y albaricoque, alguna que otra tarta de almendra y borraja, y un dulce especialísimo parecido
a las escamas de los peces llamado flor de azahar. No hay que dudarlo; en Sarrió había pocos
golosos. Después de todo, esta virtud rara en las villas de lo interior, no lo es tanto en
las poblaciones marítimas menos sometidas, como es sabido, a la influencia clerical. Porque
según la observación que puede hacerse viajando por los pueblos de lo interior de España, allí
se comen más dulces donde el culto y las prácticas de la religión absorben más parte de la
vida, y la mayor energía del sentimiento religioso se traduce en novenas, rosarios cantados,
cofradías y canónigos. Lo cual demuestra que debe de existir cierta misteriosa afinidad entre
el misticismo y la confitería.

Esta se hallaba representada en la tienda de la Morana por dos armarios de pino pintado de
azul con puertas de cristales, situados a entrambos lados del mostrador. En estos armarios
se guardaba una razonable cantidad de caramelos, rosquillas bañadas, suspiros, magdalenas,
almendrados, y sobre todo, las alabadas crucetas y famosísimas tabletas cuyo renombre habrá
alcanzado seguramente los oídos de nuestros lectores. Todo de la más remota antigüedad. Las
tabletas, cuya mágica composición nunca hemos podido averiguar, tenían un atractivo irresistible,
basado, ¡caso extraño! en su extraordinaria dureza. A la edad en que se comían las tabletas
de la Morana lo importante no era que los dulces fuesen delicados, sabrosos, exquisitos, sino
que durasen mucho. Para lograr que los dientes se hincasen en ellas, era forzoso impregnarlas
previamente de una cantidad fabulosa de saliva. Una vez hincados en su pasta pegajosa en alto
grado, el separarlos de nuevo llegaba a constituir un verdadero problema. Permítaseme dedicar
un delicado recuerdo de simpatía y reconocimiento a estas tabletas que desde los cuatro hasta
los ocho años van unidas a los momentos más dichosos de mi existencia. A su azucarado influjo
quizá deba el autor de este libro la flor de optimismo, que, al decir de los críticos, resplandece
en sus obras.

La Morana, hija y heredera de otra Morana que ya había muerto, era una mujer de cuarenta años,
pálida, con parches de gutapercha en las sienes para los dolores de cabeza. Estaba casada con
un Juan Crisóstomo, que al decir de don Segis, el capellán, no era de los Crisóstomos. Sin
embargo, cuando administraba alguna paliza a su mujer, solía mostrar cierta erudición poco común.

--«Yo que amaba a esta mujer--exclamaba con enternecimiento, arrimando el garrote a la pared.--¡Yo
que amaba a esta mujer como esposa y no como sierva, según manda el apóstol San Pablo!... ¿Tú
has leído al apóstol San Pablo?... ¡Qué habías de leer tú, gran vaca!...»

El vino era muy bueno, casi puede decirse que era lo único bueno en este establecimiento, y
eso que no paraba mucho en la bodega. Don Roque, don Segis, don Benigno, don Juan el Salado
y el señor Anselmo el ebanista, se encargaban a plazo fijo de hacerlo pasar a la suya. Era
un vino blanco, fuerte, superior, que se subía a la cabeza con facilidad asombrosa. Los tertulios
de la tienda, todas las noches, entre once y doce, salían dando tumbos para sus casas; pero
silenciosos, graves, sin dar jamás el menor escándalo. Solían salir los cinco cogidos del brazo,
apoyándose los unos en los otros. Al llegar a las tapias de la huerta del convento de las Agustinas,
orinaban. Después proseguían su camino sin decirse una palabra, aunque bufando y soplando mucho.
El instinto, que nunca les abandonaba por completo, les sugería esta prudente conducta. Comprendían
que si hablaban poco o mucho, podían enredarse en alguna disputa. De ahí las voces y el escándalo
consiguiente... Nada, nada, lo mejor era no chistar. Al llegar a sus casas se soltaban murmurando
con torpe lengua «buenas noches». El último era don Roque por vivir más lejos que ninguno.

De este modo serio, modesto, patriarcal, se emborachaban aquellos venerables ancianos todas
las noches del año. Dos de ellos, don Juan el Salado, escribiente del Ayuntamiento, y don Segis,
experimentaban ya las consecuencias de aquella vida. El Salado tenía una nariz que daba miedo
verla: el día menos pensado se le caía sobre el libro de actas. Don Segis había padecido un
ataque apoplético, de resultas del cual arrastraba la pierna derecha cual si llevase en ella
un peso de seis arrobas. Verdad que el insaciable capellán no se contentaba con los cuarterones
de vino de la confitería. Por cada uno que se tragaba era preciso que la Morana le sirviese
una copa de ginebra, la cual vertía cuidadosamente en un frasco que llevaba al efecto en el
bolsillo. Si eran seis cuarterones, seis copas; si ocho, ocho. Toda esta ginebra pasaba delicadamente
a su estómago en pequeños sorbos después que se había metido en la cama. «¿Pero don Segis,
cómo se bebe usted tanta ginebra de una vez?--No tengo más remedio--contestaba en un tono resignado
y humilde que partía el corazón.--¿Si no bebiese una copa por cada cuarterón, qué sería de
mí, hijo del alma?... ¡Pasaría la noche como un caballo!»

Las conversaciones de la tienda de la Morana eran menos interesantes y movidas que las del
Saloncillo. A los viejos tertulianos les interesaban ya poquísimas cosas en el mundo. Los asuntos
más graves de la villa, los que promovían tempestades en el Saloncillo, se trataban, o por
mejor decir, se tocaban ligeramente sin apasionamiento alguno. Que los González habían despedido
al capitán de la Carmen y nombrado en su lugar un andaluz.

--Cuando los González lo han hecho--afirmaba uno lenta y sordamente,--sus razones tendrían.

--Es verdad--contestaba otro al cabo de un rato, llevándose el vaso a los labios.

--Ripalda parecía un buen sujeto--afirmaba un tercero, después de cinco minutos, dejando el
vaso sobre el mostrador y eructando.

--Sí lo parecía--replicaba otro gravemente.

Transcurrían diez minutos de meditación. Los tertulios daban algunos cariñosos besos al vaso,
que parecía de topacio. Don Roque rompe el silencio:

--De todos modos, no hay duda que don Antonio le abrasó.

--Le abrasó--dice don Juan el Salado.

--Le abrasó--confirma don Benigno.

--Le abrasó--corrobora el señor Anselmo.

--Le abrasó completamente--resume, por fin, don Segis lúgubremente.

Lo que alteraba los ánimos una que otra vez, era la cuestión de pichones. El señor Anselmo
y don Benigno alimentaban pasión inextinguible por estos animalitos. Cada cual tenía su palomar,
sus castas, sus procedimientos de cría, y sobre tales extremos se enredaban a menudo en largas
y vivas discusiones. Los demás escuchaban gravemente sin atreverse a decidir, subiendo y bajando
el vaso del mostrador a los labios con religioso silencio. El crimen de las Aceñas les disgustó,
pero no causó en ellos la profunda desazón que en el resto del vecindario. Al cabo de cinco
o seis días tornaron a sus patriarcales costumbres. Y era tal su valor, que la mayor parte
de las noches dejaban olvidadas las armas en la tienda.

Serían las doce por filo de una, en que don Roque había rebasado con tres cuarterones más la
tasa de seis que ordinariamente se imponía, cuando las cinco columnas de la confitería de la
Morana salieron en apretada cadena hacia sus domicilios. Cerraba la marcha Marcones, con el
fusil al hombro. El primero que se soltó fué don Segis, que vivía en una casita de dos balcones,
pegada al convento de las Agustinas. Después fué don Juan el Salado. Después el coadjutor.
Por último, el señor Anselmo, sacando la enorme llave lustrosa que le servía de batuta cuando
dirigía la orquesta, abrió el taller donde dormía.

Quedó el alcalde solo con la fuerza de su mando. Dijo algo; pero la fuerza no le entendió.
Comenzaron a caminar hacia casa, que ya no estaba lejos. Mas antes de llegar a ella, don Roque,
que soplaba y bufaba como una ballena, e imitaba en lo posible la marcha jadeante y arremolinada
de este cetáceo, se paró de repente, y pronunció en alta voz un largo discurso, del cual no
entendió Marcones más que la palabra ladrones, repetida bastantes veces. Miró el alguacil con
sobresalto a todas partes por ver si veía alguno, preparando el fusil al mismo tiempo; pero
nada observó que le hiciese sospechar la presencia de los forajidos. Tornó don Roque a usar
de la palabra, si tal nombre merecía la regurgitación intermitente de una porción de sonidos
extraños, bárbaros, lamentables, que infundían tristeza y horror al mismo tiempo, y Marcones
pudo colegir entonces que su jefe deseaba que hiciesen una batida por la villa, en busca de
los criminales de las Aceñas.

Marcones meditó que la fuerza era escasa y mal prevenida para aquella empresa; pero la disciplina
no le permitió hacer objeciones. Además, nació en su pecho la esperanza de que los asesinos
fuesen poco aficionados a tomar el fresco a tales horas. Y después de haber examinado cuidadosamente
las armas, emprendieron una marcha peligrosa al través de todas las calles y callejas de la
villa. En honor de la verdad, hay que advertir que don Roque marchaba delante como cumple a
un valeroso caudillo, con su revólver en la mano izquierda y el bastón de estoque en la derecha,
exponiendo el primero su noble pecho al plomo enemigo. Marcones, agobiado bajo el peso del
fusil y de los ochenta y dos años que tenía marchaba detrás a una distancia de seis pasos próximamente.

La noche era de luna, pero negros y grandes nubarrones la ocultaban a menudo por largo rato.
Y entonces la escasa claridad de los faroles de aceite que ardían en las esquinas de las calles
no bastaba a deshacer las sombras que se amontonaban hacia el medio de ellas. Sarrió consta
de cinco principales, a saber: la Rúa Nueva, que desemboca en el muelle; la de Caborana, la
de San Florencio, la de la Herrería y la de Atrás. Estas calles son largas, bastante anchas
y paralelas entre sí. Los edificios en general son bajos y pobres. Otras calles secundarias,
en número considerable, las cruzan y las comunican. Además, en las afueras le salen algunos
rabos a la villa, donde han edificado suntuosas casas los indianos. Son lo que pudiera llamarse
el ensanche de la población.

Al llegar la columna caminando por la calle de Atrás, cerca de la de Santa Brígida, oyó gritos
y lamentos que la obligó a hacer alto.

--¿Qué es eso, Marcones?--preguntó el alcalde.

El anciano alguacil se encogió de hombros filosóficamente.

--Nada, señor; será en casa de Patina Santa.

--¿Y cómo se atreven esas pendangas?... Vamos allá, Marcones, vamos acto continuo.

«Acto continuo» era una frase de la que usaba y abusaba don Roque. Simbolizaba para él la energía,
la decisión, la rapidez de la autoridad para remediar todos los daños.

Patina Santa era el gran sacerdote de uno de los dos templos del placer que existían en Sarrió.
De vez en cuando salía por las aldeas comarcanas y traía las sacerdotisas que le hacían falta,
que nunca pasaban de cuatro. No había más gabinetes, y eso que dormían de dos en dos. Vestían
el mismo refajo de bayeta verde o encarnada, el mismo justillo sin ballenas, la misma camisa
de lienzo gordo, el mismo pañuelo de percal que cuando triscaban allá por los prados y los
montes con los vaqueros vecinos. Patina Santa, como únicos símbolos del nuevo y elevado destino
a que la suerte les había llamado, colgaba de sus orejas pendientes de perlas y aprisionaba
sus pies con zapatos descotados de sarga, los cuales eran bienes adheridos a la casa y servían
para todas las que iban llegando. Más adelante Patina, haciéndose cargo de que el mundo marcha
y que las leyes del progreso son indeclinables, tuvo la audacia de introducir en su templo
los polvos de arroz. Después compró unos medallones de doublé para colgar al cuello con un
terciopelito negro. Verdad que a todas estas reformas le estimulaba la competencia desastrosa
que le hacía Poca Ropa, el cual tenía su instituto en la calle del Reloj, al otro extremo de
la villa.

--¿Qué escándalo es éste?--gritó don Roque con voz estentórea acercándose a la inmunda casucha.

Tres o cuatro muchachos que había en la calle huyeron como pajarillos a la vista del gavilán.
Pero quedaban las palomas. Dos de ellas estaban a la puerta en camisa, las otras dos asomadas
a las ventanas en el mismo traje. Las de la puerta quisieron retirarse a la vista del alcalde,
pero éste las agarró con sus manazas.

--¿Qué escándalo es éste,...ajo?--repitió.

--Señor alcalde, nos han dado dos piezas falsas...--dijo una de ellas.

--No estáis vosotras malas piezas... ¡A la cárcel!

--¡Pero, señor alcalde!

--¡A la cárcel,...ajo, a la cárcel!--rugió don Roque.--Y vosotras lo mismo. Todo el mundo abajo.
¿Dónde está ese maricón de Patina?

¡Santo cielo, qué alboroto se armó allí en un momento!

Las niñas de la ventana no tuvieron más remedio que bajar, y Patina lo mismo, todos en camisa,
porque don Roque no admitió término dilatorio. No se oían más que gemidos y lamentos, y por
encima de ellos la voz horripilante del alcalde, repitiendo sin cesar:

--¡A la cárcel...ajo! ¡A la cárcel...ajo!

Las infelices pedían por Dios y por la Virgen que las dejasen vestirse; pero el alcalde, con
la faz arrebatada por la cólera y los ojos inyectados, cada vez gritaba con más fuerza, aturdiéndose
con su propia voz:

--¡A la cárcel...ajo!.,¡A la cárcel...ajo!

Y no hubo otro remedio. El sereno, que se había acercado al escuchar los primeros ajos, las
condujo en aquella disposición a la cárcel municipal, en compañía de su digno jefe, mientras
los vecinos, entre risueños y compasivos, contemplaban la escena por detrás de los cristales
de sus ventanas.

La autoridad de don Roque cerró por sí misma la puerta del palomar, y puso la llave «acto continuo»,
bajo la custodia de Marcones. Después continuaron su marcha peligrosa.

No habían caminado mucho espacio, cuando en una de las calles más estrechas y lóbregas, acertaron
a ver el bulto de una persona que se acercaba cautelosamente a la puerta de una casa y trataba
de abrirla.

--¡Alto!--murmuró don Roque al oído de su subordinado.--Ya hemos tropezado con uno de los ladrones.

El alguacil no entendió más que la última palabra. Fué bastante para que se le cayese el fusil
de las manos.

--No tiembles, Marcones, que por ahora no es más que uno--dijo el alcalde cogiéndole por el brazo.

Si el venerable Marcones tuviese en aquel momento cabales sus facultades de observación, hubiese
advertido acaso en la mano de la autoridad cierta tendencia muy determinada al movimiento convulsivo.

El ladrón, al sentir los pasos de la patrulla, volvió la cabeza con sobresalto y permaneció
inmóvil con la ganzúa en la mano. Don Roque y Marcones también se estuvieron quietos. La luna,
filtrándose con trabajo por una nube, comenzó a alumbrar aquella fatídica escena.

--Phs, phs, amigo--dijo el alcalde al cabo de un rato, sin avanzar un paso.

Oir el ladrón este amical llamamiento de la autoridad y emprender la fuga, fué todo uno.

--¡A él, Marcones! ¡Fuego!--gritó don Roque, dándose a correr con denuedo en pos del criminal.

Marcenes quiso obedecer la orden de su jefe, pero no le fué posible; el martillo cayó sobre
el pistón sin hacer estallar el fulminante. Entonces, con decisión marcial, arrojó el arma
que no le servía de nada, sacó el sable de la vaina de cuero e hizo esfuerzos supremos por
alcanzar al alcalde, que con valor temerario se le había adelantado lo menos veinte pasos en
la persecución del ladrón.

Este había desaparecido por la esquina de una calle.

Pero al llegar a ella la columna pudo verle tratando de ganar la otra.

¡Pum!

Don Roque disparó su revólver, gritando al mismo tiempo:

--¡Date, ladrón!

Tornó a desaparecer: tornaron a verle al llegar a la calle de la Misericordia.

¡Pum! Otro tiro de don Roque.

--¡Date, ladrón!

Pero el forajido, sin duda como recurso supremo, y para evitar que algún sereno le detuviese,
comenzó a gritar también:

--¡Ladrones, ladrones!

Se oyó el silbido agudo y prolongado del pito de un sereno, después, otro, después otro...

La calle de San Florencio estaba bien iluminada, y pudo verse claramente al criminal deslizarse
con rapidez asombrosa buscando en vano la sombra de las casas.

¡Pum, pum!

--¡Date, ladrón!

--¡Ladrones!--contestó el bandido sin dejar de correr.

Dos serenos se habían agregado a la columna, y corrían blandiendo los chuzos al lado del alcalde.

El criminal quería a todo trance ganar la Rúa Nueva con objeto tal vez de introducirse en el
muelle y esconderse en algún barco o arrojarse al agua. Mas antes de llegar a ella tropezó
y dió con su cuerpo en el suelo. Gracias a este accidente la patrulla le ganó considerable
distancia; anduvo cerca de alcanzarle. Pero antes que esto sucediese, el forajido, alzándose
con extremada presteza, huyó más ligero que el viento. Don Roque disparó los dos últimos tiros
de su revólver, gritando siempre:

--¡Date, ladrón!

Desapareció por la esquina de la Rúa Nueva. Al desembocar en ella el alcalde y su fuerza cerca
de la plaza de la Marina, no vieron rastro de criminal por ninguna parte. Siguieron vacilantes
hasta llegar a dicha plaza. Allí se detuvieron sin saber qué partido tomar.

--Al muelle, al muelle; allí debe de estar--dijo un sereno.

Y ya se disponían todos a emprender la marcha, cuando se abrió con estrépito el balcón de una
de las casas, apareció un hombre en calzoncillos, y se oyeron estas palabras, que resonaron
profundamente en el silencio de la noche:

--¡El ladrón acaba de entrar en el café de la Marina!

El que las pronunciaba era don Feliciano Gómez. La patrulla, al escucharlas, se precipitó hacia
la puerta del café, y entró por ella tumultuosamente. El salón estaba desierto. Allá en el
fondo, al lado del mostrador, se vela a tres o cuatro mozos con su delantal blanco, rodeando
a un hombre que estaba tirado más que sentado sobre una silla. El alcalde, el alguacil, los
serenos cayeron sobre él, poniéndole al pecho los chuzos, el estoque y el sable. Y a un tiempo
gritaron todos:

--¡Date, ladrón!

El criminal levantó hacia ellos su faz despavorida, más pálida que la cera.

--¡Ay, re... si es don Jaime, así me salve Dios!--exclamó un sereno bajando el chuzo.

Todos los demás hicieron lo mismo, mudos de sorpresa. Porque, en efecto, el forajido que habían
perseguido a tiros, no era otro que Marín sorprendido infraganti, en el momento de abrir la
puerta de su casa.

Hubo que llevarle a ella en hombros, y sangrarle. Al día siguiente, don Roque se presentó a
pedirle perdón, y lo obtuvo. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document02576</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>178771</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20230</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Mayor Don Roque, who from time immemorial
had been attending the shop in company with Don Morana Segis Chaplain Augustinian nuns and Don
Benigno the curate of the parish, and drinking during of the night, four to eight glasses of
wine from Rueda, depending on the circumstances, could not suffer the domestic hearth more than
three days and also went to the street. He was accompanied by octogenarian Sheriff Marcones
with carbine and saber. He went armed with pistol and sword.

Then and later, were going out and spreading through the night gatherings Don Melchor, Gabino
Maza, Pedro Miranda, Delaunay, Don Mateo, and everyone else. The Indians took longer. The same
store Graells than the Saloncillo Morana and were transformed when night falls in real stocks.
Each one of those who were arriving left Arrimadas to the wall their weapons and military equipment.
When exiting turn to take up with a dauntless courage, Cantabrian worth the blood that almost
all wore in the veins. There the old blunderbuss spark alternated as equals with the modern
American rifle twelve shots, the sword cylindrical iron with burnished sprat who keep the new poles,
the puppy rough bronze with niello revolver. And this same diversity contributed powerfully lethal weapons
to maintain in all breasts the war spirit is so necessary at that time.

They had taken some very wise, very useful. Until twelve o'clock the watchmen were ordered not
to turn off any lamp. To those they had provided new whistles infinitely louder than the old. Prevention
also had to monitor any stranger who walk the streets. Among the neighbors had agreed judiciously do
not let anyone sidewalk from ten onwards as it was not a friend. Is known all the huge impact
it has on crime this habit of leaving the pavement. With this reason, finding a night on the
streets of San Florencio Miranda and Don Pedro Feliciano Gomez, both wrapped in their carriks, with
rapiers drawn, prevented for any event Feliciano Pedro yelled at from afar:

- Hey, friend, the brook!

- Phs, phs, you let him depart - Don Pedro
answered.

- Who should you depart - replicates the merchant .-- The
stream, the stream!

- Phs, phs, then you please stop the passage
ex - meets Mr. Miranda.

Neither moved from its site.

Habíanse unmasked and showed sharp tip and of florets.

- Have the kindness ...

- Do you treat ...

Who knows the horrible tragedy that had occurred in Sarrió, if, after
quite a while found these men over and arrested on his way, had not
been recognized?

- Would you perhaps don Feliciano?

...

- Would you Don Pedro?

- Don Feliciano!

- Don Pedro!

And they came running and they shook hands warmly.

- What luck have you had that would have recognized, Don Feliciano!
- Said Mr Miranda showed his broad sword iron fist bone.

- Because
of you have not been small, Pedro! - Answered the merchant wielding
in a thin air and bluing of Toledo.

To enter the shop needed Morana down two steps. The shop was a sweet-shop even if they seem, the
only candy that were then in Sarrió. Today, if I mistake not, now has three. And it seemed to
say no, because they were sold church candles, hand and foot and heads and trunks of wax for
deals. These objects had been gradually filling all its scope, from trading to cool the main
virtue of the no sweet tooth were the residents of that town. And this is one of the characteristics
that claim for her. In Spain is very general that the inhabitants of the villages and small
towns are given with passion for sweets.

Not enjoying the pleasures of all sorts that provide the big cities, sensuality escapes from
there.

Perhaps it is argued that the Augustinian nuns Sarrió also produced sweet, but we note that this
production was limited exclusively to cheese plum, quince, pear and apricot, the occasional
almond cake and borage, and a very special sweet like the scales of the fish called orange
blossom. No doubt it; in Sarrió were few greedy. After all, this rare virtue in the towns of the
interior, not so much in maritime populations less subject, as is known, the clerical influence.
Because according to the observation that may be traveling through the towns of the interior
of Spain, there eat more sweets where worship and religious practices absorb more of the life
and greater power of religious feeling translates into novenas, rosaries
sung fraternities and canons.

This shows that there must be some mysterious affinity between mysticism and confectionery.

This
was displayed in the shop Morana two painted pine cabinets blue glass doors located at both
of sides of the counter. These cabinets was kept a reasonable amount of candy, donuts dipped,
sighs, muffins, almond, and above all, the spreaders praised and whose reputation will be very
famous tablets certainly reached the ears of our readers. Everything from ancient times. The
tablets, whose composition magic we could never find out, had an irresistible attraction, based,
rare case! in its extraordinary hardness. At an age when they ate the tablets how important
the Morana was not the sweets were delicate, delicious, exquisite, but that lasted long. To make
the teeth bite into them, was forced permeating previously a fabulous amount of saliva. Once
driven into its high-sticky paste grade, separate them again came to be a real problem. Let me
dedicate a delicate reminder of sympathy and recognition of these tablets from four to eight
years are linked to the happiest moments of my life. At the sugar influx may be the author of
this book the flower of optimism, which, critics say, shine in his works.

La Morana, daughter and heiress of another Morana already dead, was
a woman of forty, pale, with patches of gutta-percha in the temples
for headaches.

She was married to a John Chrysostom, which in the words of Don Segis, chaplain, was not the Chrysostomos.
No However, when administered a beating to his wife, used to show some unusual erudition.

- "I who loved this woman - he exclaimed with tenderness, snuggling
the stick to the wall .-- I I loved this woman as wife and not as
a servant, as mandated by the Apostle Paul!

... Did you you read the Apostle Paul? ... What you had to read you, great cow !...»

The wine was very good, almost can be said that it was the only good
thing in this establishment, and That would not stop much in the cellar.

Don Roque, Don Segis, Don Benigno, Don Juan Salado and Mr. Anselmo cabinetmaker, took care to
pass it fixed term to yours. Was white wine, strong, superior, who rose to head with astonishing
ease. The circles Store every night, between eleven and twelve, went tumbling to their homes,
but quiet, grave, without ever giving the least scandal. They used the five holding out arm in supporting
each other. Upon reaching the walls of the garden of the convent of the Augustinian urinated.
After continuing on his way without saying a word, but much huffing and puffing. Instinct, which
never completely left, I suggested this prudent conduct. Included that if they spoke little or a lot,
could become entangled in a dispute. Hence the voices and scandal Therefore ... Nothing, nothing,
it was best not complaining. To reach their homes were released muttering with clumsy language, "Good
evening." The last was Don Roque to live farther than none.

This serious, modest, patriarchal emborachaban those venerable elders
are all night of the year.

Two of them, Don Juan Salado, clerk of the City, and Don Segis, experienced and the consequences
of that life. The Salado had a nose that was scary see: when you least expect it fell on the minutes.
Don Segis had suffered a stroke, a result which dragged his right leg as if it carry arrobas
six weight. True that the insatiable chaplain was not satisfied with paneled Wine of the confectionery.
For every one that was necessary to swallow that will serve Morana a glass of gin, which carefully
poured into a bottle that led to the effect on pocket. If there were six panels, six cups, if eight,
eight. All this gin gently passed your stomach in small sips after he had gone to bed. "But
Don Segis, how much do you drink gin once? - I have no choice - he answered in a resigned tone
and humble man who broke his heart .-- If not drink a drink for every quarter pound, which would Me,
son of soul? ... I would spend the night like a horse! "

The talks were Morana shop and moved less interesting than the Club. The old commentators were
interested and very few things in the world.

Cases most serious of the town, which promoted the Saloncillo storms, were treated, or rather,
they touched lightly without any passion. Gonzalez had fired the the captain of the Carmen and appointed
in his place an Andalusian.

- When Gonzalez have - a slow and said quietly, - have their reasons.

-
It's true - answer other after a while, raising his glass to his lips.

-
Ripalda seemed a good subject - said a third, after five minutes,
leaving the glass on the counter and belching.

- Yes, it seemed -
replied another seriously.

Passed ten minutes of meditation. The gatherings gave some loving kisses the glass, topaz appeared.
Don Roque breaks the silence:

- Anyway, there is no doubt that Don Antonio scorched him.

- I burned - Don Juan says the Salado.

- I burned - confirms Don Benigno.

- I burned - corroborates Mr.
Anselmo.

- I burned completely - resume finally Don Segis grimly.

What altered the mood once in a while, was the question of pigeons. Mr. Anselmo and Don Benigno
fed unquenchable passion for these animals. Each had his loft, their breeds, breeding procedures,
and such ends often became entangled in long and lively discussions. The others listened seriously,
not daring to decide, up and down counter the glass to his lips with religious silence. The crime
of the Windmills were upset, but caused deep unease in them than in the rest of the neighborhood.
After five or six days, returned to their patriarchal customs. And such was his courage, that
most forgotten nights of weapons left in the store.

Twelve would be the edge of one, in which Don Roque had passed with three more Grilles six rate
ordinarily imposed when the five pillars of the tearoom Morana chain came in tight to their
homes. Marcones brought up the rear, with rifle on his shoulder. The first one was released
Segis don, who lived in a little two balconies, attached to the Augustinian convent. After Don Juan
was the Salado. After the coadjutor. Finally, Mr. Anselmo, pulling out the big shiny key that
served as a baton when conducted the orchestra, opened the workshop where he slept.

The mayor was just on the strength of his command. He said something, but the force did not
understand. They started walking home, which was not far. But before reaching it, Don Roque blowing
and snorting like a whale, and imitated as far as possible, swirling up gasping of this whale, suddenly
stopped, and uttered aloud a long speech, which no Marcones understood more than the word thieves,
repeated several times. He looked at the sheriff with shock all around to see if anyone saw,
setting the rifle at the same time, but observed nothing ever made him suspicious of the outlaws.
Roque turned to use a word, if that name deserved intermittent regurgitation of a portion of
sounds strange, barbaric, pitiful, that instilled sadness and horror at the same time, and Marcones
could then infer that his boss wanted them to do a sweep through the town, looking for criminals
of the Windmills.

Marcones mused that the force was low and prevented bad for that company, but the discipline not allowed
to make objections. In addition, born in his heart the hope that the murderers some fans were
taking the air at this hour. And after careful consideration weapons, they began a march through all
the dangerous streets and alleys of villa. In honor of the truth, it should be noted that Mr.
Roque was ahead and to meet a courageous leader with his revolver in his left hand and the
sword-stick on the right, exposing the first chest to lead his noble enemy. Marcones, groaning under
the weight of rifle and eighty-two years she had walked back to a distance of six steps soon.

It
was a moonlit night, but big black clouds often hid it for long.

And then the dim light of oil lamps burning in the street corners not enough to undo the shadows
that crowded into the middle of them. Consists Sarrió five main questions: la Rúa Nueva, which
flows into the spring, that of Caborana, the San Florencio, that of blacksmithing and Back.
These streets are long, wide enough and parallel. The buildings are generally low and poor.
Other secondary streets in considerable numbers, the cross and communicate. In addition, he
go outside some tails to the village, where they built sumptuous houses the Indians. They are
what might be called the expansion of the population.

Arriving on foot column by Back Street, near St. Bridget, heard screams
and laments that forced her to stop.

- What is it, Marcones? - Said
the mayor.

The old sheriff shrugged philosophically.

- Nothing, sir, will be at home in Santa Patina.

- And how dare these
mort?

... Let there Marcones, we act continuously.

"Continuous act" was a phrase that Mr. Roque used and abused.

It symbolized for him the energy, decision, the speed of the authority to remedy all damages.

Patina Santa was the high priest of one of the two temples of pleasure that existed in Sarrió.
Occasionally went into the villages and neighboring towns that brought the priestesses were
required, four ever spent. There was more cabinets, and that they slept in pairs. Dressed
the same green baize petticoat or red, the same doublet without whales, the same shirt big canvas,
the same calico handkerchief when bounded about back in the meadows and Mountains with the
cowboys neighbors. Patina Santa, as only symbols of the new and high destiny that the fate has
called them, hanging from her ears and imprisoned pearl earrings his feet with twill low-cut shoes,
which were well bonded to the house and served for all they arrived. Patina later, taking
over the world up and that the laws of progress are alienable had the audacity to enter his
temple rice powder. After doublé bought some medallions to hang around his neck with a terciopelito
black. True that all these reforms will stimulate competition disastrous he was scantily clad,
which had its school on the street the clock, on the other end the
villa.

- What scandal is this? - Roque shouted in a stentorian voice
approaching the filthy hovel.

Three or four boys who had fled into the street like birds in view of the hawk. But were the pigeons.
Two of them were at the door in shirtsleeves, leaning out the other two the windows in the same
suit.

The door wanted to pull out in view of the Mayor but he picks on
his paws.

- What is this scandal ... garlic? - Repeated.

- Mr. Mayor,
we have given two false pieces ...-- said one of them.

- You are
not bad parts you ... To jail!

- But, Mr. Mayor!

- A prison ...
garlic, to jail! - Roared Don Roque .-- And you as well.

Everyone down. Where the bugger is Patina?

Good heavens, what a fuss was assembled there in a minute!

The girls in the window had no choice but to go down, and Patina same,
all in shirt Roque admitted because no dilatory term.

Nothing was heard but groans and moans, and Above them the horrible voice of the mayor, repeating
incessantly:

- A prison ... garlic! A prison ... garlic!

The unhappy called by God and the Virgin that dejasen dress, but the
mayor, the face carried away by anger and bloodshot eyes, shouting
ever more strongly, stunned with his own voice:

- A prison ... garlic!.,
A prison ... garlic!

And there was no other choice. The watchman, who had come to hear the first garlic, conducted
in that provision to the municipal jail, with his dignified head, while neighbors, including
smiling and compassionate, watched the scene behind the glass your
windows.

Roque authority itself closed the door of the loft, and put the key 'continuing act' Marcones custody.
Then continued their march dangerous.

Space had not gone far when one of the narrowest streets and murky,
matched to see the bulk of a person who cautiously approached the
door of a house and was opening.

- Stop! - Roque whispered in the
ear of his subordinate .-- We have already encountered one of the
thieves.

The sheriff did not understand but the last word. It was enough to fell the gun was hands.

- Do not tremble, Marcones, which for now is only one - the mayor said taking her by the arm.

If the venerable Marcones sane at the time had their powers of observation, had noticed anything
in the hand of authority very definite tendency to convulsive movement.

The thief, he felt the footsteps of the patrol, turned his head with
a start and remained still with the pick in his hand.

Don Roque and Marcones also stood still.

The moon, work by filtering with a cloud, began to light that fateful scene.

- Phs, phs, friend - the mayor said after a while, without advancing a step.

Amical hear the thief this call by the authority and take flight,
it was all one.

- To him, Marcones!

Fire! - Roque shouted, turning to run hard in pursuit of the criminal.

Marcene

refused to obey the order of his boss, but it was not possible, the
hammer fell on the piston without popping the primer.

Then, with martial decision, threw the gun that it did not help anything,
pulled the sword from the sheath of leather and made a supreme effort
by meet the mayor, with reckless courage she had advanced at least
twenty steps the pursuit of the thief.

This had gone on a street corner.

But to get there could see his spine trying to win another.

Pum!

Don Roque fired his gun, shouting at the same time:

- Date, thief!

Turned away, turned to him upon arrival at Mercy Street.

Pum! Another shot of Mr. Roque.

- Date, thief!

But the outlaw, undoubtedly as a supreme source, and to prevent a
peaceful stop him, began to cry also:

- Thieves, thieves!

There was the shrill whistle and whistle of a prolonged calm, then another, then another ...

San Florencio street was well lit, and the criminal could be clearly
seen slipping with amazing speed searching in vain for the shadow
of the houses.

Pum, pum!

- Date, thief!

- Thieves! - Said the bandit while running.

Two watchmen were added to the column, and ran brandishing pikes beside the mayor.

The wanted criminal at any cost to win the New Rua order may be made
to the Dock and hide in a ship or jump into the water.

But before she tripped reach and gave his body on the floor.

Thanks to this accident earned him considerable Patrol distance walked
close to achieving.

But before this happens, the outlaw, rising with extreme alacrity, fled lighter than the wind.
Don Roque last two shots fired on his revolver, always yelling:

- Date, thief!
Disappeared at the corner of Rua Nueva. Lead her to the mayor and
his force near the square of the Navy, saw no trace of anything criminal.
Followed hesitant up to that post. They stopped not knowing what to
do.

- At the pier, the pier, there must be - a serene said.

And
they were about to undertake all the way, when you opened the balcony
of a crash house, a man appeared in his underwear, and heard these
words, which resonated deeply into the silence of the night:

- The
thief just walked into the cafe on the Marina!

He who uttered them
was Don Feliciano Gómez. The patrol, to listen, rushed to the cafe
door, and entered it noisily. The room was empty. Back in the bottom,
next to the counter, sailing three or four young men in a white apron
surrounding a man who was shot more than sitting on a chair. The mayor,
the sheriff, the calm fell over him, putting to heart the pikes, sword
and saber. And at a time they shouted:

- Date, thief!

The criminal
up to them his terrified face, paler than the wax.

- Oh, re ... if
Don Jaime, so help me God! - said a calm down the pike.

All the others
did the same, dumb with surprise. Because, in fact, the outlaw who
had persecuted to death, was none other than Marin caught red-handed,
when opening the your door.

We had to bring her shoulders, and bleed.
The next day, Mr. Roque was presented to apologize, and he got it</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>