<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document07190</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>86964</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>16747</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

Retirado el Libertador en Puerto-Principe trabajaban en tanto para organizar una nueva expedicion,
cediendo a las instancias que varios jefes y oficiales distinguidos del ejercito le habian
dirigido; y ya contaba de hecho con Brion, a cuyos buques, unidos los de Villaret formaron
una escuadrilla respetable, y con varios oficiales italianos del disuelto ejercito de Napoleon,
que con el general espanol Francisco Javier Mina habian llegado a Haiti por aquel tiempo. Hechos
sus preparativos salio del puerto de Jacmel y, el 28 de Diciembre, tras una navegacion de siete
dias, desembarcando en Juan Griego expedia una proclama-manifiesto sobre las causas y motivos
de su separacion del mando y la necesidad urgente de reunir un Congreso en Margarita para el
establecimiento de un gobierno apropiado a las circunstancias, en consonancia con la voluntad
de los pueblos libertados de la opresion; y el ultimo dia del ano, entrando en Barcelona, se
puso nuevamente a la cabeza del ejercito.

Cumplianse estos sucesos y al propio tiempo se refugiaban en el territorio venezolano los patriotas
que pudieron escapar de la sanguinaria cuchilla de Morillo, dueno ya de la Nueva-Granada. Entre
ellos se encontraban varios jefes y oficiales de merito, tanto granadinos como venezolanos,
y asi como hubieron llegado a Guadaslito para dar unidad y eficacia a los esfuerzos comunes--tal
era al menos su proposito--establecieron un gobierno, nombrando como Presidente de la Republica
al ex-gobernador de Pamplona, teniente coronel Fernando Serrano, y a Urdaneta, a Servier y
al Doctor Francisco Javier Yanes por Consejeros de Estado, con el coronel Santander como jefe
del ejercito. Este gobierno nacia muerto porque los jefes venezolanos aspiraban a concentrar
el poder en un solo jefe de confianza entre los llaneros, para que les condujese a la guerra
investido de un caracter absoluto; y renunciando Santander el mando, recayo en Paez, a quien
la junta elevo al grado de general de brigada. Pronto allego gente y se hizo temible en las
llanuras a las tropas realistas, derrotadas mas tarde por el en varios encuentros.

A principios de 1817, libertada la isla de Margarita, recuperadas las provincias de Barcelona
y Cumana, y duenos ya los venezolanos de las llanuras de Caracas, Paez habia ocupado el territorio
que se extiende entre el Arauca y el Apure, Piar seguia hostilizando al enemigo en la Guayana
y merced a los desmanes de Morillo que habian enconado el animo de los llaneros, la guerra
habia cambiado de faz y se hacia enteramente nacional, si bien aun quedaba por realizar la
grande obra de disciplinar el ejercito, cortando el vuelo a las ambiciones de algunos jefes,
nacidas del mismo desorden en que hasta entonces estuvo envuelta la causa de la independencia.

Coronado por algunos triunfos se encontraba Bolivar en Guayana, cuando tuvo noticia de que
Morillo, de vuelta ya en Venezuela, reuniendo su gente con la del coronel Don Jose Aldama,
en el Chaparro, el dia 13 de Mayo, se disponia a pasar el Orinoco al frente de 6.000 hombres,
y que Marino, aspirando como siempre al mando supremo, reunia en Cariaco un Congreso revistiendole
de poderes para legislar y ante el cual representaba la farsa de ofrecer la dimision del Libertador
con la suya propia para obtener la distincion que ambicionaba.

Este Congreso, sin autoridad legitima, nombro como funcionarios del poder legitimo a los generales
Fernando Toro y Simon Bolivar, con el coronel Francisco Javier Maiz y por suplentes a Zea,
al coronel Vallenilla y a Madariaga, que acababa de llegar de la Peninsula espanola. Marino
quedaba en el sonado cargo de general en jefe del ejercito; y Brion, complice en este descabellado
negocio, ascendia nada menos que a almirante. Aunque Piar mostro su adhesion a semejante proyecto,
la mayor parte de los jefes de division, asi como la oficialidad y la tropa, unanimes todos
y conociendo los meritos de su verdadero jefe, manifestaron la firme resolucion de seguir a
sus ordenes, y Bolivar reprobo publica y solemnemente la Asamblea de Cariaco.

Al poco tiempo, profundamente convencido de su error, llevo Brion al Liberlador su escuadra,
con la cual y la escuadrilla de Antonio Diaz salio de Pampalar el 31 del mismo mes de Mayo,
y despues de algunos combates en que los patriotas pelearon con la acostumbrada bizarria, sometio
a Guayana. Mientras verificaba esta operacion, el brigadier Don Jose de Canterac, al frente
de 3.000 peninsulares, llegaba al Morro de Barcelona y el republicano Piar, movido por la ambicion,
minaba lentamente la estabilidad de las posesiones alcanzadas, promoviendo la discordia entre
los jefes, alentando la tropa a la rebeldia y haciendo renacer la ya olvidada idea de colores
y diferencias de raza.

Semejante proceder no podia ser tolerado en los momentos en que la union era tan necesaria
para marchar viento en popa a la conquista de la independencia. Asi, pues, arrestado de orden
de Bolivar, fue conducido a Angostura, juzgado en consejo de guerra y condenado a muerte. Brion
desempeno el papel de Presidente del tribunal; y la ejecucion de la sentencia pronunciada contra
el reo tuvo lugar el 16 de Octubre de 1817, produciendo los mas excelentes resultados en el
ejercito, pues restablecio algun tanto la disciplina, afirmo la autoridad suprema, y dio una
alta idea a propios y extranos, a amigos y enemigos, de aquel gobierno militar, verdadero caos
hasta entonces.

Despues de este acto, sensible para quien como el Libertador mil veces habia combatido al lado
de tan valiente militar, puso jefes dignos de su confianza al frente de las libertadas provincias,
creo un Consejo de Estado con derecho de consulta en las materias de guerra y en las gubernativas,
con voto deliberativo en las administrativas y economicas, declarando al propio tiempo capital
y residencia provisional del gobierno de Venezuela la ciudad de Angostura. Por ultimo, dicto
una ley en la cual se mandaba repartir los bienes nacionales con justa regla y proporcion entre
sus companeros de armas; y, despues de ordenar a Zaraza y a Monagas que cubriesen con su caballeria
el primero las llanuras de Caracas y el segundo las de Barcelona, el Libertador remonto el
Orinoco con todas sus fuerzas, yendo a reunirse al ejercito que mandaba Paez en el Apure, lo
cual realizo por Enero de 1818.

El ano que espiraba habia sido fecundo en buenos resultados para las armas republicanas, no
solo en Venezuela sino tambien en Buenos-Aires, y por la proclamacion de independencia que
hizo Chile; pero el ano que daba principio habia de ser les infausto. En el sitio llamado Rincon
de los Toros, cerca de San Jose de los Tiznados, la noche del 16 de Abril, una partida de realistas
a favor de la oscuridad, penetro osadamente en el campamento de Bolivar, habiendose este visto
en peligro de perder la vida, que el cielo le conservo una vez mas como necesaria al triunfu
de la santa causa.

Hallabase despues en Guayana reorganizando sus tropas y separandose de los muchos desastres
que las habian afligido desde aquella noche fatal, cuando un comisionado de la provincia granadina
de Casanare se presento a informarle de que Paez, desconociendo su autoridad y la del Consejo
de gobierno, habia sido elevado por el ejercito del Apure a la dignidad de primer jefe y director
supremo del pais. El mismo mensajero traia el encargo de pedirle que nombrase una persona leal
y capaz que, encargada del mando general, regularizase las operaciones en su provincia. Bolivar
dio un manifiesto en que no solo se limitaba a reprobar la insurreccion, sino en el cual se
extendia a dar en cara el villano proceder a cuantos bajo una hipocrita apariencia se vendian
como amigos suyos y de la independencia nacional. En seguida ordeno que Francisco de Paula
Santander, ascendido al grado de general de brigada, con Jacinto Lara, varios excelentes oficiales
y los tenientes coroneles granadinos Antonio Obando, Francisco Velez, Joaquin Paris y Vicente
Gonzalez, con armas, municiones y demas pasase a Casanare como jefe de operaciones de un cuerpo
avanzado que alli debia formarse y mantenerse para, mas adelante, invadir la Nueva-Granada
y devolverle la libertad de que Morillo la habia privado.

En vano la fortuna, volviendo la espalda al mas constante y benemerito de los venezolanos de
su tiempo, pretendia humillar y arrebatarlo el entusiasta amor que a su patria profesaba; en
vano descargaba sobre el, en formidable turbion, defecciones y crueles golpes; en medio de
la tormenta, como la empinada palma que sacudida por el huracan se dobla para erguirse con
gran fuerza, asi el animo altivo del inquebrantable guerrero se rehacia de los vaivenes que
le azotaban y, siempre sereno, siempre confiado en la bondad de su causa, despreciando los
embates que sus emulos promovian, continuaba ocupandose de la organizacion de un gobierno que,
afianzando la libertad, a la cual habia consagrado su vida entera, labrase el bienestar futuro
de su pais y, el 10 de Octubre, propuso al Consejo de Estado que al efecto convocase la reunion
de un Congreso.

Algo mas tarde, el 20 de Noviembre, temeroso de que las potencias europeas, solicitadas por
el gobierno espanol, ya casi convencido de la inutilidad de sus esfuerzos, llegasen a prestarle
apoyo para la conservacion de sus colonias, expidio un famoso decreto en el cual declaraba
abiertamente "que el pueblo de Venezuela estaba resuelto a sepultarse todo entero en medio
de sus ruinas, por mas que la Espana, la Europa y aun el mundo entero, llegasen a tratar de
encorvarle nuevaments bajo el yugo que pronto iban a sacudir."

Esto no obstante, la adversidad le perseguia este ano hasta el ultimo dia; viendose al fin
obligado a desprenderse de la Guayana, seguia el curso del Orinoco en direccion de las llanuras
de Apure, al acercarse el nuevo ano, con objeto de consolidar el poder del gobierno entre las
tropas republicanas alli acantonadas, y con el de oponerse a Morillo en el teatro probable
de sus operaciones, marchando, en medio de todos sus reveses, siempre fijo el pensamiento en
dias de gloria para el y para su amada patria.

CAPITULO VIII

Vindicacion de Paez.--La reconciliacion.--El caudillo del Apure asciende a general.--Reunion
del Congreso y abdicacion de Bolivar que es honrado con mas gloriosos nombres.--Ideas del padre
de la patria respecto a la republica.--Propuesta hecha por el al Congreso.--Provincias representadas
en el Cuerpo Legislativo.--Persistencia de Bolivar en su renuncia. Por fin conserva su mando.--Refuerzos
extranjeros--Nueva campana.--Victoria de Paez.--Bolivar marcha a Nueva-Granada.--Disposiciones
militares.--Viaje de la expedicion y sus resultados.--Triunfo de Bolivar en Boyaca.--Fuga del
virey a Honda.--Entrada del Libertador en Bogota.--Medidas gubernativas.--Bolivar en Angostura.--Sus
gestiones respecto a la Confederacion.--Nacimiento de a Republica de Colombia.

Muchos e importantisimos eran los servicios prestados a la causa de la independencia por el
caudillo del Apure, y si la ambicion habia podido estraviarle, los medios empleados para llevarlo
a cabo no se habian desviado del santo fin; no podian mirarse como disolventes, puesto que
habian emanado del loco amor por la patria y hasta cierto punto daban una buena idea de su
genio diplomatico. Conservando en su gobierno al Libertador, rodeado de ilustres y benemeritas
personas, solo habia buscado el medio de hacerle dejar vacio su puesto de general en jefe para
entrar el a reemplazarle en el mando. Esto ni menoscababa el prestigio de la autoridad, ni
minaba la disciplina, ni amenguaba lo mas minimo el entusiasmo de los defensores de la libertad.

Bolivar y Paez se vieron en San Juan de Payara el 16 de Enero de 1819, y pronto quedaron reconciliados
por el deseo que en ambos existia de levantar el animo de sus soldados, algo abatido por los
desastres del ano anterior, y marchar en buena armonia desde enfonces al noble fin que les
hacia exponer su vida en el campo de batalla. Asi reunieron un ejercito de 2.000 ginetes y
numero igual de infantes, poco mas o menos, inclusos mil hombres mandados por el general Anzuategui
y la division a cuyo frente se hallaba Cedeno; y como sello de esta alianza, elevado Paez a
general de division, delegandole por entonces el mando de todas las tropas, con el fin de disponer
lo necesario a la reunion del Congreso, aplazada para el mes de Febrero, Bolivar se puso en
marcha con direccion a Angostura.

Paez avanzaba victorioso por las llanuras, y el Congreso de Guayana se reunia el 15 de Febrero,
dia en que Bolivar ante aquel deponia su autoridad suprema. Pero este alto Cuerpo, despues
de confirmar unanimemente los actos y disposiciones del dimitente, le aclamo de nuevo Libertador,
padre de la patria y terror del despotismo, con la mas sincera expresion de gratitud y afecto.

Conocidas eran desde 1815 las ideas del celebre campeon americano respecto a la Constitucion
de la republica, su forma de gobierno, su administracion y nombre que debia llevar. Llamariase
Colombia, como tributo de justicia, gratitud y honor al grande hombre que dio al mundo antiguo
un nuevo mundo, y en cuanto a lo demas, la forma de gobierno de Inglaterra creia ser la mas
conveniente para la nueva republica, que se compondria de Venezuela, Nueva-Granada y Quito.
A diferencia de la nacion que tomaba por modelo, el rey seria representado por un poder ejecutivo
de eleccion, vitalicio cuando mas, pero nunca hereditario, dado caso de que optara por la Republica;
un Senado legislativo hereditario y una Camara, tambien legislativa, de libre eleccion, sin
mas restricciones que las de la Baja de Inglaterra.

Esto mismo propuso al Congreso tan luego como dio principio a sus sesiones, ampliando sus antiguas
ideas con la formacion de cierto poder moral que llamo Areopago. Compondriase de dos distintas
Camaras, cuyas atribuciones eran: en la una, el velar de la educacion de los ninos desde su
cuna hasta la edad de 12 anos; y en la otra, la de castigar los vicios con el oprobio y la
infamia, y dar el premio conveniente a las virtudes publicas por medio de los honores. Semejante
innovacion fue desechada, y en cuanto a la Constitucion que se voto, el Congreso se apartaba
bastante de algunas de las disposiciones enunciadas por Bolivar.

Un Congreso general, dividido en dos Camaras de Representantes y de Senadores, ejerceria el
poder legislativo, siendo meramente vitalicios los segundos. Habria un Presidente de la Republica
por cuatro anos, y reelegible por una sola vez, encargado de ejercer el poder ejecutivo. Este,
aunque personalmente responsable ante el Congreso por usurpacion o mal uso de las rentas publicas,
traicion, venalidad o conspiracion contra la ley del Estado, gozaba sin embargo de muy amplias
facultades. Ademas habria un Vice-Presidente sucesor en los casos de destitucion, renuncia
o muerte. En cuanto al resto era grande a afinidad que existia entre este y el codigo Constitucional
sancionado en 1811 por el Congreso que Miranda reunio el 2 de Marzo.

Caracas, Barcelona, Cumana, Varinas, Guayana y Margarita por parte de Venezuela, y Casanare,
unica provincia granadina ocupada por las armas republicanas, se hallaban dignamente representadas
en esta ocasion solemne. Bolivar manifesto repetidas veces al Congreso que no se encargaria
mas de la suprema autoridad ejecutiva; pero despues de mil y mil vivas instancias por parte
de sus companeros, acepto la presidencia, que fue investida de facultades mas amplias, tanto
politicas como militares, en las provincias que fuesen teatro de la guerra. Estas atribuciones
podia delegarlas en caso de necesidad; y mientras se hallase en campana, el ciudadano Francisco
Antonio Zea, en calidad de Vice-Presidente, ejerceria la potestad ejecutiva. El ministerio
de Estado quedo compuesto de los senores: coronel Pedro Briceno Mendez como ministro de Guerra
y Marina, Diego Bautista Urbaneja del Interior y Justicia, y el Dr. Manuel Palacios de Hacienda.

Hacia el mismo tiempo desembarcaban en Angostura y Margarita tres cuerpos de tropas reclutadas
en Inglaterra, mandados por Elsom, English y Uzlar, sirviendo esto a Bolivar para completar
su plan de campana, a cuya combinacion se consagraba seriamente y con su habitual actividad.
En su consecuencia, Urdaneta paso a organizar en Margarita una division que debia componerse
de los dos cuerpos de ingleses que alli habia con English y Uzlar, y ponerse al frente de ellos
despues de haber organizado otro de gentes del pais. Hecho esto, con la escuadra de Brion debia
dirigirse a tomar Caracas y entenderse luego por la retaguardia hasta enlazar sus fuerzas con
las del ejercito del Apure, que el Libertador mandaria en persona. Mientras tanto Marino, con
la division de Oriente, distraeria la atencion del enemigo en aquella direccion. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document08882</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>168</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>15374</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

Removed-Principe Puerto Libertador while working to organize a new expedition yielding to the instances
that several distinguished leaders and officers of the army had directed, and indeed already
had with Brion, whose ships, together formed the de Villaret a respectable squad and with
several Italian officers of the disbanded army of Napoleon, with the Spanish general Francisco
Javier Mina had arrived in Haiti at that time. Acts preparations left the port of Jacmel, and on
December 28, after a voyage of seven days, landing at John Greek expedia a clear proclamation of
the causes and reasons separation of command and the urgent need to assemble a Congress in Margarita
for establishment of a government appropriate to the circumstances, in accordance with the will
peoples freedom from oppression, and the last day of the year, entering Barcelona, again made
the head of the army.

Cumplianse these events and at the same time took refuge in the Venezuelan territory patriots who escaped
the bloody knife Morillo, owner and New-Granada. Among them were several chiefs and officers of
merit, both Granada and Venezuela, and just as they reached Guadaslito to give unity and effectiveness
of joint efforts - such His purpose was at least - set up a government, naming as President of the
Republic the ex-governor of Pamplona, ??Lt. Col. Fernando Serrano, and Urdaneta, to Servier Dr.
Francisco Javier Yanes Councillors of State, as chief Colonel Santander Army. This government
was stillborn because the Venezuelan leaders aspired to concentrate power in a single head of
trust between the prairie, so that they would lead to war vested with an absolute character,
and relinquishing control Santander, went to Paez, who board to the rank of brigadier general.
Allego soon became frightening people and on plains to the royalist troops, later defeated by
him in several meetings.

In early 1817, liberated the island of Margarita, recovered the provinces of Barcelona and Cumana,
and owners and the plains of Venezuela Caracas, Paez had occupied the territory lying between the
Arauca and Apure, Piar I kept harassing the enemy in Guyana and thanks to the excesses of Morillo
who had inflamed the minds of the prairie, war face had changed and to entirely domestic,
but still remained to conduct the great work to discipline the army, cutting the flight to
the ambitions of some leaders, born of the same disorder that was previously shrouded the cause
of independence.

Crowned Bolivar was some success in Guyana, when he heard that Morillo, back and in Venezuela,
bringing his people with that of Colonel Don Jose Aldama in Chapman, the 13th of May, was preparing
to spend the Orinoco in front of 6,000 men, and Marino, hoping as always to the supreme command, a
Congress met in Cariaco coating powers to legislate and to the farce which represented the Liberator's
resignation offer with his own to get that coveted distinction.

This Congress, without lawful authority, appointed as officers of the generals legitimate power
Fernando Toro and Simon Bolivar, with Colonel Francisco Javier Maiz and alternates Zea Colonel Vallenilla
and Madariaga, who had just arrived from the Spanish mainland. Marino was struck by the general in
chief of the army, and Brion, accomplice in this crazy business, amounted to no less than Admiral.
Although Piar show its commitment to such a project, most of the heads of division, as well
as the officers and troops, unanimous all and knowing the merits
of his real boss, said the firm resolution to follow their orders,
and reprobate Bolivar solemnly publish and Cariaco Assembly.

Before long, deeply convinced of his error, I Liberlador Brion to his squad with which and the squad
Antonio Diaz came out of the same Pampalar 31 May, and after a few fights in the patriots fought
with his usual gallantry, submitted Guiana. While verifying the operation, Brigadier Don Jose de Canterac,
leading of 3,000 Spaniards, arrived at the Morro de Barcelona and Republican Piar, driven by
ambition, slowly undermined the stability of possessions reached, promoting discord between heads,
encouraging the troops to the rebellion and reviving the long forgotten
idea of ??colors and racial differences.

Such behavior could not be tolerated in a time when the union was as necessary to go from strength
to strength to conquer independence. So arrest order of Bolivar, was taken to Angostura, court-martialed
and sentenced to death. Brion performance the role of president of the court, and the execution
of the sentence pronounced against the defendant took place on October 16, 1817, producing the
most excellent results in army, as well reestablished some discipline, I affirm the supreme authority,
and gave a high idea and strangers, friends and enemies, that the
military government, chaos until then.

After this event, sensitive as the Liberator who had fought a thousand times next of such a valiant
soldier, he heads worthy of their confidence in front of the liberated provinces Council of State
created a right to consult with on matters of war and in the governmental, deliberative vote
in the administrative and economic capital at the same time declaring and temporary residence of
the government of the city of Angostura Venezuela. Finally, I teach a law which commanded national
divide property just rule and proportion between their companions in arms, and, after ordering
Zaraza Monagas and his horse covered with first the plains of Caracas and the second those of
Barcelona, ??the Liberator traces the Orinoco with all his might,
going to join the army commanded by Paez in Apure, which which was
created by January 1818.

The expiring year had been fruitful in good results for the republican arms, no only in Venezuela
but also in Buenos-Aires, and the proclamation of independence Chile did, but the first year that gave
them was to be unfortunate. In a place called Rincon of the Bulls, San Jose near the Tiznados
the night of April 16, a realistic game for the dark, boldly penetrated into the camp of Bolivar,
this having been seen in danger of losing his life, heaven will retain
one more time as necessary to triunfu of the sacred cause.

Hallab in Guyana after reorganizing his troops and separating from the many disasters that had
afflicted since that fatal night, when a commissioner of the province of Granada Casanare was presented
to inform you that Paez, ignoring their authority and the Council government, had been raised
by the army of Apure to the dignity of the first chief and director highest in the country. The
same messenger brought the custom of asking him to appoint a loyal person and capable, responsible
for overall command, regularize the operations in his province. Bolivar gave a manifesto that
not only limited to condemn the uprising, but which stretched to take on the villain come
face to those under a hypocritical appearance were sold as their friends and national independence.
Then ordered that Francisco de Paula Santander, promoted to brigadier general, with Jacinto Lara,
several excellent officers and lieutenant colonels Granada Antonio Obando, Francisco Velez, Joaquin
and Vicente Paris Gonzalez, weapons, ammunition and other pass to Casanare as chief operating
officer of a body advanced that there was to be formed and maintained
to, later, to invade New Granada and restore the freedom that had
deprived Morillo.

In vain fortune, turning their backs on the most consistent and well-deserving of Venezuelans
their time, trying to humiliate and snatch the enthusiastic love for his country he professed,
in vain discharged on, in a formidable storm, defections and cruel blows, amid the storm, as
the steep palm hit by the hurricane is folded to stand up to great strength, so proud of the
unwavering encouragement reworked warrior of the ups and downs whipped him, and always calm, always
confident in the goodness of their cause, neglecting the attacks that promoted his rivals, continued
to handle the organization of a government that strengthening freedom, which he had devoted his
whole life, till the future welfare of his country and on October
10, proposed to the State Council convened the meeting to the effect
of Congress.

Somewhat later, on November 20, fearing that the European powers requested by the Spanish government,
almost convinced of the futility of their efforts, arrived to lend support for the preservation
of its colonies, issued a famous decree which declared clear "that the people of Venezuela
was determined to bury all integers between from its ruins, for more
than Spain, Europe and even the world, arrived to try nuevaments bending
under the yoke that were soon to shake.

"

This however, persecuted him adversity this year until the last day, finally being watched forced
to give Guyana, following the course of the Orinoco in the direction of the plains of Apure,
when approaching the new year in order to consolidate the power of government between Republican
troops stationed there, and to object to in the theater probably
Morillo of its operations going amid all its setbacks, the thought
always fixed days of glory for himself and for his beloved homeland.

CHAPTER VIII

Vindication of Paez .-- The reconciliation .-- The leader of Apure amounts to general .-- Reunion Congress
and abdication of Bolivar who is honored with more glorious names of the father .-- Ideas of the
country over the republic .-- Proposal made by the Provinces .-- Congress represented in the
Legislature .-- Persistence of Bolivar in his resignation. Finally retains his command .-- Reinforcements
Foreigners - New hood .-- Victory .-- Bolivar Paez march to New-Granada
.-- Provisions Trip .-- military expedition and its results .-- Triumph
.-- Bolivar Boyaca Leakage Honda viceroy Liberator .-- Entry Bogota
governmental measures .-- .-- .-- His Angostura Bolivar efforts regarding
the Confederation .-- Birth of a Republic of Colombia.

Many and very important were the services rendered to the cause of independence by leader of
the Apure, and if ambition had been astray, the means employed to carry out had not strayed
from the holy order, they could not be regarded as solvents, since had emanated from the mad love
for the motherland and to some extent gave a good idea of diplomatic genius. Keeping in government
the Liberator, surrounded by illustrious and praiseworthy people had only sought the means
of making him leave empty his position as general-in-chief enter
to replace him in command.

This undermined the prestige or authority, or undermined the discipline nor the slightest amenguaba the
enthusiasm of the advocates of freedom.

Bolivar and Paez were in San Juan de Payara on January 16, 1819, and soon became reconciled
by the desire that both existed to lift the mood of the soldiers, some killed by the disasters of the
previous year, and march in good harmony from enfonces the noble purpose that they to put their
lives on the battlefield. So gathered an army of 2,000 horsemen and equal number of infants, more
or less, even a thousand men commanded by General Anzuategui and the division was headed by
Cedeno, and a seal of this alliance, a high Paez general division,
then delegates the command of all troops, in order to have what is
necessary for the reunion of Congress adjourned for the month of February,
was set Bolivar direction to go with Angostura.

Paez moved victorious over the plains, and the Congress of Guyana met February 15, Bolivar day that
before he deposed his supreme authority.

But this August body, after unanimously confirming the acts and provisions of retiring, he again
hailed Liberator Founding Father and terror of despotism, with the most sincere expression of
gratitude and affection.

Were known since 1815, the American champion held ideas about the Constitution of the republic,
its governance, its administration and name that was to carry. Would call Colombia, as a tribute
of justice, gratitude and honor the great man who gave the ancient world a new world, and as for the
rest, the form of government in England believed to be the most suitable for the new republic,
which would be composed of Venezuela, New Grenada and Quito.

Unlike the model nation for taking the king would be represented by an executive of choice, life at
most, but not hereditary, because if you opt for the Republic; a hereditary legislative Senate
and House, also legislative, free choice, without more restrictions than those of Lower England.

This
same proposal to Congress as soon as he was called to his sessions, extending their former
ideas with the formation of a moral power that called Areopagus. Composed of two different Chambers,
whose functions were: the one, the blurring of the education of children from birth until the
age of 12 years, and in the other, to punish the vices with the shame
and infamy, and should give the award to the public by virtue of honor.

Such innovation was dismissed, and as to the constitution that vote, Congress departed quite
a few of the requirements specified by Bolivar.

A general Congress, divided into two chambers of Representatives and Senate, would exercise legislature,
the latter being merely lifetime. Would have a President of the Republic for four years, and re-elected
only once in charge of exercising executive power. East although personally responsible to
the Congress by usurpation or misuse of the public revenue, betrayal, venality or conspiracy against
the State law, however enjoyed very broad faculties.

You would have a successor Vice-President in cases of dismissal, resignation or death. As for
the rest was great to affinity that existed between it and the Constitutional Code sanctioned in 1811
by Congress Miranda met on 2 March.

Caracas, Barcelona, ??Cumana, Varinas, Guyana and Margarita by Venezuela, and Casanare, Granada
province occupied only by the republican arms, were justly represented On this solemn occasion.
Bolivar Congress repeatedly stated that it will be good most of the supreme executive authority,
but after thousands and thousands of live bodies by of his companions, I accept the presidency,
which was vested with broad powers over both and military policies in the provinces that were
the theater of war. These powers could delegate them if necessary,
and while on campaign, the citizen Francisco Antonio Zea, as Vice-President,
exercise executive power.

Ministry of State is composed of the gentlemen: Colonel Pedro Briceno Mendez as Minister of War
and Marina, Diego Bautista Urbaneja of Interior and Justice, and Dr. Manuel Palacios of Finance.

About
the same time landed on Margarita Angostura and three bodies of troops raised in England, led
by Elsom, Inglés and Uzlar, which has served to complete Bolivar campaign plan, a combination
which was devoted seriously and with his usual activity. In consequence, Urdaneta Margarita with
organization in a division which was to consist of the two bodies of Englishmen who were there
with Inglés and Uzlar, and put in front of them After organizing other people of the country.
This done, the squad was to Brion directed to take Caracas and understood then the rear until
it joins forces with the army of the Apure, which would send the
Liberator in person. Meanwhile Marino, Eastern division, distract
the attention of the enemy in that direction</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>