<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05174</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>18594</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>22452</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent>

       *       *       *       *       *

No habiendo pasado en Toledo sino tres dias, que son suficientes para un viajero que no es
artista, apénas pude recoger impresiones rápidas. Toledo es interesante por su tipo social
y su mérito monumental; pero el primero me importaba mas que el segundo, tanto mas cuanto que
adolezco de una completa ignorancia en materia de arquitectura, pintura y escultura. Por lo
mismo no puedo emitir juicios, so pena de copiar lo ajeno (arte fea en que estoy ménos versado
aún que en bellas artes), y solo indicaré las emociones sentidas.

Toledo carece absolutamente de industria. Es una ciudad muerta ó por lo ménos paralizada. Lo
único que allí llama la atencion en lo económico es la famosa fábrica de armas, situada á la
márgen derecha del Tajo, al poniente del istmo que he descrito. Me fué imposible visitarla,
porque estaba cerrada en esos dias con motivo de la Semana Santa, que los pueblos españoles
y sus análogos celebran con la ociosidad. Supe sinembargo, que las armas toledanas eran de
las mismísimas condiciones que las de lejanos tiempos. Los siglos han pasado por encima, sin
que los forjadores se hayan dado por notificados, pues hoy los procedimientos de fabricacion
son los mismos que ahora cuatrocientos años, sin que los productos hayan mejorado notablemente.
La vieja España machaca el acero con los mismos martillos. La civilizacion moderna no ha llegado
sino hasta la estacion de ferrocarril, al pié de Toledo. De ahí para arriba.... ¡cuidado con
tocar las telarañas!

En Toledo todo lo que es monumental es interesante y curioso; todo tiene un tipo especial,
que no se encuentra en ninguna otra ciudad española con igual energía, aún en Valencia, Sevilla,
Córdoba y Granada. Donde quiera se ven alternando las construcciones góticas y las moriscas,
así como algunas del Renacimiento, resultando de esa promiscuidad los mas curiosos contrastes.--Me
detendré en los mas notables monumentos nomas, que son las joyas de esa ciudad donde corrió
la infancia de Quevedo y yacen los restos del favorito ahorcado Don Alvaro de Luna, del poeta
Moreto y del historiador Mariana.

La catedral es, sin disputa, uno de las mas grandiosos templos católicos de Europa. Todo es
allí gigantesco, severo y sombrío, como las mas típicas catedrales góticas. Si las formas exteriores
y casi todo el conjunto del edificio pertenecen á esa arquitectura majestuosa, hay muchos detalles
sinembargo, como la famosa capilla Muzárabe, que corresponden al estilo morisco, por haber
estado la catedral sujeta á cambiamientos sucesivos. Su espléndido pavimento de baldosas de
mármol blancas y azules; sus cinco naves atrevidas sostenidas por ochenta y cuatro columnas
colosales; sus veintitres capillas cuajadas de oro y ricos ornamentos; sus tres enormes rosetones
y setecientas cuarenta y siete ventanas ogivales ó circulares cubiertas de vidrios primorosos
de colores pintados al fuego; los mil adornos de las columnas y de las setenta y dos bóvedas
de las naves, de una ligereza superior; la magnificencia de las sillerías del coro, cuyos bajos
relieves son admirables; el esplendor de los tesoros ó joyas que pertenecen al templo; los
ecos profundos de los órganos, repitiéndose en mil senos de piedra; la solemne oscuridad del
recinto; los preciosos cuadros de pintura que adornan los sombríos muros; y el hormigueo de
la multitud de piadosos y curiosos, circulando como átomos bajo la estupenda mole: todo eso
hace de la catedral de Toledo, el juéves santo, un monumento que asombra, impone, embelesa
y hace enmudecer....

Allí se comprende todo el poder de la fe, que no solo inspirara á los artistas de la Edad media,
sino que les diera á sus pueblos-obreros la fuerza titánica para levantar esas montañas labradas
de granito y piedra comun, cuajándolas de primores que revelan toda la tenacidad paciente de
una creencia y las extravagancias de la supersticion. Allí se comprende tambien la fuerza de
propaganda que ha tenido el catolicismo en otros tiempos, mediante la poderosa fascinacion
ejercida sobre las muchedumbres por la majestad de los templos y la pompa soberana del culto[2].

Yo comparaba la inmensa riqueza encerrada en el «Tesoro» de la catedral, con la profunda miseria
de las clases inferiores de Toledo, ciudad que vegeta en el aislamiento, sin industria, comercio,
ni agricultura importante, y me decia con tristeza: «¡Qué bien haría la Vírgen de esta catedral
si, imitando á Isabel la Católica, no ya para descubrir un mundo sino para resucitar á Toledo,
destinara sus joyas de valor fabuloso para un ferrocarril que comunicase á esa imperial ruina
con todos los pueblos del magnífico valle del Tajo!» De cada catedral de España, sin contar
mas que los valores de lujo, puede salir un ferrocarril; pero no hay riesgo de que salga nada,
sin que por eso falten las entradas.

Sin contar catorce conventos suprimidos de frailes, y veintitres de monjas, Toledo tiene ademas
de la catedral veinte iglesias parroquiales, nueve capillas públicas y seis muzárabes. Asi,
pues, los habitantes no alcanzan para las iglesias. Despues de la catedral, las mas notables
como monumentos son: San Juan-de-los-Reyes, Cristo-de-la-luz, el Tránsito y Santa María-la-blanca;--las
dos últimas, antiguas sinagogas. Es curioso observar que en Toledo habia durante la dominacion
moruna seis iglesias, llamadas muzárabes, donde los cristianos mantenian públicamente su culto,
con expreso consentimiento de los Moros. Parece que aquellos bárbaros infieles eran amigos
de esa iniquidad de la filosofía moderna que se llama tolerancia religiosa. La Inquisicion
española les pagó mas tarde á los Moros esa tolerancia en muy buena moneda....

Los reyes de España tenian la costumbre piadosa de celebrar sus triunfos militares con la ereccion
de iglesias, ora se tratase de los Sarracenos, ora de los Portugueses ú otros enemigos. A la
victoria de Toro, obtenida contra los de Portugal, debe su existencia la preciosa iglesia de
San Juan-de-los-Reyes, de un gótico florido delicioso, mandada construir en 1476 por Fernando
é Isabel; como se debe al triunfo de Don Alfonso VI, conquistador de Toledo á fines del siglo
XI, la importancia de la curiosísima capilla denominada Cristo-de-la-luz, donde se ofició la
primera misa despues de vencidos allí los Sarracenos. Llaman la atencion en lo exterior de
la iglesia de los Reyes una multitud de grilletes, cadenas y otros instrumentos de prision,
pendientes de los muros para recuerdo de los mártires de España, pues todos esos fierros les
fueron aplicados en Granada á los prisioneros que estuvieron en poder de los Moros.

Si la iglesia, de una sola nave, formando cruz latina, es de suma elegancia y bella ornamentacion,
el claustro no es ménos interesante, apesar de sus escombros, provenientes de un terrible incendio
en 1809. Es curioso un enorme trozo de mosaico excelente que yace casi abandonado en el zaguan.
En el piso alto llama la atencion un museo de cuadros de pintura, comenzado en 1840, compuesto
de 730 cuadros y establecido justamente en la celda del famoso cardenal Jiménez de Cisneros,
primer novicio del convento allí fundado.

Cristo-de-la-luz es una curiosísima miniatura de iglesia, cuyo mérito está no solo en el orígen
y la antigüedad sino tambien en sus proporciones singulares. Mide aquel juguete de mezquita
bautizada unos 18 piés de largo sobre 14 ó 15 de ancho, con la altura proporcionada, y es de
estilo byzantino-arábigo, con tendencias en algunos detalles á la transicion del primer al
segundo período del gracioso arte sarraceno. Seis navecillas cruzadas en opuestas direcciones,
de tres en tres, y sostenidas por cuatro columnitas de granito, muy toscas, en que reposan
arcos en forma de herradura, constituyen la bóveda, que se divide en nueve cúpulas casi microscópicas,
todas diferentes, aunque análogas en su estilo. Si se pudiera arrancar y trasportar con sus
cimientos aquel juguete de arquitectura morisca, podría figurar en el mejor museo de antigüedades
como una joya de inapreciable valor.

La iglesia llamada hoy Santa María-la-blanca, abandonada y desierta, fué una elegante sinagoga,
construida hácia fines del siglo XI por los judíos de Toledo; corresponde á la época de transicion
ó segundo período del estilo árabe; y tiene adornos y formas interiores de un gusto delicioso.
El techo es un precioso artesonado de cedro, y todo el cuerpo está dividido en cinco naves;
siendo el total un cuadrilongo que mide como 80 piés de longitud por unos 62 de anchura y 50
de elevacion en el centro. Sostienen la techumbre 32 columnas octógonas, estucadas, en cuatro
filas iguales, y sobre sus capiteles se alzan 28 arcos en herradura, con bellos arabescos,
los cuales apoyan otros órdenes de columnitas preciosas, pareadas, que soportan inmediatamente
los artesonados. Estas construcciones, que me eran enteramente desconocidas (si no es en fotografías),
tenían á mis ojos un encanto infinito, y me hacian evocar mil recuerdos de la historia de los
pueblos orientales, leidas en los años de mi primera juventud. Bajo el pavimento mismo hay
subterráneos profundos que guardan los restos de muchos israelitas. ¡Cuánto no me hacia meditar
sobre las peripecías de la humanidad el abandono de aquel antiguo santuario de una raza que,
perseguida durante diez y ocho siglos por todos los pueblos en inmensa y atroz gavilla, ha
regenerado al mundo en el siglo XIX, con el poder de sus enormes capitales y su actividad industrial
y comercial, poblando á la Europa de Bancos, ferrocarriles, almacenes y fábricas! Los israelitas
se han vengado de los pueblos perseguidores, dándoles el progreso y la prosperidad y organizando
el crédito....

No ménos curiosa, aunque de proporciones muy distintas, es la otra sinagoga, llamada hoy iglesia
del Tránsito, construida á mediados del siglo XIV. Don Pedro el Cruel no lo era mucho, segun
parece, con los judíos ricos, y le permitió á su famoso tesorero y favorito, Samuel Levi, la
ereccion de aquel bello santuario de la religion israelita. Su única nave sostiene un precioso
artesonado; los muros son de un delicioso estuco, adornados con lindos azulejos en mosaico,
y labrados con los mas primorosos arabescos del tercer período de la arquitectura árabe, completamente
andaluza. Aquella sinagoga se asemeja por muchos de sus pormenores á un espléndido salon de
la Alhambra ó del Alcázar de Sevilla.

Basta de iglesias para el paciente lector. A propósito de Don Pedro el Cruel, es notable por
su interes histórico y sus sombrías proporciones la casa ó palacio que habitara en Toledo aquel
salvaje coronado. Es un edificio informe y pesado, que da la idea de los calabozos y causa
cierto estremecimiento al viajero que conoce algo las viejas historias de la vieja España.
Aparte del admirable escombro del Alcázar, son interesantes en Toledo: algunas de sus puertas
monumentales, que dan acceso á la ciudad por caminos en caracol, sostenidos por estupendos
murallones; el magnífico puente de Alcántara, de un solo arco y todo de granito; y el colegio
militar, edificio que fué convento y en cuya fachada, capilla, claustros y escalera monumental
puede admirar el viajero una multitud de objetos de arte muy interesantes.

Por lo demas Toledo es en su totalidad un inmenso y complicado monumento. Allí todo es curioso
y singular, todo llama la atencion y obliga al extranjero á detenerse á cada paso. En cada
calle, en cada esquina, en cada portal ó muro, balcon ó ventana, se ve algun objeto precioso
para el anticuario, sorprendente para el viajero que por primera vez recorre una ciudad tan
especial como aquella. Aquí se da con un trozo de mosaico precioso, una bella baldosa de mármol,
un busto raro de piedra ó una inscripcion histórica; allá con una ventana ogival, un balcon
morisco, un curioso mirador, un torreon gótico ó un escombro lamentable. Toledo es el cementerio
magnifico de dos civilizaciones, de dos razas; cada edificio es una tumba y cada puerta ó muro
contiene un epitafio....

Apresurémonos á hablar rápidamente de esa maravilla pretérita que se llama el Alcázar, para
acabar con lo monumental y mostrar al lector algunos rasgos de la fisonomía social de Toledo.
Esa admirable ruina está situada al lado oriental de la ciudad, sobre una eminencia, dominando
al mismo tiempo á Toledo y las profundidades del Tajo. Los cimientos y diferentes cuerpos y
fachadas del Alcázar datan de épocas muy distintas. Fundada en el mismo sitio una fortaleza
romana, despues goda y en seguida árabe, el conquistador de Toledo, Alfonso VI, varias veces
mencionado, le dió mas grandiosas formas, haciendo gobernador del castillo nada ménos que al
heróico Cid campeador. Muchos reyes mejoraron sucesivamente el famoso fuerte, hasta que Cárlos
V resolvió demolerlo en casi todas sus construcciones superiores, conservando solo una fachada
gótica, los sótanos y los formidables cimientos. Felipe II terminó la obra, invirtiéndose en
ella los cincuenta años trascurridos de 1534 á 1584, y trabajando allí los mas eminentes artistas,
como Villalpando, Covarrubias y Juan de Herrera. En 1710 fue incendiado el admirable palacio-fortaleza
por las tropas aliadas que luchaban contra Felipe V en la guerra de sucesion. Restaurado con
esmero, incendiáronlo á su turno en 1810 las tropas francesas invasoras, dejándolo reducido
á un sublime escombro. Hoy no quedan sino los muros interiores y exteriores, los torreones
rotos, las cuatro espléndidas fachadas, los sótanos y cimientos; sin techumbres ningunas, despedazados
los arcos que ligaban los muros, vacíos los huecos de los balcones y todo en ruina.

!Pero qué ruinas! Aquello es imponente y grandioso como una montaña desnuda, de indestructible
granito y de ladrillo durísimo. Al vagar en medio de aquellas masas colosales, por esas enormes
escaleras de piedra, sobre tantas bóvedas de inaudita fuerza y audacia singular, y en los oscuros
abismos de los inmensos subterráneos (que en un tiempo abrigaron regimientos enteros de infantería
y caballería), se siente uno poseido de un respeto profundo por el genio de los artífices,
y adquiere, interrogando los ecos de esas formidables obras, la idea completa de una civilizacion
terrible, fundada en la fuerza y el antagonismo artificial, de cuyo seno ha nacido, por uno
de esos prodigios del divino misterio del progreso, la nueva civilizacion que tiene su solo
principio en la libertad y la justicia.

El Alcázar es un cuadrado de 200 piés por lado, que presenta cuatro fachadas diferentes, espléndidas,
que no obstante cierta armonía general corresponden á diversos estilos de arquitectura, predominando
el del Renacimiento. Una de las fachadas, la mas antigua, es gótica por su carácter general,
aunque por sus detalles, posteriores, es del mismo Renacimiento. Cuatro torreones gigantescos,
en los ángulos, encuadran el edificio, dándole aspectos diferentes segun el lado por donde
se le contempla. Se compone de tres cuerpos ó pisos, sin contar el de los sótanos, que se ve
por un lado. El interior es de una esplendidez que arrebata, á pesar de su estado ruinoso.
Los estupendos sótanos, de aquel palacio-fortaleza podian contener millares de soldados, de
prisioneros y caballos, los víveres, y municiones y armas en grande escala; en fin, toda una
fuerte guarnicion ó pequeño ejército, capaz de resistir por largo tiempo el asedio. Un inmenso
subterráneo conducia desde el fondo de aquella montaña artificial hasta la márgen muy lejana
del Tajo, á una gran profundidad, para poder dar de beber á las caballerías, coger agua del
rio, etc., etc. Tal era de grandioso el sistema de arquitectura de la vieja España, que ha
dejado en todas partes los mas soberbios monumentos.

       *       *       *       *       *

Nada mas curioso que el espectáculo de las plazuelas y callejuelas de Toledo, durante la procesion
del juéves santo. Aunque naturalmente se escogen para el paso del Cristo y de la Vírgen las
calles ménos imposibles, el acompañamiento eclesiástico y popular tiene que pasar por las mas
grandes crujidas para hallar salida por aquellos pendientes y endemoniados pasadizos al aire
libre. Todo el mundo se estrecha, se codea, se pone en prensa y estrangula, resultando de la
confusion y los apuros los mas curiosos contrastes en los mil grupos que se agitan entre aquellos
desfiladeros. El lujo suntuoso de la gran dama madrileña ó toledaña, cubierta de terciopelos,
de ricos encajes y de joyas, tiene que frotarse allí contra la capa raida de paño ya pelado,
un tiempo carmelita claro y luego de un amarillo mugriento inescrutable, que es el ornamento
indispensable del toledano,--obrero, tratante ó mendigo, así como del manchego y todos los
habitantes de las dos Castillas.

En Toledo faltan absolutamente en las clases inferiores esos atavíos pintorescos, de colores
vivos y cortes caprichosos, que se ven en Valencia, en Sevilla y otras poblaciones ménos impregnadas
de los usos castellanos. En Toledo todo es triste, y el hombre de alguna comodidad, como el
menestral y el mendigo, tienen todos un aire de vetustez, de tristeza, de ruina y de miseria
que los hace sombríos á los ojos del viajero. Cuando vagaba yo en medio del largo y complicado
tumulto de la procesion, arrebatado en todas direcciones por una onda de capas amarillentas
y mantillas negras, me parecia asistir á un carnaval de la muerte. Sobre mi cabeza, á uno y
otro lado, veia los bajos balcones repletos de mujeres y niños, con aire de aplastar á los
transeuntes cayendo como enormes racimos; miéntras que el aspecto de las calles y la movilidad
de los sombríos grupos tenian no sé qué semejanza con las menudas olas y los grupos de rocas
negras, en el seno de un arrecife, agitándose desordenadamente en un dia de borrasca.

Las bandas de mendigos pululan y circulan allí por todas partes, asediando al extranjero sin
tregua. Rendido de luchar con las masas movientes en la procesion, fuí á sentarme en un banco
de piedra, á la sombra de algunos árboles en la plaza principal, llamada del Horno de Bizcochos.
Tenia sed y compré unas naranjas. Cayéronme al punto, en gavilla cerrada, siete ú ocho muchachos
hambrientos, de los mas cercanos, pidiéndome cada cual una naranja, ó un chavito, como llaman
los mendigos la moneda de cobre denominada ochavo. Alejáronse contentos al recibir algunas
monedas, y yo creia quedar en libertad para comer tranquilamente mis naranjas. Pero en breve
arremetieron de nuevo, en mayor número, á disputarse las cortezas que yo arrojaba al suelo;
y hube de ponerme en salvo para no claudicar entre aquella vorágine de mendigos impúberes.
No les bastaron las monedas y las naranjas, pues en un instante se tragaron todas las cortezas,
como si fueran pedazos de pan!

Aquella escena me afectó profundamente, tanto mas cuanto que sabia que tal ejemplo de miseria
no era una excepcion. Toledo, por mucho que se haga, no saldrá de la miseria. Es un escombro
que no tendrá resurreccion sino á virtud de esfuerzos inauditos. Siendo la metrópoli eclesiástica
del país (donde los canónigos son muy dichosos) y teniendo un gran colegio militar y una guarnicion,
admirables monumentos y carencia absoluta de industria, Toledo es un conjunto de cuatro tipos
principales que se revelan en cuatro vestidos diferentes: la sotana del clérigo, el uniforme
de vueltas amarillas y rojas del militar, el elegante paltó del extranjero curioso, y la capa
raida y nauseabunda del mendigo. Fundada con un destino militar, segun las ideas de otra civilizacion,--para
ser una fortaleza--el aislamiento es la condicion de Toledo. No puede tener industria, porque
carece de agua para mover máquinas, no habiendo sino aljibes ó cisternas; ni tiene elementos
para el comercio y la agricultura, por su posicion excepcional. Toledo, pues, seguirá siendo
una ruina sublime, una estupenda curiosidad y nada mas: el museo de la vieja España, custodiado
por clérigos, militares y mendigos!...

Toledo me ofreció la ocasin de poner á prueba mi estómago y verificar la reputacion (usurpada
la una y legítima la otra) de la olla podrida y el vino de Valdepeñas. Durante los tres dias
que pasé en la imperial Toledo, tan magníficamente cantada por Zorrilla, me vi forzado á renunciar
á la carne, recibiendo la ley de la situacion. Pero como no habia pescado, ni huevos, ni leche,
quedé á discreción de los garbanzos cocidos y otras iniquidades de la cocina española, neutralizando
algo mi desdicha con buenos tragos de un exquisito Valdepeñas. Este, sinembargo, tenia el atrevimiento
de subírseme á la cabeza, sin la menor ceremonia, obligándome á multiplicar los brebajes de
café. Tuvo al fin piedad de mí la posadera y me mandó servir puchero.--«Un puchero español!
me dije con trasporte; vamos, esto será mejor que la Catedral y el Alcázar.»

!Mentirosa ilusion! Yo habia hecho ya algunas experiencias poco satisfactorias en Barcelona
y Valencia, respecto de la olla podrida, y la habia encontrado tan sofística como la monarquía
constitucional en España. En Toledo se acabó la ilusion; el puchero legitimo terminó su mision
sobre la tierra española; hoy pertenece á la historia, como la antigua grandeza del pueblo
conquistador del Nuevo Mundo. Hoy no quedan de las glorias del puchero sino los innobles garbanzos
cocidos, capaces de indigestar á un elefante, el vil chorizo y el desvergonzado tocino, que
ha perdido su importancia desde que los moros y judíos han aceptado las impiedades de la cocina
y la bodega cristianas. Desengañado y hambriento, hube de consagrar en Toledo todo mi culto
gastronómico á las ricas naranjas valencianas y el atrevido Valdepeñas.

Apesar de algunas impresiones desagradables, Toledo me habia complacido mucho por sus enseñanzas
de carácter social, no ménos que por sus monumentos. Habia podido comparar la vieja España,
representada en Toledo, con la España regenerada y progresista, revelada en Barcelona y Madrid:--la
primera basada en el aislamiento, inmóbil, indolente, rezandera en demasía, miserable y mendicante:
la segunda buscando el progreso en la libertad y el movimiento, despreocupada, tolerante y
pensando seriamente en lo porvenir. Me despedí de Toledo como el que acaba de visitar un sepulcro
y sale del cementerio á pasos largos, volviendo á mirar hácia atras de tiempo en tiempo, con
un sentimiento mezclado de tristeza y esperanza....

       *       *       *       *       *

CAPITULO V.

       *       *       *       *       *

LA MANCHA.

Dos compañeros de viaje.--Aspecto del pais.--Recuerdos de Don Quijote.--Las poblaciones manchegas,--La
Sierra-Morena.
</sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document03439</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>231205</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>20231</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> 

       * * * * *

No, but having spent three days in Toledo, which are sufficient for a traveler who is not artist,
I could barely pick up fast printing. Toledo is interesting for its social type and their merit
monumental, but the first I cared more than the second, more especially as suffer from complete
ignorance in architecture, painting and sculpture. As I can hardly make judgments, failing to
copy what others (art ugly I'm less versed even in fine arts), and
will indicate only the emotions felt.

Toledo lacks any industry. It's a dead city, or at least paralyzed. The there only draws attention
to the economic is the famous weapons factory, situated at the right bank of the Tagus, to
the west of the isthmus that I have described. I found it impossible to visit, because in
those days it was closed because of Easter, which the Spanish people and its analogs celebrated
with idleness. HOWEVER I knew that the weapons were Toledo the very same conditions as those
of ancient times. Centuries have passed over without The makers have been given by notified today
as manufacturing procedures are the same as now four years, unless the products have improved significantly.
Spain crushed the old steel with the same hammer. Modern civilization has not reached until
the railway station at the foot of Toledo.

From up there .... Careful touch the cobwebs!

In Toledo's monumental everything is interesting and curious all have a special type not found
in any other Spanish city with the same energy, even in Valencia, Sevilla, Cordoba and Granada. Wherever
they are alternating the Gothic and Moorish and some of the Renaissance, such promiscuity resulting
from the most striking contrasts .-- Me dwell on the most remarkable monuments nomas, which are
the jewels of the city where he ran Quevedo's childhood and the remains
of the hanged favorite Don Alvaro de Luna, the poet Mariana Moreto
and historian.

The cathedral is, without doubt, one of the most magnificent Catholic churches in Europe. Everything
is there huge, stern and grim, as the most typical Gothic cathedrals. If the external forms
and almost the whole of the building belong to the magnificent architecture, there are many
details However, as a famous Mozarabic chapel, under the Moorish style, having Cathedral been
subject to successive cambiamientos. Its splendid floor tiles blue and white marble, its five ships
daring held by eighty-four columns colossal twenty-three chapels curds and rich gold ornaments,
three large rosettes and seven hundred forty-seven circular or ogival windows covered with exquisite
glass colorfully painted to fire a thousand ornaments of columns and arches seventy-two of the
ships, superior lightness, the magnificence of the choir stalls, whose low reliefs are admirable,
the splendor of the treasures or jewels belonging to the temple, the deep echoes of the organs,
repeated in a thousand breasts of stone, the dark solemn enclosure, the paint beautiful paintings
that adorn the dark walls, and tingling the crowd of pious and curious, circulating as atoms
under the great mass: all that makes the Cathedral of Toledo, Maundy Thursday, an astounding
monument, places, captivates and makes mute ....

There he understands
the power of faith, which not only inspire the artists of the Middle
Ages but give them to their villages, workers Herculean strength to
lift those mountains carved common granite and stone, studded charms
that reveal all the tenacity patient a belief and the vagaries of
superstition.

There is also the force comprises propaganda that Catholicism has had in the past, through the powerful
fascination exerted on the masses by the majesty of the temples and the sovereign pomp of the cult
[2].

I compared the immense wealth locked in the "Treasury" of the cathedral, with the deep misery
of the lower classes of Toledo, a city that grows in isolation, without
industry, trade, agriculture and important, and sadly told me: "What
good would the Virgin of the Cathedral if, in imitation of Isabel
the Catholic, not to discover a world but to resurrect Toledo devote
their valuable jewelry great for a railroad to communicate to the
imperial ruin with all peoples of the magnificent Tagus Valley!

"In every cathedral in Spain, excluding values ??more than the estate, can go a railroad, but there
is no risk of anything coming out, without thereby missing entries.

Fourteen without suppressed convents of friars, nuns and twenty, Toledo has also twenty churches
of the cathedral parish, nine public and six Mozarabic chapel. Thus, So people do not reach for
the churches. After the cathedral, the most notable as monuments are: San Juan-de-los-Reyes,
Christ-of-the-light, Transit and Santa María la white, - the last two ancient synagogues. It is
interesting to note that Toledo had during the domination Moorish
six churches, called Mozarabic, where Christians worship publicly
maintained them, with the express consent of the Moros.

It seems that those barbarous infidels were friends of the wickedness of modern philosophy called
for religious tolerance. The Inquisition Spanish later paid them to the Moors that tolerance
in very good money ....

The kings of Spain had the pious custom of celebrating military triumphs erection of churches,
now they were the Saracens, now in the Portuguese or other enemies. In Toro victory obtained against
Portugal, owes its existence to the beautiful church San Juan-de-los-Reyes, a florid Gothic
delicious, commissioned in 1476 by Fernando and Isabella, as it should be the triumph of Don
Alfonso VI, the conqueror of Toledo in the late XI, the importance
of curious chapel called Christ-of-the-light, where they performed
the first mass after the Saracens defeated there.

Call attention in foreign Kings Church a multitude of shackles, chains and other instruments in prison,
slopes of the walls to remember the martyrs of Spain, for all those irons are Granada were applied
to prisoners who were held by the Moors.

If the church, a nave, forming a Latin cross, is very elegant and beautiful ornaments, the faculty
is no less interesting, in spite of its debris, from a terrible fire in 1809. Curiously a huge
piece of excellent mosaic that lies almost abandoned in the vestibule. In the upper floor
was struck by a museum painting paintings, begun in 1840, made than 730 tables and set exactly
in the cell of the famous Cardinal Jiménez de Cisneros, first novice of the convent founded
there.

Christ-of-the-light is a curious miniature church, whose merit lies not only in the origin and seniority
but also on their unique proportions. Measures that toy mosque baptized about 18 feet long on 14
or 15 wide, with proportionate height, and is Byzantine-Arab style, with trends in some detail
the transition from first to funny second period of Saracen art. Six little ships crossed in
opposite directions threes, and supported by four granite columns,
very rough, which lie horseshoe-shaped arches, constitute the roof,
which is divided into nine domes almost microscopic all different,
but similar in style.

If you could start and transporting their foundations that toy of Moorish architecture, could be
in the best museum of antiquities like a jewel of inestimable value.

The church now called Santa Maria la Blanca, abandoned and deserted, was an elegant synagogue
built towards the end of XI century by the Jews of Toledo, corresponding to the time of transition
or second period of the Moorish style, and has interior decorations and forms a delicious
treat. The roof is a beautiful cedar paneling, and the whole body is divided into five naves; the total
being a rectangle that measures about 80 feet long and about 62 wide and 50 elevation in the
center. 32 columns holding the octagonal roof, stucco, four equal rows, and their capitals rise 28
horseshoe arches with beautiful arabesques which support orders other
precious columns, paired immediately supporting the ceilings.

These buildings, which were entirely unknown to me (if not in photo) my eyes were endless charm,
and made me conjure up a thousand memories of the history of Oriental peoples, defended in the years
of my youth. Under the same floor there deep underground that keep the remains of many Israelis.
How not to think me on the vicissitudes of humanity to abandon this ancient sanctuary of a
race that persecuted for eighteen centuries by all peoples in vast and heinous gang has regenerate
the world in the nineteenth century, with the power of their enormous capital and industrial
activity and commercial town on the European banks, railways, warehouses and factories! The
Israelites have retaliated by chasing people, giving them the progress and prosperity and organizing
credit ....

No less curious, though very different proportions, is the other synagogue, now called Church
Traffic built in the middle of the fourteenth century. Don Pedro the Cruel was not much, according
to seems, with the rich Jews, and allowed his famous and favorite treasurer, Samuel Levi, erection
of this beautiful sanctuary of the Israelite religion. His only holds a beautiful ship coffered
ceiling, the walls are a rich stucco, adorned with beautiful mosaic tiles, and carved with the most
gorgeous arabesques of the third period of Moorish architecture, completely Andalusia. Synagogue
that resembles many of its details to a splendid hall the Alhambra or the Alcazar of Seville.

Enough of churches for the patient reader. About Don Pedro the Cruel, is notable for its historical
interest and its grim proportions the house or palace that dwell in Toledo Wild crowned. It
is a report building and heavy, which gives the idea of ??dungeons and causes certain thrill
to the traveler who knows something the old stories of old Spain. Apart from the rubble of the
Alcázar admirable, are interesting in Toledo some of their doors monuments, which give access
to the city roads in shell, supported by great embankments, the magnificent bridge of Alcantara, a single
arc and all of granite and school military was building façade convent and chapel, cloisters
and staircase can admire the traveler a multitude of interesting
art objects.

For the rest Toledo is entirely a huge and complicated monument. Here everything is funny and
unique attention and all foreign forces to stop at every step. In each street, every corner,
every doorway or wall, balcony or window, you see some precious object to the antiquarian, surprising
for the traveler who goes first as a city special like that. Here there is a beautiful mosaic
piece, a beautiful marble tile, a rare bust of stone or a historical inscription; there with
ogival window, a balcony Moorish, an unusual viewpoint, a Gothic turret or a lamentable debris.
Toledo is the cemetery magnificent two civilizations, two races,
each building is a tomb and each door or wall contains an epitaph
....

We hasten to speak of that wonderful bygone quickly called the
Fortress, for end with the monumental and show the reader some features
of the social physiognomy of Toledo.

This remarkable ruin is situated on the eastern side of the city on a hill overlooking while the
depths to Toledo and the Tagus. The foundations and different bodies and Alcazar facades dating
from very different eras. Founded in the same place a fortress Roman, Gothic and immediately
after Arabic, the conqueror of Toledo, Alfonso VI, several times mentioned, gave more great
ways, governor of the castle doing nothing less than the Cid heroic. Many kings improved on the
famous fortress, until Charles V decided to demolish almost all buildings over, keeping only
a facade Gothic cellars and formidable foundation. Felipe II finished the work, invested in her
fifty years that have passed from 1534 to 1584, and worked there the most eminent artists as Villalpando,
Covarrubias and Juan de Herrera.

In 1710 was burnt the palace-fortress admirable by Allied troops who fought against Philip
V in the war of succession. Restored care, incendiáronlo his turn in 1810 the invading French
troops, leaving small to a sublime debris. Today there are but the interior and exterior walls,
the towers broken, the four splendid facades, basements and foundations, no no roofs, torn
arcs that bound the walls, empty holes of the balconies and all in ruin.

! But what a ruin! That is impressive and grand as a mountain naked, indestructible granite and
brick hard. To wander in the midst of these colossal masses, for those big stone steps on many
vaults of unprecedented strength and singular audacity, and in the dark depths of the vast underground
(which once harbored entire infantry regiments and cavalry), one feels possessed of a deep respect
for the genius of the architects, and acquires, questioning the echoes of these formidable works,
the whole idea of ??a civilization terrible, founded on force and artificial antagonism, from whose womb
was born, for a of these wonders of the divine mystery of progress, the new civilization that
has its only principle of freedom and justice.

The Alcazar is a 200 square feet per side, which has four different facades, magnificent, that despite
some general harmony correspond to different styles of architecture
dominate the Renaissance.

One of the facades, the oldest, is Gothic in its general character, although its details later,
is of the Renaissance. Four massive towers, at the corners, frame the building, giving different
aspects according to the side where it provides. It consists of three parts or floors, excluding
the basement, which is on one side. The interior is sumptuously snatching, in spite of its ruinous
state. The Super Cellars palace-fortress that could contain thousands of soldiers, prisoners
and horses, food, and ammunition and weapons on a large scale, in short, a whole small army garrison
or strong, can withstand long siege. A huge subway leading from the bottom of this artificial
mountain to the very distant margin the Tagus, to a great depth, to give drink to the horses,
take water river, etc.., etc. This was great about the system architecture
of old Spain, which has left everywhere the most superb monuments.

* * * * *

Nothing more interesting than the spectacle of the plazas and streets of Toledo during the
procession Holy Thursday. Of course it chose for the passage of Christ and the Virgin streets
less impossible, the ecclesiastical and popular support has to go through the most large cracks
to find a way out for those possessed outstanding and air passages free. Everyone is close,
rubs, put in the press and choke, resulting from confusion and distress the most striking contrasts
in the thousand groups that move among those gorges. The sumptuous luxury of the great lady from
Madrid or Toledo, covered in velvet, of rich lace and jewels, there has to rub against the RAID
layer of cloth and peeled time light brown and grimy after a yellow inscrutable, which is the
ornament Toledo indispensable, - worker, treating or beggar, and the manchego and all inhabitants
of Castile.

       

In Toledo absolutely missing in the lower classes these colorful costumes, colors Live and whimsical
cuts, which are in Valencia, Seville and other cities less impregnated Castilian applications.
In Toledo everything is sad, and a man of some comfort, as artisan and the Pauper, all have an
air of antiquity, sorrow, ruin and misery The dark makes the eyes of travelers. When I wandered
through the long and complicated tumult of the procession, carried away in all directions by
a yellowish layer wave blankets and black, seemed to me to attend a carnival of death. Over my head,
at one and On the other hand, saw the low balconies full of women and children, looking to crush
the pedestrians falling like huge clusters, while the appearance of the streets and mobility
of shadowy groups had no resemblance to know what the tiny waves and rock groups black within
a reef, waving wildly in a storm day.

The bands of beggars swarm and travel there everywhere, besieging the country without truce.
Surrendered to fight with the masses movent in the procession, I sat on a bench stone in the shade of
some trees in the main square, called Oven Biscuits. Was thirsty and bought some oranges. Cayéronme
point in sheaf closed, seven or eight guys hungry, the closest, asking each one an orange, or
a little kid, as they call beggars copper coins called farthing. Alejáronse happy to receive some
coins, and I thought his release quietly eating my oranges. But in brief attacked again in
greater numbers, to contest the bark that I threw to the ground; and I had to get in except
that no halt between prepubertal maelstrom of beggars. They are not enough coins and oranges,
because in a moment swallowed all bark like pieces of bread!

That scene affected me deeply, especially since I knew that this example
of misery was no exception.

Toledo, however much they do not come out of poverty. It is a rubble will not resurrection but
to under extraordinary efforts. Being the mother church the country (where the canons are very
happy) and having a great school and a military garrison wonderful sights and a total lack of industry,
Toledo is a set of four main revealed in four different dresses: the cassock of the priest, the
uniform of turns yellow and red military, odd overseas elegant avocado, and layer ratty beggar's
sickening. Founded with a military target, according to the ideas of another civilization,
- to be a strength - the isolation is the condition of Toledo. You can not have industry because
no water to move machines, but having no tanks or tanks, nor has elements for trade and agriculture,
for its exceptional position. Toledo, then, will remain sublime ruin, a great curiosity and
nothing more: the museum of old Spain, guarded by clerics, soldiers and beggars! ...

Toledo offered me the occasion to test my stomach and check the reputation (usurped legitimate
one and another) of the pot and wine rotten Valdepeñas. During the three days I spent in the
imperial Toledo, so beautifully sung by Zorrilla, I was forced to resign the flesh, receiving the
law from the situation. But as there was no fish, no eggs, no milk, is at the discretion of the cooked
chickpeas and other iniquities of Spanish cuisine, neutralizing something my misfortune with
good shots of an exquisite Valdepeñas. This, HOWEVER, had the audacity of subírseme at the head,
without ceremony, forcing me to multiply the brews coffee. Finally had mercy on me and sent me
the hostess serving pot .-- "A Spanish stew! I said with transportation, let this be better than the Cathedral
and the Alcazar. "

! Mentirosa illusion! I had already made some unsatisfactory experiences in Barcelona and Valencia,
on the rotten pot, and had found such sophistry as the monarchy Spain constitutional. In Toledo,
the illusion is over, the pot legitimate completed his mission on
Spanish soil, now belongs to history as the former greatness of the
people conqueror of the New World.

Today there are the glories of the ignoble but chickpea stew cooked, capable of indigestible
an elephant, the vile and shameless pork sausage, which has lost its importance since the Moors
and Jews have accepted the wickedness of the kitchen and Christian cellar. Disappointed and hungry,
I had to devote all my worship in Toledo Dining Valencia oranges to rich and bold Valdepeñas.

Despite some unpleasant impressions, Toledo had pleased me much by his teaching social, no less than its
monuments. Had been able to compare the old Spain represented in Toledo, with Spain and progressive
regenerated revealed in Barcelona and Madrid - the first based on the isolation, motionless,
sluggish, too much prayer leader, miserable and begging: the second
looking for progress in freedom and movement, carefree, tolerant and
thinking seriously about the future.

I said goodbye to Toledo as the one just visited a grave and out of the cemetery to long strides
back to look back from time to time, mixed feelings of sadness and hope ....

* * * * *

CHAPTER V.

* * * * *

LA MANCHA.

Two traveling companions aspects of the country .-- .-- .-- Memories of Don Quixote of La Mancha populations
- The Sierra Morena.</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>