<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info>
<sourceIDDoc>source-document05089</sourceIDDoc>
<sourceTextLanguage>es</sourceTextLanguage>
<sourceTextOffset>146579</sourceTextOffset>
<sourceTextLength>19476</sourceTextLength>
<sourceTextContent> Nuestro pueblo estaba
gobernado por los emperadores, que se creían el centro del mundo y de una materia divina distinta
á la de los otros seres. La vida de la nación se concentraba en la persona del soberano. Los
más altos personajes saltaban sobre la maroma y hacían otros ejercicios acrobáticos para divertir
al monarca del Imperio, que entonces se llamaba Liliput. La gran ambición de todo liliputiense
era conseguir algún hilo de color de los que regalaba el déspota para cruzárselo sobre el pecho
á guisa de condecoración. En resumen: mi país vivía sometido á una autoridad paternal pero
arbitraria, y los hombres llevaban una existencia monótona y soñolienta, al margen de todo
progreso. De las mujeres de entonces no hablemos. Eran esclavas, con una servidumbre hipócrita
disimulada por el cariño egoísta del esposo y la falsa dulzura del hogar.

Así era el Imperio de Liliput, cuando siglo y medio después de la llegada del primer Hombre
Montaña se inició la serie de acontecimientos históricos que acabaron por cambiar su fisonomía.

Un náufrago gigante que había pasado algún tiempo entre nosotros tuvo ocasión de volver á su
tierra natal valiéndose de un bote en armonía con su talla que la marea arrastró hasta nuestras
costas.

Al emprender su viaje de regreso no iba solo. Un liliputiense se marchó también; unos dicen
que de acuerdo con el gigante; otros, y son los más, suponen que se escondió en la enorme barca
con el deseo de conocer el mundo de los Hombres-Montañas.

Este viajero extraordinario es célebre en nuestra historia. Su nombre fué Eulame. Yo tengo
compañeros en la Universidad que suponen que Eulame era una mujer, pues no pueden explicarse
de otro modo tanta inteligencia y tanto heroísmo reunidos en una sola persona. Han escrito
varios libros para probar que Eulame fingió ser hombre porque en aquellos tiempos sólo dominaban
los hombres, y casi lo demuestran plenamente. Pero yo nunca me he apasionado por este misterio
de nuestra historia. Bien puede Enlame haber sido hombre, como creyeron los de su época. Una
excepción no altera la regla, y reconozco que el débil sexo masculino es capaz de producir
de tarde en tarde algún personaje célebre, sin que esto le saque de su inferioridad....

Digo que Eulame se marchó al país de los gigantes y permaneció allá algunos años. También este
período de su existencia ha dado lugar á muchos estudios históricos y críticos. Unos dicen
que anduvo por aquel mundo monstruosamente grande, de feria en feria, siendo exhibido en circos
y barracas como una curiosidad nunca vista, y que sus viajes le sirvieron para conocer los
diversos pueblos en que se hallan divididos los colosos.

Otros autores afirman, basándose en el testimonio de personas que trataron á Enlame y pudieron
oir sus confidencias, que el audaz liliputiense apenas fué conocido por la generalidad de los
gigantes. Él y el marinero en cuyo bote se escapó fueron recogidos por un gran barco, y, al
llegar á la tierra donde todo es monstruosamente enorme, los navegantes lo vendieron á un sabio,
y con él vivió, en el ambiente de una soledad estudiosa, aprendiendo con rápidas síntesis todo
lo que el ilustre gigante había buscado en los libros y en las experiencias de laboratorio
durante muchos años.

Tampoco en esta cuestión me decido ni por unos ni por otros. En realidad, no se sabe nada sobre
el primer período de la vida de Eulame, que fué tan misterioso como la juventud de muchos fundadores
de religiones. Todo lo que dicen mis compañeros de Universidad y lo que dijeron igualmente
muchos sabios anteriores está fundado en hipótesis.

Lo único cierto es que Eulame volvió á Liliput, pero no en una simple barca, como la que le
trajo á usted, Gentleman-Montaña. Al otro lado de la gran barrera de rocas y espumas levantada
por nuestros dioses quedó, según cuentan los cronistas de aquella época, un buque de proporciones
inmensas, un verdadero navío de gigantes. Un simple bote salvó el obstáculo de la muralla divina,
trayendo hasta nuestras costas á Eulame y á un Hombre-Montaña viejo, seco de cuerpo, con barba
blanca, que supongo debió ser su estudioso protector.

Éste tenía el propósito de ir trayendo en la lancha hasta nuestra tierra todos los inventos
de su mundo, de que venía repleto el navío enorme; pero nuestros dioses, como aman poco á los
gigantes, agitaron el mar sin límites con una furiosa tempestad, y el buque se estrelló contra
la barrera de rocas y de espumas.

Quedó entre nosotros el gigante viejo tan desamparado y falto de medios cual se ve usted ahora.
Además, como sus años no le permitían vivir en un mundo tan nuevo para él y tan falto de las
comodidades que necesita la vejez, murió al poco tiempo. Yo sospecho que los emperadores de
la última dinastía se sintieron inquietos tal vez por la frecuencia con que llegaban á nuestras
costas huéspedes de la misma talla, y trataron al viejo con brusquedad, sin considerar que
el pobre venía atraído por los relatos de Eulame para establecer generosamente su civilización
entre nosotros.

Su cadáver dió poco trabajo para ser anulado. Era un esqueleto recubierto de piel nada más,
y sus huesos se emplearon como ricos materiales en numerosas obras de arte. Todavía conservamos
en la Universidad varios libros de él, que me sirvieron muchísimo para el estudio de la lengua
que usted habla y para el conocimiento de las costumbres de los Hombres-Montañas.

Pero volvamos á Eulame. Al verse solo, se lanzó á predicar entre sus compatriotas las ventajas
de la civilización de los gigantes. Los descontentos del Imperio, que eran muchos, vieron en
él un jefe que podía sustituir á la dinastía reinante. Los sabios le escucharon como un maestro
divino, y todas las universidades fueron declarándose discípulas suyas. De entonces data la
introducción del inglés en este país como idioma secreto y sagrado, que sirvió para entenderse
á las personas de clase superior.

¡Las cosas que hizo Eulame en poco tiempo! Jamás se conoció en nuestra historia una actividad
como la suya. El pueblo no pudo creer que fuese un hombre igual á los demás, y le tuvo por
hijo de los dioses. Hasta la industria del país la modificó radicalmente en pocos meses. Implantó
entre nosotros todos los progresos mecánicos que había visto en el mundo de los colosos. Nuestros
ingenieros, que hasta entonces habían marchado á ciegas, moviéndose siempre dentro del mismo
círculo, luego de escuchar las lecciones de Eulame vieron nuevos caminos abiertos ante sus
ojos, y se lanzaron por ellos, haciendo descubrimientos con una rapidez vertiginosa, inventando
casi instantáneamente lo que había costado tal vez largos años de meditación en el país de
los gigantes.

El último emperador intentó asesinar al profeta; pero éste poseía la fuerza, y creyó llegado
el momento de pasar de las palabras á la acción. Había traído del otro mundo los explosivos
y las armas de fuego. Los ricos industriales partidarios del eulamelismo fabricaron secretamente
un material de guerra igual al de los Hombres-Montañas, y bastó que mil discípulos con fusiles
y cañones marchasen contra el palacio del emperador para que éste huyese, acabando en un momento
la dinastía secular.

Las viejas tropas, armadas con arcos y lanzas, se desbandaron, dando vivas á Eulame, al recibir
la primera granizada de balas de sus partidarios. El Regenerador fué elevado entonces á la
dignidad imperial, y empezó el período más agitado, más sangriento é interesante de nuestra
historia.

Debo advertir que como entonces dirigían los hombres la marcha del país, tuvieron el cinismo
de dar el nombre de época gloriosa á un período en el que murieron millones de personas, siendo
además incendiadas muchas ciudades, que aún no están reconstruidas, y devastadas provincias
enteras.

Al verse Eulame en el poder, se creyó investido de una misión sobrehumana.

Esta misión consistía en llevar á todas las naciones próximas pobladas por seres de nuestra
especie los beneficios de la civilización implantada por él. Además, como disponía de una fuerza
superior, necesitaba usarla, lo mismo que el atleta, incapaz de vivir tranquilamente sin dar
golpes contra algo para ejercitar sus músculos.

Las tropas irresistibles de Eulame marcharon contra Blefuscú, el pueblo que durante siglos
había sido nuestro adversario. Resultó una guerra fácil por la gran desigualdad entre los respectivos
armamentos; pero los de Blefuscú se defendieron con esa tenacidad irracional que la Historia
llama heroísmo, dejándose matar en cantidades enormes.

Después de haber dominado á esta nación, el conquistador llevó sus armas á otra, y luego á
otra, no quedando continente ni isla que dejase de reconocer su autoridad imperial. Pero la
misma grandeza de su éxito pesó sobre él, acabando por aplastarle. Sus generales obedecieron
á esa ley de los hombres según la cual todo discípulo, cuando se ve en lo alto, debe atacar
á su maestro.

Llegó un día en que los belicosos caudillos que gobernaban por delegación las tierras conquistadas
se sublevaron contra Eulame. Todo lo que éste había aprendido en el país de los gigantes lo
comunicó confiadamente á sus allegados: los nuevos medios de destrucción eran ya del dominio
común; sus adversarios sabían lo mismo que él; ya no era un semidiós, era un hombre como los
otros. Y como sus enemigos resultaban mucho más numerosos, le vencieron en una batalla campal
á las puertas de esta ciudad, que entonces se llamaba Mildendo, reuniéndose después en congreso
diplomático para decidir su futura suerte.

No se atrevieron á matarle porque habían sido sus discípulos; pero como deseaban verse libres
de su presencia, lo confinaron perpetuamente en una pequeña isla, en un peñón solitario y malsano,
lejos de toda vida, en las inmediaciones de la muralla de rocas y espumas que muy pocos osan pasar.

El emperador murió á los pocos años en este destierro de un modo obscuro. Aún vivían las familias
de los catorce ó quince millones de seres que habían muerto á causa de sus guerras y sus ambiciones.
Luego, con el transcurso de los años, el vulgo, que necesita para vivir el culto de los héroes
y cuando no los tiene los inventa, ha glorificado á Eulame, convirtiendo sus matanzas en hazañas
gloriosas y dando un carácter casi divino á su recuerdo.

Yo puedo enseñarle, gentleman, como unos cincuenta mil libros escritos para glorificar á Eulame
y narrar sus hazañas. Sin embargo, su herencia no pudo resultar más fatal. Este fabricante
de guerras hizo lo necesario antes de desaparecer para que nuestro mundo se viese condenado
eternamente á la guerra.

El congreso reunido en Mildendo intentó un nuevo reparto de las naciones, dividiendo las antiguas
conquistas de Eulame; pero este arreglo fué un semillero de futuras peleas. Todos los vencedores
hablaban de la paz á gritos, pero cada uno procuraba vivir más armado que los otros, y al sentirse
con mayores fuerzas exigía una porción más considerable en el reparto.

Abreviaré mi relato, gentleman, pues me duele recordar este período, el más vergonzoso de nuestra
historia. Los pueblos vivían regidos por los hombres; las armas estaban en manos de los hombres;
el trabajo lo organizaban y reglamentaban los hombres ... ¿qué otra cosa podía ocurrir?...

Los herederos del emperador organizaron cada uno á su placer el pedazo de tierra que les tocó
en el reparto. Algunas naciones se constituyeron en República; otras fueron monarquías; unas
cuantas, con el título de Imperios, restauraron la autoridad despótica y terriblemente paternal
de los antiguos soberanos.

Nuestra nación, al recobrar sus primitivos límites, creyó oportuno quedarse con dos provincias
de Blefuscú, fundándose en confusos derechos históricos. Durante varios años los de Blefuscú
sólo pensaron en recobrar estas provincias, como si les fuese imposible la vida sin ellas.
Las recordaban en sus cantos patrióticos; no había ceremonia pública en que no las llorasen;
los muchachos, al entrar en la escuela, lo primero que aprendían era la necesidad de morir
algún día para que las provincias cautivas recobrasen su libertad; los hombres organizaban
su existencia con el pensamiento fijo de que eran soldados de una guerra futura. Y al fin vino
la guerra, y los de Blefuscú nos quitaron las dos provincias.

Entonces nosotros les imitamos, y durante varios años los niños de nuestras escuelas aprendieron
que había que morir para recobrar estos territorios, y hubo cánticos iguales á los del país
enemigo, y los hombres fueron todos soldados, y surgió una segunda guerra, en cuyo transcurso
recobramos las dos provincias....

Y los de Blefuscú se prepararon á su vez para una tercera guerra....

Al mismo tiempo había luchas sangrientas entre los demás países poblados por gentes de nuestra
especie. Ninguna nación podía conformarse con sus límites actuales. A la adoración de los antiguos
dioses había sucedido la idolatría de unos trapos de colores llamados banderas. Cada uno, con
agresivo fetichismo, consideraba que el trapo de su nación era más hermoso que los otros y
debía ondear triunfante sobre los países inmediatos. Las gentes separadas por un brazo de mar,
un río, una montaña ó un bosque, llamados fronteras, se odiaban de un modo feroz, sin haberse
visto nunca.

Cada país calumniaba al otro, inventando sobre él las más absurdas mentiras, y estas mentiras
las aceptaban las generaciones siguientes sin tomarse el trabajo de comprobarlas. De padres
á hijos se perpetuaba la degollina por la simple razón de que los abuelos también se habían
degollado.

Nunca se realizaron inventos con tan asombrosa rapidez; pero todos ellos servían fatalmente
para agrandar el arte de las matanzas. La ciencia se había hecho servidora de la guerra; los
laboratorios temblaban de patriótico regocijo cuando un descubrimiento proporcionaba la seguridad
de poder exterminar mayor número de hombres. Las fábricas más potentes eran las de materiales
para la guerra. Todos los países rivalizaban en una carrera loca, buscando adelantarse los
unos á los otros en los medios de destrucción. Los hombres se mataban sobre la tierra y sobre
el mar, y hasta en el último momento llegaron á exterminarse en las silenciosas alturas de
la atmósfera.

Las fortunas más grandes de cada país las poseían los fabricantes de armamento. La lucha industrial
y los egoístas deseos de lucro tomaban un carácter de abnegación patriótica. Si un país inventaba
un cañón enorme, al año siguiente el país adversario producía otro dos veces más grande. Sobre
las olas todavía era más disparatada esta exageración de los medios ofensivos. Como Blefuscú
y nosotros estamos separados por el mar, nos lanzamos á una rivalidad devoradora de nuestras
riquezas y de nuestro trabajo.

Estudiábamos ansiosamente su flota para que nuestra flota resultase superior. Si ellos construían
un navío grande, con numerosos cañones, nosotros al momento empezábamos en nuestros astilleros
otros navíos más enormes, hasta llegar á proporciones inverosímiles, que parecían un reto al
buen sentido y á todas las leyes físicas.

Baste decir, gentleman, que hemos tenido buques de guerra más grandes que la barca que le trajo
á usted; navíos con cien piezas de artillería iguales al revólver que le sacamos del bolsillo,
ó tal vez mucho más grandes, y llevando tres mil ó cuatro mil hombres de tripulación.... En
fin, verdaderas islas flotantes.

Y lo peor fué que estas construcciones gigantescas y los gastos enormes que exigían, todo resultó
inútil. El continuo invento de medios destructivos dió vida á nuevas embarcaciones no más grandes
que algunos peces de nuestros mares, pero que, á semejanza de éstos, podían deslizarse por
la profundidad submarina, atacando de lejos á los monstruos flotantes hechos de acero. A pesar
de su humilde aspecto, muchas veces, en nuestros combates navales, echaron á pique á los navíos
gigantescos, que representaban el valor de una ciudad.

Toda guerra resultaba más mortífera y costosa que la anterior. Las madres, al dar á luz á sus
hijos, sabían que no fabricaban hombres, sino soldados.

No pretendo hacerle creer, gentleman, que la guerra era algo nuevo en nuestra historia y sólo
la habíamos conocido después que Eulame trajo sus inventos del país de los gigantes. Habíamos
tenido guerras desde las épocas más remotas, como creo que las tuvieron todos los grupos humanos.
Pero eran guerras con pequeños ejércitos, que no alteraban la vida del país; guerras sostenidas
por tropas de combatientes voluntarios y profesionales; una especie de lujo sangriento, de
elegancia mortífera, que se permitían nuestros viejos emperadores de tarde en tarde. Pero después
de la demencia ambiciosa de Eulame y del perfeccionamiento de los medios de destrucción, las
guerras fueron de pueblo á pueblo, y toda la juventud de un país, abandonando campos y talleres,
corría á matar la juventud vigorosa del otro país que había hecho lo mismo.

Cada guerra significaba un largo alto en el desenvolvimiento humano, y luego un retroceso.
En la capital de cada país había un arco de triunfo para que desfilasen bajo su bóveda unas
veces el ejército que volvía victorioso y otras los invasores triunfantes.

Después de toda guerra, el suelo abandonado parecía vengarse del olvido y de la bestialidad
de los hombres restringiendo su producción. Las grandes empresas militares iban seguidas por
el hambre y las epidemias. Los hombres se mostraban peores al volver á sus casas durante una
paz momentánea. Habían olvidado el valor de la vida humana. Reñían con el menor pretexto; se
encolerizaban fácilmente, matándose entre ellos; pegaban á sus mujeres. Además, todos eran
alcohólicos. Durante sus campañas, los gobernantes les facilitaban en abundancia el vino y
los licores fuertes, sabiendo que un hombre en la inconsciencia de la embriaguez teme menos
á la muerte.

La riqueza pública ahorrada durante muchos años se derrochaba en unos meses, convirtiéndose
en humo de pólvora, en acero hecho fragmentos, en escombros de poblaciones y de fábricas.

Cuando, al fin, llegaba la paz, era para que empezase una nueva miseria....

Los períodos tranquilos resultaban tan peligrosos como los tiempos de guerra. Siempre han existido
descontentos de la organización social; siempre los que no tienen mirarán con odio á los que
poseen. Pero después de las guerras la falta de concordia social aún era más violenta. La envidia
que siente el de abajo resultaba más amarga. Como los pobres habían sido soldados á la fuerza,
se consideraban con nuevos derechos á poseerlo todo. Cuando cesaban las guerras, los hombres
se resistían al trabajo y hablaban de un nuevo reparto de la riqueza....

Esta situación absurda no podía durar.

Yo reconozco, como he dicho antes, que existen entre los hombres almas generosas y superiores,
aunque con menos abundancia que entre las mujeres. Los crímenes originados por los hombres
no podían menos de conmover á algunas de estas almas masculinas, y un gobernante de aquella
época dió una especie de reglamento para la paz humana, dividido en catorce artículos.

Pero entre los hombres las mejores ideas se transforman y se corrompen. Hay en ellos un fondo
de egoísmo que desfigura toda idea generosa apenas se encargan de implantarla.

No había un país que dejase de alabar la paz, pero esta paz debía hacerse de acuerdo con sus
gustos y ambiciones. Todos querían que las cosas fuesen no como deben ser, sino con arreglo
á sus conveniencias. Y los catorce artículos ó puntos se vieron retorcidos y desfigurados de
tal modo, que acabaron por convertirse prácticamente en otras tantas calamidades. </sourceTextContent>
<suspiciousIDDoc>suspicious-document09306</suspiciousIDDoc>
<suspiciousTextLanguage>en</suspiciousTextLanguage>
<suspiciousTextOffset>54439</suspiciousTextOffset>
<suspiciousTextLength>17004</suspiciousTextLength>
<suspiciousTextContent> Our people were ruled by
emperors, who believed the center of the world and a different divine matter to that of other beings.
The life of the nation focused on the person of the sovereign. The characters jumped higher
on the rope and did other acrobatic exercises to amuse the monarch of the Empire, then called Lilliput.
The great ambition of every Lilliputian was to get a thread color that gave the despot to cross
over the chest By way of decoration. In short, my country was subjected to parental authority but
arbitrary, and the men wore a dull, sleepy existence, irrespective of any progress. Of the
women then do not talk. Were slaves, with a hypocritical servitude masked by the selfish love
of husband and false sweetness of home.

Such was the empire of Lilliput, where a century and a half after the arrival of the first man
Mountain began the series of historical events that ended up changing their appearance.

A castaway giant who had spent some time with us had the opportunity to return to his homeland using
a boat in harmony with its size as the tide crept into our costs.

In undertaking the return journey was not alone.

A Lilliputian also left, some say that according to the giant, others, and are the most, they
assume that he hid in the huge boat with the desire to know the world of man-mountain.

This unique traveler is famous in our history. His name was Eulame. I have a colleagues at the University
to assume that Eulame was a woman, it can not be explained otherwise much intelligence and so
heroically gathered in one person. Have written several books to prove that Eulame pretended
to be a man because in those days dominated only men, and almost fully demonstrated. But I
have never fascinated by this mystery of our history. May well have
been man Enlame as those of his time believed.

A exception does not alter the rule, and acknowledge that the weak male can produce from time
to time some celebrity, without it you out of their inferiority ....

Eulame say left the land of the giants and stayed there a few years. Also this period of its
existence has given rise to many historical and critical studies.

Some say who walked by that big monster world, from fair to fair, being exhibited in circuses
and barracks as a curiosity than ever before, and that his trip helped him to understand the
various towns in which giants are divided.

Other authors argue, based on the testimony of people who tried and were able to Enlame listen
to their confidences, the bold little Lilliputian was known for the generality of giants.
He and the sailor whose boat escaped were picked up by a ship, and,
he reached the land where everything is monstrously huge, sailors
sold him a sage, and he lived in the atmosphere of a lonely scholar,
learning everything fast synthesis illustrate what the giant had searched
in books and in laboratory experiments for many years.

Nor do I decide on this issue or for some or for others. In reality, nothing is known about
the first period Eulame life that was as mysterious as the youth
of many founders religions.

Everything they say my fellow University and also what they said many earlier scholars is based
on hypotheses.

The only certainty is that Eulame returned to Lilliput, but not on a boat just like you brought to
you, Gentleman-Mountain. Across the great barrier of rocks and foam raised by our gods was, according
to the chroniclers of the time, a ship proportions immense, a true
giant ship.

A simple boat saved the wall hindrance of divine bringing to our shores to Eulame and to an
old man-mountain, dry body with a beard white, which I suppose should have been his student protector.

This
was meant to be bringing the boat to our land all inventions their world was coming packed the
huge ship, but our gods, as they love a little to the giant shook
the boundless sea with a mighty storm, and the ship crashed the barrier
of rocks and foam.

Stayed with us so helpless giant old and lacking which means you see now. Moreover, as his years
not allowed to live in a world so new to him and so lacking in the amenities needed by the elderly,
died shortly after. I suspect that the emperors the last dynasty perhaps felt uneasy about
the frequency with which they arrived at our s costs of the same size, and tried the old abruptly,
without considering that the poor had been attracted by the stories
of Eulame to establish their civilization generously between us.

His body gave little work to be annulled. It was a skeleton covered with skin nothing more, and
their bones were used as materials rich in many works of art.

Still retain University several books about him, which helped me a lot for the study of language
you speak and the knowledge of the habits of the man-mountain.

But back to Eulame. Finding himself alone, he launched his countrymen to preach the benefits
of civilization of giants. The discontent of the Empire, who were many, saw him a leader who could
replace the reigning dynasty.

The wise men listened to him as a teacher divine, and all universities were declaring his disciples.
From then dates the introduction of English in this country as secret and sacred language,
which served to understand to upper class people.

The things he did Eulame in no time! Never in our history known activity like yours. The people
could not believe it was a man equal to the others, and we had the son of the gods. To industry
of the country changed radically in a few months. Implemented between us all mechanical progress
he had seen in the world of giants. Our engineers, who until then had gone blind, always moving
in the same circle, after listening to the lessons of Eulame new
roads were open to their eyes, and ran for them, making discoveries
with a dizzying speed, inventing almost instantly what it took perhaps
long years of meditation in the country giants.

The last emperor tried to assassinate the prophet, but he possessed the strength, and thought come
time to move from words to action. He had brought the explosives from the other world and firearms.
The rich industrial supporters secretly manufactured eulamelismo war material equal to the man-mountain,
and it was enough for a thousand disciples with rifles guns and march
on the palace of the emperor so that he would flee, ending at a time
secular dynasty.

The old troops, armed with bows and spears, they broke up, cheering Eulame, receiving the first
hail of bullets from his supporters.

The regenerator was then elevated to the imperial dignity, and began the most hectic period,
more bloody and interesting to our history.

I realize that as men then ran the country's march, had the cynicism
give the name of glorious time to a period in which millions died,
being also burned many cities, which are not yet rebuilt, and torn
provinces whole.

Eulame to be in power, it was felt invested with a superhuman task.

This mission was to bring to all the nearby nations populated by beings
of our species the benefits of civilization planted by him.

Moreover, as a force available higher need to use it, just like the athlete, unable to live
peacefully without bumping into something to exercise your muscles.

Eulame irresistible troops marched against Blefuscu, the people who
for centuries had been our adversary.

It was an easy war by the great disparity between the respective arms, but those of Blefuscu
fought with the tenacity irrational History called heroism, getting killed in huge quantities.

Having
mastered this nation, the conqueror took their weapons to another, and then to another, leaving
no continent or island ceased to recognize his imperial authority. But very greatness of his
success weighed on him, ending up smash.

His generals obeyed to the law of men according to which each pupil, when viewed on high, should attack
his teacher.

It came a day when the warring warlords who ruled conquered lands by delegation Eulame revolted
against. Everything he had learned in the land of the giants confidently announced to his relatives:
new means of destruction domain was already common opponents just as he knew, it was not a demigod,
was a man like others.

And as his enemies were much more numerous, he defeated in a pitched battle at the gates of this
city, then called Mildendo, meeting then in Congress diplomat to decide their future destiny.

They did not dare to kill him because they were his disciples, but as they wanted to be free of its
presence, perpetually confined in a small island in a lonely rock and unhealthy, far from all life,
in the vicinity of the wall of rocks and foam that few dare to go.

The emperor died a few years in exile in a dark.

Families were still living fourteen or fifteen millions of people who had died on account of their
wars and their ambitions. Then, over the years, the masses, you need to live the cult of heroes
they do not have the inventories, glorified Eulame, turning their exploits killings glorious,
giving an almost divine to his memory.

I can teach, gentleman, about fifty thousand books written to glorify Eulame and narrating his exploits.
However, his legacy could not be more fatal.

This manufacturer of war was necessary before disappearing saw our world condemned to war forever.

The
congress met in Mildendo tried a new division of the nations, dividing the former Eulame conquests,
but this arrangement was a hotbed of future fights.

All winners spoke of peace to cry, but everyone tried to live more armed than the others, and
feeling with greater forces required a considerable portion in the cast.

Shorten my story, gentleman, it hurts me to remember this period,
the most shameful of our history.

The people lived governed by men, the weapons were in the hands of men; the work is organized
and regulated men ... What else could happen? ...

The heirs of the Emperor held his pleasure each piece of land that they had to in the cast. Some
nations were established in the Republic, others were monarchies, a few, with the title of
Empires, restored the despotic and paternal terribly of the former sovereign.

Our nation, to recover their original boundaries, thought fit to keep
two provinces of Blefuscu, based on historical rights confused.

During several years of Blefuscu just thought to regain these provinces, as if life will be impossible
without them. The recalled in his patriotic songs, there was no public ceremony that did not
weep; boys, on entering school, the first thing they learned was the need to die one day to the
captive provinces regained their freedom, the men organized their
existence with fixed thought they were soldiers of a future war.

And at last came war, and those of us Blefuscu removed the two provinces.

Then

we imitate them, and for several years the children in our schools learned he had to die to regain
these territories, and there were chants of the country equal to the enemy, and the men were all soldiers,
and came a second war, during which we recover the two provinces ....

And of Blefuscu were prepared to turn to a third war ....

At the same time there were bloody conflicts between other countries
populated by people of our species.

No nation could comply with its current boundaries. The worship of the ancient idolatry gods
had happened a few colored rags called flags. Each, fetishism aggressive, felt that the cloth
of his nation was more beautiful than the others and should wave triumphant over the country
immediately.

The people separated by a stretch of sea, a river, a mountain or a forest, called borders,
is hated in a fierce, without having ever seen.

Each country slandering another, inventing on him the most absurd lies and these lies the following
generations accepted without bothering to verify them. Parent to children with slaughter perpetuated
by the simple reason that the grandparents had stuck.

Inventions were never made such an astonishing speed, but they all
served fatally to enlarge the art of killing.

Science had made the servant of the war, the trembling with patriotic glee laboratories when a discovery
provided security able to kill more men. Factories were stronger materials for war. All countries
competed in a mad race, seeking to anticipate the one another in mass destruction. The men were
killed on the ground and the sea, even at the last moment came to exterminate the silent heights
the atmosphere.

The biggest fortunes of each country possessed weapons manufacturers. The industrial action and the
selfish desire for profit taking a matter of patriotic devotion. If a country invented a huge
cannon, the following year the country produced another opponent twice as large. About waves
was even more crazy this exaggeration of the media offensive.

As Blefuscu and we are separated by the sea, we jump to a rivalry that devours our wealth and our
work.

Eagerly studied its fleet to our fleet proves superior.

If they built a large ship with many guns, us when we started in our yards other vessels more enormous,
reaching unbelievable proportions, which seemed a challenge good sense and of all physical laws.

Suffice
to say, gentleman, we've had warships larger than the boat that brought him to you; ships
with a hundred artillery pieces equal to the revolver that we took from his pocket, or perhaps
much larger, and carrying three thousand or four thousand men crew .... In Finally, real floating
islands.

And the worst thing was that these giant buildings and huge costs
required, everything was useless.

The continuous invention of destructive media gave new life to no larger boats that fish in our
seas, but, like them, could slip through underwater depth, attacking from afar the floating monsters
made of steel. Despite its humble appearance, many times, our naval battles, he scuttled vessels
giant, representing the value of a city.

Every war was more deadly and costly than before. Mothers, giving birth to children knew that did
not make men, but rather soldiers.

Do not pretend to believe, gentleman, that war was something new in
our history and only we had seen after he brought his inventions Eulame
the land of the giants.

We had wars since the earliest times, as I believe that all human groups had. But they were
wars with small armies that do not change the life of the country, wars being waged troops
of volunteers and professional soldiers, a kind of bloody luxury
of deadly elegance, which allowed our old emperors from time to time.

But after of dementia Eulame ambitious and refinement of mass destruction, wars were from town
to town, and all the youth of a country, leaving fields and workshops ran vigorous youth to
kill the other country that had done the same.

Every war meant a long high in human development, and then a setback. In the capital of each
country had a triumphal arch for a parade in your dome Sometimes the army returned victorious
and triumphant other invaders.

After every war, revenge seemed derelict land of forgetfulness and bestiality Men's restricting
production. Large companies were followed by military hunger and
epidemics.

The men showed worse upon returning to their homes during a momentary
peace.

They had forgotten the value of human life. Quarreled with the slightest pretext, are easily angered,
killing each other, beat their wives. In addition, they were all alcoholics. During their campaigns,
the leaders made it easy and plenty of wine hard liquor, knowing that a man into unconsciousness
less afraid of being drunk to death.

Public wealth saved for many years wasted in a few months, becoming
in smoke of gunpowder, in fact steel fragments, debris and plant populations.

When

at last peace came, was to start a new misery ....

The quiet periods
were as dangerous as wartime.

There have always been dissatisfied with the social organization have not always look to them
that hate possess. But after the wars the lack of social harmony was even more violent. Envy
he feels the bottom was more bitter. Since the poor had been soldiers to the force, with new
rights were considered to possess everything.

When the war ceased, the men were reluctant to work and talked about a redistribution of wealth
....

This absurd situation could not last.

I acknowledge, as I said before, there are generous souls of men and
above although less abundant than females. The crimes caused by men
could not fail to move to some of these men's souls, and a ruling
that time gave a sort of regulation for human peace, divided into
fourteen articles.

But among men the best ideas are transformed and
become corrupt. Background is in them selfishness that disfigures
all generous idea just in charge of implementing it.

There was a
country that ceased to praise peace, but this peace should be made
in accordance with tastes and ambitions. Everyone wanted things were
not as they should be, but under at his convenience. And the fourteen
articles or items were twisted and disfigured so that eventually became
almost as many calamities</suspiciousTextContent>
<equivalentType>translation</equivalentType>
<manualObfuscation>false</manualObfuscation>
<automaticNoise>false</automaticNoise>
</info>